<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477895" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Bre-X shares resume trade, wreak havoc in Toronto.</title>
<headline>Bre-X shares resume trade, wreak havoc in Toronto.</headline>
<byline>Sarah Edmonds</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bre-X Minerals Ltd. resumed trading again on Tuesday, wreaking havoc on the Toronto Stock Exchange and causing computers to crash at Canada's biggest stock market.</p>
<p>It was the first time the stock had traded since last Thursday when investors slashed almost C$3 billion ($2.19 billion) off Bre-X's stock market value.</p>
<p>A flurry of news releases, shareholder lawsuits and a deepening wrangle between Bre-X and Toronto Stock Exchange regulators left investors unclear which way to turn.</p>
<p>While the furore surrounding the troubled Calgary, Alberta-based Bre-X had shaken confidence in Canadian mining stocks, some bold investors bought the stock in droves, pushing the price up C$1.35 to C$3.85 in frenetic turnover of 7.78 million shares in the first 22 minutes of trading.</p>
<p>The stock was halted all day on Monday and re-opened midmorning on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Bre-X has been under heavy fire since last week when its partner in Indonesia, Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold Inc., revealed that early drilling samples performed during its due diligence process on the Busang gold property in the rain forests of Borneo turned up &quot;insignificant&quot; amounts of gold.</p>
<p>Bre-X, which had stated that the property could hold up to 71 million ounces of ore, issued a statement on Tuesday shedding little light on the increasingly murky situation.</p>
<p>The terse release said Bre-X needed more time to study a report from engineering firm Kilborn SNC-Lavalin related to a check assay program at the Indonesian gold property.</p>
<p>Despite strong wording contained in four class action lawsuits filed in the United States in recent days, Indonesia's Mines and Energy Minister Ida Bagus Sudjana said on Tuesday his ministry was not in a position to judge the truth of Bre-X's claims about the amount of gold in Busang.</p>
<p>North American investors, at least, appeared willing to play the odds, with many believing that the stock's potential downside has been significantly reduced.</p>
<p>But the huge volume in Bre-X shares crippled the Toronto exchange's trading systems, just as it did twice on Thursday.</p>
<p>The exchange admitted its outdated computers were unable to cope with the fantastic volume in Bre-X.</p>
<p>&quot;It's old architecture. It was developed when the volumes here at the TSE weren't as high, so it's not able to handle increased volumes that we're experiencing right now,&quot; said exchange spokeswoman Jane Wong.</p>
<p>Computer trading crashed for almost an hour on Tuesday morning. The TSE said later it would not resume trading in Bre-X shares for the rest of the day as it grappled with the technical problems.</p>
<p>Bre-X shares continued trading on Nasdaq, where they were up 75 cents to $2.50.</p>
<p>Bre-X Chief Executive David Walsh is involved in an increasingly ugly wrangle with Canada's largest stock market over whether or not the shares should remain halted.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a verbal fist fight that has developed between David Walsh and (TSE President) Rowland Fleming,&quot; said Fred Ketchen, director of equity trading at ScotiaMcLeod Inc. and chairman of the TSE's trading policy committee.</p>
<p>The TSE and Bre-X have each issued several statements in the past few days. Bre-X pleaded with the TSE to keep the stock halted until after the audit of Busang's drilling results. The exchange ignored the request, saying it was committed to providing &quot;a fair and continuous market in its listed securities for shareholders and investors.&quot;</p>
<p>Ketchen said all the material news now available was in the market and that investors knew that the next major step would be the completion of the Busang audit by Strathcona Minerals Services Inc., a Toronto-based independent engineering consulting firm.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that if it's in the market place, the public should have the right to trade on that,&quot; Ketchen said. &quot;I think that continuous trading is important.&quot;</p>
<p>He said a recommendation in the mid-1980s, which the TSE still followed, stated that trading halts should coincide with the release of material news but should be kept as short as possible.</p>
<p>Many investors were steering clear of the stock until the results of the drilling audit were revealed.</p>
<p>&quot;It's something we're avoiding. We wouldn't touch it until we have more information from Strathcona,&quot; said Yorkton Securities analyst Doug Leishman.</p>
<p>&quot;Strathcona is the referee here. We would want to see something from Strathcona before we change our opinion.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
