<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477894" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canadian bonds close weaker, spreads to U.S. widen.</title>
<headline>Canadian bonds close weaker, spreads to U.S. widen.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian bonds closed weaker on Tuesday, failing to keep pace with rising U.S. treasuries, as continued weakness in the Canadian dollar weighed on prices, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;It continues to come from the Canadian dollar. If you look across the curve, it's the short end that's suffering the most,&quot; said Harv Kalirai, Canadian analyst with New York-based I.D.E.A. &quot;The market is really apprehensive that the Fed is going to move to raise rates again.&quot;</p>
<p>Canada's 30-year benchmark bond fell C$0.25 to C$107.35 to yield 7.361 percent.  </p>
<p>The U.S. 30-year bond rose 6/32 to yield 7.08 percent. The spread between the two bonds widened to 28 basis points from 24 basis points on Monday.</p>
<p>Canadian bonds weakened as the currency traded at C$1.3890 (US$0.7199), near its two-year low of C$1.3910 (US$0.7189). Weighing on the Canadian dollar were expectations that the U.S. Federal Reserve would hike interest rates again in May. The most recent Fed rate hike weighed heavily on the Canadian dollar. Economists on Tuesday said there were growing expectations that the Bank of Canada would have to hike interest rates in order to defend the currency.  </p>
<p>The likelihood that the Bank of Canada would hike rates to defend the currency increased as the currency traded past C$1.3900, analysts said. The dollar traded as low as C$1.3902 (US$0.7193) during the session.</p>
<p>In other prices, the Government of Canada's 7.0 percent bond due 2006 fell C$0.18 to C$101.42 to yield 6.795 percent. The U.S. bond rose 5/32 to yield 6.88 percent.</p>
<p>The negative spread between the bonds narrowed to 9 basis points from 13 basis points at the close of trading on Monday.</p>
<p>The three-month cash T-bill yielded 3.27 percent against its U.S. equivalent which yielded 5.31 percent.</p>
<p>((Jeffrey Hodgson (416) 941-8105, e-mail:</p>
<p>jeffrey.hodgson@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
