<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477889" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: TSE says will not halt Bre-X on request.</title>
<headline>TSE says will not halt Bre-X on request.</headline>
<byline>Andrea Hopkins</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>After a huge volume of trade in Bre-X Minerals Ltd caused the Toronto Stock Exchange's computer trading system to crash for the second time in as many weeks, the TSE said on Tuesday it will change the way it deals with the troubled Calgary exploration firm.</p>
<p>TSE President Rowland Fleming called a news conference on Tuesday to inform the market that the exchange will no longer halt trading in Bre-X's stock until it first sees the information on which the company bases its halt request.</p>
<p>Traditionally the TSE has halted trading of a stock at the request of a company pending the release of material news.</p>
<p>Fleming charged that Bre-X took advantage of the policy to have its stock halted and then failed to report material news.</p>
<p>&quot;I think they have asked us to stretch the reasonable, the expected, approach to trading halts and the release of material information,&quot; Fleming told reporters.</p>
<p>He assured investors that Bre-X shares would resume trading when the stock market opens at 0930 EST/1430 GMT on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The TSE's antiquated computer trading system collapsed in mid-morning trade on Tuesday, crippled by a crushing volume of trades backlogged for Bre-X.</p>
<p>It was the first time Bre-X's shares had traded since Thursday, when the system crashed twice, forcing the exchange to close 15 minutes early.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, The computer trading system was down for almost an hour after crashing within minutes of a re-opening in deals on Bre-X's stock at 1030 EST/1530 GMT. A total of 7.78 million Bre-X shares changed hands before the crash.</p>
<p>Trading in Bre-X's shares were halted all day on Monday.</p>
<p>Fleming said the TSE halted trade of Bre-X shortly before the exchange opened on Monday at the request of the company, which had promised to release material information &quot;shortly&quot;.</p>
<p>He said two subsequent releases contained insufficient significant information to justify a trading halt.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that it is unreasonable to extend trading halts on the anticipation of information that may be released at some point in the future and that may be material,&quot; said Fleming.</p>
<p>He denied suggestions that the system collapse had hurt Toronto's credibility as an international market.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think this single incident can be characterized as any kind of a blemish. I don't know of an exchange in the world that hasn't had a technology problem from time to time.&quot;</p>
<p>The exchange's 20-year-old CATS (Computer Assisted Trading System) is due to be replaced later this year by a system driven by TOREX trading engines supplied by the Paris Bourse.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
