<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477949" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ajay has no funds for preferred dividend.</title>
<headline>Ajay has no funds for preferred dividend.</headline>
<dateline>DELAVAN, Wis. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ajay Sports Inc said Tuesday it has no funds immediately available to pay a dividend on its Series C 10 percent cumulative preferred stock for the first quarter ended March 31.</p>
<p>As a result, its board has not yet declared such a dividend.</p>
<p>Ajay also said its bank lender contends the company is in technical default under its loan agreement and the bank has restricted funds available to Ajay under the agreement.  </p>
<p>Ajay said it is working with new lenders to replace its current bank and to increase the company's credit line.</p>
<p>Management and the board are monitoring the loan negotiations and will address the dividend payment issue after a new lender is found.</p>
<p>It said no other dividends on the company's capital stock may be paid until the accrued dividends on the Series C preferred stock are paid.</p>
<p>Ajay manufactures and markets leisure products, including Spalding golf bags, carts, gloves and accessories, Palm Springs Golf clubs and In-Motion casual furniture.</p>
<p>	  ((Reuters Chicago Newsdesk (312) 408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I49420">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DELAVAN, Wis."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
