<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477963" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CSCE cocoa surges to over 2-1/2 year highs.</title>
<headline>CSCE cocoa surges to over 2-1/2 year highs.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>CSCE cocoa futures exploded to their highest level since July 1994, as speculators bought heavily amid bullish technical indicators, trading sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was no news and no selling,&quot; said Refco Inc analyst Ann Prendergast. &quot;Once the market got over the psychologically important level of $1,500 (a tonne basis May), it just took off.&quot;</p>
<p>Most-active May shot up $59 a tonne on the day -- or about four percent -- to $1,512, after ranging from $1,520 to $1,440. Second-month July, which peaked at a new life-of-contract high of $1,547, rose $58, to $1,540.</p>
<p>The outer months, which also hit new highs, closed up $45 to $54.</p>
<p>Cocoa prices pulled back at the outset, but reversed course after scale-down industry buying emerged at the lows and sparked a round of speculative short-covering.</p>
<p>Weakness in the U.S. dollar against the British pound also helped New York's recovery, as arbitrage favored less expensive dollar-denominated CSCE cocoa. By comparison, LIFFE cocoa futures ended softer Tuesday, with May easing one stg, to 1,016 stg.</p>
<p>Traders said fund interest emerged in New York after the CSCE May contract broke through last Wednesday's close of $1,461 and breached key technical resistance at $1,475 and $1,490.</p>
<p>&quot;It was all technical and very speculative,&quot; one dealer said. &quot;The fundamentals were actually a little bearish this week with rains returning to West Africa.&quot;</p>
<p>Weather analysts in Abidjan said on Tuesday that rains continued to strengthen over Ivory Coast's cocoa belt in mid-March after February's drought, helping the development of the mid-crop (May-September).</p>
<p>On Friday, the U.S. Department of Agriculture raised its forecast on Friday for the Ivorian 1996/97 cocoa crop to 1.10 million tonnes from 1.05 million because of an expected improvement in the mid-crop.</p>
<p>&quot;It is defying fundamentals,&quot; said Merrill Lynch analst Judith Ganes. &quot;I have not heard any news except good rains in the Ivory Coast.&quot;</p>
<p>But despite a larger Ivorian crop and plentiful near-term supplies, other analysts pointed out there is still likely to be a world cocoa deficit in 1996/97.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically, there is less cocoa this year and things are going to be a little tighter,&quot; said Smith Barney analyst Walter Spilka. &quot;I think this market is extremely undervalued.&quot;</p>
<p>Technically, some traders said May is likely to test its life-of-contract high of $1,526 on Wednesday. After that level, strong resistance was noted at $1,543.</p>
<p>But some traders said if London fails to make its due of 25-30 stg higher tomorrow, the market could be vunerable to a sell-off.</p>
<p>Traders also said May liquidation ahead of first notice day on April 17, could also put some pressure on the market.  May open interest stood at 29,669 lots as of March 31.</p>
<p>European first quarter cocoa grindings due in the next week or two may help determine the market's direction, traders said. While some operators expect good growth in the grinds -- a key indictator of consumption -- others say the grind data could prove disappointing.</p>
<p>&quot;The 1996 first quarter grinds were pretty strong,&quot; one trader said. &quot;I think it will be tough to match those numbers.&quot;</p>
<p>Volume on the exchange was heavy, at an estimated 18,724 lots, with more than half the tunover posted during the last hour of trading.</p>
<p>((--Patricia Avidan, New York Commodities Desk +1 212 859 1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
