<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477948" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Brady bonds rebound slightly in nervous market.</title>
<headline>Brady bonds rebound slightly in nervous market.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brady bond prices rebounded slightly on Tuesday after suffering sharp losses Monday, but market experts said continued volatility is likely to add to a further widening in yield spreads against U.S. Treasuries.</p>
<p>&quot;The way I would characterize today is a little bit of a correction within a bear market. I don't see this as things having turned around,&quot; said Tulio Vera, managing director of emerging markets at Bear Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
<p>Argentine FRBs ARFLC05=RR were 5/8 stronger at 89-5/8, Mexican pars MX625L19=RR were 7/8 higher at 70-7/8 and Brazil &quot;C&quot; bonds BR8D14=RR were 1-1/8 firmer at 74-7/8.  </p>
<p>Trading sources attributed Tuesday's rebound to a rise in U.S. Treasury securities after the National Association of Purchasing Management's (NAPM) March index triggered some short-covering.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's rebound in the (30-year U.S. Treasury) long bond has allowed for some recovery among Bradies,&quot; said one emerging market analyst here.</p>
<p>Still, emerging market instruments were not able to recover fully the huge losses suffered on Monday.  </p>
<p>Experts said uncertainty over when and if the Federal Reserve will move further to tighten U.S. interest rates has increased the volatility spectre for emerging debt markets.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we will continue to be in this mode for a period of time because there is still too much of a divergence of opinions out there in terms of what the next move is for U.S. interest rates. Until we get more of a consensus and more stability, it's not going to do well,&quot; said Vera.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be a lot of spread trades to be done and a continuation of volatility,&quot; said another source.  </p>
<p>Although the market will enjoy days in the plus column, Vera said he believes there will be more spread widening before there is any significant spread tightening.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, Vera said emerging market yield spreads against U.S. Treasuries have not and will not widen as dramatically as they had when the Fed began a round of tightening in February 1994.</p>
<p>He said spreads have widened out a little bit over 100 basis points since the end of February, whereas in 1994 spreads had widened by about 400 basis points in the first couple of months after the Fed tightened.  </p>
<p>Unlike 1994, the credit fundamentals of most emerging market countries are much better, experts said.</p>
<p>&quot;There were a lot of questions on the fundamentals irrespective of the interest rate backdrop. This time around there are not major destabilizing situations with countries in crisis situations that there were in 1994,&quot; Vera added.</p>
<p>(( --Diane Craft, 212-859-1946))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
