<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477911" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. stocks may face more blows from weak earnings.</title>
<headline>U.S. stocks may face more blows from weak earnings.</headline>
<byline>Cal Mankowski</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. stocks, already reeling from one hard blow in the form of higher interest rates, could crumble if corporate earnings deliver another punch.</p>
<p>&quot;Wall Street has under-estimated the impact of the strong dollar,&quot; warned Michael Metz, strategist at Oppenheimer &amp; Co.</p>
<p>He said U.S. companies are facing a &quot;double whammy&quot; with the vibrant dollar dampening overseas profits and foreign manufacturers getting a competitive advantage because the currency variations make U.S. goods more expensive.  </p>
<p>Melissa Brown, director of quantitative research at Prudential Securities, said earnings overall may provide support, but &quot;I don't think they're going to provide any impetus for the market to move up.&quot;</p>
<p>Even with earnings overall expected to be higher, not only for the first quarter but for the year, higher long term interest rates have caused a lowering of the valuation investors are willing to pay for those earnings, Brown said.  </p>
<p>Trude Latimer, an independent analyst based in Charlottesville, Va., noted that Fore Systems Inc, Informix Corp and Quickturn Design Systems Inc all warned investors Tuesday earnings expectations have been too high. All three stocks were sharply lower.</p>
<p>&quot;I havn't heard one company come out and say 'our numbers are too conservative',&quot; Latimer said.</p>
<p>A Wall Street trader, who did not want to be identified, said earnings disappointments would continue to be a factor for stocks on an individual basis, but not necessarily something that pulls the rug out from under the entire market.  </p>
<p>A survey by Institutional Brokers Estimate System on Monday showed that, of 140 companies reporting first quarter earnings already, 82, or 59 percent, had positive surprises and were significantly higher than the mean estimate of analysts. But 30 percent were negative surprises and only 11 percent were on target.</p>
<p>Rao Chalasani, strategist at EVEREN Securities, believes earnings will be up 7.0 to 9.0 percent this year.</p>
<p>&quot;That in itself is not a problem,&quot; he said, noting it is in line with the trend over the past several years.  </p>
<p>But the analyst said he is more concerned about interest rates. One week ago the Federal Reserve raised short term interest rates to 5.50 percent from 5.25 percent.</p>
<p>Chalasani believes the Dow industrials, which were up about 15 points to 6599 Tuesday afternoon, could touch 6400 on the downside. But he added the downside would probably be even lower &quot;if we see 7.25 percent on the long bond rate.&quot; The 30-year U.S. Treasury issue was slightly higher Tuesday with the yield at 7.08 percent.</p>
<p>The Dow is down nearly 500 points from its all-time closing high of 7085.16 on March 11.</p>
<p>Metz sees several factors ganging up to erode the profitability of U.S. companies. For one, efforts to contain the costs of fringe benefits for workers appear to have reached their limit. Also, wages are pushing up and for some industries commodity prices are on the rise.</p>
<p>As for the Dow industrials, he said: &quot;My guess is that we've seen the high for the year and we haven't seen the low yet.&quot;</p>
<p>When companies with reporting periods that ended March 31 begin to report, Prudential's Brown said some of the stronger reports could come from consumer cyclicals and autos. But basic industry earnings and business services, including long distance telephone companies, could be down year over year. But either way, individual stock prices may not react much as long as the reports match expectations, she added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
