<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477993" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Treasuries end higher on benign inflation gauge.</title>
<headline>US Treasuries end higher on benign inflation gauge.</headline>
<byline>Ellen Freilich</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Treasury prices closed higher on Tuesday after the prices component in a closely watched gauge of the nation's manufacturing activity fell.</p>
<p>The prices measure of the National Association of Purchasing Management's (NAPM) March index fell to 50.9 in March from 55.1 the prior month.</p>
<p>That news soothed the market's initial alarm over a jump in the overall NAPM index to 55.0 in March from 53.1 in February. A reading above 50 indicates an expanding economy.  </p>
<p>As a result, the bellwether 30-year bond ended up 9/32 at 94-13/32, its yield at 7.08 percent.</p>
<p>At the short end of the maturity curve, three- and six-month bill rates fell two basis points to 5.16 percent and 5.30 percent, respectively.</p>
<p>&quot;The big news today was the price component of the Purchasing Managers report,&quot; said Bill Hornbarger, fixed-income strategist at A.G. Edwards &amp; Sons Inc. &quot;The headline showing the gain in the overall index gave us a sharp, hard trade down. But when people saw the price index was low, the market immediately popped up.&quot;  </p>
<p>The perception that the market was somewhat oversold also prompted some short-covering, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;A couple of bad shorts helped drive the market along,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>And of the small burst of optimism that fueled some buying, Credit Suisse First Boston's chief markets strategist Matthew Alexy said, &quot;The market's been down for so long, people see a two-basis-point rally as a big deal.&quot;</p>
<p>To move higher, bond investors set aside a 2.3 percent rise in February construction spending and a 0.5 percent increase in the index of leading economic indicators.  </p>
<p>And analysts said the credit markets were scarcely in the clear.</p>
<p>Chris Rupkey, vice president and financial economist at Bank of Tokyo/Mitsubishi, said the market faced two months of economic news before the next Federal Reserve policy meeting on May 20. He said investors could not count on those data to make a decisive case for no further interest-rate tightenings.</p>
<p>&quot;Usually the economy has to run into some kind of wall -- either an unknown shock or a high wall of interest rates and I don't think anyone believes that a 5-1/2 percent Federal funds rate will slow things down,&quot; Rupkey said.  </p>
<p>The Federal Reserve raised its federal funds rate 25 basis points to 5-1/2 percent on March 25.</p>
<p>Alexy, too, said the market had a lot of data to examine between now and the next Fed meeting. In the short-term, jobless claims data for the latest week could hurt the market if the number of claims falls below 300,000, he said. A Reuters poll found economists, on average, estimated that new claims totaled 310,000 in the week ended March 29.</p>
<p>Investors are starting to focus on March payroll data, due Friday. Reuters' poll showed economists, on average, estimated that payrolls grew by 182,000 new jobs in March.  </p>
<p>But investors will be concerned if, as forecast, average hourly earnings rise 0.4 percent, Rupkey said.</p>
<p>Traders said there was some buying by investment funds and central banks.</p>
<p>Alexy cited some &quot;shortening trades,&quot; in which long paper was sold in favor of the middle of the yield curve.</p>
<p>Year bill rates slipped two basis points to 5.65 percent on Tuesday. Two-year note prices rose 2/32 to 99-23/32, yielding 6.40 percent.</p>
<p>The five-year note climbed 5/32 to 99-19/32 to yield 6.72 percent and the ten-year was up 7/32 at 95-18/32 to yield 6.88 percent.</p>
<p>(( -- N.A. Treasury Desk, 212-859-1679 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
