<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="477986" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Rep Saxton says BLS unfairly criticized on CPI.</title>
<headline>US Rep Saxton says BLS unfairly criticized on CPI.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rep. Jim Saxton, chairman of the congressional Joint Economic Committee, said Tuesday the Bureau of Labor Statistics was unfairly criticized for not acting quicker on revising the consumer price index (CPI).</p>
<p>Saxton, a New Jersey Republican, blamed the White House for not including a request for funding the CPI revision in its fiscal 1994 budget submitted in 1993.</p>
<p>&quot;It wasn't because of BLS fumbling, but rather because the White House had dropped the ball and blocked the agency's budget request for a CPI revision,&quot; he said in a statement.</p>
<p>Congress would also have had to play a part in approving such a funding request if it were made.</p>
<p>A JEC spokeswoman pointed to a paragraph of a letter Saxton received from BLS Commissioner Katharine Abraham in response to a question at a March 7 hearing about the history of decisions on funding for the CPI revision.</p>
<p>&quot;The BLS had developed plans for a possible start to the Revision in Fiscal Year 1994, but it ultimately was decided not to proceed with a request to the Congress for funds to start this work until the following year,&quot; Abraham wrote.  </p>
<p>The CPI became a political issue this year after an advisory commission headed by economist Michael Boskin reported last December that the CPI overstated cost of living by about 1.1 percentage points a year.</p>
<p>Since increases in some federal benefits such as Social Security are tied to the CPI, reducing any overstatement could mean lower increases in those benefits, which could be a politically sensitive move. But money the government would save could make balancing the budget easier.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
