<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478043" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Small banks reject U.S. banking reform compromise.</title>
<headline>Small banks reject U.S. banking reform compromise.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Small banks, among the most vocal opponents of allowing banks to combine with commercial companies under U.S. bank reform plans, on Tuesday rejected a compromise on the issue offered by one lawmaker.</p>
<p>Rep Richard Baker, sponsor of a bank reform bill in the House of Representatives, wrote to the Independent Bankers Association of America, the small bank trade group, two weeks ago offering to exempt small banks from a provision allowing mixing of banks and commercial firms.</p>
<p>But the group rejected Baker's deal in a letter dated April 1.  </p>
<p>William Sones, the group's president, told the Louisiana Democrat that small banks were not worried about being bought up by bigger commercial companies.</p>
<p>Rather, the small banks worry that they will face unfair competition from huge conglomerates comprising large banks merged with large commercial firms.</p>
<p>&quot;Allowing massive concentration in our economic and financial system would be anticompetitive and would act to the detriment of the American consumer, small business, agriculture and the elderly,&quot; Sones wrote.  </p>
<p>As congress debates bank reform legislation, most agree that the Depression-era laws separating banking from other financial service industries should be scrapped. But there is little agreement about going further and allowing banks to combine with nonfinancial companies.</p>
<p>Small banks, along with House Banking Committee chairman Jim Leach and other groups, oppose any mixing of banking and commerce.</p>
<p>Rep Baker, along with Senate Banking Committee chairman Alfonse D'Amato, have favored allowing unlimited combinations.  </p>
<p>A third approach, contained in a bill sponsored by New Jersey Republican Rep Marge Roukema and Minnesota Democrat Bruce Vento, would place a limit on a bank's permitted non-financial activity. A bank could conduct 25 percent of its business, referred to as a &quot;basket,&quot; in nonfinancial activities under the Roukema-Vento bill.</p>
<p>Sones also rejected the basket approach in his letter to Baker. &quot;Even the fallback position of the 25 percent commercial business basket ... would have the same oligopolistic effect over time,&quot; he wrote.</p>
<p>Baker had suggested, in a letter to the group's executive vice president Ken Guenther, forbidding banks with less than $500 million in assets from being acquired by a commercial firm.</p>
<p>&quot;Is this 'small bank carve-out' approach one that your members would be able to support?&quot; Baker had asked in his letter.</p>
<p>--Aaron Pressman((202-898-8312))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
