<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478038" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. money managers to ride out rocky Dow road.</title>
<headline>U.S. money managers to ride out rocky Dow road.</headline>
<byline>Jeff Coelho</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Even though rising interest rate fears have trimmed the fat off the capital markets, some U.S. money managers said the equity and bond components of their portfolios will not shift drastically in the near future.</p>
<p>Several buy-side equity and fixed income fund managers said they had already priced in a higher interest rate scenario and any moves now would be &quot;too late.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The (Federal Reserve) did the right thing by taking the punch bowl away for part of the party here,&quot; said Graham Tanaka, president of Tanaka Capital Management.  </p>
<p>&quot;Maybe the Fed intends to take rates up another quarter point ... (but) that's not going to be a big deal,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tanaka, who manages $230 million in assets, said he has not made any significant changes in his allocations.</p>
<p>&quot;We've been expecting a larger correction in the blue chips ... and we felt the large cap 'Steady Eddies' were likely to have some profit taking.&quot;</p>
<p>Tanaka said it was too late to make changes now.</p>
<p>&quot;We've made changes in the past nine months,&quot; he said, referring to his exodus out of blue chip stocks.  </p>
<p>Indeed, over the past few weeks, the Dow Jones Industrial Average took a thrashing, falling from a high of 7158.28 on March 11 to a close of 6583.48 on Monday.</p>
<p>Similarly, in the past month, the 30-year Treasury bond yield has risen to about 7.10 percent from 6.80 percent on a closing basis.</p>
<p>&quot;Back on March 3 or 4, we moved (some) of our allocation customers to cash -- out of markets totally,&quot; said Harry Clark, president of Clark Capital Management, and manager of $350 million in assets. &quot;Our models are very close to saying, 'Go' again,&quot; he said, referring to a move back into stocks.  </p>
<p>Currently, Clark's U.S. domestic allocation weight is about 70 percent equity to 30 percent bonds.</p>
<p>&quot;We've been pretty much out of bonds. While we had the allocation, we kept the allocation in 3-month T-bills because we were afraid of the long-term bond market,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clark said intermediate-term paper looked attractive as fears of higher interest rates become absorbed.</p>
<p>&quot;You may see long bonds at 7.25 percent, not much more than that. I think 8.0 percent is ridiculous,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Some analysts cautioned that the recent decline in prices of both equities and T-bonds suggests market nervousness.  </p>
<p>&quot;You will probably have a period of several months of uncertainty in the market and that is not good for multiples on stocks or rates on bonds,&quot; said Alfred Kugel, senior investment strategist at Stein Roe.</p>
<p>&quot;Those who are the most exposed have been selling and those who have been a little more cautious are watchfully waiting,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;We may get a buying opportunity on both bonds and stocks ... but you need to have some evidence that the real strong growth we had in the first quarter is going to slow down,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>For now, experts are not discounting a five or even 10 percent correction in the broader equity market.</p>
<p>&quot;The (Dow) is going to have some more volatility than we're used to seeing,&quot; said Clark. &quot;We are vulnerable to go down to the low 6000s sometime from now to June. But I think we see a decent rally back up to maybe the 6900 to 7000 area. Then I think you will get a bigger fall,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>(( -- N.A. Treasury Desk, 212-859-1562 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
