<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478026" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: MSRB readies dealers for price transparency pilot.</title>
<headline>MSRB readies dealers for price transparency pilot.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board said Tuesday it requested information from bond dealers in preparation for a Jan 1, 1998, deadline aimed at vastly improving price dissemination in the municipal bond market.</p>
<p>The board said it sent a package of materials, including a 59-part question and answer pamphlet, this week to each broker, dealer and municipal securities dealer listed in board records.</p>
<p>The package asks for contact persons, details on the types of back office systems that firms have, and how they plan to communicated with the board.</p>
<p>MSRB needs the information to launch industrywide testing beginning in July 1997 of price dissemination by dealers to institutional and retail muni investors.</p>
<p>New MSRB rules already require dealers to report dealer-to-dealer trades to the board - a step that has not required few operational changes by dealers.</p>
<p>But beginning next January, all dealer-customer trades, including trades with institutional and retail buyers, must be reported daily to the board.</p>
<p>Information will be collected in a central data base that regulators can use to monitor price reporting in the muni market.</p>
<p>&quot;To report customer transactions, more extensive programming of back-office systems will be necessary,&quot; Christopher Taylor, executive director of the MSRB said in a cover letter for this week's mailing.</p>
<p>&quot;In brief, dealers will be responsible to provide to the MSRB each day a computer-readable file of their municipal transactions with customers.</p>
<p>--Vicky Stamas, 202-898-8314</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
