<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478005" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Debt may force Liggett to seek protection.</title>
<headline>Debt may force Liggett to seek protection.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Liggett Group Inc, a unit of Brooke Group Ltd, said the many &quot;risks and uncertainities associated with the cigarette industry&quot; could prompt it to seek protection from creditors under federal laws.</p>
<p>In an annual report filed Monday with the Securities and Exchange Commission, Liggett said if it is unable to refinance or restructure, substantially all of its long-term debt would be in default.  </p>
<p>Given the impact of recent tobacco litigation settlements and increased tobacco costs, there is no assurance Liggett will meet its future earnings goal, which could lead to it seek protection from creditors under applicable laws, the annual report said.</p>
<p>Liggett has a number of payments on senior secured notes due: a mandatory principal redemption of $37.5 million on February 1, 1998, and a payment at maturity on February 1, 1999, of 107.4 million, the filing said.  </p>
<p>On March 9, 1994, Liggett entered into a revolving credit facility for $40 million with a syndicate of commercial banks. As of December 31, 1996, $23.4 million was outstanding and is due March 8, 1998, it said.</p>
<p>While Liggett management currently intends to seek to refinance and/or restructure with Liggett note holders, there are no refinancing or restructuring arrangments for the notes.</p>
<p>Based on Liggett's net loss of 1996 and projected 1997 operating results, it does not anticipate it will be able to generate sufficient cash from operations to make the payments, the annual report said.  </p>
<p>&quot;These matters raise substantial doubt about Liggett's meeting its liquidity needs and Liggett's ability to continue as a going concern,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>As a result of Liggett's reorganization, it will cut its salaried, hourly and part-time employees by 35 percent, amounting to 273 positions, over an eight-month period, the report said.</p>
<p>In January 1997, Liggett began its restructuring program going to a decentralized enterprise with four strategic business units, each a profit center and a corporate headquarters from a centralized organization.</p>
<p>The restructuring is intended to more closely align sales and marketing strategies with the requirements of regional markets as well as reduce working capital by improved production of planning and inventory control, it said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
