<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478067" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: HealthRite Inc Q4 full results.</title>
<headline>HealthRite Inc Q4 full results.</headline>
<dateline>OWINGS MILLS, Md. 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Summary Income for Year Ended December 31, 1996</p>
<p>				     1996	  1995</p>
<p> Sales		     $16,504,000 $16,019,000</p>
<p> Margin			7,288,000   6,852,000</p>
<p> Income from Operations    455,000   (380,000)</p>
<p>Net Income to</p>
<p>  Stockholders		 283,000   (366,000)</p>
<p> Earnings Per Share	     0.07	(0.09)</p>
<p> Shares Outstanding	4,313,000   4,176,000</p>
<p>HealthRite Obtains Exclusive Nautilus</p>
<p>License</p>
<p>In 1996 HealthRite secured a nationwide exclusive three year license, extendable for an additional two years, to use the Nautilus(R) name for vitamins, minerals, and nutritional products including, but not limited to, weight gain and loss products.  Nautilus is a nationally known name in the sport nutrition industry through the well-known line of fitness and rehabilitation machines.  HealthRite is the only Nautilus licensee for the consumer products it offers under the Nautilus Nutritional(R) brand in the sports nutrition sector.</p>
<p>Nautilus Nutrition also are offered through HealthRite's chain of 14 retail stores in Pennsylvania, through Stow Mills and Tree of Life distributors to the health food sector and through stores like Osco, military exchanges and other sporting goods retailers.  Nautilus Nutritional products will also he offered through domestic and foreign fitness centers in a joint marketing effort between HealthRite and Nautilus International, Inc.  As an additional promotional effort HealthRite signed an agreement recently to become the major sponsor of the Nautilus Nutritionals/Barracuda professional mountain bike team. HealthRite Leases space from Wal-Mart for &quot;New&quot; TAKE SHAPE(R)</p>
<p>Nutrition Centers</p>
<p>HealthRite will test a new health food &quot;store within a super store&quot; concept called the TAKE SHAPE Nutrition Center. The first TAKE SHAPE Nutrition center will open in a Wal-Mart Supercenter located in Lewistown, Pennsylvania in mid-April 1997.  HealthRite intends to roll out additional TAKE SHAPE Nutrition Centers on military bases and other (leased department) locations later this year.</p>
<p>Montana Naturals International, Inc. Launches New Products</p>
<p>HealthRite's wholly owned subsidiary, Montana Naturals International, Inc. (&quot;Montana Naturals&quot;), manufactures and distributes, under its own name and on a private label basis, vitamins, minerals, teas and other wellness products. The Montana Naturals Pure Energy brand of instant teas won the People's Choice Award at the National Foods Association show. Other Montana Naturals products include Pure Energy, (bars, capsules, tablets), Montana Big Sky Royal Jelly and Pure Serenity (Kava Kava).  Montana Naturals contributed $7.3 million or 44% of HealthRite's consolidated revenues and was solidly profitable in 1996.</p>
<p>Jason Pharmaceuticals, Inc. -- A Leader in Physician-Supervised Weight</p>
<p>Loss Products</p>
<p>HealthRite's other wholly owned subsidiary, Jason Pharmaceuticals, Inc., (&quot;Jason&quot;) maintained its market share in its core business of offering physician-supervised weight loss programs.  Jason's Medifast(R) and TAKE SHAPE meal replacement programs were selected to be used in a new study on obesity conducted by the National Institutes of Health.  With the increasing popularity of prescription appetite suppressant medications among consumers, Jason will release a new anorexiant therapy protocol in April, 1997. This program will incorporate the Medifast and TAKE SHAPE products with prescription weight loss drugs to provide, for appropriate patient populations, an accelerated weight loss program with balanced nutrition.  From a financial standpoint in 1996 Jason sales were $4.9 million or 30% of HealthRite's consolidated revenues.  Jason also contributed substantially to Net Income.</p>
<p>HealthRite launched over 60 new product items during 1996 and expects to reap the benefits of its aggressive product development strategy. SOURCE  HealthRite, Inc.</p>
<p>-- New York Newsdesk 212 859-1610</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I64300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OWINGS MILLS, Md."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
