<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478177" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Future Fed moves limited, tied to mkt reax - Blinder.</title>
<headline>Future Fed moves limited, tied to mkt reax - Blinder.</headline>
<byline>Isabelle Clary</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bringing U.S. economic growth down to potential would require limited tightening and depend on the performance of long-term market rates, former Federal Reserve Vice Chairman Alan Blinder said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think this (economic strength) would require a modest amount of work if you consider trend growth to be more like 2.4 percent, just to pick a number,&quot; Blinder told Reuters.</p>
<p>U.S. Gross Domestic Product (GDP) grew by an average 2.8 percent over the six quarters ended in 1996, above the 2.0- to 2.5-percent range Fed officials describe as trend growth.  </p>
<p>&quot;You are not talking about a very big change in policy,&quot; predicted Blinder, who now holds the chair of economics at Princeton University.</p>
<p>Citing &quot;persisting strength in demand,&quot; and &quot;risk of inflationary imbalances,&quot; the Fed raised the federal funds rate by 25 basis points to 5.50 percent on March 25.</p>
<p>Since that first rate hike in two years, private analysts have been divided about the amount of tightening it would take to slow the economy to a non-inflationary pace.  </p>
<p>&quot;The Fed pinned the rationale (for the rate hike) more or less on concerns that aggregate demand -- that is to say economic activity -- has been growing too rapidly and will continue to do so,&quot; the former Fed vice chairman added.</p>
<p>Blinder pointed out that the real, inflation-adjusted funds rate already is on the restrictive side and that the extent of future rate hikes &quot;depends fundamentally on the reaction of the market.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;If you get a strong market reaction, this would require fewer monetary policy changes,&quot; predicted Blinder who pointed out that the economy responds more to changes in long-term market rates than in the fed funds or discount rates.</p>
<p>The 30-year bond yield averaged 6.70 percent in 1996 and backed up to 7.10 percent after the March 25 rate hike, or about 40 basis points.</p>
<p>&quot;That is not a very large difference and by itself would have a fairly small restraining effect on aggregate demand,&quot; Blinder  said. &quot;If you think aggregate demand has a lot of momentum, the bond rate has to go higher to do the job. But there is no magic number.&quot;  </p>
<p>A rule, known at the Fed as &quot;Greenspan's Rule,&quot; estimates that a one-basis-point rise in the bond yield, if sustained over one year, subtracts $1.0 billion from GDP.</p>
<p>&quot;From where we have been lately, getting to a 7.25-percent bond yield would add up to 50 to 60 basis points (to the average of last year), and that's a sizeable amount. Each additional basis point is a tiny little bit more of tighteness,&quot; Blinder also said.</p>
<p>&quot;The funds rate per se is not a very important interest rate. Part of the job of monetary policy is try to guess what a funds rate change would do to long bond rates,&quot; Blinder pointed out.  </p>
<p>Blinder hoped Fed Chairman Alan Greenspan would continue to signal his policy intentions as he recently did in testimonies before Congress and the Joint Economic Committee.</p>
<p>&quot;The Fed was unusually direct and explicit (in its rate announcement), and especially so before the interest rate increase,&quot; Blinder also said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was very clear in the Humphrey-Hawkins testimony that a primary concern of the Fed is tight labor markets that are liable to lead to inflation,&quot; Blinder added.</p>
<p>A tightening bias has been in place since July 1996 as the unemployment rate fell to 5.5 percent and never climbed back above this level. The Fed explained the lengthy bias as a way to convey to the market that the central bank was watchful for wage-related inflationary pressures.</p>
<p>&quot;This greater degree of openness is all for the better,&quot; added Blinder, a vocal proponent of increased transparency at the Fed during his tenure at the central bank.</p>
<p>(( -- 212-859-1666 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
