<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478174" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYS wins teachers fund support on tobacco - official.</title>
<headline>NYS wins teachers fund support on tobacco - official.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York State Comptroller said Tuesday the &quot;world's largest pension fund&quot; and other major institutional investors had agreed to back his shareholder resolution to curb teenagers from smoking.</p>
<p>McCall, the sole trustee of New York State's $80 billion retirement fund, said the Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association-College Retirement Equities Fund, along with the California State Teachers Retirement System, the New York City Pension Funds, and the Minnesota State Board of Investments all had agreed to support his resolution.  </p>
<p>RJR Nabisco and Lowes Corp agreed to include McCall's resolution in their proxy statements, but Phillip Morris and UST prevented shareholders from making their stand known, McCall said.</p>
<p>McCall, along with other institutional investors, linked his concerns to the tobacco companies' outlooks for earnings.</p>
<p>&quot;As a shareholder, I am concerned that the continuing controversy over this issue contributes to economic uncertainity, and this impacts these companies' profitability. I remain convinced that it is in the interests of shareholders' long-term interests to limit kids' access to tobacco,&quot; he explained, in prepared remarks. Last year, McCall directed the state fund to halt purchases of tobacco stocks, but kept investments in the industry held through index funds.</p>
<p>John Biggs, chairman of the Teachers' Insurance and Annuity Association-College Retirement Fund, in prepared remarks, said: &quot;The boards of the tobacco companies must understand that their shareholders expect them to take a long-term view of sharholder value, and that must include responding to the overwhelming public demand that they stop advertising to children, whether directly or subtly.&quot;</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150214">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
