<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478113" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: American Exploration battles US Gulf blowout.</title>
<headline>American Exploration battles US Gulf blowout.</headline>
<dateline>HOUSTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Crews on a pair of supply boats equipped with water cannons on Tuesday were battling to contain flames from a blowout in the Gulf of Mexico off the coast of Louisiana, a federal official said.</p>
<p>A drilling rig and production platform over natural gas and oil wells operated by American Exploration Co caught fire and a derrick collapsed in the blowout shortly after 0100 CST Tuesday, a company spokeswoman said.  </p>
<p>The blowout occured over wells in East Cameron 328, a shallow-water block located in federal waters about 115 miles off the coast of Louisiana, the spokesman said</p>
<p>Fifty one workers were evacuated safely and crews from the company, along with federal regulators and firefighters from International Well Control were at the scene, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I guess right now pople are assesing how to put the fire out and how to go from here,&quot; company spokesman Frank Murphy said of flames shooting 30 feet into the sky.  </p>
<p>Oil from the well formed a mile-long sheen that was dissipating, and little environmental damage was expected from the clean-burning, largely natural gas-fed fire, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;My understanding is there is considerable damage to the drilling rig and probably going to be significant damage to the production platform,&quot; Murphy said.</p>
<p>American Exploration acquired the field last year and had completed three in a series of production wells. The platform was producing 7 million cubic feet per day of natural gas and recently began production of 350 barrels of oil per day (bpd), which was expected to rise to 1,000 bpd, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The impact on us will be in delaying what we expected to be good oil production,&quot; Murphy said. &quot;What this event will do is delay what we had hoped will be a fairly substantial increase in oil and gas production in the second quarter.&quot;</p>
<p>((-- Houston Bureau ((713 210-8508))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HOUSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
