<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478145" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Allis-Chalmers pension underfunding hurts company.</title>
<headline>Allis-Chalmers pension underfunding hurts company.</headline>
<dateline>MILWAUKEE, Wis. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Allis-Chalmers Corp said Tuesday the company's underfunding of its pension plan continues to have an adverse material effect on the company.</p>
<p>Allis-Chalmers said it is in discussions with the Pension Benefit Guaranty Corp (PBGC) and the U.S. Internal Revenue Service, but its options include another bankruptcy filing.</p>
<p>The company said its underfunding of the consolidated pension plan increased on a present value basis to $15.1 million as of December 31. In addition, the company was required to pay minimum funding requirements starting in 1996.  </p>
<p>Allis-Chalmers said it made a $205,000 payment in January 1996, but as of December 31 $2.39 million in minimum funding was past due. In 1997, cash contributions and interest of $4.56 million are due.</p>
<p>&quot;Based on the company's limited financial resources to make contributions, this requirement for contributions continues to have a material adverse effect on the company,&quot; Allis-Chalmers said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;The company is not optimistic that, in its current condition, it will be able to raise additional capital to meet its obligations under the consolidated plan,&quot; it said.  </p>
<p>Allis-Chalmers filed with the PBGC to terminate the plan.</p>
<p>The company's failure to make the 1995 minimum payment to the consolidated plan resulted in a 10 percent excise tax liability. The company said that, to date, the IRS has not assessed the additional 100 percent tax, which may be imposed on the accumulated funding obligations of 1995, and additional taxes may be imposed for 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Although it is not possible to predict the outcome of discussions with the PBGC and IRS, the company's options include seeking protection from its creditors by commencing another bankruptcy filing,&quot; the company said.</p>
<p>In addition, Allis-Chalmers said it would be difficult to carry out a meaningful acquisition due to a lack of cash for investment, restrictions on debt refinancing, as well as the underfunding of the pension plan.</p>
<p>Earlier, Allis-Chalmers reported a fourth quarter loss of $0.54 a share versus a loss of $0.26 a share last year.</p>
<p>((--Chicago newsdesk, 312-408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILWAUKEE, Wis."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
