<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478287" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: BASEBALL-WHITE SOX, EXPOS SCRATCH OUT VICTORIES TO LAUNCH SEASON.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-WHITE SOX, EXPOS SCRATCH OUT VICTORIES TO LAUNCH SEASON.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Lords of baseball had to be smiling Tuesday as the schedule makers averted a blizzard of snow-outs, and the White Sox and Expos celebrated with a pair of close wins on Opening Day of the 1997 season.</p>
<p>Placing most teams in warm weather sites or in domed stadiums to start the season proved smart as the blizzard that surprised the Northeast Monday night failed to bury any baseball games.</p>
<p>Chicago was happy after rallying for a 6-5, 10-inning victory over the Toronto Blue Jays, and Montreal gave its home town fans reason to cheer with a ninth-inning run that gave the Expos a 2-1 victory over the St Louis Cardinals.</p>
<p>The season-opening slate was not without casualty, however, as the game between the Orioles and the Kansas City Royals in Baltimore was postponed due to high winds, wind chill and dropping temperatures. It will be played Wednesday.</p>
<p>In other early games, the Cincinnati Reds romped to an 11-4 victory over the visiting Colorado Rockies. The host Texas Rangers beat the Milwaukee Brewers 6-2.</p>
<p>Seven other games were scheduled, including the World Series champion New York Yankees' opener against the Mariners in Seattle.</p>
<p>The big money investment made by Chicago this off-season paid dividends right away as slugger Albert Belle homered and drove in three runs in his White Sox debut.</p>
<p>Belle's booming two-run homer off Cy Young winner Pat Hentgen in the eighth brought Chicago within a run of the Blue Jays at 5-4. Norberto Martin, who had one homer in 140 at-bats last season, shocked Toronto closer Mike Timlin with a pinch-hit homer in the ninth to tie it.</p>
<p>Chicago capped the comeback victory when speedy Ray Durham scored all the way from first on a ground single in the hole by Tony Pena that eluded shortstop Alex Gonzalez for an error and trickled into left field.</p>
<p>Roberto Hernandez retired the Blue Jays in order in the bottom of the 10th to record the save and disappoint a home crowd of 40,299 at the SkyDome.</p>
<p>Carlos Delgado and Gonzalez homered for Toronto.</p>
<p>In Montreal, pinch-hitter Sherman Obando walked with the bases loaded in the ninth to force Henry Rodriguez in with the winning run over last year's Central Division champion Cardinals.</p>
<p>Rondell White reached on an infield single to open the ninth and went to third on a single by Rodriguez off Tony Fossas. David Segui was intentionally walked to load the bases. One out later, Obando faced six pitches from Fossas and did not swing, finally drawing a walk on an inside pitch.</p>
<p>Ugueth Urbina (1-0) worked out of a jam in the ninth to earn the win.</p>
<p>The game attracted just 33,437 fans to Olympic Stadium, the Expos' smallest Opening Day crowd at home in 11 years. The Expos won on Opening Day for just the second time in six years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
