<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478252" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. corporate debt issues ready, stability craved.</title>
<headline>U.S. corporate debt issues ready, stability craved.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. high-grade corporate debt issuers are banking on some semblance of interest rate stability later this week when a bolt of large deals will be formally offered to investors, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The yields offered could be perceived as very attractive if we start to see (rates) level off a bit,&quot; one high-grade syndicate chief said. &quot;Things will be priced to sell.&quot;</p>
<p>But high-yield issuers may not get a reprieve from the recent deterioration in market tone until hemorrhaging of cash from high-yield mutual funds subsides, according to high-yield buysiders and syndicate officials.  </p>
<p>Still, a round of calls to high-yield syndicates found deals slated for Tuesday were still in the works despite the negative implications from the net selling from mutual funds over the past few days. But firm pricing dates were hard to come by as U.S. Treasury and stock markets headed lower.</p>
<p>Topping the list for Tuesday are $150 million in 10-year senior subordinated notes from Sterling Chemical Inc via Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
<p>&quot;The deal is in the market but they're also waiting to see how the market pans out before going further,&quot; said a source close to the Sterling deal.  </p>
<p>Several other deals slated for late this week include $100 million from Urohealth Systems Inc, $215 million from Del Monte Corp, and $100 million from Flextronics International.</p>
<p>On the buyside, some managers said the market was looking for more downside before the correction ebbs and forecasted more near-term selling. Much of that selling has and will be from recent new issues, one manager said, although its magnitude should ease.</p>
<p>&quot;The quickness of the (correction) is a surprise,&quot; the manager said. &quot;I was expecting the market would grind down as opposed to it falling off the table.  </p>
<p>&quot;The first ten-points are always the worst but I don't see the market snapping back anytime soon, either,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Back in the investment grade market, the onset of perhaps $2.5 billion in supply from J.C. Penney Co will dominate the week but that will be preceded by two large deals as early as Tuesday afternoon, dealers said.</p>
<p>Co-managers Morgan Stanley &amp; Co and UBS Securities are expected to bring $350 million in 30- and 100-year bonds to market from Noble Affiliates. Another $100 million in century bonds from Amgen will be issued through a Morgan Stanley and Merrill Lynch &amp; Co group.  </p>
<p>&quot;There really hasn't been any corporate issuance to test the market this week,&quot; one manager said. &quot;People are looking to these deals as a barometer.&quot;</p>
<p>Also due to price on Tuesday is $100 million in 10-year Yankee debt from Private Export Funding Corp through an ABN AMRO-led syndicate at or near a 23 basis point spread. The notes are guaranteed by Korea Export-Import Bank.</p>
<p>((--Al Yoon, 212-859-1672))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
