<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478296" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: SOCCER-BULGARIA WARY OF DROPPING POINTS AGAINST IMPROVED CYPRUS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BULGARIA WARY OF DROPPING POINTS AGAINST IMPROVED CYPRUS.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgaria need to avoid any slip-ups against Cyprus on Wednesday if they are to keep in touch with Israel and Russia at the top of World Cup qualifying group five.</p>
<p>Israel went to the top of the standings on Monday after beating Luxembourg 3-0 but Cyprus, who beat Israel earlier in the campaign, proved they are no longer a complete pushover by holding Russia to a 1-1 draw on Saturday.</p>
<p>Bulgarian national coach Hristo Bonev, who has a good knowledge of Cypriot soccer following his spell as coach of Apoel Nicosia said on Tuesday his side would not be under-estimating the visitors as the Russians did.</p>
<p>Cyprus, who have improved in recent years, will not only have to deal with a resolute home side, but also with some very cold weather which brought heavy snowfalls to Sofia over the Easter weekend.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that the weather conditions will create equal difficulties for both sides. I do not remember our guests playing under such conditions in their own country,&quot; Bonev said.</p>
<p>&quot;But we have several very technically able players and the weather could be both favourable and unfavourable for us,&quot; he admitted.</p>
<p>Bulgaria beat Cyprus 3-1 last December and will be looking to pick up another vaulable three points under the captaincy of defender Trifon Ivanov. The volatile Hristo Stoichkov, who is at odds with Bonev, misses the game.</p>
<p>The Cypriot squad arrived in Sofia without striker Sinica Gogic who scored against Russia on Saturday but misses Wednesday's match because of an injury he picked up in the game.</p>
<p>Cyprus will also be without the suspended Costas Malekkos. Their coach Stavros Papadopulous said his team's main objective was to try and prove Saturday's draw with Russia was no fluke by gaining at least a draw against the Bulgarians.</p>
<p>Probable teams:</p>
<p>Bulgaria: Zdravko Zdravkov; Trifon Ivanov, Radostin Kishishev, Ivailo Yordanov, Gosho Ginchev, Zlatko Yankov, Emil Kostadinov, Daniel Borimirov, Ilian Iliev, Krasimir Balakov, Georgi Donkov</p>
<p>Cyprus: Andreas Petrides; Georgios Theodotou, Charalambos Pittas, Nikolaos Timotheou, Sozos Yannaki, Angelos Misos, Neophytos Larcou, Nicodemos Papavassiliou, Marios Charalambous, Ioannis Okkas, Charalambos Andreou</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
