<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478293" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: SOCCER-BOSNIA PREPARES FOR HISTORIC HOME MATCH.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BOSNIA PREPARES FOR HISTORIC HOME MATCH.</headline>
<byline>Samir Koric</byline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bosnia will make soccer history when they play their first official home match against Greece in a World Cup qualifier on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Some 40,000 Sarajevans are expected to brave winter weather to watch their national team take on Greece in the Kosevo Olympic stadium in the Bosnian capital which was been left ravaged by almost four years of war.</p>
<p>FIFA, world soccer's ruling body gave Bosnia the go-ahead to play in the city which hosted the 1984 Winter Olympics in January after the team was forced to play its home matches in Bologna, Italy, last year.</p>
<p>The International Amateur Athletic Federation helped pave the way for a return of major sports when it held a peace meeting there at the end of last summer.</p>
<p>Bosnia hopes its two star strikers, Meho Kodro of Tenerife, and Elvir Bolic of Fenerbahce, will guide the team to victory against a Greek side which is currently top of group one with the relatively modest haul of seven points from four matches. Bosnia are still mathematically in the chase in a tightly-bunched group with three points from three games, but anything other than a win will probably spell the end of their hopes for a place in next year's finals. Greek coach Costas Polychroniou said it was not the first time his team was witnessing Bosnian soccer's development.</p>
<p>&quot;The Greek team writes football history for Bosnia-Herzegovina. The first official match that Bosnia ever played was against Greece ... and now the first official match they are playing in Bosnia is again against Greece,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Greece, he said were keenly aware that Bosnia had improved markedly since they lost 3-0 to them at the beginning of September.</p>
<p>Bosnian Coach Fuad Muzurovic said his team had gained confidence from its 2-1 victory against Slovenia in a qualifying match in November.</p>
<p>&quot;The victory in Slovenia gave us hope that we can make it. But even if we don't succeed, I'm certain we will create a strong team which will be a strong candidate for qualification in the upcoming European championship.&quot;</p>
<p>Probable teams:</p>
<p>Bosnia: Mirsad Dedic; Nermin Sabic, Bakir Besirevic, Edin Ramcic, Suad Katana, Murat Jasarevic, Vlatko Glavas, Sead Halilovic, Meho Kodro, Hasan Salihamidzic, Elvir Bolic</p>
<p>Greece: Ilias Atmatsidis; Stratos Apostolakis, Koulis Karataidis, Marions Ouzounidis, Yannis Kalitzakis, Theodore Zagorakis, Ilias Poursanidis, Vassilis Tsartas or Costas Frangeskos, Christos Kostis, Demis Nikolaidis, George Donis</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
