<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478269" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: SOCCER-GERMANY IN SEARCH OF SOLID VICTORY AGAINST ALBANIA.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-GERMANY IN SEARCH OF SOLID VICTORY AGAINST ALBANIA.</headline>
<dateline>GRANADA, Spain 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>European champions Germany face Albania on Wednesday in bad need of a solid victory to maintain their hopes of qualifying for next year's World Cup finals.</p>
<p>But the Germans, who have slipped up against the unrated Albanians in the past, are likely to benefit from the decision to move the group nine game to Spain because of the conflict which has hit Albania.</p>
<p>Tirana brings back bad memories for German fans, who saw their side held to a goalless draw in the Albanian capital which cost them a place in the 1968 European championship quarter-finals.</p>
<p>Even at home they struggled for a 2-1 victory in the opening phase of the 1984 competition and both games between the teams on the way to the Euro 96 also ended 2-1.</p>
<p>Albanian officials had hoped to play in Switzerland or Austria, where tens of thousands of German fans could have made the game a money-spinner, but say they are happy with FIFA's eventual choice of venue.</p>
<p>Even in Granada the Germans are likely to be backed by a sizeable number of supporters travelling from the nearby coastal resorts.</p>
<p>The match will provide a contrast to last Saturday's game with Ukraine, when journalists, officials, security guards and stadium staff outnumbered a crowd of only 250.</p>
<p>With goalkeeper Foto Strakosha in top form, Albania did well to keep the score down to 1-0 in that game.</p>
<p>But the Albanians clearly lack preparation and in one move had all but three players caught by the Ukrainian off-side trap.</p>
<p>As a consequence German coach Berti Vogts is under no illusions as to the kind of game he is expecting.</p>
<p>&quot;The game can be compared with a cup match between a Bundesliga side and a regional league team,&quot; Vogts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to change the way the table looks at the moment and we need three points to do that.&quot;</p>
<p>Vogts has allowed Bayern Munich midfielder Mario Basler to pull out of the squad, as the player's girlfriend is expected to give birth in the next few days.</p>
<p>Basler's place will be taken by recently naturalised Karlsruhe striker Sean Dundee, who was originally meant to travel with the squad only as a &quot;tourist&quot; to get to know the national team set-up.</p>
<p>The coach, who reported no major injury worries within the squad after a training session in Frankfurt, is considering playing three strikers in a bid to make sure Germany live up to expectations.</p>
<p>For Germany, striker Juergen Klinsmann will win his 95th cap, defender Juergen Kohler will win his 90th and sweeper Matthias Sammer his 50th for united Germany -- he also had 23 for East Germany.</p>
<p>Probable teams:</p>
<p>Albania - Foto Strakosha, Ghergji Dema,  Fatos Daja, Eduard Abazaj, Rudi Vata, Salvator Kacaj, Kliton Bozgo, Artan Bellai, Bledar Kola, Altin Rraklli, Fatmir Vata</p>
<p>Germany - Andreas Koepke, Matthias Sammer, Juergen Kohler, Stefan Reuter, Thomas Helmer, Christian Ziege, Dieter Eilts, Dariusz Wosz, Andreas Moeller, Juergen Klinsmann, Fredi Bobic.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GRANADA, Spain"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
