<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478286" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: HORSE RACING-ALDANITI MAY BE LAST LEGEND.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-ALDANITI MAY BE LAST LEGEND.</headline>
<byline>Dave Thompson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>First Red Rum and then Aldaniti. These folklore winners of the Grand National are now dead and it's arguable that both horses represent the last of the authentic Aintree legends.</p>
<p>Aldaniti, the winner 16 years ago, was to have led the traditional parade of former National winners before this year's race on Saturday.</p>
<p>But he died last week, amid sadness but prompting memories of one of the great comeback stories.</p>
<p>The horse himself recovered from a series of injuries and at the same time inspired jockey Bob Champion to fight off cancer, take the ride and claim their places in the record books.</p>
<p>Their exploits even led to a film which, to its credit, did the partnership ample justice.</p>
<p>But will one be made about Saturday's winner or those to come in future years? That's doubtful.</p>
<p>When Red Rum, who died in 1995, won three times in the 1970s to be followed by Aldaniti's success in 1981, the fences were, as they had been for decades, unique, tough, uncompromising and potentially lethal.</p>
<p>Then when several horses were killed in races during the 1980s in some spectacular falls, captured graphically by the ever-increasing refinements of television playbacks, calls for changes could not go unheeded.</p>
<p>Various alterations were made and Becher's Brook -- possibly the most famous fence in the world -- was made safer.</p>
<p>It still rates as the most formidable challenge of all for horse and jockey and traditionalists should take nothing away from the race.</p>
<p>Any combination which negotiates the 30 fences safely and avoids the mayhem around them has conquered the equine equivalent of Mount Everest.</p>
<p>But, you might say, Red Rum and Aldaniti and other great names like Golden Miller did it without oxygen.</p>
<p>Despite the safety improvements, horses still die on occasions and animal rights campaigners still campaign.</p>
<p>It was one such protest before the start of the 1993 National which caused a significant delay, unsettling horses, riders -- and the starter -- and contributing in part to the ultimate farce which saw two false starts and a void race.</p>
<p>It used to be 10-1 against a horse getting round Aintree, let alone winning it. 10-1 are about the current odds for Go Ballistic, favourite for Saturday's race after running well in the Cheltenham Gold Cup last month.</p>
<p>Perhaps now the balance is about right -- probably no deaths in the afternoon but no truly great heroes either.</p>
<p>Aldaniti may have been the last.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
