<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478270" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: TENNIS-TWO SEEDS FALL ON OPENING DAY AT HILTON HEAD ISLAND.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-TWO SEEDS FALL ON OPENING DAY AT HILTON HEAD ISLAND.</headline>
<dateline>HILTON HEAD ISLAND, South Carolina 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tenth seed Karina Habsudova of Slovakia and 15th seed Elena Likhovtseva of Russia suffered first-round defeats at the Family Circle Cup women's tennis tournament on Monday as the clay court season got underway.</p>
<p>Habsudova, ranked 12th in the world, fell to 53rd-ranked Alexandra Fusai of France 7-6 6-3.</p>
<p>The 19th-ranked Likhovtseva looked to have her match well in hand before 40th-ranked Italian Silvia Farina bounced back for a 1-6 6-3 6-4 victory.</p>
<p>Ninth-seeded Iva Majoli of Croatia, the highest seed to see opening-day action, struggled early but survived with a 4-6 6-4 6-4 victory over Canadian qualifier Rene Simpson.</p>
<p>Majoli said the adjustment from playing on hardcourts to the slow, soft clay gave her some early problems.</p>
<p>&quot;It takes some time to get used to, especially as far as sliding on the court,&quot; Majoli said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's easy to lose control of your feet. In the beginning, I was a little scared, but I got comfortable later on.&quot;</p>
<p>Hard-serving Dutchwoman Brenda Schultz-McCarthy, seeded 14th, had all she could handle from Elena Makarova.</p>
<p>The Russian, ranked a lowly 93rd in the world, kept Schultz-McCarthy on court for two hours and 20 minutes before the 14th seed finally prevailed 3-6 7-6 (7-2) 6-4.</p>
<p>The strong field is headed by 16-year-old Swiss sensation Martina Hingis, who is expected to play her first match as the number one player in the world on Tuesday night.</p>
<p>Hingis, who takes five titles and a 26-0 1997 match record into this event, opens against Germany's Barbara Rittner in the second round after receiving a first-round bye.</p>
<p>Monica Seles, who was crushed by Hingis in the Lipton Championships final Saturday, is also entered into this event.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HILTON HEAD ISLAND, South Carolina"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
