<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478227" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PP&amp;L puts transition costs at $4.6 bln. [CORRECTED 00:30 GMT 2/4]</title>
<headline>PP&amp;L puts transition costs at $4.6 bln. [CORRECTED 00:30 GMT 2/4]</headline>
<dateline>ALLENTOWN, Pa. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pennsylvanian Power &amp; Light Co said its Tuesday restructuring filing with Pennsylvania regulators estimates transition costs under the plan at $4.6 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;Our projections show PP&amp;L will fail to recover about $400 million of its transition costs,&quot; the PP&amp;L Resources Inc subsidiary said. It has deferred a decision on whether or not it will seek to securitieze any portion of the transisition costs approved by regulators, as allowed by Pennsylvania law.</p>
<p>It said the plan, based on charges in effect January 1, 1997, proposes no changes in rate levels.  </p>
<p>Pointing out its rates are below the Pennsylvania average PP&amp;L said its filing with the state Public Utility Commission caps rates for four and a half years.</p>
<p>Rates will be unbundled to show three main categories -- transmission and distribution, Generation and competitive transition charges, the utility said.</p>
<p>The CTC, Competitive Transition Charge, will be used to recover transition costs, its statement explained. This charge, which is subject to regulatory approval, is not an increase in rates, &quot;simply a restatement of costs currently paid by customers.&quot;  </p>
<p>It said most of the projected transition costs result from the construction of the Susquehanna nuclear power plant. Other components include environmental protection equipment for coal-fired plants, power purchases from non-utility generators and accounting-related charges resulting from certain financial and ratemaking practices under regulation.</p>
<p>The utility noted it had expected to recover investments over periods ranging up to 40 years. &quot;With competition coming to the business, that is no longer practical.&quot;</p>
<p>Taxes, which will be unchanged under Pennsylvania's restructuring legislation, will be blended in to all three categories, spokesman Dan McCarthy said.</p>
<p>(Corrects from: &quot;The Transmission &amp; Distribution Charge will include a listing of taxes, which will be unchanged under Pennsylvania's restructuring legislation...&quot;. Reflects McCarthy's correction).</p>
<p>PP&amp;L said the 4-1/2 year cap applies to distribution rates while it plans a nine year generation cost cap.</p>
<p>PP&amp;L said it plans to participate as a power supplier in its current service territory and elsewhere and is proposing separation of its generation and electricity sales function from the tgransmission and distribution function.</p>
<p>McCarthy said this would result in separate divisions within in the utility -- an unregulated generation and retail energy supply division with &quot;fire walls&quot; separating it from the regulated distribution division.</p>
<p>((-- Jim Brumm 212-859-1710.))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALLENTOWN, Pa."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
