<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478299" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: SOCCER-COLOMBIA HIT BY SUSPENSIONS FOR PARAGUAY MATCH.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-COLOMBIA HIT BY SUSPENSIONS FOR PARAGUAY MATCH.</headline>
<byline>Brian Homewood</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombia, who have led the South American World Cup qualifying tournament from the start, could be toppled on Wednesday when they travel to second-placed Paraguay with several key players suspended.</p>
<p>Third-placed Argentina head uphill to Bolivia after one of the most pain-staking preparations for a single match in their history, hoping to build on their 1-0 win away to Colombia in February.</p>
<p>Uruguay have a chance to revive their ailing aspirations with a home game against bottom-team Venezuela as the second half of the marathon competition, in which the nine teams play each other twice, gets under way.</p>
<p>The top four countries qualify for France and with eight games left each, only Venezuela, on one point, do not have a realistic chance of reaching the finals. Only three points separate Argentina and eighth-placed Peru.</p>
<p>However, the current standings could prove deceptive as some teams have played more home games than others.</p>
<p>Paraguay, whose only defeat was away to Colombia in their opening game, trail the leaders on goal difference and have won all their games so far in their intimidating &quot;Defenders of the Chaco&quot; stadium.</p>
<p>Inspired by goalkeeper-cum-marksman Jose Luis Chilavert, Paraguay are excellently placed to qualify for the first time since 1986, especially as they have five home games left.</p>
<p>Colombia, after the morale-shattering defeat against Argentina which cost them their unbeaten record, have to plug the holes caused by the suspensions of midfielder Freddy Rincon, full-back Wilmer Cabrera and defender Jorge Bermudez.</p>
<p>The trio, whose experience would have been invaluable in the Asuncion hothouse, all have two yellow cards. Coach Hernan Dario Gomez will also have to find a new striking parter for Faustino Asprilla as first choice Ivan Valenciano is ruled out through injury.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a very difficult game,&quot; Asprilla said last week. &quot;It is important that we start picking up points again.&quot;</p>
<p>Argentina will have to overcome the altitude of La Paz, 3,600 metres above sea level, and have been training in the bleak altiplano on their own side of the border for the last three weeks in preparation.</p>
<p>&quot;The players have completed the adaptation cycle,&quot; team doctor Eduardo Bellman said at the weekend. Only Ariel Ortega, who on Sunday was voted best player in the country in a survey by the daily newspaper Clarin, did not go through the full process.</p>
<p>The match revives memories of 1973 when Argentina beat Bolivia 1-0 with a team of non-regular internationals who were picked especially to play in La Paz and spent weeks training for the match.</p>
<p>The players, controversially, did not get to play in the World Cup and the team was known as &quot;the ghosts.&quot;</p>
<p>On this occasion, however, Argentina are taking their full-strength squad and can expect a hot reception after coach Daniel Passarella described conditions in La Paz as &quot;inhuman&quot; for soccer.</p>
<p>Ecuador, in fourth place, appear well placed to reach the World Cup for the first time but have not yet won a point outside their own country and play five of their remaining games away.</p>
<p>On Wednesday they travel to Peru, who they beat 4-1 at home last year. Peru themselves have four home games left.</p>
<p>In early 1995, the two nations were involved in a border conflict that killed dozens and injured hundreds. Because of this, the national anthems will not be played to avoid arousing nationalist passions.</p>
<p>Bolivia, two points behind Ecuador, have the biggest home advantage thanks to altitude but appear to have wasted it, having drawn four of their six home games. Victory against Argentina is essential to keep them in the race.</p>
<p>Two times world champions Uruguay, who trail Bolivia on goal difference, have only three home games left and appear to be in serious danger of missing out the World Cup for the second time running.</p>
<p>Beating Venezuela at home may restore confidence but is unlikely to help them much, as all the other teams also expect to pick up three teams against a team that is out of its depth.</p>
<p>Chile, one point below Uruguay and three below Ecuador, play six of their remaining games at home, where they have a 100 percent record so far. They are not involved in the action on Wednesday, when they travel to Brazil for a friendly.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
