<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478242" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NAPM's Ore--index suggests U.S growth can continue.</title>
<headline>NAPM's Ore--index suggests U.S growth can continue.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The National Association of Purchasing Management's (NAPM) March index, at its highest level in over two years, suggests that growth in the U.S. economy can continue, according to an NAPM executive.</p>
<p>In a teleconference with reporters after the NAPM released its March report, Norbert Ore, chairman of the NAPM Business Survey Committee, said, &quot;If you look at the strength in the PMI, it seem to indicate that we can continue to have that kind of growth.&quot;  </p>
<p>Ore said the overall U.S. economy was &quot;very sound,&quot; noting, however, that it was not on a &quot;sharp upward trend.&quot;</p>
<p>NAPM on Tuesday said its index of maufacturing activity rose to 55.0 in March from 53.1 in February. The prices index fell to 50.9 from 55.1 the prior month.</p>
<p>Ore said an NAPM index of 55.0 implies a 3.9 percent pace of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth. In the January to March period, the NAPM index averaged 53.4, suggesting a 3.3 percent rate of economic expansion, he added.</p>
<p>The March NAPM reading of 55.0 marks the highest level for the index since February 1995 when it also stood at 55.0.</p>
<p>Commenting on the prince component, Ore said, &quot;Basically, we've been in a deflationary period as far as industrial prices are concerned. I think it's a reasonable expectation that we somewhat stay in a deflationary period.&quot;</p>
<p>(( -- N.A. Treasury Desk, 212-859-1660 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
