<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478297" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: SOCCER-POPESCU ADDS &quot;SCORER&quot; STRING TO HIS FIDDLE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-POPESCU ADDS &quot;SCORER&quot; STRING TO HIS FIDDLE.</headline>
<byline>Radu Timofte</byline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>At the age of 30 and at the peak of his career, Romania's midfield linchpin Gheorghe Popescu has added the status of goalscorer to his already huge reputation.</p>
<p>Fans were left delighted and sports commentators bemused last weekend when the Barcelona captain notched four slick goals in a World Cup qualifier win against Liechtenstein.</p>
<p>And there will be more to come from &quot;Gica&quot; when his playing days are over. Popescu plans to channel his efforts back into Romanian football.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll settle back home after I hang up my soccer boots,&quot; said the player who last year bought an obscure third division club in his homeland.</p>
<p>Popescu's four goals in Romania's 8-0 rout of Liechtenstein consolidated his side's record 18 goals in four preliminaries played in their eighth group games.</p>
<p>&quot;It' great to have been able to contribute to my team's victory,&quot; he said modestly.</p>
<p>&quot;But I'm a little disappointed to not have been able to beat a national record that has been standing for more than a half of a century.&quot;</p>
<p>He was referring to the record set by striker Rudy Wetzer, who scored five goals in one game, when Romania beat Greece 8-1 in Bucharest in 1930.</p>
<p>The recent 8-0 victory over Liechtenstein was the second biggest win in Romanian history after the 9-0 defeat of Finland in a World Cup qualifier in 1973.</p>
<p>&quot;My generation's team, the national team of Romania of the 1990s, deserves to set such a new record,&quot; Popescu said.</p>
<p>The midfielder has been a cornerpiece of Romania's &quot;dream team&quot; -- the most successful Romanian side in history after reaching the quarterfinals of the 1994 World Cup, beating Argentina and Colombia along the way.</p>
<p>Always a good sportsman on and off the field, Popescu is never slow to give credit where credit is due.</p>
<p>&quot;Three of my goals against Liechtenstein were due to Gheorghe Hagi, who often encouraged me to be more offensive during the game,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>As well as a lifetime friendship with Hagi, Popescu shares a nickname -- Gica -- with his national team-mate, now in midfield at Turkey's Galatasaray.</p>
<p>While the dazzling Hagi earned the nickname of the &quot;Maradona of the Carpathians&quot; for his skills on the pitch, Popescu, a powerful and balanced player with proven leadership skills, has been dubbed &quot;The Shepherd&quot; by his Romanian team-mates.</p>
<p>Living up to his reputation, Popescu has captained Barcelona for the past two years.</p>
<p>He made his international debut in 1990 and the Dutch spotted him during the Italian World Cup that year. He was signed by PSV Eindhoven where he was an instant success and proved a perfect replacement for Ronald Koeman.</p>
<p>Again following in the footsteps of the Dutch midfielder, he replaced Koeman at Barcelona in 1995, after a short spell with Tottenham in England.</p>
<p>On Wednesday Romania play in Lithuania in another World Cup qualifier, but the real test for Romania will come on April 30, when they meet the Republic of Ireland at home.</p>
<p>&quot;What matters now is not the score against Lithuania, as much as to beat them and snatch the three points we need,&quot; Popescu said before flying with his team to the Lithuanian capital Vilnius on Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LIECHT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
