<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478237" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Strong NAPM sign of vibrant economy, validates Fed.</title>
<headline>Strong NAPM sign of vibrant economy, validates Fed.</headline>
<byline>Steven Scheer</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>If the Federal Reserve needed validation for last week's interest rate hike, it got it on Tuesday morning after the latest data showed the manufacturing sector continues to thrive.</p>
<p>And as a result, the Fed might not be able to wait until July to hike rates again, making May 20 the next target date, analysts said.</p>
<p>The National Association of Purchasing Management reported that its overall index rose to 55.0 in March from 53.1 in February.  </p>
<p>New orders, supplier deliveries, employment and new export orders indices also posted gains.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly, these numbers are pointing to stronger growth through the second quarter,&quot; said David Jones, chief economist at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Co. &quot;We are looking at three consecutive (quarters) of three to four percent growth.</p>
<p>&quot;That's far in excess of the economy's longer term growth potential,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A strong NAPM report was expected, but the magnitude of the main index's rise caught some off guard. A Reuters poll had showed a consensus forecast for a 53.6 reading in March.  </p>
<p>In addition to the NAPM, the Commerce Department reported on Tuesday a 2.3 percent rise in construction spending in February -- its largest gain since March 1996.</p>
<p>The index of leading indicators, meanwhile, rose 0.5 percent in February, the index's biggest rise since February of last year.</p>
<p>&quot;Does the data validate what the Fed did? Absolutely,&quot; said Michael Strauss, chief economist at Sanwa Securities Co, referring to last Tuesday's 25 basis point rate hike. &quot;It suggests risks are there that there will be more than one tightening.&quot;  </p>
<p>U.S. Treasuries initially weakened on the trio of bond-bearish data, but players said an oversold environment capped any losses. About an hour after the 1000 EST/1500 GMT release of the data, the 30-year bond was up 3/32.</p>
<p>&quot;We have very strong data here,&quot; Strauss said. &quot;The bond market might not be acting negatively to it, but it shows strong economic activity is continuing.&quot;</p>
<p>Part of the market's response was said to be tied to the decline in the NAPM prices index to 50.9 in March from 55.1 in February.  </p>
<p>However, economists pointed out that the Fed is not looking at price measures as much as demand indicators. One of Fed Chairman Alan Greenspan's favorite components, supplier deliveries, rose to 53.6 in March, up from 51.3 in February. The index is at its highest since May 1995.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the six-point-plus rise in the employment index to 51.6 pushed the indicator to its highest level since September 1994. New orders rose to 60.3 from 57.7.</p>
<p>&quot;Even though there are no pressures on the price side, it is probably pointing to higher wage and product prices in the future,&quot; Jones said.  </p>
<p>Also posting gains were new export orders, up more than five points to 57.3, and inventories, up 2.5 points to 43.7.</p>
<p>Indexes that fell in March included production, down to 56.8 from 59.5 and imports, which fell to 48.8 from 50.9.</p>
<p>Despite those declines, the data underscored the need for the Fed to remain ahead of the curve, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking at three 'quarter-point' moves,&quot; Jones said. &quot;I don't think they can wait for July. We'll see another (tightening) May 20.&quot;</p>
<p>(( -- N.A. Treasury Desk, 212-859-1867 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
