<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478268" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: SOCCER-SUSPENSION FORCES SUKER OUT OF CROATIA-SLOVENIA QUALIFER.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-SUSPENSION FORCES SUKER OUT OF CROATIA-SLOVENIA QUALIFER.</headline>
<dateline>SPLIT, Croatia 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Croatia will miss several key players, including top scorer Davor Suker, for Wednesday's World Cup qualifier against underdogs Slovenia.</p>
<p>Croatia, currently third in the tightly-bunched group one, must beat the visitors, who have lost their three opening qualifiers, to keep the pressure on Greece and Denmark who top the group.</p>
<p>Croatia drew 1-1 with Denmark on Saturday -- their second home slip after managing only a 1-1 draw with Greece -- and anything other than a win on Wednesday would leave them fcing an upward struggle to qualify for the 1998 World Cup in France.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to beat the Slovenes. We are in a difficult position now, plagued by injuries, and we cannot afford any more slips,&quot; coach Miroslav Blazevic said.</p>
<p>Suker, Croatia and Real Madrid's top scorer, will miss the game after picking up a second yellow card on Saturday while stopper Zvonimir Soldo of VfB Stuttgart is out after injuring a knee in the same game.</p>
<p>Goran Vlaovic of Valencia will take Suker's place in the attack next to Alen Boksic of Juventus, while young defender Dario Simic of Croatia Zagreb is a most likely substitute for Soldo.</p>
<p>There is no place for goalkeeper Drazen Ladic, blamed for the mistake which allowed Brian Laudrup to equalise eight minutes from the end of Saturday's match with a long-range speculative shot.</p>
<p>Ladic will be replaced by Hajduk Split's Tonci Gabric.</p>
<p>Earlier last week, Blazevic was left without defenders Igor Stimac of Derby County and Mario Stanic of Parma because of injuries.</p>
<p>To add to Blazevic's problems, Robert Jarni is doubtful with a back injury.</p>
<p>The Slovenes believe they can upset the Croatians playing a defensive game and looking for breaks on the counter-attack.</p>
<p>&quot;It is true that Croatians are favourites and that the quality of their team is better. But if we could surprise Austria, why we could not do it to Croatians.</p>
<p>&quot;Our goal is at least a point, but it will be no tragedy if we lose,&quot; coach Zdenko Verdenik said. Slovenia beat Austria 2-0 in a recent friendly. Probable line-ups: Croatia: Tonci Gabric; Nikola Jerkan, Slaven Bilic, Dario Simic, Robert Jarni, Niko Kovac, Aljosa Asanovic, Zvonimir Boban, Robert Prosinecki, Alen Boksic, Goran Vlaovic Slovenia: Bosko Boskovic: Robert Englaro, Miran Srebrnic, Ales Krizan, Dzoni Novak, Marinko Galic, Ales Ceh, Saso Udovic, Zlatko Zahovic, Primoz Gliha, Ermin Siljak.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SPLIT, Croatia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
