<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478398" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: LIEPAJA METALURGS TO GET INVESTMENT, EYES BOURSE.</title>
<headline>LIEPAJA METALURGS TO GET INVESTMENT, EYES BOURSE.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Liepajas Metalurgs, the only metal producer in Latvia, said on Tuesday that its majority owner Agrosin has decided to invest $5.5 million in upgrading its rolling-mill and it is considering a bourse listing.</p>
<p>&quot;The reconstruction has to be completed by August, September,&quot; managing director of the plant, Valerii Terentjev, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We will thus be able to produce finer grade rolled metal sheets, for which there is more demand,&quot; he demanded.</p>
<p>Metalurgs is also considering a listing on the stock exchange but it has not decided which list, the official list or the secondary list.</p>
<p>&quot;The intention is there but the final decision on when and which list will be taken by the shareholders general meeting,&quot; Terentjev added.</p>
<p>The meeting is to take place at the end of April but a date has not yet been set.</p>
<p>The contoling stake of Liepaja was bought by the Russian, Belorussian, Singapore joint venture late last year and according to privatisation regulations it had to invest some $5.5 million during the next three years.</p>
<p>Agrosin owns 72 percent of Liepajas and it employs 2,400 workers. The company says it exports 95 percent of its output.</p>
<p>Liepajas produced 290,000 tonnes of rolled steel last year and plans to produce 445,000 tonnes of rolled steel in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;We feel much more secure with the new investor, having solved the problems of financing and scrap metal deliveries, which is our main raw material,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The company's main export market is South East Asia, North Africa and the U.S..</p>
<p>-- Martinsh Gravitis, Riga newsroom +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
