<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478308" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NCAA BASKETBALL-KENTUCKY DEFENSE NO PROBLEM FOR YOUNG ARIZONA CHAMPIONS.</title>
<headline>NCAA BASKETBALL-KENTUCKY DEFENSE NO PROBLEM FOR YOUNG ARIZONA CHAMPIONS.</headline>
<byline>Gary Hill</byline>
<dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Indiana 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Young, fearless and uncannily quick, the Arizona Wildcats scarcely blinked at the normally intimidating pressure defence of Kentucky, and so took away the defending champions' college basketball crown.</p>
<p>&quot;They did a great job of handling our pressure,&quot; said Kentucky high scorer Scott Padgett after Arizona's 84-79 overtime victory Monday night. &quot;Before the game they said they could do it.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously they really worked on handling our pressure, and they went out there and they kept their cool, and they didn't rush things, and that's why they handled our press so well.&quot;</p>
<p>The key to breaking Kentucky's fullcourt press was 19-year-old freshman Mike Bibby, whose speed while dribbling often had him racing downcourt ahead of the two or three Kentucky players who had tried to trap him in the backcourt.</p>
<p>But Bibby, who scored 19 points, had four assists, snared an astonishing team-high nine rebounds and got three steals, had plenty of help against the press.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically I think our guys, we kept coming to the ball,&quot; said team leader Miles Simon, voted the Final Four's most outstanding player after he scored 30 points in the final.</p>
<p>&quot;We never floated away from Mike if he was in trouble. And we saw one thing when we watched the tapes -- that we could break the press down off the dribble and we could basically get to almost halfcourt and get skip passes. And our spacing was just tremendous.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody just kind of worked together on their team when it came to the press, and they never really got tired, and they just kept it up,&quot; said Kentucky star Ron Mercer.</p>
<p>&quot;We've been working on the press since day one when we came to practice,&quot; said Bibby, who exemplifies Kentucky coach Rick Pitino's description of the Arizona players as too young to know they should be nervous.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the greatest competition is what we see every day and that's in practice,&quot; added Bibby. &quot;And our team is just so quick out there.&quot;</p>
<p>Quick indeed. Pitino had conceded his team was not as quick in the frontcourt, but it turned out the Kentucky guards were not as quick as their Arizona counterparts either.</p>
<p>Pitino confessed he had wanted to change Kentucky's usual strategy for this game. &quot;If I had any druthers tonight -- we didn't press the first 5 1/2 minutes of the game -- I wouldn't have pressed at all if we could get the pace a little higher.&quot;</p>
<p>But eventually, Kentucky had to revert to its usual tactics, to no avail.</p>
<p>&quot;I think they came out and tried to fool us at the beginning. They didn't press for the first couple of minutes,&quot; said Simon.</p>
<p>&quot;But we knew it was going to come eventually. They pressed the whole game. And one thing, they were not getting turnovers and easy baskets off of it. And continually we were able to break it and break it. And eventually, running 94 feet the whole game, they were going to get tired.</p>
<p>&quot;And I think at the end you could see they were dragging a little bit.&quot;</p>
<p>Arizona coach Lute Arizona revealed that, even though his players had never faced a true pressing team during the season, they practiced against it every day.</p>
<p>Added Olson, who won his first national championship in four trips to the Final Four and Arizona's first in three: &quot;It was definitely a cat fight, I'll tell you that. I'm not sure that two teams could expend more energy than these two teams did. Shots were difficult to come by.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we made it difficult for them to get the shots.&quot;</p>
<p>In the end, people were talking about Arizona's defence, not Kentucky's.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought Kentucky did a great job early of adjusting to what we were doing defensively and you saw them get some interior feeds and easy baskets on us,&quot; said Olson.</p>
<p>&quot;So what we did is we just said: OK, guards, you have got to get through that screen. And if you don't get through the screen, then the big guys have got to recognise that and we've got to make the switch, because in most cases the switch is followed by a pop-out to the three-point line....</p>
<p>&quot;It's like, OK, we need to do this, we need to adjust this way. And you can talk about it from a coaching standpoint but if the players are not alert and communicating then you're going to have problems.&quot; But Olson's players executed.</p>
<p>Arizona was especially effective in shutting down Ron Mercer, the scoring star heading for the NBA after just two seasons at Kentucky.</p>
<p>&quot;One thing on Mercer,&quot; said Simon, &quot;we knew he was going to curl-cut (off screens) a lot, and that's exactly what he did. Our objective was to fight around the screens and be there when they caught the ball.</p>
<p>&quot;And our big men, if we (the guards) got caught for a second, they were heading out and helping us tremendously.&quot;</p>
<p>Mercer wound up getting off just nine shots, making five and totalling only 13 points. He admitted: &quot;They made it tough for me to score.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INDIANAPOLIS, Indiana"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
