<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478359" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVAKIA: SLOVAK PM SCUTTLES PRAGUE TRIP OVER CZECH ATTITUDE.</title>
<headline>SLOVAK PM SCUTTLES PRAGUE TRIP OVER CZECH ATTITUDE.</headline>
<byline>Jan Krcmar</byline>
<dateline>BRATISLAVA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Slovak Prime Minister Vladimir Meciar's visit to Prague planned for this month will probably be postponed over recent criticism of Bratislava by Czech media and politicians, his spokeswoman said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The prime minister (Meciar) considers the postponement of his visit as correct in view of the given political and media campaign in the Czech Republic,&quot; spokeswoman Magda Pospisilova told a news conference during a regular government session.</p>
<p>Pospisilova said Meciar was reacting to recent statements by Czech President Vaclav Havel and Premier Vaclav Klaus on Meciar's planned trip to Prague, which would have been his first since the split of the Czechoslovak federation in 1993.</p>
<p>The Czech CTK news agency last week quoted Havel as saying Meciar was welcome but that he would also be told things he might not want to hear.</p>
<p>It also quoted Klaus as saying his government had more important things to do than to prepare for a Meciar visit.</p>
<p>The two countries split and became independent after 75 years of life as Czechoslovakia in which the larger Czech part played the dominant role.</p>
<p>The main purpose of the visit, which has not yet been officially cancelled, was to sign final agreements on the controversial division of property of the former federation.</p>
<p>A statement by the Slovak foreign ministry issued on Friday already signalled that Bratislava was upset with Prague.</p>
<p>&quot;The Slovak side is concerned over the atmosphere in the Czech Republic which is lately increasingly... influencing the preparations (of the visit),&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;Some Czech politicians, even after four years of the existence of an independent Slovak Republic, have been unable to rid themselves of the feeling of superiority and tutelage on the basis of which they comment on internal political events in their neighbouring country in a manner which is impermissible in the relations of two sovereign states,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Some Czech politicians and commentators have criticised the Meciar government for its handling of recent strikes by actors and students and the recent forcible break-up by police of a culture ministry sit-in by protesting actors who called for the dismissal of culture minister Ivan Hudec.</p>
<p>The Slovak foreign ministry said the meeting with the Czechs must have &quot;suitable prerequisites and an adequate atmosphere.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The Slovak side remains interested in settling remaining open questions in mutual relations, it added.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRATISLAVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVAKIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
