<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478394" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: INTERVIEW - CSOPAK PINS HOPES ON DEMAND RISE.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - CSOPAK PINS HOPES ON DEMAND RISE.</headline>
<byline>Emese Bartha</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungary's Csopak Rt is going ahead with plans to become an increasingly trading-oriented group, founded on hopes of a recovery in domestic consumption, CEO Gyorgy Markovszky told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation may change within three years with domestic consumption beginning to grow strongly and certainly only those who have already established themselves will be in a position to meet consumer demand,&quot; he said in an interview.</p>
<p>For 1997 the group expects an over 900 million forint consolidated pre-tax profit on sales of 18 billion forints, he said. In 1996 the group had a pre-tax profit of 371.2 million forints on sales of 8.61 billion.</p>
<p>After the U.K.-based East European Food Fund had acquired a just over 30 percent stake in Csopak by subscribing a 700-million forint new share package, the group which operates in the western part of Hungary, speeded up its trade-linked investments.</p>
<p>The investment brought the group's issued share capital to 2.2 billion in mid-December.</p>
<p>&quot;Processes have started which are re-orienting Csopak into a trading group from its classic role as a holding company,&quot; Markovszky said.</p>
<p>As part of the change, Csopak boosted its stake in Forum Rt trading company to 75 percent plus one share and acquired 100 percent of Chance 96 Kft, which holds more than 99 percent of retail trading company Pannonker Kft.</p>
<p>Also earlier this year, a consortium made up of Balaton Invest 96 Kft - which is owned by the managements of Csopak and Balaton Fuszert - and of Dunantuli Befektetesi Consortium, which includes Hungarian food industrial companies, acquired a 50 percent plus one share stake in Balaton Fuszert.</p>
<p>Asked about future relations with Balaton Fuszert, whose privatisation had failed several times, Markovszky said the two companies had launched a mutually advantageous common supply strategy.</p>
<p>&quot;We have also set up a joint strategic business policy which means the two companies will gradually move closer to each other,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Csopak's plans for 1997 include the consolidation of earlier acquisitions rather than going ahead with news ones, the CEO said.</p>
<p>&quot;With the exception of Balaton Fuszert we'd like to merge the trading companies in a time shorter than medium term so that we can appear as an integrated organisation.&quot;</p>
<p>Csopak which will hold its annual general meeting on April 26 will ask its shareholders' approval to merge four of its subsidiaries into the group.</p>
<p>Also at the general meeting local government shareholders of household chemicals trading subsidiary Komfort Rt will exchange their Komfort shares for Csopak shares, raising Csopak's share capital by up to 250 million forints.</p>
<p>Asked about the future of group member Anaconda cosmetics industrial unit which had a consolidated sales revenue of 450 million forints last year almost exclusively on the Hungarian market, Markovszky said Csopak was negotiating to find a strategic investor for Anaconda.</p>
<p>&quot;If we favour growth then we will need an international strategic investor,&quot; Markovszky said. &quot;The Hungarian market is small as a cosmetics market -- only Hungarian companies who also supply international markets will survive.&quot;</p>
<p>As for Csopak's bakery activity centering around Gyori Sutopipari Kft, plans include further expansion, not only geographically but also in terms of the product range, Markovszky said.</p>
<p>-- Budapest newsroom +36 1 327-4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
