<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478317" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: BASKETBALL-OLYMPIAKOS BEAT CHAMPIONS TO ADVANCE TO FINAL FOUR.</title>
<headline>BASKETBALL-OLYMPIAKOS BEAT CHAMPIONS TO ADVANCE TO FINAL FOUR.</headline>
<byline>Costas Paris</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greek champions Olympiakos advanced to Rome's Final Four on Tuesday with a second straight EuroLeague quarter-final win against titleholders and bitter rivals Panathinaikos .</p>
<p>Thousands of Olympiakos fans at the packed 17,000-seat Peace and Friendship Stadium stormed inside the court to celebrate the 65-57 victory, raising players to their shoulders amid a host of red and white balloons, the club's colours.</p>
<p>&quot;Buy your tickets for Rome now,&quot; speakers inside and out the stadium urged the jubilant fans who later headed to central Athens squares for an all-night party with champagne and beer.</p>
<p>Olympiakos, finalists in 1994 and 1995, put on a show of class and strength in the second half, scoring at will from outside the D with playmakers Milan Tomic (17 points, three triples), David Rivers (11 points) and guard George Sigalas (12 points) all on target.</p>
<p>It was their second straight European triumph against arch-rivals Panathinaikos in six days after winning the first leg quarter-final away by the surprising margin of 69-49.</p>
<p>Panathinaikos, the most expensive club in Europe,  battled well until halftime, when they led 39-37, but they were nervous in the second half, with their usual top marksman, American playmaker Byron Dinkins, scoring only two points while their other top gun, German guard Michael Koch, was pointless.</p>
<p>Spanish forward Feran Martinez top-scored for the visitors with 20 points but he fought alone against the taller Olympiakos front line and ran out of speed towards the end.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a great night for us,&quot; Olympiakos' Serb coach Dusan Ivkovic said.</p>
<p>No tickets were given to Panathinaikos fans to avert clashes. There had been no Olympiakos supporters at the first leg.</p>
<p>Panathinaikos had the best record in this season's expanded EuroLeague with 13 wins in 16 games while Olympiakos (9 wins, 7 defeats) suffered several surprising reverses.</p>
<p>But Olympiakos recovered in recent weeks showing their strength with away wins against Russia's CSKA, and Yugoslavia's Partizan Belgrade to reach the quarter-finals.</p>
<p>Both clubs are regulars at the Final Four. Olympiakos beat Panathinaikos twice in the 1994 and 1995 tournament, but Panathinaikos managed to clinch their first title last season, against Barcelona.</p>
<p>Olympiakos will play either Stefanel Milan or Ljubljana in the Rome semifinal, on April 22.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
