<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478337" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: ACCOUNTING MOVES PUSH CZECH SPT TO LOSS.</title>
<headline>ACCOUNTING MOVES PUSH CZECH SPT TO LOSS.</headline>
<byline>Alan Crosby</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>SPT Telecom a.s., the Czech Republic's main telephone operator, on Tuesday said it posted a 483 million crown 1996 net loss as the company made one-off moves to provision itself against structural changes.</p>
<p>SPT Chief Financial Officer Urs Kamber told journalists that the firm posted the loss, according to international accounting standards (IAS), due to one-time extraordinary charges of 8.757 billion crowns.</p>
<p>&quot;We are driving toward the fact that we will face tougher, real competition. The way to face this efficiency (of competitors) is by being operationally efficient ourselves,&quot; Kamber said. &quot;We felt the firm was at a point where we could take these charges now.&quot;</p>
<p>Despite the drop in profit, SPT posted a 1995 IAS net profit of 4.83 billion crowns, analysts applauded the move, saying it could help the company down the road.</p>
<p>&quot;The move makes sense. It appears as though they are trying to optimalise their tax position and I don't think it has anything to do with the functioning of the company or the quality of earnings,&quot; said Jan Sykora of Wood and Company.</p>
<p>&quot;If the loss is its final results, it can be carried forwad for the next seven years, so it's a good thing to clean the balance sheet and have a tax shield for the next couple of years,&quot; added one Prague analyst.</p>
<p>In explaining the loss, Kamber said 1.752 billion crowns was provisioned as the firm prepares for layoffs and restructuring that should see SPT shed some 10,000 of its current 26,800 workforce by the year 2000.</p>
<p>He said that SPT hopes to layoff some 5,000-6,000 employees through job redundancies as it moves to digitalisation which is less labour intensive, with the additional losses coming through attrition, currently at about 12 percent annually.</p>
<p>He added that a 7.005 billion crown impairment charge was also recorded including &quot;a reduction of the accumulated depreciation accounted for in the 1993 opening accounts under IAS&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;In light of our activities in 1996, I am pretty happy with the results&quot; Kamber said adding the firm should return to profitability in 1997.</p>
<p>Kamber said that costs had risen more than expected in 1996, especially in the area of wage growth, but this was in line with the wage growth throughout the country.</p>
<p>Nominal industrial wages rose 17.4 percent, year-on-year, in 1996, and has become one of the key economic points, with both the government and central bank saying something must be done to curb wages in 1997.</p>
<p>Total staff costs at SPT hit 6.24 billion crowns in 1996, up from 4.83 billion for the previous year. Total 1996 operating costs were 18.31 billion, up from 13.76 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;We had to install some 417,000 lines in 1996, and the work that it took...from a planning and cost standpoint were tremendous,&quot; Kamber said.</p>
<p>He added that at the end of 1996, phone lines per employee were 108, but that the number should rise to over 300 per employee by the year 2000.</p>
<p>He said that SPT hopes to install another 450,000 new lines in 1997, with revenues projected to rise by about 20 percent.</p>
<p>SPT is currently seeking a credit rating from Standard and Poor's, to give the firm &quot;more borrowing flexibility&quot;, though no international bond issue for this year has yet been approved.</p>
<p>Long distance revenues accounted for 70 percent of revenues, he said adding that domestic charges would slowly rise, and eventually create a more balanced distribution of revenues.</p>
<p>-- Prague Newsroom, 420-2-2423-0003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
