<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478309" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NHL-LEMIEUX MOVES UP ALL-TIME GOALS LIST IN PITTSBURGH WIN.</title>
<headline>NHL-LEMIEUX MOVES UP ALL-TIME GOALS LIST IN PITTSBURGH WIN.</headline>
<dateline>PITTSBURGH 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mario Lemieux moved up the NHL all-time goal scoring list and helped his team move up in the race for playoff positions in leading his Pittsburgh Penguins to a 4-3 victory over the Florida Panthers on Monday.</p>
<p>Lemieux and Jaromir Jagr each had a goal and an assist as the Pengins scored the game's first three goals and held on for a narrow victory.</p>
<p>Lemieux's powerplay goal with 90 seconds left in the second period gave Pittsburgh a 4-2 lead, but it turned out to be the game winner after Rob Neidermayer scored for Florida at 7:36 of the third to make it a one-goal game.</p>
<p>The goal was the 47th of the season for Lemieux and number 610 of his brilliant career, moving him into a tie with the great Bobby Hull for sixth place on the all-time list.</p>
<p>Ian Moran and Josef Beranek also scored and Ron Francis added two assists for Pittsburgh, which moved into a fifth-place tie with the idle New York Rangers in the Eastern Conference, five points behind fourth-place Florida.</p>
<p>Ken Wregget made 26 saves to help the Penguins close in on a post-season position that would give them home ice advantage in the first round of the playoffs.</p>
<p>&quot;That was a gratifying win, we got off to a good start,&quot; Pittsburgh coach Craig Patrick said. &quot;I don't think you ever have an easy game against Florida, they work so hard and when they get down I don't know how they can work harder.&quot;</p>
<p>Jagr's 46th goal at 3:04 of the second period made it 3-0. But Scott Mellanby scored two minutes later for Florida on a powerplay and Ed Jovanovski closed the Panthers within one before Lemieux gave the Penguins a bit of breathing room.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought we played great in the second and third period, we dominated them,&quot; Florida coach Doug MacLean said. &quot;It was frustrating at the end.&quot;</p>
<p>John Vanbiesbrouck stopped 28 shots for Florida and picked up an assist on Mellanby's goal.</p>
<p>In Edmonton, Arturs Irbe made 17 saves in relief of Roman Turek and the Dallas Stars moved within three points of first-place Colorado in the Western Conference with a 3-1 victory over the Oilers.</p>
<p>Benoit Hogue put Dallas on the scoreboard at 1:43 of the second period and Greg Adams and Guy Charbonneau scored 67 seconds apart in third period for a 3-0 Dallas lead.</p>
<p>Irbe entered the game with 31 seconds left in the first period after Turek twisted his left knee. He surrendered just a short-handed goal to Daniel McGillis at 12:53 of the third period.</p>
<p>Dallas improved to 46-23-6 with 98 points setting a single-season franchise record. The Stars are also one win shy of the franchise record for seven consecutive victories set 17 years ago when the club was the Minnesota North Stars.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PITTSBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
