<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478316" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: BASKETBALL-BARCELONA WIN IN CONTROVERSIAL FINISH.</title>
<headline>BASKETBALL-BARCELONA WIN IN CONTROVERSIAL FINISH.</headline>
<dateline>BARCELONA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Barcelona set-up a third and decisive leg of their European championship quarter-final with Bologna on Tuesday as a last-gasp triple-shot which would have won the tie for the Italians was controversially ruled out.</p>
<p>The Spaniards' 75-73 victory means that qualification for the Final Four will go down to a third game to be played on Thursday in Bologna, where the Italians won 70-65 last week.</p>
<p>But Teamsystem Bologna will claim they should already be through from a match that ended in total confusion.</p>
<p>They had whittled a gap of 16 points at the break down to just three when Oscar Myer was fouled with four seconds on the clock.</p>
<p>Eric Murdock made the first free throw but deliberately missed the second to allow the chance of a three-pointer. In the ensuing scrum Bologna regained possession and got the ball to Dan Gay.</p>
<p>He landed his throw but as he began his celebrations the score was ruled out -- apparently for a foul by Gay.</p>
<p>The Teamsystem players and officials were incensed at the decision, especially top-scorer Carlton Myers who paced up and down outside the referees' changing room for five minutes after the game.</p>
<p>The chaos continued as Barcelona's Arturas Karnishovas returned to the court to take two free shots after it was realised Gay's foul was his fifth. However, before he could begin the team managers met and decided it was a pointless exercise.</p>
<p>Barcelona lost last year's final to Panathinaikos in high drama in the dying seconds.</p>
<p>&quot;We're fed up with last-minute controversies... it would have been unjust if Teamsystem had won after we had been 16 points ahead,&quot; said Barcelona coach Aito Garcia.</p>
<p>Garcia's side had allowed Teamsystem an early lead, but with Serbian Alexander Djordjevic shaking off a leg injury to inspire them, burst to lead 48-32 at the break.</p>
<p>But the Italians came back strongly to outscore the hosts 14-5 to leave the game at 70-66 with three minutes on the clock.</p>
<p>It then came down to the final play -- which will no doubt be discussed long and hard before Thursday's decider.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BARCELONA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
