<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478334" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: HUNGARY TO FOCUS ON GROWTH AND STABILITY - FINMIN.</title>
<headline>HUNGARY TO FOCUS ON GROWTH AND STABILITY - FINMIN.</headline>
<byline>Sandor Peto</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungary's policy will continue to focus on economic growth and stabilisation despite government plans to cut inflation radically next year and the nearness of the 1998 elections, Finance Minister Peter Medgyessy said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Speaking to stockbrokers and journalists during his visit to the Budapest Stock Exchange, Medgyessy shrugged off concerns often quoted in the press over the country's economic course.</p>
<p>&quot;Any softening in economic stabilisation could harm sustainable, long-term economic growth,&quot; he said. &quot;There is agreement on economic stabilisation within the government.&quot;</p>
<p>Hungary cut its budget and current account deficits substantially with an economic stabilisation programme launched in March 1995, while real wages dropped more than 10 percent.</p>
<p>The government expects living standards to rise slightly this year, while growth of two to three percent in gross economic product (GDP) is targeted for this year, compared with stagnation in 1995.</p>
<p>Medgyessy added that the anti-inflationary programme, being prepared by the Finance Ministry and the National Bank of Hungary (NBH), would not recreate restraint on the economy.</p>
<p>&quot;I cannot imagine (anti-inflationary) measures drastic enough to harm the beginning of economic growth,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Urged by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) for a radical cut in inflation, the government is preparing an anti-inflationary programme for 1998, to reduce the pace of nominal wage and price increases .</p>
<p>This programme, the details of which have not been published yet, would be an alternative of previous plans, which target a cut of five percentage points in inflation in 1998.</p>
<p>The government forecasts average CPI of some 17 percent for this year, down from 23.6 percent in 1996, and said the alternative programme could further reduce inflation to single-digit figures in 1998.</p>
<p>However, the more radical anti-inflationary programme can only be carried out if wide-scale price and wage agreement with the employees and the trade unions is reached, Medgyessy said.</p>
<p>Otherwise the government will return to its previous plans of a more moderate reduction in the inflation rate, he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
