<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478305" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: SOCCER-TURKEY MUST BEAT DUTCH TO KEEP WORLD CUP HOPES ALIVE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-TURKEY MUST BEAT DUTCH TO KEEP WORLD CUP HOPES ALIVE.</headline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Netherlands will be looking to repeat their away victory over Turkey in the qualifying campaign for the 1994 World Cup on their return there for a group seven match on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The Dutch beat the Turks 3-1 in Istanbul in December 1992 and followed that up with a win by the same scoreline in Utrecht two months later as they successfully bid for a place in USA '94.</p>
<p>They are now looking to pull further ahead at the top of group seven following their 4-0 win over San Marino at home on Saturday by recording another win over the Turks in the provincial city of Bursa.</p>
<p>But Turkey, who have won one, drawn one and lost one of their three matches so far, know they must win Wednesday's match to retain any realistic hopes of a place in next year's finals in France.</p>
<p>Belgium's 2-1 win over Wales on Saturday did the Turks no favours, leaving them in fourth place, five points behind the second-placed Belgians, albeit with a match in hand.</p>
<p>&quot;Belgium's win wasn't good for us but at home we are strong enough to beat any team, including Holland,&quot; Turkey's coach Mustafa Denizli said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>His opposite number Guus Hiddink said: &quot;Turkey have some star players in their squad but Belgium have had some very good results in their last four matches. In order to keep in with a chance in this group, Turkey must beat us.&quot;</p>
<p>The Dutch will be without Arsenal striker Dennis Bergkamp, whose fear of flying sees him excused from duty, but otherwise Hiddink will be relying on most of the team which beat San Marino.</p>
<p>Ajax's Ronald de Boer sat out the San Marino game with a sore knee and others picked up minor injuries during game, but all should be fit by Wednesday, Hiddink said.</p>
<p>There are few surprises in the Turkish team which has so far failed to live up to the high expectations of this football-crazy nation.</p>
<p>Most of Denizli's squad come from Turkey's &quot;big four&quot; clubs -- Galatasaray, Besiktas, Fenerbahce and Trabzonspor -- but youngsters Hasan Sas of Ankaragucu and Samsunspor's Celil Sagir have been called up to add some bite to the midfield.</p>
<p>The Turks will be relying on fanatical home support and the unfamiliar surroundings of Bursa, more famous for its Turkish baths and car-factories than sporting prowess.</p>
<p>&quot;We are ready for the difficult test against Holland. My players believe, like me, that we will make it to the World Cup finals,&quot; Denizli said.</p>
<p>    Probable teams:    Turkey - Rustu Recber; Alpay Ozalan,</p>
<p>Bulent Korkmaz, Ogun Temizkanoglu, Tayfun Korkut, Oguz Cetin, Abdullah Ercan, Hasan Sas, Hami Mandirali, Hakan Sukur, Celil Sagir.</p>
<p>Netherlands: Edwin van der Sar; Michael Reiziger, Frank de Boer, Jaap Stam, Arthur Numan, Aron Winter, Wim Jonk, Clarence Seedorf, Phillip Cocu, Ronald de Boer, Patrick Kluivert.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
