<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478353" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: BRITISH AIRWAYS SEES DAILY RIGA FLIGHTS.</title>
<headline>BRITISH AIRWAYS SEES DAILY RIGA FLIGHTS.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Airways (BA) on Tuesday said that it sees the possibility for daily connections between Latvian capital Riga and London's Gatwick airport soon.</p>
<p>BA started flying to Riga on March 31, the first flights to any of the Baltic states.</p>
<p>&quot;The number of flights may be increased from four a week to a daily service in the not too distant a future,&quot; Harvey Lines, Manager Baltic States, told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope Riga will be as successful as other new east European destinations, like Kiev and Baku,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>BA plans to have 60 passangers per flight on average and in order to balance the incoming passenger flow it is targetting both business and leisure markets, Lines said.</p>
<p>&quot;Riga is featuring as a new alternative to Budapest and Prague for short-term trips on BA Holidays,&quot; Lines said.</p>
<p>The departures are geared to flights beyond London, of which there are almost 500 and an average working day.</p>
<p>A special price of $299 both ways is in place until June and an increase of some $20 is expected after that.</p>
<p>The British carrier has agreements in place with Estonian and Lithuanian aviation companies for connecting flights and it is also considering northern Lithuania and Western Estonia to generate passengers.</p>
<p>Three companies, including Latvia's national carrier Air Baltic, part-owned by Scandinavian Airlines fly to London at the moment and BA considers that in medium and long-term the passenger flow through Riga will grow.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope to especially generate more inflying passengers.. We are not only promoting our business, but also Latvia abroad,&quot; Lines said.</p>
<p>-- Martinsh Gravitis, Riga newsroom +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BALTST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
