<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478314" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL - AMERICAN LEAGUE TEAM SKETCHES FOR 1997 SEASON.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL - AMERICAN LEAGUE TEAM SKETCHES FOR 1997 SEASON.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are brief sketches of American League teams heading into the 1997 season starting on Tuesday (in order of last season's finish):</p>
<p>--- EAST DIVISION ---</p>
<p>NEW YORK YANKEES - World Series champions turning over closer chores to young Panamanian Mariano Rivera now that ace John Wetteland has signed on with the Texas Rangers. Mike Stanton, Jeff Nelson, Graeme Lloyd counted on for critical set-up role performed so brilliantly last year by Rivera. Former Baltimore lefty David Wells takes place of Jimmy Key in the rotation.</p>
<p>1996 record: 92-70 (World Series champions)</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>BALTIMORE ORIOLES - May have improved clubhouse chemistry with loss of Bobby Bonilla, Wells. Key takes Wells' place. Biggest off-season change was internal as iron man Cal Ripken hands shortstop job to Mike Bordick and steps over to play third. Eric Davis expected to give speed/power lift to attack.</p>
<p>1996 record: 88-74</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>BOSTON RED SOX - Lost longtime ace Roger Clemens to Toronto. Experimenting all over diamond. Moved regular shortstop John Valentin to second base to make room for young Nomar Garciaparra, and could have whole new outfield with converted infielder Wil Cordero in left, Japan League returnee Shane Mack in centre and Tiger castoff Rudy Pemberton in right. Jimy Williams takes over as manager.</p>
<p>1996 record: 85-77</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>TORONTO BLUE JAYS - Made biggest improvement over off-season. Added Clemens to formidable rotation that already includes Cy Young winner Pat Hentgen and ERA leader Juan Guzman. Added bats of Carlos Garcia (second base), Orlando Merced (outfield) and Benito Santiago (catcher) to bolster weak offence.</p>
<p>1996 record: 74-88</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>DETROIT TIGERS - Added speedy centerfielder Brian Hunter, shortstop Orlando Miller and stopper Todd Jones. Bright spot on staff could be young lefty starter Justin Thompson. Slugging first baseman Tony Clark looks like the real thing but team has long way to go.</p>
<p>1996 record: 53-109</p>
<p>--- CENTRAL DIVISION ---</p>
<p>CLEVELAND INDIANS - Big changes in Tribe team that went to World Series two years ago but still look powerful. Added Matt Williams, Marquis Grissom and David Justice. Gone is Albert Belle and Kenny Lofton. Jim Thome switches to first. Cloud hangs over legal problems facing closer Jose Mesa.</p>
<p>1996 record: 99-62</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>CHICAGO WHITE SOX - Added Albert Belle but lost ace starter Alex Fernandez. Jaime Navarro, Doug Drabek try to pick up the rotation. Badly hurt by injury to power-hitting third baseman Robin Ventura, who could miss most of the year.</p>
<p>1996 record: 85-77</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>KANSAS CITY ROYALS - Also busy in off-season, putting life into offence by adding Chili Davis, Jeff King and Jay Bell. If promising arms like Jose Rosado, Chris Haney and Brian Bevil develop could get interesting.</p>
<p>1996 record: 80-82</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>MILWAUKEE BREWERS - Have basically stayed pat. Have righthander Cal Eldred for full season and hope young Jeff D'Amico continues to progress as a starting pitcher.</p>
<p>1996 record: 80-82</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>MINNESOTA TWINS - Added catcher Terry Steinbach to attack and hope for continued development of young players such as Rich Becker, Matt Lawton and rookie Todd Walker. Pitching is a problem, but team could be on upswing.</p>
<p>1996 record: 78-84</p>
<p>--- WEST DIVISION ---</p>
<p>TEXAS RANGERS - Fixed only big problem from last year by signing relief ace Wetteland. Now hope shortstop Benji Gil and centerfielder Damon Buford can replace departed Kevin Elster and Darryl Hamilton. Slugger Juan Gonzalez to miss early going due to injury.</p>
<p>1996 record: 85-76, first place</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>SEATTLE MARINERS - Fortified starting staff with acquisition of Jeff Fassero and Scott Sanders. If fireballing Randy Johnson can return to form following injury-plagued 1996 season, the offensive-minded Mariners could overtake Texas.</p>
<p>1996 record: 85-76</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>OAKLAND ATHLETICS - Brought back Bash Brother Jose Canseco, reuniting him with Mark McGwire. Offence may be hurt by lack of table setter unless young shortstop Tony Batista steps up. Starting pitching could be a strength but bullpen is suspect.</p>
<p>1996 record: 78-84</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>ANAHEIM ANGELS - Biggest change was in name as have dropped state moniker in deference to locals in area and new owner Disney. Terry Collins is new manager. Rookie Darin Erstad may make a splash in an already lively lineup.</p>
<p>1996 record: 70-91</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
