<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478323" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: SOCCER-BETIS FORCED TO IMPROVISE IN CUP SEMIFINAL.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BETIS FORCED TO IMPROVISE IN CUP SEMIFINAL.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spanish Cup favourites Barcelona and Real Betis will be without a number of top foreign players for their semifinal, second leg matches this week.</p>
<p>But whereas Barcelona can rely on one of Europe's strongest squads to defend a 4-0 lead over second division Las Palmas, Betis will field an improvised team for a tough tie at Celta Vigo.</p>
<p>Celta are still smarting over going down to what they believe was an unsporting goal in the first leg.</p>
<p>The only goal of the match was scored by Nenad Bjelica after the Betis midfielder failed to return possession from a throw-in after the Celta defenders had put the ball into touch so that an injured team mate could be treated.</p>
<p>The game had already been interrupted by a string of stoppages for injuries and cramp, all of them suffered by Celta men, and the Betis players were quick to put the blame on the incident on their opponents.</p>
<p>&quot;However much their fans shout, they (the crowd) are not going to score goals,&quot; said Betis defender Juan Merino.</p>
<p>For Celta, losing Cup finalists to Zaragoza in 1994, Wednesday's tie represents the last opportunity for success after a mediocre season.</p>
<p>Betis -- who will lose key wingers Robert Jarni and Findi George and three other players to international duty -- have not reached the final for 20 years.</p>
<p>Securing a meeting with Barcelona in this year's final  is especially important as it could determine which continental competition the southerners play next season.</p>
<p>With a UEFA Cup place virtually a certainty, Betis currently trail the Catalans only on goal difference in the league.</p>
<p>One of the two clubs looks set to seal Spain's second European Cup place, leaving a berth in the Cup Winners' Cup to a team who finish third in the league and lose the final.</p>
<p>Barcelona manager Bobby Robson is sure enough of a result to rest goalkeeper Vitor Baia, who played a fine game against Valencia on Sunday just 24 hours after turning out for Portugal.</p>
<p>But defenders Gheorghe Popescu and Laurent Blanc and strikers Ronaldo and Emmanuel Amunike will all answer the call of country rather than club on Thursday evening.</p>
<p>Also out is defender Sergi Barjuan who fractured his arm in the first leg.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
