<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478324" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: HORSE RACING-DORANS PRIDE IN EMOTIONAL WIN FOR INJURED PARTNER.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-DORANS PRIDE IN EMOTIONAL WIN FOR INJURED PARTNER.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ireland's top novice chaser Dorans Pride brought the curtain down on a successful season with an emotional win in the grade one Power Gold Cup at Fairyhouse, County Meath, on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Third in the Gold Cup at Cheltenham in March, Dorans Pride took his career earnings to over 250,000 Irish pounds ($394,000) with his 17th win but on this occasion he was forced to race without his regular partner Shane Broderick.</p>
<p>Broderick, 22, took a heavy fall when riding at Fairyhouse on Monday and was taken unconscious to hospital and later transferred to intensive care, reportedly with spinal injuries.</p>
<p>Latest hospital reports said that Broderick had regained full consciousness overnight.</p>
<p>&quot;This one is for Shane,&quot; a visibly upset Tom Doran, the winning owner, said.</p>
<p>There were no cheers of joy and no backs were slapped when Richard Dunwoody, who deputised for Broderick, led Dorans Pride into the winners' enclosure.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought about pulling him (Dorans Pride) out of the race but Shane would have wanted him to run,&quot; Tom Doran said.</p>
<p>Dorans Pride, the 7-4 on-favourite, landed the two and a half miles) 4-km) race by five lengths from 3-1 chance Jeffell with Consharon (20-1) well back in third.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
