<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478333" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: WEEK AHEAD-SAFRICA FEB CREDIT TO SLOW, RESERVES UP.</title>
<headline>WEEK AHEAD-SAFRICA FEB CREDIT TO SLOW, RESERVES UP.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>High South African interest rates and slowing consumer spending will put the brakes on private sector credit extension in February, a trend seen continuing in the months ahead, economists said.</p>
<p>Unusually high credit growth in January, a month which traditionally sees a sharp slowdown after the spendthrift Christmas season, will further help depress the February figure, they said.</p>
<p>A Reuters poll of nine economists forecast annual credit growth in February easing to between 15.50 percent and 16.92 with the consensus at 16.39 percent. This compares with a preliminary rise of 17.07 percent in January.</p>
<p>The latest data will be released on Wednesday at 1500 GMT.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that credit extension on the consumer side is slowing to a certain extent due to high debt levels, high interest rates and slowing growth in consumer sales,&quot; said Dennis Dykes, chief economist at banking group Nedcor.</p>
<p>The downward trend was expected to remain intact in coming months, with credit extension expected to have peaked in January when it soared above 17 percent from 16.09 percent in December.</p>
<p>But Herman van Papendorp, economist at SMK Securities, told Reuters the main reason for the expected decrease last month was the unseasonally high January base.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that the January numbers made a mockery of the normal seasonal patterns should probably ensure that the February growth rate will come down a bit,&quot; van Papendorp said.</p>
<p>Economists said money supply was also expected to come in at a lower rate than January for statistical reasons.</p>
<p>&quot;Both (money supply and credit extension) are coming off a fairly high base, which is quite a big factor,&quot; Dykes said.</p>
<p>Money supply growth increased 16.06 percent year-on-year in February last year, while credit growth rose 17.42 percent over the same period.</p>
<p>Economists forecast the latest M3 figure falling to between 14.75 percent and 15.75 percent with consensus at 15.1 percent from a preliminary January figure of 16.89 percent.</p>
<p>Van Papendorp said the money supply figure had been difficult to calculate as the government deposit component had not yet been made available. The monthly exchequer data has not yet been made public due to release of the budget on March 12.</p>
<p>Also due out this week is South African gold and foreign exchange reserves data for March which is expected to have edged up as capital continued to flow into the country.</p>
<p>Economists expected a gross reserves figure of between 11.5 to 13.5 billion rand with consensus at 12.58 billion rand. This compares to 12.49 billion rand in February.</p>
<p>&quot;There are a number of positive factors, including very strong net foreign purchases of bonds and equities, a stronger rand, particularly at month-end and the current account was likely roughly in balance,&quot; economists at Standard Bank's economic unit wrote in a research note.</p>
<p>But other analysts said there were some negative factors weighing on the figures, such as the first repayment on an IMF loan and the extent that the Reserve Bank would have repaid a 2.1 billion rand loan it took out in February.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a mixed bag,&quot; said one economist who declined to be named.</p>
<p>The gold component of the equation was expected to stay steady, shrugging of a decline in the rand gold price and getting little benefit from a listless dollar bullion price.</p>
<p>Under a new Reserve Bank policy of putting the reserves data into the market as soon as possible, the figures could be released as early as Wednesday at 1600 GMT.</p>
<p>But a Reserve Bank official said a more likely date was 1600 GMT on Thursday. The net reserves figure and full breakdown of the data will be released on April 8, he said.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E513">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
