<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478442" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Zinc shakes off weaker LME to end above $1,300.</title>
<headline>Zinc shakes off weaker LME to end above $1,300.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zinc bucked a weaker trend in the LME base metals complex on Tuesday in thin post-holiday business to touch a fresh 4-1/2 year peak.</p>
<p>Three month zinc prices burst through the $1,300 level during a late rally on the afternoon kerb to close $14 stronger at $1,309, just $1 below the peak.</p>
<p>Funds apparently jumped back into the market after stocks fell by 13,025 tonnes in the morning, traders said.</p>
<p>Prices failed at their first try in the morning to sustain a move back above the $1,300 level, but when the downside held at $1,291, a second try was successful.</p>
<p>There was talk that the zinc inventory drawdown, which moved from Rotterdam and Antwerp LME warehouses, went to stockpiles of U.S. producers who were anticipating further strong demand.</p>
<p>The close was bullish on the charts, but the market was also starting to look overbought again, said analyst Helen Williamson of broker Brandeis. The market would have to consolidate above $1,300 to build a base so it could make more upside progress, she added.</p>
<p>The other metals all finished with losses after copper failed on the upside.</p>
<p>In the morning, copper prices tried to break through $2,380/85 per tonne resistance in the morning, but slumped on disappointment from a smaller than expected 6,225-tonne stocks fall.</p>
<p>The market managed to pull itself off its low of $2,348 and end the afternoon kerb only $12 easier at $2,360.</p>
<p>The converging 10-day and 30-day moving averages should give good support around $2,355, chartists said.</p>
<p>The premium of cash over three months metal eased by $5-$8, ending the day indicated at $48/$50.</p>
<p>Aluminium was hit by some late selling and ended the kerb near its lows at $1,630.50, down $11.50.</p>
<p>More tests of the downside were on the cards after the weak close with $1,600 the next major support level, analysts said.</p>
<p>Nickel, the only metal to show a rise in stocks, failed to hold above $7,800, ending the day $45 weaker at $7,760.</p>
<p>Stocks had risen by 240 tonnes.</p>
<p>Tin finished $25 softer at $5,860 and lead was quiet, ending at an indication of $688/89 versus a prior kerb close of $686.</p>
<p>Alloy closed $4 weaker at $1,540.</p>
<p>--Eric Onstad, London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
