<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478499" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Nigeria's detained Ogoni complain of ill-treatment.</title>
<headline>Nigeria's detained Ogoni complain of ill-treatment.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nineteen youths from the Ogoni tribe awaiting trial for the same murders for which author Ken Saro-Wiwa was hanged have complained of some of their number suffering in detention from blindness, disease and torture.</p>
<p>Human rights lawyer Gani Fawehinmi said in a statement issued on Tuesday that he had filed a suit requesting bail for the 19 last week in the southeast Rivers state capital of Port Harcourt where they are detained.</p>
<p>In affidavits supporting the application, the detainees said only by freeing them would the military government proceed with the case which dates from 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;The feeding of all the applicants is incredibly poor and terrible,&quot; said the affidavit, adding: &quot;Most of the applicants have developed various diseases.&quot;</p>
<p>It said one of them identified as Babina Vozor &quot;is now blind&quot; while another called Kale Beete &quot;is left with incomplete fingers&quot;, alleging the injuries resulted from police torture.</p>
<p>Yet another applicant whose name was not provided &quot;was bitten by a snake and it was only by administering native medicine that he was treated.&quot;</p>
<p>There was no government response to the affidavits and no date was fixed for hearing the bail applications, made public in the same week the United Nations human rights commission is expected to focus on Nigeria at its Geneva forum.</p>
<p>The Ogoni 19 have been held since 1994 and are awaiting trial over the 1994 murder of four pro-government Ogoni chiefs.</p>
<p>Saro-Wiwa and eight other Ogoni activists were executed in 1995 for the murders, sparking international outrage and steps by Western countries and the Commonwealth of former British territories to isolate Nigeria.</p>
<p>A high court judge issued an injunction in 1995 restraining the tribunal from hearing the case against the Ogoni 19.</p>
<p>Fawehinmi said he was directed to take over the case by the Movement for the Survival of Ogoni Peoples (MOSOP), whose new leader Ledum Mittee is in exile. Mittee was tried with Saro-Wiwa but discharged and acquitted and went into exile shortly after.</p>
<p>The 19 youths are also members of MOSOP which has been campaigning for self-determination for the 500,000 Ogoni people.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
