<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478452" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK broker Lambert forms German joint venture.</title>
<headline>UK broker Lambert forms German joint venture.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Insurance broker Lambert Fenchurch Group Plc said on Tuesday it was forming a joint venture in general insurance broking with Pantaenius GmbH &amp; Co of Germany.</p>
<p>Lambert Fenchurch will acquire a 40 percent stake in Pantaenius, the company said in a statement.</p>
<p>Pantaenius is headquartered in Hamburg and is one of the leading yacht insurers in Europe, but has developed a general insurance broking arm.</p>
<p>The yacht insurance broking part of the company will remain wholly under the ownership of its chairman Harald Baum.</p>
<p>Lambert Fenchurch will pay 4.5 million marks for the stake in Pantaenius plus the share capital of Lowndes Lambert Deutschland AG.</p>
<p>The German joint venture follows a similar deal in the U.S. last month, when Lambert Fenchurch teamed up with Reliance and MTS Insurance Services.</p>
<p>Unaudited accounts showed Pantaenius' 1996 general insurance brokerage at 7.8 million marks and a pre-tax profit of 955,000 marks.</p>
<p>Lambert Fenchurch Group was formed earlier this year by the merger of Lowndes Lambert and Fenchurch Plc.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Insurance News 44 171 542 2769</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
