<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478433" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: NWE gasoline eases on weaker crude in quiet market.</title>
<headline>NWE gasoline eases on weaker crude in quiet market.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>NWE gasoline eased on Tuesday in quiet trade.</p>
<p>&quot;It's fairly quiet. We're in a new month and people are busy deciding their positions but there's not much physical activity,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Eurograde barges traded at $199 fob ARA in late trade, having been done at $200 in early trade. Many sellers said they were not interested in prices below $200.</p>
<p>Traders said a combination of weak crude prices, high gasoline stocks in the region and insipid demand was likely to pressure prices lower.</p>
<p>&quot;With this lovely weather we may expect consumption to rise a bit. I would expect to see some German end-user demand, but until the high stock positions many of us had ahead of Easter are cleared the market's unlikely to rise that much,&quot; said one trader in the ARA region.</p>
<p>Few expected prices to remain on the wane for long, saying that players would not want to maintain short positions with the U.S. driving season just around the corner.</p>
<p>On the swaps front, an April paper was done at 202, while May paper traded at $202.75.</p>
<p>An April cargo swap was rumoured done at $209 cif NWE, but this was not confirmed.</p>
<p>The arbitrage window to the United States was not quite open, traders said. &quot;It's touch and go on the arb front. We've cargoes going over but that's material we organised weeks ago,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>-- Melanie Goodfellow, London Newsroom, +44 171 542 7714.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
