<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478427" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Wet Brent trades at May -94 cts, Nigerians weaker.</title>
<headline>Wet Brent trades at May -94 cts, Nigerians weaker.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Sea physical crude differentials again reflected the pressure of persistent oversupply on Tuesday when a Brent Blend cargo traded at a 94 cent discount to May paper, traders said.</p>
<p>That was two cents dearer than the 96 cent differential achieved for the same cargo on Monday, but was a full six cents weaker than values seen on Thursday.</p>
<p>With BP alone holding 10 cargoes of unsold April Brent, values could continue close to a dollar discount for much of the week, some traders said.</p>
<p>BP took their tally of unsold Brents into double figures on Tuesday by keeping a cargo loading April 16-18 brought forward from Wednesday's chains.</p>
<p>An Ekofisk changed hands at unchanged values, with a cargo loading April 22-24 at Dated Brent minus three cents.</p>
<p>Paper also showed weakness. April/May was around -60/-52 cents, with May/June at -18/14 cents and June July at -4/-1 cents.</p>
<p>CFDs were 25 to 15 cents weaker for this week and next week. April 1-4 were equivalent to May -85/-65 cents and April 7-11 was May -65/-60 cents.</p>
<p>April 14-18 traded at June -57 cents, equivalent to May - 41 cents.</p>
<p>A fourth Forties cargo was cancelled on Tuesday because of underperformance at one of the fields contributing to Britain's largest crude stream, oil traders said.</p>
<p>Enterprise cancelled the 600,000 barrel cargo scheduled to load on April 25-30 as a result of lower than expected output from the Scott field.</p>
<p>The four cancellations cut the original April Forties programme by four cargoes to 40, excluding crude piped straight to the Grangemouth refinery.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
