<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478444" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK Feb gas production falls from Jan highs - Woodmac.</title>
<headline>UK Feb gas production falls from Jan highs - Woodmac.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.K. natural gas production fell in February to 11,512 million cubic feet a day (mmcfd) from record levels reached in January, consultants Wood Mackenzie said in their April North Sea report.</p>
<p>Unseasonably mild weather during February stifled gas production, which was down 570 mmcfd on the same month last year, when demand was driven by cold weather to record levels, Wood Mackenzie said.</p>
<p>Poor demand was reflected from a drop in output of 13 percent from the Morecambe fields which have a big swing capacity.</p>
<p>Wood Mackenzie revised January production up by 561 mmcfd to 12,888 mmcfd due to a conversion error in the production figures for the Morecambe fields reported last month.</p>
<p>But even according to initial calculations, January production set a new record, beating the previous high of 12,074 mmcfd set in February 1996.</p>
<p>Following is a field by field breakdown of U.K. North Sea gas production in million cubic feet a day:</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 5387</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300014">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
