<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478466" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: CRICKET - Rixon sees faint light at end of tunnel.</title>
<headline>CRICKET - Rixon sees faint light at end of tunnel.</headline>
<text>
<p>WELLINGTON, April 1 - New Zealand cricket coach Steve Rixon says he can see light at the end of the tunnel -- but the light isn't bright enough to force him to don his trademark designer sunglasses, NZPA reports.</p>
<p>The Kiwis last week completed a satisfactory first term under Rixon's guidance, a record of three test wins and five one-day successes hinting at what New Zealand are capable of.</p>
<p>Three test losses and eight one-day defeats, invariably suffered when the side played well below their best, mean much work remains before the New Zealanders attain anything near the consistency required to gain respectability on the international  </p>
<p>stage.</p>
<p>&quot;The results overall worked out pretty well but there was a fair bit of under-achieving this season as well,&quot; Rixon said.</p>
<p>New Zealand were competitive whenever they played anywhere near their potential, as evidenced by convincing test wins over Pakistan in Lahore and Sri Lanka in Dunedin and Hamilton.</p>
<p>But anything less than 100 percent output translated into decisive defeat, as experienced in the home test series against England and the second test against Pakistan in Rawalpindi.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone has to do their job, and when they do we will probably beat most sides,&quot; Rixon said.  </p>
<p>&quot;But we don't have world class players like a Hadlee, a Crowe, a Steve Waugh or a Shane Warne.&quot;</p>
<p>New Zealand are now in better shape than seven months ago, according to Rixon. He inherited a team from previous coach Glenn Turner, whose test form was poor but whose one-day results were on the improve.</p>
<p>It was another summer of change for New Zealand. Players such as Mark Greatbatch, Justin Vaughan, Danny Morrison and captain Lee Germon were cast aside at various stages, and while none of the dumpings was a painless exercise each was necessary, Rixon believes.  </p>
<p>&quot;All were given opportunities and it was known from day one what we expected, and that it was going to be implemented. I'm not sure a lot of people thought it would happen though.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no problem with change and I have no problems with any of the decisions which have been made this season.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no doubts that we are in a healthier state now then we were seven months ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The introduction of guys like Matt Horne and Daniel Vettori, plus the recalls of Heath Davis and Geoff Allott are all signs of the future.  </p>
<p>&quot;I can now see daylight at the end of the tunnel and I'm excited about that. At times this season I wondered whether the daylight was going to come.</p>
<p>&quot;Potentially, and I know that's a dreadful word, there is a base here for a brand new era -- and a horribly exciting one.&quot;</p>
<p>The swift elevation of teenaged left arm spinner Vettori into the national ranks paid instant dividends as he picked up 18 wickets in his first four tests, while Horne's promotion seems set to be rewarded as he strives to bolt down the troublesome No 3 batting position.  </p>
<p>On the back of an outstanding Shell Trophy season, Horne looked totally at ease at the highest level, and there is every indication he will develop into a player of class.</p>
<p>Fast bowlers Davis and Allott shone in the latter stages of the season, but their future progress may be hampered by injury.</p>
<p>Allott sat out the last series against Sri Lanka because of a serious back complaint which in all probability will rule him out of the Independence Cup quadrangular limited overs tournament in India next month, while Davis showed a big heart to play on despite knee and achilles tendon problems.  </p>
<p>These two, allied with New Zealand's best bowler in tests this season Simon Doull, appeal greatly as potentially potent matchwinners in years to come.</p>
<p>But the most significant personnel change made under Rixon was Stephen Fleming's ascension to the captaincy in place of Germon.</p>
<p>He had a dream introduction to the fulltime job when New Zealand rolled Sri Lanka in both tests last month and squared the limited overs series against the world one-day champions.</p>
<p>Rixon refused to draw comparisons between Germon and Fleming.  </p>
<p>&quot;But I will say that what I see now is a very content unit and I think that contentment comes from a guy who hasn't changed as a person.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no pretences about Flem and the guys appreciate that. I think he's done a marvellous job so far, and he will get better and better.&quot;</p>
<p>New Zealand's progress this season was handicapped by the fragility exhibited by their batsmen, who largely failed to stamp their mark.  </p>
<p>Only three centuries were forthcoming in tests, Fleming and Astle reaching three figures against England in Auckland, while opener Bryan Young's epic unbeaten 267 against Sri Lanka in Dunedin has to go down as the individual highlight of the year.</p>
<p>Rixon is still somewhat perplexed at the inability of his batsmen to dominate.</p>
<p>&quot;I said from the start that I thought our batting would be our strength. I still say that and I still believe that ... and I am still waiting.</p>
<p>&quot;But Rome wasn't built in a day.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
