<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478470" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Bre-X to resume trading at 1030 EST.</title>
<headline>Bre-X to resume trading at 1030 EST.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bre-X Minerals Ltd shares will resume trading today at 1030 EST/1530 GMT, the Toronto Stock Exchange said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Bre-X had not yet filed an expected news release containing &quot;material&quot; information with the TSE surveillance department, exchange officials said.</p>
<p>Bre-X stock trading was halted all day Monday in Toronto and on Nasdaq.  </p>
<p>Nasdaq said it would also resume the stock at 1030 EST/1530 GMT.</p>
<p>&quot;The company has not yet issued a news release, as it undertook to do yesterday, and it is inappropriate to further delay the resumption of trading,&quot; the TSE said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;The exchange reaffirms its commitment to provide a fair and continuous market in its listing securities for shareholders and investors,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>After Bre-X issued a release on Monday, the TSE said trading in Bre-X would start trading again this morning after dissemination of additional news.</p>
<p>&quot;The company said new material information will be available from a report by (assay company) Kilborn and has undertaken to issue a news release before the opening of the market (Tuesday),&quot; the TSE said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Bre-X closed last Thursday at 2.50, down 13 from last Tuesday's close.</p>
<p>((Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8100))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
