<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478450" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK Takeover Panel not considering hostile rule change.</title>
<headline>UK Takeover Panel not considering hostile rule change.</headline>
<byline>Alexander Smith</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Takeover Panel has no plans to limit a bidder's ability to buy shares in a target company during a takeover, its director general Alistair Defriez said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I can assure you that there are no plans or proposals being considered that would change that rule,&quot; Defriez told Reuters.</p>
<p>He was responding to a Financial Times report on Tuesday which said the panel was reviewing its rules governing share purchases, including the bidder's right to buy up to 30 percent of a target's shares in the market before an offer gets regulatory clearance.</p>
<p>Defriez said he was &quot;more than a bit surprised&quot; by the article, which said the panel is being urged to change its rules to limit market purchases or stop the practice altogether.</p>
<p>The debate was prompted by last year's takeover of British regional electricity company Northern Electric by U.S. power group CalEnergy.</p>
<p>The paper said Northern's then chairman David Morris argued CalEnergy had an unfair advantage because it was able to buy 30 percent of Northern's shares at a time when the price was depressed because of the possibility of the offer being referred to the Monopolies and Mergers Commission (MMC).</p>
<p>When the bid was cleared Northern's share price recovered and CalEnergy's offer received 20 percent acceptances, in addition to its 30 percent, this meant the U.S. firm won by a tiny margin.</p>
<p>The Financial Times quoted Morris as saying the 30 percent limit should be cut to 15 percent. It said another option under consideration was for a target company to be able to appeal to the panel for the bidder's right to make share purchases if regulatory uncertainty was depressing its share price.</p>
<p>Defriez told Reuters that Morris was a great supporter of the panel and had expressed his views to the panel and to others.</p>
<p>But he said there was &quot;no plan to change the rules in this area&quot;, although the panel was looking at other issues raised by Northern's battle with CalEnergy. &quot;Its fair to say we are reviewing the issues raised (by the bid),&quot; he added.</p>
<p>This was usual practice after a controversial bid and was simply part of the panel's ongoing aim of safeguarding shareholders' interests.</p>
<p>&quot;It is quite normal and proper to examine what has happened,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Corporate financiers have speculated that there could be changes to the rules regarding the buying of shares by advisors to the firms involved in a hostile bid, an issue raised by the Northern battle.</p>
<p>BZW, the investment banking arm of Britain's Barclays Plc, was last month criticised by the panel for failing to disclose all the facts, including a performance fee, during hearings over the conduct of the bid.</p>
<p>There was widespread debate about whether advisors to a company should be allowed to buy shares in a firm they were defending or making a bid for. Defriez said the review process into issues raised by the bids was continuing.</p>
<p>He said when it came to the question of a company buying shares in a bid target there were &quot;arguments for and against&quot; but the panel took the view &quot;that the market should not be unduly fettered&quot; and should be able to deal in the shares.</p>
<p>He said there was no intention to even review the limit on the buying of shares, adding that it would be a &quot;draconian step&quot; to further limit such buying.</p>
<p>And there were no plans to alter the Takeover Panel's &quot;Blue Book&quot;, which lists its 10 guiding principles and its rules. The rules are &quot;from time to time reviewed and revised to take account of changes in practice and opinion&quot;.</p>
<p>Defriez said it was important that the code should remain flexible and adaptable to changes in practice and sentiment. &quot;One of the advantages of the code is its flexibility,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
