<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478486" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Zaire's Tshisekedi is veteran Mobutu foe.</title>
<headline>Zaire's Tshisekedi is veteran Mobutu foe.</headline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1996-04-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Veteran opposition firebrand Etienne Tshisekedi, nominated by Zaire's opposition alliance as new prime minister, is a one-time ally of President Mobutu Sese Seko who became one of his most implacable foes.</p>
<p>For his supporters, who are legion in the teeming slums of Zaire's crumbling capital Kinshasa, he is the staunchest and most incorruptible opponent of Mobutu.</p>
<p>They see the burly leader of the Union for Democracy and Social Progress (UDPS) as the one man who has stood up to Mobutu in public, in government, and in face-to-face meetings.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi has gone to some lengths to cultivate his image as a man of the people, avoiding the typical excesses of Zaire's ruling elite. He drives a modest Peugeot.</p>
<p>But some diplomats question his democratic credentials.</p>
<p>&quot;For much of his career he worked with Mobutu,&quot; one Western diplomat said. &quot;He is bombastic, inflexible and intolerant of opposition.&quot;</p>
<p>Political rivals blame him for the fragmentation of Zaire's political opposition.</p>
<p>A native of Zaire's diamond-mining province of Kasai, Tshisekedi, 64, spent his formative political years as both a diplomat and a minister of Mobutu, who has ruled since 1965.</p>
<p>Unlike many other Zairean politicians, his about-face, when it came in the late 1970s, was radical and enduring -- costing him spells in prison.</p>
<p>He spearheaded domestic calls for multi-party politics which, coupled with pressure from abroad, forced a reluctant Mobutu to start to open the door to democracy in 1990.</p>
<p>At the height of the campaign for democracy he denounced Mobutu as a &quot;human monster&quot; and called for the president to flee the country or stand trial for corruption and other crimes.</p>
<p>In 1991, Mobutu, under foreign pressure to introduce democratic reform, appointed him first state commissar (prime minister). Mobutu dismissed him 12 days later when he refused to swear an oath of allegiance to him.</p>
<p>A sovereign national conference elected Tshisekedi prime minister in 1992. Mobutu sacked him again in 1993 but this time Tshisekedi refused to go and maintained a parallel government.</p>
<p>Later that year, he successfully led a campaign which blocked the introduction of five-million-zaire bank notes. Soldiers who were nevertheless paid in the notes went on a looting spree.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi refuses to accept his removal as prime minister and holds a cabinet meeting every Thursday under a shaded terrace of his modest residence in Kinshasa's Limete district.</p>
<p>But the October 1996 revolt in the east changed the balance of power in Zaire.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi met Mobutu in December in France, where Mobutu was convalescing after cancer surgery, and called for talks with Laurent Kabila and his rebels.</p>
<p>What looked like a &quot;reconciliation&quot; with Mobutu came to nought when Tshisekedi announced that Mobutu would return to Zaire and name him prime minister, but turned out to be wrong.</p>
<p>Born on December 14, 1932, in the central city of Kananga, Tshisekedi trained as a lawyer and graduated from the Catholic Lovanium University in Kinshasa in 1961.</p>
<p>As interior minister from 1965, when Mobutu seized power, until 1968, he helped write the N'Sele Manifesto which laid the groundwork for Zaire's conversion to single-party rule.</p>
<p>He served as justice minister and planning minister before going to Morocco as ambassador in 1969. He was later vice president of the national assembly and chairman of the national airline, Air Zaire.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi started speaking out against the government in 1980 as a founding member of the Group of 13, an organisation of parliamentarians who published a letter to Mobutu condemning government corruption and calling for democratic reforms.</p>
<p>As a result, Tshisekedi was arrested in 1982 and sentenced to 15 years in prison for treason. He was released the following year after protests from Amnesty International and other human rights groups.</p>
<p>From time to time thereafter, Tshisekedi was placed under house arrest or imprisoned for mounting anti-Mobutu protests.</p>
<p>At one point the government announced he had been placed in a mental institution after trying to stage a demonstration against Mobutu in the capital.</p>
<p>He has been married to Marthe Kasalu since 1961. They have six sons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
