<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478418" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK Labour's call for change strikes chord with some.</title>
<headline>UK Labour's call for change strikes chord with some.</headline>
<byline>Alan Wheatley</byline>
<dateline>NORTHAMPTON, England 1996-04-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>It's time for a change, says Labour Party leader Tony Blair, and Sandra Keel for one agrees.</p>
<p>Keel, 45, runs a market stall in Northampton, one of a clutch of middle England towns with marginal seats where Britain's May 1 election will be won or lost.</p>
<p>Keel voted for the ruling Conservative Party at the 1992 election but, unhappy with what she sees as a decline in the national health service, plans to switch to Labour, which has been in opposition since 1979.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel we need a change of government. People can be in power too long,&quot; Keel said as a beaming Blair shook hands and chatted with shoppers on his first formal day of campaigning.</p>
<p>Blair was taking his message to the Conservative-held marginal seat of Northampton North a day before Prime Minister John Major was expected to sound a theme of reassurance but no revolution when he unveils his party's manifesto on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Another stall holder, Jim McLeavy, 54, said he too was ready to desert the Conservatives: &quot;I just think a change is due, just to pep things up a bit.&quot;</p>
<p>Watching the crush of well wishers, photographers and the plain curious was Richard Bone, 62, yet another former Conservative voter who said Labour would get his vote this time because he was angry that the sell-off of Britain's utility companies had made some executives overnight millionaries.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not happy about all this privatisation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Keel, McLeavy and Bone are exactly the sort of conservative -- with a small 'c' -- voters that Blair has been wooing since he became Labour leader in July 1994 and started force-marching the party to the centre ground of British politics.</p>
<p>His message is honed to appeal to those Britons who believe that the economic reforms pushed through by the Conservatives during the past 18 years were overdue but are worried that the price paid has been too high.</p>
<p>Keel, for example, works as a volunteer with the elderly disabled and says the decline in services they get has been &quot;frightful.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair repeats almost to the point of monotony that he will not promise the earth -- &quot;We're not promising a revolution, we're promising a fresh start for Britain&quot; -- but he says a Labour government would make a difference.</p>
<p>&quot;The election's going to be about the many, not the few -- how Britain is run for all its people not simply a privileged elite,&quot; he says from the pull-out 'people's platform' of his campaign battle-bus.</p>
<p>He greets a crowd with a 'Hello Northampton!&quot; like a rock star on tour and quickly sketches how education and the health service would be the priorities of his government.</p>
<p>&quot;I say to the people of Britain: be strong, be of good courage. Put your trust in us and we will repay that trust a thousand times over in the years ahead,&quot; he says.</p>
<p>A couple of hours later in Derby, he is appealing for the trust of a different audience -- small businessmen who demand reassurance that trade unions under a Labour government would not once again get too big for their boots.</p>
<p>Blair not only gives the promise, he says the history of the past 25 years would have been different if Labour had grasped the nettle of union reform in the late 1960s as Margaret Thatcher subsequently did in the 1980s.</p>
<p>&quot;We paid a heavy price for that and we're not going to pay it again. Now my generation of the Labour Party is absoutely determined about this,&quot; Blair says. &quot;If I depart from that, everything that we want to achieve is laid at nought -- and I'm not going to do that.&quot;</p>
<p>At the end of the first full day on the stump, the message has come across loud and clear: if you want a change, but not too much change, vote Labour.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NORTHAMPTON, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
