<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478456" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Late bond market prices.</title>
<headline>Late bond market prices.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>This is how major world bond markets were trading in late European business on Tuesday.</p>
<p>GERMANY - Bund futures spent much of the day drifting at markedly lower levels, awaiting with the rest of the global debt market any indication about the direction of U.S. interest rates. The June Bund future on the London International Financial Futures and Options Exchange (LIFFE) was trading at 99.47, down 0.54 from Thursday's settlement price.</p>
<p>BRITAIN - Gilt futures closed sharply lower, although opening lows were fought off, after a survey showing the acceleration in UK manufacturing levelled off in March failed to shake off bearish overtones from the United States. The June long gilt future on LIFFE was trading at 108-13/32, down 18/32 from Thursday's settlement price.</p>
<p>FRANCE - Bond futures failed to recover from a weak start and followed Bunds lower in a quiet but gloomy session and traders saw little prospect of significant gains ahead of key U.S. jobs data due on Friday. The June notional bond future on the MATIF in Paris settled at 127.44, down 0.82 from Thursday's settlement price.</p>
<p>ITALY - Debt futures closed easier but off session lows after a nervous session with all eyes on the U.S. markets and weaker T-bonds in the afternoon. The June bond future on LIFFE was trading at 124.02, down 0.91 from Thursday's settlement price.</p>
<p>UNITED STATES - U.S. Treasuries opened marginally higher in coupons and a touch lower in bills as players geared up for the monthly report from the National Association of Purchasing Management. The June Treasury bond future on the Chicago Board of Trade was trading at 107-18/32, up 11/32 from Monday's settlement price. The long bond was quoted to yield 7.08 percent.</p>
<p>JAPAN - The key June Japanese government bond futures contract ended slightly higher after paring most of the day's gains in the afternoon. In after hours trading the June future on LIFFE was trading at 125.71, down 0.41 from Monday's settlement price on the Tokyo Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>EUROBONDS - Falling bond and equity markets kept many Eurobond players on the sidelines, with business already slow due to the Easter holiday. SBC Warburg lead managed two short-dated dollar bonds. Abbey National set a $300 million three-year bond, priced to yield 12 b.p. over U.S. Treasuries. European Investment Bank issued a $300 million four-year bond, flat to Treasuries.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
