<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478401" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: PRESS DIGEST - ROMANIA - APRIL 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - ROMANIA - APRIL 1.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Here are highlights of stories in Romania's press on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>Business:</p>
<p>ADEVARUL</p>
<p>- The government approved a 18.35 percent wage indexation for the second quarter of 1997.</p>
<p>- The president of Lockheed Martin of the United States is visiting Romania to look into investment opportunities in Romania's defence industry.</p>
<p>ROMANIA LIBERA</p>
<p>- Foreign investors to Romania need to fight red tape and bribery, U.S. businessmen told a Romanian government delegation at the &quot;Invest Romania&quot; conference in Washington last week.</p>
<p>- The Employers' Association called on trade unions urging them to avoid strikes and protests, saying interruptions in economic activities might seriously affect living standards.</p>
<p>- The health budget was raised to 3.2 percent of gross domestic product from a previous 2.7 percent after a government meeting on Monday.</p>
<p>EVENIMENTUL ZILEI</p>
<p>- Lockheed plans to open a representative office in Romania, the newspaper says.</p>
<p>- State-owned Banca Romana pentru Dezvoltare and Banca Agricola would be the first banks to go private in Romania, said senator Varujan Vosganian, head of parliament's finance commission. He said the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development was willing to buy shares in Banca Agricola.</p>
<p>CURIERUL NATIONAL</p>
<p>- Wages in the banking system were the highest in Romania in February, with the monthly average amounting to 858,300 lei, National Statistics Commission data showed. Average monthly wage in February was 456,300 lei.</p>
<p>General:</p>
<p>ROMANIA LIBERA</p>
<p>- Renel RA electricity authority threatened to cut power supplies to Romania's Putna monastery, which owes it 12 million lei in unpaid bills.</p>
<p>- The ruling National Peasant Party (PNT-CD) hailed King Michael's approach of British authorities in support of Romania's integration into the NATO.</p>
<p>- River Danube's Sulina channel was closed on Sunday when Romania's Tismana cargo ship loaded with 2,887 tonnes of rolled iron got stranded due to strong winds.</p>
<p>- Workers at Bucharest Urbis plumbing factory staged a spontaneous protest when its management announced workers would have to switch to eight-hour instead of six-hour working shifts if they wanted higher wages.</p>
<p>ADEVARUL</p>
<p>- Interior Minister Gavril Dejeu sacked eight of Romania's 42 county police heads, saying the move was meant to &quot;foster the quality and efficiency of police activity&quot;.</p>
<p>- An invitation to Romania to start membership talks with the NATO is seriously considered, U.S. Ambassador to Bucharest Alfred Moses said in an interview.</p>
<p>- Strong winds caused power failures in some 130 villages, mainly in southern Romania.</p>
<p>EVENIMENTUL ZILEI</p>
<p>- Bucharest City Hall could be forced to cut pledged free urban transportation facilities for pensioners, giving them only a 50 percent discount, vice-mayor Anton Vatasescu said.</p>
<p>($ = 6,996 lei)</p>
<p>-- Bucharest Newsroom 40-1 3120264</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
