<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478484" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Refugees empty camp under Zairean rebel orders.</title>
<headline>Refugees empty camp under Zairean rebel orders.</headline>
<byline>Matthew Bigg</byline>
<dateline>GOMA, Zaire 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of sick and exhausted Hutu refugees straggled south of Zaire's rebel-held northeastern capital on Tuesday after leaving a camp under rebel orders.</p>
<p>The Rwandan and Burundian refugees moved south of Kisangani and in the east towards Rwanda as Zaire's war rivals jockeyed for battlefield position with their first talks tentatively set for Saturday.</p>
<p>Aid workers said nearly 20,000 Hutu refugees, who abandoned their camp at Lula seven km (four miles) south of Kisangani on Monday, were in poor shape, straggling nearly 20 km (12 miles) along a jungle path.</p>
<p>&quot;It is desperate. You have people by the side of the road lying on a few bits of cloth trying to cover themselves with leaves and blankets,&quot; said U.N. refugee agency spokesman Paul Stromberg in Kisangani.</p>
<p>&quot;Now with these rains it is much worse. People are lying on their backs moaning or trying to wave to attact attention.&quot;</p>
<p>The rebel Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire (AFDL) demanded the refugees leave Lula on Monday and move south away from Kisangani city for security reasons.</p>
<p>The Tutsi-dominated rebels fear the refugees include former Rwandan Hutu troops and militiamen who had a major role in the 1994 genocide in Rwanda of an estimated 800,000 Tutsis and Hutu moderates.</p>
<p>Stromberg said 700 of the most vulnerable refugees remained at Lula and the rest were strung out to the south, where another 60,000 Hutu refugees are trapped after fleeing rebel advances.</p>
<p>He said the U.N. refugee agency had made little progress in negotiations with rebels on a plan to move the refugees, some of whom are too weak to walk, by air, road and on foot to Rwanda.</p>
<p>The agency said on Monday up to 30,000 refugees had arrived at Karuba village in Masisi district west of the eastern city of Goma, which borders on Rwanda, saying they wanted to go home.</p>
<p>It was unclear why they emerged from hiding but Tutsis in Masisi say the Tutsi-dominated rebels have been killing Hutu farmers in the region, accusing them of siding with the Rwandan Hutus.</p>
<p>Ailing President Mobutu Sese Seko will send a seven-man team headed by his security adviser to represent the government in talks with Laurent Kabila's AFDL rebels in South Africa this week, Zaire's state television said on Monday.</p>
<p>The team, which includes Foreign Minister Kamanda wa Kamanda and representatives of both the opposition and the president's supporters in the transitional parliament, will travel to South Africa on Thursday, it said.</p>
<p>State radio on Monday reported fierce fighting around the rebel-held port of Moba on Lake Tanganyika.</p>
<p>Expatriates and traders in the southern mining capital of Lubumbashi said the Shaba province rail hub of Kamina -- a 24-hour rail journey from Lubumbashi -- fell to the rebels on Monday without a fight.</p>
<p>AFDL rebels took up arms in October, vowing to topple Mobutu, who has dominated the former Belgian colony in Central Africa since a 1965 coup. They have seized a quarter of the country.</p>
<p>Mobutu, who had cancer surgery in Europe in August, has seen his grip on Zaire weaken as rebels advanced. Many Zaireans, weary and impoverished after three decades of his rule, welcome rebel advances.</p>
<p>In New York, U.N. officials said the organisation's special Zaire envoy Mohamed Sahnoun would lead the talks in South Africa. Sahnoun also represents the Organisation of African Unity, which brought the two sides together last week in Togo.</p>
<p>U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan appeared to have asserted his authority to have Sahnoun play the lead negotiating role following a series of summits and a plethora of special envoys on Zaire.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GOMA, Zaire"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
