<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478435" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Coffee, copper slide in post-holiday lull.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Coffee, copper slide in post-holiday lull.</headline>
<byline>Paul Carrel</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Coffee slid lower on Tuesday propelled by selling in the U.S. but the market mood was subdued as investors returned from the Easter holiday with few fresh factors to feed on.</p>
<p>In the base metals market the trend was down too, with copper sliding lower in lacklustre trade on the London Metal Exchange (LME) and dragging down nickel and aluminium in its wake.</p>
<p>&quot;It has been awful all day -- we might as well have extended the holiday,&quot; one LME trader said.</p>
<p>But copper was still well within its trading range and ended the day down $12 at $2,360. Aluminium closed $11.5 lower at $1,630.5.</p>
<p>Zinc managed to buck the downtrend in metals and made gains on the back of a 13,025 tonne fall in stocks. It closed at $1,309, close to a new 4-1/2 year high of $1,310.</p>
<p>Coffee spent the morning playing catch-up with New York, which was open on Monday while there was no trade in London, and rose $10 before shadowing the American market lower in the afternoon.</p>
<p>Benchmark May robusta futures closed down $23 at $1,612 a tonne. Cocoa was also pressured on the downside by arbitrage trade after the New York open and May futures closed one stg lower at 1,016 stg.</p>
<p>Elli Gifford, an independant analyst said that technically the London coffee market showed no clear picture.</p>
<p>&quot;It's directionless,&quot; she said. &quot;I expect no major moves.&quot;</p>
<p>Precious metals prices went their separate ways, with silver falling while gold shaded higher.</p>
<p>Gold prices were bolstered by sharp losses on Wall Street on Thursday and Monday as investors liquidated their stocks and sought sanctuary in the safety of the bullion market.</p>
<p>The market also shrugged off fresh news regarding Bre-X Mineral Ltd.'s controversial Busang gold deposit, analysts said. Announcements last week that the deposit may not be as rich as previously thought had put about $1.00 on the price of gold.</p>
<p>Bullion edged higher to the key $350 mark and  gained $1.90 to reach $350.25 by 1645 GMT.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, silver, platinum and palladium lost ground amid concerns about industrial demand in the aftermath of last week's hike in U.S. interest rates, dealers said.</p>
<p>Silver tested key technical support at the $5.00 level after losing its footing in New York on Monday, but closed at $5.04, down nine cents.</p>
<p>On the Chicoago Board of Trade (CBOT) soybean futures were sharply higher by 1645 GMT after USDA corrected its March 1 quarterly stocks figure to 1.056 billion bushels, 22 million bushels below the 1.078 billion bushel-figure released on Monday.</p>
<p>At 1645 GMT May futures were up three cents at $4.00-1/2.</p>
<p>IPE Brent futures were in poor health as they caught up with a sell-off in New York on Monday. But the downtrend was stemmed by forecasts of colder weather in the U.S.</p>
<p>May Brent slid to $19.01 before recovering to $19.15 by 1745 GMT. Some key prices at 1745 GMT on Tuesday</p>
<p>						Thursday   Tuesday</p>
<p>Ldn Spot Gold($ per ounce)		348.35     350.25</p>
<p>IPE Brent Crude Oil (May)		  19.41	19.13</p>
<p>Ldn Metal Exchange(3 mths delivery)</p>
<p>Copper ($ per tonne)		    2,372.00   2,360.00</p>
<p>Aluminium ($ per tonne)		 1,642.00   1,630.50</p>
<p>LIFFE Robusta Coffee ($/tonne) May) 1,632.00   1,612.00</p>
<p>Cocoa (Stg per tonne) (May)	   1,017.00   1,016.00</p>
<p>White Sugar ($ p/t May)		   305.50     307.50</p>
<p>Chicago Board of Trade Wheat</p>
<p>(Cents per bushel)(May)			399	  400-1/2</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
