<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478464" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: PRESS DIGEST-Australian Sports News - April 2.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST-Australian Sports News - April 2.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Australian Football League veteran, Carlton's Greg Williams, may see his career in jeopardy when he faces the tribunal to answer to the serious charge of interfering with an umpire tonight. Williams, winner of two Brownlow medals but with 22 matches in supensions, was charged with interfering with umpire Andrew Coates after Monday's Carlton-Essendon match. Page 20.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian Rugby League player Greg Alexander will tonight be named in the New South Wales team for the opening match of the Super League Tri-series against Queensland at Sydney Football Stadium on April 11. Alexander is returning to the game after a six ear representative football absence and five years after his brother's death. Page 20.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian National Basketball League team the Canberra Cannons is today expected to make a decision on a second foreign player after negotiating with American swingman Mario Donaldson and US centre Willlie Simmons to fill the vacancy left by off guard Ronie Henderson. Page 19.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>Despite Australia's best performance in one-day cricket since the World Cup one year ago, doubts over Australian cricket captain Mark Taylor's form have been fuelled after the captain admitted he was &quot;mentally tired&quot; and needed rest. He will almost certaily hand over the captaincy to wicket-keeper Ian Healy for Wednesday's third limited-overs international against South Africa at Newlands in Cape Town. Page 40.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Two-time world record holder and dual Olympian Phil Rogers will at age 25 be the most experienced member of the Australian team at the world shortcourse swimming championships in Sweden starting on April 17. Rogers intends to keep competing at the highest level in order to be able to take part in the 2000 Sydney Olympics. Page 40.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian Institute of Sport head gymnastics coach Ju Ping Tian says she has been left physically and mentally scarred by the allegations of verbal abuse of her students. Ju Ping was cleared by the seven month inquiry in late 1995, but says she suffered energy and eyesight loss as a result. Page 38.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>In the wake of Monday's spiteful Essendon-Carlton match at the Melbourne Cricket Ground, the Australian Football League has moved to separate players from opposing teams as they leave the ground. The AFL yesterday revealed a strict policy forcing players o use dressing rooms on the opposite side of the MCG, with the home club gaining first choice of dressing room. Page B12.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian Socceroos coach Terry Venables will almost certainly face accusations of conflict of interest when Sydney United goalkeeper Zeljko Kalac joins the Venables owned English club Portsmouth. Kalac recently played for the Socceroos in an internationl tournament and is expected to transfer to Portsmouth for about $A600,000 after the Ericsson Cup season. Page B10.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>According to Australian Opals women's basketball coach Tom Maher, the team will go into tonight's first test against Japan with a different line-up to the one that took the bronze medal in Atlanta. Chief playmaker Michele Timms and back-up guard Sandy Brodello are out, with stalwart Robyn Maher coming off the bench. Page B10.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE HERALD SUN</p>
<p>Australian Football League Sydney Swans player Paul Roos has not been ruled out of Saturday's match against the Western Bulldogs despite suffering what appeared to be a serious knee injury at the weekend. Last night Swans coach Rob Snowdon said the medialligament left knee strain would undergo a test tomorrow night. Page 66.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian triple national car rally champion Neal Bates will shake up super tour racing this season in a new Toyota Camry for half of this year's 2.0 litre races. The rest of the season he will be driving factory cars from Audi, BMW and Volvo. Page 64.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victoria's St Kilda Beach was recently home to more than 100 Victorian secondary school students in the inaugural Foxtel School Surf League. Tested in the competition were swimming, board paddling, beach running and resuscitation in a competition designedto introduce secondary school students to the sport of surf lifesaving. Page 63.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE DAILY TELEGRAPH</p>
<p>Super League Perth Reds player Mark Geyer will face up to 12 weeks suspension after Super League commissioner Jim Hall yesterday laid two foul play charges against him. Geyer will plead not guilty to the charges of a grade four reckless tackle and eye-gouing. Page 70.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Top Australian horse trainer Gai Waterhouse, husband Robbie Waterhouse and father Tommy Smith were the key players at the William Inglis Easter Yearling Sale in Sydney yesterday after purchasing five horses for a A$520,000 outlay. Two years ago Gai shocke the industry when she bought a Danehill colt from the sales ring for A$575,000. Page 72.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Australian Cricket Board has informed the fledgling Australian Cricketers' Association it will refuse to work with former chief executive Graham Halbish, now the players' national director. ACB chairman Denis Rogers said legal advice had been sought on Halbish's appointment as a consultant to the association. Page 66.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
