<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478463" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - European markets hit hard by Wall St selloff.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - European markets hit hard by Wall St selloff.</headline>
<byline>Malcolm Davidson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stock markets plunged across Europe on Tuesday as traders returned from their Easter break to catch up with two days of heavy losses on Wall Street.</p>
<p>The London, Paris and Frankfurt bourses all fell more than two percent in early trading, with investors asking whether this could be the start of the long predicted end to the stocks bull run.</p>
<p>&quot;Is the big correction people have been warning about finally here? This could certainly be the start of it. The mood is very nervous,&quot; one dealer said after another big selloff in New York.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials average lost 157 points to 6,583 on Monday after shedding 140 points last Thursday -- a decline over the two days straddling Easter of 4.3 percent.</p>
<p>European bond markets also fell in early trade, dragged down by the gloom in global bond markets, while the dollar softened as traders returned to their desks in nervous mood after the sharp falls in U.S. asset markets.</p>
<p>In contrast, gold started the day $1.45 stronger with traders saying they expected the precious metals market to be well supported by investors looking for refuge from turmoil elsewhere.</p>
<p>Some of Europe's smaller equity markets were suffering even worse than the big bourses at the start, with Amsterdam and Stockholm sliding more than four percent. Tokyo fell only 0.74 percent, however.</p>
<p>&quot;Taking all of Europe, those that were first will be last and vice versa. Peripheral countries which have benefited most on (European and economic union) convergence plays will be correspondingly harder hit on a sell-off,&quot; Schroders equity strategist Paul Walton said.</p>
<p>&quot;So you'd be looking at Italy and Spain and perhaps Portugal. Then there's some huge PEs (price/earnings ratios) now in Scandinavia.&quot;</p>
<p>Between last Thursday, when most European markets closed for the holiday weekend, and the resumption of trade on Tuesday, the Dow dived 250 points, hit by higher bond yields, worries about a further tightening of U.S. interest rates and a consequent fall in corporate earnings.</p>
<p>Despite that, London dealers said they detected some support from the hope that Europe was decoupling from the U.S. market.</p>
<p>&quot;This is going to be a test of just how decoupled these markets truly are,&quot; one said. &quot;One should take into account the more moderate valuations here. It's going to be pretty grim but I don't want to predict the wheels falling off yet.&quot;</p>
<p>By 0900 GMT London's blue chip FTSE 100 index was down 2.18 percent at 4,218.9 points but off the worst levels hit at the start.</p>
<p>Paris fell more than 2.5 percent at the opening, with losses spreading across the board, but Frankfurt fared even worse.</p>
<p>The 30-share DAX index had shed 3.84 percent by 0900 GMT with traders predicting spreading losses.</p>
<p>In Paris, one trader said: &quot;It's a very agitated market, all my phones are ringing constantly. I have no time to speak.&quot;</p>
<p>With talk about the U.S. Federal Reserve being forced to tighten monetary policy once more, the markets looked set for a torrid week ahead of the release of U.S. March non-farm payrolls data on Friday.</p>
<p>Before that the markets will be focusing on Tuesday's U.S. February leading indicators, construction spending and March National Association of Purchasing Management (NAPM), due at 1500 GMT.</p>
<p>Foreign exchange traders said they expected the dollar to remain nervous ahead of these indicators.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks as if the Fed will be tightening again...But the buoyancy in the U.S. economy argues for a firmer dollar,&quot; said Tony Norfield, treasury economist at ABN AMRO.</p>
<p>&quot;It is hard to see why, for economic or policy reasons, the dollar is sliding. Data from Germany remains weak and other core European countries look in pretty poor shape.&quot;</p>
<p>By 0900 GMT, the dollar was at 1.6680 marks and 123.48 yen, compared with 1.6763 marks and 123.48 yen in late European trade on Thursday.</p>
<p>While a strong NAPM could knock the dollar, as the market anticipates the effect of higher rates on U.S. stock and bond markets, the effect might not last.</p>
<p>&quot;I think any negative impact will be short-lived,&quot; said Chris Turner, currency strategist at BZW, adding that medium and long-term the U.S. unit will find support from a strong U.S. economy.</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 0900 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar was at 1.6680 marks and 123.48 yen, compared with 1.6763 marks and 123.48 yen in late European trade on Thursday.</p>
<p>STOCK MARKETS AT 0900 GMT</p>
<p>LONDON - The FTSE-100 index was down 94.0 points, or 2.18 percent, at 4,218.9.</p>
<p>PARIS - The CAC-40 was down 79.49 points, or 2.99 percent, at 2,577.19.</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - The 30-share DAX index was down 131.65 points, or 3.84 percent, at 3,297.40.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold started at $351.0 an ounce in Zurich against $348.55 in London before four-day break. Silver fell five cents to $5.08.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
