<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478410" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - Amstrad sells mobile phone business.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Amstrad sells mobile phone business.</headline>
<byline>Arindam Nag</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>British electronics group Amstrad Plc took another step towards restructuring its operations on Tuesday by announcing plans to sell its mobile phone firm Dancall Telecom A/S to Germany's Robert Bosch GmbH for 92 million pounds ($150.9 million).</p>
<p>Investors welcomed the sale to Bosch Telecom GmbH, a division of Robert Bosch as Amstrad announced it would return some value from the sale to its shareholders.</p>
<p>News of the disposal boosted Amstrad's shares to a 1997 high of 226 pence, up 26 pence from its previous close.</p>
<p>&quot;The sale will make Amstrad more cash rich, and shareholders would get some,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>The sale came as good news after a long time for Amstrad shareholders who had to witness the group struggling to stay alive and a far cry from its status in the 1980s as a high-growth darling of the market.</p>
<p>Those were days when it was riding on the success of its personal computers and hi-fi products before it began losing market share to bigger Japanese and U.S. competitors.</p>
<p>&quot;The group will still have to launch an exceptionally good product to bring back the excitement,&quot; an analyst said.</p>
<p>Amstrad's consumer electronics division has been its main drain on the group and was restructured into its Betacom unit as part of the group's operational changes. Amstrad's chairman Alan Sugar said he still appreciated Amstrad's investment in Dancall but regretted that its potential was never understood by financial institutions as it had not made a profit since the acquisition.</p>
<p>&quot;Amstrad felt that it had taken Dancall as far as it could,&quot; Sugar said.</p>
<p>Andreas Nobis, a board member of Robert Bosch told Reuters that the German group would retain the entire workforce of Dancall and would increase its plant capacity to over two million telephones per year.</p>
<p>&quot;We will continue with all the research, and there will be no redundancies,&quot; Nobis said.</p>
<p>Dancall Telecom was previously called Dancall Radio A/S unitl it ran into financial problems in the late 1980s. Amstrad acquired its assets, mainly inventory and goodwill, from its receivers in September 1993 through a new company Dancall Telecom for 6.3 million pounds.</p>
<p>Nobis said it felt Dancall's main weakness had been its inability to achieve sufficient volumes.</p>
<p>Sugar said Amstrad did not want Dancall, strapped for cash, to lose its market to bigger competitors.</p>
<p>&quot;...We decided the best route wold be dispose of the company to a major international organisation that had a depth of technical support and worldwide distribution, and be realistically far better qualified to take the company forward,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dancall's managing director will become a member of the management team of the Terminal Division of Bosch Telecom and Bosch would make fresh investments, although Nobis said it was too early to give any estimates.</p>
<p>Bosch will allow Dancall to retain its brand name on its phones where the 'Dancall' brand is popular, such as in Denmark and other Scandanavian countries, but would be using the 'Bosch' name in other markets.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
