<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478453" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK gilts this week - UK election key until U.S. data.</title>
<headline>UK gilts this week - UK election key until U.S. data.</headline>
<byline>Catherine Bremer</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>UK gilts will be on the alert for any flutters emanating from British politicians who unveil their election manifestos this week, although U.S. employment data on Friday has more market-moving potential, analysts said.</p>
<p>As the election battle gathers pace, analysts said the market has factored in a UK rate hike by June regardless of the outcome on May 1, since such a move is viewed as an economic necessity rather than a result of political factors.</p>
<p>Bank of America senior economic adviser Jeremy Hawkins told Reuters Financial Television a quarter point rise is likely after the polls.</p>
<p>&quot;A 50 basis point hike could be warranted once the election is out of the way, but it's more likely that the new Chancellor would still want to see 25 basis points - or moves of that order - rather than coming out and shocking people with a 50 basis point hike.&quot;</p>
<p>Opinion polls predict the opposition Labour Party will secure a clear majority. Its manifesto, due on Thursday, will be scrutinised for details of fiscal policies and its attitude towards a European single currency.</p>
<p>Societe Generale gilts analyst Tom Rayner said given Labour's lead, the contents of the ruling Conservative party's manifesto on Wednesday would not be an issue.</p>
<p>&quot;The market's going to assume that whatever they suggest they're not going to be able to implement,&quot; he said. &quot;What Labour are saying -- that they're going to keep spending under control, keep to the 2.5 percent inflation target, and not touch income -- this is all far more interesting to the market.&quot;</p>
<p>BZW gilts analyst Kevin Adams said Labour's plans for raising additional tax from the corporate sector could prompt a shift to gilts by acting as a burden on the equity market.</p>
<p>&quot;But given the recent strong performance of gilts, it would take a significant change to spur further outperformance.&quot;</p>
<p>Adams added the key focus for gilts would come on Friday when the U.S. releases employment data for March, dictating the level of the long bond yield, and setting the tone for gilts. &quot;It could push us in either direction -- we could go back to 7.0 percent (from 7.098 percent on Monday) if we get weak data, or to 7.25 if the data is stronger,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The non-farm payroll data follows last week's 25 basis point rate rise which confirmed a shaky picture for the U.S. Treasuries market and had a knock-on effect on gilts.</p>
<p>Analysts said that effect would be felt for some time in the gilt market and could result in the five to 10 year yield spread narrowing.</p>
<p>UK February consumer credit and March money supply data on Wednesday would be less of a focus for the gilts market, analysts said.</p>
<p>Rayner said he thought the March MO figure would be stronger than forecast, many of which had not accounted for the sharp jump in the amount of cash in circulation over the Easter weekend as consumers raided their bank accounts.</p>
<p>He said consumer credit figures were also likely to show a pick up.</p>
<p>The distributive trade survey for March, published by the Confederation of British Industry will hold the market's interest on Thursday, as analysts said it would indicate any slowing in the strong pattern in consumption set by the first two months' figures.</p>
<p>Adams said he expected the figures to be softer than previously, but pointed out they could be boosted by the early Easter this year and &quot;should be taken with a pinch of salt&quot;.</p>
<p>If they were strong, Adams said the market may find itself &quot;tarred with the same brush as the U.S.&quot;</p>
<p>Recent data has indicated the service sector is far outperforming other industries, and analysts said a new CIPS report on Friday would cast some welcome insight on the sector.</p>
<p>&quot;It should provide some enlightening information,&quot; said Rayner. &quot;Everyone is expecting to see a fairly bright outlook for services, but I wonder whether the survey might be even stronger than people's expectations... if it does point to a firmer first quarter, it's going to be negative for gilts.&quot;</p>
<p>He said with the spread over Bunds now at 186 basis points, it could drift out to 190 if the survey is very strong.</p>
<p>&quot;But we're getting to levels where gilts are looking fairly good value and as long as sterling remains firmer I think we probably won't widen much further.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
