<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478472" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada dlr slides to end weakest in nearly 2 years.</title>
<headline>Canada dlr slides to end weakest in nearly 2 years.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canada's dollar ended weaker on Tuesday at C$1.3888 (US$0.7200) from Monday's close of C$1.3839 (US$0.7225) under continued pressure from speculation the U.S. Federal Reserve would hike interest rates again.</p>
<p>The currency hit its weakest level at C$1.3889 (US$0.7199) since April 7, 1995 under pressure from the possibility of wider spreads between Canadian and U.S. interest rates.</p>
<p>Analysts said that selling pressure on the Canada dollar would persist as long as the Bank of Canada resisted the pull of higher interest rates and market speculation leaned toward another U.S. rate hike in May.  </p>
<p>&quot;The overriding issue here is that the Fed has tightened, the Bank (of Canada) hasn't. The market is not willing to live with a widening in the differential in monetary policy between Canada and the U.S.,&quot; said Andrew Spence, a senior economist with Deutsche Morgan Grenfell.</p>
<p>Traders also said the dollar had weakened due to shaken international investor confidence in Canadian markets because of the troubled saga of Bre-X Minerals Ltd.</p>
<p>The Toronto Stock Exchange's computer trading system collapsed under the groaning weight of trading volume in Bre-X on Tuesday and twice last Thursday.  </p>
<p>Continued uncertainties about the value of Canadian prospecting company Bre-X Minerals Ltd's gold find at Busang, Indonesia, thought to be one of the world's largest, threw markets into more turmoil on Tuesday. Concerns surfaced last week that the site may contain much less gold than stated, stunning mining experts and investors. Bre-X said last Wednesday that there appeared to be a &quot;strong possibility that potential gold resources have been overstated.&quot;</p>
<p>The news followed the mysterious death of Bre-X chief geologist Michael de Guzman, who fell out of a helicopter on his way to Busang on March 19.  </p>
<p>On the crosses, the Canadian dollar dropped to 1.2010 marks from 1.2098 marks on Monday and dipped to 87.81 yen from Monday's 89.41 yen.</p>
<p>((Paul Casciato, Reuters Toronto Bureau 416 941-8100 or email: paul.casciato@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
