<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478487" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Mobutu's arch-foe nominated as Zaire premier.</title>
<headline>Mobutu's arch-foe nominated as Zaire premier.</headline>
<byline>William Wallis</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1996-04-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zaire's opposition nominated Etienne Tshisekedi, President Mobutu Sese Seko's arch-foe, as new prime minister to steer the country through negotiations with rebels who hold a quarter of the nation's territory.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi has long favoured talks with rebel chief Laurent Kabila to end the war launched from eastern Zaire in October.</p>
<p>But few Zaireans have any illusion that his eventual appointment could make any difference to the conflict, in which rebels have outclassed a demoralised government army.</p>
<p>Many Zairean politicians said they expected Mobutu to move quickly to sign Tshisekedi's appointment into law, thus handing his political rival a poisoned chalice.</p>
<p>&quot;This could be the ruin of Tshisekedi,&quot; a politician said.</p>
<p>After a week of bitter wrangling, the leadership of the USORAL opposition alliance voted overwhelmingly on Tuesday night for the appointment of Tshisekedi as replacement for prime minister Kengo wa Dondo, who resigned a week ago. The vote was 54 for and eight against with 10 abstentions. &quot;We have just designated Mr Tshisekedi wa Malumba as prime minister,&quot; USORAL leader Frederic Kibassa told the pro-Mobutu Presidential Movement in parliament.</p>
<p>Presidential Movement leader Idambituo Bakata indicated Mobutu would endorse the appointment of the man he sacked as prime minister in December 1992. A sovereign conference reappointed Tshisekedi but Mobutu again dismissed him in 1993.</p>
<p>&quot;I would like to express my great joy, the joy, I think, of all the nation, for the simple fact that today you have given us a conclusion that many of our citizens were waiting for,&quot; Bakata said on the nomination.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi, 64, has huge popular support in Zaire.</p>
<p>But with rebels keeping up pressure on the battlefield while preparing for negotiations, even some of Tshisekedi's staunchest supporters say he could be Mobutu's last prime minister.</p>
<p>Kabila has made clear that he will not accept politicians who collaborate with Mobutu in a transitional government Kabila hopes will be formed after negotiations due to start in South Africa at the weekend.</p>
<p>Under Zaire's transitional constitution, the Presidential Movement which forms the majority in parliament has to approve the nomination before Mobutu formally signs it into law.</p>
<p>Parliament voted nearly two weeks ago to oust Kengo, a part-Tutsi who has been widely denounced for weakness in dealing with the rebellion spearheaded by ethnic Tutsis.</p>
<p>Banyamulenge Tutsis took up arms in October after local authorities tried to expel them to their ancestral homeland in Rwanda.</p>
<p>The rebels have captured key towns in east and south Zaire, and have now set their sights on the Shaba provincial capital Lubumbashi, Zaire's mainstay copper and cobalt mining hub situated close to Tshisekedi's Kasai tribal area.</p>
<p>President Mobutu, suffering from prostate cancer, is sending a seven-man team headed by his security adviser to represent the central authorities in talks with Kabila's Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire (ADFL) in South Africa this week, Zaire's state television said on Monday.</p>
<p>The team, which includes Foreign Minister Kamanda wa Kamanda and representatives of both the opposition and the president's supporters in the transitional parliament, will travel to South Africa on Thursday, it said.</p>
<p>In the northeast, thousands of sick and exhausted Hutu refugees from Rwanda and Burundi struggled to get clear of the battle zone, moving south from rebel-held Kisangani and in the east towards Rwanda.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
