<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478439" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Air HK gives UK agents fuel surcharge promise.</title>
<headline>Air HK gives UK agents fuel surcharge promise.</headline>
<byline>Bob Murphy</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Air Hong Kong's UK station said it has told its customers that whenever possible they will in future be given 28 days' notice of any future fuel price surcharges that may be imposed.</p>
<p>Along with many other carriers, all-cargo carrier AHK introduced a surcharge --in line with that charged by British Airways World Cargo -- of six pence per kg on freight carried on its ex-UK services, last autumn after jet fuel prices soared.</p>
<p>UK country manager Bob Wetherill told Reuters that his forwarders and shippers were then given two weeks' notice of the surcharge implementation, although many other carriers gave their customers no warning.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to be fair to our agents and shippers,&quot; said Wetherill, explaining that they in turn had to pass on the information -- and the surcharges -- to their own clients.</p>
<p>AHK is 75 percent owned by Cathay Pacific Airways and Wetherill said he had asked his head office in Hong Kong if and when the current fuel surcharge would be lifted.</p>
<p>&quot;I have yet to receive an answer but I believe that as soon as fuel prices return to July 1996 levels, then the surcharge currently in place should be withdrawn,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are already getting questions from our customers on what the situation is with the surcharge,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Delta Air Lines, Virgin Atlantic Airways and United Airlines have announced they are lifting their fuel surcharges.</p>
<p>In the UK, Lufthansa Cargo AG has promised to give its forwarder and shipper customers one month's notice of any future fuel surcharge implementations.</p>
<p>-Reuters Air Cargo Newsroom Tel +44 171 542 7706; fax +5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
