<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478460" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - RBNZ chief wants new NZ FX/interest rate mix.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - RBNZ chief wants new NZ FX/interest rate mix.</headline>
<byline>Lisa Wilson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Reserve Bank of New Zealand (RBNZ) governor Don Brash said on Tuesday he would like a new mix of lower foreign exchange rates and higher interest rates to take the economy forward.</p>
<p>Since January 1993, the currency has risen more than 40 percent against the U.S. dollar, advancing from US$0.5010 to as high as US$0.7170 in November 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd be much happier with a somewhat lower exchange rate and somewhat higher interest rates,&quot; said Brash in an interview with Reuters Financial Television (RFTV).</p>
<p>&quot;We've had a very strong rise in exchange rates and a fall in interest rates. Now I'd prefer to see a different combination -- somewhat lower exchange rates and somewhat higher interest rates,&quot; Brash said.</p>
<p>New Zealand's strong currency has hit exporters particularly hard, and put pressure on the new centre-right National-New Zealand First coalition to curb spending plans.</p>
<p>The RBNZ does not set interest rates administratively, like most central banks of industrialised countries, but relies on regulating the amount of cash in the system. Brash added, &quot;We can be happy with a lower currency if we have higher interest rates and vice versa.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked to give an optimum level for the New Zealand dollar, he said, &quot;The best level for the currency is the level which delivers ongoing price stability. At this point, we look as though this will be achieved.&quot;</p>
<p>The New Zealand dollar was trading at US$0.6970 by 1304 GMT, compared with US$0.6950 at the Wellington close on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Brash repeated the central bank's view inflation would fall below 1.0 percent next year, then rise through 1999 to 2000.</p>
<p>&quot;The biggest single factor in the second half of this year particularly is the delayed response of New Zealand prices to the rise in the exchange rate which we've seen over the last two or three years,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Although the inflation target band was increased last year to zero-to-3.0 percent from zero-to-2.0 percent, Brash said, &quot;I'd be very disappointed indeed if we went above 3.0 percent.&quot;</p>
<p>If inflation did go above the 3.0 percent target, he said he would reconsider his position as governor. &quot;Whenever we go outside the target, over the top or under the bottom, I look very carefully at my position and so does the board,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In terms of gross domestic product data, Brash said he was as surprised as many analysts were by the strength of the December quarter, when the economy grew 0.7 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;We were expecting GDP in the March 97 quarter to be up by only some 2.0 percent over the March 96 quarter and in fact it looks at this stage as though it might be slightly stronger,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- International Bonds Unit +44 171 542 6137</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
