<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478400" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: LAUMA 1996 PROFITS STABLE, SEES LOWER 1997.</title>
<headline>LAUMA 1996 PROFITS STABLE, SEES LOWER 1997.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lauma, a leading textile and lingerie producer on the privatisation list, on Tuesday reported 1.38 million lats of after-tax profit in 1996 versus a 1.25 million lat profit the previous year.</p>
<p>The 1996 turnover was 21.14 million lats, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;The company plans to increase its net turnover to 23.68 million and after-tax profit will be 1.33 million lats,&quot; the company said in a statement.</p>
<p>Lauma, which employs some 2,400 people, decided at its shareholders' meeting in March to pay 30 percent of the profit in dividends.</p>
<p>The company, currently on the privatisation list, is still mostly state owned, with 4.10 million lats of its basic capital in state hands versus total share capital of 5.98 million lats.</p>
<p>French corset producer Naturana, Belorussian Milavica and some Latvian companies are also among its shareholders.</p>
<p>Lauma's biggest export market is the former Soviet Union with 66.4 percent sold there in 1996.</p>
<p>Some 27 percent of its output stays in the Baltic market, of which 12.9 percent in Latvia.</p>
<p>Some six percent of Lauma's produce is exported to Germany, France and Scandinavia with exports to Europe planned to increase slightly in 1997, a company spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have introduced new, high-quality materials, like Lycre from Dupont,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>-- Martinsh Gravitis, Riga Newsroom, +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I43000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
