<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478447" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: LIFFE cocoa bounces late but still ends softer.</title>
<headline>LIFFE cocoa bounces late but still ends softer.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>LIFFE cocoa futures ended down on Tuesday but off session lows made after arbitrage between London and New York markets emerged in the afternoon.</p>
<p>The spread with lead month May cocoa in New York stood at about 211.53 at London's close as May closed down 1 at 1,016 stg per tonne on LIFFE. July ended down 4 at 1,028.</p>
<p>Outright activity was sluggish, but switches were active to help boost volume to a total 6,978 contracts. Traders said trade houses did switches in December/May 1998, December/July and December/September.</p>
<p>Once arbitrage evaporated, prices rebounded but failed to erase all losses.</p>
<p>In the near-term, traders and analysts expected mostly range-trading with some downside risk.</p>
<p>One trader saw the CFTC's Commitment of Traders report released over the weekend as a bearish sign. The report showed speculators accumulating more long positions.</p>
<p>An analyst at Merrill Lynch also said the market looked vulnerable because of the lack of encouraging fundamental news.</p>
<p>&quot;Arrivals data has pointed to an even higher Ivorian crop than many had anticpated,&quot; Merrill Lynch said in its biweekly outlook. &quot;Arrivals in the next weeks will confirm whether the mid-crop is indeed large. With the main crop figures better than expected, many feel there is little reason for the mid-crop to come in small, especially since earlier concerns about dry weather and possible stress to the crop has faded.&quot;</p>
<p>Weather analysts in Abidjan said on Tuesday that rains continued to strengthen over Ivory Coast's cocoa belt in mid-March after February's drought, favouring development of the mid-crop (May-September).</p>
<p>GNI forecasts a 1.1-million tonne Ivory Coast crop.</p>
<p>Some analysts also said sterling's recent rise against the dollar contributed to cocoa's failure to rally sharply.</p>
<p>But technically, analysts and traders were impressed with cocoa's resilience against a chart gap between 989 and 982.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch said in a report that seasonals were pointing to a period of higher prices and increased volatility but warned that &quot;price hikes are usually followed by an equally forceful selloff. With the open interest over 100,000 lots and speculators long, we see the market as extremely vulnerable.&quot;</p>
<p>For cocoa to look very bullish again, a trader said May would first have to rally above 1,048 stg and July through 1,055.</p>
<p>--Medora Lee, London newsroom  +44 171 542 8072</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
