<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478502" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.Africa rand/bonds closing report.</title>
<headline>S.Africa rand/bonds closing report.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African long bonds ended around 12 basis point softer after the Easter break on Thursday, ruffled by a fall in U.S. assets markets as fears about a further rise in U.S. interest rates continued.</p>
<p>At 1402 GMT the key R150 bond was yielding 15.29 percent -- its worst level of the day and a two-month high --  from 15.13 percent late on Thursday.</p>
<p>Bond dealers said the market was nervous to break the 15.30 percent level on the top as players were keen to remain square ahead of the release of March gold and foreign exchange reserves data due out at 1600 GMT on Tuesday.</p>
<p>In addition, players were awaiting February money supply and private sector credit extension figures due at 1500 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Economists polled by Reuters expected a gross reserves figure of between 11.5 to 13.5 billion rand with consensus at 12.58 billion rand compared to 12.49 billion rand in February.</p>
<p>&quot;The market was marked up on the back of the U.S. and sentiment is generally nervous,&quot; one trader at a leading bank said.</p>
<p>He said there had been some institutional nibbling at the higher levels.</p>
<p>&quot;The 15.30 percent level will most likely hold because players are keen to remain square ahead of the local economic data due out today and tomorrow,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Economists polled by Reuters forecast the latest M3 figure falling to between 14.75 percent and 15.75 percent with consensus at 15.1 percent from a preliminary January figure of 16.89 percent.</p>
<p>Annual credit growth was seen easing to between 15.50 percent and 16.92 with the consensus at 16.39 percent compares with a preliminary rise of 17.07 percent in January.</p>
<p>Bond traders said the 15.28 to 15.30 percent levels were critical ones on the upside and that it appeared a weaker trend was creeping into the local market.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like we're now in the correction that everyone has been looking for and with the Reserve Bank starting its funding soon the market is not going to strengthen quickly,&quot; a second trader said.</p>
<p>The Bond Exchange said foreigners were net buyers of 203.72 million rand's worth of South African bonds on Thursday after buying 480.64 million rand's worth on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Nominal cumulative volumes on Thursday -- a settlement data -- were pegged at 37.82 billion rand from 8.12 billion rand on Wednesday.  </p>
<p>On the forex side, the rand moved over three cents firmer to an intraday best level of 4.39 on the U.S. dollar but retraced most of its gains during the day on offshore profit-taking.</p>
<p>At 1440 GMT it was trading at 4.4190/20 versus the dollar from 4.4215/4245 late on Thursday.</p>
<p>The driving force behind the unit's early morning gains was offshore and local dollar sales with forex dealers pinpointing the 4.39 level as the big one to break on the downside although they said this would be tough.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd be surprised to see 4.39 go...I would say the market is a bit confused at the moment, sentiment is mixed and it looks more likely that we will drift between 4.4050 and 4.4200 in the immediate future,&quot; a trader at a foreign bank said.</p>
<p>Against the crosses, the rand was last at 7.2710/2804 against sterling from 7.1882/2008 and at 0.3769/3773 marks from 0.3799/3805 marks.</p>
<p>Money market rates remained within their recent ranges with three-month deposit rates quoted steady at 16.50 to 16.55 percent offered and the 90-day BA rate at between 15.90 to 16.10 percent.</p>
<p>South Africa's money market shortage was still above the 10 billion rand mark on Saturday, rising to 10.455 billion rand from 10.980 billion rand on Thursday, the Reserve Bank said.</p>
<p>-- Vera von Lieres, Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
