<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478501" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.African stock market closing report.</title>
<headline>S.African stock market closing report.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African shares ended well down after enduring an early battering on the back of Wall Street's second successive heavy fall, dealers said.</p>
<p>The South African drop joined in a global rush of falling shares as major world financial markets followed New York's lead and share prices tumbled.</p>
<p>&quot;Wall Street hit us pretty hard, but that was to be expected,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>On Monday heightened concern about the outlook for U.S. interest rates sent New York stocks down for the second straight session. The Dow industrials tumbled 157 points to 6,583. The drop came after a 140 point slide on Thursday.</p>
<p>South Africa's all-share index lost 132.4 points, or 1.87 percent, to 6,962.4 as industrials dropped 164.8 points, or 1.98 percent, to 8,174.6.</p>
<p>Nearly all blue-chips posted price losses as only 56 shares -- mostly small firms -- managed to crawl upwards while 287 counters sank into the red.</p>
<p>Anglo lost 500 cents to 268.50 rand and De Beers dropped 425 cents 156.75 rand. Confusion reigned around SA Breweries as the firm become caught in a rumour mill about a possible Austrian deal with drinks group BBAG.</p>
<p>BBAG said the firm had made a bid, but SAB scotched the talk saying only informal and fruitless discussions had taken place with one of BBAG's shareholders.</p>
<p>&quot;There was no formal bid, no formal negotiations,&quot; SAB corporate finance and development director Malcolm Wyman told Reuters.</p>
<p>SAB ended the day down 300 cents to 137.00 rand.  </p>
<p>Dealers said that there had been little bargain-hunting at lower levels and this explained why share prices had not been able to build up any recovery after the early fall. All market eyes will now be on Wall Street's performance overnight.</p>
<p>&quot;It all hinges on Wall Street, but there will probably be a rise,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>U.S. analysts have predicted a short-term rally, but in the longer term see the overall correction going down to around 6,400/500.</p>
<p>South Africa's gold shares initially fared better and offered some stubborn resistance to the market's downward trend. However, a renewed bout of jitters on the bullion price tweaking below $350 an ounce sent them down in the afternoon.</p>
<p>The golds index ended down 9.3 points to 1,292.3.</p>
<p>Trade on the day was marred by an electrical power failure at around 0900 GMT that saw business suspended for about an hour and also crashed the bourse's phone lines and personal computers.</p>
<p>However, the Johannesburg Stock Exchange was at pains to point out that its JET equities trading system had not been at fault.</p>
<p>&quot;The (JET) trading system has not gone down. We are having trouble with the electricity. Whether it is a power failure or a power surge we don't know,&quot; the spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Trading resumed at around 1030 GMT and dealers said the halt had had little effect on the day's trade as most orders had been placed early in the morning. &quot;It had no real impact,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>South African share futures also tumbled early on and remained near their low levels, smarting from the losses on Wall Street.</p>
<p>The all-share June contract was last at 6,365/80 from 6,509 as the industrials contract dipped to 7,930/45 from 8,118.</p>
<p>The golds contract, however, recovered nearly all of its lost ground and was at 903/913 from 919.</p>
<p>-- Paul Harris, Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
