<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478598" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: UNHCR says Sarajevo denies housing to minorities.</title>
<headline>UNHCR says Sarajevo denies housing to minorities.</headline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) on Tuesday accused Bosnian Moslem authorities in Sarajevo of disriminating against Serbs and Croats trying to return to flats it had repaired.</p>
<p>The Sarajevo canton had permitted only Moslem families to move into flats repaired by the UNHCR at a cost of 6.8 million German marks ($4 million), a UNHCR spokesman told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;For months now the cantonal minister of housing has failed to present 29 families with the keys to their newly-renovated apartments despite sufficient evidence of their tenancy rights,&quot; said UNHCR spokesman Kris Janowski.</p>
<p>&quot;Virtually all those concerned are Serbs and Croats which gives us cause to believe that they are being discriminated against because of their ethnicity,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Munib Buljina, minister for housing in the Sarajevo canton, was unavailable for comment.</p>
<p>Janowski said the refusal by Sarajevo authorities to permit minorities to return to their homes threatened &quot;Sarajevo's image as a multi-ethnic city&quot; and violated the spirit of the UNHCR housing project.</p>
<p>The UNHCR has repeatedly tried to persuade the cantonal authority &quot;to reverse its position but so far to no avail&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Despite reports of abuses in Sarajevo, Janowski said the city was still far more tolerant towards ethnic minorities than other towns, including Serb-controlled Banja Luka or Croat-controlled western Mostar.</p>
<p>Sarajevo was once known for its mixed population but after the Bosnian conflict and a 43-month long Serb siege, the city is predominantly Moslem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
