<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478543" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: FEATURE - Untangling corporate South Africa.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Untangling corporate South Africa.</headline>
<byline>Ben Hirschler</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Slowly but surely corporate South Africa is untangling the complex web of cross-shareholdings that built the inward-looking conglomerates of the apartheid era.</p>
<p>A few more threads will unravel this month when the industrial group Malbak Ltd, with interests ranging from vehicle retailing to pharmaceuticals, completes an unbundling of assets that it says will boost shareholder value by 15 percent.</p>
<p>Malbak is the third major industrial holding company to break itself up, following a lead first set by Barlow Ltd and Gencor Ltd in 1993.</p>
<p>The past year has seen a flood of companies following suit, including the biggest investment trust Genbel South Africa Ltd.</p>
<p>Marinus Daling, chairman of life assurance giant Sanlam which has used its controlling stakes to pioneer restructuring at Gencor, Genbel and Malbak, is an unbundling enthusiast.</p>
<p>He sees long-term gains beyond the once-off unlocking of the discount to net asset value at which conglomerates' shares typically trade.</p>
<p>&quot;I have always been of the very strong belief that what drives unbundling is the focus of management,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;If you can focus the minds of the management so that they can create better companies on an ongoing basis, then you will continue to add value for shareholders and that, in my view, is the important part of it.&quot;</p>
<p>ISOLATIONIST PAST</p>
<p>South Africa's conglomerates are largely a product of the isolationist past when exchange controls locked up capital, forcing diversification into a host of industries at home. Those controls still remain but their days are numbered.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Trevor Manuel announced the latest steps to dismantle capital controls in his March 12 budget, including key concessions for companies who will be able to raise funds internationally against their domestic balance sheets.</p>
<p>&quot;In the past, people couldn't take their money and expand their core business internationally. The moment you can do that there is an incentive to break down the conglomerates and focus your business,&quot; said Daling.</p>
<p>At the same time old trade barriers are coming down, exposing industry to the icy blast of foreign competition.</p>
<p>In today's climate the logic of diversified groups with tentacles in every corner of the South African economy is proving harder to justify.</p>
<p>Conglomerates, often controlled via pyramids in which a holding company owns 50 percent of another holding firm which owns 50 percent of yet another, were an early target for the African National Congress government.</p>
<p>But recently the political heat has been turned down as the same structures that helped enrich the Rupert and Oppenheimer families have been put to use by black empowerment groups, like Nthato Motlana's New Africa Investments Ltd.</p>
<p>MARKET PRESSURE</p>
<p>Instead, the pressure is coming from the market and demands from shareholders that conglomerates unlock share discounts.</p>
<p>Dana Becker, head of research at ING Barings in Johannesburg, believes the unbundling trend is becoming unstoppable, driven by not only by domestic considerations but also by a new-found desire to please global investors.</p>
<p>&quot;We are getting a lot more interest from foreign investors in our stock market and if you are an unfocused conglomerate you are very undesirable in the eyes of a foreign investor.&quot;</p>
<p>Foreign fund managers, looking for &quot;pure plays&quot;, wanted to buy direct into operating companies, he said.</p>
<p>Market talk suggests other candidates for unbundling could include Murray and Roberts Holdings Ltd and Gold Fields of South Africa Ltd.</p>
<p>But the biggest of them all, Anglo American Corp of South Africa Ltd, is resisting the trend, professing itself happy with its diversity.</p>
<p>Robin McGregor, an independent analyst and member of the government's Competition Board, says Anglo's industrial holding concern Anglo American Industrial Corp Ltd (Amic) would be a natural for unbundling.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a clear trend. It's happened with three major holding companies -- Barlows, Gencor and now Malbak -- and the only really major one left is Amic. With a bit of luck they will do it as well,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Amic chairman Leslie Boyd rules out such a move.</p>
<p>&quot;If you haven't got big companies, you can't do big things. And if you can't do big things, then you can't compete in the global village,&quot; Boyd said recently.</p>
<p>ANGLO KEEPS EMPIRE</p>
<p>Amic, like parent Anglo, sees no reason to break up its empire. But a subtle shift is nonetheless under way at Anglo, which has already dismantled some operations in order to transfer assets to black hands.</p>
<p>Two years ago its JCI group was split into three new companies -- JCI Ltd, Johnnies Industrial Corp Ltd and Anglo American Platinum Corp Ltd -- the first two of which are now under black control.</p>
<p>South Africa's biggest company is currently engaged in a strategic review which could see the disposal of certain &quot;non-core&quot; interests.</p>
<p>At the same time it is busy expanding its international mining interests, taking a 28 percent stake in Lonrho Plc with a clear eye to that firm's African mines.</p>
<p>Anglo may retain its structure, but gradually South Africa's economic colossus could be evolving into more focused international resources concern, analysts believe.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
