<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478552" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albanian PM visits rebel-held south for talks.</title>
<headline>Albanian PM visits rebel-held south for talks.</headline>
<byline>Stephen Weeks</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanian Prime Minister Bashkim Fino went to the rebel-held south on Tuesday for the first time since insurgents seized the region last month and immediately began talks with their leaders.</p>
<p>He arrived by helicopter in the stronghold of Gjirokaster, 30 km (20 miles) from the Greek border, and was greeted warmly by rebels bristling with guns, local reporters said.</p>
<p>Fino, the former Socialist mayor of Gjirokaster, also shook hands with Gjoleke Malaj, the rebel boss in Tepelene to the north.</p>
<p>He told reporters he was in the region to meet the &quot;legal representatives of local power and public order&quot; but quickly moved to discussions with rebels and elected officials alike.</p>
<p>Elected officials have remained in the region but the south has been run by rebel Committees of Public Salvation since the army was driven out and weapons depots looted in early March.</p>
<p>&quot;I thank the salvation committees for the role they played at a moment of paralysis of local power,&quot; he told an assembly which grouped elected officials and rebel committees.</p>
<p>&quot;But I would like to make clear that without restoration of legal instititions, calm and order cannot return and general elections held,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Right-wing President Sali Berisha was forced to name Fino, an opposition Socialist, to head an all-party crisis government on March 11. Berisha also bowed to demands elections be held three years early and they are due in June.</p>
<p>Albania has been swept by violence since January when a number of popular investment schemes collapsed, wiping out millions of dollars in savings.</p>
<p>The anti-government riots and protests evolved into a full- scale uprising against Berisha, who is blamed for letting the fraudulent &quot;pyramid&quot; schemes flourish.</p>
<p>Most of the south is now outside of government control and the rebels' main demand is that Berisha quit.</p>
<p>Fino's visit to the south could cause even deeper divisions in the fragile all-party cabinet formed after army and police forces collapsed in the turmoil and rebels seized thousands of weapons.</p>
<p>Fino's appointment ended the grip on power which Berisha's Democratic Party had held since 1992, but the compromise has been strained from the start with both sides already vying for the June election.</p>
<p>The Socialists met recently with rebels holding the port of Vlore, where the uprising began, and drew the wrath of Berisha.</p>
<p>&quot;Each party ... must decide either to be on the side of the legitimate government or the side of the communist rebels that want to overthrow the government by force of arms,&quot; a senior Berisha advisor, Genc Pollo, said on Sunday.</p>
<p>Fino's trip to Gjirokaster and later to rebel-held Tepelene is likely to undermine relations with Berisha and the Democrats further.</p>
<p>After his trip to the rebel south, Fino will leave by car on Wednesday for Greece to meet Prime Minister Costas Simitis to discuss the Albanian crisis.</p>
<p>Fino will be joined in Greece by Albania's ministers of finance, interior and foreign affairs for a two-day visit.</p>
<p>About 350,000 illegal Albanians work in Greece, having fled across the long border after the fall of communism. Greece also keeps an eye on a large ethnic Greek community in Albania.</p>
<p>The large minority communities have caused friction between the Balkan neighbours in the past but both sides have worked in recent years to improve relations.</p>
<p>Fino and Simitis, both Socialists, will discuss bilateral relations and the crisis in Albania. Fino will be sounding out Greece's views as a European Union member and as a participant in a planned multinational force in Albania, his office said.</p>
<p>Italy pressed on with preparing the multinational security force for lawless Albania on Tuesday and tried to ease strained relations by calling for a joint Rome-Tirana inquiry into the sinking of an Albanian refugee boat last week.</p>
<p>The Italian-led force will include contingents from Greece, France, Turkey, Spain and Romania. The U.N. backed force will protect international relief supplies for Albania.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
