<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478509" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Retreating Zaire soldiers disarmed in Lubumbashi.</title>
<headline>Retreating Zaire soldiers disarmed in Lubumbashi.</headline>
<byline>Richard Meares</byline>
<dateline>LUBUMBASHI, Zaire 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Government soldiers fleeing advancing rebels arrived in Zaire's second city of Lubumbashi, but were disarmed by military police to prevent looting, expatriate sources said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Some 120 soldiers who abandoned the rail and military town of Kamina on Sunday seized a train to take them on the 24-hour journey to Lubumbashi, the hub of Zaire's copper industry in southern Shaba Province.</p>
<p>The city is the immediate target of rebels who took up arms last October to topple President Mobutu Sese Seko, in power since 1965. Rebels now hold a quarter of Zaire, which is the size of Western Europe.</p>
<p>The retreating soldiers entered Lubumbashi in the same disorderly fashion they have done in other cities before abandoning them to rebels advancing steadily from the east.</p>
<p>&quot;They didn't respect any of the normal traffic rules,&quot; said one irate expatriate, surprised at how quickly the train of soldiers, and another carrying 18 fleeing officers, had reached the province's capital 600 km (370 miles) away.</p>
<p>There is little but bush and a few small trading or mining towns on the way.</p>
<p>Military police, about the only remaining force in the area with full uniforms, were waiting for them at Lubumbashi's elegant colonial railway station when they arrived and cordially disarmed them without resistance, the sources said.</p>
<p>The fall of Kamina, which effectively cuts Lubumbashi from the rest of government-held Zaire and traps soldiers on one side of the rebel lines, failed to cause much concern in the city whose main goal is to survive the civil war unscathed.</p>
<p>&quot;Our soldiers just ran away without a fight,&quot; said waiter Kaizer Nzenga, with hoots of laughter.</p>
<p>People in Shaba, which has fought several times to secede from Zaire, say rebel leader Laurent Kabila is a saviour whose arrival they long for.</p>
<p>Their main fear is looting by retreating soldiers, who last ransacked the town in 1991 in a pay dispute.</p>
<p>&quot;The boys who only earn about a dollar or two a month, they want to loot. It has almost become a habit,&quot; said Frances Mwepu, a student.</p>
<p>There is little sign in Lubumbashi of any attempt to mount a credible defence of the town, whose streets are full of talk that the army is melting away as the rebels approach.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm meant to be defending the airport but of course I'm not going to fight,&quot; said one soldier in town.</p>
<p>Rebels or local sympathisers are only 220 km (120 miles) away in the small town of Kasenga on the Zambian border. Expatriate sources said an army attempt to retake the town this week had failed.</p>
<p>The biggest concern in Lubumbashi on Tuesday was that peace talks between the rebels and the Kinshasa authorities, due this weekend in South Africa, might delay the advance.</p>
<p>&quot;They really should come as soon as possible and not delay,&quot; said Nzenga.</p>
<p>Mobutu was away in Europe for cancer treatment for most of the time since the rebellion erupted. After months of tough talking, he yielded to battlefield pressure and agreed to negotiations with the rebels.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUBUMBASHI, Zaire"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
