<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478514" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: Sudan rebels say seized four northeast districts.</title>
<headline>Sudan rebels say seized four northeast districts.</headline>
<byline>Peter Smerdon</byline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sudanese rebel leader John Garang said on Tuesday rebels seized four districts in northeast Sudan in an offensive aimed at cutting Khartoum's main link with the outside world.</p>
<p>He said a coalition of rebels &quot;liberated&quot; the districts of Karora, Itairba, Agiti and Agigi last week and over the weekend and were advancing towards the town of Tokar.</p>
<p>Garang, leader of the Sudan People's Liberation Army (SPLA) and military commander of the National Democratic Alliance (NDA), said NDA forces were destroying Khartoum's &quot;military and security machine&quot; in the northeast.</p>
<p>&quot;The citizens of the four districts have returned to their normal life and are forming their civil administrations from within the local population,&quot; Garang said in a statement issued by the SPLA office in the Eritrean capital Asmara.</p>
<p>He said relatives and families of more than 100 prisoners of war seized by rebels in the last week should know they were in safe hands and were receiving &quot;the good treatment they deserve&quot;.</p>
<p>In Khartoum, the army journal al-Nasr said on Tuesday that independent militias killed 70 SPLA guerrillas and captured 18 in an attack on the rebels near Akobo on the Ethiopian border in the south on Monday.</p>
<p>The rebels say the northeast offensive is aimed at cutting the road between Khartoum and Port Sudan on the Red Sea.</p>
<p>Tokar is 150 km (90 miles) southeast of Port Sudan, the main link for Africa's largest country to the rest of the world.</p>
<p>The nearest stretch of the 670-km (420-mile) road from Khartoum to Port Sudan is about 100 km (60 miles) northwest of Tokar, which is another 100 km (60 miles) northwest of Karora.</p>
<p>Sudanese officials said on Monday that government forces were fighting Eritrean and Ethiopian troops which had taken control of border areas in Red Sea state in the northeast.</p>
<p>The government-owned Sudan al-Hadith newspaper quoted Red Sea state governor Badawi al-Khair Idris as saying the Eritreans had looted property, imprisoned local leaders and killed a 70-year-old religious figure. There was no independent confirmation of the report.</p>
<p>Eritrea, Ethiopia and the rebels have denied accusations from Khartoum since January that Eritrean and Ethiopian troops were fighting alongside rebel forces in the east and northeast.</p>
<p>Northern rebels of the NDA opposition coalition based in Eritrea attacked the army on the Sudanese side of the border with Eritrea in January but failed to capture much territory.</p>
<p>Rebel units farther south, led by the southern-based SPLA, captured the Sudanese towns of Kurmuk and Qeissan on the Ethiopian border in an attack coordinated with the northerners.</p>
<p>The campaign against the Islamist government shifted in March to the far south, where the SPLA captured the major town of Yei and began to advance towards the regional capital Juba.</p>
<p>The SPLA has been fighting since 1983 for greater autonomy or independence for the Christian and animist south from the Moslem and Arabised north. It and its allies say they want a popular uprising in Khartoum to topple the Islamist government.</p>
<p>But diplomats doubt the rebels can trigger such an uprising and say the only way to end the civil war is by negotiation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
