<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478557" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: PRESS DIGEST - Slovenia - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Slovenia - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>DELO</p>
<p>- Slovenia will contribute troops to the international security force that is to be sent to Albania next week, Albanian radio news said.</p>
<p>- Slovenian Prime Minister Janez Drnovsek was the most popular politician in Slovenia last month, an opinion poll by Delo showed.</p>
<p>- The number of visitors to Slovenia's coastal resorts over the easter holidays rose by 21 percent compared to last year.</p>
<p>- According to an opinion poll by Delo 39 percent of Slovenians questioned were dissatisfied with the government's performance in March, 23 percent said they were satisfied, and the rest had no opinion on the issue.</p>
<p>- An economic delegation from Thailand starts a three day visit to Slovenia on Tuesday.</p>
<p>- Slovenian inflation in March eased to 7.4 percent compared to March 1996, the Slovenian Statistical Office reported.</p>
<p>DNEVNIK</p>
<p>- The Slovenian Defence Ministry plans to cut its military forces to 35,000 from 65,000 as a part of the army's structural preparation for NATO.</p>
<p>VECER</p>
<p>- An agreement between Slovenian banks to cut interest rates on deposits by about 15 percent comes into effect on Monday.The Office for Protection of Competition said that the agreement should promote long-term savings.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
