<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478525" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMEROON: Death toll in Cameroon Anglophone region hits 10.</title>
<headline>Death toll in Cameroon Anglophone region hits 10.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Wotany</byline>
<dateline>YAOUNDE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Clashes between security forces and attackers in Cameroon's volatile English-speaking North-west province have killed 10 people but will not be allowed to disrupt the May election timetable there, the government said.</p>
<p>With legislative elections planned for May, President Paul Biya's communication minister, Augustin Kontchou Koumegni, told a news conference late on Monday that appropriate measures had been taken.</p>
<p>He declined to speculate on the identity of the attackers but police have blamed English-speaking separatists, saying they were trying to steal arms and ammunition from security forces in the provincial capital Bamenda and nearby towns.</p>
<p>&quot;Appropriate measures have been taken to safeguard peace and public order and to ensure that these disturbances do not in any way disrupt the legislative election timetable for this province,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The opposition Social Democratic Front of John Fru Ndi has accused the government of dirty tricks and seeking an excuse to postpone the poll, for which no precise date has been fixed, in the province.</p>
<p>Kontchou said that three paramilitary gendarmes and seven attackers had been killed in the attacks. In the latest, in Bafut, 35 km (20 miles) south of Bamenda, on Monday one attacker was killed, he added. Kontchou said 12 arrests had been made.</p>
<p>An indefinite overnight curfew is in force in the province.</p>
<p>The election will be the second parliamentary poll since Cameroon's sometimes turbulent transition to multi-party democracy began in 1990.</p>
<p>Part of the opposition boycotted the last poll in 1992. Biya supporters secured a majority after allying with a minor party.</p>
<p>Biya, who took over from independence president Ahmadou Ahidjo in 1982, faces a presidential election in October.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CAMER">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="YAOUNDE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMEROON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
