<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478548" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Provisions push Czech SPT into loss, shares fall.</title>
<headline>Provisions push Czech SPT into loss, shares fall.</headline>
<byline>Alan Crosby</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>SPT Telecom a.s. , the Czech Republic's main telephone operator, on Tuesday reported a 483 million crown ($16.7 million) net loss for 1996 as it booked one-off provisions against structural changes.</p>
<p>Chief Financial Officer Urs Kamber told journalists that the firm posted the loss, according to international accounting standards (IAS), due to one-time extraordinary charges of 8.757 billion crowns.</p>
<p>&quot;We are driving toward the fact that we will face tougher, real competition. The way to face this efficiency (of competitors) is by being operationally efficient ourselves,&quot; Kamber said. &quot;We felt the firm was at a point where we could take these charges now.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;In light of our activities in 1996, I am pretty happy with the results,&quot; he said, adding that the firm should return to profitability in 1997.</p>
<p>It made an IAS net profit of 4.83 billion crowns in 1995.</p>
<p>Some analysts applauded the move, saying it could help the company further down the road.</p>
<p>&quot;The move makes sense. It appears as though they are trying to optimise their tax position and I don't think it has anything to do with the functioning of the company or the quality of earnings,&quot; said Jan Sykora of Wood and Company.</p>
<p>&quot;If the loss is its final results, it can be carried forward for the next seven years. So it's a good thing to clean the balance sheet and have a tax shield for the next couple of years,&quot; added another Prague analyst.</p>
<p>In explaining the loss, Kamber said 1.752 billion crowns covered provisions as the firm prepares for layoffs and restructuring that should see SPT shed some 10,000 of its current 26,800 workforce by 2000.</p>
<p>SPT aims to lay off 5,000-6,000 employees through job cuts as it moves to digitalisation, which is less labour-intensive, with the additional losses coming through attrition, currently at about 12 percent annually.</p>
<p>He added that a 7.005 billion crown impairment charge included &quot;a reduction of the accumulated depreciation accounted for in the 1993 opening accounts under IAS&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The depreciation was a little higher than expected but the cash flow figures are coming through as expected and it is basically these one-off adjustments that have made the bottom line sag,&quot; said Anna Bossong of ING Barings in London.</p>
<p>But not all analysts were impressed with the figures, while SPT shares themselves lost minor ground, falling 25 crowns on the Prague Stock Exchange on Tuesday to close 3,425.</p>
<p>&quot;We really hadn't expected such a disaster and frankly it is a disaster,&quot; said Radek Vavra of Citicorp Securities.</p>
<p>He added that activity was thin throughout the day, but could pick up and possibly cause further losses on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Kamber said that costs had risen more than expected in 1996, especially in the area of wage growth, but this was in line with wage developments throughout the country.</p>
<p>Nominal industrial wages rose 17.4 percent, year-on-year, in 1996. This has become one of the key economic points, with both the government and central bank saying something must be done to curb wages in 1997.</p>
<p>Total staff costs at SPT hit 6.24 billion crowns in 1996, up from 4.83 billion for the previous year. Total 1996 operating costs were 18.31 billion, up from 13.76 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;We had to install some 417,000 lines in 1996 and the work that it took...from a planning and cost standpoint was tremendous,&quot; Kamber said.</p>
<p>He added that at the end of 1996, the number of phone lines per employee was 108 but this should rise to more than 300 per employee by 2000.</p>
<p>He said that SPT hoped to install another 450,000 new lines in 1997, with revenues projected to rise by about 20 percent.</p>
<p>SPT is currently seeking a credit rating from Standard and Poor's to give the firm &quot;more borrowing flexibility&quot;, although no international bond issue for this year has been approved yet.</p>
<p>Long distance revenues accounted for 70 percent of totalrevenues, he said, adding that domestic charges would rise slowly and eventually create a more balanced distribution of revenues.</p>
<p>-- Prague Newsroom, 420-2-2423-0003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
