<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478555" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Belarus-Russia deal costly for Moscow - spokesman.</title>
<headline>Belarus-Russia deal costly for Moscow - spokesman.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A controversial draft pact which would commit Russia and Belarus to a close union could worsen Russia's strained finances, the chief government spokesman said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Igor Shabdurasulov told a news conference that the draft Union Treaty was not yet ready -- a day before President Boris Yeltins and Belarus President Alexander Lukashenko were expected to meet in Moscow to sign it.</p>
<p>&quot;It (the agreement) means taking away some financial resources,&quot; Shabdurasulov said. &quot;To a certain extent it will make the financial situation in Russia more complicated.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Even on April 1 this document cannot be considered ready for signing. Even today very serious work is continuing.&quot;</p>
<p>The document provides for close coordination of foreign, military and economic policies between the two former Soviet republics. But it stops short of merging the Slav neighbours into a single state.</p>
<p>Shabdurasulov's remarks appeared to reflect a struggle in Russia's political elite over the draft, which was prepared by Russian and Belarus teams behind closed doors. The official text of the draft treaty has not been published.</p>
<p>Russian liberals have urged Yeltsin not to strike any deal with Lukashenko, a hardliner who has cracked down on his political opponents and expelled a U.S. diplomat, accusing him of interfering in internal affairs.</p>
<p>Yeltsin on Wednesday dispatched security adviser Ivan Rybkin to Minsk to talk to Lukashenko. &quot;He is charged with meeting...Lukashenko and handing him a message from the president of Russia,&quot; the Kremlin press service said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
