<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478591" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungary forint eases vs dlr, strong vs NBH basket.</title>
<headline>Hungary forint eases vs dlr, strong vs NBH basket.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungary's forint could not recoup its morning losses against the dollar by the end of Tuesday afternoon trade and stayed at the National Bank of Hungary's resistance level (NBH bid), dealers said.</p>
<p>The forint finished at 175.68/73 to one dollar, compared with 175.70 just before the midday break and 175.55/60 at the opening.</p>
<p>The forint, which floats against a basket of 30 percent dollar and 70 percent mark, tracked the movements of the dollar/mark on international markets all day.</p>
<p>Dealers said the forint moved in a narrow range betwen 175.55 and 175.75, adding that the forint stayed right at the upper end of the NBH's 4.5 percent wide intervention band.</p>
<p>They said the forint had been pushed to the NBH bid since last week by foreign currency sales of foreign investors, who took advantage of the reduction of the forint's monthly devaluation rate on Tuesday to 1.1 percent from 1.2 percent.</p>
<p>The forint was also strengthened by the NBH's 0.25 percent hike in the interest rate of its six-month deposit facility last Monday, dealers added.</p>
<p>&quot;I can imagine that (foreign investors) will continue to sell, thanks to the NBH's rate hike,&quot; said Attila Behan of ING Bank. &quot;The central bank's aim with the measure was to keep the market attractive for foreigners.&quot;</p>
<p>Following the rate hike, a declining trend of government security yields was not likely to continue, and the yields may even rise slightly, making savings in forints more attracting, he said, adding that the forint was likely to stay near the NBH bid in the near future.</p>
<p>-- Sandor Peto, Budapest newsroom (36 1) 327 4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
