<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478584" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Yugo Feb inter-company debt hits 10 bln dinars.</title>
<headline>Yugo Feb inter-company debt hits 10 bln dinars.</headline>
<byline>Amra Kevic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Growing internal debt and insolvency among Yugoslav firms remain a key factor in the unfavourable business climate in early 1997, the Belgrade-based Institute for Market Research (IZIT) said in its latest report.</p>
<p>&quot;The number of insolvent firms in February rose to 22,356, or two percent more than the previous month,&quot; IZIT chief research economist Slobodan Milosavljevic said.</p>
<p>The total matured debts of these firms, employing around 618,000 people, reached 7.05 billion dinars ($1.27 billion), exceeding M1 money supply by nearly a third, according to data from the central bank's Accounts and Payments Office.</p>
<p>&quot;If the matured debts of other firms that were not insolvent in February are included, this amount is close to 10 billion dinars,&quot; Milosavljevic said.</p>
<p>In a poll conducted by the institute among 200 industrial firms, 68.5 percent said their matured debts had grown in February, while 62 percent said their matured claims had risen.</p>
<p>Disastrous financial discipline only magnifies the negative results, Milosavljevic said.</p>
<p>&quot;Financial non-discipline is rising, liquidity is declining and a large amount of the money supply is still in channels of the 'grey' economy,&quot; IZIT director Jovan Todorovic said.</p>
<p>The prevailing negative trends were more pronounced in February and the first half March, with 41 percent of firms polled describing the economic climate as bad and only four percent as good.</p>
<p>The persistent key obstacles are lack of capital and high insolvency of Yugoslav banks and firms.</p>
<p>The months-long growing discrepancy between the highest and lowest average wages has now peaked at more than 12 times.</p>
<p>At the bottom of the ladder are textile, footwear and rubber industry workers who on average receive 150-200 dinars, and on the other end are bank, insurance and housing maintenance employees earning 1,800-1,900 dinars per month.</p>
<p>Low purchasing power on the local market and barriers to foreign markets have for several months been limiting overall demand and economic activity in the country.</p>
<p>To prevent a further stagnation in economic trends in coming months, problems of ownership transformation, solvency, financial discipline and the huge fiscal burden on the economy must be resolved, the institute said.</p>
<p>According to the institute's poll, most firms did not expect an improvement in the next three or even six months.</p>
<p>&quot;Optimism is weakening because the limitations faced by firms are huge -- lack of working capital, no signals of Yugoslavia's return to international financial institutions and declining demand on the domestic and foreign markets,&quot; Milosavljevic said. -- Belgrade newsroom +381 11 222 4305</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
