<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478513" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOMALIA: Somali faction holds six Kenyans at port.</title>
<headline>Somali faction holds six Kenyans at port.</headline>
<dateline>MOGADISHU 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Somali businessman said authorities loyal to faction leader Hussein Aideed arrested on Tuesday six Kenyan crew members of a ship docked at the Somali port of Merca.</p>
<p>The businessman, Abdi Farah Idle who had hired the ship to carry 800 tonnes of coffee from the Kenyan port of Mombasa, said the Kenyans were charged with violating immigration regulations.</p>
<p>He told reporters immigration officers were demanding a fine of $500 each from the six Kenyans. Businessmen and clan elders in Merca, south of Mogadishu, were negotiating for the release of the men.</p>
<p>A government headed by Hussein Aideed has campaigned in vain for international recognition and imprisoned several foreigners in the last two years, charging them with breaking immigration rules.</p>
<p>The foreigners were released after diplomatic intervention by their countries.</p>
<p>Aid agencies have demanded Somali faction leaders take steps to safeguard foreign aid workers in Somalia, which has had no central government since the fall of late dictator Mohamed Siad Barre in 1991.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SOMAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOGADISHU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOMALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
