<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478551" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin backs Russia-Belarus union-Kremlin.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin backs Russia-Belarus union-Kremlin.</headline>
<byline>Oleg Shchedrov</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin threw his weight on Tuesday behind an agreement on forming a union with Belarus, a Kremlin spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;President Yeltsin states clearly and unequivocally that he is an initiator of the unification of the two fraternal states and their peoples, a consistent and firm supporter of it,&quot; the spokesman quoted presidential press secretary Sergei Yastrzhembsky as telling Russian reporters.</p>
<p>Yastrzhembsky said Yeltsin was planning to sign the Union Treaty with Belarus President Alexander Lukashenko on Wednesday and initial a charter which will later be offered for public discussion in both countries before ratification.</p>
<p>He said the one-month discussion of the charter should not be done by holding a referendum.</p>
<p>Interfax news agency quoted Yastrzhembsky as saying that the union between Russia and Belarus was a matter of paramount importance for both countries.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a geopolitical necessity and an economic reality,&quot; Yastrzhembsky said. But he added that the union document should be treated with caution.</p>
<p>&quot;Before such a step, one should check 100 times to make truly integrational steps,&quot; Yastrzhembsky said.</p>
<p>Less than 24 hours before the meeting between Yeltsin and Lukashenko, it was not clear what kind of document they would sign. The text of the union treaty has been prepared behind closed doors and has not been published in Russia.</p>
<p>A copy of the draft, leaked to the press, provides for close coordination of foreign, military and economic policies but the two Slav states will remain independent. But it stops short of proclaiming a full merger.</p>
<p>The draft document has prompted protests by Belarus nationalists who accuse their hardline leader of surrendering the former Soviet republic's five-year independence.</p>
<p>Russian opponents of the deal say the principle of &quot;one country one vote&quot; included in the treaty is not fair because Russia's population is 15 times bigger and its is economically stronger than Belarus.</p>
<p>Russian liberals have also urged Yeltsin not to make any deal with Lukashenko becasue of his bad record on human rights.</p>
<p>Interfax news agency quoted Yastrzhembsky as denying media reports that the planned union had split the government.</p>
<p>But communists and their allies argue that a union with Belarus was needed and opinon surveys have shown that it had good chances to be backed by the population.</p>
<p>Interfax qoted unnamed Kremlin sources as saying Yeltsin could persuade Lukashenko to sign a short declaratory statement which would keep supporters of the union happy and would not commit Moscow to any obligations.</p>
<p>&quot;The Russian president is known as a master of intrigue who can find unusual solutions in a short time,&quot; the source told Interfax.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
