<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478565" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: Kiev local favoritism seen spurring Motorola exit.</title>
<headline>Kiev local favoritism seen spurring Motorola exit.</headline>
<byline>Irene Marushko</byline>
<dateline>KIEV, Ukraine</dateline>
<text>
<p>Motorola Inc.'s withdrawal from a large mobile telephone network project in Ukraine came as no surprise to analysts who say Kiev has been playing favourites with local companies.</p>
<p>&quot;What this does is takes the real players out and lets the guys on the fringe come in and take over,&quot; one Western analyst said Tuesday.</p>
<p>Motorola announced last week it would pull the plug on a project to launch a global system for mobile communications phone network known as GSM 900 with its local partner, Ukrainian Radio Systems. Motorola owned 49 percent of the venture.</p>
<p>Foreign investors have viewed the former Soviet republic's underdeveloped telecommunications system as a potentially lucrative opportunity but complain about deterrents such as inconsistent laws, corruption and high taxes.</p>
<p>&quot;There were ever-changing terms and conditions,&quot; said Motorola country manager Gregory Perchatsch, who declined to provide further details but said his company had invested several million dollars in setting up the system.</p>
<p>A Ukrainian Communications Ministry spokesman countered, &quot;There were equal conditions for the tender. Why isn't Motorola happy when the other two winners are? It's Motorola's problem.&quot;</p>
<p>Motorola plans to continue participating in a local GSM 1800 network and to sell telecommunications equipment but it had forecast investing $500 million in the next 15 years to supply equipment and to back Ukrainian Radio Systems.</p>
<p>Under Ukrainian law, only local companies are entitled to frequencies.</p>
<p>The Western analyst said Schaumburg, Ill.-based Motorola had quit in reaction to the bidding process for frequencies, which has been drawn out and reportedly seen frequency prices hiked.</p>
<p>&quot;They just said they're not playing this game anymore,&quot; the analyst said.</p>
<p>Three companies, including two foreign joint ventures and a newly created Ukrainian company, won bids in February.</p>
<p>But the Ukrainian government said it would not allocate frequencies for another five months because the companies -- URS-Motorola, Ukrainian Mobile Communications (UMC) and Kiev Star -- were not equally ready to begin.</p>
<p>The analyst said Kiev Star, an unknown concern started last year and thought to be the parent of a Kiev newspaper, needed to find financial backing and equipment. &quot;Kiev Star wouldn't survive without the five months,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Motorola opened its representative office in Ukraine in late 1993 and UMC was formed in 1992.</p>
<p>UMC, owned by the government, the German company Deutsche Telekom AG, Denmark's Tele Danmark AS and the Netherlands' Koninklijke PTT Nederland NV, threatened to withdraw after the government raised tariffs last year.</p>
<p>Some company officials at the time accused Ukraine of shutting out Western competitors from the GSM market.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34531">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV, Ukraine"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
