<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478529" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Shell Nigeria says oil flow down only 50,000 bpd.</title>
<headline>Shell Nigeria says oil flow down only 50,000 bpd.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Nigerian unit of Royal Dutch Shell Group said on Tuesday its crude oil output was now only 50,000 barrels per day (bpd) below normal from 210,000 bpd last week when it was disrupted by communal unrest.</p>
<p>&quot;Oil production is slowly getting back to normal and we are currently just over 50,000 bpd below normal production level,&quot; said a company spokesman in Lagos.</p>
<p>He said in the eastern division all the production disrupted in the Nembe area had been restored while in the western division all but two flow stations had resumed operations.</p>
<p>&quot;In the western division, Batan and Jones Creek flow stations resumed production yesterday. We intend to restart Odidi and Egwa oil fields today,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The shortfall of 50,000 bpd is coming from Egwa and Odidi,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Output was halted at all the affected stations on March 22 by a political dispute between villagers and the military government.</p>
<p>The people had been protesting against relocation of their local government headquarters in the western division while in Nembe they were protesting against the merger of two communities into one municipal council.</p>
<p>The Shell spokesman said the force majeure declared as a result of the output disruptions with effect from April 2 were in respect of Bonny light crude only.</p>
<p>&quot;Outstanding nominations in Bonny will be delayed by three days,&quot; he said, adding that &quot;exports at Forcados terminal have not been affected.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Shell expected all its operations to be back to normal toward the end of April.</p>
<p>--Lagos newsroom +234 1 2630317</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
