<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478560" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albania to consult Rome, Athens over aid force.</title>
<headline>Albania to consult Rome, Athens over aid force.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1996-04-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albania steps up contacts with Italy and Greece on Wednesday over plans for a U.N.-approved multinational force of some 5,000 men to protect aid shipments to the lawless state.</p>
<p>Albanian Prime Minister Bashkim Fino was to travel to Greece after a day in southern Albania, in rebel hands since an insurrection last month, for talks with Prime Minister Costas Simitis on the Italian-led force.</p>
<p>Albanian Defence Minister Shaqir Vukaj was in Italy, trying to prepare the force and smooth relations strained by the sinking of an Albanian vessel packed with refugees in the Adriatic last week after a collision with an Italian corvette.</p>
<p>Tirana says at least 80 people drowned in Albania's worst maritime disaster of modern times. Many of the 34 survivors accused the Italians of ramming their ship, charges the navy denied.</p>
<p>Albanian anger with Italy over the sinking has overshadowed Rome's preparations to lead a force of some 5,000 troops to help distribute food and medical aid in Albania. But both Rome and Tirana insist the mission should go ahead.</p>
<p>&quot;The sea tragedy...and the arrival of the military units from friendly countries, under Italian command, do not have any connection with one another,&quot; Albanian President Sali Berisha said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't say that a military mission is not dangerous, but I am sure that the danger of this mission is not great, and that this mission will be very successful,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Vukaj was due to travel to the port of Brindisi, near where the vessel sank on Friday, for talks with his Italian counterpart Beniamino Andreatta, who has said the force could start deployment by about April 10.</p>
<p>In Rome, military experts from countries planning to contribute to the multinational force were also due to meet to work out details of the force that will help Albania overcome its worst crisis since the fall of communism in 1990.</p>
<p>Italy will lead the force, aimed at securing the ports of Durres and Vlore and Tirana airport. So far Italy is expected to provide 2,000 to 2,500 troops, France 1,000, Greece 700, Turkey 500, Spain 500 and Romania 400.</p>
<p>Fino, 34, went to the southern town of Gjirokaster on Tuesday, where he was warmly greeted by rebels bristling with guns, and toured the region as far north as Tepelene for talks on Albania's three-month crisis.</p>
<p>He announced that the feared Shik secret police had been disbanded. Shik was set up in 1991 after the collapse of the Stalinist regime which ran Albania for 45 years.</p>
<p>Fino's visit to Gjirokaster, where he was mayor of the opposition Socialist party until dramatically summoned to head an all-party crisis government on March 11, was likely to enrage right-winger Berisha.</p>
<p>Looting and banditry flared in March after protests over the collapse of high-risk savings schemes this year spilled over into insurrection. Scores of people have been killed.</p>
<p>In the tangle of Albanian politics, Berisha has accused the Socialists of siding with rebels who are demanding his resignation. Berisha has called early elections for June.</p>
<p>Without mentioning Fino's visit to the south, Berisha took a swipe at rebel councils and members of opposition parties in the government, including the Socialists, who signed a statement on Friday calling for Berisha's resignation.</p>
<p>Berisha accused parties of working with &quot;committees of gunmen, made up of left extremists, Mafia members, traffickers&quot; to &quot;exploit this deplorable situation for ill-intended political aims&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
