<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478563" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AZERBAIJAN: French foreign minister meets Azeri president.</title>
<headline>French foreign minister meets Azeri president.</headline>
<dateline>BAKU 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Foreign Minister Herve de Charette met Azeri President Haydar Aliyev on Tuesday during a brief visit aimed at advancing negotiations over the country's territorial conflict with neighbouring Armenia.</p>
<p>De Charette told reporters before the meeting: &quot;France wants a settlement based on international principles.&quot;</p>
<p>An Azeri Foreign Ministry spokesman said the talks would focus on the nine-year conflict between Moslem Azerbaijan and Christian Armenia over the disputed enclave of Nagorno-Karabakh, whose ethnic Armenian population broke away from Azeri rule in the late 1980s.</p>
<p>Aliyev said he welcomed the commitment to a settlement from Paris, which is a co-sponsor of peace talks under the auspices of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe.</p>
<p>De Charette was due to fly on to the Armenian capital Yerevan later in the evening, where he will meet President Levon Ter-Petrosyan on Wednesday, officials said.</p>
<p>The latest round of negotiations between Azeri and Armenian representatives began on Tuesday in Moscow.</p>
<p>Their conflict over Nagorno-Karabakh killed thousands until a ceasefire came into effect in 1994 but no lasting settlement has been achieved.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARMEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="AZERB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAKU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AZERBAIJAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
