<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478587" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Serbia needs $1 bln, but not in one go - minister.</title>
<headline>Serbia needs $1 bln, but not in one go - minister.</headline>
<byline>Gordana Filipovic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Serbia wants to reform its ailing economy and needs heavy external support to do the job, but the economy is not ready for a quick infusion of massive foreign funds, a senior government official said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Serbia could become an open market economy in two years but it needs fresh financial support to get capital-strapped industry back on its feet,&quot; Serbian Minister for Economic and Ownership Transformation Milan Beko said.</p>
<p>Beko, recently appointed as the first Serbian privatisation minister, said one billion dollars in fresh external support would do wonders for the economy devastated after almost four years of war-related sanctions.</p>
<p>&quot;Yugoslav economy relies on nearly $1 billion dinar equivalent in the M1 money supply. You can imagine what another billion dollars would do for this economy,&quot; the minister told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;But we are not ready to digest another billion dollars straightaway. To increase the economy's absorbency power, we need to make local industries produce at competitive prices and raise purchasing power of local consumers,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Instead, Beko said $200 million or $300 million would be just as beneficial, giving support to monetary stability and allowing the state to initiate some important projects, including agriculture, highways and telecommunications.</p>
<p>Apart from the desired $1 billion to substitute the lack of working capital, Yugoslavia would need another $1 billion a year to upgrade its infrastructure over the next several years, he said.</p>
<p>But foreign capital was too cautious to invest in an economy using 25-30 percent of its installed capacities, lagging far behind its 1990 levels, and too indebted to count on external borrowing.</p>
<p>Yugoslavia's external debt is unofficially estimated at around $9 billion.</p>
<p>Beko said the country urgently needed to begin debt rescheduling talks with its creditors and in the meantime saw the economy relying more on direct investment and only to a lesser degree on some fresh borrowing.</p>
<p>Some money would be needed to finance the current account deficit, expected to run at around $1 billion per year for several years ahead.</p>
<p>The government needed to round up the legal framework but also to complete infrastructure of the local financial market and make it fit for a liberal economy, he said.</p>
<p>But any substantial inflow of foreign capital was seen as wishful thinking for a country still banned from international financial institutions.</p>
<p>Foreign investors by-passed Yugoslavia during years of sanctions and its rating on world capital markets remains very low as it has still not rejoined the International Monetary Fund, World Bank or World Trade Organisation, Beko said.</p>
<p>&quot;But while waiting on membership in those institutions, we can at least clean up at home first,&quot; the minister said. -- Belgrade newsroom, +381 11 222 4254</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
