<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478523" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: PRESS DIGEST - Nigeria - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Nigeria - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are significant stories in the Nigerian press on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAILY TIMES</p>
<p>- Some of the distressed banks which were unable to meet a March 31 deadline to recapitalise or be liquidated and in which investors have shown serious interest are likely to get another period of grace before the hammer falls on them.</p>
<p>- Nigeria starts negotiations with World Bank to take an $18 million loan due to it for various environmental protection projects, says director-general of federal environmental protection agency, Adegoke Adegoroye.</p>
<p>- Seven ships expected at Lagos port this week with 35,000 metric tonnes of cement.</p>
<p>- Nigeria's privately owned Peak Petroleum Industries Ltd secures joint venture deal with U.S. firm NTI Resources to explore and produce oil and gas in Nigerian offshore wells.</p>
<p>- Four firms start test-run operations at export processing zone in Calabar in the southeastern Nigeria.</p>
<p>THE GUARDIAN</p>
<p>- Central bank formally loses its autonomy with publication of decree under which it reports to finance ministry.</p>
<p>- State oil firm NNPC, faced with acute shortages, rations fuel supply to Lagos depots.</p>
<p>- Transfer of accounts of government companies to commercial banks from central bank is suspended in order to stem high level of money in circulation, sources say.</p>
<p>- Nigerian Railway Corporation is set to spend 2.64 billion naira to install micro-wave digital communication system, says transport minister Major-General Ibrahim Gumel.</p>
<p>THISDAY</p>
<p>- Members of opposition NADECO group on exile in London are stranded because British government has not acted on their two-year-old requests for asylum.</p>
<p>- Security agents may raid communities in search of arms and ammunition in the midwestern oil town of Warri where Shell oil company workers were held hostage last week.</p>
<p>- Sources say state oil firm NNPC is considering Paris, rather Vienna for its European coordinating office, which was closed down in London two weeks ago.</p>
<p>($1=85)</p>
<p>-- Lagos newsroom +234 1 2630317</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
