<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478544" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin backs Belarus union but outcome in doubt.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin backs Belarus union but outcome in doubt.</headline>
<byline>Alastair Macdonald</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin threw his weight on Tuesday behind an agreement that would unite Russia with Belarus, but official sources said bitter wrangling in the Kremlin meant the final look of any deal was far from certain.</p>
<p>Belarus President Alexander Lukashenko, whose crackdown on opponents and distaste for market economics have drawn criticism in Russia and the West, flew to Moscow late on Tuesday. He is due to sign an accord with Yeltsin in the Kremlin on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Russian media said he left Minsk nearly 12 hours ahead of schedule. Kremlin officials told Itar-Tass news agency he might hold new talks with Yeltsin before the planned signing ceremony.</p>
<p>NTV, a commercial Russian television station which has come out publicly against the union and whose Minsk bureau chief was deported to Moscow this week, said Lukashenko was angry at last-minute changes proposed by Yeltsin aide Ivan Rybkin.</p>
<p>The Kremlin said security council secretary Rybkin, who met Lukashenko in Minsk on Tuesday, proposed only minor &quot;editorial&quot; changes to a draft union treaty. But NTV quoted sources close to Lukashenko saying Russia had proposed a much diminished deal.</p>
<p>&quot;Alexander Lukashenko's reaction was highly explosive,&quot; NTV's Minsk correspondent said, forecasting that accords between Belarus and Russia were on the point of collapse.</p>
<p>The Kremlin said Yeltsin was committed, however.</p>
<p>&quot;President Yeltsin states clearly and unequivocally that he is an initiator of the unification of the two fraternal states and their peoples, a consistent and firm supporter of it,&quot; his press secretary Sergei Yastrzhembsky said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a geopolitical necessity and an economic reality.&quot;</p>
<p>But Kremlin sources told Reuters that rival liberal and conservative camps in the government and presidential administration were still arguing over what would be signed.</p>
<p>Liberals led by First Deputy Prime Minister Anatoly Chubais fear union with Lukashenko's Belarus could harm the Russian economy and reinforce political reactionaries. They have been fighting a fierce backroom action against a draft accord drawn up by Lukashenko and leading Moscow conservatives last month.</p>
<p>A joint Russian-Belarussian parliamentary assembly, set up by a treaty signed last April 2, approved the draft on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The communist chairman of Russia's lower house, Gennady Seleznyov, noted there was opposition but said he was sure Yeltsin would sign something close to what the deputies agreed.</p>
<p>Yeltsin's communist opponents strongly favour a merger with Belarus as the first step to recreating the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Viktor Chernomyrdin, a relative conservative in the government since the appointment of Chubais and other liberals last month, said a union treaty would be signed on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Aman Tuleyev, a communist and minister for relations with ex-Soviet states, said the latest plan was for Lukashenko and Yeltsin to sign a 10-point &quot;memorandum&quot; on Wednesday, allowing further public debate about a detailed treaty.</p>
<p>Yastrzhembsky said the president would sign the Union Treaty on Wednesday and initial a charter to be offered for a month of public discussion in both countries before ratification.</p>
<p>Union is generally seen as popular in both countries, although the prospect of five years of independence from Moscow coming to an end has sparked street protests in Minsk.</p>
<p>About 300 people joined a banned demonstration on Tuesday. Police arrested about 20 without violence. The nationalists have called for Lukashenko's opponents to march on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The emotional appeal of uniting the Slav cousins means few Russian politicians oppose the idea outright. Russian policymakers also see advantages from the move as a response to NATO plans to expand westward into eastern Europe.</p>
<p>The draft -- much of it vague and contradictory -- foresaw close coordination of foreign, military and economic policies, but stopped short of merging the neighbours into a single state.</p>
<p>Government spokesman Igor Shabdurasulov said on Tuesday the planned union could be costly for Moscow and economists warned it would be hard to integrate Russia's open economy with the centrally planned Belarussian one.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
