<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478594" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: Ukraine, with less Turkmen gas, may revamp buying.</title>
<headline>Ukraine, with less Turkmen gas, may revamp buying.</headline>
<byline>Rostislav Khotin</byline>
<dateline>KIEV 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkmenistan, which cut gas supplies to Ukraine last week, may force changes in Ukraine's gas import system but will not dent Kiev's energy-hungry economy, energy analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Turkmen President Saparmurat Niyazov said last week that his desert Central Asian state had cut all gas supplies to Ukraine because of unpaid bills.</p>
<p>The cut could be the first real challenge to Ukraine's gas import scheme, in which trading companies are approved by the government to contract for gas supplies.</p>
<p>The scheme is supposed to introduce more competition to the market, but it has led some traders to say there is not enough transparency and competitiveness.</p>
<p>&quot;The cut could lead to changes in the system of gas imports from Russia and from Central Asia and gas distribution here,&quot; one analyst said.</p>
<p>Ukraine still owes about $200 million to Turkmenistan for supplies delivered before 1996.</p>
<p>Analysts said that around a dozen of Ukraine's gas traders owe Russian and Turkmen exporters $272 million for supplies in 1995-1997.</p>
<p>Niyazov blamed the cut on trading companies supplying Ukraine, while Ukraine's president, Leonid Kuchma, promised on Monday to develop closer links with Turkmenistan to buy gas on longterm contracts.</p>
<p>Most of Ukraine's Turkmen gas imports are carried out by Itera-Ukraine, a joint venture with Itera International Energy Corp.</p>
<p>Kuchma said Itera was to supply Ukraine with 11.1 billion cubic metres this year.</p>
<p>An Itera spokesman said at the weekend that the row with Turkmenistan was linked to differences in interpreting contracts, but declined to give further details.</p>
<p>&quot;Let the supplies stop -- there is enough gas here,&quot; one Ukrainian gas trader said, adding that Ukraine had about two billion cubic metres of Turkmen gas in storage.</p>
<p>&quot;The main threat -- a cold winter -- is over and there is no danger anymore.&quot;</p>
<p>Under a government-sponsored scheme set up in 1995, private and state companies are selected to supply gas to Ukraine and to collect debts for unpaid gas.</p>
<p>The government had hoped the scheme would help it to pay off its debts to the Russian gas monopoly, Gazprom  GAZP.RTS.</p>
<p>Kiev still owes $1.5 billion for Russian supplies over 1993 and 1994 but this debt has been rescheduled.</p>
<p>But opponents to the gas distribution scheme say that the scheme -- which thrives on barter payments -- has helped to fuel a payments crisis which left $2.2 billion in salaries and pensions unpaid.</p>
<p>Ukraine is one of the world's largest gas importers.</p>
<p>In addition to Turkmen gas, Kiev is also due this year to import 53 billion culic metres from Gazprom as well as up to 10 billion cubic metres from Uzbekistan.</p>
<p>Kiev's annual gas output is 18 billion cubic metres.</p>
<p>Kuchma has criticised the gas trading scheme as not being competitive enough and has welcomed Niyazov's suggestion that the two countries sign a deal on long-term supplies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURKM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
