<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478561" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia, Belarus aim to sign union, but talks go on.</title>
<headline>Russia, Belarus aim to sign union, but talks go on.</headline>
<byline>Alastair Macdonald</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1996-04-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin plans to sign a treaty on Wednesday linking Russia to its western neighbour Belarus, but last-minute opposition from Kremlin liberals has left the scope of the union in doubt.</p>
<p>Belarussian President Alexander Lukashenko, whose crackdown on opponents and distaste for free market economics have drawn criticism from Russia and the West, flew to Moscow late on Tuesday after lengthy talks with Yeltsin aide Ivan Rybkin.</p>
<p>There were conflicting reports about his intentions and Kremlin sources said in-fighting was continuing between liberals and conservatives in the Russian government.</p>
<p>Lukashenko's departure for the noon (0800 GMT) signing had been expected only on Wednesday morning. Kremlin officials told Itar-Tass news agency the Belarussian leader might hold early morning face-to-face talks with Yeltsin before the ceremony.</p>
<p>Security Council secretary Rybkin had been sent to Minsk with what the Kremlin called minor amendments to a draft treaty agreed by Lukashenko and Russian officials last month.</p>
<p>But Russia's commercial NTV television, which has openly voiced the private concerns of Kremlin liberals and come out against a merger with Belarus, quoted sources close to Lukashenko as saying Yeltsin wanted to scale back the scope of the treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;Alexander Lukashenko's reaction was highly explosive,&quot; NTV's Minsk correspondent said, forecasting that accords between Belarus and Russia were on the point of collapse.</p>
<p>But Interfax news agency, seen as close to Lukashenko, later quoted an official in his administration as saying that the Belarussian leader approved Moscow's &quot;remarks and proposals&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;These corrections do not change the essence of the union treaty nor its scope,&quot; the Belarus official said.</p>
<p>A draft of the &quot;Treaty on a Union of Belarus and Russia&quot;, obtained by Reuters on Monday, provided for the two former Soviet republics to coordinate foreign, economic and defence policies but stopped short of a merger into a single state.</p>
<p>Yeltsin publicly backed the treaty on Tuesday and Russian Prime Minister Viktor Chernomyrdin insisted it would be signed.</p>
<p>&quot;President Yeltsin states clearly and unequivocally that he is an initiator of the unification of the two fraternal states and their peoples, a consistent and firm supporter of it,&quot; Kremlin spokesman Sergei Yastrzhembsky said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a geopolitical necessity and an economic reality.&quot;</p>
<p>Kremlin sources told Reuters that the details were still in doubt as Yeltsin faced competing claims from supporters and opponents of the union, which aims to build on a bilateral &quot;community&quot; treaty signed exactly a year ago on April 2, 1996.</p>
<p>The opposition has been behind the scenes, partly because the idea of union with their 10 million Slav cousins is broadly popular with the 150 million Russians. A poll by the &quot;Public Opinion&quot; foundation on Tuesday found 59 percent wanted a merger.</p>
<p>Liberals, in a strong position since Anatoly Chubais was named first deputy to Chernomyrdin last month, fear union could harm Russia's economy and make Lukashenko, who once professed an admiration for Adolf Hitler, a key player in Moscow politics.</p>
<p>Aman Tuleyev, a communist brought in last year as minister for relations with ex-Soviet states, said the liberals had succeeded in watering down plans for Wednesday and that Yeltsin and Lukashenko would now sign only a 10-point &quot;memorandum&quot;, allowing further public debate about a detailed union treaty.</p>
<p>Yastrzhembsky said the presidents would sign the treaty on Wednesday but initial a charter to be offered for a month of public discussion in both countries before ratification.</p>
<p>Russian communists, who dominate parliament, see union with Minsk as the first step to rebuilding the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>A joint Russian-Belarussian parliamentary assembly, a product of last year's accord, approved the draft treaty on Tuesday and deputies said it could be ratified in weeks.</p>
<p>Yeltsin has hailed ties with Minsk as a model for closer integration throughout the Commonwealth of Independent States, the loose grouping which replaced the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>Some Russian policymakers see a deal with their western neighbour as a response to NATO expansion into eastern Europe.</p>
<p>Belarussian nationalists plan more anti-union protests on Wednesday. About 20 were arrested at a small rally on Tuesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
