<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478550" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albanian PM tells rebels secret police disbanded.</title>
<headline>Albanian PM tells rebels secret police disbanded.</headline>
<byline>Stephen Weeks</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanian Prime Minister Bashkim Fino went to the rebel-held south on Tuesday for the first time since insurgents seized the region and told their leaders that the dreaded Shik secret police had been disbanded.</p>
<p>&quot;Since yesterday, there is no more Shik in Albania,&quot; he told rebels at a meeting in the southern town of Gjirokaster, 30 km (20 miles) from the Greek border.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to build a new intelligence service, with a new face,&quot; Fino said. &quot;From now, anyone who identifies himself as a Shik officer is a liar.&quot;</p>
<p>Fino said he met President Sali Berisha on Monday and they accepted the resignations of Shik chief Bashkim Gazidede and his deputy Bujar Rama. The finance ministry had stopped funding for the group from Monday, he said.</p>
<p>Shik, the National Information Service, was set up in 1991 after a Stalinist regime which had ruled the Balkan country for 45 years collapsed.</p>
<p>Shik replaced the sinister Sigurimi secret police which had helped impose communist rule but became equally feared in its own right. Gazidede's resignation has been a main demand of the rebels who seized southern Albania in early March.</p>
<p>Fino arrived by helicopter in Gjirokaster and was greeted warmly by rebels bristling with guns, local reporters said. A former Socialist mayor in Gjirokaster, he also shook hands with Gjoleke Malaj, the rebel boss in Tepelene to the north.</p>
<p>He told reporters he was in the region to meet the &quot;legal representatives of local power and public order&quot; but quickly moved to discussions with rebels and elected officials alike.</p>
<p>Elected officials have remained in the region but the south has been run by rebel Committees of Public Salvation since the army was driven out and weapons depots looted in early March.</p>
<p>&quot;I thank the salvation committees for the role they played at a moment of paralysis of local power,&quot; he told an assembly which grouped elected officials and rebel committees.</p>
<p>&quot;But I would like to make clear that without restoration of legal instititions, calm and order cannot return and general elections be held,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Berisha was forced to name Fino, an opposition Socialist, to head an all-party crisis government on March 11. Berisha also bowed to demands for elections three years early and they are due in June.</p>
<p>Albania has been swept by violence since January when a string of popular investment schemes collapsed, wiping out millions of dollars in savings.</p>
<p>The anti-government riots and protests evolved into a full- scale uprising against Berisha, who is blamed for letting the unregulated and fraudulent &quot;pyramid&quot; schemes flourish.</p>
<p>Most of the south is now outside government control and the rebels' main demand is that Berisha quit.</p>
<p>Fino's visit to the south could cause even deeper divisions in the fragile all-party cabinet formed after army and police forces fled in the turmoil and rebels seized thousands of guns.</p>
<p>Fino's appointment ended the grip on power which Berisha's right-wing Democratic Party had held since 1992 but the deal has been strained from the start with both sides already vying for the June election.</p>
<p>After the Socialists met rebels holding the Adriatic port of Vlore last week, a senior Berisha adviser said parties must decide whether they were siding with the &quot;legitimate government or ... communist rebels that want to overthrow the government&quot;.</p>
<p>After his trip to the rebel south, Fino will leave by car on Wednesday for Greece to meet Prime Minister Costas Simitis to discuss the Albanian crisis.</p>
<p>Fino will sound out Greece's views as an EU member and a participant in a planned multinational force in Albania, his office said.</p>
<p>Italy will lead the multinational security force to protect international humanitarian aid convoys. The force will include contingents from Greece, France, Turkey, Spain and Romania.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
