<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478542" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GHANA: FEATURE - Ghana's fetish priests free slaves.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Ghana's fetish priests free slaves.</headline>
<byline>Vincent t'Sas</byline>
<dateline>MEPE, Ghana 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The owner of one of Ghana's voodoo-style fetish shrines thumbprinted documents confirming the liberation of his 45 slaves, including a girl aged six who in earlier times might have been fed to the crocodiles.</p>
<p>In exchange, he got five cows, one bull and the equivalent of about $1,650.</p>
<p>In the second half of 1996, 344 female shrine slaves known as Trokosi were freed from nine shrines in the West African nation better known for its gold mining and cocoa.</p>
<p>Trokosi are women given as slaves, usually at an early age, by families who believe they must appease the fetish or spirit of the shrine because a family member has committed a crime.</p>
<p>If not appeased, believers fear, the fetish will gradually kill the whole family by sending diseases or other calamities.</p>
<p>The practice is rooted in traditional voodoo beliefs, and fetishes are still much feared in Ghana.</p>
<p>SLAVES SHARED OWNER'S BED</p>
<p>Initially the girls were fed to crocodiles or otherwise killed. Later the priests agreed to keep them as slaves, mainly to work the shrine's land, do the priest's housekeeping and share his bed.</p>
<p>&quot;I am happy. But I will be very happy if I can get some money to trade with,&quot; said Mama Yorhome, 42, who became a Trokosi at seven and has six children from the priest.</p>
<p>The youngest Trokosi released recently, six-year-old Eworfe Agbosu, told Reuters that she was happy to go to school.</p>
<p>Like the other slaves, she was given a Certificate of Emancipation.</p>
<p>&quot;I am happy that they are free now because there were too many of them and also they had too many children. We could no longer take good care of all of them and they were suffering,&quot; said one of the shrine's owners, Togbe Vuke Nyamedi.</p>
<p>&quot;We have actually lost count of our children,&quot; he said when asked how many children he and his four co-owners of the shrine had with the Trokosi.</p>
<p>The area that became modern-day Ghana, a popular destination for African Americans on visits to trace their roots, helped feed the transatlantic slave trade that uprooted millions of Africans and shipped them to the Americas.</p>
<p>Mauritania, which straddles black and Arab Africa, is a more common modern target for anti-slavery campaigners.</p>
<p>Emile Short, Ghana's Commissioner for Human Rights and Administrative Justice, watched the latest liberation ceremony.</p>
<p>He urged parliament to pass a law against the practice of Trokosi but cautioned that liberating the women was not enough.</p>
<p>&quot;Many of the girls have been traumatised by the many years of bondage and servitude. They are in desperate need of counselling, financial support and rehabilitation,&quot; he told local officials.</p>
<p>THE FETISH IS NOT DEAD</p>
<p>The shrine owner, meanwhile, warned the community that the fetish was not dead, as was being rumoured, notably among the youth of Mepe. &quot;The houses of those who steal will be destroyed,&quot; he told them.</p>
<p>The Adido shrine in Mepe is a mud hut to which only the priest has access to carry out numerous rites. The fetish is a spirit and therefore invisible. The women lived in huts surrounding the shrine.</p>
<p>The 344 shrine slaves released in the second half of last year also lived along the Volta River, about 150 km (90 miles) east of the capital Accra.</p>
<p>The total number of Trokosi in the Volta Region is estimated at about 4,500, excluding their estimated 16,000 children.</p>
<p>Ghana's parliament is expected to pass a bill this year to outlaw the practice.</p>
<p>The release of the women has been achieved through lengthy negotiations with shrine owners and traditional chiefs.</p>
<p>Foreign non-governmental organisations paid the owners of the nine shrines each about three million cedis ($1,650) as well as five cows and one bull -- to encourage them to breed cattle rather than children.</p>
<p>&quot;This change of practice will boost the meat industry in the region,&quot; said Walter Pimpong of International Needs, one of the non-governmental organisations.</p>
<p>The idea is that in future, families who want to repent for misdeeds can donate cattle to the shrine instead of little girls.</p>
<p>($1=1,810 cedis)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GHANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEPE, Ghana"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GHANA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
