<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478520" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Mobutu adviser to lead Zaire team to rebel talks.</title>
<headline>Mobutu adviser to lead Zaire team to rebel talks.</headline>
<byline>William Wallis</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A seven-member team led by President Mobutu Sese Seko's security adviser, Honore Ngbanda, will represent Zaire's divided political family at talks with rebels in South Africa this week.</p>
<p>State television reported that the team, which includes Foreign Minister Kamanda wa Kamanda and representatives of both the opposition and Mobutu supporters in the transitional parliament, will travel to South Africa on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The delegation of negotiators will be going to Pretoria on Thursday where they will find already the special envoy of the United Nations and the Organisation of African Unity, Mohamed Sahnoun,&quot; the television said late on Monday.</p>
<p>The United Nations said on Monday that Sahnoun, whose five-point peace plan has won wide acceptance, would chair the talks.</p>
<p>The Kinshasa delegation reflects widely divergent positions of the opposition and presidency. A senior government official said that Ngbanda was expected to have the final word on crucial issues emerging from the talks.</p>
<p>The rebels, who took up arms in October vowing to topple Mobutu, have said that the talks would lead to a meeting between their leader, Laurent Kabila, and Mobutu.</p>
<p>Rebel spokesmen have said that Mobutu, who seized power in 1965, has to negotiate his departure.</p>
<p>There was some concern in political circles in the Zairean capital that the Kinshasa negotiatiors representing the chaotic nation's government and institutions would spend as much time contesting issues amongst themselves as with the rebels.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that we will not find a common point of view,&quot; Andre Boboliko, vice-president of parliament from the radical opposition, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Boboliko headed the Zaire delegation at a special OAU summit in Togo last week, which brought the two sides together -- for a symbolic handshake if not for formal negotiations.</p>
<p>Boboliko is not part of the new delegation, but Valentin Mubaki, who replaces him for the radical opposition, said the talks would take the form of a round-table conference.</p>
<p>In Kinshasa, over a week after Mobutu accepted Prime Minister Kengo wa Dondo's resignation, the opposition Sacred Union of the Radical Opposition and its Allies (USORAL) has been unable to agree on a successor.</p>
<p>USORAL is constitutionally responsible for the designation of a new prime minister but bitter divisions within the opposition have blocked consensus on a common candidate.</p>
<p>At least five candidates are in the running.</p>
<p>The alliance was scheduled to meet in parliament on Tuesday to designate a single candidate after parliamentarians and political leaders failed to produce any results on Monday.</p>
<p>The opposition has until Thursday to name a successor to Kengo before his job is put to a vote in parliament.</p>
<p>The parliament grew out of Zaire's often turbulent democratic transition.</p>
<p>Mobutu, who had cancer surgery in Europe in August, bowed to foreign and domestic pressure for multi-party politics in 1990 but implementation has dragged.</p>
<p>Until the rebellion, he had been talking about contesting presidential elections, which had been due by July.</p>
<p>The rebels now control a quarter of Zaire.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="OAU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
