<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478657" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Czech fund buys into Bulgaria's Mollovbank.</title>
<headline>Czech fund buys into Bulgaria's Mollovbank.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Czech Investment Fund Istrocapital acquired a $6.25 million stake or 92 percent in Bulgaria's private Mollovbank which was placed in receivership last year, a central bank official said.</p>
<p>&quot;The central bank now has grounds to lift the restrictions imposed on Mollovbank after the Chech fund has transferred $6.5 million to our account in New York,&quot; a Bulgarian National Bank (BNB) official, who declined to be named, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Mollovbank, renamed after the acquisition into Eurobank, is expected to boost its capital to 10.7 billion levs from current 800 million levs through a new share issue, the official said.</p>
<p>Last week the BNB decided to take over the powers of Mollovbank's shareholders' meeting for the next three months, which empowered the BNB to decide on its capital raise.</p>
<p>The BNB put Mollovbank in receivership, dismissed its management and appointed sequestrators on September 23 to prevent its insolvency, citing a negative capital-to-assets ratio of 19 percent and outstanding payments of 22 million levs.</p>
<p>On October 31 the BNB filed a bankruptcy suit against Mollovbank, saying the bank's performing assets were not large enough to cover its liabilities.</p>
<p>&quot;The BNB will withdraw the insolvency suit, filed against Mollovbank through the Sofia City Court on grounds of the fresh investment,&quot; the BNB official said.</p>
<p>&quot;Lifting receivership restrictions on Mollovbank (Eurobank) is a signal that the BNB is prepared to ease restrictions over other banks, in which investors show serious interest,&quot; the official added.</p>
<p>Since last May the BNB has filed insolvency suits against sixteen state and private banks, a third of Bulgaria's banks.</p>
<p>So far only two banks - Madan-based Krystalbank, which stopped operating in November 1995 and the state-owned Mineralbank have been declared bankrupt so far. -- Roumiana Tikholova, Sofia Newsroom, 359-2-84561</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
