<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478691" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: PRESS DIGEST - Latvia - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Latvia - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the main stories in Latvian newspapers on Tuesday, prepared for Reuters by the Co-operation Fund. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- President Guntis Ulmanis wants parliament to reconsider the law on gambling, under which businesses organised in basements would be banned from July 1.</p>
<p>- A delegation of the U.S. Congress, headed by senator Gerald Solomon, visited Latvia on March 28-29. The congressmen said that Latvia fulfills NATO requirements to those nations willing to join the alliance.</p>
<p>- The Cabinet ruled to boost the main stock of Latvia's Privatisation Agency to 1.4 million lats.</p>
<p>- The tariffs of Lattelekom increased by an average 10 percent from March 31.</p>
<p>DIENA</p>
<p>- A Norwegian oil tanker suffered serious damage after hitting a quay in the port of Ventspils due to engine failure.</p>
<p>- The World Bank has agreed a $20 million loan to Latvia's highway building project.</p>
<p>- A study carried out by the statistics committee with the World Bank reveal that the income of 68 percent of Latvia's inhabitants is below the crisis subsistence level of 52 lats. Some 44 percent receive an income below the minimum salary or 38 lats per month.</p>
<p>BIZNES &amp; BALTIYA</p>
<p>- Civil servants are to file their income declarations by April 15.</p>
<p>- Welfare Minister Vladimir Makarov is on visit to Washington until April 4 to sign a $40 million World Bank loan agreement for Latvia's welfare project.</p>
<p>DIENAS BIZNESS</p>
<p>- British Airways made its first flight from Riga to London on March 31.</p>
<p>- Japanese securities housae Nomura has offered to place all of Unibanka's state-owned stock, which is earmarked for sale abroad. The investment house announced its intention to buy more than $4.1 million worth of Unibanka's stock.</p>
<p>- The Latvian Ports Council wants to open rep offices in Brussels, Bremen and Moscow to promote Latvian transit services.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
