<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478658" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungary dealers expect stable repo for 2 or 3 week.</title>
<headline>Hungary dealers expect stable repo for 2 or 3 week.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungarian money market dealers expect the National Bank of Hungary (NBH) to keep the repo rate steady for at least two to three weeks, a Reuter survey of eight dealers showed on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The NBH's recent moves have indicated the central bank wants to keep market interest rates at the current levels in the near future, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;(The NBH) seems to have decided to stabilise interest rates at the current level for a longer period,&quot; said Postabank's Karoly Barath. &quot;I do not expect a cut in the next two or three weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>The NBH has cut its repo rates with almost monthly regularity in the past few months in line with a decline in inflation.</p>
<p>However, NBH President Gyorgy Suranyi said recently that the central bank was intent on keeping 12-month government securities yield levels at above 20 percent to protect savings.</p>
<p>Following Suranyi's announcement, the NBH raised the interest rate of its six-month deposit facility by 0.25 percent to 21.00 percent and introduced a 12-month deposit facility at 20.50 percent.</p>
<p>After the NBH moves, which hit the market by surprise, previous repo cut expectations cooled, dealers said.</p>
<p>Seven of the eight dealers in the survey said they did not expect a repo cut in the next two or three weeks, while the eighth dealer was uncertain.</p>
<p>Most dealers said the NBH was unlikely to cut its repo rates by more than 0.25 percent in the next one or two months, but a 0.25 percent cut in the one-week and one-month reverse repo rates may come, they said.</p>
<p>Two main economic research centres said last week that the current level of inflation was not likely to drop by the end of the third quarter of the year.</p>
<p>Inflation is running at 18.8 percent and the NBH expects it to be close to 17 percent in December, while a recent Reuters poll of 15 analysts showed that market expectations for December year-on-year inflation averaged 18.39 percent.</p>
<p>-- Sandor Peto, Budapest newsroom (36 1) 327 4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
