<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478625" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian MinFins ease with Bradys on Dow Jones fall.</title>
<headline>Russian MinFins ease with Bradys on Dow Jones fall.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prices of Russian MinFin bonds tracked the downward trend of emerging markets after sharp falls on Wall Street, dealers said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The Dow Jones Industrial Average ended a volatile trading session off 157.11 points at 6583.48 late on Monday. MinFins closely track Brady Bonds and other emerging market debt.</p>
<p>			tranche   Apr 1		   Mar 31</p>
<p>    1999 maturity   (3)     85.15-85.40	   85.30-85.60</p>
<p>    2003 maturity   (4)     61.00-61.25	   61.70-62.00</p>
<p>    2008 maturity   (5)     42.00-42.25	   42.75-43.05</p>
<p>    2006 maturity   (6)     48.15-48.40	   48.60-48.90</p>
<p>    2011 maturity   (7)     36.30-36.55	   36.70-37.00</p>
<p>&quot;Trading opened lower as New York was selling MinFins late yesterday on uncertainty about the Dow Jones,&quot; Natsionalny Rezervny Bank dealer Denis Pakhomov said.</p>
<p>An International Moscow Bank dealer said prices went down further in early trading but later found support on short-covering.</p>
<p>Dealers said range-trading dominated the market awaiting further moves in U.S. Treasuries. They added trading was mainly seen between banks themselves as investors abstained from active moves.</p>
<p>They forecast prices were likely to fluctuate around the current levels or ease further on nervousness about a further U.S. interest rate hike, which many analysts expect could from the Federal Open Market Committee Meeting in May.</p>
<p>--Artyom Danielyan, Moscow Newsroom (095) 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
