<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478689" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: PRESS DIGEST - Bulgaria - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Bulgaria - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the main stories in Sofia newspapers today. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>TRUD</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's caretaker cabinet raised electricity charges by an average of 30 percent and central heating charges by 70 percent, effective from April 1.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's interim government said the regional governors of the Black Sea ports of Burgas and Varna could hold tenders to allow commercial activities on the Black Sea beach strip, Construction minister Nikola Karadimov said.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's cabinet raised prices of imported wheat to $160 per tonne from $150 per tonne in a bid to compensate losses of state mills caused by the difference between imported grain prices and flour prices at the domestic market.</p>
<p>A kilogramme of bread is expected to cost 695 levs due to the new grains prices.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's Association of Commercial Banks (ACB) approved amendments to its statutes allowing representative offices of foreign banks in Bulgaria to acquire associate membership in the Association, ACB chairman Ognyan Enchev said.</p>
<p>24 CHASA</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's caretaker cabinet reduced petrol prices by 8-9 percent and diesel prices by 15 percent, effective from April 1 because of the lev's recovering against the dollar on the domestic interbank foreign exchange market.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's interim government proposed to the President Petar Stoyanov to appoint former Prime Minister Filip Dimitrov as permanent representative to the United Nations in New York.</p>
<p>PARI</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's government set up an Agency under the Industry Ministry to cope with the problems of small and middle-size industrial firms.</p>
<p>-- The Sofia City Court declared state-owned Mineralbank insolvent at the request of the Bulgarian National Bank.</p>
<p>Mineralbank was placed in receivership on May 17 1996.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's cabinet aprroved a $50 million stabilisation plan for state-owned Biochim bank in line with pledges made to international lenders to stabilise ailing banks.</p>
<p>The funding should be secured by a credit line opened by the state Bulbank to the government.</p>
<p>STANDART</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's Privatisation Agency (PA) Supervisory Board is expected to elect today a new executive of the Agency.</p>
<p>Former PA executive director Vesselin Blagoev was sacked on March 26 with motives of a lack of initiative and flexibility in the privatisation process, as well as a lack of coordination between the agency's executive body and the supervisory board and government. -- Sofia Newsroom, (++359-2) 981 8569</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
