<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478602" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: First-tier trading keep Bucharest bourse high.</title>
<headline>First-tier trading keep Bucharest bourse high.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bucharest bourse traders said active trading, especially on the first tier, kept volumes high on Tuesday, with 1.96 million shares chaging hands on turnover of 2.7 billion lei, almost unchanged from the previous level.</p>
<p>Heavyweights Azomures SA fertiliser maker and chemical plant Oltchim SA dominated the session again, taking a combined 90 percent of turnover. But they both ended weaker with supply outrunning demand.</p>
<p>Azomures closed 70 lei lower at 1,670 and Oltchim lost 160 lei to end at 1,210.</p>
<p>Traders said most of the selling pressure came from small shareholders looking for investment opportunities elsewhere.</p>
<p>&quot;They are willing to sell even at lower prices to get some money together and throw it into banks in exchange for nice returns,&quot; said one broker.</p>
<p>Commercial banks in Romania pay an average 130 percent per year on one-month deposits, up from 50 percent in the New Year.</p>
<p>The most active on the second tier on Tuesday was dye maker Policolor SA, which traded some 81,000 shares on turnover of 127.3 million lei. But selling pressure depressed its price by 50 lei to a 1,580 close.</p>
<p>Most other second-tier shares fell or stayed flat and four had no trade.</p>
<p>Three companies -- syringe maker Sanevit SA, Impact SA real estate company and carbide maker Carbid-Fox SA -- were suspended pending announcements on shareholders' meetings held last week.</p>
<p>Terapia SA pharmaceuticals company joined the market on Tuesday and traders said demand had pushed its price to a 2,100 lei close, up from 1,500 at the opening.</p>
<p>Two unofficial indices -- the VAB and the BIG -- fell from the previous session by 3.0 and 3.05 percent respectively. The BIG first-tier index was 1,599.77 points, 4.36 percent down on the previous session.</p>
<p>		Mar 27  Mar 26  Week's change  1997 high   1997 low</p>
<p> VAB-Index  479.7   494.8     +1.9 pct	  555.9	262.0</p>
<p> BIG-Index  499.48  515.16    +1.88 pct	 557.56     266.43</p>
<p>($=6,974 lei)</p>
<p>-- Luli Popescu, Bucharest Newsroom 40-1 3120264</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
