<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478640" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish Celuloza to invest PLN 835 mln in 5 years.</title>
<headline>Polish Celuloza to invest PLN 835 mln in 5 years.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's largest paper producer Zaklady Celulozy i Papieru Celuloza SA, due to be soon privatised, plans to invest 835 million zlotys in modernisation over the next five years, the firm's head said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;(The investment) should be financed jointly by us and the strategic investor...We do not plan new share issues,&quot; Celuloza's president Leopold Garbacz told a news conference.</p>
<p>The treasury ministry wants to sell up to 65 percent of shares in Celuloza, based in the northen city of Swiecie, to a strategic investor and float 15 percent of its shares this month on the Warsaw bourse.</p>
<p>The strategic investor could possibly increase Celuloza's capital, said Dariusz Olszewski, the deputy president of Towarzystwo Doradztwa Inwestycyjnego which advises the ministry on the sale.</p>
<p>The deputy director of treasury ministry's privatisation department Jacek Strzelecki, also present, declined to disclose details of the current negotiations on the Celuloza sale with prospective strategic investors.</p>
<p>The ministry has earlier said the sale could be completed in April.</p>
<p>Celuloza's Garbacz said the company would like to attract a large firm from the paper sector as its strategic investor.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like to be inside some giant (company)... thanks to which we would get new technologies and know-how,&quot; Garbacz said.</p>
<p>The public subscription for Celuloza's 7.5 million shares, with a minimum price of 15 zlotys each, is scheduled for April 15-18. The sale of tranche, representing 15 percent of the firm's capital, is due on April 22.</p>
<p>According to estimates, Celuloza netted 73 million zlotys last year on sales of 697.6 million zlotys and not 79.5 million zlotys and 714.7 million zlotys respectively as reported in the firm's issue miniprospect.</p>
<p>In 1995 the company netted 110 million zloty on 760 million zloty revenues.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
