<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478662" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia, Belarus wrangle over &quot;costly&quot; Union deal.</title>
<headline>Russia, Belarus wrangle over &quot;costly&quot; Union deal.</headline>
<byline>Janet Guttsman</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Last-minute haggling between Russian and Belarussian officials over details of a document on a union between their two states continued on Tuesday amid signs that the Russian leadership could be beginning to get cold feet.</p>
<p>Government spokesman Igor Shabdurasulov told a news conference the planned union between Russia and its western neighbour could be costly for Moscow and that the text of the document had not yet been finalised.</p>
<p>&quot;It (the agreement) means taking away some financial resources. To a certain extent it will make the financial situation in Russia more complicated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Russia would have to assess all political and economic aspects of the deal before making a final decision, he said.</p>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin had been due to sign the paper with his Belarussian counterpart Alexander Lukashenko on Wednesday. On Tuesday he dispatched security adviser Ivan Rybkin to Minsk with a personal message for Lukashenko.</p>
<p>The original draft, obtained by Reuters earlier this week, had been contradictory, insisting that the former Soviet republics would remain separate sovereign states but that union decisions had to be obeyed.</p>
<p>It called for socially oriented market reforms -- a dream to conservative hardliners in Belarus but a nightmare for the young team trying to build a competitive market economy in Russia.</p>
<p>Kremlin sources said Russia's First Deputy Prime Minister Anatoly Chubais, appointed earlier this month to coordinate the economic reform programme, wanted to scrap the initial 17-page draft and replace it with a two-page declaration of intent.</p>
<p>But he faces tough opposition from more conservative ministers, some of whom see union with Belarus as a way to strengthen Russia and boost its international standing.</p>
<p>&quot;If everything goes all right, the treaty will be signed. It is of major significance,&quot; Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov told reporters in the Russian parliament on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not talking about an immediate union of the two states, we are talking about speeding up the process of integration. The whole world is following this path, why should we and Belarus go in different directions.&quot;</p>
<p>Liberals in Russia and in Belarus' nationalist opposition say the deal would hurt both countries' national interests and Western economists say it could be hard to integrate two totally different economic systems or to swap virtually worthless Belarus roubles for much more valuable Russian ones.</p>
<p>Russia has privatised much of its industry and is allowing managers to make their own decisions. The Belarussian economy is still strictly regimented, centrally controlled and largely state owned.</p>
<p>&quot;Until Belarus goes through some privatisation, the economies are totally incompatible and will not be made compatible through political fiat,&quot; said Keith Darden, who is researching integration in the Commonwealth of Independent States.</p>
<p>Russian newspapers said Yeltsin had not yet made a final decision on the Union Treaty, which lists ways in which the two former Soviet republics will cooperate and coordinate policy, but insists they will remain separate states.</p>
<p>The liberal newspaper Izvestia questioned the Kremlin's rush to promote the treaty without proper public debate.</p>
<p>&quot;They are deciding the fate of Russia behind the backs of the people,&quot; it said in its lead article. &quot;Was it agreement or conspiracy prepared in the corridors of power?&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
