<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478651" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish KPW to examine Polifarb merger-term protest.</title>
<headline>Polish KPW to examine Polifarb merger-term protest.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Polish Securities Commission (KPW) will examine whether any law was broken concerning last week's shareholders meetings of Polifarb Cieszyn and Polifarb Wroclaw, which plan to merge, the KPW said.</p>
<p>KPW spokeswoman Beata Stelmach told Reuters on Tuesday that the commission received a letter on Friday from Wroclaw shareholders protesting the terms of the merger planned for mid-year, and that a decision could come as early as this week.</p>
<p>&quot;It bothers us a little that there are shareholders who have certain doubts on the whole procedure that went on at the general shareholders meeting...so we decided to look into the matter,&quot; Stelmach said.</p>
<p>Last week Credit Suisse Asset Management, which manages the London-listed Central European Growth Fund, wrote a letter for the fund and other U.S. and U.K. Wroclaw shareholders, asking the commission to prevent Cieszyn's version of the merger.</p>
<p>Cieszyn shareholders last Monday approved a merger plan giving them 53.5 rather than 50 percent of the new firm by increasing a planned pre-merger bonus issue for Cieszyn shareholders to 6.375 from 2.98 million shares.</p>
<p>Wroclaw shareholders approved the merger last Tuesday but did not vote on Cieszyn's version of the plan.</p>
<p>Wroclaw officials have said a mutual shareholder, BIG, might dispute Cieszyn's version in court but that the merger was still likely to go through as a delay would cost both firms.</p>
<p>-- Steven Silber +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
