<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478600" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Dow pulls Hungarian shares down, futures plunge.</title>
<headline>Dow pulls Hungarian shares down, futures plunge.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Hungarian share market closed lower weighed on by the Dow Jones index's plunge on Monday but above the day's lows as market participants returned after Easter, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;People seemed to have panicked in early trading...but by late trading buyers reappeared,&quot; said Andrea Keresztesi of ABN-AMRO Hoare Govett.</p>
<p>The BUX index closed at 5,319.20 points, down 94.50 points or 1.78 percent. From Tuesday on the closing BUX is calculated based on closing prices instead of average prices so far.</p>
<p>A stock exchange official told Reuters that although the continuous calculation of the BUX index did begin on Tuesday as said last week, it will only be available real-time after a test period, expectedly on April 14.</p>
<p>The bourse, however, provided the main figures after the close of the market. Accordingly, the BUX opened at 5,254.79 points, bottomed out at 5,222.73 points and hit a day's high of 5,333.10 points.</p>
<p>Analysts said Tuesday's fall did not come as a surprise.</p>
<p>&quot;Markets, such as Hungary... have become a little bit more vulnerable to shifts in sentiment, especially if it is coming from the U.S. because of the importance of U.S. funds in the emerging European markets,&quot; said Roger G. Monson, chief equity strategist at Daiwa Europe in London.</p>
<p>&quot;That has to be considered as a vulnerable point.&quot;</p>
<p>Tuesday's losers included meat processor Pick which closed at 10,800 forints, down 760, chemicals Borsodchem, which fell 255 forints to end at 6,265 and hotelier Danubius which lost 205 forints to 5,095.</p>
<p>Chemicals TVK not only recouped from early losses but went to positive territory to close at 2,270 forints,up 45.</p>
<p>Analysts said the market may benefit from an economic rise on the longer run, but the Dow's performance will have a strong say in the near-term outlook of the Budapest Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;The strong point for Hungary certainly would include the recovery in economy and the very strong profits performance of most companies which have well exceeded the strength that you would have assumed from domestic economic conditions,&quot; Daiwa's Monson said.</p>
<p>&quot;(But) if there is a crash on Wall Street or a small crash like we had the last two days, it's pretty much impossible to assume this market will be able to avoid a hit,&quot; Monson said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
