<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478605" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Croatian stocks ease, seen stagnating.</title>
<headline>Croatian stocks ease, seen stagnating.</headline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Croatian stocks continued to slide on Tuesday and market watchers foresaw price stagnation for most issues amid scarce activity throughout the week.</p>
<p>&quot;There are a few buying orders for this week, but this is all very weak,&quot; said one trader with a large foreign client base.</p>
<p>Analysts said the market might have been affected by a Dow Jones Index decline that caused most European bourses to slump after Easter holidays.</p>
<p>Three of the eight active issues fell on Tuesday, only one rose and four were flat.</p>
<p>Volume was three times higher at 4,688 shares from Friday's meagre 1,182, turnover also rose to 1.9 million kuna from 0.8 million kuna.</p>
<p>The only gainer, food processor Podravka, inched up one kuna to 290 kuna and was the most actively traded issue with 3,032 shares sold. But traders showed little faith in its recovery.</p>
<p>The top loser was drugs firm Pliva, falling 10 kuna to 450 with 729 units sold, but it was also seen as posting mild gains until the company releases 1996 earnings figures.</p>
<p>Zagrebacka Banka's ordinary shares traded flat at 1,850 kuna, selling only five shares. Its preference stock lost 15 kuna to 985 kuna on volume of 114 shares.</p>
<p>Zoran Ilic of Consult Invest brokerage said he expected no market recovery before mid-April, when nation-wide local elections are to be held.</p>
<p>&quot;Bank stocks are the only trumps until then,&quot; he said, adding this mostly applied to Varazdinska Banka.</p>
<p>Zagreb's bourse said on Tuesday that it approved the listing in the top stock bracket of Varazdinska Banka ordinary and preferred shares from next week, alongside with Pliva and Zagrebacka Banka.</p>
<p>One ordinary share in Varazdinska fetched 42,000 kuna for its 16,000 face value in a sole deal a fortnight ago.</p>
<p>Prospects for tourist issues were not very bright despite encouraging forecasts for this summer's season after poorer than expected results last year and high costs.</p>
<p>&quot;Even a 20 percent increase will mean just squaring up to zero for most of them,&quot; one analyst said.</p>
<p>The only active hotel stock, Laguna, ended the day three kuna weaker at 1,440 kuna. The company said it had a new shareholder, Banque National de Paris (BNP), after BNP bought an 11 percent stake in it from Banque Indosuez.</p>
<p>Confectioner Kras, Adriatic pipeline operator Janaf and hotelier Jadranturist all remained unchanged and Ilic said Kras could fall further as the interest in the share remained lacklustre.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
