<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478641" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia faces indigestion if it swallows Belarus.</title>
<headline>Russia faces indigestion if it swallows Belarus.</headline>
<byline>Peter Henderson</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belarus, a hangover from the Soviet era, could become a huge economic headache for reform-minded Russia if President Boris Yeltsin agrees to a union with his tiny neighbour, analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Yeltsin is expected to sign a new union treaty on Wednesday with the conservative president of Belarus Alexander Lukashenko, who leads a country of just 10 million people bordering Russia and Poland.</p>
<p>With Russia traumatised by the 1991 break-up of the Soviet Union, few politicians in Moscow would dare to oppose categorically any overtures from a former Soviet republic interested in returning to the fold.</p>
<p>But the two nations have gone in different directions since 1991, with Russia reforming and Belarus supporting an old-style centralised economy by printing money.</p>
<p>&quot;It (the agreement) means taking away some financial resources,&quot; said Russian government spokesman Igor Shabdurasulov. &quot;To a certain extent it will make the financial situation in Russia more complicated,&quot; told a news conference on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Top Russian officials including new First Deputy Premier Boris Nemtsov say that union should not be hurried, but Yeltsin's spokesman said the president was a &quot;firm and consistent&quot; supporter of it.</p>
<p>Belarus, with official gross domestic product (GDP) of about $6-8 billion, is a minnow compared with Russia's $400 billion economy.</p>
<p>The analysts said coordinated monetary policy was a key to union. But Russia could lose up to five percent of GDP if it swapped virtually worthless Belarus roubles for much more valuable Russian ones at a one-to-one rate.</p>
<p>&quot;Quite a lot of Russian regions are unreformed, but fortunately they do not have central banks,&quot; said Al Breach, an economist at the Russian European Centre for Economic Policy.</p>
<p>&quot;Belarus runs a large deficit and funds it through printing money. It is like Russia was in 1994, and they are not looking at doing reforms, almost,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Russia has privatised much of its industry but the Belarussian economy is still strictly regimented, centrally controlled and largely state-owned.</p>
<p>A stable currency would allow Belarus to trade with Russia, and perhaps with the West. Belarussian factories which once made refrigerators, tractors and other goods from Russian parts, could afford to buy the parts again if their money were convertible.</p>
<p>Belarus has been unwilling to reform much so far, putting off the years of pain undergone by Russians. A Western economist said Belarussian reports of economic growth last year were based on stockpiles of unwanted goods.</p>
<p>The International Monetary Fund and World Bank have both quit lending to Belarus due to the slow pace of reform, although they say they are ready to resume support programmes if reforms start again.</p>
<p>Keith Darden, a researcher studying integration of the Commonwealth of Independent States -- a union of former Soviet states except the Baltic countries -- said Russian-Belarussian integration would take years.</p>
<p>&quot;Until Belarus goes through some privatisation, the economies are totally incompatible and will not be made compatible through political fiat,&quot; he said. Russia and Belarus might still try to force the process, he added.</p>
<p>Belarus has enraged Russia by failing to meet its side of a customs union. Belarus's neighbours, especially Ukraine, have poured alcohol and sugar through Belarus's leaky border into Russia, tax free.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone was taking advantage of the open border with Russia to send their products through,&quot; Darden said.</p>
<p>Economists said the new treaty was unlikely to bring about change soon. The draft effectively replaces an agreement last year which said monetary policy should be coordinated by the end of 1997.</p>
<p>The new treaty sets no schedule for economic integration and says coordinated reforms, a treaty goal, should be amended to local needs.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a complete wish list, a load of waffle,&quot; said one Western economist. &quot;This union is a joke.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
