<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478681" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: Kazakhs to sell 60 pct of Embamunaigaz oil company.</title>
<headline>Kazakhs to sell 60 pct of Embamunaigaz oil company.</headline>
<dateline>ALMATY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Kazakh government announced on Tuesday a tender for a 60 percent stake in the former Soviet republic's fourth largest oil producer, Embamunaigaz.</p>
<p>The government says Embamunaigaz, located in northwest Kazakhstan, is sitting on 65.7 million tonnes of oil reserves.</p>
<p>The finance ministry's state property department told Reuters bids from foreigners and domestic investors would be accepted until April 29.</p>
<p>&quot;But if we receive bids from serious investors before the expiry of the official deadline, we will not wait until April 29 and hold the tender earlier,&quot; a department official told Reuters.</p>
<p>Each investor must make a refundable deposit equivalent to $500,000 to take part in the tender.</p>
<p>An official statement obtained by Reuters said investors wanting to compete in the tender must offer an investment programme along with social and environment protection programmes.</p>
<p>Participants in the tender will also have to outline future payments to the Kazakh budget, including taxes, royalties and bonuses.</p>
<p>The tender is part of a fast-track sell-off of Kazakh energy enterprises -- unprecedented for an ex-Soviet state -- aimed at filling the cash-strapped government's coffers.</p>
<p>Embamunaigaz's production totalled 1.74 million tonnes last year.</p>
<p>Analysts at investment company Global Kazkommerts Securities Inc said in a recent report that the enterprise is Kazakhstan's fourth largest oil producer, accounting for approximately 10 percent of Kazakhstan's output.</p>
<p>The government currently holds an 85 percent stake in the company, 10 percent of shares are owned by the workforce and the remaining five percent is held by investment funds.</p>
<p>After the tender the government plans to offer part of its remaining stake in Embamunaigaz -- alongside shares in other energy concerns -- to portfolio investors on the country's nascent stock market, which plans to start trading by the end of the year.</p>
<p>($1 = 74.0501 Kazakh tenge)</p>
<p>--Dmitry Solovyov, Almaty Newsroom, +7 3272 509410</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALMATY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
