<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478613" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Milling wheat futures rise in sleepy Budapest mkt.</title>
<headline>Milling wheat futures rise in sleepy Budapest mkt.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Milling wheat futures prices rose on the Budapest Commodity Exchange (BCE) on high demand but overall grains turnover remained unimpressive, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The nearest maturities rose as there were no sellers on the market,&quot; said Robert Vajo of Termin.</p>
<p>May milling wheat rose by the daily allowed 400 forints per tonne to end at 25,230 but only one contract changed hands.</p>
<p>Other milling wheat maturities rose by between 60 forints for August and 390 for July, with only the September maturity remaining unchanged at 22,800 forints.</p>
<p>In contrast, maize futures had a balanced trade with only May and July advancing by 80 and 250 forints.</p>
<p>&quot;Neither domestic nor international trends would have justified serious maize price movements,&quot; Vajo said.</p>
<p>May maize, which still has a large number of open contracts, accounted for almost half of Tuesday's total grains turnover in volume terms with 324 contracts.</p>
<p>Total grains turnover was a below-average 705 contracts or 285.9 million forints, of which maize accounted for 394 contracts and milling wheat for 311.</p>
<p>Prices closed unchanged for feed wheat, feed barley and sunflower as none were traded.</p>
<p>Lot size= 20,000 kgs</p>
<p>($1=175.64 Hungarian forints)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
