<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478643" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin sees gains in Belarus union but runs risks.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin sees gains in Belarus union but runs risks.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Heritage</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin is pushing Russia towards union with Belarus in the belief that it will boost his image in the eyes of ordinary Russians and steal the thunder of his nationalist and communist foes.</p>
<p>But the trail he is blazing is also fraught with risks, raises questions about the future of human rights, stability and democracy in Russia and could have a serious impact on relations with other former Soviet republics and the West.</p>
<p>&quot;I am for integration, for brotherhood, for unity. But unity on what basis? On what concrete issues?&quot; Vladimir Lukin, a liberal who heads parliament's foreign affairs committee, asked on Tuesday in the weekly Moscow News.</p>
<p>&quot;When you try to find the answer, you understand immediately -- the proposed union is dangerous for democracy in Russia.&quot;</p>
<p>Kremlin sources say liberals' concerns over the speed of integration have split the authorities in Moscow and prompted a rearguard action against signing a Union Treaty on Wednesday.</p>
<p>A government spokesman said on Tuesday the treaty was still not ready for signing. Much may depend on last-minute haggling and whether the accord has any more significance than previous deals on integration which had little effect in practice.</p>
<p>The controversial figure of hardline Belarus President Alexander Lukashenko looms large over the Union Treaty, which would allow close coordination of foreign, military and economic policies but stop short of merging the Slav neighbours.</p>
<p>His authoritarian style, lack of tolerance of opposition and a crackdown on the media have alienated the West and deeply troubled Russian liberals who say Yeltsin must seek guarantees from Lukashenko on human rights and democractic freedoms.</p>
<p>&quot;You cannot talk about negotiating integration with a state where there is political repression, conditions for the normal existence of the opposition are ruled out and the work of the media is restricted,&quot; liberal leader Grigory Yavlinsky said.</p>
<p>But Yeltsin, 66, has shrugged off any concerns and pushed ahead with moves to strengthen ties with Belarus.</p>
<p>Integration with Belarus offers Yeltsin a chance to lift his low popularity ratings because many Russians are nostalgic for the Soviet empire.</p>
<p>&quot;He knows he can't do much in other areas such as the economy, where the trends are not good. He needs success stories and he needs them fast,&quot; said Andrei Kortunov, head of the Russian Science Foundation think-tank.</p>
<p>Integration with Russia's western neighbour of 10 million people trumps Yeltsin's communist and nationalist foes who have campaigned for rebuilding ties with former Soviet republics.</p>
<p>&quot;The position of anyone who serves the process of integration will be supported...in principle, in this case, even Yeltsin,&quot; communist leader Gennady Zyuganov told Reuters.</p>
<p>Yeltsin, apparently driven by a genuine conviction that integration is good for Russia, may also be trying to rid himself of any guilt over the break-up of the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>He signed the pact at the Belarussian nature reserve of Belovezhskaya Pushcha on December 8, 1991, which consigned the superpower to history.</p>
<p>Union with Belarus is seen in some quarters as a response to NATO's plans to expand eastwards, which Minsk and Moscow oppose. Belarus also offers Russia a corridor to the West for lucrative energy supplies.</p>
<p>Some analysts say Yeltsin favours integration because it will involve creating a Supreme Council to oversee the union, and that he might try to stay in power by keeping his place on this council when his presidential term ends in the year 2000.</p>
<p>But the risks are potentially huge. Economic reforms have made little headway in Belarus and some economists say the cost of absorbing the less wealthy state will be costly for Russia.</p>
<p>Liberals fear Lukashenko will get a foothold on power by gaining a say in decisions affecting Russia and that this will suit opponents of Yeltsin who would welcome any steps that would give the Belarus leader a chance to take charge in Moscow.</p>
<p>&quot;The 'Belarus factor' is not as important for such people as the &quot;Lukashenko factor&quot;, in which they see a real opponent of the course of Russian reforms,&quot; Lukin wrote.</p>
<p>The international consequences could also be alarming. The United States has led Western isolation of Lukashenko and Minsk by cutting off aid and the Commonwealth of Indepednent States, grouping 12 former Soviet republics, is wary of union.</p>
<p>&quot;I am against unification at different levels inside the CIS...as this is absolute nonsense. This is a way to the destruction of the CIS,&quot; Ukrainian President Leonid Kuchma told a news conference in Kiev on Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
