<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478607" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>LITHUANIA: Lithuanian shares slide in dull trade.</title>
<headline>Lithuanian shares slide in dull trade.</headline>
<dateline>VILNIUS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lithuanian shares slid on Tuesday and dealers said that short-term gains were not likely.</p>
<p>Overall central market volume was just over 1.1 million litas and the Litin A index fell 83.17 points to 2,523.80. The Litin G index dipped 39.46 points to 2,250.74.</p>
<p>&quot;We had a full list today for the first time in a while as all of the shareholders' meetings are over, and that affected the supply and demand ratio,&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>Other dealers said that investors were still examining the results of the meetings as they prepared to change their portfolios.</p>
<p>Many of the country's leading blue chip companies also failed to pay dividends and that has put buyers off a bit, dealers said.</p>
<p>Losers included Vilniaus Bank, which saw its preferntial shares fall ten percent to 207.00 litas from 230.00 litas in trade of only 828.00 litas.</p>
<p>Ukio Bank's shares also dropped ten percent, easing to 15.39 litas from 17.10 litas in trade of 3,070 litas. The bank earlier reported a loss of 7.7 million litas for 1996.</p>
<p>Lithuanian Gas fell to 2.14 litas from 2.30 litas and its shares turned over 15,000 litas.</p>
<p>Lithuania Energy was one of the few gainers, advancing to 3.50 litas from 3.30 litas in relatively high trade of almost 320,000 litas.</p>
<p>Block trades reached over 3.1 million litas.</p>
<p>--Ed Stoddard, Vilnius newsroom +370 2 22 35 17</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LITH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VILNIUS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LITHUANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
