<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478633" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Yugoslav dinar black market rate rises slightly.</title>
<headline>Yugoslav dinar black market rate rises slightly.</headline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Yugoslav dinar's value on the black market rose slightly to 3.7 dinars to the German mark early in the week from 3.8 dinars over the weekend due to low supply of the local currency.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, dealers were buying marks at 3.7 and selling them at 3.8 dinars.</p>
<p>&quot;There just aren't any dinars around and few people are offering to sell their marks,&quot; a street dealer told Reuters.</p>
<p>After a monetary expansion late last year, the central bank tightened monetary reigns and cut M1 money supply to 5.233 billion dinars in January from 5.504 billion in December.</p>
<p>The Yugoslav banking system does not enjoy the confidence of the population after banks froze hard currency accounts in 1991 and several crashed pyramid savings schemes.</p>
<p>Some analysts attributed the shortage of dinars to plummeting living standards and the population's dwindling purchasing power, not leaving enough cash on the side to purchase hard currency &quot;savings&quot;.</p>
<p>The price of a monthly consumer basket of food and drink products for a family of four in February stood at 1,471 dinars ($265), or more than two average wages for the same month.</p>
<p>&quot;Although official statistics put monthly inflation in March at just 1.0 percent and average wages at 12 percent above the previous month's, people just aren't buying, which the decline in demand and retail sales clearly indicates,&quot; an independent economist said.</p>
<p>The official exchange rate of 3.3 dinars to the mark was set in November 1995 after a 70 percent devaluation which brought it in line with the then black market rate. -- Amra Kevic, Belgrade newsroom +381 11 222 4305</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
