<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478609" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: IMF's Camdessus meets senior Russian ministers.</title>
<headline>IMF's Camdessus meets senior Russian ministers.</headline>
<byline>Peter Henderson</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>International Monetary Fund (IMF) Managing Director Michel Camdessus met top reformers from Russia's new cabinet on Tuesday for talks on the fund's delayed loan to Russia.</p>
<p>Camdessus, in town for what Russian news agencies say are talks crucial to the resumption of disbursements from the IMF's $10 billion three-year loan, met Anatoly Chubais and Boris Nemtsov, the first deputy premiers in charge of the economy.</p>
<p>He was also due to have further talks with Prime Minister Viktor Chernomyrdin and meet privatisation minister Alfred Kokh on Tuesday, government spokesman Igor Shabdurasulov told a news conference.</p>
<p>Itar-Tass news agency said that Chubais, a reformer recently promoted by President Boris Yeltsin and charged with leading a new wave of economic reform, was to discuss monopoly reform and tax collection with Camdessus.</p>
<p>A member of the State Duma lower house of parliament's influential budget committee said Camdessus would take part in a joint meeting with the industry policy committee on Thursday morning and field questions from the panels in which the communist party and its allies are strongly represented.</p>
<p>RIA news agency quoted a source close to the IMF as saying &quot;an understanding had been reached&quot; between Camdessus and Chernomyrdin on the IMF's disbursement of delayed tranches of the loan during Monday's meeting.</p>
<p>Interfax news agency quoted a government source as saying an IMF delegation negotiating Russia's 1997 economic plan, which both sides must agree for lending to continue, had placed new conditions for the plan at the last minute before signing.</p>
<p>Officials at the Moscow office of the IMF, which has delayed several monthly tranches of the $10 billion Extended Fund Facility because of concern at the low level of Russian tax revenues, were not available for comment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
