<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478680" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: PRESS DIGEST - Yugoslavia - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Yugoslavia - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Serbian and Montenegrin press on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified them and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>			    - SERBIA -</p>
<p>POLITIKA</p>
<p>- Yugoslavia has not held any prisoners of war in its territory since January 1994, says federal foreign ministry in a memorandum for the U.N. Human Rights Commission session in Geneva.</p>
<p>- Committee for protection of rights and interests of displaced persons asks OSCE to supervise local elections in eastern Slavonia and to allow Croatian Serbs living in Yugoslavia to vote.</p>
<p>- Sartid steel works from Smederevo produced 750,000 tonnes of steel last year and plans to produce one million tonnes this year. Last year's exports were worth $85 million, $20 million in January and $15 million in February.</p>
<p>- One of the largest Yugoslav commercial banks Vojvodjanska Banka has charged Deloitte and Touche to make a study for its reorganisation.</p>
<p>- Yugoslav and republican agriculture ministers Nedeljko Sipovac and Jovan Babovic agree that drafting of long-term agriculture development strategy to year 2020 should start.</p>
<p>- Yugoslav airlines JAT is celebrating its 70th anniversary.</p>
<p>NASA BORBA</p>
<p>- Belgrade students set up student parliament.</p>
<p>- Now is the moment to resolve the Kosovo issue with independent Kosovo as a platform of departure, says Hidaet Hiseini, Vice-President of the Democratic League of Kosovo.</p>
<p>- London Euromoney rates Yugoslavia 166th out of 179 countries based on general economic risk.</p>
<p>- The second draft of the information law will be presented this week, says Serbian Information Minister Radmila Milentijevic.</p>
<p>VECERNJE NOVOSTI</p>
<p>- The Yugoslav government plans to sell four of its six 20-year old Lear-jet 25 planes at the price of 500,000 to 800,000 dollars per plane.</p>
<p>- Nothing spectacular expected to happen at the Serbian-Kosovo Albanian round table scheduled in New York from April 7-9 but it is important that we will sit down and talk together, says New Democracy President Dusan MIhajlovic.</p>
<p>BORBA</p>
<p>- Serbia concession law to be passed urgently at next republican parliament session, says Serbian construction minister Branislav Ivkovic.</p>
<p>BLIC</p>
<p>- Bus producer Ikarbus of Zemun plans to incerase production by 30 percent this year. Between 200 and 300 buses were produced last year.</p>
<p>			    - MONTENEGRO -</p>
<p>POBJEDA</p>
<p>- Inflation in the first three months this year was 6.5 percent in Montenegro and 2.6 percent in Serbia, according to the Federal statistics office.</p>
<p>- Montenegro will reform its secondary school education.</p>
<p>- Montenegro will have a shortage of electric energy worth $20 million this year that the Montenegrin power company will not be able pay for with the present electricity prices, says the company director Slobodan Dakovic.</p>
<p>- There are 65,000 persons registered with the Montenegrin Unemployment Office.</p>
<p>- Internal party struggle in the National Party coincides with friction in the ruling Democratic Party of Socialists ahead of the presidential elections later this year and possible early parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>- Podgorica local bus company will be privatised. -- Belgrade Newsroom +381 11 2224254</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
