<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478767" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuela labor reforms to take time - Petkoff.</title>
<headline>Venezuela labor reforms to take time - Petkoff.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Venezuelan Planning Minister Teodoro Petkoff rebutted government critics Tuesday, saying recently proposed labor reforms would inevitably take time to implement and forcing the pace would require black magic.</p>
<p>The government reached a surprise, ground-breaking agreement March 16 with union and private sector leaders over reform of the country's severance pay and crumbling social security systems.</p>
<p>The cabinet is due to approve supporting changes in the Labor Law on Wednesday, before sending the complex severance pay reform bill to Congress for discussions expected to take some time.  Once the bill is passed, a new minimum salary will be announced.  &quot;If the reforms are approved quickly, so too will the new minimum salary,&quot; Petkoff told reporters.</p>
<p>But: &quot;Only two weeks have passed since we announced the agreement, which took nine years to reach.  Rafael Caldera, not Mandrake (the magician) is the head of the country,&quot; he said, in reply to reporters' questions as to how long he expected congress to take.</p>
<p>The characteristically bald-speaking Petkoff added that neither was Finance Minister Luis Raul Matos Azocar Lotario, referring to magician Mandrake's cartoon sidekick.</p>
<p>((-- Omar Lugo, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
