<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478700" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: Ukraine 1997 sunseed output seen up to 2.30 mln T.</title>
<headline>Ukraine 1997 sunseed output seen up to 2.30 mln T.</headline>
<dateline>KIEV 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ukraine, eastern Europe's largest sunflower seed grower, has forecast a harvest of 2.30 million tonnes this year, up from 2.04 million tonnes in 1996, an Agriculture Ministry official said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Our plans call for sowing 1.83 million hectares with sunflower seed during the spring campaign, so we are forecasting output of 2.30 million tonnes,&quot; Valentyn Tymoshenko, deputy head of the ministry's crop department, told Reuters.  </p>
<p>Tymoshenko said sowing would begin this month and that Ukraine's small number of private farmers were expected to contribute a small amount to the final figure.</p>
<p>The ministry had forecast the 1996 sunflower seed harvest at 2.70 million tonnes, but drought was blamed for lowering the final figure.</p>
<p>Ukrainian farmers sowed 1.75 million hectares with sunflower in 1996 and yields were 1.15 tonnes per hectare. In 1995, Ukraine harvested 2.75 million tonnes and yields were 1.54 tonnes per hectare.</p>
<p>Ukraine produced 572,800 tonnes of sunflower oil and exported about 320,000 tonnes of sunflower seed to European countries and Turkey last year, the Statistics Ministry said.</p>
<p>The Agriculture Ministry has estimated the annual refining capacity of Ukraine's sunseed processing plants at 2.5 million tonnes.</p>
<p>--Yuri Kulikov, Kiev Newsroom, +380 44 244 9150</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
