<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478776" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Sears de Mexico shares up in late trade.</title>
<headline>Sears de Mexico shares up in late trade.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares listed by retail chain Sears Roebuck de Mexico were sharply higher in late trade on the Mexican Stock Exchange on Tuesday on rumors the company may sell some of its assets.</p>
<p>Sears B1 class shares were up 1.52 pesos to 15.02 pesos, after climbing 60 centavos on Monday.</p>
<p>The stock's strong gains for the second day in a row attracted attention as they bucked an otherwise bearish market.  </p>
<p>Dealers said there were market rumors about Sears Mexico possibly selling assets or a stake in the company and added there was no fundamental reason for the company's shares to be rising so sharply.</p>
<p>&quot;The stock was very cheap in terms of its price/book value ratio, but there are also rumors of an asset sale,&quot; a Mexico City desk trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are a lot of buy orders for the stock, and we are wondering why.  There are rumors, but nothing concrete,&quot; another desk trader said.</p>
<p>A floor trader consulted on Monday said he had heard rumours holding company Grupo Carso was to buy a stake in Sears Mexico.</p>
<p>Both companies declined to comment on any possible deals.</p>
<p>Sears, Roebuck and Co holds a 75 percent stake in Sears Roebuck de Mexico, and the remaining 25 percent is in the hands of private investors.</p>
<p>((--Martin Roberts, Mexico City newsroom +525 728-7907))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
