<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478740" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peru arrests Czech for smuggling animals.</title>
<headline>Peru arrests Czech for smuggling animals.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Customs officials said they arrested a Czech man on Tuesday for trying to smuggle exotic animals out of Peru, while three Chileans and a Spaniard were detained with more than 22 pounds (10 kg) of cocaine.</p>
<p>The five men were arrested as they were about to board a KLM flight to Amsterdam at Lima's Jorge Chavez airport.</p>
<p>Czech citizen Ales Havelka, 27, confessed to trying to spirit out 35 animals of endangered species, customs officials said. Two boas, 17 monkeys, 10 mata-mata turtles, five midget crocodiles and a lizard were found drugged and stuffed in plastic containers inside a suitcase, they added.</p>
<p>Under Peruvian law, conviction for smuggling endangered animals carries a three- to four-year prison sentence.</p>
<p>The four nabbed on drug possession charges said they did not know each other although, according to customs, they were smuggling the drugs in the same way -- in bags taped to their bodies and in the soles of their shoes.</p>
<p>Customs anti-narcotics officers said they detained Chilean citizens German Vereceli, 54, with 6.1 pounds (2.7 kg) of cocaine; Mario Valadares, 64, with 5.6 pounds (2.5 kg); and Juan Stumf, 24, with 5.2 pounds (2.3 kg). Spanish citizen Jose Mora, 72, was arrested with 5.2 pounds (2.3 kg).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
