<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478711" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Momentum slows in search for Peru crisis solution.</title>
<headline>Momentum slows in search for Peru crisis solution.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Cawthorne</byline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pre-Easter optimism had all but vanished on Monday as Marxist rebels accused Peru's government of dragging its feet in talks toward a negotiated solution in the 104-day hostage crisis.</p>
<p>&quot;The slowness is due to the government's intransigence,&quot; charged &quot;Comrade Alejandro&quot;, a Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement (MRTA) military leader in Peru's eastern jungle.</p>
<p>&quot;The prisoners' issue is still not resolved,&quot; he added in a communication with Reuters. &quot;We will stay (in the residence) as long as is necessary to achieve the freedom of our prisoners.&quot;</p>
<p>The MRTA's demand for the release of jailed comrades has been the main sticking point since 20-odd rebels led by Nestor Cerpa blasted their way into the Japanese ambassador's residence during a cocktail party on Dec. 17.</p>
<p>Diplomatic and media circles were convinced last week the government and MRTA were close to an agreement involving asylum in Cuba for the hostage-takers, a possible ransom deal and the release of some lower-level prisoners.</p>
<p>But that optimism was dashed over the weekend as the MRTA made a string of tough public statements via the Internet, a banner draped outside the residence and a walkie-talkie conversation between Cerpa and journalists.</p>
<p>A member of a three-man mediation team known as the guarantors' commission, Archbishop Juan Luis Cipriani, also sounded a discouraging note as he said he had no news to report after a day of contacts with the government.</p>
<p>&quot;No problem is eternal and this one will be settled ... Bit by bit, we're getting closer. But I have nothing new to add,&quot; he told reporters on Monday night after meeting another guarantor, Canadian ambassador Anthony Vincent. Cipriani snapped at reporters to &quot;go to bed and don't bother us.&quot;</p>
<p>Fujimori said over the weekend he was still hopeful of a solution, but was not prepared to shift his position on the prisoners issue.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a lot of speculation during Holy Week that there would be a peaceful solution, but we were conscious that we were not in the final stage, that the conditions were not right,&quot; Fujimori said in a television interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Naturally we are hopeful that it will be the soonest possible, but we do not foresee a date.&quot;</p>
<p>Although attention has been focused on possibilities for a peaceful solution, crack troops have been training in case of an assault and, according to intelligence reports, the MRTA has slipped an extra 70 fighters into Lima as a potential backup for those inside the residence.</p>
<p>Fujimori met on Monday at the presidential palace with his chief negotiator in the crisis, Domingo Palermo, and the three-man guarantors' commission overseeing negotiations to end Latin America's longest hostage siege.</p>
<p>Japanese government observer Terusuke Terada was also present at the meeting which lasted nearly two hours.</p>
<p>The guarantors have been holding &quot;parallel&quot; meetings with the MRTA and the government during a period of &quot;reflection&quot; since the last and tenth round of face-to-face talks on March 12. Last week's speculation focused on a supposed blueprint proposal by the guarantors to end the crisis.</p>
<p>Cipriani denied on Sunday that talks between the two sides had broken down and called for patience and tolerance on all sides, saying &quot;we are trying to move as fast as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>The mainly middle-aged male hostages spent a quiet Easter weekend under the guns of their MRTA captors, with whom they are said to have now formed close personal ties.</p>
<p>While concern centred on the health of the hostages, Alejandro insisted the jungle-trained rebels inside were still in peak condition. &quot;They are doing well, both physically and morally,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
