<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478703" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: PRESS DIGEST - Hungary - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Hungary - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Here are highlights of stories reported by Hungary's press, based on information by Nepszabadsag's Hungary Around the Clock service. For further details on how to subscribe to Hungary Around the Clock, please contact Monica Kovacs at (361) 351 7142 or fax your request to (361) 351 7141.</p>
<p>ALL PAPERS</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Gyula Horn said Sunday that an agreement with the churches relating to basic issues such as the financing of public service activity, support for the religious sphere and the settlement of ownership of one-time ecclesiastical property is expected to be reached by late June, following consultation which ended on March 26.</p>
<p>- Leading officials at the Foreign and Defence Ministries will today discuss the possibility of sending a Hungarian military contingent as part of an international peacekeeping force in Albania.</p>
<p>- Judges from the International Court of Justice in the Hague will go on a fact-finding tour of the stretch of the Danube under dispute in the ongoing trial of the Gabcikovo case, for four days starting today.</p>
<p>- A senior Hungarian government official said on Friday that a Russian proposal for rescheduling payment of the remainder of that country's state debt to Hungary appears to have won acceptance by Hungary. (Sat.)</p>
<p>- The price of electrical energy is set to increase by 3.6 percent from April.</p>
<p>VILAGGAZDASAG</p>
<p>- The general assembly of Borsod-Abauj-Zemplen County will open an office in Brussels in early April, announced Hans Beck, ambassador at the EU's Budapest mission during a visit to the county at the weekend.</p>
<p>- Eximbank signed a contract Friday with 20 domestic commercial banks for a $240 million loan scheme available for export financing, said managing director Ivan Nyiri.</p>
<p>- MOL Rt. has purchased a 75 percent stake in its former Austrian distributor Mineralkontor and renamed the company MOL Austria GmbH.</p>
<p>- The Audi plant in Gyor is set to produce the world's most advanced diesel engine from April. The new model is a 24-valve, 2,500 cubic cm, 15 horsepower engine, to be installed in the new A8 and A6 models.</p>
<p>MAGYAR HIRLAP</p>
<p>- Inflation may drop to 12-14 percent next year and 8 percent in the year 2000, reveals the Ministry of Finance's economic programme for 1998-2000 to be submitted to the economic cabinet on Wednesday.</p>
<p>- The State Privatisation and Holding Co. published Friday the third list of companies set to undergo simplified or accelerated privatisation.</p>
<p>- A dinosaur egg which a 17-member team of scientists nursed around the clock for 64 days in the hope of breathing life into it is expected to hatch today, April 1, in a special cage near the the monkey enclosure at Budapest Zoo, according to this paper's April 1 edition.</p>
<p>NAPI GAZDASAG</p>
<p>- The board of directors of Budapest Bank will propose that a 12 percent dividend on last year's profits be paid to shareholders on each type of share, as revealed in the bank's AGM invitation.</p>
<p>- The long-distance bus company Volanbusz posted sale of HUF 8.5 billion last year. The company plans to raise ticket prices by 20 percent and replace 30-35 percent of its 892-strong fleet this year.</p>
<p>- From April 1, the Budapest Stock Exchange will calculate its BUX index based on the closing prices of shares, instead of the daily average rate.</p>
<p>			     -- Budapest newsroom (361) 327 4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
