<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478755" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico City enters era of telephone competition.</title>
<headline>Mexico City enters era of telephone competition.</headline>
<byline>David Luhnow</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico City opened its doors to long-distance telephone competition on Tuesday, officially ending Telefonos de Mexico's decades-old grip on the sprawling metropolis.</p>
<p>The city is the 21st Mexican city to allow competition since the start of the year. But by any measure, it is the jewel of the national telephone market -- accounting for about a third of Mexico's $4 billion long-distance market.  </p>
<p>&quot;Mexico City is the most important market in Mexico by far. ...It has higher purchasing power, a concentration of business and more long-distance traffic,&quot; said Tony Figuerido, a telecommunications analyst at Caspian Research in New York.</p>
<p>The capital city of some 18 million, one of the world's largest, accounts for nearly a third of the country's nine million telephone lines and is the center of Mexican business and government.</p>
<p>Mexico City's telephones will open to competition on a piecemeal basis to allow Telefonos de Mexico, known as Telmex, enough time to connect its rivals to its huge local network.  </p>
<p>Starting on Tuesday, some 400,000 telephone lines in Mexico City will open to long-distance competition each week, a process that will end in mid-May.</p>
<p>Competition in Mexico's long-distance market officially began last year, but it was not until this year that rivals were allowed to connect to Telmex's network for a small fee while they built their own networks.</p>
<p>Since January, cities such as Monterrey, Guadalajara and Puebla -- the three largest in Mexico besides Mexico City -- have welcomed the shift, which allows residents to pick their carriers through a pre-subscription balloting process.  </p>
<p>A slew of companies has lined up to beat Telmex on its own turf. The most important are Alestra -- a partnership between Grupo Financiero Banamex-Accival and AT&amp;T Corp of the United States -- and Avantel -- which includes MCI Communications, Mexican industrial company Alfa SA and holding company VISA-Bancomer.</p>
<p>So far, Telmex has mounted a better-than-expected defense, winning most of the pre-subscription ballots in the major cities. With the Mexican carrier keeping customers who do not choose any of its rivals, analysts estimate that it has held on to about 80 percent of the market.  </p>
<p>Still, analysts are cautious about declaring Telmex the outright victor in Mexico's new telephone wars. While Alestra and Avantel have wooed fewer customers, they have likely won over many large-volume users such as businesses.</p>
<p>&quot;It is too early to tell. We really are concerned about traffic volume, but we have no information about that yet. Even though the numbers look good on the surface, I think Telmex will lose more market share,&quot; Figuerido said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
