<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478709" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONDURAS: Three die in U.S. Air Force plane crash in Honduras.</title>
<headline>Three die in U.S. Air Force plane crash in Honduras.</headline>
<byline>Gustavo Palencia</byline>
<dateline>TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. Air Force cargo plane burst into flames when it crashed on landing in Honduras on Tuesday, killing three Americans and injuring seven, two of them critically, U.S. officials said.</p>
<p>The charred corpses were dragged from the wreckage of the C-130 Hercules, that flew out of Howard Air Force Base in Panama City, veered off the runway as it landed at Tegucigalpa airport, and ploughed in flames into a nearby street.</p>
<p>&quot;A C-130 flew out of Howard Air Force Base sometime this morning and skidded off the runway and into the town upon landing at the international airport in Honduras,&quot; said. Capt. Chris Yates, a spokesman for the U.S. Southern Command based in Panama.</p>
<p>&quot;It is believed all passengers are military members. Two of the seven injured are in critical condition. One has a broken back and the other is suffering from multiple fractures and severe burns,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Charred bits of the wreckage were scattered in the street that runs alonside the Toncontin international airport, and the cockpit and tail were split virtually in two.</p>
<p>Fire crews said the flames engulfed the three dead before they could be rescued. They were &quot;carbonized&quot;, Marcos Lozano, spokesman for the Red Cross in Tegucigalpa, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Red Cross worker Karina Ordonez who was at the scene said the three dead were in or near the cockpit.</p>
<p>The injured scrambled from the wreckage and some were burning, eyewitnesses said.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the 'gringos' (Americans) walked out of the plane, he was bleeding and burned. Another came behind him in flames. We stopped the burning,&quot; Honduran Mario Medrano said on national television.</p>
<p>Toncontin airport is in a heavily-populated suburb in southern Tegucigalpa. Its runway is short and it is surrounded by steep, cloud-covered hills. Aircraft must bank sharply when coming in to land.</p>
<p>&quot;After the plane crashed it burst into flames in the middle of the street. Miraculously there was only a taxi going past, and that was not damaged,&quot; Fire Department official Francisco Moncada told Reuters.</p>
<p>In Washington, Army Lt. Col. Stephen Campbell, a Defence Department spokesman, said three of the seven survivors were reported to be in stable condition and two were walking.</p>
<p>He said the plane and its crew were attached to the 440th Airlift Wing, an Air Force Reserve unit based in Milwaukee, Wisconsin and on temporary duty in Panama. He said the plane was flying routine support missions in the region.</p>
<p>The U.S. military has some 500 personnel stationed at the Palmerola base in Honduras, some 50 miles (80 km) north of Tegucigalpa.</p>
<p>The cause of the crash was not yet known, but the U.S. Embassy in Tegucigalpa said an investigation was underway.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONDURAS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
