<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478763" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Caracas stocks close off, unmoved by CANTV div.</title>
<headline>Caracas stocks close off, unmoved by CANTV div.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Caracas stocks closed off in thin trade, unmoved by news that leading companies CANTV and Electricidad de Caracas had declared dividend payments for the year, traders said.</p>
<p>While foreign funds continue to wait out Venezuelan equities, locals investors were unimpressed by CANTV's announcement late Monday of 13.24 bolivar per share dividend, traders said, leaving other share prices wallowing in a lackluster session.</p>
<p>&quot;That's only 0.6 percent of the share price -- okay if you didn't expect anything,&quot; said one broker in a typical comment.  </p>
<p>Nevertheless as CANTV was not due to begin dividend payments until 1998, this dividend is &quot;a good sign that the company is making profits and paying them out,&quot; said Intervalores broker, Ricardo Marino.</p>
<p>&quot;Let's hope next year the payment will be larger,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Leading utility Electricidad de Caracas also said it would pay a three bolivar per share cash dividend, plus a one share per 25 stock dividend, but the announcement similary failed to move the market.  </p>
<p>Merinvest's composite  index, which includes CANTV, fell 0.81 points to end at 95.98 points.</p>
<p>Among traded issues, 27 fell, eight rose and five closed flat.</p>
<p>Electricidad's dividend announcement followed a decision late Monday to increase the ceiling on the company's authorized capital to 335 billion bolivars from 204 billion. The company, which currently has some 168 billion bolivars of paid-in capital, annually increases the limit to allow for share dividends.</p>
<p>The bolsa's 19-share index fell 0.16 percent to close at 6,321.19 points as eight million shares traded, worth 1.5 billion bolivars ($3 million), according to preliminary figures from the exchange.  </p>
<p>((-- Silene Ramirez, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600)) (c) Reuters Limited 1997</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
