<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478795" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil lets cities refinance social security debt.</title>
<headline>Brazil lets cities refinance social security debt.</headline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazilian President Fernando Henrique Cardoso Tuesday signed a decree allowing states and cities to renegotiate their debts with the INSS national social security agency, officials said.</p>
<p>The decree allows states and cities to refinance their overdue social security payments up to 240 months at a cost equivalent to the Selic overnight call money rate.</p>
<p>Officials said the measure would increase INSS payments by 40-45 million reais a month.  </p>
<p>Some 4,000 cities are behind on social security payments and can refinance that debt for eight to 20 years, allocating three to nine percent of the revenue they receive from the federal government under constitutional transfers.</p>
<p>Debts to the INSS by city or state-owned foundations can also be included in the deal.</p>
<p>Private hospitals affiliated to the public health system will also be able to renegotiate for up to 96 months debts to the social security system, allocating revenue they receive from the SUS public health system.  </p>
<p>Presidency sources said Cardoso hoped to win the support of mayors in the battle to push civil service reform through Congress and also for Congressional approval of the Fiscal Stabilization Fund (FEF), a key fiscal tool which allows the government to sidestep constitutional rules on spending.</p>
<p>((-- Michael Christie, Brasilia newsroom 55-61-2230358))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
