<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478772" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NICARAGUA: Deportation seen deepening Nicaragua's poverty.</title>
<headline>Deportation seen deepening Nicaragua's poverty.</headline>
<byline>David Koop</byline>
<dateline>MANAGUA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The feared deportation of thousands of Nicaraguans living illegally in the United States would sink the country even deeper into poverty, economists said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The Nicaraguan economy is not capable of absorbing at one blow 60,000 heads of families entering the labour market,&quot; economist Alejandro Martinez Cuenca, president of the International Foundation for the Global Economic Challenge (FIDEG), told Reuters.</p>
<p>Nicaraguans illegally in the United States were given a special last-minute reprieve on Monday as a U.S. federal judge delayed the scheduled April 1 implementation of tough, new immigration laws.</p>
<p>For illegals from other countries the reprieve was only until April 5. But President Arnoldo Aleman claimed that Nicaraguan nationals -- he estimated 60,000 in the United States were in danger of deportation -- will have until July to legalise their status.</p>
<p>Aleman, Nicaragua's Catholic Church and economists said that Nicaragua, with 50 percent of its work force unemployed or underemployed and 70 percent of its population in poverty, was not prepared to receive these deported Nicaragans.</p>
<p>At his Easter mass, Nicaragua's powerful Cardinal Miguel Obando y Bravo made a special call for U.S. officials to &quot;wait for our country to establish adequate conditions to receive them&quot; before starting the deportations.</p>
<p>Martinez said the initial effect of the deportations would be expansive as the returning Nicaraguans brought home their savings, but this would be short-lived if they failed to find work or economic opportunities.</p>
<p>&quot;If these people don't succeed in inserting themselves in the economy, they will enter the already large army of the unemployed,&quot; said Martinez, who was Nicaragua's finance minister in the 1980s.</p>
<p>But Martinez said the most damaging result would be the loss of the incoming money these people send to support their families in Nicaragua.</p>
<p>He said a FIDEG study concluded that Nicaraguans living abroad send between $150-$200 million a year back to the country -- equal to about 25 percent of Nicaragua's total exports in 1996.</p>
<p>Most Nicaraguan expatriates, many of whom fled its civil war in the 1980s, live in the United States or Costa Rica.</p>
<p>The FIDEG study concluded that 37 percent of families received money from abroad with many families wholly dependent on this money for survival.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NICG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANAGUA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NICARAGUA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
