<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478719" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexicans lambast new U.S. immigration law.</title>
<headline>Mexicans lambast new U.S. immigration law.</headline>
<byline>Dan Trotta</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexicans across the political spectrum on Tuesday blasted a tough new U.S. law against illegal immigration as a violation of international human rights and a black day for Mexico.</p>
<p>The new law, which became valid on what Mexican media have dubbed &quot;Black Tuesday,&quot; imposes tough barriers against illegal immigration and has raised fears of mass deportations of Mexicans and other Latin Americans.</p>
<p>It authorised the hiring of thousands of new border guards, fining immigrants for crossing the border illegally, and barring deported immigrants from returning for up to 10 years.</p>
<p>Any crackdown against illegal immigration automatically angers Mexicans, millions of whom migrate, legally and illegally, across the 2,000-mile (3,000-km) border to the United States in search of jobs each year.</p>
<p>Mexicans make up the largest immigrant population in the United States and money they send is one of Mexico's largest sources of hard currency and virtual lifeline to poor relatives back home.</p>
<p>The Party of the Democratic Revolution (PRD), Mexico's main leftist party, called on the Mexican government to sue the United States in the World Court, saying the law violated international human rights norms.</p>
<p>&quot;Behind this is a racist, xenophobic and aggressive environment against non-U.S. peoples,&quot; Ricardo Pascoe Pierce, the party's secretary for international relations, told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is not an energetic and decisive response by the Mexican government, it will leave this (immigrant) population completely defenceless,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Mexico's Foreign Ministry said last week the government would not allow the U.S. law to damage the &quot;dignity&quot; and &quot;human rights&quot; of its citizens, but critics in the Mexican opposition called the response timid.</p>
<p>Deputies in Mexico's lower house of Congress repeated earlier condemnations of the U.S. law and also urged Mexican President Ernesto Zedillo to tackle President Bill Clinton on the issue when he makes his first state visit to the country May 6-7.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
