<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478717" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chilean shares close stable as calm returns.</title>
<headline>Chilean shares close stable as calm returns.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chilean shares closed slightly lower in moderate trade on Tuesday with investors breathing a sigh of relief after the volatility in recent sessions, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Chile is fortunately achieving some degree of independence from Wall Street,&quot; said Guillermo Tagle, head of research at Santander Investments.</p>
<p>Trading at the opening is expected to continue steady, provided there is no untoward macro-economic news or surprise movement in New York, said dealers.  </p>
<p>The 40-share index closed down 0.04 percent at 113.58 points. The general index shed 0.07 percent to 5,274.53 points.</p>
<p>Turnover was a moderate 10.7 billion pesos.</p>
<p>Traders said the market did not react to news that consumer prices rose 0.3 percent in March, as the figure was in line with analysts expectations.</p>
<p>Gainers included forestry firm Masisa which climbed on hopes the firm will show an improvement in its earnings this year, said Tagle.  </p>
<p>Masisa ended up 4.19 percent at 220 pesos.</p>
<p>Other winners included pension fund manager Habitat, up 5.12 percent at 77 pesos and power utility Chilgener which firmed 1.7 percent at 2,690 pesos.</p>
<p>Losers included winery Emiliana, down 12.31 percent at 57 pesos and investment company Oro Blanco which shed 3.43 percent to 2.25 pesos.</p>
<p>((-- Margaret Orgill, Santiago newsroom, 562-699-5595x212))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
