<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478766" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Jewish group blasts Argentine court as anti-semitic.</title>
<headline>Jewish group blasts Argentine court as anti-semitic.</headline>
<byline>Gary Regenstreif</byline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Jewish group, the Simon Wiesenthal Centre, has denounced members of Argentina's Supreme Court as anti-Semitic for saying Jews may have been responsible for blowing up the Israeli Embassy in Buenos Aires in 1992.</p>
<p>The Los Angeles-based group's charges in a letter released on Tuesday intensified the pressure on authorities in Argentina, home to one of the world's largest Jewish communities, to find the culprits after five years of fruitless investigations.</p>
<p>&quot;Five years after the massacre, and in light of the obvious lack of results in the probe, it is unacceptable that members of the court try to turn the victims into aggressors,&quot; Sergio Widder, the center's Latin American representative, said in a letter to Argentine Justice Minister Elias Jassan.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no precedents in the history of our institutions that one of the supreme powers of the Argentine democratic state is driven by a prejudice so obviously anti-Semitic,&quot; Widder said.</p>
<p>The March 1992 explosion killed 29 people and injured more than 200. It was followed two years later by a blast at the AMIA Jewish community centre in Buenos Aires that killed 86 people.</p>
<p>No one has been charged in either bombing but Supreme Court Chief Justice Julio Nazareno recently confirmed a newspaper report that some members of the tribunal thought radical right-wing Jewish groups may have been responsible for the embassy explosion.</p>
<p>&quot;This incident appears to be an updated version of those who deny the Holocaust and who suggest it was an invention of the Jews to gain some sort of advantage,&quot; said Widder, who sent a similar letter to Congress on Monday night.</p>
<p>Late last month, Israel's U.N. envoy cited a statement by a leader of the Hamas Islamic Resistance Movement as implying Hamas was responsible for the 1992 bombing of the embassy. Israel has in the past blamed Iranian-backed fundamentalists.</p>
<p>Those court members who believe Jews were responsible were apparently basing their beliefs on recent findings of the National Academy of Engineers that the explosion came from inside the diplomatic mission. But security forces combing the site after the blast concluded the explosion was caused by a car bomb.</p>
<p>Argentine Foreign Minister Guido Di Tella described the Wiesenthal Centres &quot;anti-Semitic&quot; charges as unjust on Tuesday and reiterated the government's assertion that a &quot;a terrorist who blew himself up in a car bomb&quot; was responsible. Di Tella recently described the investigation as &quot;a total failure&quot; and said the case had not been handled with the urgency it deserved.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
