<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478731" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil Santos stevedores to begin strike April 2.</title>
<headline>Brazil Santos stevedores to begin strike April 2.</headline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stevedores at Brazil's key port of Santos are set to begin a two-day strike at 0700 local/1000 GMT April 2 over a labor dispute, said the first treasurer of the Stevedores Union.</p>
<p>&quot;We are having meetings now but the strike will go ahead,&quot; said Antonio Pinheiro.</p>
<p>&quot;The idea is to strike on a regional level, that is in Santos, on April 2 and April 3. Then if there is no advance in negotiations, the strike will spread to a national level on April 4,&quot; he added.  </p>
<p>Although other unions are not expected to join the stevedores, the port is expected to be brought to a halt by the strike action, said an official at the Port Operators' Union.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment, it is just the stevedores. But that is sufficient to bring the whole port to a stop without a doubt,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>The stevedores are striking in protest at a new ruling which takes effect tomorrow allowing company workers from steel mill Companhia Siderurgica Paulista (Cosipa) to operate Cosipa's private terminal at the port, Pinheiro said.  </p>
<p>The terminal was privatised as part of an ongoing national program which has been meeting resistance from unions and has already resulted in several stoppages.</p>
<p>An official at the National Portworkers Federation said he had not heard of any specific plans for a national strike but did not rule the possibility of a nationwide stoppage in the near future because of the privatisation program.  </p>
<p>&quot;We are expecting to have a very big strike throughout all Brazil...I do not know at the moment of any definite strike but things are certainly heading that way,&quot; said Jose Horatio Freitas, administrative and financial secretary.</p>
<p>Santos is Brazil's key port and stoppages in the past have hit shipments of sugar, coffee and grains such as soybeans.</p>
<p>((-Caroline Bulloch, Rio de Janeiro newsroom, 5521 5074151))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
