<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478710" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peru hostage talks at standstill, gloom sets in.</title>
<headline>Peru hostage talks at standstill, gloom sets in.</headline>
<byline>Roger Atwood</byline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A new pessimism surrounded Peru's 105-day hostage standoff on Tuesday after a key mediator said the country's &quot;heart is completely broken&quot; by the siege with no new peace talks in sight.</p>
<p>President Alberto Fujimori appealed for patience in ending the siege in a phone conversation with Bolivian President Gonzalo Sanchez de Lozada, whose ambassador to Peru is among the 72 hostages held under the guns of Marxist rebels.</p>
<p>&quot;He doesn't believe there will be a rapid solution to the crisis,&quot; Sanchez de Lozada said on Monday, referring to Fujimori, adding that &quot;new disagreements&quot; had appeared in efforts to end the siege, according to news reports in Lima.</p>
<p>An even more discouraging note came from Archbishop Juan Luis Cipriani, member of a three-man mediation team known as the guarantors' commission, who had no progress to report after meetings with Fujimori and his chief negotiator.</p>
<p>&quot;No problem is eternal and this one will be settled. ... Bit by bit, we're getting closer. But I have nothing new to add,&quot; Cipriani said on Monday night after talks with fellow mediator and Canadian ambassador Anthony Vincent.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Peru's heart is completely broken,&quot; a tired-looking Cipriani said. &quot;It's really been many weeks now and I feel much pain in my heart.&quot;</p>
<p>The sudden gloom stood in contrast to the quickening pace towards an agreement reported by diplomats last week after a series of meetings between mediators and Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement (MRTA) hostage-takers. But the government and MRTA rebels have not met face-to-face since March 12 and no new talks were on the agenda.</p>
<p>Thick winter fog rolling in off the Pacific has enveloped the mansion every morning, reinforcing the gloomy mood at the house surrounded by crack police forces, armoured vehicles and legions of reporters. About 20 MRTA rebels, some teenagers, blasted into a party at the Japanese ambassador's home on Dec. 17 and took all 500 guests hostage, shocking millions of Peruvians who believed Fujimori's assertion that guerrilla groups had been crushed.</p>
<p>The MRTA gradually freed all but 72 of the captives, keeping influential figures like Fujimori's brother Pedro, two cabinet ministers and the former chief of the anti-terrorism police force.</p>
<p>Talks appear to have foundered on the MRTA's demands for release of its roughly 450 jailed comrades in exchange for the hostages. Fujimori has refused to consider the demand but is widely reported to be willing to free some MRTA detainees who have not yet been convicted or have been convicted of non-violent crimes.</p>
<p>Freeing MRTA prisoners could have political costs for Fujimori. Polls show that about 90 percent of Peruvians, weary from 17 years of violence that has claimed 30,000 lives, oppose any guerrilla release even if it means letting the hostage siege drag on indefinitely.</p>
<p>An MRTA rebel spokesman blamed government &quot;intransigence&quot; on Monday for the slow pace of talks. &quot;We will stay (in the residence) as long as necessary to obtain the freedom of our prisoners,&quot; the spokesman known as Comrade Alejandro said from a MRTA stronghold in the central jungle in Junin department.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
