<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478773" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Colombia unveils plans for telecom revolution.</title>
<headline>Colombia unveils plans for telecom revolution.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombia will spend $10 billion in the next 10 years on revolutionizing the country's telecommunications network, President Ernesto Samper said Tuesday.</p>
<p>Samper said Colombia's telecommunications infrastructure would grow by about 12 percent per year and is forecast to contribute eight percent of Colombia's annual gross domestic product by 2007, compared with the current level of about 2.4 percent of GDP.  </p>
<p>In a speech at the presidential palace in Bogota, Samper did not mention what role domestic and foreign private enterprise would be allowed to play in Colombia's telecommunications revolution, except to say that more concessions would be granted to private cellular phone companies in 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;This plan aims to put us on a par with with the most developed countries in terms of telecommunications,&quot; Samper said.  </p>
<p>The aims of the plan, which will run from 1997 to 2207, include more than doubling the number of phone lines in service to about 12.8 million, or 30 lines per 1,000 inhabitants, one of the highest levels in latin America.</p>
<p>Samper said the number of cellular phone users was forecast to grow from current levels of about 300,000 to more than three million.  In addition he said the plan aimed to offer Internet services to 1.5 million subscribers by 2007 and pipe cable television into four million homes in the same period.  </p>
<p>The Communications Ministry was unable to give figures about the current levels of Internet and cable TV usage.</p>
<p>Under the terms of the plan Colombia's national phone company Telecom would undertake to repair all faulty lines within two weeks, compared with the currrent average of about eight months.</p>
<p>In addition to the $10 billion infrastructure spending, samper said additional amounts would be spent on marketing telecommunications services.</p>
<p>&quot;This plan will finally permit Colombia to come of age in terms of telecommunications infrastructure,&quot; Samper said.</p>
<p>((-- Karl Penhaul, Bogota newsroom, 571 610 7944))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
