<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478784" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Belgian PM calls Mercosur &quot;disorganized&quot;.</title>
<headline>Belgian PM calls Mercosur &quot;disorganized&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene said during a visit to Argentina that the Mercosur customs union, currently embroiled in a trade dispute, needs to get better organized, the Argentine news agency DyN reported on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;One challenge for Mercosur is if it can continue to work in such a disorganized way as it has until now,&quot; the Belgian prime minister said in a speech late Monday.  </p>
<p>To be sure, Dehaene said he recognized &quot;the successes&quot; of the customs union formed by Brazil, Argentina, Uruguay and Paraguay. He said his country would lobby the European Union to forge closer links with Mercosur, which also includes Chile as an associate member.</p>
<p>The comments of the Belgian leader, made on the first day of a three-day visit, were especially relevant coming amid a trade dispute that undermines Mercosur's credibility as it tries to forge stronger links with the European Union.  </p>
<p>Argentina, Uruguay and Paraguay are seeking to persuade their trading partner Brazil to exempt them from new import restrictions, which they view as protectionist.</p>
<p>Desperate to slim its trade gap, Brazil's central bank last week ruled that most Brazilian importers with financing of under 360 days have to take out foreign exchange contracts on the day they receive their goods from customs.</p>
<p>Dehaene met President Carlos Menem twice during his first official visit to Argentina, the main aim of which was to promote his country's role in the Argentine privatization process.</p>
<p>One Belgian company has won a tender to dredge the Parana river and Belgium's Solvay has a major stake in the Argentine petrochemicals industry.</p>
<p>The Belgian prime minister's visit ends Wednesday, when he flies on to neighboring Uruguay.</p>
<p>(( Stephen Brown, Buenos Aires Newsroom +541 318-0695))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MRCSL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
