<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478713" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Britain offers Colombia emergency aid for refugees.</title>
<headline>Britain offers Colombia emergency aid for refugees.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain has offered emergency aid to Colombia to cope with a human tide fleeing violence in the northwest of the country, officials said on Monday.</p>
<p>The aid offer, which still has to be approved by the British government's Overseas Development Agency, was made through the British Embassy in Bogota, an embassy source said.</p>
<p>More than 2,500 people, mainly women and children, arrived in Mutata, in the violence-torn region of Uraba, over Easter, the Rev. Leonidas Moreno of the Catholic Church-run Commission for Justice, Peace and Life said. Hundreds more were making their way along treacherous jungle tracks, he added.</p>
<p>The people were forced to abandon their homes in the face of threats from right-wing death squads and fighting between leftist guerrillas and the army in the Rio Salaqui basin area of Choco province in the western half of the Uraba region.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a horrible, terrifying situation, like an image from Rwanda,&quot; Moreno told Reuters by telephone from the regional center of Apartado. &quot;Some of those coming from Rio Salaqui have been walking for a month across mountains and along jungle tracks. They are fleeing because they are in fear of their life and do not feel protected by anybody.&quot;</p>
<p>Abelardo Parra, a local government official in northwest Antioquia province, said he had asked for help from Britain.</p>
<p>An embassy source in Bogota said: &quot;At this stage we are looking into providing emergency aid to deal with this situation.&quot; The source said initial aid would likely consist of tents to house the refugees and emergency food supplies.</p>
<p>Moreno estimated there were at least 7,000 internal refugees in Uraba. In addition to the 2,500 people in Mutata, about 4,000 more were in temporary shelters in Turbo, a small port on the Gulf of Uraba, and another 70 families fled the mountain village of La Union, near Apartado, last week.</p>
<p>Several hundred others have fled through the Darien Gap and into remote areas of neighboring Panama, Colombian Ambassador Edgardo Sales told reporters on Monday.</p>
<p>In recent weeks the army has waged an offensive against Marxist rebels in the region in a bid to cut off what it believes are lucrative arms and drug trafficking routes in and out of Colombia via Panama.</p>
<p>Right-wing paramilitary groups, meanwhile, have been waging a scorched earth policy to clear entire villages of what they claim are guerrilla sympathizers.</p>
<p>In comments to reporters on Monday, army commander Gen. Manuel Jose Bonett denied reports the army had bombed and strafed communities in Choco and said the refugees were ordered to leave their homes by the guerrillas.</p>
<p>&quot;We bombarded an area three weeks ago where there were no houses, just jungle. The guerrilla strategy is to force these people to move out in order to create social problems in larger towns,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The government estimates more than 900,000 people have been displaced in Colombia in recent years as a result of the country's long-running guerrilla war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
