<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478745" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil Ag Min authorises Indonesia cocoa imports.</title>
<headline>Brazil Ag Min authorises Indonesia cocoa imports.</headline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's Minister of Agriculture has given the go-ahead to three companies to import 4,000 tonnes of Indonesian cocoa beans, the president of one of the companies said.</p>
<p>&quot;We received a fax today from the Ministry of Agriculture authorising the imports...Between today and tomorrow we hope to finish negotiating prices,&quot; said Wady Jasmin of Joanes Industria, a subsidiary of the U.K's E.D. and F. Man.</p>
<p>Joanes is to import 1,750 tonnes, Chadler a further 1,750 tonnes and the Brazilian arm of Swiss food giant Nestle SA the remaining 500 tonnes.</p>
<p>Jasmin said he understood the Brazilian arm of Cargill Inc had also received a fax to import a further 2,000 tonnes of Indonesian cocoa from a different seller.</p>
<p>The four companies had approached the Agriculture Ministry after reaching a consensus with producers over a supply shortfall at the start of the Bahian midcrop, normally harvested between May and September but expected to start late this year.</p>
<p>Producers have given their blessing to up to 15,000 tonnes of cocoa imports until August.</p>
<p>Jasmin said the 4,000 tonne shipment should leave Indonesia in the next few days. The journey is expected to take around two months.</p>
<p>Indonesia is currently the only country which has been pre-certified as free of risk by the Brazilian government following new regulations set down after a number of problems with the purchase of 5,000 tonnes of Ivorian beans in 1995.</p>
<p>The cocoa to be imported will come from a particular growing region in Indonesia which had been certified as free of risk after a group of Brazilian officials visited the region at the end of 1995.</p>
<p>The Indonesian embassy was asked by the Agriculture Ministry last month to check that conditions in the area had not changed.</p>
<p>Over the coming months the companies may also request the Agriculture Ministry to conduct a risk assessment survey of imports from the Ivory Coast but this is not an urgent issue, Jasmin said.</p>
<p>((-Caroline Bulloch, Rio de Janeiro newsroom, 5521 5074151</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100144">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
