<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478862" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>new Zealand: PRESS DIGEST - New Zealand newspapers - Apr 2.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - New Zealand newspapers - Apr 2.</headline>
<text>
<p>THE DOMINION</p>
<p>The longest-serving MP, Labour's Jonathan Hunt, admitted on Tuesday night that he spent $29,170 on taxi fares in the year to June 30 last year. Hunt cited the distance between Auckland airport and his home near Piha, plus his position at the time as senior opposition whip, as reasons for the hefty taxi bill. Page 1.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Parliament's privileges committee will probably rule this afternoon on the contempt of Parliament charge against Deputy Prime Minister Winston Peters, Attorney-General Paul East said last night. He said the committee would not disclose its decision before reporting back to Parliament in three weeks. Page 1.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>A huge fight was likely if the government ignored sensible options and decided to join court action over Maori trout fishing rights, Treaty of Waitangi Fisheries Commission chairman Sir Tipene O'Regan said. &quot;Maori parties with a major interest will be forced into full-scale war instead of being in a position to negotiate an outcome responsibly.&quot; Page 1.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>NZ First MP Tukoroirangi Morgan said no public money was involved in paying for his car and he will have lease documentation changed to record his own name. Land Transport's motor registration records show Raukura Hauora O Tainui Trust as owners of $49,000 Ford Fairmonts used by Morgan and Aotearoa Television Network director Morehu McDonald. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Deregulation on a scale unseen since Labour's 1980s heyday has been called for by the government's competition overlord, Commerce Minister Juhn Luxton. Primary producer boards are on Luxton's hit list to open the floodgates of competition. Luxton is Associate Agriculture Minister as well as Commerce Minister. Also in his sights are pharmacists, optometrists, teachers, lawyers, and local and central government monopolies. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Anyone wanting to make submissions on the bill setting up the proposed national referendum on compulsory superannuation will have to be quick. Public submissions on the Retirement Savings Scheme Referendum Bill were called on Tuesday but the closing date is Friday April 18 - less than three weeks away. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Forcing beneficiaries to look for work was not a cost-driven move, but one aimed at trying to get them back into employment, Social Welfare Minister Roger Sowry said on Tuesday. In changes coming into effect this week, people on domestic purposes and widow's benefits, and spouses of unemployment beneficiaries have to try to find part-time work or training if their children are over 14. If they don't, they face cuts in payments or losing their benefits. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Beneficiaries, like everyone else, must expect to face penalties if they break the law, Prime Minister Jim Bolger said on Tuesday. Justice Minister Dough Graham said that the government had decided to allow unpaid court fines -- which threaten to soar to $210 million this year -- to be deducted from welfare payments. However, critics say benefits are already so low that any reduction would cause further hardship. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>A referendum on dumping the Treaty of Waitangi would achieve nothing other than prove that non-Maoris outnumbered Maoris, Labour MP Mike Moore said on Tuesday. The referendum was being promoted by good New Zealanders who were not racist, but there was a danger it would attract white radicals, he said. Aucklander Mark Whyte wants to collect the 241,000 signatures necessary to enforce a national referendum. He says the Treaty is outdated and should be replaced with a forward-looking constitution. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Alliance MPs began a special two-day caucus meeting on Tuesday night to discuss strategies for action that the party will take during the two and a half years till the next general election. Among the issues to be discussed are the Alliance's relationship with the Labour party, water privatisation, and opposition to the proposed compulsory superannuation scheme. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Manufacturers in the top half of the North Island are being hit with the double-whammy of a continuing high dollar and a slow down in New Zealand sales, leading to the loss of thousands of jobs. The northern region Employs and Manufacturers Association's survey of business conditions for February showed that a total turnover was down five percent compared with February 1996. The survey covers 120 companies, both large and small and in various sectors and areas of Auckland, Waikato and Bay of Plenty. Page 12.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Visa credit card holders racked up NZ$3.6 billion in spending in 1996, Visa said on Tuesday. The spend-up was an increase of 20 percent over calendar 1995, with total transactions rising 12 percent to 34.6 million, indicating consumers used their cards on average for more expensive purchases. The number of Visa cards in New Zealand also rose 14 percent to reach 1.4 million, Visa said. Page 12.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Defiance Foods' 1200 preference shareholders would have to wait to learn about parent Defiance Mills' plans to buy back shares, Defiance Mills chairman Tom O'Brien said on Tuesday. It would only confuse the market to reveal details before the Commerce Commission ruled on the sale of Defiance Foods' New Zealand assets to Goodman Fielder, O'Brien said. A decision on the $48 million buyout is expected by April 10. Page 12</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Radio Network is &quot;highly likely&quot; to take the Commerce Commission to the High Court after the commission rejected the network's bid to buy Christchurch stations C91FM and i94FM, network chief executive Joan Withers said on Tuesday. Withers said the network saw the decision as significant as Christchurch was an important market. Page 13.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
