<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478899" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Family doubts Bre-X geologist killed himself.</title>
<headline>Family doubts Bre-X geologist killed himself.</headline>
<byline>Dolly Aglay</byline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The family of the late Filipino geologist who discovered what was initially said to be the biggest gold find this century expressed doubts on Tuesday that he committed suicide.</p>
<p>&quot;For somebody who is on top of the world, for somebody who has got a great family and six beautiful kids whom he adores so much...I don't see any reason...(why) he would commit suicide,&quot; Simplicio de Guzman, brother of late Bre-X Minerals Ltd chief geologist Michael de Guzman told Reuters.</p>
<p>De Guzman fell from a helicopter while returning to the Busang gold find he helped discover in Indonesia's East Kalimantan province. His body was brought to Manila on Saturday from Jakarta 11 days after the incident.</p>
<p>Some Indonesian officials have called de Guzman's death a suicide saying he had left letters that said he was suffering from acute hepatitis.</p>
<p>When asked if he or other members of the family saw any indication in the past that the Filipino geologist was suffering from any serious illness, Simplicio de Guzman said: &quot;No.&quot; &quot;Medical reports would show that he does not have hepatitis,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A Singapore clinic which examined de Guzman gave him a clean bill of health when he was tested last February, the Philippine Daily Inquirer newspaper quoted Simplicio as saying on Monday.</p>
<p>But the paper also said de Guzman had been stricken by malaria 14 times in the past from his frequent exploratory trips to the jungles of Kalimantan on Indonesia's side of Borneo island.</p>
<p>Simplicio said the de Guzman family was still waiting for the report of the autopsy done by Indonesian officials.</p>
<p>&quot;The Philippine embassy in Indonesia promised to secure a copy of it (autopsy report) and immediately send it,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Simplicio said his family believed his brother struck a mountain of gold in Busang.</p>
<p>&quot;He would always talk about it in big terms and he always believed that he was on to something big, but as to the bigness of it he never really specified,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Canada's Bre-X Minerals Ltd became a darling of the Toronto Stock Exchange after it reported the Busang gold strike, which was initially said to have been the biggest find since gold was discovered in South Africa's Witwatersrand late in the 19th century.</p>
<p>Bre-X said early this year the Busang deposit held at least 71 million ounces of gold worth about $20 billion at current gold prices.</p>
<p>But Bre-X shares plunged after the company said the deposit might not be as big as projected.</p>
<p>Bre-X has a 45 percent stake in the Busang property, Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold Inc of the United States 15 percent and Indonesian interests the rest.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
