<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478834" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil's Franco to announce 1998 candidacy - report.</title>
<headline>Brazil's Franco to announce 1998 candidacy - report.</headline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former Brazilian president Itamar Franco will announce his candidacy in next year's presidential elections when he meets with President Fernando Henrique Cardoso on Wednesday, a prominent television commentator said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Franco plans to head a coalition of left-wing parties against Cardoso's expected 1998 re-election bid, Globo television commentator Ricardo Boechat said in a report on the &quot;Bom Dia Brasil&quot; (Good Morning, Brazil) breakfast program.  </p>
<p>A presidential spokeswoman confirmed Cardoso and Franco were due to meet for dinner on Wednesday but said she did not know what would be on the agenda.</p>
<p>Franco has been hinting for months he would like to be president again. He has repeatedly claimed he, not Cardoso, deserves the credit for the Real Plan that cut Brazil's once rampant inflation to about ten percent last year.</p>
<p>Cardoso was finance minister in Franco's government when the Real Plan was introduced in 1994.</p>
<p>Franco was elected vicepresident to Fernando Collor in 1989 and took over the presidency in 1992 when Collor resigned amid a corruption scandal. He is currently Brazil's representative at the Organization of American States in Washington.</p>
<p>An opinion poll published in March by the private Ibope polling company found Franco would win just three percent of votes, compared with 46 percent for Cardoso if the latter was allowed to run for a second term.</p>
<p>Brazil's Senate is mulling a constitutional amendment which would undo a ban on re-election and allow Cardoso to run in 1998. The amendment has already been passed in the Chamber of Deputies.</p>
<p>(( -- William Schomberg, Brasilia newsroom 5561 2230358))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
