<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478878" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: KL palm oil ends mostly down, outlook seen mixed.</title>
<headline>KL palm oil ends mostly down, outlook seen mixed.</headline>
<text>
<p>PALM OIL FUTURES	    PALM OIL PHYSICAL</p>
<p>Jun (3rd pos) 1,257 rgt/tonne	  Apr (south) 1,292.50*</p>
<p>Open/Hi/Low 1,255/1,258/1,251	  Prev close 1,295</p>
<p>Prev settlement  1,258		   * sellers prices</p>
<p>PALM OIL FUTURES - Prices rebounded on some late covering to end mixed after a slow trading day. Sharp falls in soyoil futures in Chicago and lack of demand had dragged prices down earlier. June futures, which traded in seven-ringgit range today, may trade between 1,250 and 1,260 ringgit.</p>
<p>PALM OIL PHYSICAL - The market was also uncertain and interest was on nearby crude palm oil and RBD palm olein.  </p>
<p>Soyoil fell because of high USDA 1997 planted soybean acreage estimates. USDA on Monday estimated 1997 soybean plantings at 68.8 million acres, the highest since 1980 and well above trade expectations for 65.85 million.</p>
<p>The market is directionless in the absence of fresh leads and traders are waiting for the Egyptian tender on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are waiting for the Egyptian tender tomorrow,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Third month June futures contract closed at 1,257 ringgit ($507.67), down one ringgit from Monday.  </p>
<p>The contract is likely to trade in the 1,250 and 1,260. If it breaks the 1,260 level, the next resistance will be at 1,280, a chartist said.</p>
<p>Among physicals, Apr (south) crude palm oil was offered at 1,292.50 ringgit against bids of 1,290, after trading at 1,285 and 1,290. Apr (central) saw offers at 1,282.50 against bids 1,277.50.</p>
<p>May (south) was offered at 1,287.50 and bids at 1,282.50, and May (central) at 1,280 against 1,275.  </p>
<p>Among refined products, Apr RBD palm oil was offered at $545 a tonne FOB Malaysia, May $542.50, June at $540 and July/Aug/Sep at $537.50.</p>
<p>Apr RBD palm olein saw offers at $582.50, May at $577.50, Jun at $575 and July/Aug/Sep at $570. May was traded at $575.</p>
<p>Apr RBD palm stearin was offered at $437.50 and Apr/May palm fatty acid distillate saw sellers at $297.50.</p>
<p>--Tan Lee Lee (603-230-7510) ($1=2.4760 ringgit)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
