<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478856" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuela cabinet eyes iron, aluminum firm sales.</title>
<headline>Venezuela cabinet eyes iron, aluminum firm sales.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Venezuelan cabinet on Monday confirmed its plans to privatize the parastatal Corporacion Venezolana de Guayana's (CVG) aluminum and iron firms.</p>
<p>&quot;We had a special cabinet meeting today solely to back the sale,&quot; said Alberto Poletto, president of the Venezuelan Investment Fund (FIV), the state body in charge of privatization.</p>
<p>&quot;We ended the meeting feeling energized and ready to take decisions ... everyone was in complete accord to move the sales ahead and close them,&quot; Poletto told reporters.</p>
<p>The sales to private investor groups are expected to raise around $3 billion, but have already been repeatedly delayed and are expected to face further opposition when the sales contracts go before Congress.</p>
<p>Poletto, who was accompanied by CVG president Elias Ynaty, said the proposed sales contracts would go to President Rafael Caldera for approval on Wednesday, and would be forwarded to Congress within four weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;We're moving ahead at an adequate speed: prudently and carefully but surely,&quot; Poletto said.</p>
<p>Early discussions of the companies' sale have drawn loud protest from some congressmen who argue Venezuela is selling the companies far too cheaply.</p>
<p>Political analysts note that Venezuela's largest party, social democrat Democratic Action (AD), as well as left-leaning Radical Cause, both of which have deep roots in the CVG's labor unions, are at best lukewarm to the proposal.</p>
<p>And local end users of aluminum, such as can manufacturers who want to be sure of a secure supply of aluminum after the sale, have also joined the protest.</p>
<p>But the government has only belatedly begun to publicly deploy arguments for the companies' sale, such as CVG's environmental liabilities.</p>
<p>&quot;Thanks to privatization, we would be free of those,&quot; said Poletto who added the estimated clean-up cost for investors would top $200 million.</p>
<p>The government has said it is sticking to its plans to sell the iron and aluminum firms during the second half of the year, despite opposition and a busy legislative schedule in Congress.</p>
<p>&quot;How the timetable (of the companies' sale) works out depends on Congress,&quot; Ynaty said.</p>
<p>Venezuelan political analysts have said that the sale of CVG's iron company, Sidor, will probably go ahead on schedule.</p>
<p>But the more complex sale of the four aluminum sector companies -- Venalum, Bauxilum, Alcasa and Carbonorca -- is likely to be delayed beyond presidential elections in December 1998, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Although the aluminum privatization may fail, there is a reasonable chance that Sidor will make it through unscathed,&quot; financial magazine VenEconomy said.</p>
<p>Venezuelan investors have said they are paying close attention to the privatizations as a further sign of the government's willingness to continue reforms, after an unexpected agreement announced earlier this month to reform severance pay.</p>
<p>((-- John Paul Rathbone, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22450">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
