<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478829" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Troubles of Mexican airline Taesa mount -- paper.</title>
<headline>Troubles of Mexican airline Taesa mount -- paper.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico's third largest airline Taesa owes money not only to creditor banks but also to the government in taxes and social security payments, the daily El Economista said Tuesday.</p>
<p>Citing unnamed sources, the daily said the debts of the airline amount to $400 million to seven creditor banks, while government debts total 100 million pesos to the Finance Ministry and the Mexican Social Security Institute.</p>
<p>El Economista reported last week that two Mexican banks are seeking the liquidation of Taesa because the airline has lost two-thirds of its share capital and is unable to pay debts.  </p>
<p>El Economista has said that Bancomer, Mexico's second largest bank, recently filed a petition in a Mexico City court for Taesa to be declared bankrupt.</p>
<p>A Bancomer spokesman at that time was not able to confirm the suit against Taesa. Neither Taesa nor Bancomer spokesmen could be reached for comment this morning.</p>
<p>Taesa, an airline that grew rapidly during the administration of former president Carlos Salinas (1988-1994), had a 30 percent market share in that period but then suffered, as all Mexican airlines did, in the December 1994 devaluation.</p>
<p>((-- Chris Aspin, Mexico City newsroom +525 7287902))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
