<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478858" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Broadcasting Corp Midday Update.</title>
<headline>Australian Broadcasting Corp Midday Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>COLSTON CAN STAY IN PRESIDENT'S POSITION: GOVT</p>
<p>Acting Prime Minster, Tim Fischer, says Independent Senator Mal Colston has made a lot of mistakes over his travel allowance, but the Government won't prevent him acting as Senate President.</p>
<p>Senator Colston is acting in the role while the President, Margaret Reid, is overseas.</p>
<p>Mr Fischer he's aware of growing public anger at the Government's handling of issues involving the Senator but the Colston affair is a matter for the Senate and due process.</p>
<p>Mr Fischer says Senator Colston won't be in charge of deciding whether his case should be referred to the Federal police.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MTIA SAYS LAST BUDGET WAS DAMAGING TO INDUSTRY</p>
<p>A large manufacturing industry group has called on the Government not make any more cuts to industry in the upcoming Budget, saying ad hoc measures in the last Budget were damaging. The Metal Trades Industry Association is releasing it's pre-budget submission today.</p>
<p>The association says many of the government's decisions were wrong, such as axing the DIFF scheme for exporters and dropping financial incentives for big employers to train.</p>
<p>It says the last budget saw growth in the manufacturing sector slow to zero.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>POLICE DOORKNOCK HOMES IN MACKAY MURDER HUNT</p>
<p>Mackay police are conducting a doorknock this morning in a hunt for clues to a fatal shooting in the north Queensland city last night.</p>
<p>Police say a 46-year-old man was shot in the back while attempting to flee from an intruder he disturbed in his backyard about 8.15 last night.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>TERRITORY WARNS IT CAN BYPASS VIDEO BAN</p>
<p>Northern Territory Attorney General Denis Burke says the Territory will withdraw from the co-operative video classification regime if the Federal Government decides to ban X-rated vidoes.</p>
<p>Mr Burke says the Territory would set up its own classification board to maintain its censorship arrangements.</p>
<p>He says he's confident federal Attorney General Daryl Williams will argue strongly on the Territory's behalf during debate in Cabinet today.</p>
<p>Mr Burke says the Federal Government is better off leaving the issue alone.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FRUIT FLY OUTBREAK COULD HAVE BEEN WORSE: FRUITGROWERS</p>
<p>The Northern Victoria Fruitgrowers Association says to some extent fruitgrowers have been fortunate in the timing of a fruit-fly outbreak in Shepparton.</p>
<p>Executive officer, Norm Mitchelmore, says the outbreak will be costly but comes just past the major harvest for some fruits and most fruit will pass quarantine because of the way it's been stored.</p>
<p>Goulburn Valley fruitgrowers face trade restrictions for the next 12 months because of the fruit fly</p>
<p>Mr Mitchelmore says orchardists were only released from restrictions a month ago from the last outbreak in 1995.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>LEGAL COST GUIDE NEEDED, SAYS COMMISSIONER</p>
<p>The New South Wales Legal Services Commissioner says he wants an annual survey on legal fees published so consumers can determine if they're being charged fairly by solicitors.</p>
<p>Commissioner Steve Mark has criticised the legal profession's reluctance to give cost quotes to clients and says he'll have talks later this year about publishing the survey.</p>
<p>In his annual report for 1995-96, Mr Mark says of the 11,000 complaints received about solictitors 41 per cent concerned solicitors' costs and bills and 40.5 percent concerned ethics.</p>
<p>The report found the public are also concerned about rudeness and what they perceive as bullying by legal practitioners.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
