<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478813" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Soy shipping conditions at key Brazilian ports.</title>
<headline>Soy shipping conditions at key Brazilian ports.</headline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Key Brazilian ports reported the following conditions for shipments of soybeans and soy products:</p>
<p>PARANAGUA:</p>
<p>Vessels: Ocean Lady loading 47,000 tonnes soymeal. Lepetane loading 22,000 tonnes soymeal. Flag Supplier loading 54,200 tonnes soybeans. Sun P loading 55,000 tonnes soybeans. Humber loading 55,000 tonnes soybeans/meal.</p>
<p>Trucks: A total 2,124 trucks arrived on March 31, a new record for the port. Of this, 1,677 trucks unloaded soybeans, 348 soymeal and 99 trucks vegetable oils including soyoil.</p>
<p>Loading: No figures available.</p>
<p>Stocks: No figures available.</p>
<p>NOTE: Loading of grains at the port's export terminal was suspended at 0750 local/1050 GMT because of rain. The port expects loading to continue sporadically throughout the day insofar as rains allow.</p>
<p>SANTOS:</p>
<p>Vessels: Hilon of Sparta loading 55,000 soybeans. Huta Kotowice waiting to load 54,000 tonnes soybeans. Aghia Trias loading 59,126 tonnes soybeans at Cargill private terminal.</p>
<p>Road: 385 trucks arrived on March 31 unloading 9,940 tonnes soybeans and 34 trucks arrived unloading 797 tonnes soymeal.</p>
<p>Rail: 43 wagons arrived unloading 2,005 tonnes soymeal and nine wagons arrived unloading 562 tonnes soymeal.</p>
<p>Stocks: 80,141 tonnes soybeans, 4,714 tonnes soymeal.</p>
<p>Loading: In the month of March, the port terminal loaded 138,094 tonnes soybeans and 15,001 tonnes soymeal. The Cargill private terminal loaded 70,196 tonnes soybeans and 32,723 tonnes soymeal.</p>
<p>NOTE: Loading of grains at the port's export terminal was suspended because of rain at 1730 local Monday. Facilities remained shut Tuesday morning.</p>
<p>RIO GRANDE:</p>
<p>Vessels: China Spirit to start loading 30,000 tonnes soymeal. Boris Livanov expected April 2, to load 19,000 tonnes soybeans. Dunga Saga Satu expected April 6, to load a total of 45,000 soymeal at two separate private terminals. Ariston expected April 8, to load 12,000 tonnes soyoil. NOTE: The port, which was recently privatised, does not release any information on arrivals and stock levels.</p>
<p>((--Joelle Diderich, Sao Paulo newsroom +55 11 248 5417))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
