<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478882" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Australia's Howard says China visit succcesful.</title>
<headline>Australia's Howard says China visit succcesful.</headline>
<byline>Scott Hillis</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian Prime Minister John Howard on Tuesday met Chinese President Jiang Zemin and hailed his visit to China as a successful attempt to bolster economic ties between Beijing and Canberra.</p>
<p>&quot;I have been able to emphasise the partnership of the government and Australian business community in building a strong relationship with China,&quot; Howard told Jiang during talks at the Diaoyutai State Guesthouse in Beijing.</p>
<p>Howard said he had also told his Chinese hosts disagreements over human rights could arise in the future but that Canberra would seek to address differences through dialogue.</p>
<p>&quot;I have raised (human rights) in a fashion that I believe is not going to detract from the positive achievements on other fronts,&quot; Howard told a news conference.</p>
<p>China's Foreign Ministry on Tuesday said it welcomed such an attitude, saying there was nothing to be gained by confrontation on human rights.</p>
<p>Howard said he had appealed to Premier Li Peng on Monday to release jailed Australian businessman James Peng and said such a move would help relations between the two countries.</p>
<p>&quot;In different ways, the matter will be further pursued,&quot; Howard said of Peng's case. He did not elaborate.</p>
<p>Peng was jailed for 18 years in 1995 on charges of embezzlement. Peng has insisted the charges were trumped up by powerful business rivals.</p>
<p>Diplomats said Howard's visit was intended mainly to boost economic relations, and the prime minister said such ties had been the focus of meetings with senior Chinese leaders.</p>
<p>&quot;We do have a strong and sensible relationship built on those twin pillars of mutual interests and mutual trust,&quot; Howard said, adding that he had invited Jiang and Li to visit Australia but that no dates had been set.</p>
<p>Travelling with the prime minister is a business group that includes representatives of firms that already have a strong presence in the Chinese market, as well as companies looking to tap into new areas such as finance.</p>
<p>Howard on Tuesday also presided at a ceremony marking the opening of a Beijing branch office of the Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd and spoke at a seminar for Chinese firms seeking to list shares in Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;This is yet another element of the burgeoning economic, commercial and business association between Australia and China,&quot; Howard said of the bank office deal.</p>
<p>Howard said he and Li had agreed to explore the feasibility of cooperation in finance, insurance and social welfare, adding that China's huge economic boom would make Beijing less likely to threaten its neighbours.</p>
<p>China is Australia's fifth largest trading partner, with two-way trade worth $6.3 billion in the year to June 30, 1996, but diplomats say plenty of room remains to expand links.</p>
<p>Howard's visit is also intended to help repair damage to relations from issues including Canberra's military ties with the United States and its welcome last year for exiled Tibetan spiritual leader the Dalai Lama.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama fled Tibet in 1959 after the failure of an uprising against Chinese rule.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
