<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478877" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asia Gas Oil/Jet - Diesel offered at higher levels.</title>
<headline>Asia Gas Oil/Jet - Diesel offered at higher levels.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore gas oil market saw sellers trying to push prices higher from Monday to meet a firm bid from a local trader who did not purchase any cargoes, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>However, the market believed that the local trader would continue to buy for another week which provided some cheer to trading firms who have large volumes of arbitrage cargoes.</p>
<p>The trader, who has bought nearly seven million barrels over the past one month, pushed his bid higher for an April 18-22 lifting cargo to $27.20 per barrel free-on-board basis.  </p>
<p>But traders noted that the four cargoes which the trader bought on Monday between $26.50 and $26.80 was for a later period in April.</p>
<p>Sellers emerged with offers for April 25-29 at $26.90 per barrel and for earlier timings at $27.10-$27.25.</p>
<p>The firmer tone on the gas oil market was also seen on swaps with April gaining 40-45 cent per barrel from a day earlier to be last quoted at $26.30/$26.40. The swaps players were also bullish that the local trader would remain to support prices for some time.  </p>
<p>The jet/gas oil regrade has fallen further with April seen at minus 60/40 cents on Tuesday from minus 50/30 cents.</p>
<p>The spiralling swaps regrade was reflected on physical barrels with an offer of April 25-30 jet fuel at $25.30 a barrel, with buyers remaining at bay.</p>
<p>Traders were waiting for some direction from Nepal's kerosene tender May delivery which was expected to be awarded later on Tuesday. The lowest offer was seen at $206 per tonne cost-and-freight Indian east coast, much lower than in the last tender for March delivery at $235-$240 per tonne.  </p>
<p>The best offer into Nepal's 1.0-percent sulphur diesel tender was seen at around $192-$193 per tonne, c-and-f east coast, also lower than the $202.75 per tonne awarded in the previous tender for March delivery.</p>
<p>Taiwan's jet fuel tender for May delivery closes on Tuesday and was expected to be awarded on Wednesday at much lower levels than in the last tender for end April delivery, traders said.</p>
<p>(Prices in dollars per barrel)</p>
<p> MTH FOB SIN		     BUY/SELL     PREV BUY/SELL</p>
<p> MAR JET KEROSENE/KERO     25.00/25.30	 25.30/25.60</p>
<p> MAR GAS OIL 0.5% S	  26.60/27.10	 26.50/26.90</p>
<p> APR JET/GAS OIL SWAPS	-0.60/-0.40	-0.50/0.20</p>
<p> APR GAS OIL SWAPS	   26.30/26.40	 25.85/26.00</p>
<p> MAY GAS OIL SWAPS	   25.25/25.35	 25.00/25.20</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3084)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
