<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478859" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: PRESS DIGEST - Australian General News - April 2.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Australian General News - April 2.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW</p>
<p>Victorian Treasurer Alan Stockdale argued yesterday for a change to the State Government's original plan for the electricity industry, saying instead of keeping the State's high-voltage electricity grid, PowerNet Victoria, as a &quot;natural&quot; monopoly, it should privatised by the end of the year in a sale which could raise more than A$1.5 billion. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Speaking at a symposium in Beijing yesterday, Prime Minister John Howard called on the Federal Opposition to provide bipartisan support for the major overhaul of Australia's financial system expected to result from the release next week of the Wallis Report. His comments come amid increased signs that the Coalition could face problems in the Senate implementing some of the more drastic reforms. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Following accusations from service providers that Telstra is limiting competition and damaging their industry by failing to solve problems with the billing system FLEXCABS, the national carrier announced last night it would file a new service level guarantee tomorrow with industry regulator Austel to lessen the time taken to transfer customer accounts and to provide more accurate bills. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard's plan to repair Australia's strained relationship with China on his visit appears to be proving successful, with Chinese President Jiang Zemin agreeing yesterday to upgrade political, military and economic links with Australia,especially between economic ministers and officials. Page 5.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN</p>
<p>Following his meeting with China's President Jiang Zemin, Prime Minister John Howard said in a press conference yesterday the Chinese Government is not 'unhappy' with Australia's defence alliance with the US. There was also optimistic signs Chinese officals are willing to re-open talks on the sensitive human fights issue with Howard. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Victorian Minister Health Rob Knowles has announced the State Government has ordered a police investigation into the State's ambulance service after a draft report by Auditor-General Ches Baragwanath raised serious concerns to the Government involving the intergraph communications system and irregularities in contractual and tendering arrangements. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Federal Attorney-General Daryl Williams is considering devising a new classification covering non-violent erotica after extensive Cabinet discussions yesterday. The backdown comes after heated criticism from the ACT Government, and would be an alternative to the total banning of the X-rated industry, one of the Coalition's election promises. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Australian wheat industry received further good news yesterday with reports wheat growers will receive an extra A$3 a tonne for their produce. Wheat exporters have sold nearly 15 million tonnes of wheat to overseas markets, three quarters of this yeas' expected crop. Page 3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD</p>
<p>New South Wales Legal Services Commissioner Steve Mark says the State Government's deregulation of the legal service in 1994 may have disadvantaged consumers rather than helping them, after he found legal charges in the State are so high many people cannot afford a lawyer. His report shows many lawyers are breaching the law and are failing to give people an estimate of potential costs. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The worst drop of the American Dow Jones since the Gulf War in 1990 has sent Australia's stock market tumbling, as A$10.6 billion was wiped of the value of Australian shares. The fall is Australia's biggest since March last year, with the All Ordinaries ndex falling to 70.1 points to 2352.2. Page 1</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard has defended his decision not to directly raise the issue of Australia's US alliance with Chinese Government officials yesterday, despite it being the key reason for strained diplomatic relations last year. However, on his final day in china, Howard won agreement for improved military contracts in what is seen as a counterbalance to Australia's ties with America. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Australian cricket captain has Mark Taylor has admitted his is &quot;disturbed&quot; over his recent poor form and has dropped himself for tonight's one day match against South Africa in Cape Town. Taylor says he only regards the seven one day games as &quot;free hits&quot; but says his decision to drop himself should have no bearing on his selection as Australian captain for the up-coming tour of England. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE</p>
<p>The Victorian Government has ordered an investigation into allegations that official guidelines were breached and excess payments made under Metropolitan Ambulance Service contracts in the lead-up to Intergraph winning a contract to provide a computer disatch system for ambulances. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Just hours after Prime Minister John Howard claimed success in announcing China has agreed to boost military, political and bureaucratic contacts with Australia, the Chinese Government made it clear last night Howard's proposal for a dialogue on human rigts may be rejected, saying Australia must abandon its &quot;confrontational&quot; stance as a precondition to future talks on the issue. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Veteran Australian Football League player, Carlton's Greg Williams, was charged by the League yesterday with interfering with umpire Andrew Coates in Monday's game against Essendon at the Melbourne Cricket Ground. Williams' appearance before the AFL Tribunal tonight will be his eighteenth, and if he is found guilty, he may face a lengthy suspension. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Lyle Doniger, one of three Australians sentenced yesterday to a 50-year sentence in Thailand's Kiong Prem Prison, spent his first night in the infamous &quot;Bangkok Hilton&quot; last night in a five-metre by 10-metre cell he shares with 60 other prisoners. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
