<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478855" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil police arrested after TV film shows killing.</title>
<headline>Brazil police arrested after TV film shows killing.</headline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>A group of Brazilian military police officers was arrested on Monday after Globo television aired amateur video footage allegedly showing Sao Paulo police killing a civilian, extorting money and beating motorists with batons.</p>
<p>The film, taken over several nights in the suburbs of greater Sao Paulo, allegedly shows military police setting up a roadblock ostensibly to check identity papers and car documents in a hunt for drug traffickers.</p>
<p>The leader of the operation, identified by Globo through his nickname &quot;Rambo&quot;, was shown hitting drivers and passengers of stopped cars with his baton and strolling around with a gun in his hand.</p>
<p>One man was beaten and taken behind a wall. A few minutes later, a shot was heard. it was not clear if the man was killed.</p>
<p>Video footage taken a few nights later when another roadblock was set up in the same place allegedly showed officers taking bribes from drivers.</p>
<p>After beating up the occupants of one car, &quot;Rambo&quot; was filmed firing twice into the back of the vehicle as it drove away. Globo said a passenger was hit and died later in hospital.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Military Police Headquarters in Sao Paulo said several police officers were arrested on Monday night pending an investigation after the television station showed officials the video, which was aired publicly on Monday night.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment the General Command of the Military Police in Sao Paulo is meeting to decide what to do,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Human rights groups say police violence plagues Brazil's larger cities, especially Rio de Janeiro and Sao Paulo.</p>
<p>U.S. group Human Rights Watch/Americas issued a report in December severely criticising the impunity police enjoy in Brazil but praising the efforts of President Fernando Henrique Cardoso's government to protect human rights.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
