<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478804" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico Cetes rate inches down on stable peso.</title>
<headline>Mexico Cetes rate inches down on stable peso.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexican overnight Cetes rates opened down 10 basis points at 21.90 percent on Monday on an early recovery in the peso, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;The peso is trading well and that is a clear sign that current (domestic) interest rates are attractive,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Benchmark 48-hour peso contracts rebounded from an initial slide to stand unchanged in early trade, at 7.9090/7.9140 per dollar.</p>
<p>Traders said the peso recovered as pressure eased from the U.S. bond market.  </p>
<p>The U.S. 30-year Treasury bond was up 9/32 in early trade to yield 7.08 percent, in what traders said was a response to data published by the National Association of Purchasing Managers.</p>
<p>Overnight rates on bank paper meanwhile stood unchanged at 23.40 percent, after an initial surge to 23.70 percent.</p>
<p>A money market analyst said international investor interest in the market had also helped to ease pressure on overnight Cetes rates.</p>
<p>&quot;Holdings and positions by international investors have held very steady,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Liquidity of 2.471 billion pesos was programmed to return to the system from prior central bank participation.</p>
<p>Dealers said they had revised earlier estimated of liquidity flows as Banco de Mexico held an overnight secondary auction late Monday for 200 million pesos, which it assigned at 23.59 percent. ((--Elena Vega, Mexico City newsroom +525 728-9554))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
