<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478886" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: PRESS DIGEST - Hong Kong newspaper headlines - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Hong Kong newspaper headlines - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Hong Kong press on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>-- MING PAO -- About 200 unarmed Chinese soliders might come to Hong Kong this month to carry out preparation work ahead of the handover on June 30. Sources said the British side had been trying to postpone the signing of the agreement on People's Liberation Army advance troops to force China to give in over the issue of right of abode.</p>
<p>-- Taiwanese authorities decided to investigate the planned investment in a Chinese power plant by Taiwan's biggest industrial conglomerate, Formosa Plastics Group.</p>
<p>-- WEN WEI PO -- Australian Prime Minister John Howard said China and Australia would establish a pragmatic and effective partner relationship.</p>
<p>-- China released its 1996 Human Rights White Paper, summarising its human rights achievements last year. The document stressed that the government always gave priority to people's rights to survive and develop.</p>
<p>-- ECONOMIC JOURNAL -- The shares of several companies involved in the garment retailing business in China have fallen in recent months due to a weak garment market.</p>
<p>-- HONGKONG STANDARD -- A veiled challenge to President Jiang Zemin's authority over the three-million-strong People's Liberation Army had been thrown down by China's number three, Qiao Shi, in an interview with a French newspaper.</p>
<p>-- China was considering allowing the Special Administrative Region government to set up an office in Taiwan to handle visa arrangements for Taiwanese people going to Hong Kong. The idea was said to be acceptable to Taipei.</p>
<p>-- SOUTH CHINA MORNING POST -- According to a top aide of Chief Executive-designate Tung Chee-hwa, there was no need and no place for a &quot;commissar&quot; or political adviser to liaise with China because Tung had substantial contacts with Chinese leaders.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6441</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
