<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478800" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: France, Chile look to boost trade, cultural ties.</title>
<headline>France, Chile look to boost trade, cultural ties.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO, Chile 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chile and France will concentrate on strengthening trade and cultural ties during President Eduardo Frei's visit to Paris next week, French Ambassador Gerard Cros said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;For us the first emphasis is to increase France's economic presence in this country, which is not bad but could be better,&quot; Cros told reporters after a meeting with Foreign Minister Jose Miguel Insulza. &quot;I believe President Frei's speeches in Paris will be very useful to convince French businessmen to invest here.&quot;</p>
<p>Frei will visit France from April 10-11, holding talks with French President Jacques Chirac and addressing the French chamber of commerce. His trip comes just weeks after a high-profile visit by Chirac to Latin America, including stops in Brazil and Argentina, which was aimed at boosting French trade and investment in the region.</p>
<p>The two leaders will sign at least eight bilateral accords including agreements between both countries' diplomatic academies, on technical co-operation and television.</p>
<p>France is Chile's fourth largest trading partner in Europe with bilateral trade totalling nearly $1 billion in 1995. The balance is in favour of Chile. Main Chilean exports to France include copper, fresh fruit and seafood.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO, Chile"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
