<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478861" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: TIMELINES-Today in History - April 2.</title>
<headline>TIMELINES-Today in History - April 2.</headline>
<text>
<p>** BIRTHDAYS **</p>
<p>Danish writer of Fairy Tales, HANS CHRISTIAN ANDERSEN, was born on this day in 1805.</p>
<p>British actor SIR ALEC GUINNESS, who won an Oscar for &quot;The Bridge On The River Kwai&quot;, was born in 1914.</p>
<p>Australian world champion motor racing driver SIR JOHN ARTHUR (JACK) BRABHAM was born at Hurstville in Sydney in 1926. In 1959 he became the first Australian to take out the World Drivers' Championship, repeating the feat in 1960 and 1966. He was Australian Champion in 1955, 1963, and 1964, and was knighted in 1979.</p>
<p>American soul singer MARVIN GAYE was born in 1939.  </p>
<p>American country and pop singer EMMYLOU HARRIS was born in 1948.</p>
<p>US singer with 'Bananarama' KEREN JANE WOODWARD was born in 1963. Their first record appeared in 1981. Hits included &quot;Really Saying Something&quot; (1982), &quot;Shy Boy&quot; (1982), &quot;Cruel Summer&quot; (1983), &quot;Venus&quot; (1986), &quot;Love In The First Degree&quot; (1987), &quot;I Want You Back&quot; (1988) and &quot;Help&quot; (1989).  </p>
<p>				** EVENTS **</p>
<p>    1792 :    The first 'silver dollar' of America's new</p>
<p>currency was struck in Philadelphia.</p>
<p>    1810 :    NAPOLEON BONAPARTE married MARIE LOUISE, daughter</p>
<p>of the Austrian Emperor.  </p>
<p>    1821 :    CHARLES THROSBY explored the Molonglo and</p>
<p>Queanbeyan regions of New South Wales, calling the area the 'Limestone Plains'.</p>
<p>    1873 :    Toilets were fitted to British trains for the</p>
<p>first time, but only in sleeper carriages.</p>
<p>    1921 :    The IRA bought its first consignment of 'Tommy</p>
<p>Guns' (machine guns) from the United States.  </p>
<p>    1938 :    The Spannish civil war ended.</p>
<p>    1949 :    Neon signs were switched on again in Britain after</p>
<p>a ten year ban. The ban was introduced at the start of World War II.</p>
<p>    1953 :    A new vegetable went on sale in Australia.</p>
<p>Melbourne greengrocers were selling the aubergine or eggplant.  </p>
<p>    1961 :    The Aboriginal Advancement Council decided to</p>
<p>protest to all Federal MPs about apartheid in Australia.</p>
<p>    1974 :    French President GEORGES POMPIDOU died.</p>
<p>    1977 :    British racehorse RED RUM became the first horse</p>
<p>ever to win 3 Grand Nationals (previous victories 1973, 1974).  </p>
<p>    1978 :    One of the brightest stars of the Australian</p>
<p>entertainment scene, GLORIA DAWN, (who began performing in Melbourne at the age of 2 and throughout her career refused to use bad language on stage) died.</p>
<p>    1979 :    Mass graves were found in the &quot;killing fields&quot; of</p>
<p>Cambodia, bringing fears that up to a million people may have died during POL POT's Khmer Rouge communist regime. POL POT had conducted a 3-year 'experiment' to take Cambodians back to &quot;Year Zero&quot;, forcing city people to live in the countryside and killing all opponents to his ideological purism.  </p>
<p>    1982 :    Argentinian forces took control of the Falkland</p>
<p>Islands, ordering British Marines in the capital Port Stanley to surrender.</p>
<p>    1987 :    The controversial Australia Card was thrown out by</p>
<p>the Senate.</p>
<p>    1991 :    Soviet coal miners staged a strike across the</p>
<p>USSR.  </p>
<p>    1991 :    British businessman ROGER COOPER was freed from an</p>
<p>Iranian prison, after serving half his 10-year sentence for alleged spying.</p>
<p>    1991 :    DIEGO MARADONA flew home to Argentina, just hours</p>
<p>before being banned from playing sport in Italy for failing a drug test.  </p>
<p>(Compiled from ABC ARCHIVES, ABC RADIO NATIONAL, &quot;On This Day&quot; published by REED INTERNATIONAL BOOKS LIMITED, &quot;The Chronicle Of The 20th Century&quot; published by PENGUIN BOOKS and &quot;Rock And Pop (Day By Day)&quot; published by BLANDFORD BOOKS.)</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
