<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478901" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Cambodian PM calls for referendum on monarchy.</title>
<headline>Cambodian PM calls for referendum on monarchy.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cambodian co-Premier Norodom Ranariddh on Tuesday called for a referendum on the thorny question of whether to keep the country's popular monarchy.</p>
<p>Prince Ranariddh, son of King Norodom Sihanouk, said he had no immediate designs on the throne but that the Cambodian people should decide the issue.</p>
<p>The monarchy question has driven a wedge in Ranariddh's fragile coalition government with co-Premier Hun Sen, who has sought to curb the monarchy's political influence.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to organise a referendum. We have to ask the people's will,&quot; he said, adding he believed there was broad support for the monarchy.</p>
<p>Hun Sen said in mid-March he would cancel general elections expected in November 1998 if the highly popular king abdicated to take part in politics.</p>
<p>Ranariddh's royalist FUNCINPEC party and Hun Sen's ex-communist Cambodian People's Party are expected to oppose each other in the next election.</p>
<p>Ranariddh, speaking in an interview with Reuters, said he wanted to concentrate on politics with a goal of becoming the sole prime minister after national polls.</p>
<p>&quot;No one for the time being can really take care of (my) royalist FUNCINPEC party...,&quot; he said. &quot;My objective is to be the next prime minister and the only prime minister.&quot;</p>
<p>The current uneasy coalition was formed after U.N.-sponsored elections in 1993.</p>
<p>Hun Sen has said he would ask Sihanouk to ban members of Cambodia's royal family from politics unless they renounced their royal titles, a proposal Ranariddh has called unconstitutional.</p>
<p>Ranariddh said he would ask Hun Sen to reconsider his position on the monarchy and said the most likely solution to their differences was a referendum after the wishes of the king, who recently advised the government to take up the problem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
