<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478967" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesia palm olein stable in late trade.</title>
<headline>Indonesia palm olein stable in late trade.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesian palm olein prices were generally stable in late trading on Tuesday, with a lack of fresh leads keeping a lid on demand, traders said.</p>
<p>They said palm olein was quoted at 1,395-1,400 rupiah/kg in Jakarta, unchanged from the opening, but offers were also heard at 1,390 rupiah. Crude palm oil was done at 1,231 rupiah/kg at a tender in the North Sumatran city of Medan on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Trading was sluggish in the absence of fresh news,&quot; one trader said. &quot;Buyers are only taking what they need immediately, preferring instead to wait for developments.&quot;  </p>
<p>Traders said they expected local palm olein prices to hover around the current level through the week, but added that there was pressure from players with ample stocks.</p>
<p>&quot;One player with 2,000 tonnes of imported RBD palm oil is selling below the market range,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Data from Belawan Port showed that the MT Kraton will leave the North Sumatran port on Tuesday with 2,000 tonnes of palm olein for Semarang.</p>
<p>-- K.T. Arasu, Jakarta newsroom + 6221 384-6364</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
