<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478904" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Gingrich vow to defend Taiwan lacks teeth - analysts.</title>
<headline>Gingrich vow to defend Taiwan lacks teeth - analysts.</headline>
<byline>Lawrence Chung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Taiwan government, eager to court U.S. support against arch rival China, is expected to roll out the red carpet for Newt Gingrich when the controversial U.S. House speaker arrives on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But Taiwan analysts said Gingrich's three-hour visit and his defiant vow to defend the island against a potential mainland Chinese attack had more to do with U.S. party politics than righteous sympathy for Taiwan's diplomatic isolation.</p>
<p>Still, both Taiwan and China stood to make gains through Gingrich's visits, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;His tough talks in mainland China were aimed to increase his popularity by showing he had guts and strong moral obligations for the democratic Taiwan,&quot; said Hu Fo, a law professor at National Taiwan University.</p>
<p>During his visit to China in late March, Gingrich was quoted as telling Chinese officials that the United States would defend Taiwan against a mainland attack. He also publicly criticised China for human rights abuse.</p>
<p>While Gingrich sought to take the moral highground abroad, his popularity back in the U.S. had fallen recently due to alleged ethics abuses for which the House voted earlier in 1997 to fine him US$300,000.</p>
<p>&quot;His (Gingrich's) tough statements... were meant for Americans back home rather than for cross-strait governments,&quot; said Chang Lin-chen, professor of political science at National Taiwan University.</p>
<p>She said Gingrich's defiance against China may help win support from some conservative Republicans in the U.S., and strengthen his speakership in the House.</p>
<p>The White House, seeking to defuse Gingrich's comments lest they would threaten a gradual improvement in U.S.-China ties, on Monday downplayed his tough talks by saying they did not represent the views of the U.S. government.</p>
<p>Gingrich was &quot;speaking for himself,&quot; when commenting on U.S. policies toward China, White House spokesman Mike McCurry said.</p>
<p>Analysts said China's reaction to Gingrich's remarks was mild because Beijing was able to extract certain gains from the his visit.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically, the Chinese communists are trying to compete with Taiwan in winning support from both the House and Senate. It was already a small victory for the mainland to have Gingrich come for a visit,&quot; Professor Chang said.</p>
<p>Professor Hu said Taiwan, which has spent years trying to woo Congressional support, was eager to host Gingrich, even for only three hours.</p>
<p>&quot;Gingrich's Taiwan trip means the government's efforts to improve relations with U.S. congressmen is not wasted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Taiwan and China have been political rivals since they split after a civil war ended in 1949. The U.S. switched formal diplomatic recognition to Beijing from Taipei in 1979, but maintains a right to arm and even defend Taiwan against Chinese threats.</p>
<p>China regards Taiwan as a renegade province and vows to reclaim it one day, by force if necessary.</p>
<p>A western diplomat in Taiwan said Gingrich is known to waver on Taiwan despite his recent tough words.</p>
<p>&quot;It would not be surprising in his upcoming meeting with (Taiwan President) Lee Teng-hui if Gingrich embarrasses the president by demanding that Taiwan not seek independence,&quot; the diplomat said.</p>
<p>Gingrich is scheduled to meet with Lee on Wednesday immediately after he arrives in Taipei. He is also scheduled to have lunch with Vice President Lien Chan before ending his three-hour trip.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
