<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478996" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan oil sector faces tough second year of reform.</title>
<headline>Japan oil sector faces tough second year of reform.</headline>
<byline>Miho Yoshikawa</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>There is little relief in sight for Japan's battered oil companies as they enter the second year of market deregulation, industry analysts say.</p>
<p>Many analysts said some of the companies will face a real challenge to survive in 1997, a year after oil refiners lost their exclusive right to import oil products on April 1, 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be rough this year. The real test (for the companies) will come this year and next year,&quot; said Toshinori Ito, Daiwa Institute of Research senior analyst.</p>
<p>Market deregulation forced the oil industry to introduce changes and take steps to streamline, but the measures have not been enough to bail the industry out of its difficulties.</p>
<p>Gasoline prices -- previously set artificially higher than most other oil products -- have fallen since oil refiners introduced a new wholesale pricing system last spring. The corresponding increase in gas oil and kerosene prices have not been high enough to offset the drop in revenue.</p>
<p>Nikko Research Centre analyst Takashi Kawai said the sales margins on gasoline fell by 10 yen (about eight cents) per litre in the fiscal year which ended on March 31 compared with a year earlier.</p>
<p>Given that about 50 million kilolitres (kl) of gasoline is sold in Japan every year, that means the industry lost profits of 500 billion yen ($4.03 billion) in gasoline sales alone, he said.</p>
<p>Kawai said the oil industry faced structural problems, including too much refining capacity.</p>
<p>Japan also has too many petrol stations which has led to cut-throat competition and thin margins. Analysts expect the current number of petrol stations, 60,000, to be reduced to about 38,000 by 2005.</p>
<p>But it will cost about up to 40 million yen ($322,000) for a refiner to close each station it owns.</p>
<p>In addition, the oil companies have not yet faced the full onslaught of cheaper oil product imports, as a weaker yen and relatively expensive overseas oil product prices made importing an unattractive venture.</p>
<p>&quot;We didn't see more firms importing last year because it wasn't profitable,&quot; Daiwa's Ito said, adding it would grow given the right business conditions.</p>
<p>Imports of refined products rose 13.9 percent year-on-year in 1996 to 40.5 million kl. The increase was largely seen in imports of kerosene due to a cold spell. Gasoline imports, which were expected to increase sharply, fell by 13.7 percent.</p>
<p>Analysts also said the post-deregulation era could see several mergers or tie-ups.</p>
<p>In February, Japan's fifth and sixth largest oil distributors -- Showa Shell Sekiyu KK and Mitsubishi Oil Co Ltd -- said they were studying a possible merger of their oil refining and distributing divisions.</p>
<p>Giant oil refiners Nippon Oil Co Ltd and Idemitsu Kosan Co Ltd already have cooperative ties in such areas as distribution, and Ito said the ties could increase once Nippon Oil begins producing gasoline with the same benzene content as Idemitsu, which is expected to happen within the next year.</p>
<p>($1=124 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
