<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478913" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Exiled Tiananmen activist granted Taiwan residency.</title>
<headline>Exiled Tiananmen activist granted Taiwan residency.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan has granted permanent residency to Chinese dissident Wuerkaixi, who shot to fame in Beijing's 1989 Tiananmen Square pro-democracy protests and fled into exile after they were crushed.</p>
<p>&quot;The Mainland Affairs Council has agreed to let Wuerkaixi stay in Taiwan permanently,&quot; an official of the cabinet's top China policymaking body told Reuters by telephone.</p>
<p>The official said Wuerkaixi was not the first mainland dissident granted Taiwan residency, but he would not name others.</p>
<p>The United Evening News said Wuerkaixi's case had been approved because Taiwan recognised his &quot;outstanding achievement in leading the pro-democracy movement&quot; and because he may face unspecified imminent danger.</p>
<p>The government has maintained a low-profile in handling Wuerkaixi's application to avoid further angering Beijing, which has viewed the island as a renegade province since a civil war spilt them in 1949, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>As a student, Wuerkaixi was one of the most outspoken leaders of the Tiananmen Square pro-democracy movement that swept China in May and June of 1989.</p>
<p>The ethnic Uighur student from China's far western Xinjiang province sprang to fame in May 1989 when he argued with Chinese Premier Li Peng in a televised meeting with student leaders who were demanding greater democracy in China.</p>
<p>After China's army crushed the demonstrations on June 3-4, 1989, with the death of hundreds, Wuerkaixi fled into exile and was granted political asylum in the United States.</p>
<p>He married a Taiwanese woman in August 1994 and recently has been hosting a television interview show.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
