<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478912" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan's MOF defends bank restructuring plans.</title>
<headline>Japan's MOF defends bank restructuring plans.</headline>
<byline>Linda Sieg</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Japanese Finance Ministry official on Tuesday defended a plan to restructure troubled Nippon Credit Bank Ltd as a move which would benefit other financial institutions as well as help soothe market jitters.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a convoy system at all,&quot; the official told reporters and a large group of analysts from foreign brokerages and banks. &quot;We are asking cooperation of several financial institutions which are beneficiaries of this restructuring plan.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They understand why we are asking their cooperation but psychologically there is some reluctance, I don't deny that. However, theoretically they are the beneficiaries of this bailout plan, they understand that,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Nippon Credit Bank (NCB), one of the nation's wobbliest banks and the smallest of Japan's three long-term credit banks, announced on Tuesday that it would restructure, halting overseas operations, selling off its Tokyo headquarters and posting losses to dispose of problem loans.</p>
<p>Separately, Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd, Japan's 10th biggest commercial bank, and regional bank Hokkaido Bank Ltd, both based in Sapporo, announced they would merge next April and withdraw from overseas operations by next March.</p>
<p>Analysts said the NCB restructuring plan was insufficient to solve the bank's big bad-loan woes and would also place an unfortunate burden on stronger, healthier banks.</p>
<p>They also said the merger of the Hokkaido-based banks would not succeed in solving their underlying bad loan problems.</p>
<p>The finance ministry official, however, said both moves would help ease market anxiety while the withdrawal of both from overseas operations would show market forces were at work.</p>
<p>&quot;We think these are significant steps to stabilise the market,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;The withdrawal from international markets of these two banks shows that the stronger banks stay in the world market, so in that sense this is a kind of restructuring (of the industry).&quot;</p>
<p>The official said the ministry hoped to hear from other banks about their response to the scheme by June, when NCB holds its annual shareholders' meeting.</p>
<p>He repeated Japanese authorities' commitment not to let the nation's top international banks fail, but said other banks might &quot;quietly withdraw&quot; from overseas markets if they faced serious problems.</p>
<p>&quot;If anything happens to them, quiet withdrawal will be implemented by cooperation between Japanese banks and Japanese authorities,&quot; he said, adding that he did not think that any of the nation's top 20 banks were &quot;insolvent.&quot;</p>
<p>A decision on whether to rescue banks with purely domestic operations will depend in future on the potential risk to the financial system and damage to other institutions, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;For the domestic market, we have a very solid principle -- if one bank's problems may cause a chain reaction or may cause financial system risk, then we will make the utmost effort to prevent that situation from happening.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
