<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478911" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Gingrich's Asia tour puts spotlight on Taiwan.</title>
<headline>Gingrich's Asia tour puts spotlight on Taiwan.</headline>
<byline>Alice Hung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A whirlwind Asian tour by blunt-speaking U.S. congressional chief Newt Gingrich has put the spotlight on Taiwan-China frictions, seen by Beijing as the chief irritant in U.S.-China ties.</p>
<p>The hubbub that has followed Gingrich to South Korea, Hong Kong, China and Japan was expected to grow louder in Taiwan on Wednesday with the speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives insisting on seeing the island and its leaders first-hand.</p>
<p>Gingrich was to meet President Lee Teng-hui and lunch with Vice President Lien Chan during a three-hour visit.</p>
<p>Differences over Taiwan have long been a major irritant to the sensitive Sino-U.S. relationship, already battered by disputes over human rights, copyright piracy and trade.</p>
<p>Gingrich strode boldly into the fray, saying that he had told China's communist leaders that Washington would defend Taiwan from a Chinese attack -- a statement that sent U.S. officials running for cover.</p>
<p>The U.S. State Department took pains to say Gingrich was &quot;speaking for himself&quot; and that U.S. policy stops short of any commitment to defend Taiwan, though Secretary of State Madeleine Albright said a Chinese attack would be a &quot;grave concern&quot;.</p>
<p>China nonetheless lashed out on Tuesday, warning Washington not to interfere in Chinese dealings with Taiwan and urging it to halt sales of large-scale high-technology arms to Taipei.</p>
<p>&quot;The issue of Taiwan between China and the United States is just one issue, that of non-interference in China's internal affairs,&quot; Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Shen Guofang told a news briefing in Beijing.</p>
<p>&quot;We are always for peaceful reunification with Taiwan, but if a situation of independence occurs in Taiwan or foreign forces interfere in Taiwan, then we will take other necessary measures,&quot; he said, restating longstanding Chinese policy.</p>
<p>Beijing has considered Taiwan a rebel province since the defeated Nationalist government fled there in 1949 and vows to retake the island by force if it declares independence or if foreign forces interfere there.</p>
<p>Shen hinted that Washington already was crossing the line.</p>
<p>&quot;The large amount of U.S. weapons sales to Taiwan to a certain degree supports and connives at Taiwan separatist forces and hampers the process of peaceful reunification,&quot; Shen said.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope the United States will take the stance of not interfering in China's internal affairs on the Taiwan issue, and even more that it will not make large sales of advanced weapons,&quot; Shen said.</p>
<p>A fledgling democracy that in 1996 held the first popular presidential election in Chinese history, Taiwan espouses reunification but not before Beijing itself embraces democracy and ends the Communist Party dictatorship.</p>
<p>In what Taiwan officials called a coincidence, the island test-fired two U.S. Hawk missiles in the Taiwan strait on Tuesday in an exercise seen as bolstering defences against China.</p>
<p>Taiwan hailed the continuing supply of U.S. munitions, which include Patriot antimissile missiles and advanced F-16 fighter jets but not the submarines that Taipei hoped to buy.</p>
<p>&quot;Normally, we would not comment on any ongoing arms deal, but for any deal which can help increase our defence needs or maintain peace and stability in a region, we are pleased to have it struck,&quot; said military spokesman Kung Fan-ting.</p>
<p>Kung declined comment on a report by the state-run Central News Agency that Washington had agreed to sell Taiwan 54 AGM-84A Harpoon missiles and 21 Super Cobra attack helicopters, while turning down a request for submarines.</p>
<p>Washington recognised Beijing's communist government in 1979, breaking off ties with Taiwan's exiled Republic of China to do so, but maintains a right to arm the capitalist redoubt.</p>
<p>In a clear signal, Washington sent two aircraft carriers to the region when Beijing mounted what it acknowledged were intimidating war games in waters near Taiwan during the island's historic March 1996 presidential election.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
