<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478968" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Formosa sparks debate on Taiwan's China policy.</title>
<headline>Formosa sparks debate on Taiwan's China policy.</headline>
<byline>Alice Hung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan's cautious investment policy towards China came under fire on Tuesday following cancellation of a major mainland project, with analysts and lawmakers urging more liberalisation despite political risks.</p>
<p>They also criticised the government for failing to enact clear guidelines for investment in rival China, a shortcoming exposed by Formosa Plastics' decision to drop a power plant project.</p>
<p>&quot;Local businesses are told to refrain from temptation and adopt patience. The question is, how long should they wait?&quot; legislator Chen Ching-pao of the ruling Nationalist Party asked parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;The government's mainland policy is ambiguous,&quot; said lawmaker Chen Chiung-tsan. &quot;It lacks concrete and detailed planning. What is more, the government does not give local businesses a clear direction.&quot;</p>
<p>After a day of uncertainty over the fate of the US$3 billion thermal power station in China's Fujian province, Formosa said on Monday it would respect the government's policy and abandon the giant investment.</p>
<p>Taiwan Economic Minister Wang Chih-kang told reporters that Taiwan had no intention of allowing Formosa to finance the plant, urging Taiwan firms to consider &quot;social responsibility&quot; when investing in the mainland.</p>
<p>Taipei is concerned that its prosperous economy could become too dependent on the mainland, thereby leaving the island politically vulnerable. Some 30,000 Taiwan businesses have poured more than US$30 billion into China since an unofficial thaw in ties began in the 1980s.</p>
<p>Communist China has regarded Nationalist-ruled Taiwan as a renegade province since a civil war split them in 1949, vowing to retake the island by force if necessary.</p>
<p>Taiwan forbids direct China investments, obliging firms to route even small investments through Hong Kong or other third territories after obtaining permits from the Economic Ministry.</p>
<p>An opinion poll conducted by the Mainland Affairs Council, Taiwan's top policymaking body towards China, showed more than 50 percent of Taiwan people supported a tougher China policy amid communist leaders' hostility against the island.</p>
<p>Echoing the government's caution, lawmaker Lee Chin-yung of the pro-independence Democratic Progressive Party, compared Taiwan investors' &quot;mainland fever&quot; to the recent outbreak of a deadly and highly contagious hog disease on the island.</p>
<p>&quot;The government should demonstrate the same determination to terminate the economic foot-and-mouth disease as it did on the hog foot-and-mouth disease,&quot; Lee said.</p>
<p>But some analysts said the government's cautious attitude towards China investment could dampen business confidence.</p>
<p>The mass circulation United Daily News questioned the government's very commitment to a free economy.</p>
<p>&quot;The government has not had clear guidelines to govern Taiwan businesses' investment in the mainland,&quot; the newspaper said. &quot;But it wastes no time to scare companies after their mainland investment projects are made public.</p>
<p>&quot;How can Taiwan claim to be liberalised and internationalised? How can Taiwan's environment be fit for investment?&quot; the daily asked.</p>
<p>Formosa Plastics on Monday appealed to the government not to adopt policies that jeopardised Taiwan's economic growth.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan should continue to step up efforts at internationalisation and liberalisation in order to attain continuous growth,&quot; the company said. &quot;Economic growth is more important to Taiwan than to other countries.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
