<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478980" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore shares rally off new low, end up.</title>
<headline>Singapore shares rally off new low, end up.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Tuesday afternoon rally spurred by improved sentiment for Wall Street and blue chip bargain hunting saw Singapore shares claw back an 18-point plunge to end the day slightly firmer.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a bit of concensus this afternoon that the Dow might rebound after falling 300 points over the last two trading days so that helped move the index up,&quot; a local dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a bit of bargain hunting going on -- I don't think this is the start of a major rebound,&quot; another said.</p>
<p>At Tuesday's end, Singapore's key Straits Times Industrials Index was up 1.67 on Monday's close to stand at 2,074.67.</p>
<p>The rally, following a plunge to a new year low of 2,055.41, was fuelled by blue chip counters led by Fraser &amp; Neave, up Singapore $0.40 at S$12.20, and Keppel Corp up S$0.15 at S$9.25.</p>
<p>Singapore Press foreign stock was top of 140 gainers, up S$0.60 to S$26.90 largely on positive news about Singapore's newly liberalising telecommunications market in which the firm has a stake in a cellular and paging network.</p>
<p>Leading 240 losers was UOB Bank's foreign share tranche, down S$0.60 at S$14.40.</p>
<p>Total traded volume on Tuesday was a thin 143.0 million shares.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
