<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478938" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila's Premiere eyes Orion distribution rights.</title>
<headline>Manila's Premiere eyes Orion distribution rights.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippines' Premiere Entertainment Productions Inc said on Tuesday it is negotiating with US-based Orion Pictures Corp to be the exclusive distributor of its films in the country.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a possibility that we will close a deal with Orion for the distribution of their films here. We're trying to get that exclusive right to distribute their films here,&quot; Premiere chairman Espiridion Laxa told reporters at the start of its initial public offering (IPO) roadshow.</p>
<p>Premiere is set to submit its final proposal to Orion soon, he said.</p>
<p>Premiere is the first movie production company seeking a listing on the Philippine Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>Premiere is selling 180 million common shares, or 34.62 percent of the company, to the public at one peso apiece starting April 2.</p>
<p>This year, the company has earmarked 148 million pesos to produce 10 to 12 feature films, comptroller Susan Alpasan Tan said.</p>
<p>The company is projected to post a 17.388 million peso net income this year against a net loss of 14.418 million pesos last year after it produced four movies, two of which were dismal flops.</p>
<p>&quot;Premiere is going through a process of transition. It hibernated for so many years ... (But) the management is catching up with the trend,&quot; Laxa said.</p>
<p>The company aims to produce films which would be exhibited abroad. It has so far co-produced two films, one with Paramount Pictures, to be shown commercially in other countries.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't have plans to gain supremacy in the industry ... We just want to have our place, a prominent place in the movie industry. We are serious in going global,&quot; Laxa added.</p>
<p>Laxa also said the company is looking at the possibility of venturing into the television business.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a possiblity that we will be involved in managing a new television company ... Negotiations are ongoing now,&quot; he added, but declined to give specifics.</p>
<p>The IPO is to be exclusively sold to Filipino investors due to a statute banning foreigners from owning media firms.</p>
<p>Tentative listing date is set on May 5.</p>
<p>- Manila newsroom 63 2 8418938 Fax 8176267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
