<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478932" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: ASIAN DEBT MARKETS - China Construction raises FRN.</title>
<headline>ASIAN DEBT MARKETS - China Construction raises FRN.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>China Construction Bank showed a US$200 million floating rate note issue to an appreciative audience on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Asian debt markets also offered the debut floating rate certificate of deposit issue for the Philippine Bank of Communications.</p>
<p>China Construction Bank's five-year notes pay a coupon of 30 basis points over the six-month London Interbank Offered Rate.</p>
<p>They were launched at par and re-offered at 99.871 to give a fixed re-offer yield of 33 basis points.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch Far East was the bookrunner.</p>
<p>Bayerische Landesbank Hong Kong, Daiwa Securities (HK), Development Bank of Singapore and Sakura Finance Asia were lead managers along with Merrill Lynch.</p>
<p>While the pricing was considered a mite tight at 33 basis points all-in, banks nevertheless joined in droves. Seventeen banks in addition to the lead managers joined the group as co-lead managers and co-managers.</p>
<p>The issue closed and was freed to trade by 0900 London time.</p>
<p>With many investors wary of South Korean and Thai credits in the wake of the two countries' financial problems, China and Hong Kong have become the new darlings of the Asian debt markets.</p>
<p>&quot;With Korea and Thailand in disarray, investors are worried about more bad news, so they are looking at Hong Kong and China,&quot; said one syndicate manager.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a lot of interest in the China issues, particularly in the state banks and the ITIC (International Trust and Investment Corp) deals,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>China credits also benefit from rarity value, but this may change as more and more Chinese entities tap the international capital markets.</p>
<p>Beijing's China International Trust and Investment Corp is the latest Chinese institution to eye the market, mandating CS First Boston to arrange a financing.</p>
<p>China Investment Bank is seeking US$100 million five-year money through a floating rate note issue, while Bank of China is expected to launch its new issue later this month.</p>
<p>Philippine Bank of Communications, the country's 15th largest bank in terms of assets, launched its debut FRCD, a three-year deal with annual puts that pays an all-in return of 110 basis points. ABN Amro Bank is the bookrunner.</p>
<p>In the loan market, Japura Plc, a Singapore incorporated investment holding company owned 52 percent by Hong Kong tycoon Li Ka-Shing, 24 percent by Cheung Kong (Holdings) and 24 percent by Hutchison Whampoa Ltd, is seeking US$712 million through a term loan/revolving credit facility.</p>
<p>CIBC CEF Singapore is co-ordinating arranger and bookrunner.</p>
<p>Proceeds of the facility will be used for general working capital. Bankers pointed out that Cheung Kong and Hutchison have various property and other projects in the works that require financing.</p>
<p>In other news of Hong Kong loans, bankers expect Hang Lung Development to distribute invitations for its HK$4.8 billion financing this week.</p>
<p>-- Andrea Ricci (852) 2843-6371 fax (852) 2845-0636</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
