<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478915" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Malaysian rubber prices down at close.</title>
<headline>Malaysian rubber prices down at close.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysian rubber prices lost their midday firmness to close lower, with traders saying the market had to succumb to weak consumer demand.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices have to come down...we are still much higher than Indonesia,&quot; said a trader in Kuala Lumpur.</p>
<p>At the close, the Malaysian Rubber Exchange and Licensing Board quote May RSS1 buyer at 297.50 cents () a kg, down a cent from Monday. May SMR20 buyer was a cent lower at 285.50.</p>
<p>An official trade source said the only known business for the morning was 500 tonnes of SMR20 transacted for Dubai at 284.50 cents a kg for late April delivery.  </p>
<p>Dealers in private trading houses quoted the SMR 20 at 284/285 cents a kg for May, SMR CV at 351, SMR L at 331, SMR 5 at 293, SMR 10 at 286 and drum latex FOB at 235.</p>
<p>Dealers said although prices were coming down, they still had some way to go before being able to compete with Indonesia.</p>
<p>The INRO five-day moving indicator was quoted at 227.96 Malaysian/Singaporean cents per kg on March 31, down from the 228.25 on March 27. The daily indicator also ended lower at 228.34 against 228.70 previously.</p>
<p>-- K. Baranee Krishnaan (603-230 8911) ($1=2.4760 ringgit)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
