<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478975" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Highlights of Nippon Credit's restructuring plan. [CORRECTED 11:20 GMT]</title>
<headline>Highlights of Nippon Credit's restructuring plan. [CORRECTED 11:20 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are the main points of the restructuring measures unveiled on Tuesday by Japan's troubled Nippon Credit Bank (NCB) :</p>
<p>-- to post current loss of 350 billion yen in 1996/97 ended on March 31 on bad loan write-offs and falling Tokyo stocks.</p>
<p>Despite a special profit of 67 billion yen from planned real estate sales, it will post a net loss of 285 billion yen for the year. The bank would pay no dividends to its shareholders in the second half of the year.</p>
<p>-- to write off 460 billion yen worth of problem loans, including those made to its failed financial affiliates. NCB would then complete the necessary bad loan write-offs by setting aside special reserves which will cover 48 percent of its problem loans worth 1.26 trillion yen.</p>
<p>-- to withdraw from overseas operations and focus instead on domestic services to improve its business efficiency. It will close five overseas branches and seven representative offices and also sell its subsidiaries.</p>
<p>It would take a considerable time to complete the withdrawal procedure, it said.</p>
<p>-- to take the following steps, which NCB said would boost its profit by some 50 billion yen over the next five years.</p>
<p>A) cutting the number of executives from the current 25 and stop paying them bonuses while reducing executive salaries by 50 percent.</p>
<p>The president will return his executive salary.</p>
<p>B) reducing the workforce by 600 to 2,300 (Corrects from 2,900) by March 1998 and introducing early retirement. The bank will cut workers' salaries by 10-30 percent and employ a new wage system.</p>
<p>C) restructuring operations at six out of 18 branches to concentrate on bond sales operations.</p>
<p>D) selling the real estate of all of its operating branches, including the headquarters in Tokyo and its Osaka branch office, as well as employee welfare facilities.</p>
<p>-- NCB said it has given up supporting its three non-bank units. Facing its own problems, NCB has decided to stop giving further assistance.</p>
<p>-- NCB said it hopes to boost its capital by about 300 billion yen and attain a capital adequacy ratio of about six percent at the end of March 1998.</p>
<p>It is seeking the use of 80 billion yen from a special fund set up by Japan designed to deal with bad loans at failed housing loan firms, or &quot;jusen&quot;, and is also asking various other public and private institutions for financial support.</p>
<p>--- NCB aims to become a professional bank which will mainly serve medium- and small-sized companies.</p>
<p>IT will focus on securitisation of properties, liquidation of various debts, risk management using interest rate and currency swaps and management of various assets. NCB hopes to position itself as soon as possible into a manageable size of 10 trillion yen in total assets and 2,000 employees.</p>
<p>An advisory committee will be set up to advise NCB.</p>
<p>-- NCB top executives will decide whether to resign or not at an appropriate time, after stabilising the bank's business. NCB said the current management must restore credibility and stabilise its business by gaining the understanding and cooperation from shareholders, clients and other financial institutions. -- Tokyo Equities Desk +81-3-3432-9404</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
