<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478933" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: WFP chief says food cut to North Korean military.</title>
<headline>WFP chief says food cut to North Korean military.</headline>
<byline>Teruaki Ueno</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korean food shortages have become so bad that for the first time rations to the military have been cut and people were eating tree bark, World Food Programme chief Catherine Bertini said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Bertini, executive director of the United Nations World Food Programme (WFP), warned the situation was so dire that North Korea could run out of food within the next three months.</p>
<p>&quot;What I do know is that millions of people are going to starve to death this summer if the international community does not get a lot of food to North Korea soon,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Although the 1.1-million-strong military was better fed than ordinary citizens in North Korea, there were first signs that the food crisis was hitting even the armed forces, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;The government gives more food per person per day to the military than to the general population,&quot; Bertini, who visited North Korea last month, told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;But even rations to the military have been cut recently,&quot; she said without elaborating.</p>
<p>Floods in 1995 and 1996 ruined rice fields, washed away roads and left half a million North Koreans homeless out of a population of 23 million, according to relief organisations.</p>
<p>Bertini, a former U.S. assistant secretary of Agriculture, said North Korea was giving 100 grammes (3-1/2 oz) of rice a day to each citizen, half last year's amount, and one-quarter of what people received before two consecutive years of flood.</p>
<p>Bertini said there were fewer children in school because of a lack of food and she saw at first hand children with reddish hair and distended bellies, signs of advanced malnutrition.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation is very dire and it's going to get worse,&quot; she said. &quot;It is so bad that people are resorting to eating bark from trees and as a result they are having a lot of intestinal problems because it's not easy to digest.&quot;</p>
<p>The Rome-based WFP, the U.N. emergency food aid provider, appealed for $41 million in mid-February to stave off famine in North Korea.</p>
<p>The funds would buy 100,000 tonnes of food aid over the next year for 1.7 million of the most vulnerable flood victims, mainly farmers and children.</p>
<p>&quot;But we know from our own assessments that there is a need for a total of 2.3 million tonnes of food,&quot; Bertini said.</p>
<p>&quot;Projections are between April and June the country will run out of food to feed its people,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>She quoted North Korean officials as telling her the Stalinist country could run out of food in April.</p>
<p>&quot;My biggest impression was that people do hard manual labour all day, thousands of thousands of people,&quot; she said. &quot;There aren't tractors in the fields and there are a very few oxen in the fields, so people work with shovels.&quot;</p>
<p>Bertini was unable to confirm some reports that several thousand people have died of starvation in North Korea's north-eastern provinces since last September.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't confirm that, but it wouldn't surprise me if that was true,&quot; Bertini said. &quot;We haven't seen that ourselves.&quot;</p>
<p>Bertini urged donor nations not to hold back from food aid because of worries it would go mainly to North Korea's military.</p>
<p>&quot;If nations give through the World Food Programme, they can be sure it will go directly to those in need,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Bertini arrived in Tokyo on Tuesday hoping to persuade Japan to step up its food aid to North Korea.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
