<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478906" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Latexx in Indonesia glove making venture.</title>
<headline>Latexx in Indonesia glove making venture.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysian glove maker Latexx Partners Bhd said on Tuesday it has ventured into the production of rubber gloves in Indonesia through its 99 percent-owned subsidiary, PT Latexx Technologies.</p>
<p>Following the venture, Latexx is proposing a one-for-two rights issue of 10 million shares at 3.60 ringgit per share and a one-for-one bonus issue of 20 million shares, the company said in a statement.</p>
<p>It also plans an employees' share option scheme of five million shares and to double the company's authorised share capital to 100 million ringgit.</p>
<p>PT Latexx would be principally engaged in the manufacture of rubber latex gloves for medical purposes, high technology manufacturing and food-based industries upon commencement of its operations in early 1998, Latexx said.</p>
<p>The 103.5 million ringgit project is scheduled to be implemented in three phases with 36 production lines, which when fully operational, will have a production capacity of 2.16 billion pieces a year, it said.</p>
<p>Latexx said proceeds from the proposed rights issue would be used for investment in PT Latex Technologies.</p>
<p>The balance of the project cost would be financed by offshore borrowings and internally generated funds.</p>
<p>Following the proposals, the share capital of Latexx will increase to 55 million ringgit from the existing 20 million and net tangible assets per share to 2.87 ringgit from 2.51 ringgit.</p>
<p>Latexx shares were suspended since March 26 at the company's request pending an announcement. The stock was last traded at 13.80 ringgit.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-206 2323)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
