<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478944" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: FOCUS-Manila stocks, unnerved by Dow, take beating.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Manila stocks, unnerved by Dow, take beating.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippine shares, unnerved by Wall Street's slump, took a beating on Tuesday and analysts said recovery of the local bourse hinged on how soon the Dow would calm down.</p>
<p>Investors stayed on the sidelines, awaiting cue from New York, and absence of any fundamental news also helped dampen trading, analysts said.</p>
<p>The main index sank 51.19 points, or 1.59 percent, to 3,171.79 points with the number of losers overwhelming gainers 103 to 26. Turnover value was a modest 2.9 billion pesos on a total of volume of 9.875 billion shares.</p>
<p>The drop reflected a general decline in other Asian stock markets which also reacted negatively to a sharp drop in U.S. share prices and to their own domestic problems, analysts said.</p>
<p>The mining sector provided one of the few bright spots in Manila in a day where all of the other sub-indices slumped at the close.</p>
<p>Mining shares bounced back from Monday's heavy losses to close 67.30 points or 1.17 percent higher at 5,811.15 in an apparent technical correction after having been on the retreat, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously, the only factor dominating all markets in the region would be Wall Street,&quot; said Louie Bate, managing director for Equities Brokerage Trading at ING Baring Securities Philippines Inc.</p>
<p>Bate said the chances of the market perking up would depend on how soon the &quot;gloomy shadow&quot; cast by Wall Street would lift.</p>
<p>&quot;Any abrupt (Dow) change will have an influence on our market ... So far, we remain hostage to Wall Street,&quot; Bate said.</p>
<p>Joel Santillan, research head of Asiamerit Securities Inc., said fears of successive hikes in U.S. interest rates were keeping away investors.</p>
<p>&quot;On top of that, there's a tendency for people to take profits at this time ... A rebound in New York would really help,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>One of the day's many losers was shipping firm WG&amp;A, which declared one of its luxury ships a total loss after it caught fire while anchored in the Manila harbour last week.</p>
<p>WG&amp;A shares traded 50 centavos or 17.24 percent lower at 2.40 pesos in late Tuesday trade with volume totalling 1.89 million shares.</p>
<p>But WG&amp;A officials said the vessel was fully covered by insurance and its loss would not hurt company finances.</p>
<p>One factor that may spark interest in the sluggish market is the eagerly awaited initial public offering of Equitable Banking Corp on Thursday, analysts said.</p>
<p>The bank's offering involves 85,412,820 shares priced at 113.30 pesos each.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll see, I'd like to hope so,&quot; Santillan said, when asked if Equitable's debut could lift the market out of the doldrums.</p>
<p>-- RUBEN ALABASTRO 841 8913 Fax 817 6267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
