<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478919" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Malaysia urges role with Germany in technology.</title>
<headline>Malaysia urges role with Germany in technology.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysian King Tuanku Ja'afar urged visiting German President Roman Herzog on Tuesday to form a high-technology collaboration between the two countries to help Malaysia's industrialisation.</p>
<p>&quot;Since Malaysia is shifting from labour-intensive manufacturing, there is good potential for cooperation in high-tech industries,&quot; the king said at a state banquet held in honour of the German president.</p>
<p>Herzog arrived in Malaysia on Tuesday for a five-day visit aimed at strengthening bilateral ties, officials said.</p>
<p>The king invited Germany to participate in economic &quot;growth triangles&quot; formed by Malaysia and its neighbours.</p>
<p>He said Malaysia was particularly impressed with Germany's reunification, which he said gave hope that industrialised nations were capable of implementing structural changes to help developing economies.</p>
<p>Herzog is in Kuala Lumpur with a 100-member delegation.</p>
<p>A government statement said Herzog will hold talks with Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad on Wednesday.</p>
<p>For the rest of his visit, Herzog will tour the newly built Kuala Lumpur Tower for telecommunications and fly to the east Malaysian state of Sarawak on Borneo, the statement said.</p>
<p>The national Bernama news agency said Germany was Malaysia's leading European trading partner after Britain. Trade between the two countries swelled to 8.6 billion marks ($5.14 billion) in 1995 from 2.25 billion marks in 1987, Bernama said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
