<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478978" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China prepares talks to end Vietnam oil dispute.</title>
<headline>China prepares talks to end Vietnam oil dispute.</headline>
<byline>Mure Dickie</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Beijing is preparing to begin negotiations with Vietnam to help resolve a diplomatic row over the ownership of oil-rich waters in the South China Sea, Chinese officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;China is currently preparing for expert-level talks with Vietnam,&quot; said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Shen Guofang.</p>
<p>The talks would focus on the sovereignty of seas off central Vietnam where exploratory drilling by a Chinese rig has sparked verbal sparring between Hanoi and its huge northern neighbour, said an official of China's main offshore oil firm.</p>
<p>Disputes over territory and resource exploration in the South China Sea continued to trouble Sino-Vietnamese relations, despite the steady improvement in ties in recent years, Shen told a news briefing in Beijing.</p>
<p>China and Vietnam fought a brief but bloody border war in 1979 and clashed at sea in the 1980s, but Shen expressed confidence that negotiations would ease the communist neighbours' current differences.</p>
<p>&quot;We can resolve these problems through peaceful and friendly consultations,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Vietnamese Foreign Minister Nguyen Manh Cam said on Monday he hoped talks with China could begin this week on claims to the area, about 64.5 nautical miles off its central coast, where China's Kan Tan III rig has been drilling.</p>
<p>An official of the China National Offshore Oil Corp said negotiations would be carried out by foreign affairs experts.</p>
<p>&quot;The talks will focus on the division of the sea and will discuss who owns that continential shelf and economic region,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Vietnam has repeatedly demanded that China withdraw its rig and support vessels from the disputed area immediately, and has said it wants talks to start as soon as possible.</p>
<p>China was expected to send an expert team to Vietnam this week to discuss the issue, diplomats in Hanoi said.</p>
<p>A Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman said last week that China cherished its ties with Vietnam, but that the actions of the Kan Tan III were beyond criticism.</p>
<p>&quot;It is irreproachable for China's Kan Tan III rig to carry out normal operations in the northern part of the South China Sea on China's declared continental shelf and exclusive economic zone,&quot; spokesman Cui Tiankai said.</p>
<p>Officials of the China National Offshore Oil Corp, which already oversees exploitation of lucrative gas fields off the southern island province of Hainan, have also said they have no immediate plans to move the rig.</p>
<p>&quot;Why should we leave the area?&quot; one official said last week. &quot;When the exploration is finished we will move the rig.&quot;</p>
<p>The oil exploration row is the latest in a long series of territorial disputes, ideological differences and historical grievances to strain Sino-Vietnamese socialist solidarity.</p>
<p>The two nations have competing claims on areas along their land border, on parts of the Tonkin Gulf and on the Paracel Island chain, which lie east of the latest area of dispute.</p>
<p>They are also among six regional claimants to the Spratly Islands further to the south.</p>
<p>Both sides have in recent years agreed to shelve some border problems and have worked hard to improve ties and boost border trade, but the temptation to exploit the oil-rich waters they dispute has been a constant threat to their rapprochement.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
