<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478964" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Malaysia seen main gainer of Japanese fund flows.</title>
<headline>Malaysia seen main gainer of Japanese fund flows.</headline>
<byline>Madhav Reddy</byline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Malaysian ringgit is expected to be the main beneficiary as Japanese funds target high-yielding Southeast Asian currencies in Japan's new financial year, dealers and analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Though far more subdued than in the past few years, the traditional funds flow from Japan to Southeast Asia starting April 1 would eventually boost currencies and provide fresh liquidity to the region's stock markets, they said.</p>
<p>Dealers in the region reported a start to Japanese inflows. Reflecting this, the Malaysian ringgit rose to 2.4750/60 to the dollar by 0330 GMT against 2.4790/4800 overnight. At 1016 GMT, the ringgit was trading at 2.4758/69.</p>
<p>Supported by a weaker U.S. dollar and some fresh fund buying, the Singapore dollar also rose to 1.4390/4400 a dollar against 1.4430/40. By 1016 GMT, it had firmed to 1.4383/93.</p>
<p>&quot;Many Japanese investors are buying the ringgit and the Singapore dollar. Over the next few days, or probably this whole month, they are going to load heavily into these two currencies,&quot; said a dealer with an European bank in Singapore.</p>
<p>But some economists said slowing economic growth in Southeast Asia and higher interest rates in the United States would slow Japanese fund flows to the region.</p>
<p>&quot;Any strong capital flows from Tokyo into the region is unlikely under the current environment,&quot; said C.H. Kwan, senior economist at Nomura Research Institute Ltd's Center for Policy Research.</p>
<p>He said at the moment there were &quot;such stock bearish factors as higher U.S. interest rates and not-so-brilliant performance of the corporate SE Asia&quot;.</p>
<p>A weak yen trend was also a drag. Southeast Asian currencies are loosely linked to the strengthened dollar. Stronger local currencies make Southeast Asian assets more expensive to Japanese investors who are wary of currency risks.</p>
<p>The European bank dealer said Japanese funds are largely bypassing the Thai baht and the Indonesian rupiah because of market uncertainties in the two countries.</p>
<p>Foreign exchange dealers in Jakarta said Japanese funds established some rupiah positions on Tuesday, but volumes were low.</p>
<p>&quot;Indonesia is close to elections, while there is some crisis of confidence in the Thai economy. People are going to countries with more stability, like Singapore and Malaysia,&quot; said a U.S. bank dealer in Singapore.</p>
<p>The rupiah, a recent favourite among international investors because of its high interest rates, would attract fresh funds after the Indonesian general elections on May 29, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Medium to long-term, Indonesia is a great bet, though before the elections there is some uncertainty,&quot; said Dilip Ratha, regional economist with W.I. Carr in Singapore.</p>
<p>Fund managers in Thailand were unlikely to see a significant inflow of Japanese funds to the country any time soon because of slowing economic growth and a bearish stock market.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it (inflow) is going to come immediately. You know that the Thai economy is (weak) and the stock market is in an unfavourable condition,&quot; Mitsuyasu Yamamoto, head of Japanese Institutional sales at Capital Nomura Securities, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The ringgit is the favourite for the Japanese among the regionals because of its improving economic fundamentals, tight monetary policy and push factors from other high yielders,&quot; said Jimmy Koh, economist with I.D.E.A. in Singapore.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-230 7509)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
