<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478974" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai stocks end down, finance shares sold off.</title>
<headline>Thai stocks end down, finance shares sold off.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thai stocks pared losses in the Tuesday afternoon session but ended the day sharply lower as the market tracked an overnight 2.3 percent fall on Wall Street.</p>
<p>The SET Index ended 10.69 points or 1.52 percent lower at 694.74. The SET 50 fell 0.75 points, or 1.44 percent, to 51.43. Turnover was 1.81 billion baht.</p>
<p>Finance stocks bore the brunt of the sell off losing 2.87 percent on concerns Thai lending rates might follow any further hike in US rates and concerns about the how the first quarter results of listed companies might fare, traders said.  </p>
<p>&quot;A few back of envelope calculations will tell you how poor securities trading revenues are going to be in the first quarter for these firms,&quot; said the head of institutional sales at a leading European broker.</p>
<p>Analysts expect most finance and securities firms to post negative growth during first quarter results, brokers said.</p>
<p>The sector has been hit by declining asset quality, rising costs of funds and falling trading revenues.</p>
<p>Fears U.S. rate rises could see the dollar appreciate against the yen, and renew pressure on the Thai baht was also a concern among foreign clients, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
