<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478994" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: China Construction Bank US$200 FRN group forms.</title>
<headline>China Construction Bank US$200 FRN group forms.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A management group has formed for China Construction Bank's US$200 million floating rate notes issue due 2002, bookrunner Merrill Lynch Far East said.</p>
<p>The five-year notes were issued at par and re-offered at a fixed 99.871. They pay a coupon of 30 basis points over the six-month London Interbank Offered Rate and a fixed re-offer yield of 33 basis points over LIBOR.</p>
<p>Fees are 25 basis points split as 10 basis points for management and underwriting and 15 basis points for selling. There is a praecipium of 12.5 basis points which is to be added to the management and underwriting fees.</p>
<p>Lead managers are Bayerische Landesbank Hong Kong, Daiwa Securities (HK), Development Bank of Singapore, Merrill Lynch Far East and Sakura Finance Asia.</p>
<p>Co-lead managers are Fuji International Finance, HSBC Markets, LTCB Asia, Paribas Capital Markets, Sanwa International Finance and SBC Warburg.</p>
<p>Co-managers are BA Asia, Bear Stearns Asia, BOC International, Baden-Wurttembergische Bank, CARIPLO Hong Kong, CITIC Industrial Bank, Dresdner (South East Asia), Industrial and Commercial Bank of China, Malayan Banking Berhad, SanPaolo Bank Singapore and Tokyo-Mitsubishi International (HK). The payment date is April 11.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843 6960</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
