<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478979" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Indonesia details Apr LSWR schedule, outlook dim.</title>
<headline>Indonesia details Apr LSWR schedule, outlook dim.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia's state oil company, Pertamina has announced the loading schedule for its 3.6 million barrels of low sulphur waxy residue (LSWR) for lifting in April, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The volume is lower than the initial allocation for March at 3.7 million barrels but traders were bearish amid a surplus of oil due to weak regional demand.</p>
<p>They said further to the April allocation, around 400,000 to 500,000 barrels of LSWR scheduled for March lifting has been rolled over for lifting in April.  </p>
<p>An additional 500,000 barrels can also be expected to be allocated later in April, they said.</p>
<p>There was also about 1.0 million barrels of straight-run LSWR available from Singapore and Malaysia in April, they said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, demand was very thin with Japan projected to take up to 1.1 million barrels, South Korea taking 500,000 barrels, Italy taking its usual 560,000 barrels and India importing up to 200,000 barrels. These totalled up to only 2.36 million barrels.</p>
<p>&quot;There is zero demand from China, Taiwan, Australia and the US,&quot; said a trader on possible outlets.  </p>
<p>Traders said US buyers are only interested if prices, currently over $17.00 per barrel free-on-board Indonesia, fall to around $16.00.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices should fall, but a lot depends on what happens this week,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>He said there were storage problems and Pertamina was starting to put pressure on term buyers to lift barrels.</p>
<p>But sellers in the spot market were not yet aggressive and were only indicating a high premium of around 65 cents per barrel over the Pertamina formula, although some traders assessed the premium at around the 40-cent mark.  </p>
<p>The details of the April loading schedule are as follows (in thousand barrels):</p>
<p>LOADING FROM FLOATING STORAGE PLATINUM (OFF SUMATRA)</p>
<p>    TIMING	VOLUME	 COMPANY</p>
<p>Mar    2-4	   400	 Perta</p>
<p>     11-13	   200	 British Petroleum (BP)</p>
<p>     11-13	   140	 Kipco</p>
<p>     11-13	   160	 Perta</p>
<p>     19-21	   200	 BP</p>
<p>     19-21	   200	 Indoil</p>
<p>     28-30	   200	 BP</p>
<p>     28-30	   120	 Indoil</p>
<p>     28-30	    80	 Kipco</p>
<p>    SUB-TOTAL:   1,700</p>
<p>LOADING FROM PAKNING (SUMATRA)</p>
<p>	 3-5	   200	 Pacific Petroleum</p>
<p>    LOADING FROM DUMAI    (SUMATRA)</p>
<p>	9-11	   300	 BP</p>
<p>     26-27	   200	 Indoil</p>
<p>    SUB-TOTAL:     500</p>
<p>LOADING FROM SAMBU JETTY</p>
<p>	 2-4	   200	 Indoil</p>
<p>     22-24	   200	 BP</p>
<p>    SUB TOTAL:     400</p>
<p>LOADING FROM BALIKPAPAN (KALIMANTAN, BORNEO)</p>
<p>	8-10	   200	 Far East Investment (FEI)</p>
<p>     11-13	   200	 FEI</p>
<p>     18-20	   140	 FEI</p>
<p>     18-20	    60	 Indoil</p>
<p>     22-24	   180	 Itochu</p>
<p>     22-24	    20	 Indoil</p>
<p>    SUB TOTAL:     800</p>
<p>    TOTAL	  3,600</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3086)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
