<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478961" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Newspaper spoof amuses HK on April Fool's Day.</title>
<headline>Newspaper spoof amuses HK on April Fool's Day.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>If you believe what you read in the newspapers, China has changed its mind and may just allow Britain to keep Hong Kong. But it's April Fool's Day, and the paper is a fake.</p>
<p>Mysterious authors of an Asian Wall Street Journal lookalike newspaper treated Hong Kong newsrooms to a host of outrageous stories on April 1, the traditional day for tricks and pranks. But none were true and nobody was conned.</p>
<p>Circulated free under the giveaway title, &quot;The Asian Wall Street Gerbil&quot;, its authors swung from jibes at the offspring of Indonesian President Suharto and Japan's Imperial household to far-fetched political exposes. It also appeared on the Internet.</p>
<p>The lead story said China would let Britain keep Hong Kong, otherwise due to revert to Beijing on July 1, but would receive Britain's strife-torn province of Northern Ireland instead.</p>
<p>In another report, China claimed sovereignty over territorial waters extending all the way across the Pacific into San Francisco Bay, on evidence dating from the &quot;Spam&quot; dynasty.</p>
<p>Readers were also given the inside story to flights on Singapore Airlines, one of the world's most profitable carriers.</p>
<p>Passengers who made advances on stewardesses or who were found chewing gum were strapped to duty-free carts and caned, while those found with drugs were hanged along the aisle as a spoof on the island-state's tough laws.</p>
<p>The prank, which caused mirth in many Hong Kong newsrooms, kept phones ringing all day at the Asian Wall Street Journal, the serious-minded, small-print broadsheet newspaper that the spoof was cloned to resemble.</p>
<p>&quot;No, I have no idea where it came from. But it certainly didn't have anything to do with us,&quot; the real Journal's editor Urban Lehner told Reuters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
