<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478952" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China sets tax for foreign bank yuan business.</title>
<headline>China sets tax for foreign bank yuan business.</headline>
<byline>Graham Earnshaw</byline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>China has set the income tax rate for foreign banks doing local currency business at 33 percent, the same as that for Chinese banks, officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Chinese bankers welcomed the move, saying the tax rate would enable Chinese banks to compete with their foreign counterparts on an equal footing, while foreign bankers said they had expected the news.</p>
<p>&quot;It will make profitability rather slim given the margins we might get in present conditions,&quot; said one European banker in Shanghai. &quot;But it's a trial period, and I think we have to look to the long-run.&quot;</p>
<p>The Beijing-based International Business Daily said the State Council (cabinet) had decided that foreign banks doing Chinese yuan business would pay 33 percent income tax.</p>
<p>It also decided to lower income tax for all Chinese banks, insurance firms and other financial institutions to 33 percent from 55 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;This puts Chinese and foreign banks on the same level as far as income tax (on local currency business) is concerned,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>Officials at the State Administration of Taxation confirmed the move and said tax polices on other aspects of foreign bank business were unaffected.</p>
<p>Foreign banks in China are currently taxed largely at a 15 percent rate on foreign exchange transactions.</p>
<p>Eight foreign banks in Shanghai have been given approval to do limited yuan business and three of them have started processing loans and deposits in the past few days.</p>
<p>But the scale of the business is expected to be so small for the foreseeable future that it hardly matters what the tax rate is, another European banker said.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't make a difference, and it won't for several years given the level of business,&quot; the banker said. &quot;It will be no more than a trickle. There cannot be a massive flow of business moving over to foreign banks from the Chinese banks.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;In the long-term, give it five to 10 years, it'll be a different ball game,&quot; he added. &quot;I would expect that around the year 2000 the Chinese will start granting licences to foreign banks across the board to do yuan business.&quot;</p>
<p>A Chinese banker with a major state bank welcomed the unified 33 percent tax rate.</p>
<p>&quot;With foreign banks doing the local currency business, we felt it was unfair to pay a much higher tax,&quot; the banker said. &quot;The unified tax is good and allows us domestic banks to compete equally with our foreign counterparts.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;For the time being, the foreign bank yuan business is restricted,&quot; said another banker. &quot;But I believe China will open the whole market to the outside world before too long. A unified tax is fair.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
