<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="478947" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai March inflation higher than expected.</title>
<headline>Thai March inflation higher than expected.</headline>
<byline>Vithoon Amorn</byline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thailand's annual inflation rate rose 4.5 percent in March, partly driven up by price increases for rice and tap water, the commerce ministry said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The rise in the consumer price index was above economists' expectations for a 4.1-4.3 percent increase, but the news failed to stir local financial markets, brokers and analysts said.</p>
<p>March consumer prices compared with CPI rises of 4.3 percent in both February and January, the ministry said.</p>
<p>But the latest snapshop of Thai inflation appeared far more benign than last year's performance, when the annual CPI rate ran at a lofty 7.3 percent.</p>
<p>Prices for both food and non-food products rose 0.5 percent month-on-month in March, against an average 0.2 percent increase for the same month in the past 10 years, it added.</p>
<p>&quot;The figure is quite higher than what I predicted. Under the current sluggish economy in which purchasing power is weak, I would have expected prices to remain pretty mild,&quot; Vuth Puthamon of Multi-Credit Corp of Thailand told Reuters.</p>
<p>A hike in tap water prices in the Bangkok metropolitan area last month likely contributed to the higher consumer prices, the ministry said.</p>
<p>&quot;The March figure was slightly higher than expected...but it is not that bad. I think overall 1997 inflation could still be restrained to a 4.0-4.5 percent range,&quot; said a foreign analyst who declined to be named.</p>
<p>Thailand's 1996 annual inflation rate stood at 5.9 percent.</p>
<p>Analysts did not expect March inflation to further hurt the bearish Thai stock market which has been hammered by a string of negative news in the past year due to a slowing Thai economy, depressed property sector and turmoil in the financial industry.</p>
<p>&quot;It would probably not affect stocks which have come off quite a bit because of Wall Street,&quot; the foreign analyst said, adding that investors currently focused more on Thai current account and trade deficits than inflation.</p>
<p>Vuth of Multi-Credit said consumer prices would accelerate in April and May due to seasonal factors. The Thai summer usually pushes up food costs and the re-opening of schools in mid-May spurs education spending.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
