<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479079" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Monsanto to buy rest of Calgene for $240 million.</title>
<headline>Monsanto to buy rest of Calgene for $240 million.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Commins</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Monsanto Co., in a move to expand its biotechnology and food science businesses, said Tuesday it agreed to acquire the remaining shares of Calgene Inc. that it does not own for $240 million.</p>
<p>Monsanto, which owns 54.6 percent of Davis, Calif.-based Calgene, said it offered to buy the rest of the company for $8 a share, an increase from its previous offer of $7.25 a share.</p>
<p>For Monsanto, owning all of Calgene underscores its plans to bring biotechnology further up the food chain, observers said.</p>
<p>Monsanto is currently involved in agricultural biotechnology, developing genetically altered crops that can fight off insects and withstand the use of certain herbicides in the field. This kind of biotechnology is aimed at helping farmers increase their yields.</p>
<p>With the most recent deal, Monsanto gains further access to Calgene's research in producing genetically modified oils, fresh produce and cotton -- products used by consumers. Natwest Securities analyst Mark Wiltamuth called this the &quot;second wave of agricultural biotechnology.&quot;</p>
<p>Monsanto has been transforming itself into a life sciences company, with agricultural, food ingredient and pharmaceutical holdings, and plans to spin off its chemical businesses later this year.</p>
<p>&quot;This will promote the closer working relationships and the greater sharing of technologies that are only possible with full ownership of the company,&quot; Monsanto Executive Vice President Hendrik Verfaillie said in a statement. &quot;We can now better realise the benefits from Calgene's research by combining our technology efforts and bringing products to market more rapidly.&quot;</p>
<p>Calgene Chairman Lloyd Kunimoto said much of his company's research has focused on using genetic engineering to produce oils that may be healthier for consumers.</p>
<p>&quot;Our strong suit is using genetic engineering to modify oil composition,&quot; said Kunimoto, who will stay on with Calgene as it becomes part of Monsanto.</p>
<p>Calgene's &quot;flagship product,&quot; Kunimoto added, is a modified canola oil that contains at least 40 percent of a fatty acid called laurate, which is typically found in tropical crops like coconuts.</p>
<p>While this gives the laurate canola certain properties similar to cocoa butter, Kunimoto said it does not promote cholestrol in the body, a criticism of tropical oils.</p>
<p>Calgene's other biotech products include fresh tomatoes and strawberries with improved flavor and shelf-life, naturally coloured cotton fibers and herbicide-tolerant and insect-protected cotton.</p>
<p>Moving into the genetically modified food arena is not without its risks, since many consumers harbour fears and doubts about the safety of these products, said Teresa Thiel, professor of biology and director of biotechnology at the University of Missouri.</p>
<p>&quot;We as consumers are very concerned about the quality of the food and the content of the food,&quot; Thiel said, pointing to recent protests in Europe over genetically altered crops such as Monsanto's Roundup Ready soybeans, which can withstand use of the Roundup herbicide.</p>
<p>Monsanto said it will commence a tender offer for the remaining Calgene shares on April 7. It took an initial 49.9 percent stake in Calgene in March 1996 and purchased an additional 6.25 million shares for a 54.6 percent stake in November 1996.</p>
<p>In January, it proposed acquiring the rest of Calgene for $7.25 a share. The revised bid of $8 a share was approved by a special committee of Calgene's directors who are neither designees of Monsanto nor Calgene employees.</p>
<p>The two companies also agreed in principle to settle putative class actions that were filed after Monsanto's initial $7.25 a share offer.</p>
<p>Kunimoto said he believed the $8 a share price for his company's stock will give shareholders &quot;a fair premium on their investment.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25670">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
