<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479057" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton, King Hussein meet on Mideast crisis.</title>
<headline>Clinton, King Hussein meet on Mideast crisis.</headline>
<byline>Gene Gibbons</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton and Jordan's King Hussein conferred on Monday on how to halt a new cycle of Israeli-Palestinian violence, and Clinton said he was &quot;prepared personally to do anything I can&quot; to save the Middle East peace process.</p>
<p>He indicated that personal intervention might move forward within a week or so if Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu went ahead with plans to visit with American Jewish leaders. &quot;I expect to see him,&quot; the president said.</p>
<p>In Jerusalem, Netanyahu's office announced that he would make a quick trip to Washington beginning on Sunday night. &quot;The prime minister ... is happy to have an opportunity to meet with President Clinton,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;We've got to try to keep the lid on things over there ... It is not going to be easy,&quot; Clinton said, referring to increasingly violent clashes between Israelis and Palestinians and the stalling of peace negotiations.</p>
<p>He told reporters he and Hussein had exchanged ideas in 45 minutes of talks on how to restore an environment of security and trust between Israel and the Palestinians.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm prepared personally to do anything I can to get this process back on track and move it forward but I think the less I say about it the more likely I am to have some success ... particularly in the next two to three weeks,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>King Hussein, the fourth Middle Eastern leader to visit Clinton in the past few weeks, agreed at the start of their meeting that &quot;we are certainly passing through a difficult stage&quot; in the peace process.</p>
<p>But the king stressed that much progress had been made and said &quot;conditions are not what they were 20 years ago&quot; when Israel was in a state of war with all its Arab neighbours.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if he would send U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright to the region, Clinton replied: &quot;At the right time I certainly want her to go, but I want it to be part of a clear strategy designed to produce progress.&quot;</p>
<p>Israeli-Palestinian talks have been frozen since Netanyahu on March 18 broke ground for new Jewish settlements in Arab East Jerusalem, triggering West Bank violence that continued on Tuesday for a 13th day. That confrontation has worsened even as Clinton has held talks with the leaders of Israeli, Egypt, the Palestinians and now Jordan.</p>
<p>The United States has urged Palestinian leader Yasser Arafat to make clear he renounces violence as a political instrument, and Clinton said after his meeting with King Hussein that Arafat had &quot;made several moves in the last few days which are encouraging.&quot;</p>
<p>But he added: &quot;A precondition of going forward is a commitment of zero tolerance for terrorism ... a determination to do all that can reasonably be done to maintain the peace, so that in negotiations progress can be made.&quot;</p>
<p>Later, asked if Netanyahu were expected to visit the United States this weekend, Clinton replied: &quot;Yes, I undertand he's coming and I certainly hope to see him. I expect to see him ... I think it's important for us to talk and I'm glad he's coming.&quot; White House officials said it seemed likelier the Netanyahu visit might be early next week, however.</p>
<p>At the State Department, spokesman Nicholas Burns criticised Sunday's decision by Arab League foreign ministers to suspend normalisation of ties with Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;Surely it cannot be the right policy for the Arab countries to avoid Israel, to downgrade their relationships with Israel ... when finally, over the last couple of years, we've started to make ... progress,&quot; Burns said. &quot;... And surely, the Arab countries need to be serious about peace with Israel.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
