<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479058" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton asks FCC to study effects of liquor ads.</title>
<headline>Clinton asks FCC to study effects of liquor ads.</headline>
<byline>Arshad Mohammed</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton on Tuesday asked the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) to study curbing television liquor ads following the industry's decision to abandon its nearly half-century-old voluntary ban.</p>
<p>At a White House ceremony and in a letter to FCC Chairman Reed Hundt, Clinton said he wanted the independent federal agency to study what effect such ads would have on underage drinking and then to explore &quot;possible actions&quot; on the matter.</p>
<p>&quot;Liquor has no business with kids, and kids should have no business with liquor. Liquor ads on television would provide a message of encouragement to drink that young people simply don't need. Nothing good can come of it,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Clinton, who had criticised the industry's decision last year to end the voluntary ban in effect for television ads since 1948 and radio ads since 1936, told reporters that he hoped liquor manufacturers would rethink their position.</p>
<p>&quot;My message to the liquor industry is simple,&quot; he said. &quot;For 50 years you have kept the ban. It was the responsible thing to do. For the sake of our parents and our young people, please continue to keep that ban.&quot;</p>
<p>He added: &quot;Barring that, we will work to find ways to respond to the decison by the distilled spirits industry. We will do what we must do to support our parents, to help them do their jobs.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton's remarks, made in the White House Roosevelt Room, fit squarely with the family-oriented themes of his successful 1996 presidential campaign. They also reflected his increasing use of the White House as a bully pulpit on social issues in the tradition of former President Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
<p>The National Association of Broadcasters (NAB) immediately came out against his stance, citing the Constitution's First Amendment guarantee of freedom of speech.</p>
<p>&quot;The major broadcasters and virtually all group owners of radio and TV stations have said no to hard liquor ads, despite the spirits industry's decision to end its 50-year voluntary ban on broadcast advertising,&quot; it said. &quot;As strong defenders of the First Amendment, we remain staunchly opposed to government efforts to dictate appropriate forms of speech.&quot;</p>
<p>The Distilled Spirits Council, an industry group, issued a statement arguing that it was unfair and inaccurate to draw a distinction between advertising for hard liquor and for beer and wine, whose ads were not covered by the voluntary ban and have run on television for decades.</p>
<p>But Clinton dismissed this as a rationale for liquor advertising, saying the use of alcohol should not be promoted. &quot;At a minimum, there should be no backsliding,&quot; he said. &quot;There is something to be said for not making matters worse.&quot;</p>
<p>In addition to his remarks, Clinton made his case in a letter to FCC Chairman Hundt which the White House released.</p>
<p>Without specifying precisely what he wanted the FCC to do, Clinton urged the independent federal agency which regulates the broadcast industry to look into what effect the ban's ending may have and then to study &quot;appropriate actions.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I urge the Commission to take all appropriate actions to explore what effects might ensue in light of the decision by manufacturers of hard liquor to abandon their longstanding voluntary ban on television advertising, specifically the impact on underage drinking,&quot; Clinton wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;I would appreciate your help and (that) of the Commission in exploring the possible actions you could take to support our parents and children in response to the manufacturers' decision to break with the long and honourable tradition of not advertising on the broadcast medium,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hundt said in a statement the appropriate FCC response would be &quot;to issue a Notice of Inquiry that raises all the questions about hard liquor ads on TV so that we can base any recommendations for actions on the record we will develop.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
