<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479029" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Mideast violence surges, Clinton to meet Netanyahu.</title>
<headline>Mideast violence surges, Clinton to meet Netanyahu.</headline>
<byline>Danny Gur-arieh</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1996-04-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spiralling violence between Israelis and Palestinians has jeopardised peacemaking and prompted a pledge from President Bill Clinton to get involved personally.</p>
<p>Four Palestinians were killed on Tuesday in the bloodiest single day since peace moves hit a snag last month when Israel started building a new Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Israeli officials said Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu would meet Clinton in Washington early next week for the first time since the violence erupted.</p>
<p>&quot;We've got to try to keep the lid on things over there ... It is not going to be easy,&quot; Clinton said after meeting Jordan's King Hussein in the White House.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm prepared personally to do anything I can to get this process back on track and move it forward, but I think the less I say about it the more likely I am to have some success in doing that,&quot; Clinton told reporters.</p>
<p>In the Palestinian-ruled Gaza Strip, two Palestinians were killed in explosions that Israel said were botched suicide bombings aimed at Jewish school children.</p>
<p>Hours later, Israeli forces shot dead two Palestinians in separate incidents in the West Bank as violence flared for a 13th straight day.</p>
<p>Hamas and the Islamic Jihad, groups whose militants have killed scores of Israelis in suicide bombings, said Israel was behind the blasts and vowed to take revenge.</p>
<p>&quot;Qassam will not hesitate to respond to the Zionist crimes painfully and quickly in the heart of Tel Aviv and the biggest cities of the Zionist entity,&quot; said a leaflet issued by Izz el-Deen al-Qassam, Hamas's military wing.</p>
<p>The blasts occurred around 7 a.m. (0400 GMT) as settlers and school children were leaving the isolated enclaves of Kfar Darom and Netzarim south of Gaza City.</p>
<p>Palestinian security sources identified the two dead Palestinians as Anwar al-Shabrawi, 21, and Abdullah Ramadan al-Madhoun, 19, both from Jabalya. Israel Television said an anonymous caller claimed responsibility on behalf of the Islamic Jihad.</p>
<p>The violence mirrored a war of words between Israeli and Arab leaders that has erupted since Netanyahu broke ground for the settlement designed to tighten Israel's grip on Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Egypt, the first Arab state to make peace with Israel, said the settlement had brought roller-coaster Middle East peacemaking to a 20-year low point.</p>
<p>Netanyahu shot back, accusing Egypt of fomenting anti-Israel sentiment in the Arab world, which was considering a freeze on normalising ties and re-instating an economic boycott of the Jewish state. It was the harshest exchange in years.</p>
<p>Western officials said Washington was trying to put together a package of measures to defuse Israeli-Palestinian tensions. These would include accelerating talks on a final settlement of the 100-year-old Jewish-Arab conflict and an Israeli pledge to curb settlement.</p>
<p>The U.S. had hoped passions would cool on both sides after initial protests over the Jerusalem building project, but instead clashes have broken out in Palestinian towns and a Hamas suicide bomber killed three Israelis in a Tel Aviv cafe.</p>
<p>&quot;The prime minister has decided to make a quick visit to the U.S. beginning this Sunday night. The prime minister...is happy to have an opportunity to meet President Clinton,&quot; said Netanyahu's office in a statement, adding that he would also meet administration officials and congressmen.</p>
<p>The U.S. has sponsored the talks since a 1991 Middle East peace conference in Madrid.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
