<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479033" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Family of murdered nurse reject mercy plea.</title>
<headline>Family of murdered nurse reject mercy plea.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Drees</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The brother of an Australian nurse murdered in Saudi Arabia brushed off on Tuesday what his lawyers said was an appeal for mercy by the attorney of two British nurses charged with the killing.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not going to be pushed around by the defence lawyers or the press regarding what to do here,&quot; Frank Gilford, 58, said in a statement issued by his lawyers in Saudi Arabia, the International Law Firm.</p>
<p>&quot;I am surprised, though, that their lawyers are making this appeal before there has been a trial,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Salah al-Hejailan -- the lawyer of Deborah Parry, 41, and Lucille McLauchlan, 31, who were charged with murdering colleague Yvonne Gilford -- denied he had issued a clemency appeal.</p>
<p>&quot;That is absolutely not true,&quot; Hejailan told Reuters.</p>
<p>Robert Thoms, a lawyer in Hejailan's firm, confirmed a document had been sent to Gilford's lawyers in Riyadh, but said it was &quot;a rationale for the early waiver of the death penalty&quot; and not an appeal for mercy.</p>
<p>Under Islamic sharia law, which is enforced in Saudi Arabia, people convicted of premeditated murder are normally subject to the death penalty unless the victim's family grants clemency.</p>
<p>Parry and Mclauchlan were charged with murdering their 55-year-old colleague in her dormitory room at the King Fahd military medical complex in the oil-rich city of Dhahran on December 11. She had been stabbed, bludgeoned and suffocated.</p>
<p>No date for a trial has been set.</p>
<p>&quot;(The document) was given to the lawyers of Mr Gilford in Riyadh for the sole purpose of passing it to Mr Gilford for his private reflection,&quot; Thomas said.</p>
<p>Hejailan had been quoted by Saudi papers in January as saying he would appeal to the victim's family for mercy.</p>
<p>Gilford's family in Australia had previously ruled out clemency, saying the two should face the maximum punishment.</p>
<p>Attorney Jim Phipps of the International Law Firm said the 17-page document was signed by Hejailan and dated March 27.</p>
<p>&quot;This was a mercy appeal and our client has responded to the extent that he wishes to at this time,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Saudi police said the nurses confessed to the murder and the confessions had been filed with a board of three judges.</p>
<p>But Hejailan's firm said the women had withdrawn their confessions, and one of them had retracted a statement saying she had a lesbian relationship with the victim. The women said the confessions had been extracted under duress, the firm said.</p>
<p>The International Law Firm said Gilford responded to the nurses' claims of duress with disbelief.</p>
<p>&quot;How can I take their claim seriously when their own lawyer says the authorities have been fair,&quot; Gilford said in the statement.</p>
<p>Hejailan has maintained that the nurses have been treated well since their arrest.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not at all inconsistent that the nurses maintain that the confession was given under duress but to say overall that the treatment of the nurses has been fair and balanced,&quot; Thoms said on Tuesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
