<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479017" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Shanghai T-bill repo rates end down, spots up.</title>
<headline>Shanghai T-bill repo rates end down, spots up.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Contracts on the treasury bill repurchase market in Shanghai closed down across the board on Tuesday on a powerful technical correction after sharp rises on Monday, traders said.</p>
<p>The annual rate for the most active seven-day contract plunged to 11.4 percent from 30 percent on Monday.</p>
<p>Total turnover of the six-contract market fell to 7.2 million lots from 13.1 million.</p>
<p>One lot is 1,000 yuan face value of treasury bills.</p>
<p>&quot;The correction has been expected after surges on Monday as the (domestic) A share bull run continues,&quot; a trader said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Despite today's fall, the performance of the A share markets will continue to be the biggest single market-moving factor for the repo contracts,&quot; said a second trader.</p>
<p>&quot;Continued heavy issues of new A shares are expected to support the repo rates in the medium term,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Contracts on the T-bill spot market in Shanghai ended up across the board due to a strong technical rebound supported by high yields of the existing countract after successive losses in the past few weeks, traders said.</p>
<p>The most active 10-year bond maturing in 2006 rose to 117.40 yuan from 116.29 yuan.  </p>
<p>Combined volume of the seven-contract market more than doubled to 1.9 million lots. Spot prices had fallen in recent weeks with the active A share markets sucking money out of the spot market.</p>
<p>But the contracts now have an average yield of around 10 percent per year, much higher than the 7.47 percent rate for one-year bank deposits, supporting Tuesday's technical rebound, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Market sentiment is good because of the high yields,&quot; said one trader. &quot;But the rising A share markets have indicated even higher returns in the past few weeks. The perfomance of the A markets will continue to be a key factor in the near term.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
