<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479026" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel, PLO trade blame in Gaza explosions.</title>
<headline>Israel, PLO trade blame in Gaza explosions.</headline>
<byline>Taher Shriteh</byline>
<dateline>DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two Palestinians were killed in blasts in the Gaza Strip on Tuesday which Israel said were botched suicide bombings aimed at Jewish school children.</p>
<p>The PLO charged Israeli troops were behind one of the blasts which came against a backdrop of crumbling Middle East peace moves and Israeli accusations Palestinian President Yasser Arafat has failed to curb militants in areas of the West Bank and Gaza under his control.</p>
<p>In separate incidents in the West Bank, Israeli forces shot dead two Palestinians as violence flared for a 13th straight day over the building of a Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>The Israeli army said two bombers died in separate attacks near isolated Jewish settlement enclaves in self-ruled Gaza. Palestinians conceded one of the dead men blew himself up but said the other was killed by a bomb or grenade thrown from an Israeli jeep. No Israelis were hurt in the incidents.</p>
<p>Near Kfar Darom settlement, a Palestinian dressed in military uniform was ripped apart and five Arab taxi passengers were wounded in the morning explosion on the main Gaza-Rafah road near Deir al-Balah refugee camp.</p>
<p>&quot;In Kfar Darom area an Israeli military jeep hurled a grenade or a bomb at (Palestinian) passersby killing one and wounding others. This is information that we have collected from passersby and victims,&quot; Ahmed Abdel-Rahman, secretary-general of the Palestinian cabinet, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The Israeli army rejected the Palestinian account.</p>
<p>&quot;It is absolutely incorrect. There were two suicide attacks and two bombs,&quot; an army spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>Earlier, Palestinian police officials said that a man with five kg (11 lb) of explosives on his back blew himself up on the side of the road at 7 a.m. (0400 GMT) about two km (1.5 miles) from the Jewish settlement of Netzarim south of Gaza City.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's twin attacks ... are proof that the terror campaign continues,&quot; Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;The terrorist organisations ... continue to understand they have a green light from the Palestinian Authority to perpetrate their savagery,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu said a PLO crackdown on militants was a precondition to any progress in peace talks: &quot;It so far has not done so and if peace is to survive it must do so immediately.&quot;</p>
<p>The militant Hamas and Islamic Jihad groups denied they were behind the explosions, accusing Israel of ordering the blasts to sour relations between Hamas and the Palestinian Authority.</p>
<p>&quot;This bombing was done by the Israeli intelligence and its (Palestinian) collaborators in an attempt to create an internal problem between the Islamic movement and the Palestinian Authority,&quot; Hamas official Sayed Abu Musameh told Reuters.</p>
<p>Israel Television said an anonymous caller claimed responsibility for the attacks on behalf of the Islamic Jihad and identified the two bombers as Abdallah Ramadan al-Madhoun and Anwar Ahmad al-Shabrawi.</p>
<p>The report said one of the militants worked for the Palestinian preventive security service in Gaza.</p>
<p>Both Gaza explosions occurred around 7 a.m., the time Israeli children leave two nearby Jewish settlements on buses for school, Jewish settlers said.</p>
<p>&quot;We can suppose that the operative goal at that hour was school buses or settler commuters who go to work at that hour,&quot; Israeli Southern Commander Shlomo Yanai said.</p>
<p>Last month an anonymous caller told police Hamas had carried out a suicide bombing in Tel Aviv in which three Israeli women were killed. The PLO denies it has given a &quot;green light&quot; to militants.</p>
<p>In the West Bank town of Nablus, Israeli soldiers shot and killed Palestinian policeman Haitham Mansour, 20, during clashes between stone-throwing Palestinians and Israeli troops, witnesses said. Mansour was not in uniform when he was shot.</p>
<p>&quot;The brain itself was outside the skull,&quot; Arab surgeon Husam Jamhara told Reuters. Hospital officials said five Palestinians were treated for live or rubber bullet wounds in the clashes.</p>
<p>Mansour, his body shrouded in a Palestinian flag, was buried later on Tuesday to a 21-gun salute and full military honours.</p>
<p>In a second incident, an Arab teenager identified as Kamal al-Zaro was shot dead in Hebron. The Israeli army said soldiers spotted several Arabs engaging in theft. It said all but one fled in a car and that troops shot him as he fled on foot.</p>
<p>&quot;The suspect did not stop and soldiers fired at him,&quot; an army spokesman said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
