<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479080" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S., EU face off in meat export fight.</title>
<headline>U.S., EU face off in meat export fight.</headline>
<byline>Maggie McNeil</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A trans-Atlantic dispute over meat inspection procedures blew up Tuesday into a full-fledged trade fight as Washington acted to cut off imports of European Union meat, and the EU effectively halted incoming shipments of U.S. poultry.</p>
<p>The moves were expected to disrupt the bilateral trade of hundreds of millions of dollars worth of meat, poultry and dairy products for at least several months, but officials on both sides promised they would try to settle the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;We intend to continue to work to reach an acceptable agreement in the coming months and to minimise trade disruptions to the extent possible,&quot; U.S. Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said in a statement announcing the action.</p>
<p>But Glickman said he was disappointed that after three years of negotiations a deal could not be brokered, and U.S. industry officials applauded the administration's stance.</p>
<p>&quot;We strongly support the U.S. government's actions because we must live by science-based agreements if the global trading system is to work,&quot; said Nick Giordano of the National Pork Producers Council.</p>
<p>The U.S. poultry industry angrily accused Europe of hiding behind a &quot;smoke screen&quot; of unfounded concerns over U.S. meat and poultry inspection methods in an effort to illegally block sales of U.S. goods.</p>
<p>&quot;It is hard to understand how the EU can refuse to accept U.S. inspection when we are in the midst of implementing the most modern, most science-based meat inspection system in the world,&quot; said Jim Rieth of the National Turkey Federation.</p>
<p>But in Brussels, Belgium, EU officials said the U.S. action against European meat exports was unjustified on health grounds and regrettable.</p>
<p>Sparking the blow-up was the inability of U.S. and EU officials to settle an old dispute over meat import inspection standards. Agreement on the so-called veterinary equivalency issue would allow each side to accept meat and poultry products from the other even if inspection methods differ.</p>
<p>Negotiators had worked all last week to beat an April 1 deadline by which the EU said it would implement new inspection standards for U.S. poultry shipments that the American industry says are unfair and cannot be met.</p>
<p>Washington had warned it would play hardball if the EU took such action, and on Tuesday both sides lived up to their threats.</p>
<p>As promised, the EU imposed new rules throughout its 15 member nations that would require U.S. poultry and meat exporters to meet European inspection standards.</p>
<p>Affected almost immediately will be some $100 million worth of U.S. poultry, dairy and egg shipments normally sold to the EU.</p>
<p>Paul Drazek, senior trade advisor at the Agriculture Department, said the United States will no longer provide export certificates for the shipments because of the new rules.</p>
<p>Washington quickly slapped the EU with new requirements that threaten to cut off some $300 million in annual meat imports from the EU. Most of those imports are Danish ham.</p>
<p>Under a new system to take effect immediately, over 100 European meat and poultry packing and processing plants will now have to meet U.S. inspection standards. U.S. officials said most of these plants will probably be taken off the Agriculture Department's approved list of exporters in the next few days.</p>
<p>Political pressures played a role on both sides of the Atlantic in the dispute.</p>
<p>In Europe, recent public concerns about Mad Cow disease and the official handling of the crisis has been high, and lawmakers there want to be seen as safeguarding public health.</p>
<p>In Washington, the administration is courting farm group support for fast-track trade authority, and needed to take an aggressive stance to support U.S. agricultural interests.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
