<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479005" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asia Product Swaps - Diesel up on new prompt demand.</title>
<headline>Asia Product Swaps - Diesel up on new prompt demand.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore gas oil swaps extended its early day rally late afternoon on Tuesday despite a weaker crude on expectations of continued physical purchases by a local trader.</p>
<p>&quot;Gas oil firmed because of what happened last night and people expect Hin Leong to continue buying,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>April gas oil was last quoted at $26.30/$26.50 per barrel up from Monday's $25.85/$26.00, brokers said.</p>
<p>The market traded earlier in the day at $26.30 and $26.40 per barrel, they said.  </p>
<p>May gas oil was last quoted at $25.25/$25.35, up about 30 cents from Monday. May gas oil traded at $25.00 and $25.05 while April/May was traded at $1.00 per barrel compared to the 85 cents traded late last week.</p>
<p>Traders said most players expected local trader Hin Leong to continue buying physical cargoes at least for another week and the higher swaps prices were a reflection of this.</p>
<p>On Monday, Hin Leong bought four cargoes of 150,000-barrels each at between $26.50 and 26.80 per barrel for end April lifting, free-on-board Singapore, taking their purchase tally to nearly 7.0 million barrels since March 3.  </p>
<p>The hikes came despite a 30 cent fall to May Brent crude prices on London's International Petroleum Exchange to last trade at $19.08 per barrel.</p>
<p>Overnight May WTI crude on NYMEX fell 29 cents to $20.40 per barrel.</p>
<p>The jet fuel/gas oil spread or regrade was quoted unchanged at -50/-30 cents. April regrade traded earlier Tuesday at -43 cents, brokers said.</p>
<p>Fuel oil swaps were also quoted unchanged in quiet trade with April seen at $99.50/$100.50. Brokers said it traded earlier in the day at $99.50 and $99.75 per tonne.  </p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom (+65-870 3093)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
