<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479094" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. judicial officer draws Ellis Island boundaries.</title>
<headline>U.S. judicial officer draws Ellis Island boundaries.</headline>
<byline>James Vicini</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Supreme Court-appointed officer on Tuesday proposed what he said was a &quot;workable&quot; solution to settle a dispute between New York and New Jersey over ownership of Ellis Island, the landmark U.S. immigration processing centre from 1892 to the mid-20th century.</p>
<p>Law professor Paul Verkuil, in a 168-page report, recommended New York keep ownership over the most historic part of Ellis Island but New Jersey get the bulk of the land.</p>
<p>He said New York should keep jurisdiction of about five acres (2 hectares) including the main building where the immigration processing once took place while New Jersey should get most of the landfill portions, about 22 acres (9 hectares) that were added to the island over the years.</p>
<p>While Ellis Island, now a museum run by the National Park Service and visited by millions every year, has fallen within New York borders since the 17th century, New Jersey sued in 1993, claiming parts of it. Verkuil was named to hear the case and conducted a 23-day trial last summer, hearing witnesses and considering nearly 2,000 documents entered into evidence.</p>
<p>Verkuil said New York's territory should include the main immigration building, the land directly in front of it and a triangle-shaped area on the island's southeastern side. &quot;The proposed remedy resolves several issues of concern. First and foremost, it is a workable and clean boundary line,&quot; he wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;Second, it retains the time-honoured connection between the main building -- the immigration locus -- on the original island and the city of New York.</p>
<p>&quot;Moreover, because the restored main building remains part of New York and the ferry slip in front of it will still be New York's territory, visitors coming from the Battery on the Statute of Liberty/Ellis Island ferries will continue to land on New York territory,&quot; Verkuil said in his report.</p>
<p>But he said New Jersey should get the land that was added to the original island, created by landfill between 1890 and 1934, and deserved a shared role in the island's operations. He said New York has jurisdiction over Ellis Island as it existed when a 1834 agreement was reached but failed to meet the burden of proof to show it acquired the landfill portions.</p>
<p>&quot;New Jersey has won a major decision,&quot; state Attorney General Peter Verniero said. &quot;This is the first time that it has been acknowledged that New Jersey owns one of the great symbols of America.&quot;</p>
<p>New York's Attorney General, Dennis Vacco, issued a scathing statement criticising the recommendation, saying it &quot;defies common sense, ignores the law and rewrites history.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Verkuil &quot;rejected the truth that, beyond our legal proof, New York's claim to Ellis Island is clearly and indelibly inscribed in the hearts and beliefs of the millions of immigrants who set foot here.&quot;</p>
<p>Vacco vowed to challenge the recommendation before the Supreme Court. The justices may decide to hear oral arguments in the long-running legal battle in their term that begins in October, and will have the final word in the boundary dispute.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
