<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479054" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dow ends slightly higher in small rebound.</title>
<headline>Dow ends slightly higher in small rebound.</headline>
<byline>Richard Melville</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Blue-chip stocks closed moderately higher on Tuesday in a small rebound after a sharp two-session sell-off sparked by fears that the Federal Reserve will raise interest rates again soon.</p>
<p>The Dow Jones industrial average rose 27.57 points to 6,611.05. Analysts were quick to caution, however, that the gains wiped out only a small fraction of the nearly 300-point loss the Dow index has suffered since last Thursday.</p>
<p>Several said that despite the welcome respite, the outlook will remain extremely uncertain, at least as long as the questions that triggered the decline go unanswered.</p>
<p>&quot;My sense is we're still in the midst of a painful period that still has a way to go,&quot; said Alan Ackerman, market strategist at Fahnestock &amp; Co. &quot;But there's still a lot of uncertainty ahead and will be until we have a better handle on what the Federal Reserve will do next.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts noted that pharmaceutical and finance stocks posted a solid day, notable because the groups have led the market's roller-coaster ride this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The two leadership groups, banks and drugs, were trying to reassert their leadership today,&quot; said Scott Bleier, chief investment strategist at Prime Charter Ltd.</p>
<p>Chase Manhattan Corp. gained 1-5/8 to 95-1/2, Citicorp rose 4-1/4 to 112-1/2 and Dow component J.P. Morgan &amp; Co. Inc. added 1-5/8 to 99-7/8.</p>
<p>Among drug companies, Dow stock Merck &amp; Co. Inc. rose 2-3/8 to 86-5/8 and Pfizer Inc. rose 7/8 to 85.</p>
<p>Another key sector, technology, failed to shake off the effects of its malaise. Analysts said any real reversal in the downturn would likely first take root among tech stocks.</p>
<p>&quot;I think anyone watching for a bottom should watch the techs,&quot; said Richard Cripps, chief market strategist at Legg Mason Wood Walker. &quot;Last July, the techs were the first group to go lower, first to bottom and first to turn higher again,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>While the group as a whole failed to match the modest rally in blue chips, some of the sector's bellwether stocks did show signs of life. Microsoft Corp. rose 1-9/16 to 93-1/4 and Intel Corp. rose 3/16 to 139-5/16.</p>
<p>Bonds rose despite a stronger-than-expected National Association of Purchasing Management report.</p>
<p>The key 30-year Treasury bond rose 8/32, or $2.50 on a $1,000 bond. Its yield, which moves in the opposite direction of the price, edged down to 7.08 percent from 7.10 percent at Monday's close.</p>
<p>But with critical monthly payrolls, wage and unemployment data due Friday, the interest rate outlook remains far from clear, leaving market matters looking anything but certain.</p>
<p>&quot;We're probably going to have more days like today for a while, up 20 points and then down 20,&quot; Bleier said. &quot;But if rates go through 7.20 percent, all bets are off.&quot;</p>
<p>Among individual issues, database software firm Informix Corp. sank 5-7/32 to 9-29/32 and electronic systems design software maker Quickturn Design Systems Inc. lost 7-3/4 to 8-1/4, both after profit warnings.</p>
<p>Catalina Marketing Corp., a provider of in-store electronic marketing programmes for consumer-goods companies, sank 10-3/4 to 29-7/8, also after warning of disappointing quarterly results.</p>
<p>Embattled Canadian mining company Bre-X Minerals Ltd. rebounded a bit, rising 3/4 to 2-1/2 on Nasdaq after being halted all day Monday. Frantic trading in the stock caused computers at the Toronto Stock Exchange to crash.</p>
<p>The Nasdaq Composite index fell 4.77 points to 1,216.93.</p>
<p>The Standard &amp; Poor's composite index of 500 stocks edged up 2.52 points to 759.64. The American Stock Exchange index lost 2.44 to 566.27.</p>
<p>The NYSE Composite index of all listed common stocks rose 1.25 to 399.80. The average share was up 12 cents.</p>
<p>The Wilshire Associates Equity Index -- the market value of NYSE, American and Nasdaq issues -- was 7,222.417, up 8.886, or 0.12 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
