<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479018" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesian success with hybrid corn seen limited.</title>
<headline>Indonesian success with hybrid corn seen limited.</headline>
<byline>K.T. Arasu</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia will remain dependent on corn imports this year despite the introduction of a high-yielding hybrid variety, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>They said local feedmills were believed to have locked in imports of at least 500,000 tonnes of corn, mostly from South America and the United States, for arrivals in the early part of the third quarter of this year.</p>
<p>Traders also said the hybrid corn was not expected to boost production significantly.</p>
<p>&quot;I think news about hybrid production in Indonesia is a bit ... overstated,&quot; one senior trader told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Output has been disappointing due to farmers' reluctance to grow the variety or their inability to follow procedures such as proper fertilising to ensure good yields,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Agriculture Ministry had said the government aimed to reduce imports of corn, also known as maize, this year by extensively planting a hybrid variety, whose yields could be as much as three times the 2.2 to 2.5 tonnes per hectare of ordinary varieties.</p>
<p>A ministry official told Reuters in January that a total of 885,000 hectares would be planted with the hybrid variety this year, and another 900,000 hectares in 1998.</p>
<p>He said Indonesia's corn production was expected to rise to 9.2 million tonnes this year from 8.0 million in 1996, when imports amounted to some 1.6 million tonnes.</p>
<p>&quot;Indonesia's quest for self-sufficiency in corn is pretty much in the very early stage,&quot; one trader said. &quot;I have been getting feedback from the industry that corn production from the hybrid variety has not been up to official expectations.</p>
<p>&quot;The seeds are expensive, and fertiliser costs are high while at the same time they have to compete with imported corn from countries such as China and the United States,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The trader said local feedmills had ordered at least 500,000 tonnes of corn for arrival in the early part of the third quarter of this year, adding that some 400,000 tonnes were were scheduled for arrival in the second quarter.</p>
<p>&quot;My estimate is that Indonesia will import about the same amount of corn this year as it did in 1996,&quot; he said. &quot;Demand in the feedmeal sector is growing steadily, and growing affluence will see more Indonesians eating chicken.&quot;</p>
<p>Corn is used to produce animal feed, and is also consumed by humans in the form of oil and as food.</p>
<p>The trader said annual per capita consumption of chicken in Indonesia, the world's fourth-most populous country with 200 million people, was some 3.5 kg, just half the amount in the Philippines and among the lowest in booming Southeast Asia.</p>
<p>Another trader said there were some farmers in East Java who were not keen on switching to hybrid corn.</p>
<p>&quot;The farmers feel the corn they grow has a sweet taste and will have better market access than the hybrid variety,&quot; he said. &quot;It's things like this that are affecting the increased cultivation of hybrid corn in some places.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
