<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479095" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Snow buries New England, thousands lose power.</title>
<headline>Snow buries New England, thousands lose power.</headline>
<byline>Leslie Gevirtz</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>An early spring blizzard buried New England and the Northeast under nearly three feet (90 cm) of heavy, wet snow that downed power lines, closed airports and was blamed for causing three deaths.</p>
<p>Forecasters were receiving reports of up to 35 inches (88 cm) of snow in parts of Massachusetts and the Catskills region of New York, with accumulations of 18 inches (46 cm) to two feet (61 cm) in large sections of Connecticut, New Hampshire and Rhode Island.</p>
<p>Massachusetts Gov. William Weld declared a state of emergency, telling non-essential state workers to stay home. In Boston, Mayor Thomas Menino ordered City Hall, buried under two feet (61 cm) of snow, closed. And in New Hampshire, the legislature voted not to open on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Day care centres, schools and colleges in the region were closed as were most businesses in central and western Massachusetts. Hundreds of thousands of residents from Pennsylvania to parts of Maine remained without power.</p>
<p>&quot;It is still quite a vicious storm and it is continuing,&quot; Massachusetts Emergency Management Agency executive director Peter LaPorte said.</p>
<p>Boston, which closed off most of its subway system and halted bus service for the first time in 20 years, was still struggling at midday to open Logan International Airport. Airport officials had hoped to have one runway cleared for emergencies by 10 a.m., but that time passed with little progress. Snow continued to fall at Logan where accumulation topped 20 inches (51 cm) and strong winds piled drifts up to to eight feet (240 cm).</p>
<p>Hartford's Bradley International Airport was re-opened at about 10 a.m. EST (1500 GMT) after being closed for more than 12 hours.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, state police in the region reported hundreds of stranded cars, trucks and minor accidents as they continued their struggle to clear interstate highways and roads. New York State police blamed the weather for the death of a 36-year-old man in a traffic accident in the Catskill region late on Monday.</p>
<p>Thousands of stranded travelers spent the night in temporary shelters in northeastern Pennsylvania and Chester County in suburban Philadelphia as snowfall totals ranged from six inches (13 cm) to as much as two feet (61 cm). By Tuesday morning, the snow was rapidly melting, although high winds were expected.</p>
<p>Around 14,000 homes in the Philadelphia area lost power and 10,000 remained without service.</p>
<p>In New York, both Con Edison and the Long Island Lighting Co reported several thousand customers were without power. But the largest blackouts were in Massachusetts and Connecticut.</p>
<p>Two of the three power lines that provide electricity to Cape Cod's 300,000 residents were out and Commonwealth Electric officials were carefully monitoring the third line.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Boston Edison reported 50,000 of its customers were without electricity and it would be up to a week before all service was restored, a spokesman said.</p>
<p>Northeast Utilities, which serves Connecticut and western Massachusetts, reported 100,000 customers without power, while Massachusetts Electric, a subsidiary of the New England Electric System, reported another 96,000 in the dark.</p>
<p>Public Service of New Hampshire and Central Maine Power also reported scattered outages totalling 8,000 customers.</p>
<p>In Maine, which was spared the storm's most vicious wrath, two fishermen died when their vessel capsized at Lubec near the New Brunswick border. Officials there blamed the deaths on the storm's severe winds, which topped 65 mph (104 kph) along parts of the New England coast.</p>
<p>The storm, which continued to lash Boston and eastern Massachusetts at midday, was expected to taper off by late afternoon.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
