<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479030" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: PLO official says Israeli govt should be toppled.</title>
<headline>PLO official says Israeli govt should be toppled.</headline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior Palestinian official said on Tuesday Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's government should be toppled to protect Israel's interests.</p>
<p>Nabil Shaath, minister for planning and international cooperation in the Palestinian National Authority, also told reporters the United States was shirking from its responsibility as a sponsor of the peace process.</p>
<p>&quot;The current Israeli government has lost for Israel all the benefits of peace that were beginning to come forth under the previous government... it must be toppled to protect Israel's interests,&quot; Shaath said ater meeting Egyptian Foreign Minister Amr Moussa.</p>
<p>On Monday the Arab League recommended freezing links with Israel and reactivating a trade boycott in a show of unified Arab anger at Israel's decision last month to start building a Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Netanyahu brushed off the decision as &quot;absurd&quot; and said Arabs were ganging up against his country.</p>
<p>&quot;The Arab resolution has made Netanyahu completely lose his balance,&quot; Shaath said.</p>
<p>The Palestinian official said the United States should take a more assertive role to solve the crisis that has erupted since Israel's unilateral decision to build the settlement in disputed East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>&quot;The American position until now is weak and hesitant and is not up to the level of responsibility of America as a sponsor of the peace process,&quot; Shaath said.</p>
<p>&quot;We urge the United States to bear its responsibility.&quot;</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton said on Tuesday he was &quot;prepared personally to do anything I can&quot; to rescue the Middle East peace process, possibly including a meeting with Netanyahu this weekend.</p>
<p>Shaath said he would meet French Foreign Minister Herve de Charette in Paris on Wednesday &quot;in our conviction of the importance of a continued high-level European role&quot;.</p>
<p>Arabs welcome a more prominent role for the European Union in the Middle East peace process, hoping it will offset what they see as the pro-Israeli bias of the United States.</p>
<p>France on Tuesday urged Israelis and Palestinians to resume talks to dispel a crisis in their relations and warned the peace process was in danger.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
