<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479028" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Gaza bombs, war of words, mire Mideast peace.</title>
<headline>Gaza bombs, war of words, mire Mideast peace.</headline>
<byline>Robert Mahoney</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Suicide bombings in Gaza, the shooting deaths of two Palestinians in the West Bank and a war of words between Israel and Arab states pushed Middle East peacemaking closer to the edge on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Israel said two men in Palestinian police uniforms blew themselves up in separate attacks aimed at Jewish settlers in the PLO-ruled Gaza Strip. One of the men wore a belt of explosives. No Israelis were hurt.</p>
<p>Palestinian security officials said one man was a suicide bomber but they blamed Israeli soldiers for killing the second man and wounding five Palestinians in a taxi with a grenade.</p>
<p>In the West Bank, Israeli soldiers shot a plainclothes Palestinian policeman in the head during clashes with stone-throwers after a protest march in Nablus. Soldiers also shot dead a Palestinian teenager at a checkpoint in Hebron.</p>
<p>Youths hurled rocks at troops in Jenin and Qalqilya. They replied with rubber bullets and tear gas. It was the 13th consecutive day of unrest in Palestinian areas, the most sustained protests since the 1993 Israel-PLO peace accord.</p>
<p>The violence mirrored a war of words between Israeli and Arab leaders that has erupted since Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu broke ground for a Jewish settlement designed to tighten Israel's grip on Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Egypt, the first Arab state to make peace with Israel, said the settlement had brought roller-coaster Middle East peacemaking to a 20-year low point.</p>
<p>Netanyahu shot back, accusing Egypt of fomenting anti-Israel sentiment in the Arab world, which was considering a freeze on normalising ties and re-instating an economic boycott of the Jewish state. It was the harshest exchange in years.</p>
<p>In Washington, Jordan's King Hussein prepared to meet President Bill Clinton in an attempt to prevent a collapse of the process launched in Madrid six years ago to bring Israel's four other Arab neigbours to sign peace treaties similar to Egypt's.</p>
<p>On the eve of the White House meeting Clinton received a &quot;sober&quot; report on the Middle East from U.S. diplomatic troubleshooter Dennis Ross.</p>
<p>Ross failed in two days of separate talks with Palestinian President Yasser Arafat and Netanyahu last week to broker a resumption of contacts between the two leaders who Western diplomats say no longer trust each other.</p>
<p>Netanyahu said he was weighing a trip to Washington next week to seek U.S. help out of the impasse.</p>
<p>Western officials said Washington was trying to put together a package of measures to defuse Israeli-Palestinian tensions. These would include accelerating talks on a final settlement of the 100-year-old Jewish-Arab conflict and an Israeli pledge to curb settlement.</p>
<p>The U.S. had hoped passions would cool on both sides after initial protests over the Jerusalem building project but instead clashes have broken out in Palestinian towns and a Hamas suicide bomber killed three Israelis in a Tel Aviv cafe.</p>
<p>Hamas, an Islamic fundamentalist group, denied it was behind the two Gaza explosions. It accused Israel of orchestrating the blasts to damage relations between Islamic groups and Arafat's self-rule Palestinian Authority. The Islamic Jihad group also denied responsibility.</p>
<p>Arafat said one man had blown himself up and accused Israeli soldiers of killing the other. The Israeli army rejected Palestinian reports that a soldier had thrown a grenade or bomb.</p>
<p>Netanyahu seized on the Gaza incidents as evidence that Arafat had given a green light to Hamas and the smaller Moslem group Islamic Jihad to attack Israelis.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's twin attacks miraculously did not claim lives but they are proof that the terror campaign continues and that the light hasn't changed,&quot; Netanyahu told reporters. &quot;We think that what has to be done -- right now -- is that the Palestinian Authority fulfil its most basic commitment...to fight terrorism.&quot;</p>
<p>Arafat said a further crackdown could backfire.</p>
<p>&quot;What will be the reaction from our side, to control more and more? For every pressure there is a reaction. This is natural law,&quot; Arafat told a meeting in Gaza.</p>
<p>The blasts occurred around 7 a.m. (0400 GMT) as settlers and school children were leaving the isolated enclaves of Kfar Darom and Netzarim south of Gaza City.</p>
<p>Hamas official Sayed Abu Musameh blamed Israel for the blasts.</p>
<p>&quot;This bombing was done by the Israeli intelligence and its (Palestinian) collaborators in an attempt to create an internal problem between the Islamic movement and the Palestinian Authority,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>On the political front Netanyahu said he was considering forming a unity coalition government with the Labour opposition and other parties to achieve a &quot;wide national front&quot; for a final peace deal.</p>
<p>&quot;The big question is whether a unity government would create such a front or break it. Would it be a government of unity or two governments,&quot;' he told Army radio.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
