<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479001" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: KL shares end with extended losses on Dow's fall.</title>
<headline>KL shares end with extended losses on Dow's fall.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kuala Lumpur shares closed with extended losses, in sympathy with weaker regional markets after a 157-point drop on Wall Street overnight, dealers said.</p>
<p>Market sentiment had already been affected by Bank Negara's curbs on lending to property and share buying, announced last Friday. &quot;There was some technical buying but it did not follow through in the afternoon. Sentiment is weak at the moment,&quot; said a Mayban Securities dealer.</p>
<p>The Composite Index of 100 large-capitalised stocks ended down 15.33 points at 1,187.77. The index hit its lowest level in three-and-a-half months of 1,182.65 in early trade.  </p>
<p>Dealers said shares would remain weak on Wednesday if the Dow fell further.</p>
<p>Analysts said some investors expect the U.S. Federal Reserve to continue tightening interest rates through the year, and that should cap the U.S. stockmarket.</p>
<p>Banking and property stocks remained under selling pressure following the central bank curbs.</p>
<p>Malayan Banking, Arab-Malaysian Merchant Bank, Commerce-Asset, Bandar Raya and Land &amp; General fell between 18 and 80 cents each.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
