<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479003" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Korea gold prices up on brisk demand, falling won.</title>
<headline>Korea gold prices up on brisk demand, falling won.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea's domestic gold prices rose over the past week, buoyed by rising industrial demand and by the steady slide of the won against the U.S. dollar, bullion traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The local unit fell despite news the government would take steps to boost the local currency, the traders said.</p>
<p>Traders said industrial demand was seen picking up recently, but the amount has been limited due to a downturn in the local economy.  </p>
<p>&quot;We have seen continued demand for industrial use, especially for catalytic converters, in past weeks,&quot; a dealer with Tong Yang Global said.</p>
<p>The won slid on Tuesday to 896.50 won against the dollar from 887.70 a week ago, with the country's growing trade deficit one of the main factors in its fall.</p>
<p>The telegraphic transfer selling rate for customers posted by the Korea Exchange Bank fell 9.0 won to 899.80 won to the the dollar from 890.80 won a week ago.</p>
<p>The rate is regarded as a benchmark for foreign exchange rates by local companies.  </p>
<p>South Korea's customs-cleared trade deficit widened to US$1.88 billion in March from a $446 million deficit in the same period last year.</p>
<p>South Korea's customs-cleared trade deficit totalled $7.43 billion in the first quarter of 1997, up from $4.17 billion in the same period last year.</p>
<p>Gold producer LG Metals' daily selling price for the yellow metal, regarded as a benchmark by the local bullion wholesale market, rose on Tuesday to 10,550 won per gram from 10,400 won a week ago.</p>
<p>It said silver was by two won to 162 won a gram.  </p>
<p>(US$1 = 899.80 won)</p>
<p>-- Jae Hur, Seoul Newsroom (822) 727 5651</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
