<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479016" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: NCB plan, Hokkaido merger to remove uncertainty - BOJ.</title>
<headline>NCB plan, Hokkaido merger to remove uncertainty - BOJ.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bank of Japan (BOJ) Governor Yasuo Matsushita said on Tuesday that the comprehensive restructuring of Nippon Credit Bank Ltd (NCB) and the merger of two banks in Hokkaido will contribute significantly to removing uncertainties from and ensuring credibility in the Japanese financial system.  </p>
<p>&quot;The two plans that were announced today...will contribute significantly, individually and collectively, to removing uncertainties from, and ensuring credibility in, the Japanese financial system,&quot; Matsushita said.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not believe any funding problem might arise with respect to these banks, but should there be a temporary liquidity shortage, we as the central bank are ready to provide the necessary support, as we have already made clear,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Matsushita added that the BOJ, in cooperation with the government, remained totally committed to maintaining the overall stability of the Japanese financial system.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd and Hokkaido Bank Ltd said earlier on Tuesday that they will merge by April next year with the aim of becoming a &quot;super-regional&quot; bank.  </p>
<p>Matsushita said measures taken by NCB and the two Hokkaido banks were significant in the sense that they represented voluntary action to prepare for coming reforms under Japan's &quot;Big Bang&quot; financial deregulation.</p>
<p>He said the BOJ, along with the Ministry of Finance, had decided to extend necessary support to NCB from the standpoint of maintaining the overall stability of the Japanese financial system.</p>
<p>The BOJ believed that restoring confidence in NCB by resolving its financial problems was an urgent task for the benefit of Japan's financial system, Matsushita said.</p>
<p>The credibility of NCB had significantly deteriorated in domestic and overseas markets since last autumn, but at the same time the bank had played an important role in those financial markets, in terms of the size and range of transactions.</p>
<p>So the BOJ believed it was necessary for NCB to deal with its financial difficulties quickly for market stability both at home and abroad, Matsushita said.  </p>
<p>&quot;It is considered indispensable to dispose of NCB's non-performing loans and reconstruct its capital base simultaneously...on condition that the bank strenuously pursues comprehensive restructuring,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At the strong request of the government, the BOJ had decided to help NCB reconstruct its capital base by utilising a special fund originally set up to deal with the bad loans of failed &quot;jusen&quot; mortgage firms, he said.</p>
<p>A total of 80 billion yen would be used from the jusen fund, he said.</p>
<p>Asked whether the BOJ saw a need to replenish the jusen fund, Matsushita said he did not see any need to do so at present.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81401">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
