<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479019" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan Macronix says no US patent infringement.</title>
<headline>Taiwan Macronix says no US patent infringement.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Macronix International Corp, a top Taiwan semiconductor maker, said on Tuesday it had never infringed on a patent as alleged in a complaint filed by Atmel Corp with the U.S. International Trade Commission.</p>
<p>&quot;The complaint alleges infringement by Macronix of a single 13-year-old patent owned or controlled by Atmel relating to encoding identifying information, such as who is the manufacturer on a computer chip,&quot; Macronix said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;Macronix is confident it has never infringed on any of the claims of this patent and intends to vigorously contest the unwarranted allegations of patent infringement alleged by Atmel.&quot;  </p>
<p>Macronix said it has complied fully with the applicable industry standard to a silicon signature for identifying information on a chip.</p>
<p>&quot;Macronix is prepared to fully cooperate with the current ITC investigation. It also expects to prevail in any action by Atmel against the company,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Macronix listed American Depositary Receipts in New York's NASDAQ exchange York in May 1996.  </p>
<p>The statement said the company is now the world's seventh largest maker of non-volatile memory chips, including flash memory, EPROM and mask ROM.</p>
<p>-- Taipei Newsroom (5080815)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34531">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
