<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479024" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TUNISIA: EU head sees Malta forum as helping Middle East.</title>
<headline>EU head sees Malta forum as helping Middle East.</headline>
<dateline>TUNIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union (EU) council of ministers' chairman said on Tuesday that Arab states who plan to freeze ties with Israel will not boycott a Mediterranean meeting in Malta this month that the Jewish state will attend.</p>
<p>Hans van Mierlo, who is also Dutch foreign minister, told reporters in Tunis: &quot;We are very happy that the Arab states decided last night to take part in the Malta conference. There was a danger that the Middle East issue causes a problem. It is not the case...We are relieved.&quot;</p>
<p>Ministers from the EU and the south Mediterranean, including Egypt, Syria, Lebanon, Jordan, Morocco, Tunisia, Algeria, the Palestinian Authority and Israel are due to meet in Malta on April 15 and 16 to assess progress in the Euro-Med Partnership agreed in Barcelona in 1995.</p>
<p>Arab-Israeli relations have plummeted since Israel  started building a Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem. On Monday the Arab League recommended freezing links with Israel and reactivating a trade boycott.</p>
<p>But van Mierlo said of the freeze of relations with Israel: &quot;I must say that I do not understand the sense of this. I confess that it is not up to me to say what to do....If this helps restart the peace process, I would agree. But I have doubts.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We regret the deadlock in the Middle East peace process. We will do all what we can to have it restart, though our means are limited...What I hope is that the Malta conference will influence positively the peace process,&quot; Mierlo said.</p>
<p>He confirmed that Syria and Lebanon as well as Israel and the Palestinian Auhority would attend the conference.</p>
<p>Van Mierlo was speaking after talks with his Tunisian counterpart Abderrahim Zouari on cooperation between the EU and Tunisia, which was the first Mediterranean country to sign a free trade zone accord with the EU in 1995.</p>
<p>Van Mierlo earlier visited Algiers, where he held talks with Algerian President Liamine Zeroual on cooperation with Algeria ahead of the Malta forum.</p>
<p>&quot;For us, Algeria is very important as a partner but also because we share together the responsibility of the Malta conference as co-sponsors...,&quot; van Mierlo said.</p>
<p>Algeria is spokesman for the Arab group involved in the Barcelona partnership.</p>
<p>The EU delegation also held talks with Algerian officials on Algeria's negotiations with the EU on an association accord which will open the Algerian economy to competition in a Mediterranean free zone by the year 2010, the Algerian state-run radio said.</p>
<p>Van Mierlo said the EU was looking with interest to Algeria's June 5 parliamentary elections &quot;because political stability would result in improved security&quot;.</p>
<p>The EU delegation, which includes European Commission vice-president Manuel Marin, started its tour in Morocco, Algeria and Tunisia and is due to hold talks in Malta on Wednesday and in Egypt and Turkey on Thursday to prepare the Malta conference, officials said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARABST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALTA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TUNIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TUNIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TUNISIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
