<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479118" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Man kills self in apparent cult suicide copycat.</title>
<headline>Man kills self in apparent cult suicide copycat.</headline>
<dateline>MARYSVILLE, Calif. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 58-year-old recluse was found dead in his home in a remote mountain canyon in northern California in an apparent copycat of the mass suicide of Heaven's Gate cult members, police said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>A suicide note, found next to the body of Robert Nichols in his trailer home outside Marysville, read: &quot;I'm going to the spaceship with Hale-Bopp to be with those who have gone before me.&quot;</p>
<p>The 39 members of the Heaven's Gate cult committed suicide in their rented million-dollar mansion in the exclusive San Diego, California, suburb of Rancho Santa Fe last week.</p>
<p>Videotaped suicide notes discovered along with their bodies last Wednesday showed the members believed an alien spaceship hiding behind the Hale-Bopp comet would transport them to heaven.</p>
<p>Yuba County Undersheriff Gary Finch said when Nichols' body was found on Sunday it was draped in a purple shroud similar to the shrouds covering the bodies of the Heaven's Gate cult members.</p>
<p>Nichols had a plastic bag over his head and had apparently died from gas poisoning by putting a hose from a propane tank into the bag, Finch said.</p>
<p>But Marysville resident Alison Mattorolo, whose husband Richard discovered Nichols' body, said she had known the dead man for a number of years and that he was &quot;never a cult member and never even expressed any interest in cults.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;He was very much into astrology. He thought this comet was the second coming of Christ. It was a separate thing, nothing to do with cults,&quot; she told Reuters.</p>
<p>Mattorolo said Nichols had been a roadie for the Grateful Dead and had written a book on his experiences with the fabled rock group called &quot;Truckin' With the Grateful Dead to Egypt.&quot; He had been in the process of writing a second book on the group, she added.</p>
<p>Mattorolo said Nichols' death shocked and upset her. &quot;I never thought he would do anything like this. He has always been kind of trippy, like the flower children. He was a loner, but he was a happy-go-lucky sort.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARYSVILLE, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
