<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479123" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Stocks, bonds firmer; dollar falls on trade tensions.</title>
<headline>Stocks, bonds firmer; dollar falls on trade tensions.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Blue-chip stocks rebounded moderately on Tuesday after a massive sell-off in the last two sessions, while bonds rose on signs that inflation was under control.</p>
<p>The dollar fell sharply amid fresh signs of trade tension between the United States and Japan.</p>
<p>The Dow Jones industrial average rose 27.57 points to 6,611.05. Analysts were quick to caution, however, that the gains wiped out only a small fraction of the nearly 300-point loss the Dow index has suffered since last Thursday.</p>
<p>Several said despite the welcome respite, the outlook would remain extremely uncertain, at least as long as the questions that triggered the decline go unanswered.</p>
<p>&quot;My sense is we're still in the midst of a painful period that still has a way to go,&quot; said Alan Ackerman, market strategist at Fahnestock &amp; Co. &quot;But there's still a lot of uncertainty ahead and will be until we have a better handle on what the Federal Reserve will do next.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts noted that pharmaceutical and financial stocks posted a solid day, notable because the groups have led the market's roller-coaster ride this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The two leadership groups, banks and drugs, were trying to reassert their leadership today,&quot; said Scott Bleier, chief investment strategist at Prime Charter Ltd.</p>
<p>Bonds rose as the key price component of the National Association of Purchasing Management report fell despite a sharp rise in the overall index.</p>
<p>The key 30-year Treasury bond rose one quarter point, or $2.50 on a $1,000 bond. Its yield, which moves in the opposite direction of the price, edged down to 7.08 percent from 7.10 percent at Monday's close.</p>
<p>But with critical monthly payrolls, wage and unemployment data due Friday, the interest rate outlook remained far from clear, leaving market matters looking anything but certain.</p>
<p>The dollar ended Tuesday at 121.73 Japanese yen, up from its low of 121.40, but far below 123.78 late Monday. Against the German mark, the dollar fell to 1.6663 vs. 1.6750 late Monday.</p>
<p>Soybean prices soared after the Agriculture Department revised down an estimate of soybean stockpiles it had issued a day earlier.</p>
<p>At the Chicago Board of Trade, soybeans for delivery in May soared 19-3/4 cents to $8.75-1/2 a bushel after rising as much as 30 cents earlier.</p>
<p>Corn prices also were boosted by the spillover from soybeans, with May corn ending up 3 cents a bushel at $3.13.</p>
<p>Overseas, London's FTSE 100 share index finished 64.8 points lower at 4,248.1, the day's best level. In Tokyo, the 225-share Nikkei average shed 133.81 points, or 0.74 percent, to 17,869.59.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
