<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479151" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USDA says 25.6 mln acres offered in CRP signup.</title>
<headline>USDA says 25.6 mln acres offered in CRP signup.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Agriculture Department Tuesday said preliminary figures showed 25.6 million acres were offered in the Conservation Reserve Program signup that closed last Friday.</p>
<p>USDA said that, of the total, nearly eight million acres were new and offered for the first time and the remaining approximately 18 million acres were currently enrolled in CRP contracts due to expire in September.  </p>
<p>Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman cautioned in a statement that the figures were preliminary estimates and that the final numbers may be different.</p>
<p>Sign up for the revamped land-idling program began March 3 and closed March 28. Producers will be notified by mid-June if their land has been accepted.</p>
<p>USDA said Texas finished the signup with the most acres offered, some 3.4 million acres, followed by 2.5 million acres in North Dakota and 2.3 million in Montana.  </p>
<p>Glickman said the large pool of offers for the program would allow USDA to enroll those acres yielding the highest environmental benefits.</p>
<p>&quot;That helps us get the biggest bang for the taxpayers' buck,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>USDA has come under fire from critics who say the new CRP could end up retiring productive farm land.</p>
<p>A big question remaining is how many acres USDA will accept into the program. White House budget assumptions were that CRP contracts would be written this year on 19 million acres.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, the Clinton Administration said it would defer sign-up of two million acres and use those funds to pay a company not to mine near Yellowstone National Park. Glickman recently told lawmakers that that decision was made under the theory USDA would have &quot;great difficulty&quot; signing up 19 million acres in fiscal 1998.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
