<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479138" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Lost hikers found on Oregon's Mount Hood.</title>
<headline>Lost hikers found on Oregon's Mount Hood.</headline>
<dateline>PORTLAND, Ore. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rescuers on Tuesday found four climbers who had been missing on Oregon's Mount Hood since a blizzard hit the dangerous peak Easter Sunday.</p>
<p>The four climbers, all in their 30s, were found hiking down the mountain near Portland as the blizzard conditions cleared.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the best-case scenario,&quot; said Clackamas County Deputy Sheriff Damon Coates.</p>
<p>The climbers, Michael Whelan and Shawn Corrigan of Bend and Colette Whelan Ownes and Robert Sheley of Portland, set out at 5 a.m. Sunday on a planned day hike to the summit, the state's highest peak at 11,245 feet.</p>
<p>The weather was clear and bright, but by 11 a.m. a snowstorm had hit the mountain.</p>
<p>&quot;We had 75 mph winds and blizzard conditions,&quot; Coates said. Rescue efforts were interrupted Monday morning because of continued bad weather.</p>
<p>The four, with provisions for about a day, sheltered themselves in a snow cave until conditions improved.</p>
<p>After they were found, rescuers discovered the group's mountain locator unit had malfunctioned.</p>
<p>&quot;They activated it Sunday night, but it was not emitting a signal,&quot; Coates said. It was the first time in his 10 years of mountain rescue work that he could remember such a malfunction.</p>
<p>Coates said Mount Hood was entering its most dangerous season, as spring attracts numerous climbers who can be surprised by rapidly changing weather conditions.</p>
<p>So far this year there have been no fatalities on the mountain, although two lost snowboarders recently were found by rescuers in separate incidents.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTLAND, Ore."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
