<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479135" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kaczynski wins round in challenge to cabin search.</title>
<headline>Kaczynski wins round in challenge to cabin search.</headline>
<dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. magistrate on Tuesday ordered prosecutors to turn over a key document to Unabomber suspect Theodore Kaczynski's lawyers, who have asked the court to throw out evidence against their client.</p>
<p>In a partial victory for the defence team, U.S. Magistrate Gregory Hollows at a hearing in Sacramento granted Kaczynski's requests for a government document about the search of his cabin, and opened the door for broader discovery by his lawyers, who are challenging physical evidence that allegedly incriminates the former mathematics professor.</p>
<p>Hollows said the defence could have a copy of the partial draft of the original search warrant affidavit for Kaczynski's remote Montana cabin. Federal investigators used the final affidavit to obtain a search warrant to enter the cabin.</p>
<p>In addition, Hollows said he would review certain other documents not yet turned over to the defence. These documents include reports and files about 12 people that the defence alleges were other &quot;serious&quot; suspects in the FBI's Unabomber investigation, as well as documents about DNA evidence.</p>
<p>After studying these documents, Hollows said he would decide whether any should be released to the defence.</p>
<p>The defence has asked the court to throw out all of the evidence seized by the FBI at Kaczynski's Montana cabin in April last year.</p>
<p>The defence alleges that the search was illegal because the FBI's affidavit supporting its request for a search warrant contained misleading information.</p>
<p>Kaczynski, 54, was arrested in April 1996 at his rustic one-room cabin in Montana. He is accused of being the shadowy Unabomber, who killed three people and injured 23 during an anti-technology bombing campaign between 1978 and 1995.</p>
<p>Prosecutors and investigators have said they found extensive evidence at the cabin incriminating Kaczynski, including bomb components and a diary that they say contained his &quot;detailed admission&quot; about the Unabomber attacks.</p>
<p>At Tuesday's court hearing, prosecutors argued that the defence had already received all of the documents that they are entitled to.</p>
<p>Kaczynski has been charged in Sacramento with four bombings, two of them deadly. Kaczynski, who is being held in Sacramento, has pleaded not guilty.</p>
<p>His trial is scheduled to start in November.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SACRAMENTO, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
