<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479150" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Soybeans hit new 8-year highs, lumber also rises.</title>
<headline>Soybeans hit new 8-year highs, lumber also rises.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Soybean prices soared on Tuesday after the Agriculture Department revised down an estimate of soybean stockpiles it had issued a day earlier and rattled the nerves of grain traders worried about supplies.</p>
<p>At the Chicago Board of Trade, soybeans for delivery in May soared for 30-cent-per-bushel limit gains at the opening and set a new life of contract high at $8.85-3/4 before closing at $8.75-1/2, up 19-3/4 cents.</p>
<p>July delivery soybeans, also subject to existing stocks rather than the autumn crop supplies, rose as high as $8.88 a bushel during the day, the highest price for soybeans since September 1988. July closed at $8.78-1/2, up 20-1/2 cents.</p>
<p>Triggering the surge was a stunning revision by the Agriculture Department on Tuesday of its estimate for soybean stockpiles as of March 1. It said that figure was actually 1.056 billion bushels, 22 million bushels below the 1.078 billion bushels it had estimated in a report on Monday.</p>
<p>Rich Allen, a department official, said the correction -- the first in three decades by the department on a grain stocks report -- was due to a mathematical error in calculating soybean stocks now in storage in the state of Mississippi.</p>
<p>But traders, already nervous that overheated demand from exporters and soybean processors this year could use up even last year's bumper crop, said the change was a shocking reminder of how quickly soybeans were disappearing.</p>
<p>&quot;It absolutely, completely turned around the psychology of the market from 18 hours ago,&quot; said Charlie Sernatinger, grain analyst with E.D. and F. Man International. &quot;This morning they walked in and said, 'We don't have enough beans.'&quot;</p>
<p>Soybean prices at this time of year are usually under pressure as Brazil and Argentina harvest their crops and begin feeding international customers. Soybeans are used for dozens of industrial products from edible oils to paints.</p>
<p>South American bumper crops are expected again this year, but traders are focusing instead on a record rate of consumption by soybean crushers and booming exports.</p>
<p>As of March 20, soybean exports since September 1 totaled 18.66 million metric tons, against 15.89 million a year earlier. The soybean &quot;crush&quot; to produce soybean meal and oil has also been running at record levels all winter.</p>
<p>Traders said they expect the Agriculture Department to cut its estimate of soybean end-season stocks as of September 1 to below 140 million bushels, itself only a 2-1/2 week supply, in its next report on supply and demand on April 11.</p>
<p>&quot;This number implies lower ending stocks, but I'm expecting a rationing of demand on the export side in both meal and beans,&quot; said Mark Weidner, an oilseeds analyst with Cargill Investor Services. &quot;Just based on this report, it would have to imply ending stocks under 130 (million bushels).&quot;</p>
<p>Buoyed by the strength in soybeans, soybean meal for May delivery closed with near-limit gains of $9.20 a ton at $292.20. May soyoil rose 0.24 cent a pound to 24.16 cents.</p>
<p>Corn prices also were boosted by spillover from soybeans, with May corn ending at $3.13, up 3 cents a bushel.</p>
<p>But May wheat closed 3-3/4 cents lower at $3.93-3/4, with traders discouraged by no fresh news that India would be buying more wheat after purchasing a million tons last week.</p>
<p>At the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, lumber prices closed higher after the Commerce Department said construction spending in February rose at the fastest rate in almost a year, up 2.3 percent to an annual $603.8 billion.</p>
<p>Lumber for May delivery closed up $4.50 at $385.00 per thousand board feet.</p>
<p>A lack of any large new imports of Canadian lumber with the start of a new 12-month period of quota-regulated shipments on April 1 was also supportive, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;There didn't appear to be a big influx of lumber based on the new quota year, at least to this point,&quot; said Neil Schmaedick, Smith Barney Forest Products analyst.</p>
<p>&quot;So some people are stepping forward on the retail side and filling in what they need to buy,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At the New York Mercantile Exchange, crude oil ended lower, as a rise in demand by refiners was still not enough to absorb a steady stream of imports, traders said.</p>
<p>Crude oil for delivery in May closed 13 cents a barrel lower at $20.28.</p>
<p>&quot;You have a situation where refinery demand for crude is seen rising and you would think that would absorb all the crude, but it hasn't,&quot; said John Saucer, analyst with Smith Barney in Houston.</p>
<p>May delivery unleaded gasoline ended 0.55 cent a gallon lower at 62.67 cents and May heating oil 0.47 cent a gallon lower at 53.95 cents.</p>
<p>Traders pointed to steady North Sea and West African crude oil shipments arriving at terminals in the Gulf of Mexico amid weaker demand for crude oil in Europe.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
