<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479124" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Stifel lawyers eyeing next U.S. move in muni case.</title>
<headline>Stifel lawyers eyeing next U.S. move in muni case.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lawyers for former Stifel, Nicolaus &amp; Co. executive Robert Cochran said they are watching closely the federal government's next move after a federal appeals court decided last week to throw out the 1996 criminal conviction of their client.</p>
<p>&quot;We're very pleased,&quot; B.J. Rothbaum said, responding to the U.S. 10th Circuit Court of Appeals' March 27 reversal of last Spring's federal jury conviction of Cochran on eight of 21 counts of cheating two municipal authorities on bond deals.</p>
<p>Rothbaum said the U.S. could ask for a rehearing of the three-judge panel's ruling by the full appeals panel or ask the U.S. Supreme Court to consider hearing an appeal. The Securities and Exchange Commission also could seek civil action against Cochran.</p>
<p>Also, Cochran himself may want to pursue some litigation, Rothbaum said, refusing to comment futher.</p>
<p>In late August, U.S. District Judge Ralph Thompson sentenced Cochran to seven years and three months in prison and ordered him to return $629,000 in illegal profits on a $76.7 million airport issue and a $265 million healthcare authority deal.</p>
<p>Cochran lawyers appealed the decision, arguing Cochran never harmed the municipal authorities and, therefore, should not have been convicted of wire fraud.</p>
<p>They also said Cochran had no &quot;fiduciary&quot; relationship with the authorities, and therefore, no duty to disclose fees that government lawyers said he had illegally pocketed.</p>
<p>The appeals court last week ruled that, while the case involved &quot;greed&quot; it did not necessarily involve &quot;criminal liability.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;At oral argument, the government could not inform us of any statute, common law, or contractual provisions that required disclosure of the fee,&quot; the appeals panel said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a significant decision,&quot; Harvey Pitt, a partner at Fried Frank Harris Shriver &amp; Jacobson and former SEC official, said. &quot;It suggests a continuing theme of judicial impatience with government prosecutors who try to define the standards as they go along.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically, what the court is saying is that if you think the law should cover this, that's fine. Then tell people that. If you haven't done that, don't try to sue them.&quot;</p>
<p>Christopher Taylor, executive director of the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board, noted the 15-member board could enact a rule that would address, at least in part, the appeals panel's concerns. The panel is examining whether or not to tighten disclosure requirements for financial advisers and underwriters in an effort to deter conflicts of interest in the underwriting process.</p>
<p>&quot;The board is looking at the underwriting process and the roles and responsibilities of financial advisers and underwriters,&quot; Taylor said.</p>
<p>Heather Ruth, president of PSA The Bond Market Trade Association, called the decision &quot;interesting&quot; and said she would comment after reading court documents.</p>
<p>-- Vicky Stamas, 202-898-8314</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
