<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479168" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US trade rhetoric pushes dlr/yen to lower US close.</title>
<headline>US trade rhetoric pushes dlr/yen to lower US close.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar ended sharply lower against the yen and modestly weaker versus the mark on Tuesday, plagued by signs of mounting trade tensions between the U.S. and Japan.</p>
<p>An anemic recovery in U.S. stocks and speculation that Japan's quarterly &quot;tankan&quot; survey of business sentiment would show ample strength when it is released on Wednesday, also hurt the dollar, dealers said.</p>
<p>The greenback ended the day at 121.78/88 yen, up from its session low of 121.40, but down from its opening rate of 123.60/70.  </p>
<p>Against the mark, the dollar also fell, closing at 1.6663/68 versus 1.6700/10 in early trade.</p>
<p>The dollar traded progressively lower against the yen as the day unfolded, touching its lows after stop-loss sell orders were triggered on a move below 122.20 and then 122.00.</p>
<p>Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin got the ball rolling in the afternoon when he told reporters ahead of a six-day trip to Asia that starts on Thursday, that he would not welcome a reversal in the progress Japan has made in cutting its trade surplus.  </p>
<p>These remarks followed earlier comments from U.S. House Speaker Newt Gingrich on Tuesday, who said in a meeting with Japan's Trade Minister Shinji Sato, that current exchange rates meant Japan's trade surplus with the U.S. was becoming a cause for concern.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen tons of interest to sell the dollar against the yen,&quot; said Ricardo Gomes, foreign exchange manager at Republic National Bank of New York.</p>
<p>&quot;All the comments have combined to make people nervous about the Japanese trade surplus and if dollar/yen continues to go higher it's not going to help the situation.&quot;  </p>
<p>Traders said interest to buy yen was broad, coming from U.S., Japanese as well as European players. Expectations that Japanese financial institutions would buy dollars at the beginning of Japan's new fiscal year were dashed on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Dollar/mark and dollar/Europe in general have been exhibiting some weakness over the past couple of sessions that was not reflected in dollar/yen, so there might have been a little bit of catch-up,&quot; said Bob Lynch, senior currency analyst at MMS International.  </p>
<p>Traders said rumors of a strong tankan report had the market nervous and prompted covering of short-yen positions throughout the session.</p>
<p>Heavy sales of dollars for yen filtered through to weakness against the mark. Persistent, albeit modest, weakness in stocks for much of the session also weighed on the U.S. currency.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials popped higher just ahead of the close to end up 28 points at 6611 on Tuesday, after shedding close to 300 points in the previous two trading days.  </p>
<p>Expectations of higher U.S. interest rates were fueled on Tuesday by heady gains in the National Association of Purchasing Management's March manufacturing index, which rose to 55.0 from 53.1.</p>
<p>In other trade on Tuesday, the dollar ended slightly lower at 1.4410/20 Swiss francs against 1.4420/30 at the open. The British pound rose to $1.6518/28 from $1.6440/50, while the Australian dollar ended at $0.7859/64 versus $0.7875/80 at the open.</p>
<p>The dollar slipped to Canadian $1.3883/88 from $1.3885/90 in early trade.</p>
<p>((-- Noah Barkin, N.A. Treasury Desk, 212-859-1673))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
