<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479137" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CFTC report indicated rough times for gasoline.</title>
<headline>CFTC report indicated rough times for gasoline.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The CFTC Futures Commitment of Traders Report last week foreshadowed a decline in gasoline prices and next week's report will likely reflect the bearish turn by showing a decline in gasoline open interest.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a lot of speculative length in gasoline, so I have to think gasoline was looking vulnerable to profit-taking, which was what we have seen,&quot; said John Saucer, analyst with Smith Barney in Houston.</p>
<p>For the two weeks ended March 25, long positions held by non-commercial traders had increased by 3,497 contracts to 14,097. Open interest for gasoline, the amount of long or short positions at the end of a trading session, stood at 99,180, particularly high for the unleaded contract.</p>
<p>Speculators had bought gasoline expecting the spot contract was poised to begin its traditional spring rally in anticipation of the summer driving season.</p>
<p>Since March 25, spot gasoline has fallen 3.85 cents a gallon on the New York Mercantile Exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;I think in the next report we are going to see that a lot of that (open interest) has disappeared, that there are not many new long or shorts that have entered gasoline,&quot; said Tom Bentz, analyst with ING Derivatives in New York.</p>
<p>Gasoline was vulnerable to profit-taking by jittery traders when crude prices continued to slide on ample supply, analysts said.</p>
<p>Commercial players such as refiners had increased their short positions in crude by 12,236 contracts to 262,845 contracts. The wisdom of these large players, typically described as the &quot;smart money,&quot; panned out. Since March 25, spot crude has fallen 71 cents a barrel.</p>
<p>Speculative short positions in heating oil showed a sharp decrease, a move deemed fairly typical as heating oil's price firms this time of year as refiners shift away from distillate output to focus on gasoline production.</p>
<p>-- New York Energy Desk, 212-859-1620</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
