<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479193" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton appears in pressroom for April Fools' joke.</title>
<headline>Clinton appears in pressroom for April Fools' joke.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton made a surprise appearance at the White House press room on Tuesday and, in an April Fools' joke, said spokesman Mike McCurry had hurt his knee and would be replaced by a 25-year-old aide.</p>
<p>&quot;I came here today because I thought I should personally deliver some disturbing news,&quot; a sombre-faced Clinton told reporters, several of whom scurried into the room.</p>
<p>&quot;Mike McCurry has just made a fool of himself by taking an unfortunate fall on dimly lit steps here at the White House. We believe he may have torn a tendon in his upper right thigh, which could give him a six-inch (15 cm) incision,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Until we can bring him back to full health, Kris Engskov is going to do the daily briefing,&quot; Clinton said, prompting applause and cheers for the popular aide, who is responsible for shepherding the &quot;pool&quot; of reporters that follows the president whenever he leaves the White House.</p>
<p>Clinton, who is recovering from surgery to repair a tendon he tore in his right knee last month, hobbled into the press room on his crutches for the announcement. The remarks almost exactly mirrored the briefings McCurry gave after an accident in Florida on March 14 when the president tripped on a step and hurt his knee, but Clinton gave a humorous twist to his answers.</p>
<p>Asked if McCurry had consumed any alcohol before his alleged stumble, Clinton replied: &quot;And beer and wine.&quot;</p>
<p>The president's doctor told reporters after the Florida accident that Clinton had not had anything to drink.</p>
<p>Clinton said the reason reporters were not told sooner of McCurry's supposed injury was &quot;because we're pretty sneaky around here.&quot; The White House was criticised for not informing the pool more quickly when Clinton injured himself.</p>
<p>Asked if Engskov's mild Arkansas accent would get in the way of his new duties, Clinton said: &quot;I thought we should have a press secretary that did not have an accent for the first time in four years.&quot;</p>
<p>Engskov, one of the younger aides in the White House press office, then took to the podium and said: &quot;April Fools&quot; and an uninjured McCurry proceeded with his regular daily briefing.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
