<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479136" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Export Business - Grain/oilseeds complex.</title>
<headline>Export Business - Grain/oilseeds complex.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Grain and oilseed exports reported by USDA and private export sources.</p>
<p>WHEAT SALE  - Mexico bought 25,000 tonnes of U.S. spring wheat on Monday night, several U.S. exporters said. Shipment was slated for April 1-10. No details on prices were given.</p>
<p>CORN SALE - South Korea bought 52,500 tonnes of U.S. yellow No. 2 corn from Cargill at $149.75 per tonne, C &amp; F, for July 1-20 shipment if sourced from U.S. Gulf and July 15-August 5 if sourced from PNW.  </p>
<p>TAPIOCA SALE - A South Korean buyers' group, known as the &quot;Big Feed Mills,&quot; bought a combined 30,100 tonnes of Thai tapioca from Haitai International Inc through a closed tender, an official of the buyers' group said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>VEGOIL SALE - South Korea's National Livestock Cooperatives Federation said on Tuesday it bought 28,000 tonnes of rapeseed meal and passed on tenders for another 14,000 tonnes of rapeseed meal and 30,000 tonnes of tapioca hard pellet due to high offer prices. An NLCF official said it was unable to buy 8,000 tonnes of grain screening pellet due to an absence of offers.  </p>
<p>CORN TENDER - South Korea on Tuesday invited tenders to buy 52,500 tonnes of U.S. yellow No.2 corn. Traders said shipment was set for July 1-20 if sourced from the U.S. Gulf, July 15-August 5 if sourced from the Pacific Northwest, or June 20-July 10 if from Argentina. Arrival was set for Inchon.</p>
<p>- The Philippines said it will buy 40,000 tonnes of corn for shipment not later than April 15. The state-owned firm said in an announcement in Philippine newspapers that it planned to hold a bidding for the supply of 15,000 tonnes of U.S. yellow corn number 2 on April 2. It will also seek tenders for the supply of 25,000 tonnes white kernelled corn.  </p>
<p>LENTIL TENDER - Syria's General Establishment for Cereal Processing and Trade has offered 16,000 tonnes of lentils for export, an official spokesman said. An international call for prices setting April 8 as final date to receive bids had been issued. Confirmation would be made on April 9. The spokesman said the lentils of the 1996 crop would be ready for shipment in May. Partial offers will be acceptable up to 1,000 tonnes and the establishment has the right for partial confirmation.</p>
<p>VEGOIL TENDER - Egypt seeks up to 45,000 tonnes of veg oils for May delivery. The deadline for bids was April 2.  </p>
<p>BARLEY TENDER - The South African Wheat Board said it was offering 25,150 tonnes of feed grade barley for export sale no later than April 30.</p>
<p>RICE TENDERS - Iran is seeking to buy 400,000 tonnes of rice from Thailand but a deal has not been concluded yet, Thai Commerce Minister Narongchai Akrasanee said on Monday.</p>
<p>- Syria seeks 12,000 tonnes of white rice for shipment between April 20 and May 20. April 8 is the final date for bids and result will be announced on April 16.  </p>
<p>MARKET TALK - Taiwan corn buying interests will remain sidelined through April as a foot and mouth disease outbreak in the hog herd slashes demand for feed corn, grain buyers said.... Indonesia is believed to have snapped up at least 500,000 tonnes of corn while Thai buyers are sniffing for 50,000 tonnes of soymeal, traders said on Tuesday....Stevedores at Brazil's key port of Santos are set to begin a two-day strike on Wednesday over a labor dispute. The port is expected to be brought to a halt by the strike action. If no progress is made in negotiations by Friday, the union will call a nationwide strike.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
