<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479147" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. MUNICIPAL FOCUS - Prices flat, tone firmer.</title>
<headline>U.S. MUNICIPAL FOCUS - Prices flat, tone firmer.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. municipal bond prices ended flat but with a firmer tone as the market survived one round of economic data and braced for more--including March employment--later this week.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The market is really underperforming the government market,&quot; one trader said. &quot;No one seems to have any money to spend.&quot;</p>
<p>Players are looking for direction and treading carefully in the meantime, the trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is so much ecomomic data out this week, and no one is really sure which way the taxable market is going to go,&quot; he said. &quot;If this data is positive for the economy, negative for the markets, most of the investors will run to the hills.&quot;</p>
<p>On Friday, the market is set to receive March employment figures. Economist polled by Reuters expect non-farm payrolls to grow by 182,000 versus 339,000 the previous month.</p>
<p>While the trader described Tuesday's muni market action as &quot;sluggish,&quot; a municipal analyst said activity was moderate during the morning, with a pickup seen following the March National Association of Purchasing Management report at 1000 EST. Activity was light during the afternoon, the analyst said.</p>
<p>Players took heart from NAPM's prices component, which dipped to 50.9 in March from 55.1 in February. NAPM overall however rose to 55.0, its highest level since an indentical reading in February 1995.</p>
<p>Other Tuesday data also showed expansion, but took a backseat to NAPM. Construction spending rose 2.3 percent in February compared with a revised 0.3 percent gain in January, and leading indicators were up 0.5 percent last month against 0.3 percent the month before.</p>
<p>In muni cash, high-grade issues ended flat, but with a slightly better tone, the analyst said. Dollar bonds ended unchanged after being quoted in a range all day, he said.</p>
<p>In debt futures, the June municipal contract closed up 8/32 at 111-28/32. The June T-bond contract also closed up 8/32 at 107-15/32. The MOB spread was 141 ticks.</p>
<p>In the government market the benchmark 30-year bond closed up 9/32 at 94-13/32 to yield 7.08 percent.</p>
<p>Turning to new issues, Smith Barney Inc said it repriced $176 million King County, Wash., bonds, lowering the yield in the 2015 maturity to 5.875 percent from 5.90 percent.</p>
<p>((--Kathie O'Donnell, 212-859-1655))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
