<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479111" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Snow buries New England, three dead.</title>
<headline>Snow buries New England, three dead.</headline>
<byline>Leslie Gevirtz</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>An April Fools' blizzard was blamed for three deaths and left more than a half million New Englanders without power on Tuesday as the vicious northeastern storm continued to batter the region.</p>
<p>Accumulations of up to 30 inches (76 cm) were reported in western Massachusetts, while in the Boston metropolitan area 2 feet (0.7 metres) of heavy, wet snow was reported. Further east on Cape Cod, the National Weather Service was reporting heavy snow with winds gusting over 65 mph (104 kph) in Falmouth. Waves 20 to 30 feet (6 to 9 metres) high crashed along the shorelines of Long Island and Cape Cod.</p>
<p>Massachusetts Gov. William Weld declared a state of emergency on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The heaviest snowfall appeared to be in the Catskill and mid-Hudson valley region of New York, where accumulations topped 32 inches (81 cm), the weather service said.</p>
<p>Snow, falling at the rate of an inch (2.5 cm) an hour in Boston, was expected to taper off by midday in most of the region, but strong winds with gusts of up to 30 mph (48 kph) were expected to continue. The winds combined with heavy, wet snow blew down power lines throughout the region.</p>
<p>Northeast Utilities, which serves Connecticut and western Massachusetts, reported some 100,000 customers without power. Eastern Utilities, which serves Rhode Island and southeastern Massachusetts reported 31,000 customers without service.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect to have most service back this evening, but in the Brockton (Massachusetts) area, customers may not get service back before Thursday,&quot; Eastern Utilities spokeswoman Elaine Hunt said.</p>
<p>Boston Edison reported more than 50,000 customers without power. &quot;We've had a hundred crews on all night and we know 36 crews are headed here from Canada. We're also looking for help from New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Vermont,&quot; Boston Edison spokesman Mike Monahan said. He estimated it would be up to a week before service was fully restored to some 50,000 customers.</p>
<p>Massachusetts Emergency Management Agency executive director Peter LaPorte said, &quot;It is still quite a vicious storm and it is continuing. We have half a million people without power.&quot;</p>
<p>Power outtages were also reported by Public Service of New Hampshire and Central Maine Power.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, travelers were finding it hard going. Boston's Logan International Airport, which closed at midnight when snow was falling at the rate of 2 inches  (5 cm) an hour, hoped to have one runway open for emergencies on Tuesday morning. Bradley International Airport in Hartford, which closed on Monday night, remained shut. The airport in Manchester, New Hampshire, was also closed, officials there reported.</p>
<p>Both New York's LaGuardia Airport and John F. Kennedy Airport were reporting delays.</p>
<p>Large parts of Interstate 95, the main north-south road through the northeast, were closed to traffic. Mass transit in the region was either stopped or operating with long delays.</p>
<p>Police in Maine, New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Connecticut, Rhode Island and New York reported many traffic accidents. New York State police blamed the death of a 36-year-old man, killed in a traffic accident in the Catskill region, on the storm.</p>
<p>In northern Maine near the Canadian border, officials blamed the weather for the death of two fishermen whose vessel was capsized by the storm's high winds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
