<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479141" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Hamas leader seeks release from prison.</title>
<headline>Hamas leader seeks release from prison.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Gail Appleson, U.S. Law Correspondent</p>
<p>An imprisoned political leader of the militant Palestinian group Hamas is seeking his release because the U.S. government has failed to extradite him to Israel, according to court papers made available on Tuesday.</p>
<p>In January, Mousa Mohammed Abu Marzook gave up his fight against extradition from the United States. His lawyers now argue that under federal law, the U.S. government was required to surrender him to Israel or release him no later than March 28.</p>
<p>Federal prosecutors have said the deadline is April 6. A hearing on the petition is scheduled for Tuesday afternoon.</p>
<p>&quot;This is probably the first case in the annals of United States extradition practice where a person is ordered extradited and is willing to be extradited and the Government refuses to extradite or release him for political reasons, preferring instead to keep him confined in perpetual limbo in federal jail,&quot; a petition filed late on Monday in Manhattan federal court said.</p>
<p>Last year a federal judge ordered Abu Marzook extradited to Israel and another judge confirmed the ruling in October. Although Abu Marzook initially appealed the rulings, his lawyers announced in January he wanted to drop the fight.</p>
<p>It is believed that Israeli and American officials have been trying to find ways to avoid extraditing Abu Marzook to Israel out of fear it would lead to violence.</p>
<p>In 1995 Israel announced it had formally asked the United States to hand over Abu Marzook, alleging he was responsible as the head of Hamas's political arm for attacks that killed scores of Israelis.</p>
<p>Israel did not contend that Abu Marzook personally committed any of the violent acts, but charged that he is criminally liable because of his high-level role in allegedly directing, controlling and financially supporting Hamas's activities.</p>
<p>Abu Marzook has denied involvement in any violence.</p>
<p>He was arrested on July 25, 1995, at a New York airport as he flew to the United States -- where he had lived for many years -- after immigration officials found his name on its &quot;watch list&quot; of people with &quot;known or suspected ties to terrorist activities.&quot;</p>
<p>Israel had requested his arrest and his extradition, alleging that the U.S.-educated Gazan was involved in a number of fatal bombings, shootings and stabbings between 1990 and 1994 and has raised money for and controlled the leadership of the military wing of Hamas.</p>
<p>Abu Marzook has a home and business in Virginia, but U.S. and Israeli authorities charged he frequently travelled to the Middle East to promote violence and undermine peace efforts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
