<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479179" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT soymeal ends near limit up, soyoil higher.</title>
<headline>CBOT soymeal ends near limit up, soyoil higher.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soymeal futures ended near the $10 per ton upper limit on Tuesday after setting contract highs on news USDA corrected its quarterly soybean stocks figure, traders said.</p>
<p>The May soymeal contract peaked at $293.00 per ton, the highest since 1988.</p>
<p>Soyoil futures also ended higher on spillover support from strength in soymeal and soybeans.</p>
<p>USDA on Tuesday corrected its March 1 quarterly stocks figure to 1.056 billion bushels, 22 million bushels below the 1.078 billion bushels released on Monday. They cited a mathematical error in calculating Mississippi off-farm stocks.</p>
<p>The stocks cut augmented concerns that tight U.S. soybean supplies will not last through August.</p>
<p>Soymeal futures opened up the $10 per ton limit and contract highs were set in the nearbys.</p>
<p>But soymeal slipped off the highs late, closing just shy of limit gains as locals and commercials sold, traders said.</p>
<p>Soymeal ended $9.70 to $3.30 per ton higher with May up $9.20 at $292.20 a ton and December up $3.30 at $220.50. Soyoil ended 0.30 to 0.16 cent per lb higher with May up 0.24 at 24.16 cents.  </p>
<p>&quot;A lot of people bought it on the opening in response to USDA's report but when it's all said and done, we're already trading these stocks numbers,&quot; said Bill Biedermann, director of research at Allendale Inc.</p>
<p>Some floor sources also pointed to news rains had halted exports from Brazil's key Paranagua port. That factor was considered secondary to the USDA news but traders cited ideas any delays would force buyers to turn to tight U.S. supplies.</p>
<p>On the day, commercials were mostly sellers of soymeal. Cargill Inc sold 200 lots each May, July, August and September. Merrill Lynch sold 400 May. Prudential Securities bought 400 May and ING bought 400 December, traders said.</p>
<p>In soyoil, funds bought at least 1,000 lots on the day. Griffin Trading bought 600 lots May, Rosenthal Collins bought 300 lots each May and July and Rand Financial bought 500 May and 100 September.</p>
<p>Soymeal volume was estimated by CBOT at 15,000 lots, compared with Monday's actual volume of 17,856 lots. Soyoil volume was pegged at 16,000 lots, against Monday's 17,618 lots.</p>
<p>((Emily Kaiser 312-408-8749))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
