<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479119" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYS Assembly opposes plan to pay off Attica bonds.</title>
<headline>NYS Assembly opposes plan to pay off Attica bonds.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York State Assembly Tuesday swiftly signalled it would fight a new plan by Gov George Pataki to use part of a big surplus to pay off Attica Prison Bonds sold under the former Cuomo Administration.</p>
<p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, D-Manhattan, defended his estimates of how much of a windfall the state can expect, which have been substantially larger than the Republican governor's and accused Pataki of playing a shell game. He spoke with reporters in Albany after meeting with the governor and the Senate Majority Leader.</p>
<p>Noting the Attica bonds were not callable, Silver said: &quot;If you could pay them off, it would be something we'd consider. But you're not paying them off. It's an acknowledgement that the revenue that the Assembly said is there is there, that's clear, and it's a gimmick that's made up to say, well, let's hide this money.&quot;</p>
<p>In 1991, former Gov Mario Cuomo sold the Attica Correctional Facility to a state agency, the Urban Development Corp. The agency then paid the state $242 million for Attica with funds raised by a bond sale that was supported by state debt service payments, according to Pataki. The Attica bonds were not callable until 2020, but the governor proposed using $250 million of an expected surplus to defease them, a step he said would save taxpayers $200 million in interest costs.</p>
<p>Pataki, who also spoke with reporters, was equally quick to question the Speaker's motives in criticizing his proposal. &quot;Well, coming from the person who voted for the gimmick in the first place, I'm not surprised, but I think it would be a symbol of our return to financial solvency.&quot; When asked why he did not select callable bonds, Pataki, who has not hesitated to bash the Cuomo Administration for this one-shot, replied: &quot;It depends on the maximum benefit to the taxpayer.&quot;</p>
<p>The Senate Majority Leader, Joseph Bruno, R-Troy, said that while he was willing to look at Pataki's proposal, his priority for the expected windfall was reducing taxes. &quot;I'm not committed to doing anything with the surplus other than tax reform and some of the tax cuts that we've proposed, that's a priority.&quot;</p>
<p>New York State monitors have criticized the governor for not using the surplus to retire some of the state's debt, and a large, conservative taxpayer association, CHANGE-New York, quickly expressed its support for Pataki's plan.</p>
<p>&quot;The Attica sale and lease back trick--financed with taxpayer dollars--was embarrassingly egregious, even for Mario Cuomo. Gov Pataki deserves credit for erasing this blot from New York's fiscal record,&quot; said Brian Backstrom, the group's vice president, in prepared remarks.</p>
<p>Pataki earlier said the state had an almost $1.4 billion surplus in fiscal 1997, while next year, the state could count on another $860 million.</p>
<p>Despite having a bigger pot of money to divide, a task presumably easier than parceling out a falling amount of revenues, the governor was sufficiently comfortable with the state again failing to have a new budget enacted by its April 1 deadline to josh with reporters about it.</p>
<p>Asked how the budget talks went, he said: &quot;We are just very, very far apart, and I am amazed at how far apart we are now that it is August 1, oops, that might be prophetic unless things change, because we're simply not going to allow a budget that undoes the progress of the last two years to be adopted.&quot; He has accused the Assembly, which has drafted its own budget, of returning the state to policies that failed in the past.</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
