<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479194" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME hogs retreat to lower close, pork bellies up.</title>
<headline>CME hogs retreat to lower close, pork bellies up.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Expectations for weaker cash hog prices and profit taking sparked by an overbought condition pushed most months of CME hog futures to lower closes, traders said. Pork bellies again rallied on cash belly strength and technical support, sources said.</p>
<p>Hog futures closed 1.175 cent a lb lower to 0.100 higher with April off 0.475 at 72.500 cents. August set a new contract high of 78.750 cents before falling to close 0.750 lower at 77.950 cents. October also posted a new high early.</p>
<p>Pork bellies finished 2.225 to 0.225 cent per lb higher with May up 2.025 cent at 80.075 cents. July paced the gain.</p>
<p>Futures had climbed to an overbought condition since news of Taiwan's foot and mouth outbreak and a bullish USDA Hogs and Pigs report, and light profit taking developed. Expectations of weaker cash hog prices for much of the rest of the week as pork demand wanes, turned the outlook for hog prices lower, traders noted.</p>
<p>&quot;Expectations cash markets will weaken into the end of the week with heavy (hog) runs today&quot; pressured hog futures, said Dale Benson, vice president and senior analyst with Dean Witter.  </p>
<p>Cash loin prices jumped last week following a ban on Taiwan pork exports but the price surge turned off domestic interest, sources said. Demand for hams also waned seasonally after Easter and only pork bellies and trimmings were showing further strength this week, sources noted. This accounted for part of the strength in pork belly futures, they said.</p>
<p>Early fund buying subsided and belly futures slipped from best levels into midday on profit taking. But renewed buying prompted by the firm noon cash belly quote lifted prices into technical buy points. That sparked a renewed fund buying surge late which touched off buy stops and took prices up to new day's highs by the close, they said.</p>
<p>May traded above 78.400 cents, the 40-day moving average and belly futures now look like they will test the high on the charts, chartists said.</p>
<p>Traders also noted that the last Hogs and Pigs report was actually more bullish to bellies and increased user interest for bellies may indicate an early start to seasonal demand. Expectations of a bullish CME Out-of-Town Report Tuesday added to overall strength, they said.</p>
<p>Analysts' estimates on the weekly report ranged from in 650,000 to 1.25 million lbs.</p>
<p>However, pit traders generally were looking for a net in movement of 500,000 lbs or less.</p>
<p>After the close, the CME reported a net in-movement of just 236,000 lbs of bellies into CME approved warehouses outside Chicago last week.</p>
<p>Rand Financials remained a notable seller in hog futures, traders said. In hog options, Cargill Investor Services actively bought the June 82 call/81 put strangle early. Fimat Futures USA sold June 83 calls and Rosenthal Collins sold December 66 puts late. Commission house sold October 70 puts, pit sources said.</p>
<p>Cargill notably bought May bellies late. Refco also bought after early demand from  Rand Financials, LFG, Rosenthal Collins and E.D.&amp;F. Man, pit sources added.</p>
<p>((Jerry Bieszk 312-408-8725))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
