<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479174" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. says Russia-Belarus union must meet terms.</title>
<headline>U.S. says Russia-Belarus union must meet terms.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States said Tuesday a planned union between Russia and Belarus would need to meet a series of conditions before winning Washington's approval.</p>
<p>But the State Department stopped short of condemning the plan, saying a document due to be signed on Wednesday in Moscow looked more like a cooperation agreement than a real merger.</p>
<p>The United States has opposed any attempt to reconstitute the Soviet Union ever since it broke into 15 separate republics in 1991.</p>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin threw his weight on Tuesday behind the union agreement with Belarus, but official sources in Moscow said bitter wrangling in the Kremlin meant the final look of any deal was far from certain.</p>
<p>State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns said Washington still needed to know more about the accord before pronouncing on it, and he listed a string of conditions it should meet.</p>
<p>&quot;We certainly would want to make sure ... that any agreement is voluntary; that it's mutually beneficial; that it's outward looking and does not create new lines of division in Europe,&quot; Burns told a news briefing.</p>
<p>&quot;And we certainly would want to be assured that the people of the countries affected would have had a chance to express themselves, express their views in a fair and open political process.&quot;</p>
<p>Burns said that while Russia had such a process, &quot;I'm not sure that Belarus is such a state.&quot;</p>
<p>A draft of the agreement foresees close coordination of foreign, military and economic policies between Russia and Belarus, but stops short of merging the neighbours into a single state.</p>
<p>&quot;What we've seen in the margins today does not seem to be a true union. It seems to be perhaps increased cooperation,&quot; Burns said.</p>
<p>The United States has expressed increasing concern over the policies of Belarus President Alexander Lukashenko since he took office three years ago, and said last month it was downgrading its relationship with Minsk.</p>
<p>Burns charged on Tuesday that in the last few weeks the atmosphere in Belarus had become &quot;increasingly autocratic and dictatorial and anti-democratic&quot; with arrests of journalists and opposition protesters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BYELRS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
