<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479121" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chrysler March total sales fall from a year ago.</title>
<headline>Chrysler March total sales fall from a year ago.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chrysler Corp. Tuesday kicked off the traditional start of the spring selling season by reporting a 3.4 percent drop in March sales as weak car results outweighed steady demand for minivans and Jeep vehicles.</p>
<p>Despite some hefty incentives, passenger car sales at the the U.S. No. 3 automaker fell 9 percent to 74,126. Light truck sales, including pickup trucks, sport utility vehicles and minivans, were 136,389, unchanged on a percentage basis from 136,642 a year ago.</p>
<p>Chrysler, which added dealer incentives of up to $600 on top of its retail rebates last month, sold a total of 210,515 vehicles in March. Sales for the first quarter of 1997 were 572,655, a decline of 1.9 percent from the 1996 first period.</p>
<p>Chrysler, the first of the Big Three automakers to report sales, said its Dodge Caravan and Plymouth Voyager minivans, as well as Jeep Grand Cherokee and Wranger sport utility vehicles, had year-over-year sales gains.</p>
<p>For owners of 1984-96 minivans, Chrysler is offering retail rebates of $500 to $750 on 1997 models. The company also has recently instituted a new finance rate program that lowers interest payments for most long-term loans.</p>
<p>A shortage of popular extended cab models contributed to lower pickup sales. Ram pickup truck sales fell 9 percent to 31,713, while Dakota compact pickup truck sales fell 2 percent to 11,566. The pickup results also were affected by strong year-ago sales.</p>
<p>Chrysler officials, citing solid minivan sales, higher retail car sales and fewer fleet sales, nevertheless painted an upbeat picture for the month.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like it's going to be a pretty good car and truck year all the way around,&quot; said Steve Torok, executive director of sales and marketing operations.</p>
<p>Torok said Chrysler will continue to remain competitive with Japanese vehicles now carrying heavy incentives, but he said the automaker did not expect a significant increase in overall incentive spending.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Japanese automakers reported mixed results for March. Honda Motor Co. Ltd., up against a record March record a year ago, posted a 6.6 percent decline in sales for the month to 79,490.</p>
<p>Total car sales tumbled nearly 16 percent to 67,377. One of the biggest drops occurred with the Accord sedan, where sales plunged 34 percent to 27,165. Total truck sales, spurred by 8,981 CR-V mini sport utility vehicles sales, rose to 12,113.</p>
<p>Honda spokesman Mike Spencer said tight supplies of the popular Accord also contributed to the decrease. Some Accord models have a 30-day supply on dealer lots, while the average for the Accord is 35 days. The industry considers 60 days supply to be ideal.</p>
<p>&quot;It's one of those problems you love to have,&quot; said Spencer, who added the company does not plan to import more vehicles to ease the problem.</p>
<p>Mitsubishi Motor Corp. attributed its 37 percent March sales jump to the popularity of its new Montero Sport sport utility vehicle. Mitsubishi's March sales of the vehicle, launched in December, were 3,093. Overall, the Japanese automaker sold 16,704 vehicles last month.</p>
<p>Subaru of America Inc., a unit of Fuji Heavy Industries Ltd., reported an 8.3 percent decline to 9,102 vehicles. Isuzu Motors Ltd. had March sales of 7,388, down 2.6 percent.</p>
<p>General Motors Corp. is scheduled to report sales Wednesday, and Ford Motor Co. on Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
