<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479162" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US spot prods steady in thin trade, NYMEX weakens.</title>
<headline>US spot prods steady in thin trade, NYMEX weakens.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. spot product differentials showed little movement Monday, with many buyers holding back on their early month purchases, traders said.</p>
<p>However, outright prices eased in line with the NYMEX weakness, as May heating oil shed 0.47 cent and May gasoline shed 0.55 cent by the close.</p>
<p>Sellers tried to boost New York Harbor (NYH) heating oil diffs after the blizzard that hit upstate New York and Massachusetts Monday, though forecasts for much warmer temperatures later this week prevented prices from rallying higher.</p>
<p>&quot;All the sellers are mimicking Sun Co's posting at 2.25 cents (over the NYMEX), and the buyers are just laughing at that,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Bids for the prompt NYH heat oil sat at about 1.75 cents over the screen.</p>
<p>The outage of the 30,000 barrel per day catalytic cracker at Amoco's Texas City, Texas refinery lifted U.S. Gulf (USG) gasoline diffs slightly during early action, though no sustained interest was seen.</p>
<p>USG conventional unleaded M1 barrels for back 10th cycle delivery on the Colonial Pipeline traded at 3.15 cents under the print early in the day, though offers fell back to about 3.25 cents under by the NYMEX close, up about 0.25 cent on the day.</p>
<p>-- Matt Daily, New York Energy Desk +1 212 859 1620</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
