<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479172" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dollar ends lower as U.S.-Japan trade tensions mount.</title>
<headline>Dollar ends lower as U.S.-Japan trade tensions mount.</headline>
<byline>Noah Barkin</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar ended sharply lower against the yen and the mark on Tuesday amid fresh signs of trade tension between the United States and Japan.</p>
<p>Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin told reporters ahead of a six-day trip to Asia that begins on Thursday that he would not welcome a reversal in the progress Japan has made in cutting its trade surplus.</p>
<p>These remarks followed earlier comments from U.S. House Speaker Newt Gingrich on Tuesday. He said in a meeting with Japanese Trade Minister Shinji Sato that current exchange rates meant Japan's trade surplus with the United States was becoming a cause for concern.</p>
<p>Taken together, the comments fuelled speculation that U.S. tolerance of a strong dollar was limited, pushing the currency to its lowest level against the yen in roughly three weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen tons of interest to sell the dollar against the yen,&quot; said Ricardo Gomes, foreign exchange manager at Republic National Bank of New York.</p>
<p>&quot;All the comments have combined to make people nervous about the Japanese trade surplus and if dollar/yen continues to go higher, it's not going to help the situation.&quot;</p>
<p>The dollar ended the day at 121.73 yen, up from its low of 121.40, but substantially down from 123.78 on Monday. Against the mark, the dollar fell to 1.6663 versus 1.6750 on Monday.</p>
<p>Also weighing on the dollar against the yen was speculation that Japan's closely watched quarterly &quot;tankan&quot; survey of business sentiment would show ample strength upon its release on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the tankan report has a lot of the market nervous,&quot; said Paul Park, a dollar/yen trader at Mellon Bank in Pittsburgh. &quot;I don't think it will provide any relief to dollar bulls.&quot;</p>
<p>Dealers said heavy sales of dollars for yen filtered through to weakness against the mark. A less-than-spectacular day for U.S. stocks also weighed on the U.S. currency.</p>
<p>After shedding close to 300 points on the previous two trading days, the Dow Jones industrial average traded lower for much of Tuesday before ending up 27.57 points at 6,611.05 on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Expectations of higher U.S. interest rates were fuelled on Tuesday by heady gains in the National Association of Purchasing Management's March manufacturing index, which rose to 55.0 from 53.1.</p>
<p>In other trading on Tuesday, the dollar ended lower at 1.4415 Swiss francs against 1.4485 on Monday. The British pound rose to $1.6530 from $1.6395.</p>
<p>The dollar rose to Canadian $1.3892 from $1.3845.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
