<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479159" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Documents suggest tobacco firms courted youths.</title>
<headline>Documents suggest tobacco firms courted youths.</headline>
<dateline>PHOENIX 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The tobacco industry manipulated nicotine levels and courted underage smokers despite knowing for years that its product was toxic, according to tobacco industry documents cited Tuesday in a published report.</p>
<p>The Arizona Republic, citing confidential internal documents it had obtained, said the Liggett Group Inc. weighed using a synthetic substance in its products because of the &quot;severe toxicity of nicotine.&quot;</p>
<p>The newspaper also said the tobacco industry tailored its marketing campaigns to specific groups, based on race, age and gender.</p>
<p>One memo states a new packaging should be used &quot;so as to have more appeal to youth.&quot;</p>
<p>Another said 16- to 21-year-olds are &quot;in the formative years (when) smoking starts and brand preferences are developed.&quot;</p>
<p>The documents were made public as part of a historic settlement between Liggett, Arizona and 21 other states that are suing major tobacco companies in an effort to recover the Medicaid costs of treating smoking-releated ailments.</p>
<p>The Republic said the documents, made available by the state attorney general's office at the paper's request, account for just a fraction of what exists. Most are under seal in various state courts.</p>
<p>But the newspaper said the information, made available Monday, offered an outline that suggests Liggett knew cigarettes were habit-forming.</p>
<p>It also pointed to evidence that the company grappled with the product's ill effects on health.</p>
<p>&quot;Is it morally permissable to develop a safe method for administering a habit-forming drug, when, in doing so, the number of addicts will increase?&quot; a company researcher asked in a 1978 memo from obtained by The Republic.</p>
<p>The document goes on to suggest that tobacco will always be used and that the company's real duty &quot;lies in diminishing the adverse consequences.&quot;</p>
<p>A draft memo from 1970 also questions whether the Council for Tobacco Research should pursue studies of health-related problems linked to cigarettes, saying the efforts had failed to take pressure off the industry.</p>
<p>Additionally, the documents show that Liggett watched its competitors closely, monitoring their efforts to win over potential customers.</p>
<p>According to a report prepared by the consulting firm Arthur D. Little, the tobacco industry tried to tailor its marketing to specific groups.</p>
<p>The newspaper said one section of the report said &quot;Spanish and Negro groups like to purchase only the best of everything -- they are not looking for bargains.&quot;</p>
<p>The newspaper quoted another section of the report as saying &quot;there must be a racial slant in the marketing efforts&quot; directed toward minorities, &quot;while in the case of the Jewish market, this is not a requirement.&quot;</p>
<p>Liggett Group is a unit of Brooke Group Ltd.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHOENIX"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
