<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479192" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT wheat ends mostly lower on late sag in soy.</title>
<headline>CBOT wheat ends mostly lower on late sag in soy.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A late sag from the day's highs in soybean futures triggered broad-based speculative selling in the neighboring wheat pit and CBOT wheat futures ended mostly lower, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody was selling because beans were down 10 cents from their highs,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>But wheat was boosted in early dealings by a surge in the CBOT soy complex, which was buoyed by a downward correction by USDA in its estimate for March 1 U.S. soybean stocks.</p>
<p>Wheat also was hit by rumblings in the export market, including persistent talk India was no longer in the market for wheat.</p>
<p>The wheat market was weakened late Monday on talk India over the weekend cancelled a tender for 500,000 tonnes of optional-origin wheat. Overall good crop conditions in U.S. winter wheat areas also checked gains.</p>
<p>Sources this week said very little soft red winter wheat was damaged by floods in Ohio and U.S. Great Plains hard red winter wheat was said in overall good condition.</p>
<p>Wheat closed 3-3/4 cents per bushel lower to four higher, with May down 3-3/4 at $3.93-3/4 a bushel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
