<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479117" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pena does not rule out interim nuclear waste storage.</title>
<headline>Pena does not rule out interim nuclear waste storage.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Paul</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Energy Secretary Federico Pena on Tuesday did not rule out building a temporary facility to store nuclear waste in Nevada, although the White House has opposed Republican proposals to build such a site.</p>
<p>But Pena said any decision on a temporary site depended on whether the Energy Department decides it can build a permanent dump in Nevada's Yucca Mountain to bury radioactive waste from nuclear power plants.</p>
<p>His comments appeared to be in line with the key provision in Republican legislation due to be debated in the Senate next week, which the White House has repeatedly said it would veto.</p>
<p>The Senate bill would force the government to build an interim facility in Nevada near Yucca Mountain for the nuclear waste, if the department decides by 1998 that the mountain can later be used as a permanent dump.</p>
<p>The issue must be resolved this year, because a 1982 law requires the government to take responsibility for commercial nuclear waste by February 1998, while the Energy Department expects to have a dump ready only in 2010 at the earliest.</p>
<p>Environmentalists and the Clinton administration are opposed to running the risk of transporting radioactive waste from dozens of power plants across the country to a central interim site until it is known where the waste will be buried permanently.</p>
<p>&quot;The administration's position is very straightforward,&quot; Pena said. &quot;The president said he believes it is inappropriate to make a prejudment about an interim site prior to the time that the viability assessment is done in 1998.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We ought to take the best scientific and engineering analysis we have when that assessment is made in 1998 and that should then inform us as to what steps should follow,&quot; he said at a press roundtable.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Republican Sen. Frank Murkowski of Alaska, one of the sponsors of the Senate bill, called Pena's comments &quot;good news.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Secretary Pena has just made an argument on behalf of our bipartisan legislation,&quot; the spokesman said. &quot;Chairman Murkowski has already invited him to work with the Senate to iron out any remaining differences.&quot;</p>
<p>Pena said the administration remained concerned that the legislation might undermine federal, state and local laws designed to protect the environment and public safety in the rush to build an interim facility.</p>
<p>Although the bill was pegged to the Department's Yucca Mountain assessment in 1998, he said the administration was worried that the bill left the &quot;impression&quot; it was &quot;predetermining an interim site decision.&quot;</p>
<p>Lawmakers and utilities have been pushing the government to build an interim storage facility to hold up to its side of the 1982 law.</p>
<p>Several states have asked a court to freeze utilities' payments into the federal nuclear waste fund, which has already collected $12 billion from ratepayers, until the government takes over the waste.</p>
<p>Pena is set to meet with nuclear utility executives on Thursday to discuss options for the government to live up to its contract to take responsibility for the waste.</p>
<p>&quot;I take that (contract) very seriously,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Pena declined to list the options he would discuss, but said storing the waste at existing Energy Department facilities was not one of them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
