<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479198" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. debt futures end higher amid shortcovering.</title>
<headline>U.S. debt futures end higher amid shortcovering.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. debt futures finished higher on shortcovering after recent losses, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;We saw a fair amount of short covering, and the excuse that people used was the price component on the NAPM,&quot; a Eurodollar trader said. &quot;But it's just an excuse because the other numbers were quite strong,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Early in the session, the March National Association of Purchasing Management (NAPM) index was reported at 55.0 compared with 53.1 in February. The employment component rose to 51.6 from 45.4 and the prices index fell to 50.9 from 55.1.</p>
<p>February construction spending surged 2.3 percent.  </p>
<p>Traders said the market absorbed the robust data very well and built gains amid strong volume.</p>
<p>&quot;The numbers weren't too bad,&quot; another Euro trader said. &quot;The employment part was pretty bearish but I think they are looking at the prices more.&quot;</p>
<p>A Treasury bond futures trader noted hefty buying interest from dealers all day. He blamed an afternoon dollar/yen decline for a pullback from the high in June T-bond futures. He said 107-16/32 to 107-24/32 had good volume on the day.</p>
<p>&quot;Dollar/yen pulled us into a rotation down, but I think we saw the lows until Friday,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're going to chop around sideways to higher,&quot; the trader said.</p>
<p>Key U.S. employment data will be released on Friday and some traders said the market could remain choppy and indecisive until then. Some tied strength on Tuesday to the perception that any risk in the jobs data would be for a weak  number.</p>
<p>At 0730 CST/1330 GMT on Friday, the March non-farm payrolls report will be released. They are forecast to rise 182,000 compared to a 339,000 gain in February. The unemployment rate was forecast to edge down slightly to 5.2 percent from 5.3 percent.  </p>
<p>At the close, June T-bonds were up 8/32 at 107-15/32, 10-year notes were up 6/32 at 105-22/32, muni-bonds rose 8/32 to 111-28/23, September T-bills rose 0.045 bps to 94.275, and September Eurodollars were up 0.025 bps at 93.710. ((DerivativesDesk(312)408-8750)) E-mail:derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
