<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479185" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX crude ends weak facing a stream of imports.</title>
<headline>NYMEX crude ends weak facing a stream of imports.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX crude ended down Tuesday as the rise in crude demand by refiners is still not high enough to absorb a steady stream of imports, analysts and dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;You have a situation where refinery demand for crude is seen rising, and you would think that would absorb all the crude, but it hasn't,&quot; said John Saucer, analyst with Smith Barney in Houston.</p>
<p>May crude ended 13 cents off at $20.18 a barrel. May gasoline settled 0.55 cent a gallon lower at 62.67 cents. May heating oil finished off 0.47 cent a gallon at 53.95 cents.  </p>
<p>Traders noted a bevy of North Sea and West African crude arriving in the U.S. Gulf amid poor crude demand in Europe. Still, the amount of imports were not deemed unusual for this time of year when U.S. refineries need crude to make gasoline for the summer driving season.</p>
<p>Refinery utilization rates increased a sharp 2.3 percentage points to 92.7 percent for the week ended March 21, the American Petroleum Institute (API) said.</p>
<p>News that some imports are being delayed failed to support crude prices.  </p>
<p>On Tuesday, the Nigerian unit of Royal Dutch Shell Group declared a force majuere effective April 2 for its Bonny light crude after civil unrest disrupted output last week.</p>
<p>&quot;The Shell Nigeria announcement was shrugged off by the market which goes to show how bearish the market is right now,&quot; said Saucer.</p>
<p>Dealers also said there was position squaring amid bearish expectations for Tuesday evening's weekly oil inventory report from the API.</p>
<p>Gasoline stocks typically fall the last week in March which Tuesday's report will reflect. But, last week's anticipated stock fall is seen tempered by high production levels and lacklustre demand.</p>
<p>-- Harry Milling, New York Energy Desk, 212-859-1761</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
