<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479206" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT corn ends mostly higher on soybean gains.</title>
<headline>CBOT corn ends mostly higher on soybean gains.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT corn futures closed mostly higher on a rally in soybeans tied to news USDA had corrected its March 1 quarterly soybean stocks report, traders said.</p>
<p>USDA adjusted downward to 1.056 billion bushels its estimate of U.S. soy stocks as of March 1. The government Monday had pegged the soybean stocks at 1.078 billion bushels.</p>
<p>&quot;The government change was a surprise, it shocked everybody. It means beans (prices) have to go up and cut off demand,&quot; said Paul Haugens, vice president for Chicago-based trade house FIMAT Futures.</p>
<p>&quot;It means the carryout will be drawn down to around 110 million or 100 million bushels and beans will have to go to nine dollars (per bushel) or better to ration demand,&quot; Haugens said. &quot;Corn gets dragged along with this stuff.&quot;</p>
<p>Nearby contracts in corn gained relative to new crop partly on the gains in soybeans and there was spillover impact from Monday's USDA quarterly corn stocks data and 1997 U.S. prospective plantings report.</p>
<p>Corn closed 3-3/4 cents per bushel higher to 1/4 lower, with May up three at $3.13 a bushel. New crop December closed 1/4 higher at $2.91-3/4.  </p>
<p>The government Monday released a U.S. corn stocks tally as of March 1, which came in at a level slightly below trader expectations. USDA also released a prospective U.S. corn plantings number for 1997 at a level above average trader expectations.</p>
<p>Positioned CBOT bull spreaders again profited as the July/December widened 3-1/2 cents per bushel to close at 22-1/4 cents, premium the July, traders noted.</p>
<p>The market took note of news Taiwan corn buying will be sidelined through April as a hog foot and mouth disease slashed demand for corn there. But talk circulated that Indonesia overnight bought at least 500,000 tonnes of corn.</p>
<p>The four- and 20-day moving averages (MA) for the May contract were giving off bullish signals early Tuesday.</p>
<p>The four-day MA for May was at $3.06-1/2 and the 20-day was at $3.03.</p>
<p>Technicians said first support in the May was at $3.06 and second support was at $2.99-1/2. The session low for May was $3.12. First resistance was at $3.12-1/2 and second resistance was at $3.19. The session high for May was $3.20.</p>
<p>The nine-day relative strength index (RSI) for the May closed at 67.7 percent. The market generally views an RSI of 70 or more as overbought and 30 or less as oversold.</p>
<p>ADM Investor Services spread one million bushels of May/December at 23 cents, premium May, traders said. Griffin Trading did three million bushels of July/December at 23 cents, premium July, traders said.</p>
<p>Cargill Inc bought three million bushels of May and sold two million May, floor sources said. Merrill Lynch Futures sold four million Julhy and sold three million bushels of May. Refco Inc bought five million bushels of July and Prudential Securities bought three million bushels of July, traders said.</p>
<p>Corn futures volume was estimated by the CBOT at 90,000 contracts, above the 85,347 traded Monday.</p>
<p>In corn options, Refco Inc bought 800 May $3.10 calls and sold 800 July $3.40 calls, Term Commodities bought 1,000 May $3.10 puts at 4-1/8 to 4-1/2 cents, E.D. and F. Man International bought 800 December $2.40 puts, traders said.</p>
<p>Corn options volume was estimated at 25,000 contracts, below the 28,951 traded Monday.</p>
<p>((Sam Nelson 312-408-8721))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
