<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479274" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. retail pork prices seen rising this summer.</title>
<headline>U.S. retail pork prices seen rising this summer.</headline>
<byline>Bob Burgdorfer</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. consumers longing for grilled pork chops or pork steaks this summer may have to pay higher prices thanks to a couple of recent global developments.</p>
<p>&quot;They (supermarkets) are going to be expecting pretty high wholesale prices,&quot; said Kevin Bost, a meat analyst with Topco Associates, a nationwide supplier of meat to supermarkets. &quot;Therefore I would expect those expectations to be reflected in retail prices.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. government action that could halt meat imports from Europe, along with a ban on pork exports from Taiwan, could both work to raise prices in the United States, industry analysts said.</p>
<p>Bost said the higher prices may spur consumers to cut back on their pork purchases.</p>
<p>&quot;They will buy smaller quantities of it. The function of price is to ration demand,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tight pork supplies may make this form of rationing necessary. Japan is expected to buy more U.S. pork, after its leading supplier Taiwan halted pork exports last month because of an outbreak of foot and mouth disease.  </p>
<p>And on Tuesday, the U.S. Agriculture Department said it would implement a new meat inspection system that could halt the import of some $300 million worth of European meat.</p>
<p>U.S. wholesale pork prices have risen sharply since Taiwan banned exports on March 20, and they may move still higher, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts said the action against Europe, which stemmed from a dispute over inspection methods, might support prices for some some pork cuts, but would have less influence on prices than the Taiwan action.</p>
<p>In 1996, Taiwan shipped about 267,000 tonnes of pork to Japan, and U.S. meat analysts expect U.S. pork to fill much of that void. Japan last year bought 108,565 tonnes of U.S. pork, according to Japanese data.</p>
<p>Dale Benson, a livestock analyst with Dean Witter, said the U.S. primarily buys hams from Europe, and Tuesday's action could underpin ham prices.</p>
<p>Benson said prices for pork loins, from which pork chops and steaks are made, may rise sharply this summer.</p>
<p>&quot;The Japanese use more loins than anything,&quot; he said, which should keep supplies tight for that cut.  </p>
<p>However, Benson cautioned that supermarket pork prices are already high, and further increases could prompt shoppers to turn to beef for their summertime cookouts.</p>
<p>&quot;Supermarkets, if they advance prices much more (for pork), will lose sales,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The meat dispute with Europe could underpin U.S. pork prices but the situation may be resolved before imports are actually halted, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;It may take a few weeks to implement and by that time they might come to terms,&quot; said Chuck Levitt, a meat analyst with Alaron Trading Corp. &quot;It wouldn't serve their best interest to end up in a meat war with the U.S.&quot;</p>
<p>Levitt said demand for European beef was hurt by fears of bovine spongiform encephalopathy, or &quot;mad cow&quot; disease.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100119">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
