<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479254" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYS gov sees bigger surplus, plans to repay debt.</title>
<headline>NYS gov sees bigger surplus, plans to repay debt.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York State Governor, getting the benefit of big earnings by Wall Street financial houses, said Tuesday there was a bigger surplus in fiscal 1997, adding extra revenues also can be expected next year.</p>
<p>Gov. George Pataki said New York State, whose 1997 fiscal year ended on March 31, has $370 million of additional unbudgeted revenues, on top of the $1.05 billion surplus that already was included in next year's budget.  </p>
<p>Further, Pataki said that another $490 million was found in a consensus revenue forecasting conference, bringing the total amount available for fiscal 1998 to $860 million. New York State has for the 13th year in a row begun a new fiscal year without having approved a new budget for it.</p>
<p>The Republican governor and the Senate, which is led by Republicans, and the Democrat-controlled Assembly missed a March 10 deadline for agreeing on a revenue prediction, and Pataki said his budget officials would be meeting with legislative leaders to give them more information for the next round of talks. Pataki's estimates have been more conservative than the legislature's, especially the Assembly's.</p>
<p>Pataki was quick to warn the Assembly, which he said wants to raise spending by $4 billion in its one-house budget, from using the surplus unwisely. &quot;We owe it to the taxpayers to use our surplus responsibly. The Assembly Democrats want to embark on the largest single spending binge in the history of our state,&quot; he said, in prepared remarks.</p>
<p>The governor's plans include using $250 million to pay off outstanding bonds on Attica State Prison, which he said would save more than $200 million in future interest. He also wanted to use $435 million to advance the first phase of his school tax relief plan by one year. And $18 million would be used to pay off state-supported bonds that financed &quot;Harlem Valley,&quot; saving about $12 million in interest costs. A spokesman was not immediately available to describe what Harlem Valley was. Another $157 million was available for &quot;other budget priorities,&quot; Pataki said.</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
