<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479233" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USDA to tighten drill after error rattles markets.</title>
<headline>USDA to tighten drill after error rattles markets.</headline>
<byline>Leila Corcoran</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>World commodity markets reeled Tuesday after the Agriculture Department admitted that for the first time in three decades, it goofed in calculating U.S. soybean stocks.</p>
<p>Prices soared around the globe as traders, analysts and farmers digested the news that already tight U.S. soybean stocks were 22 million bushels lower than the department initially said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's embarrassing and it makes us look silly,&quot; said Ray Halley, chief of the crops branch of the Agriculture Department's National Agriculture Statistics Service.</p>
<p>On Monday, in its quarterly report on the amount of grain in U.S. bins, the Agriculture Department pegged U.S. soybean stocks at 1.08 billion bushels. But the department uncovered the 22-million-bushel error later in the day after a telephone call from a concerned market analyst.</p>
<p>It issued a correction early Tuesday, cutting the figure to 1.06 billion bushels in the first revision of this magnitude by the department since the 1960s.</p>
<p>The correction stunned world traders, who consider the Agriculture Department an authoritative source of supply and demand estimates.</p>
<p>Soybean futures on the Chicago Board of Trade shot up as much as 30 cents a bushel on the news in trading that one market player called &quot;wild and woolly.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone was surprised. This was a substantial turnaround in the numbers,&quot; said Sheldon Hauck, head of the National Soybean Processors Association. &quot;We sure hope that these are the right numbers now,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>July soybean contracts ended up 20-1/2 cents a bushel at $8.78-1/2 on the Chicago Board of Trade.</p>
<p>The Agriculture Department gathers and calculates thousands of statistics each year, using armies of analysts and computer programmes. Department officials said the embarrassing error was made by an employee in its Mississippi field office who made a math mistake.</p>
<p>&quot;We pride ourselves on not making mistakes like this,&quot; said Halley. &quot;But when you look at the volume of data, it's easy to see how people get tired and the review process breaks down.&quot;</p>
<p>Halley said the department planned to tighten the drill to prevent another mistake of this kind. It was not immediately clear if the department's Office of Inspector General or any of the congressional committees with oversight over the Agriculture Department would take action.</p>
<p>One former Agriculture Department official, speaking on condition of anonymity, recalled that the department conducted a review and several employees left after an error on stocks in the 1980s.</p>
<p>U.S. soybean stocks are forecast to tumble to the lowest level in 20 years this fall, and the department's revised measure of current stocks added to fears that supplies would not last through August.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100223">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
