<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479271" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kennedy Center concert hall gets a hearing aid.</title>
<headline>Kennedy Center concert hall gets a hearing aid.</headline>
<byline>Michael Posner</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A $10 million overhaul of the Kennedy Centre concert hall is underway that officials said on Tuesday should end a chronic hearing problem and improve the prestigious music hall.</p>
<p>Music director Leonard Slatkin of the National Symphony Orchestra and Lawrence Wilker, president of the John F. Kennedy Centre for the Performing Arts, told a news conference the renovation should be completed by Oct. 24.</p>
<p>Slatkin, who succeeded renowned cellist Mstislav Rostropovich last year as music director, also announced he will lead the orchestra on a three-week tour of Europe with 14 concerts in Germany, Austria, the Netherlands, France and Britain starting on Sept. 20.</p>
<p>A new $1 million &quot;acoustics cloud&quot; that will hang over the cavernous 25-year-old hall should solve the problem of musicians not able to hear colleagues play and concert-goers getting echoes of notes.</p>
<p>Slatkin said &quot;listeners basically were not getting enough of the low ends and the high frequencies were too shrill.&quot; Some people were sitting in &quot;dead spots&quot; in the hall.</p>
<p>Reporters wearing hard hats were escorted into the concert hall, which is now an empty shell, without seats, its Norway-donated chandeliers or its stage backdropped with a massive organ. The only sounds came from workers wielding welding torches high above on scaffolds.</p>
<p>Besides acoustical improvements, new seating arrangments will be constructed, with some seats on the stage. Seats where listeners could not see the stage at all will be eliminated. New ramps and seats for the disabled are being installed but overall there will be fewer seats, 2,448 instead of 2,759.</p>
<p>Paul Scarbrough, an acoustical designer, told reporters &quot;there were a number of sources of echoes around the hall, so if you sat in certain locations, particularly like the box tier on the side, you'd get a very distracting second image of the sound.&quot;</p>
<p>He said &quot;the  canopy will help break up those kinds of reflections and direct the sounds to the audience in a clearer way, so they get a very intimate sound quality.&quot;</p>
<p>The centre, which also includes theatres and opera halls, was built as a memorial to the late President John Kennedy and is one of the nation's busiest entertainment centres.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
