<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479208" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FCOJ futures close narrowly mixed, consolidate.</title>
<headline>FCOJ futures close narrowly mixed, consolidate.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Frozen concentrated orange juice May futures fell barely below unchanged on the close after local and trade buying supported prices throughout the day, dealers said.</p>
<p>The front three months fell to new contract lows in early trade, but technically-driven buying pushed the market higher after prices failed to rack up additional losses.</p>
<p>May settled down 0.20 cent at 76.15 cents per lb, having ranged from 76.75 to 75.50 cents, a new contract low. The back months finished 0.05 lower to 0.05 firmer.</p>
<p>Support was seen at 74.00 and then at 72.00 cents in May.</p>
<p>Volume was estimated at 3,500 lots compared to Monday's official 6,513 lots.</p>
<p>Analysts said today's gains represent a temporary correction to recent losses, adding that prices should continue to fall amid abundant supplies.</p>
<p>&quot;The market will be burdened with supplies for the next few years,&quot; an analyst said.</p>
<p>The Brazilian state of Sao Paulo said its orange crop could reach 381.8 million 40-kg boxes in 1997/98 compared to about 355 million boxes this year.</p>
<p>The Brazilian Association of Citrus Exporters will release its first estimate of Brazil's 1997/98 crop on May 20.</p>
<p>Also, Mexico said it will produce about 48,000 tonnes of orange juice concentrate in 1997, down from 50,000 tonnes in 1996. Most of the concentrate will be exported.</p>
<p>SNIM, a branch of the Mexican Trade Ministry, blamed the decline on a rise in demand for fresh orange juice following the country's economic recovery.</p>
<p>Industry sources expect the U.S. Department of Agriculture to raise Florida yields in its next report, released April 11.</p>
<p>&quot;There is plenty of juice on the planet and there will be for a long time,&quot; the analyst said. &quot;All we can do is wait for the technicals to become oversold.&quot;</p>
<p>Following today's close, the U.S. Department of Agriculture said Brazil's 1996 orange juice output would reach 1.14 million tonnes, compared to 1.06 million tonnes in its previous estimate.</p>
<p>Exports were estimated at 1.095 million tonnes versus 1.05 million tonnes previously.</p>
<p>((Suzanne Rostler, New York Commoditites, 212-859-1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
