<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479251" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INSIGHT-June U.S. T-bonds could be set for upturn.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT-June U.S. T-bonds could be set for upturn.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>June U.S. Treasury bond futures, having held key support at 106-22, could be set for a recovery, or at least a period of basing, technical analysts said Tuesday.</p>
<p>June T-bonds bounced off 106-25/32 in early trading Tuesday and were up moderately in afternoon activity. The 106-22 level was the low struck on September 19, 1996.</p>
<p>Richard Scarlata, editor of the Sutton Advisory Letter, said he has turned bullish on bonds on a 10-day, 30-day and 90-day basis after bonds reached both yield and price support.  </p>
<p>&quot;In my view, the debt market has already discounted the worst that could possibly happen in terms of the Federal Reserve and monetary tightening,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He noted that June bonds reacted little to a string of stronger than expected economic data that included February construction spending and leading economic indicators and the March National Association of Purchasing Management index.</p>
<p>&quot;If they get any kind of good news, which means slowing economic growth and better inflation numbers, they're just going to rally sharply,&quot; he said, referring to bonds.  </p>
<p>James Grauer, president of Omnitrage, said that while bonds could see some further upside over the near term, they are more likely beginning a period of basing.</p>
<p>&quot;For the moment, we have an extremely oversold condition,&quot; he said. &quot;There's a very high probability of a bounce, and we're getting that today.</p>
<p>&quot;But I don't look for very much on this,&quot; he said, adding that the market's near-term upside could be limited to the 109 area.</p>
<p>Scarlata said he expects a near-term move in June bonds to their March 25 high at 109-25/32 on their way to 111-28/32.  </p>
<p>&quot;The market has a tendency to come back to that level,&quot; he said of 111-28/32. &quot;I wouldn't have turned long-term bullish if I hadn't at least expected that move.&quot;</p>
<p>Grauer said he is not bearish toward bonds but does not see a great deal of upside potential even though his daily stochastic chart is forming a &quot;beautiful&quot; bullish divergence.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a case where the fundamentals are simply swamping the technicals,&quot; he said, adding that the market's basing pattern could last until the Federal Reserve has finished raising interest rates, which could come as early as May.  </p>
<p>T-bonds(M):  Support			    Resistance</p>
<p>107-02  Channel support	     108-07  Approx 7.0 pct yield</p>
<p>106-22  Sept 19 low		   109-22  March 13 high</p>
<p>106-18  Approx 7-1/8 pct yield    109-23  Trendline-early Feb</p>
<p>Eurodollars(U):</p>
<p>93.510  7-month low-Sept 19	 93.790  March 26 high</p>
<p>93.200  8-1/2-month low Sept 6    93.880  200-day moving avg.</p>
<p>93.090  1-3/4-year low July 8     93.900  1-week high-March 25</p>
<p>((Chicago Derivatives Desk 312-408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail:derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
