<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479255" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FORECAST-Tempered gasoline stock draw seen in APIs.</title>
<headline>FORECAST-Tempered gasoline stock draw seen in APIs.</headline>
<byline>Harry Milling</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tuesday evening's oil inventory data from the American Petroleum Institute (API) is expected to show a seasonal draw in gasoline stocks, but the draw is seen tempered by high output and lacklustre demand, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a strong seasonal bias for gasoline stock draws, but consumption seems to be leveling out when production is high,&quot; said Jim Ritterbusch, Sweeney Oil trader in Illinois.</p>
<p>A Reuters poll of trader estimates forecasted gasoline stocks could show a draw of 500,000 to three million barrels.  </p>
<p>The data reflects the week ended March 28.</p>
<p>Gasoline demand begins to rise in the spring until peaking during the summer driving season. Traders said demand for gasoline by retailers built up with much more momentum a year ago, so this year's seasonal draw in the last week in March will not be as steep.</p>
<p>&quot;There has also been a huge amount of imports of (gasoline) feedstock,&quot; said Ritterbusch, noting gasoline output has risen sharply in tandem. Refinery runs are expected to rise another 0.25 to 0.50 percentage point after rising a sharp 2.3 percentage points for the week ended March 21.  </p>
<p>Even with the increasing in refinery utilization rate, crude stocks are expected to rise by up to three million barrels.</p>
<p>&quot;With demand for crude low in the Europe, North Sea crude has to find somewhere to go,&quot; said a Houston crude trader, attributing the rise in crude stocks to an increase in North Sea crude imports.</p>
<p>But, analysts said the amount of crude imports falls within a seasonal trend. U.S. refiners need more crude in the spring to make gasoline. Moreover, gasoline demand is bound to pick up, analysts said.  </p>
<p>&quot;I would not write off gasoline just yet. Gasoline demand typically peaks around July and August, and refiners are usually prepared before then,&quot; said John Saucer, analyst with Smith Barney in Houston.</p>
<p>Distillate stocks, which include heating oil and diesel, are seen falling a little more than one million barrels. Distillate stocks trend downward in the spring and summer as refiners focus on gasoline output.</p>
<p>-- New York Energy Desk, 212-859-1620</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
