<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479259" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USDA soy end-stocks seen below 140 mln bu- traders.</title>
<headline>USDA soy end-stocks seen below 140 mln bu- traders.</headline>
<byline>Emily Kaiser</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Agriculture Department's cut in quarterly soybean stocks means supplies will fall below a forecast tight 140 million bushels this summer unless prices rally enough to curb crushing and exports, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to average weekly crush and export use at 34.3 million bushels to meet USDA's goals, and last week we were at 40.4,&quot; said Steve Freed, analyst with ADM Investor Services.</p>
<p>&quot;Next week could be 48 (million). We're considerably ahead of the pace needed to meet USDA's 140 million,&quot; Freed said.  </p>
<p>The USDA on Tuesday corrected its March 1 soybean stocks figure to 1.056 billion bushels from the 1.078 billion bushels it reported on Monday. The year-ago figure was 1.190 billion.</p>
<p>The lower revision, which USDA said was based on a miscalculation of supplies in Mississippi, compounded fears that U.S. supplies may not last through August. CBOT soybean and soymeal futures soared for limit gains at Tuesday's open.</p>
<p>&quot;It absolutely, completely turned around the psychology of the market from 18 hours ago,&quot; said Charlie Sernatinger, grain analyst with E.D. and F. Man International. &quot;This morning they walked in and said, 'We don't have enough beans.'&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;We cannot survive on a 140 carry right now,&quot; Sernatinger said. USDA on March 11 estimated September 1, 1997, soybean ending stocks at 140 million bushels, or roughly 2-1/2 weeks' usage.</p>
<p>Mark Weidner, an oilseeds analyst with Cargill Investor Services, said the cut in quarterly stocks ensured a drop in ending stocks unless prices rallied to ration demand.</p>
<p>&quot;This (quarterly stocks) number implies lower ending stocks, but I'm expecting a rationing of demand on the export side in both meal and beans,&quot; Weidner said. &quot;Just based on this report, it would have to imply ending stocks under 130.&quot;  </p>
<p>The U.S. Census Bureau said processors crushed record amounts of soybeans in December and January</p>
<p>Last week's National Oilseed Processors Association weekly crush reached 28.32 million bushels, below recent levels of 30 million bushels but well above average, analysts said.</p>
<p>Dean Witter analyst Jerry Gidel said the current usage pace suggests ending stocks could drop to 100 million bushels.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm looking at 100 million bushels right now,&quot; Gidel said. &quot;The reality is at this point the market needs to do some more price rationing. We've got to get the price high enough to have stocks at 130 to 140 million.&quot;  </p>
<p>Gidel and others said that price was probably between $9.20 and $9.60 per bushel, basis CBOT May and July futures.</p>
<p>At that level, crush and export usage combined should drop below 35 million bushels, analysts said.</p>
<p>As of March 20, soybean exports since September 1 totalled 18.66 million tonnes, versus 15.89 million a year earlier.</p>
<p>ADM's Freed said the weekly crush woul need to fall to 24.8 million bushels with export inspections at 10 million bushels.</p>
<p>&quot;We know the inspections have to drop down below 10 million,&quot; Freed said. &quot;I think next week they're going to be 20 million, so that's not going to help much. Crush needs to average 24.8 million.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We went through March at above-average crush and export,&quot; Cargill's Weidner said. &quot;We're going to have to see it drop below 35 million (bushels) combined crush and export per week. We need to see crush at 24 to 25 million.&quot; ((Chicago Newsdesk 312-408-8749))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100223">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
