<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479281" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US crossover investors recoil from emerging mkts.</title>
<headline>US crossover investors recoil from emerging mkts.</headline>
<byline>Nailene Chou Wiest</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Expecting a further credit crunch ahead, U.S. crossover investors have beaten a quick retreat from the emerging markets, experts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The tolerance for risk is changing,&quot; said Raul Elizalde, senior quantitative analyst at ING Barings, noting fear of dwindling liquidity across a broad swath of assets, including emerging markets.</p>
<p>Except for funds dedicated to emerging markets, others shed assets that are not tied to their performance benchmarks in a volatile market, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;They do not stick to the non-core investments through thick and thin,&quot; Elizalde said.</p>
<p>Barely six months ago, when investors from global fixed income and high yield funds piled into emerging markets, the &quot;mainstreaming&quot; was hailed as a significant development.</p>
<p>Unlike hedge funds, which were often perceived as fickle, the increasing presence of mainstream institutional investors with longer investment horizons was expected to reduce volatility in the emerging markets.  </p>
<p>But using a phrase coined by Texas billionaire and U.S. Presidential candidate Ross Perot, traders said they heard a &quot;giant sucking sound&quot; of money exiting the market from crossover investors and hedge funds alike.</p>
<p>The outflow began in late February when U.S. Federal Reserve Chairman Alan Greenspan expressed concerns about inflated asset prices and hinted about credit tightening to pre-empt rising inflation, they said. At that time, traders predicted the exodus would continue until excess leverage trades were unwound.  </p>
<p>Some analysts said the impact of higher rates on the unwinding of &quot;carry trades&quot; would be less severe this year than in 1994 when the Fed began a series of rate hikes because the current U.S. yield curve is much higher and flatter.</p>
<p>But others pointed out that the liquidity that flooded the market until February cannot be attributed solely to U.S. interest rate levels.</p>
<p>&quot;You have to look at Japan and EMU,&quot; ING's Elizalde said.  </p>
<p>The uncertainty of global interest rates would exact a heavy toll on emerging markets, which are more vulnerable to expected volatility in interest rates than to rising rates per se, analysts and traders said.</p>
<p>They cited the example in 1996 that spreads of Brady bonds over U.S. Treasuries actually narrowed while the long bond yield climbed slowly.</p>
<p>Thanks to the improving economic fundamentals in Latin America, major Brady debt countries are now on much sounder footing than in 1994, said John Cadley, vice president at J.P. Morgan Securities.  </p>
<p>Sovereign spreads should continue to tighten over time, which would put the gains of emerging markets debt ahead of other &quot;high beta&quot; assets, such as high-yield corporate bonds, he added.</p>
<p>Beta measures the relationship between an investment's risk and the market's risk.</p>
<p>Cadley asserted that despite anecdotal evidence, spreads have not been proven to have a positive correlation to interest rates on a consistent basis.</p>
<p>Assuming the interest rate risk is hedged away, the yield spread differential between emerging debts and high-yield corporate bonds could narrow by up to 100 basis points over the next 12 months, he predicted.</p>
<p>Currently, the spread of the Merrill Lynch high-yield bond index over U.S. Treasuries was about 270 basis points, and the differential of the J.P. Morgan Emerging Market Bond Index Plus over Treasuries was 470 basis points, Cadley added.</p>
<p>(( -- 212-859-1674 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
