<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479216" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME live cattle end lower on dull cash cattle,beef.</title>
<headline>CME live cattle end lower on dull cash cattle,beef.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lackluster direct fed cattle trade and renewed rolling of longs out of April weighed on CME live cattle futures at the close, traders said. Feeder cattle futures were pressured by higher grain futures.</p>
<p>Live cattle closed 0.250 cent per lb lower to 0.050 higher with only October up and April off 0.225 at 68.250 cents. Feeder cattle finished 0.275 to 0.700 cent per lb lower with May off 0.425 at 69.425 cents.</p>
<p>A lack of cash trade weighed on sentiment in live cattle and prices moved lower in slow dealings. Falling boxed beef prices also pressured the market, traders said.</p>
<p>USDA reported midday beef cut-out values Tuesday down $0.33 to $0.62 per cwt. The drop extended a several-day slide in beef values that started last Wednesday.</p>
<p>Nearby cattle futures weakened further late when longs, mostly funds, rolled positions into June after commercials had rolled their short April positions early.</p>
<p>There is a large open interest in April that needs to be reduced, traders added.</p>
<p>LIT division/First Options spread long June/short April late with locals on the other side, traders said. ED &amp; F Man, Prudential Securities and FIMAT Futures also did the spread.</p>
<p>E.D.&amp;F. Man and RBH notably sold June early, pit sources said.  </p>
<p>In live cattle options, commission houses bought April and June 70 calls early and sold both 68 puts and calls in April during the day. There was renewed June 61 put selling late, pit sources added.</p>
<p>Feeder cattle futures were pushed to lower closes by sharply higher grain futures, traders in that pit said. The rally in corn futures offset supportive effects of a higher CME feeder cattle index and expected pickup in demand for feeders to go on pastures which are starting to green up in portions of the U.S. The market also looks technically toppy, traders said.</p>
<p>The latest CME feeder cattle index was up $0.39 at $69.98 per cwt.</p>
<p>LIT division of First Options bought May early and sold April late, traders said, and R.J. O'Brien and Rosenthal Collins bought April while ABN Chicogo Corp and Rosenthal bought May. Refco bought August. FIMAT Futures USA spread long April/short May early, pit sources said.</p>
<p>((Jerry Bieszk 312-408-8725))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
