<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479228" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US wheat in key HRW states reported in good shape.</title>
<headline>US wheat in key HRW states reported in good shape.</headline>
<byline>Nigel Hunt</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Key U.S. hard red winter wheat states such as Kansas and Oklahoma appear poised for much larger crops this year than last although much will depend on conditions during the next few weeks, agronomists said.</p>
<p>&quot;In comparison to last year it is a helluva lot better. We could use a rain but it is not urgent,&quot; said Jim Shroyer, extension wheat specialist at Kansas State University.</p>
<p>Kansas grain dealers said the crop had the potential to exceed 400 million bushels. Last year's crop was estimated by the U.S. Department of Agriculture at 255 million bushels.  </p>
<p>Shroyer, who declined to predict the crop size, said above normal temperatures, wind or the lack of rain could cut into the crop's potential.</p>
<p>He also said winterkill had been discovered in three or four counties on the eastern edge of central Kansas and more may be uncovered in the next week or so.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen a little winterkill in certain areas. Cold temperatures in January did a little more damage than I would have anticipated, mainly on wheat that was planted just a little bit later than normal,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Leaf rust was also considered a threat.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're a little bit concerned that leaf rust will raise its ugly head and be a problem as there are fairly high levels in Texas and Oklahoma,&quot; Kansas State's Shroyer said.</p>
<p>The weekly state crop report issued Monday, classified 85 percent of the Kansas wheat crop in good or excellent condition, versus 14 percent at the same stage last year.</p>
<p>In Oklahoma the outlook was also promising.</p>
<p>&quot;If we get rain this week I don't think we could ask for things to look any better than they do now,&quot; said Gene Krenzer, extension agronomist at Oklahoma State University.  </p>
<p>Oklahoma has had two successive poor crops, with last year's 93.1 million bushels representing a drop of more than 50 percent from 1994's 143.1 million.</p>
<p>&quot;We should be significantly better than the last couple of years. It could be all the way from 120 million bushel to 210 million right now. The weather we have in the next six weeks is extremely critical to what happens,&quot; Krenzer said.</p>
<p>He said to fulfil the potential, Oklahoma needed &quot;timely rains and cool enough during May to fill the grain properly.&quot;</p>
<p>Krenzer said leaf rust would be a major concern, particularly if the crop received the rains it needs.</p>
<p>In Texas statewide wheat condition was rated at 76 percent of normal, well above 36 percent last year, according to the state's weekly crop report.</p>
<p>It said irrigated fields were continuing to make good progress while dryland fields were stressed and in need of rain. It also noted isolated fields had signficant rust problems.</p>
<p>Last year Texas produced 75.4 million bushels of winter wheat, marginally down from 75.6 million a year earlier, according to U.S. Department of Agriculture data.</p>
<p>((Chicago newsdesk 312-408 8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
