<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479286" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: San Francisco area job market leads state - report.</title>
<headline>San Francisco area job market leads state - report.</headline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jobs lost in the San Francisco Bay area during the 1990-1994 recession have been replaced by jobs with comparably high wages, according to an economic report released on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Last year, the Bay area added about 100,000 non-farm payroll jobs, according to a report in the Bay Area Council's quarterly Bay Area Economic Pulse newsletter.</p>
<p>Economist Joe Nation, editor of Economic Pulse, said his review of job quality showed that Bay area jobs pay higher wages than the state average and that average wages in the Bay area increased at the rate of inflation in 1996.  </p>
<p>The wage gains were led by employment growth in high-wage, high-skilled manufacturing, and in a variety of professional services, Nation's report said.</p>
<p>The report said that the average wage in the Bay area in late 1996 was $34,700, nine percent above the statewide average of $31,900 and 11 percent above the $31,000 California average excluding the Bay area.</p>
<p>Employment growth in the lowest-wage sector, retail trade, has been disproportionately small in the Bay area, the report said. Retail trade registered only an 11 percent share of growth over the past three years, about one-half the level expected, the report said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
