<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479231" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: OPTIONS - Vols soft as dollar seeks clear trend.</title>
<headline>OPTIONS - Vols soft as dollar seeks clear trend.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Implied volatilities for dollar-pair options eased as the dollar continued to probe for a trend against major currencies.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is really struggling to see a clear trend,&quot; said a New York-based trader for a Japanese bank.</p>
<p>Options traders in Chicago said a large sale overnight of one-year dollar/yen volatility continued to weigh on levels in in U.S. trading, but the effect was mitigated somewhat by the dollar's pullback versus the yen.  </p>
<p>The dollar slid below 122.00 yen around midday after U.S. Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin said he did not want to see progress in the U.S.-Japan trade imbalance reversed, following similar remarks by U.S. House Speaker Newt Gingrich.</p>
<p>One-month dollar/yen volatility at midday was at 10.0/10.3 percent, down about 0.3 point from the previous day. One-week dollar/yen slipped 0.5 point to 10.0/11.0 percent.</p>
<p>Currency options markets in general were said to be gearing back up as European traders returned from the Easter holiday and participants contemplated new strategies at the start of Japan's new fiscal year.  </p>
<p>Many analysts are looking for Japan's &quot;tankan&quot; survey of business sentiment to set the dollar's next course.</p>
<p>This morning, expectations for a positive survey outlook were supporting the yen and underpinning dollar/yen volatilities, traders said.</p>
<p>The Japanese bank trader said she expected to see increased corporate interest in 127 and 128 yen puts as a hedge for exporters if the dollar rebounds to crack the 125 yen level.  </p>
<p>Meanwhile, one-month dollar/mark volatility was essentially flat at 9.3/9.5 percent, with one-week declining to 8.5/9.5 percent.</p>
<p>Dollar/mark risk reversals were skewed to mark calls, at 0.05/0.25, with dollar/yen reversals at par, quoted at -0.2/0.2.</p>
<p>Chicago Derivatives Desk ((312-408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail: derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
