<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479275" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INTERVIEW-Invacare sees Healthdyne growth.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW-Invacare sees Healthdyne growth.</headline>
<byline>Robin Sidel</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Invacare Corp said Tuesday its proposed acquisition of Healthdyne Technologies Inc would provide sizable savings and new opportunities for the sale and marketing of Healthdyne medical devices.</p>
<p>Invacare also said it has not received a response from Healthdyne to its newly-revised hostile bid.  On Monday, Invacare raised its offer to $173 million from $166 million.</p>
<p>&quot;We basically offered this additional price to try to encourage (Healthdyne chairman Parker Petit) to sit down and talk with us,&quot; Mixon said in a telephone interview.  </p>
<p>The higher bid marked the second increase for Invacare since it launched the hostile offer for Healthdyne at $12.50 per share in January.  The bid is now worth $13.50 per share.</p>
<p>Healthdyne, which rejected the previous offers, could not be reached for comment.</p>
<p>Mixon declined to discuss specific cost savings anticipated from a Healthdyne acquisition but noted that most analysts pegged the figure at $5 to $7 million.</p>
<p>And although there is little overlap in the product lines of the two companies, Mixon said the products are complementary.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're a very strong marketing company.  They are very weak in the sales and marketing side.  Frankly, I don't think they'll fare very well long-term against their competitors unless they do have a strong marketing organization,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Mixon downplayed speculation Healthdyne may be seeking a &quot;white knight&quot; in order to avoid a deal with Invacare.</p>
<p>&quot;You know they're looking for one, but I don't think anybody can buy it at $13.50 (per share) and run it stand-alone and get an acceptable return on investment...There are some great healthcare companies out there, but they don't have any synergies&quot; with Healthdyne, he said.  </p>
<p>Invacare raised its bid for Healthdyne just days after the Georgia legislature rejected a measure requiring public companies to stagger the election of board directors.  The measure would have crushed takeover attempts, like that of Invacare, in which an unwelcome bidder sought to take control by replacing a company's board.</p>
<p>Shares of Healthdyne rose 11/64 to 14-1/4.</p>
<p>Mixon said the takeover effort is not interfering with Invacare's daily operations, noting that the hostile bid will be at least partly funded from profits made when it bought 4.9 percent of Healthdyne last year for less than $9 per share.</p>
<p>&quot;Right now I have a $3.5 million gain which I will use to offset the legal costs and banking costs and so forth,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He also noted that Invacare is well-placed to operate with or without Healthdyne, adding &quot;it would be nice to have it. We're serious about it.  Our future doesn't depend on having it.  If we lose, we lose.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I37200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
