<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479394" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Syria calls on Europe to aid ailing peace process.</title>
<headline>Syria calls on Europe to aid ailing peace process.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Syrian Foreign Minister Farouq al-Shara called on Europe on Tuesday to help save the ailing Middle East peace process and tried to present fresh Arab attempts to isolate Israel as the best way to revive talks.</p>
<p>After a meeting with Spanish leaders in Madrid, Shara said Arab states wanted to freeze ties with the Jewish state and revive an economic boycott to draw international attention to what he called Israeli damage to the peace process.</p>
<p>&quot;We passed the resolution to awaken international public opinion including inside Israel to see what their government has done to the peace process and how it is leading this process to its graveyard,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Arab League foreign ministers, frustrated at Israeli settlement policy, recommended freezing links with Israel and reactivating an old economic boycott at a meeting in Cairo on Monday.</p>
<p>A senior Spanish official said Madrid did not support the decision which it sees as obstructing further peace talks.</p>
<p>&quot;We understand the frustration of the Arab countries...but naturally we regret this measure which cuts off the paths of dialogue,&quot; the state secretary for foreign policy and the EU, Ramon de Miguel, said at a joint news conference with Shara.</p>
<p>&quot;Spain continues to believe that it is only through permanent dialogue that the Middle East's problems can be resolved,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Shara, who also met Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar, said the peace process was in desperate need of outside help to stop it from collapsing.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like to see a vigorous European effort to contribute to the peace process alongside the U.S. which is a major co-sponsor to the process,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said the Arab League's decision would shut the gates of normalisation and the U.S. also criticised the resolution.</p>
<p>The crisis between Arab states and Israel came to a head when Israeli bulldozers broke ground at a Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem in March and after an attack by a Palestinian suicide bomber in Tel Aviv which killed three Israeli women.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SYRIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
