<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479314" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Atlanta Braves battle April Fool's day.</title>
<headline>Atlanta Braves battle April Fool's day.</headline>
<byline>David Morgan</byline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Atlanta Braves were flooded with phone calls on Tuesday after radio announcers said the championship team would be sold to Walt Disney Co., move to Orlando, Fla., and trade a star infielder.</p>
<p>The April Fool's Day prank stories were news to anyone who forgot to check a calendar before leaving home. They were spouted by morning radio shows and repeated around office coffee machines.</p>
<p>While one Atlanta radio station reported that the Braves were bound for Florida's Walt Disney World another told fans the team was trading star infielder Chipper Jones. Coming on the day of the season opener against Houston, the phony reports about Jones had some loyal supporters of the 1996 National League champs up in arms.</p>
<p>&quot;We've had fans call and it's a big pain,&quot; Atlanta Braves spokesman Jim Schultz said. &quot;We have a season kick-off luncheon scheduled for April 8. We've even had people calling up and threatening to cancel their tickets because of the Chipper story.&quot;</p>
<p>Both stories were based partly on real events: the Braves recently announced plans to move their spring training facilities next year to a Disney complex in Orlando and last month they traded two outfielders.</p>
<p>Schultz said he also had fielded rumours that someone had blown up the Olympic cauldron, a fixture of the Olympic Stadium until the facility was renamed &quot;Turner Field&quot; and handed over to the Braves.</p>
<p>But the spokesman had no knowledge of a radio report that Time Warner had decided to sell the team to Disney and that their new parent would move them to Orlando, home of the giant Walt Disney World theme park. That was the subject of a memo circulated through the CNN newsroom in Atlanta.</p>
<p>&quot;Be especially careful of what appears to be 'news' today. Already the national desk has received one official-looking fax that the Time Warner name is being changed to Turner Time,&quot; the CNN memo warned. &quot;If something seems too unbelieveable to be true, it probably isn't.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
