<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479378" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ky. judge bows out of Lilly Prozac case.</title>
<headline>Ky. judge bows out of Lilly Prozac case.</headline>
<byline>Kevin Drawbaugh</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Kentucky judge removed himself from a case involving Eli Lilly &amp; Co after the company won a stay barring him from holding a hearing on the partial settlement in 1994 of a key Prozac liability lawsuit.</p>
<p>In an order issued Friday, Jefferson Circuit Court Judge John Potter recused himself from the case.</p>
<p>He wrote, &quot;The focus of the case is shifting from what the various parties did ... to whether this court should be the person to hear the evidence.&quot;  </p>
<p>He continued, &quot;The spotlight should be on what, if anything, is under the log, not on the person trying to roll it over.&quot;</p>
<p>Attorneys for Indianapolis-based Lilly Thursday had asked the Kentucky Court of Appeals to remove Potter from the case, alleging that he was unable to be impartial.</p>
<p>&quot;He's absolutely not impartial ... He can't be the judge in an impartial manner if he is the one conducting the investigation and bringing forth the facts. In our view, another judge ought to be appointed,&quot; said Lilly spokesman Edward West in an interview.  </p>
<p>Potter had scheduled a hearing for last Thursday to look into how much money Lilly paid plaintiffs more than two years ago to settle a portion of a lawsuit stemming from the 1989 Standard Gravure printing plant massacre in Louisville.</p>
<p>The hearing was canceled on the orders of the Kentucky Court of Appeals, to which Lilly had appealed for a stay.</p>
<p>The lawsuit was filed two-and-a-half years ago by the survivors and family members of the victims of the workday massacre, in which 47-year-old Joseph Wesbecker shot and killed himself and eight others and wounded 12 at the printing plant, where he had been an employee.  </p>
<p>At the time of his rampage, Wesbecker was on several medications, including Prozac. Those filing the lawsuit alleged that Prozac caused Wesbecker's behavior and sought $50 million in damages from Lilly.</p>
<p>A jury in Potter's court found Lilly not liable. But Lilly acknowledged for the first time last week that it reached an agreement that settled the damages portion of the case before the verdict was returned, a legal intricacy over which the drug manufacturer and Potter had wrangled for years.</p>
<p>The amount and exact terms of the partial settlement, which would likely have been revealed in Potter's hearing, are still not publicly known.</p>
<p>The stay of Potter's hearing is temporary, but Potter said in court documents that it will likely postpone for months any further action under a new judge.</p>
<p>((--Chicago Newsdesk 312-408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
