<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479395" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO to ask Hungary, Poland, Czech to join in July.</title>
<headline>NATO to ask Hungary, Poland, Czech to join in July.</headline>
<byline>Merissa Marr</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States and Spain have agreed that Hungary, Poland and the Czech Republic should be invited to join NATO at July's Madrid summit and that Slovenia and Romania should also be considered for membership, Spanish government sources said.</p>
<p>U.S. Assistant Secretary of State Strobe Talbott and Spanish Defence Minister Eduardo Serra met in Madrid on Tuesday to discuss NATO issues including the Western alliance's relations with Russia.</p>
<p>&quot;They examined which countries would enter in the first and second wave and the three that they agreed would be announced in Madrid in July were Hungary, Poland and the Czech Republic,&quot; a Spanish government official told Reuters after the meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;Slovenia and Romania are also in the running but are less likely,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A Foreign Ministry spokesman said the U.S. and Spain agree it was vital that NATO seal an agreement to ease Moscow's fears over NATO expansion.</p>
<p>Moscow is fiercely opposed to the West's plans to take in former Soviet-bloc states in Eastern Europe. But the U.S. is adamant.</p>
<p>&quot;The U.S. and Spain agreed that securing NATO's relationship with Russia was desirable before July, even if a special summit meeting was necessary,&quot; Foreign Ministry spokesman Inocencio Arias told Reuters, adding an additional meeting with Russia could take place in late May or early June.</p>
<p>&quot;It was agreed that it is important to have a stable and sound relationship with Russia and to have a Russia that feels secure,&quot; Arias said.</p>
<p>The U.S. and Spanish teams asserted that no country should have the right to veto the wishes of others to enter NATO, Arias added.</p>
<p>Spain reiterated its demand for a command covering all its territory when it enters NATO's military structure, Arias added.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not want to interfere with Portugal, but Spain wants to command the Spanish side of the peninsula and the (Canary) islands,&quot; Arias said.</p>
<p>Spain joined NATO in 1986 but is not yet part of its integrated military command. The country's conservative government has signalled it plans to complete the step later this year after the Madrid summit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
