<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479361" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: April snow knocks out power across U.S. Northeast.</title>
<headline>April snow knocks out power across U.S. Northeast.</headline>
<byline>Leslie Gevirtz</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Utilities in the Northeast and New England were reporting more than 250,000 customers without power as wet, heavy snow and high winds pelted the region.</p>
<p>Utility company spokesmen said some of their customers would remain without electricity through Friday.</p>
<p>Northeast Utilities, which serves Connecticut and western Massachusetts, reported 100,000 customers without power. Eastern Utilities, which serves Rhode Island and southeastern Massachusetts, reported 31,000 customers without service.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect to have most service back this evening, but in the Brockton (Mass.) area, customers may not get service back before Thursday,&quot; Eastern Utilities spokeswoman Elaine Hunt said. At the height of the storm, some 51,000 Eastern Utilities customers were powerless.</p>
<p>Boston Edison reported more than 50,000 customers without power.</p>
<p>&quot;We've had a 100 crews on all night and we know 36 crews are headed here from Canada. We're also looking for help from New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Vermont,&quot; Boston Edison spokesman Mike Monahan said.</p>
<p>He estimated it would be up to a week before service was fully restored to all 50,000 customers.</p>
<p>Public Service Co of New Hampshire (PSNH) was reporting 6,100 customers without service with significant outages in Manchester, Hillsboro and Newport. A spokeswoman said the company was able to bring in crews from Canada to help with the battle of downed powerlines.</p>
<p>Central Maine Power reported 1,800 customers were without power on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, in New York, Long Island Lighting Co (LILCO) said 3,400 of 31,000 customers, whose service was disrupted overnight, were still without power early Tuesday.</p>
<p>Most of the outages was caused by high winds and wet snow snapping overhead power lines, but in a few cases, the wires were knocked down due to cars skidding into roadside power poles, a LILCO spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>&quot;There were no transmission outages,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Consolidated Edison Co of New York (Con Ed) said a total of 16,000 of its customers, mostly in suburban Westchester County just north of New York City, lost power during the snowy, windy night.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking at a majority of them restored tonight,&quot; said Con Ed spokesman Michael Spall, referring to the 13,000 customers still without power this morning.</p>
<p>In northern New Jersey, Public Service Electric and Gas Co (PSE&amp;G) said about 5,000 electricity customers were still without power. At the height of the storm, 30,000 customers were in the dark.</p>
<p>The hardest hit area was Princeton, where 2,500 customers were still without service due primarily to circuit problems.</p>
<p>The spokesman could not comment on when full restoration of service would occur.</p>
<p>The utility, a unit of Public Service Enterprise Inc, serves 2.2 million electric and gas customers throughout the state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
