<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479356" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US appeals panel to hear landmark muni case May 6.</title>
<headline>US appeals panel to hear landmark muni case May 6.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A federal appeals court announced it will hear oral arguments next month in the appeal of a landmark U.S. Tax Court ruling that upheld the IRS' authority to bill investors for the interest on muni bonds that IRS says are taxable, a lawyer for investors said.</p>
<p>Mary Reichert, a partner with Bryan Cave in St. Louis, said the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals sitting in Pasadena, California will hear arguments in Harbor Bancorp v Commissioner of Internal Revenue on May 6 at 900 EDT.  </p>
<p>The case dates back to 1992 when IRS declared as taxable $30 million in bonds originally sold by Riverside County Housing Authority to build two multifamily housing projects in California.</p>
<p>The Whitewater Garden project was never built and the Ironwood project was constructed, but not with bond proceeds.</p>
<p>Both deals were rushed to market on Dec. 31, 1985 by New York City undewriter Matthews &amp; Wright to beat a new federal curb on &quot;arbitrage&quot; - profits made by selling tax-exempt bonds and reinvesting the proceeds in higher yielding bonds.  </p>
<p>Securities and Exchange Commmission later revoked Matthews &amp; Wright's broker-dealer license after concluding that the Dec 31 bond closings were a &quot;sham&quot; because no cash actually changed hands.</p>
<p>Internal Revenue Service then moved to collect nearly $68,000 in back taxes on the interest investors earned from the two bond deals. But attorneys for bondholders said their clients should not be punished because neither they or the municipalities knew of any wrongdoing.</p>
<p>The tax court rejected the argument. It said the hastily drawn up papers used at the so-called closing of the bond deals should have tipped off the localities.</p>
<p>Even if there were no clues, IRS does not have to take into account whether a municipality knew about a possible viiolation, the tax court judges added.</p>
<p>The tax court decision was not unanimous. Julian Jacobs, tax court judge that heard the oral arguments, dissented.</p>
<p>Reichert said the case is critical because &quot;it's the first time the commissioner of the IRS has attempted to tax individual bondholdholders.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It's a threat to investors. The importance of this case is the ability of the commissioner of the IRS to tax individual bondholders over a decade after they bought&quot; the bonds, Reichert said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
