<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479387" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Suez announces return to profit, backs merger.</title>
<headline>Suez announces return to profit, backs merger.</headline>
<byline>Myra MacDonald</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>French holding company Cie de Suez announced on Tuesday it returned to profit in 1996 and said its board had unanimously backed in principle a merger with utilities group Lyonnaise des Eaux.</p>
<p>It said in a statement that it made a net attributable profit -- after payment to minorities -- of 843 million francs ($150 million) in 1996 after a loss of 3.96 billion francs the year before.</p>
<p>Analysts had forecast a net profit, before payment to minorities, of about 1.15 billion francs.</p>
<p>Suez also said it would make an exceptional dividend payment in June to reflect capital gains made last year on the sale of investment bank Banque Indosuez.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman declined comment on the amount of the dividend, which has been demanded by Suez shareholders as the price of their approval for the merger with Lyonnaise. &quot;The (Suez) board unanimously gave a favourable welcome to the principle of this merger,&quot; Suez said in a statement.</p>
<p>Earlier on Tuesday glassmaker Saint-Gobain, which holds slightly over six percent of Suez, said it wanted a payout equivalent to some 3.4 billion francs before any merger and said it would reduce its stake by an unspecified amount.</p>
<p>Saint-Gobain head Jean-Louis Beffa said his demand for a special payout was shared by other Suez shareholders including banking group Banque Nationale de Paris and insurer Axa-UAP. BNP and Axa had no comment.</p>
<p>Analysts said the payout demands could reduce Lyonnaise's interest in a merger with Suez, whose main attraction is a big cash pile estimated at some five to six billion francs.</p>
<p>Beffa's comment that Saint Gobain would sell Suez shares also implied a lack of confidence in the new group. &quot;Asking for a special dividend immediately is effectively saying that this money can be used in a better way than in the new group,&quot; Jerome Labin at brokers Pinatton said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is saying indirectly that you do not believe the new group will show enough profitability,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Suez has declined all comment on its talks with Lyonnaise, except to say that the boards of both companies will hold special meetings on April 11 to discuss a merger plan.</p>
<p>French newspapers have suggested that Suez and Lyonnaise, which held unsuccessful merger discussions two years ago, would have to steer a fine line to make their alliance work while maintaining the backing of Suez shareholders.</p>
<p>&quot;Suez and Lyonnaise des Eaux seem resolved to carry out this merger, but not at any price. If certain Suez shareholders go too far, they would prefer to cancel rather than get involved in something removing value or implying dismemberment,&quot; Le Monde newspaper said over the weekend.</p>
<p>Beffa said Suez should pay its shareholders some 10 percent of financial assets, which he estimated at 34 billion francs -- two-thirds of Suez's total assets of 53 to 56 billion francs.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to say that out of the 34 billion francs in financial assets, a distribution of around 10 percent to shareholders would not seem shocking to me,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>This was not just a demand by Saint-Gobain. &quot;It is a demand of BNP, of Saint Gobain, and of Axa,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Generale des Eaux, another Suez shareholder and rival to Lyonnaise des Eaux, has also said it plans to try to obtain maximum shareholder value from Suez before any merger.</p>
<p>Lyonnaise shares closed down 3.65 percent at 554 francs, while Suez shares were down 1.72 percent at 285.9 francs, compared with a 2.82 percent fall in the CAC-40 blue chip index.</p>
<p>But one analyst, who declined to be named, said that the sharp fall in Lyonnaise shares did not suggest the market believed the merger deal was under threat.</p>
<p>It suggested rather that the market, like the chairman of Saint-Gobain, believed there was little to be gained in the short term from the merger with Suez. Suez has little identity left after it sold key assets, including investment bank Banque Indosuez, to cover disastrous property losses.</p>
<p>Lyonnaise's future, he said, depended much more on its ability to come up with a long-term expansion strategy, possibly into telecommunications, rather than its partnership with Suez. ($ = 5.626 French Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
