<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479324" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: New York State plans to appeal Ellis Island ruling.</title>
<headline>New York State plans to appeal Ellis Island ruling.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York State said Tuesday a Special Master had ruled that New York should have sovereignty of about five acres of the developed part of Ellis Island but gave New Jersey control over around 20 acres, mainly landfill.</p>
<p>Even though New York keeps control of the historic part of the island, including the federal immigration museum, the New York State Attorney General, Dennis Vacco, said he planned to challenge the decision in the Supreme Court.  </p>
<p>&quot;I will challenge the Special Master's recommendations to the Supreme Court to preserve New York's central -- and undeniable -- place in our nation's immigrant history,&quot; he said, in prepared remarks. Vacco noted that the Supreme Court still must decide whether to adopt, reject or alter the Special Master's recommendation.</p>
<p>An official of the New Jersey Attorney General's office, who declined to be named, said, &quot;We think it's a win, obviously, for us,&quot; adding the Special Master recommended the state get about 22 acres of Ellis Island's 27.5 acres.</p>
<p>While the island is owned by the federal government, the battle hinges on which state sets its future, with New York casting itself as a preservationist.</p>
<p>Vacco said, &quot;For the first time, Ellis Island would be exposed to a hodge-podge of preservation rules -- including many less stringent than New York's -- that jeopardize our ability to ensure that this jewel is protected for future generations.</p>
<p>Christopher McKenna, a spokesman for Vacco, said that unlike New Jersey, New York was not planning to develop the island with hotels. New York at present gets sales taxes assessed on items sold by the museum, which add up to about $300,000 a year, he added.</p>
<p>Ellis Island, located in New York Harbor about one-and-a-half miles south of Manhattan's Battery Park, was the entry point for over 17 million of European immigrants from its opening in 1892 to its closing in 1954, according to the National Park Service.</p>
<p>The recommendation by the Special Master does not affect the famed Statue of Liberty, located on a separate island, McKenna said. He added New Jersey no longer seemed to be pursuing its claims to the Statue of Liberty. &quot;The sort of dropped that. They haven't pressed it.&quot;</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
