<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479383" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Power struggle reported in Ariane launch company.</title>
<headline>Power struggle reported in Ariane launch company.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS</dateline>
<text>
<p>A power struggle has broken out in Europe's Arianespace rocket launch company, industry sources said Tuesday.</p>
<p>France, the largest shareholder, wants to name the head of the European Space Agency, Jean-Marie Luton, as president of Arianespace, instead of Charles Bigot's long-designated successor, Francis Avanzi.</p>
<p>Arianespace, based near Paris, controls more than half of the world's commercial satellite launch market. It launches the Ariane-4 rocket series from the ESA launch site in Kourou, French Guiana on the northeast coast of South America.</p>
<p>Both contenders are French. Bigot, 65, plans to retire before the end of this year. A board meeting will be held April 17 at which France is expected to press for reversal of Avanzi's appointment.</p>
<p>Avanzi's supporters in the company regard him as a more positive and independent leader and argue that Luton might merely take orders from the French government.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not about personalities, this is about who can best lead Arianespace in the ferocious commercial context in the coming years,&quot; a source close to Arianespace management said.</p>
<p>&quot;Avanzi is best qualified -- he can keep Ariane at the top. We don't want the (French) government pushing someone on us.&quot;</p>
<p>Avanzi, 43, was previously president of the aircraft engine manufacturer CFM International. He has held the No. 2 post at Arianespace since January 1996, when he was destined by the board for the top job.</p>
<p>Luton has been at the head of the 14 nation ESA since 1990.</p>
<p>While Avanzi has support among European industrial partners, the French Space Agency CNES holds 32 percent of the company and holdings by other state-controlled companies give French interests a total of 55 percent of the company.</p>
<p>Germany holds 18.5 percent, Italy 8.11 percent. Other stakeholders are mainly in the European Union.</p>
<p>Arianespace faces strong American competition from the planned purchase of McDonnell Douglas Corp. by Boeing Co., which will give the U.S. company the Delta family of launch vehicles and the Sea Launch project scheduled to start launching commercial satellites next year from an offshore platform.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
