<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479307" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INSIGHT-Dlr/yen eyes 122.10, after support breaks.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT-Dlr/yen eyes 122.10, after support breaks.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dollar/yen has a target of 122.10 in its sights, after punching below 123.40 on Tuesday, currency chartists said.</p>
<p>Taking its cue from dollar/mark's recent weakness, the dollar's move lower against the yen accelerated Tuesday when it slumped below supports near 123.30/40, which marked a floor for trade since late last week, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have clearly broken below those levels now and the focus is turning to support centered on 122.10 yen,&quot; said Darren Spain, global foreign exchange analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston.  </p>
<p>&quot;Dollar/yen is now playing catch up with dollar/Europe,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Resistance for the dollar now lies at previous support by 123.30 yen, analysts said.</p>
<p>The dollar's retreat on Tuesday bogged down as it ran into a series of minor support points with a locus around 122.50.</p>
<p>The 38-percent Fibonacci retracement of the March advance from 119.85 to 124.47 yen was punctured at 122.70 yen.</p>
<p>Below there, trendline support connecting lows at 122.05 yen, 122.14 yen and 122.15 yen from March 18, 20 and March 24, respectively, comes into play at 122.40 yen, traders said.  </p>
<p>&quot;It seems like we're  pretty congested in here, 122.10 yen late this week is a pretty good floor,&quot; said Ken Boyer, foreign exchange analyst at MMS International. &quot;We are seeing some more downside, but relatively limited.&quot;</p>
<p>In lockstep with dollar/yen's decline, the mark/yen cross surrendered gains posted on Monday and early Tuesday, when it flirted with levels above 74 for the first time since mid-February.</p>
<p>The sagging cross is currently standing by initial support at 73.35 yen. But Spain said he expects this minor prop to yield, extending weakness to important support at 72.45/50.  </p>
<p>Resistance lies at 73.85/90, a combination of Tuesday's breakdown point and last week's high, chartists said.</p>
<p>Dollar/mark is holding relatively steady above Tuesday's 1.6663 low, after the previous day's sharp rebound cast some doubt on the bearish head and shoulder scenario spotlighted by analysts during Monday's initial slump to 1.6610.</p>
<p>&quot;I still see (the head and shoulders) as being in play, just not quite as impulsively bearish,&quot; Boyer said.</p>
<p>Downside targets lie at Monday's low, followed by 1.65 marks and a measured objective near 1.63 marks, analysts said.</p>
<p>((--Alden Bentley, 212 859 1667))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
