<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479463" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India to pay 600 rupees bonus on wheat purchases.</title>
<headline>India to pay 600 rupees bonus on wheat purchases.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian government ministers on Tuesday agreed to pay a 600 rupees bonus per tonne to farmers, for the wheat it procures from them, in addition to the current purchase price of 4,150 rupees.  </p>
<p>&quot;The cabinet in its meeting held today has decided that the farmers will be paid a central bonus of 600 rupees per tonne in addition to the minimum support price for wheat procured for the central pool during the 1997/98 (April-March) season,&quot; a government statement said.</p>
<p>The bonus will be payable on the wheat offered for sale to the procurement agencies for the central pool upto June 10, 1997, the statement said.</p>
<p>Newspapers last month reported that Prakash Singh Badal, who heads the agriculturally-rich state of Punjab, had threatened to curb procurement in his state if the government did not raise procurement prices to 5.25 rupees from 4.15 rupees per kg.</p>
<p>Indian Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda had urged Badal to &quot;cooperate&quot; in wheat procurement.</p>
<p>The government buys wheat to build up its buffer stocks, which it then uses to control prices by releasing stocks through a state-run distribution system.</p>
<p>The statement said the cabinet has also decided to continue the ban on export of wheat and wheat products in 1997/98.</p>
<p>&quot;It has also been decided that the licensing and stock holding limits of wheat would continue in 1997/98 season also,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>-- New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
