<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479433" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian parties hold talks to defuse crisis.</title>
<headline>Indian parties hold talks to defuse crisis.</headline>
<byline>Jawed Naqvi</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's ruling coalition and its ally-turned-foe, the Congress Party, were holding talks on Tuesday in an effort to defuse a crisis that has threatened Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's government, politicians said.</p>
<p>They said the right-wing Hindu Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP), India's main opposition group, was also talking to both sides to weigh the consequences of Sunday's decision by the Congress to withdraw its make-or-break support for Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>Parliament officials said all the major parties were also locked in talks to rescue the federal budget for fiscal 1997/98 (April-March) from the political chaos.</p>
<p>&quot;A combination of political incest and promiscuity is evident,&quot; said a former Congress minister opposed to party president Sitaram Kesri's Sunday decision to topple Deve Gowda and to stake his own claim to form a government.</p>
<p>&quot;The BJP is talking to the Congress through middlemen, the Congress is talking to the United Front, and they are all talking to each other, usually secretly,&quot; the politician said.</p>
<p>The Press Trust of India (PTI) quoted Congress officials as confirming that talks were being held between the two former allies.</p>
<p>&quot;We are always for negotiations and without any condition,&quot; PTI quoted senior Congress leader K. Karunakaran as telling reporters. He was responding to a question on whether talks were taking place with the United Front.</p>
<p>PTI quoted Congress general secretary Meira Kumar as also confirming that talks were going on with the United Front but she refused say at what level they were being held.</p>
<p>The United Front had urged the Congress on Monday to reconsider its decision to bring down Deve Gowda's government.</p>
<p>Politicians said several options were being considered by both sides, including the replacement of Deve Gowda by someone from the United Front who would be acceptable to the Congress.</p>
<p>Kesri told a news conference on Sunday that he was himself a candidate for Deve Gowda's job.</p>
<p>The ruling coalition officially denied the prime minister's job was negotiable. &quot;The United Front is solidly with Mr Deve Gowda today, and will remain so tomorrow,&quot; its spokesman Jaipal Reddy said.</p>
<p>The embattled government moved on Tuesday to win public support with a proposal to get its budget approved by parliament despite the threat to Deve Gowda's political survival.</p>
<p>The United Front said it was confident of getting the budget approved either before a vote of confidence Deve Gowda must face by April 11 or soon afterwards, by proposing a special session of parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we owe it to the country not to force an economic crisis,&quot; said Sitaram Yechury, a communist member of the United Front's decision-making Steering Committee.</p>
<p>&quot;This government has generated unprecedented enthusiasm in the country for coalition politics. People will not forgive us if politicians hold the economy to ransom for their narrow ambitions. I am confident the budget will be passed.&quot;</p>
<p>The BJP said the budget could be passed only after the trust vote was first considered by parliament. The Congress said it might seek unspecified changes before approving the budget.</p>
<p>President Shankar Dayal Sharma asked Deve Gowda on Monday to face a vote of confidence in parliament by April 7 to prove his majority, but extended the time by four days to allow him to host a meeting of foreign ministers of the Non-Aligned Movement due in New Delhi that day.</p>
<p>The United Front controls only 178 seats in the 545-member in the Lok Sabha. The Congress party had reluctantly shored up the government with its 140 deputies since June.</p>
<p>The BJP and its allies have 194 deputies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
