<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479487" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: RGC unit to exploit S.Lanka titanium mine.</title>
<headline>RGC unit to exploit S.Lanka titanium mine.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>RGC Mineral Sands Ltd, a unit of Australia's Renison Goldfields Company, is holding talks with the Sri Lankan government to exploit a titanium mine on the island's northeast coast, government officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The Industrial Development Ministry was seeking clarification on a proposal from RGC Mineral Sands for a joint venture to mine and manufacture value-added products from the Pulmoddai mine, one of the world's richest titanium ore deposits, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to go for value-addition in a big way,&quot; a senior ministry official said.</p>
<p>RGC had responded to a government invitation sent out last August to form a joint venture with state-owned Lanka Mineral Sands, which operates the Pulmoddai mine, to make value-added products.</p>
<p>The Pulmoddai mine's mineral sands deposits are rated as one of the world's best with a heavy mineral content of between 60 and 70 percent, compared with a mineral concentration of between 1.5 and 25 percent in Australia, the Geological Survey and Mines Bureau said.</p>
<p>Mineral sands contain ilmenite and rutile, raw materials for titanium dioxide which is used in the aerospace and pigment industries, Mines Bureau officials said.</p>
<p>Total proven reserves of ilmenite alone at Pulmoddai, about 260 km (163 miles) northeast of the capital Colombo, are over five million tonnes, they added. Pulmoddai can produce 150,000 tonnes of ilmenite, 10,000 tonnes of rutile and 6,000 tonnes of zircon annually.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka exports all its mineral sands production. However, Pulmoddai port is vulnerable to bad weather and shipping is limited to between April and October, the officials said.</p>
<p>The government, which is keen to attract foreign investors, has stepped up security at the Pulmoddai mine since separatist Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam rebels attacked a Philippine vessel loaded with 13,000 tonnes of mineral sands last August.</p>
<p>Navy patrols now escort foreign ships carrying mineral sands.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
