<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479461" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India seeks dialogue with Gulf Cooperation Council.</title>
<headline>India seeks dialogue with Gulf Cooperation Council.</headline>
<byline>Hari Ramachandran</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India hopes to increase co-operation with member countries of the Gulf Cooperation Council, President Shankar Dayal Sharma told Oman's Sultan Qaboos bin Said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We feel that a dialogue and exchange of visits with the Council will promote mutual understanding and help realise the inherent potential for cooperation between India and the GCC as a whole,&quot; the president said in a banquet speech in honour of Sultan Qaboos.</p>
<p>Sharma said India had close links with the members of the GCC, which account for a considerable segment of its foreign trade and are home to more than 2.5 million Indian expatriate workers.</p>
<p>The six-member GCC comprises Oman, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain, Qatar, Saudi Arabia and Kuwait.</p>
<p>Qaboos, who arrived earlier on Tuesday on his first official visit to the South Asian country, expressed the hope that his talks with Indian leaders would bolster relations between the two countries.</p>
<p>Qaboos called on Sharma soon after his arrival to a ceremonial welcome. He is due to hold talks with Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I am looking forward to talks with the Indian Prime Minister and hopeful these talks will bear benefit for both countries,&quot; Qaboos told reporters on his arrival.</p>
<p>&quot;I am very happy to pay my first state visit to India,&quot; Qaboos, accompanied by 14 ministers and aides, said.</p>
<p>Qaboos last month cancelled a trip to India citing bad weather on the flight route over the Arabian Sea.</p>
<p>The two nations are due to sign agreements on double taxation, investment protection and science and technology during the Sultan's four-day visit, Omani officials said.</p>
<p>The countries are key members of the recently inaugurated 14-member Indian Ocean Rim Association for Regional Cooperation.</p>
<p>Sharma said it was a matter of great satisfaction that the association provided a new forum for enhanced cooperation beyond bilateral ties.</p>
<p>Both countries have carried out a feasibility study for a proposed underwater gas pipeline from Oman to India. But Indian officials say the project has been bogged down by a lack of political will on both sides and cash.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GCC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="OMAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
