<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479477" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian oil price hike inevitable - securities firm.</title>
<headline>Indian oil price hike inevitable - securities firm.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India cannot avoid raising its state-fixed petroleum product prices, securities firm SBI Capital Markets Ltd (SBICAP) said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Petroleum products price hike is inevitable to get out of the unsustainable situation caused by high oil pool account deficit,&quot; SBICAP said in a research report.</p>
<p>India's oil pool account reconciles the state-fixed administered pricing mechanism with free market conditions.</p>
<p>The oil pool account is a balancing mechanism whereby refineries are compensated for subsidised prices of several petroleum products in India.</p>
<p>The oil pool account deficit for 1996/97 (April-March) is estimated to be running a deficit of 155 billion rupees ($4.3 billion).</p>
<p>&quot;We estimate that a 20 percent hike across the board would be necessary to wipe out the year end oil pool account deficit,&quot;SBICAP said.</p>
<p>It said mounting unpaid dues to refining firms from the oil pool has led to a working capital problems.</p>
<p>&quot;The oil companies are expected to resort to short-term debt funds leading to high interest expense,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>It said Indian refiners are expected to achieve 35 percent to 40 percent earnings growth in 1998/99 (April-March) as new projects get commissioned.</p>
<p>Supply of oil shares would increase over the next three to four years as the government brings down its stake to 51 percent, SBICAP said.</p>
<p>SBICAP expects local supply of refined products to catch up with demand as refining capacity increases by 130 percent to reach 139 million tonnes per year by 2001/02.</p>
<p>&quot;However, reliance on imports will continue as crude production is likely to stagnate,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>SBICAP expects India's demand for petroleum production to increase by an annual 8.3 percent over the next five years.</p>
<p>India's three leading refiners are Indian Oil Corp Ltd, Bharat Petroleum Corp Ltd and Hindustan Petroelum Corp Ltd -- all of them state-controlled.</p>
<p>-- Bombay newsroom +91-22-265 9000 ($ = 35.78 Indian Rupees)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
