<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479408" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Suez 1996 net attrib 843 mln Ffr.</title>
<headline>Suez 1996 net attrib 843 mln Ffr.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Year to December 31, 1996.</p>
<p>(Figures in millions of French francs unless stated)</p>
<p>    Net attributable			     843  vs   loss  3,959</p>
<p>Pre-tax, pre-exceptional on</p>
<p>	  current structure basis	    2,312  vs	   1,679</p>
<p>Impact of French property crisis</p>
<p>					     loss  2,541  vs   loss  5,003</p>
<p>    Exceptional result			   121  vs   loss    658</p>
<p>    Contribution from companies sold	 951  vs		23</p>
<p>NOTE - Cie de Suez, giving its 1996 results in a statement, said it expected a further rise in its pre-exceptional profit in 1997. It said the 1997 accounts would include a capital gain of more than 750 million francs on the recent sale of shares in Accor by Societe Generale de Belgique and in Factofrance Heller by the Suez parent company itself.</p>
<p>Suez said the &quot;contribution from companies sold&quot; item comprised both the income from those companies, including any exceptional items, and the results obtained by selling them. The contributions came mostly from Banque Indosuez (300 million francs) and Gartmore (505 million francs).</p>
<p>Suez said the contribution to its consolidated net result from Societe Generale de Belgique was 1,126 million francs.</p>
<p>Net attributable income of 843 million francs took account of losses on sales of third-party property loan portfolios and promotions for the company's own account (961 million francs) and of provisioning for AXA-UAP shares (500 million).  </p>
<p>Suez said pre-exceptional income (based on current structure) included 742 million francs from utility services, up 38 percent from the year before. Financial services for individuals brought in 1,251 million francs, up 24 percent.</p>
<p>In the property sector, Credisuez cut its net exposure by 6.2 billion francs for a loss of 2.5 billion. Net property exposure was left at 4.8 billion francs on December 31, 1996.</p>
<p>One-off profits of 121 million francs included exceptional gains of 791 million francs, mainly from capital gains on non-strategic assets. These included Salins du Midi, Financiere Desjardins Laurentienne, Wafabank and IMS. They also included exceptional losses of 670 million francs, notably the 500 million franc provision for AXA-UAP shares.</p>
<p>-- Paris newsroom +331 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
