<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479442" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indians resigned to spells of political turmoil.</title>
<headline>Indians resigned to spells of political turmoil.</headline>
<byline>Clarence Fernandez</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Many Indians said on Tuesday they were resigned to another period of political and economic unrest as their country headed deeper into uncertainty.</p>
<p>The Congress party withdrew its vital backing for Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's ruling coalition on Sunday and government must now win a vote of confidence by April 11 to stay in power.</p>
<p>Congress, which took a severe drubbing at the polls that brought Deve Gowda to power in June 1996, has staked a bid to form the next government.</p>
<p>&quot;I think its going to be difficult for any single party to form the government from now onwards,&quot; said Rajesh Mhatre, 33, an executive with a large Bombay shipping firm.</p>
<p>&quot;But all the governments are going to be equally shaky because they have so many different pressures to respond to.&quot;</p>
<p>Deve Gowda's 15-party United Front government, which ranges across the spectrum from free traders to communists, had managed to paper over its differences for nearly 10 months, said Naresh Patil, 19, an arts student at a south Bombay college.</p>
<p>&quot;It's surprising that it lasted so long,&quot; Patil said. &quot;But now neither the Congress nor the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) has enough seats and there's going to be a lot of horsetrading.&quot;</p>
<p>The United Front controls only 178 seats in the 545-member lower house of parliament, the Lok Sabha. Congress had reluctantly shored up the government with its 140 deputies.</p>
<p>The BJP and its direct allies command 193 deputies in the lower house, which currently has 543 sitting members.</p>
<p>In Deve Gowda's home state of Karnataka, some people said the crisis was a mixed blessing.</p>
<p>Kumar, a taxi driver in the capital of Bangalore, said the tight security around Deve Gowda's visits to the state had inconvenienced ordinary people.</p>
<p>&quot;Gowda has visited Bangalore at least 25 times since he became prime minister, leading to traffic snarls and inconvenience,&quot; said Kumar, who has only one name.</p>
<p>&quot;We will not have such problems now,&quot; he added. &quot;Even if he comes, there will not be much security and traffic problems.&quot;</p>
<p>In New Delhi, people said they had become resigned to frequent changes in the government and the cabinet.</p>
<p>&quot;Governments and ministers change so frequently in this country that it is hardly possible to keep track of them,&quot; said 34-year-old Delhi housewife Anuradha Verma.</p>
<p>Others said the crisis was a predictable outcome of Congress's desire to continue calling the shots, even though it had been pushed out of power.</p>
<p>&quot;This outcome was more or less expected,&quot; said Subhash Chander, 53, a government employee in the postal service.</p>
<p>&quot;The voters felt cheated when rival parties decided to form an alliance after the elections and not before the elections and also when they decided to accept Congress support,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a struggle for power,&quot; said former Indian foreign secretary J.N. Dixit. &quot;Congress feels that its influence is diminishing, especially after a positive budget by Chidambaram. Therefore it does not want the government to stabilise.&quot;</p>
<p>Finance Minister P. Chidambaram's budget for 1997/98 had cheered big business and industry with plans to slash personal and corporate income-tax rates, spurring a surge in share prices after it was unveiled on February 28.</p>
<p>The government vowed on Tuesday to make every effort to have parliament approve the budget ahead of the vote of confidence, pushing up share prices on the Bombay Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>The benchmark 30-share index dropped more than eight percent on Monday, partly due to fears that the government's proposed budget would fall victim to the crisis.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
