<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479474" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Enron Oil begins natural gas production in India.</title>
<headline>Enron Oil begins natural gas production in India.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Enron Oil and Gas India, an affiliate of U.S. multinational Enron Oil and Gas Co., said on Tuesday it had begun supply of natural gas from India's offshore Tapti oil field from March 31.  </p>
<p>&quot;Tapti is expected to produce at least 4.2 milion cubic metres per day of natural gas by the end of 1997, becoming a significant source of clean burning fuel for Indian industry,&quot; the firm said in a statement.  </p>
<p>&quot;Completion, including the development of the process and procedures for sale and delivery of the natural gas to Gas Authority of India Ltd (GAIL), will guide additional international investment for India's needs,&quot; Enron Oil &amp; Gas India Ltd quoted Forrest E. Hoglund, chairman and CEO of the Houston-based Enron Oil &amp; Gas Company, as saying.</p>
<p>Natural gas from the offshore Tapti field is being produced by a consortium of Enron Oil &amp; Gas, Reliance Industries Ltd and the state-run Oil and Natural Gas Corp.</p>
<p>&quot;The participants believe that this level of production (4.2 million cubic metres per day) can be maintained for a period of 25 years, resulting in aggregate production of 30 billion cubic metres of natural gas or more,&quot; the statement added.</p>
<p>The Tapti field was awarded by the government in February 1994 as one of 31 offshore oil and gas fields offered for private development in the first international bid solicitation.</p>
<p>The consortium has invested over nine billion rupees to install three well platforms, one processing platform and one flare platform, apart from drilling wells and pipelines to deliver the gas to ONGC's pipeline system, the statement added.</p>
<p>Enron Oil &amp; Gas India is the operator and holds a 30 percent interest in the Tapti field, located off the industrial town of Hazira on the west coast, north of Bombay.</p>
<p>Reliance holds 30 percent interest and ONGC holds the rest.</p>
<p>The consortium is also working to expand production in the Panna and Mukta fields, it said.</p>
<p>-- Bombay newsroom +91-22-265 9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25120">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
