<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479403" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Arab states request emergency U.N. Assembly session.</title>
<headline>Arab states request emergency U.N. Assembly session.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Arab states requested an emergency special General Assembly session following two U.S. vetoes in the Security Council in a Mideast dispute, a spokesman for the Palestine Liberation Organisation said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>In an effort to deal with Israel's construction of new housing in historically Arab East Jerusalem, decried by the PLO and its Arab allies, the PLO spokesman said the 22-member Arab group wrote to Secretary-General Kofi Annan requesting the assembly session under a 1950 &quot;uniting for peace&quot; formula.</p>
<p>This requires the secretary-general to canvass the U.N. membership and summon a meeting of the assembly 24 hours after a simple majority of its 185 members inform him that they back the request for a session. An Arab source said that could occur late this week or next week.</p>
<p>The &quot;uniting for peace&quot; formula was originated by the United States to enable the General Assembly to act &quot;if the Security Council, because of lack of unanimity of the permanent members, fails to exercise its primary responsibility for the maintenance of international peace and security.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. vetoes on March 7 and March 21 prevented action by the Security Council on Israel's plan to build 6,500 homes for Jews on land captured during the 1967 Middle East war. The site, between Jerusalem and Bethlehem, is called Jabal Abu Ghneim in Arabic and Har Homa in Hebrew.</p>
<p>The assembly adopted a resolution on March 13 by 130 votes to two, with two abstentions, calling on Israel to abandon the building project. There is no veto in the assembly, whose resolutions are not binding.</p>
<p>Nine emergency special assembly sessions have been held so far. The first two were in November 1956, on the Suez and Hungary crises, and the most recent was in January-February 1982, on the situation in the occupied Arab territories.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARABST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
