<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479432" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's Congress will accept anyone but Deve Gowda.</title>
<headline>India's Congress will accept anyone but Deve Gowda.</headline>
<byline>Jawed Naqvi</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's Congress Party said on Tuesday it was prepared to accept another candidate from the ruling United Front alliance to replace Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda, whom it has vowed to topple.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not against any member of the Steering Committee (of the United Front). My only complaint is against Deve Gowda,&quot; Congress president Sitaram Kesri said in a television interview two days after declaring himself a candidate for the top job.</p>
<p>Kesri's statement came as the United Front and the Congress, its ally-turned-foe, finished a day of talks in an effort to defuse the crisis that has engulfed Deve Gowda's government.</p>
<p>Politicians said the right-wing Hindu Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP), India's main opposition group, was also talking to both sides to weigh the consequences of the Congress' Sunday decision to withdraw its make-or-break support for Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>Hong Kong-based Star TV's mainly Indian news programme quoted Kesri as hinting that he would accept G.K. Moopanar, head of the Tamil Maanila Congress which is a key constituent of the United Front, as the next prime minister.</p>
<p>Parliament officials said all the major parties were also locked in talks to rescue the 1997-98 budget from the political chaos.</p>
<p>&quot;A combination of political incest and promiscuity is evident,&quot; said a former Congress minister opposed to Kesri's decision to topple Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>&quot;The BJP is talking to the Congress through middlemen, the Congress is talking to the United Front, and they are all talking to each other, usually secretly,&quot; the politician said.</p>
<p>The Press Trust of India (PTI) quoted Congress officials as confirming that talks were being held between the two former allies.</p>
<p>&quot;We are always for negotiations and without any condition,&quot; PTI quoted senior Congress leader K. Karunakaran as telling reporters. He was responding to a question on whether talks were taking place with the United Front.</p>
<p>PTI quoted Congress general secretary Meira Kumar as also confirming that talks were going on with the United Front but she refused say at what level they were being held.</p>
<p>The United Front had urged the Congress on Monday to reconsider its decision to bring down Deve Gowda's government.</p>
<p>The ruling coalition has officially denied the prime minister's job is negotiable. &quot;The United Front is solidly with Mr Deve Gowda today, and will remain so tomorrow,&quot; its spokesman Jaipal Reddy said.</p>
<p>The government moved on Tuesday to win public support with a proposal to get its budget approved by parliament despite the threat to Deve Gowda's political survival.</p>
<p>The United Front said it was confident of getting the budget approved either before a vote of confidence that Deve Gowda must face by April 11 or soon afterwards, by proposing a special session of parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we owe it to the country not to force an economic crisis,&quot; said Sitaram Yechury, a communist member of the United Front's decision-making Steering Committee.</p>
<p>&quot;This government has generated unprecedented enthusiasm in the country for coalition politics. People will not forgive us if politicians hold the economy to ransom for their narrow ambitions. I am confident the budget will be passed.&quot;</p>
<p>The BJP said the budget could be passed only after the confidence vote was first considered by parliament. The Congress said it might seek unspecified changes before approving the budget.</p>
<p>The United Front controls only 178 seats in the 545-member in the Lok Sabha. The Congress party had reluctantly shored up the government with its 140 deputies since June.</p>
<p>The BJP and its allies have 194 deputies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
