<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479400" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Convicted French killers on fresh murder trial.</title>
<headline>Convicted French killers on fresh murder trial.</headline>
<dateline>PERIGUEUX, France 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two homeless Frenchmen serving life sentences for murder went on trial again on Tuesday in the southwest town of Perigueux charged with torturing and killing a young soldier.</p>
<p>One of the accused, Francis Heaulme, 38, is a self-confessed serial killer imprisoned for two murders and being investigated for 10 more. He boasts he has killed 20 people.</p>
<p>The other, Didier Gentil, 33, was jailed for life for the rape and murder of a seven-year-old girl.</p>
<p>Both deny killing 19-year-old conscript Laurent Bureau, whose body was found with his skull smashed in 11 years ago in a Perigueux gym, and their lawyers argued in court a mysterious third man could be guilty.</p>
<p>As the trial opened, the court accepted their demand to summon as witnesses three other homeless men questioned earlier by police about the killing but released.</p>
<p>Heaulme was jailed for 20 years five years ago for the killing of a nurse in Brittany. He was given a life sentence two years later for stabbing to death a 14-year-old girl in eastern France.</p>
<p>He has told police he killed about 20 other people as he wandered about the country. He is under investigation in connection with 10 separate murders committed between 1984 and 1989, including those of three young women in the east, two boys on the Riviera, and a 60-year-old farmer in the south.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PERIGUEUX, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
