<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479437" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: Bangladesh PM offers talks with opposition.</title>
<headline>Bangladesh PM offers talks with opposition.</headline>
<byline>Shakeel Anwar</byline>
<dateline>DHAKA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bangladesh's Prime Minister Sheikh Hasina, in a bid to defuse simmering political tension, has offered to hold talks with her main political foe and predecessor, Begum Khaleda Zia, Hasina's aides said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I am ready to sit with the opposition leader (Khaleda) to discuss any issue of national importance,&quot; they quoted Hasina as saying late on Monday.</p>
<p>Hasina, who took office in June last year after her Awami League defeated Khaleda's Bangladesh Nationalist Party (BNP) in general elections, said she was ready for a live debate on television with the opposition leader on all issues.</p>
<p>&quot;We have...invited the opposition leader to sit for open dialogue to explain to the people what we are doing and what the (opposition) are doing,&quot; her aides quoted Hasina as telling editors of local newspapers and news agencies on Monday night.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to make everything clear to the people as we believe in the democratic system,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The BNP said the government must first free detained political opponents and stop harrassing others before discussions could begin.</p>
<p>&quot;A congenial atmosphere has to be created before any dialogue can take place,&quot; BNP Secretary-General Abdul Mannan Bhuiyan told a news conference in Dhaka.</p>
<p>Bhuiyan said Khaleda had not received any formal invitation for dialogue.</p>
<p>&quot;We will only respond to any such dialogue if they (government) stop filing false cases against opposition leaders, stops arresting opposition activists and release those who have been detained,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hasina has repeatedly denied charges that her government has jailed opposition activists and has accused the BNP of sabotaging her development efforts.</p>
<p>The BNP enforced a general strike on March 23 in its first major offensive to destabilise Hasina's nine-month-old government.</p>
<p>Bhuiyan said the party would hold demonstrations nationwide on April 6 and April 12 to protest what he said was the ruling party's &quot;oppressive treatment&quot; of political opponents and to press other demands.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DHAKA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
