<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479402" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy plans third ENI tranche.</title>
<headline>Italy plans third ENI tranche.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Italian Treasury said on Tuesday it planned to place a third tranche of energy giant ENI on the stock market by the summer and share analysts expected the latest sale to prove another big success.</p>
<p>&quot;The share placement will be completed by the summer,&quot; the Treasury said in a statement after the Milan market closed.</p>
<p>The Treasury currently holds 69 percent of ENI and Treasury Minister Carlo Azeglio Ciampi has said the state's holding will not fall below 51 percent.</p>
<p>Share analysts said they expected ENI to follow its usual pattern of offering a tranche of about 15 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;There will definitely be good demand -- it's one of the better performers because it's so huge and diversified and has good underlying assets,&quot; said one London analyst who declined to be named. He saw particular interest from U.S. investors.</p>
<p>ENI American Depositary Receipts are already traded in New York.</p>
<p>The Treasury said it would give further details of the ENI3 offer in the next few days.</p>
<p>The offer follows a record second tranche sale in November 1996, which raised 8.87 trillion lire ($5.3 billion) after the exercise of an over-allotment, or &quot;green shoe&quot; option because of heavy demand, and an initial 15 percent sale in November 1995.</p>
<p>ENI made a consolidated net profit of 4.45 trillion lire in 1996. The company's shares closed 0.79 percent weaker at 8,393.</p>
<p>Italy's centre-left government is determined to press on with its privatisation programme, which also includes the merger and subsequent sale of telecommunications holding Stet and operating unit Telecom Italia this autumn, despite opposition from key ally, the hard-left Communist Refoundation party. ($1=1,669 lire)</p>
<p>-- Rome newsroom +396 678 2501</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
