<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479411" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: OSCE envoy to meet Italy's Prodi on Albania force.</title>
<headline>OSCE envoy to meet Italy's Prodi on Albania force.</headline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The OSCE special envoy to Albania Franz Vranitzky is due to meet Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi on Wednesday to discuss the creation of a multinational force, an OSCE spokeswoman said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Former Austrian chancellor Vranitzky will travel to Italy for a one-day visit to meet Prodi and Foreign Minister Lamberto Dini on behalf of the Vienna-based Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).</p>
<p>Italy said on Tuesday it would stick to its plan to lead an international force to Albania, despite mounting domestic pressure to think twice after the fatal sinking at the weekend of a crowded boat carrying Albanian refugees.</p>
<p>Austria was &quot;basically prepared to send a force of around 100 soldiers to protect relief convoys to Albania&quot;, but that depended on the outcome of Vranitzky's meeting in Rome, a defence ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>Italy, France, Greece, Turkey, Spain and Romania have already offered to contribute troops to an international stabilisation force in Albania.</p>
<p>Europe's top security forum will also send a small team to Albania in the next few days to start laying the ground for the arrival of an OSCE mission which will monitor fresh elections in the country in June, the organisation said.</p>
<p>The troubled Balkan state descended into anarchy after collapsed bogus savings schemes sparked violent protests two months ago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
