<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479455" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Indian business and political stories in leading newspapers prepared for Reuters by Business News and Information Services Pvt Ltd, New Delhi Tel:3324842, 3351006, 3761233 Fax:+91-11-3351006</p>
<p>Internet:</p>
<p>biznis@giasbm01.vsnl.net.in</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch</p>
<p>for their accuracy.</p>
<p>		   -------oo0oo-------</p>
<p>			TOP STORIES</p>
<p>The Hindustan Times</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER TO SEEK TRUST VOTE BY APRIL 11</p>
<p>The president asked Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda to seek a vote of confidence in the lower house by April 11. The Congress party formally staked its claim to form a government. The president initially gave Gowda time until April 7 to prove his majority. But it was postponed in view of the forthcoming Non-Aligned Movement ministerial meeting. Gowda ruled out his resignation and said he would not recommend the dissolution of the lower house either. He claimed he would be able to prove his majority.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Observer</p>
<p>UNITED FRONT ASKS CONGRESS TO REVIEW STAND</p>
<p>The ruling United Front urged the Congress party to reconsider its decision to withdraw support to the 10-month-old Deve Gowda government. A senior leader said the steering committee of the Front was of the view that even at this stage, the Congress should reconsider its stand. The committee described the decision as unfortunate.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Economic Times</p>
<p>SPEAKER URGED TO SAVE BUDGET</p>
<p>The speaker of the lower house of parliament was expected to mount an operation to salvage the budget so that the current political uncertainty would not derail the economy. Political sources said he might convene an all party meeting to put across the point that political party leaders should show their commitment to the economy and ensure it did not receive a setback.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>FOREIGN INVESTMENTS WORTH 13.65 BLN RUPEES APPROVED</p>
<p>The government approved foreign direct investments worth 13.65 billion rupees spread across textiles, engineering, power, automobile spares, software, consultancy services and electronics. The list contained 83 approved projects.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>BOMBAY BOURSE INDEX MELTS 302.64 POINTS</p>
<p>The Bombay bourse index (Sensex) posted its fourth largest plunge ever, skidding 302.64 points (8.2 percent) to close at 3,360.89 as blue chip stocks took a sharp beating in panicky trade. The National bourse (NSE) relaxed its daily stock price limits in active scrips after the market plummeted. But the bourse regulator and NSE officials maintained the situation was under control and there was no need to panic. The NSE index closed 89.50 points lower at 968.30 after the bourse relaxed its daily circuit breaker in leading stocks to 10 percent from seven percent.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Financial Express</p>
<p>CUT IN CUSTOMS DUTY FAILS TO PERK UP EXPORTERS</p>
<p>Exporters were disappointed at the reduction in customs duty on the import of capital goods, both new and second-hand, from 15 to 10 percent under the export promotion capital goods (EPCG) scheme. They were also unhappy that under the zero duty EPCG scheme, reduction in the threshold limit for import of capital goods was not applicable to the small-scale sector, high tech products, gems and jewellery items and garments, which have great export potential. Exporters had expected the government to lower 15 percent customs duty under the EPCG scheme to five percent.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Standard</p>
<p>RUPEE PIERCES 36-MARK VS DOLLAR</p>
<p>The rupee touched 36.02 against the dollar in the wake of a speculative frenzy stirred up by political uncertainty. Banks went on a dollar buying spree, expecting a rush for the greenback from exporters looking for cover. The conjectural variation in the market finally lead the rupee to appreciate and close at 35.87/35.88. While banks felt the Indian currency would depreciate, importers expected strong dollar inflow and did not buy the greenback.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>VSNL EXERCISES $80 MLN GREENSHOE</p>
<p>Videsh Sanchar Nigam (VSNL), the state-owned telecom monopoly, exercised the $80 million greenshoe option on its recent $448 million global depository receipts (GDR) issue. VSNL issued an additional 2.83 million shares, taking the total offering to $527 million after opting for the greenshoe. It issued a total of 18.9 million shares. The first tranche of the issue proceeds aggregating $448 million have already come in. The VSNL GDR was last traded at $17.50-$17.75 on the London Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>CENTRAL BANK INTRODUCES 14-DAY T-BILLS</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) announced the introduction of 14-day intermediate treasury bills as an alternative to the on-tap treasury bills which would be phased out from April 1. The discount rate for the 14-day bills would be set every three months and the effective yield on this instrument would be equivalent to the interest rate on ways and means advances. The bills would be sold only to state governments, foreign central banks and other specified bodies.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>STATES TO END TAX BREAKS</p>
<p>State governments would, henceforth, stop giving tax concessions to attract industries. This was in keeping with a decision taken by state finance ministers nearly two years ago. The decision implied that tax holidays, deferred payment of taxes and similar concessions would be stopped. However, Finance Ministry officials said concessions granted earlier would continue.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>TRUCKERS BEGIN NATIONWIDE STRIKE</p>
<p>Transporters across the country decided to begin their proposed indefinite strike from midnight, following the failure of talks with senior government officials. The transporters are protesting against the service tax imposed on transport of goods by road and a steep increase in insurance premia by various insurance companies.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>IMPORT CURBS ON 542 ITEMS LIFTED</p>
<p>The government announced a new export-import policy which removed 542 items, 380 of them consumer goods, from the restricted list of imports. It also replaced the value-based advance licensing and passbook schemes for exporters with a new duty entitlement passbook scheme and announced incentives to spur exports in the agriculture, software and electronics and, gems and jewellery sectors.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
