<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479430" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>DENMARK: Novo Nordisk ready to buy, willing to merge.</title>
<headline>Novo Nordisk ready to buy, willing to merge.</headline>
<byline>Soeren Linding Jakobsen</byline>
<dateline>COPENHAGEN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Danish pharmaceuticals and biotechnology group Novo Nordisk said on Tuesday that it was ready to buy new business where suitable and also did not rule out the possibility of a merger if the right partner appeared.</p>
<p>&quot;In our current phase it is good to have funds available if the possibility of acquiring new products or firms crops up in our core activity areas,&quot; Novo Nordisk deputy chief executive Kurt Anker Nielsen told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;We have the power to do this now without asking anybody else's permission,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Novo Nordisk's own capital at end-1996 stood at 72 percent of its balance and the group has just negotiated new credit facilities of $600 million.</p>
<p>&quot;If we could club together with a firm whose activities fitted in as well with Novo as Nordisk Gentofte, we would work towards such an aim, &quot; Nielsen said.</p>
<p>The original Novo Industri merged with Denmark's Nordisk Gentofte in 1989 to become a world leader in insulin and industrial enzyme products.</p>
<p>Nielsen was adamant that Novo Nordisk would only consider merging if it kept its independence and was an equal partner.</p>
<p>He added that Novo Nordisk's capital structure had become excessively heavy, especially when the group aimed at having own capital at 60-65 percent of balance.</p>
<p>&quot;We reduced liquidity in the form of securities, among other things, as we felt that Novo Nordisk was now so big and recognised a firm that we could conduct financing operations outside our balance,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Novo Nordisk has four core business activities - diabetes care, women's hormone replacement products, human growth hormones and industrial enzymes.</p>
<p>&quot;We have said all along that size is not absolutely vital. We reckon it is important to be big within selected product areas and we are well on the way to being just that, so we do not risk being forced into the arms of one of the big global players, &quot; Nielsen said.</p>
<p>Novo Nordisk has recently set annual growth targets for its two biggest activities, industrial enzymes and diabetes treatment of 10-15 percent and 7-10 percent respectively.</p>
<p>Hormone replacement products for women were seen growing by 10-15 percent too, it said, with growth hormones not expected to do quite so well.</p>
<p>Novo Nordisk said it considered the United States, where it has 20 percent of the diabetes care market, as offering the greatest growth potential for its key insulin products.</p>
<p>On March 12, Novo Nordisk posted a bumper pre-tax profit of 2.521 billion crowns, 17 percent up on 1995 on eight percent higher consolidated turnover of 14.873 billion crowns and forecast solid progress continuing in 1997.</p>
<p>-- Copenhagen newsroom +45-33969653</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COPENHAGEN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DENMARK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
