<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479456" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: PRESS DIGEST - Bangladesh Newspapers - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Bangladesh Newspapers - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Bangladesh press on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>THE DAILY STAR</p>
<p>The government has decided to take stern action against those manpower agents who have illegally sent Bangladeshi people to Malaysia.</p>
<p>Opposition Bangladesh Nationalist Party (BNP leader Begum Khaleda Zia on Monday gave a seven-day ultimatum to the government to arrest the killers of two of her party workers in Feni district.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>THE INDEPENDENT</p>
<p>The 12th meeting of the foreign ministers' meeting of the Non-alligned Movement (NAM), scheduled from April 4 to 8 in New Delhi, will mainly discuss the issues relating to the reorganisation of the United Nations.</p>
<p>The government has decided to distribute the state-owned land among the landless people across the country.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>BANGLADESH OBSERVER</p>
<p>Armed tribals stormed a remote rural market in the hilly Bandarban district on Sunday evening and looted goods and cash from about hundred shops.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Abdus Samad Azad leaves for Seoul on Tuesday in quest of Korean investment and jobs for Bangladesh.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>FINANCIAL EXPRESS</p>
<p>World Bank's Resident Mission chief Pierre Landell Mills said on Monday Bangladesh capital market earned the reputation as a problem area, shying away foreign portfolio investors.</p>
<p>The government has taken steps for creating natural park and sanctuary for birds. REUTER</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
