<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479469" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's Hindalco plans aluminium complex.</title>
<headline>India's Hindalco plans aluminium complex.</headline>
<dateline>BHUBANESHWAR, India 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's largest private aluminium maker Hindalco Industries plans to set up an integrated aluminium complex in the eastern state of Orissa, state officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>They said the proposed complex is expected to cost 100 billion rupees.</p>
<p>Orissa government officials said the proposed complex will comprise of a one-million-tonne per annum alumina refinery and a 250,000-tonne per yer greenfield aluminium smelter.</p>
<p>Oficials said Hindalco will take on lease the Kodngamali-Pottangi mines of the state-run Orissa Mining Corp (OMC) to procure bauxite for its refinery.</p>
<p>The smelter will come up near IB valley in western Orissa, officials said. The company also plans to set up a capitve power plant of 600 megawatt close to a coal deposit in the valley.</p>
<p>Officials said Hindalco, a flagship company of the Aditya Birla group, and OMC signed a memorandum of understanding (MOU) on Saturday to set up the complex.</p>
<p>&quot;This project is another step to add value to the minerals yet to be exploited in the state,&quot; said S.B. Mishra, a senior Orissa government official.</p>
<p>Orissa Chief Minister J.B. Patnaik told Reuters &quot;The details of the terms and conditions, the mining area and other related things will be worked out at the time of signing the agreement.</p>
<p>Hindalco's plant at Renukoot in the northern state of Uttar Pradesh has a aluminium metal production capacity of 210,000 tonnes and alumina output capacity of 350,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Officials said the company planned to increase its aluminium capcity to 242,000 tonnes and alumina capacity to 450,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Hindalco is the third Indian company planning an integrated aluminium complex after Indian Aluminium Company (INDAL) and Larsen and Toubro.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22450">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BHUBANESHWAR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
