<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479404" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: St-Gobain sees weak glass prices in Europe.</title>
<headline>St-Gobain sees weak glass prices in Europe.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>East German production of flat glass, spurred by unusually high levels of state subsidy, are helping depress European prices, the chairman of French glass-maker Saint-Gobain said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The start of the year has seen a weak market in flat glass, where the trend of the second half has continued,&quot; Jean-Louis Beffa told analysts. There are no signs of recovery so far but it was &quot;not impossible&quot; there could be a pick up in the second half when demand strengthens.</p>
<p>Saint-Gobain is raising prices and would see if these would hold. It did not want to lose market shares, he said.</p>
<p>Generally, the French market was rising in line with official growth forecasts, around 2.3 percent, Beffa said.</p>
<p>Germany was growing at roughly the same rate, perhaps a little less than France, he said. Italy, however showed a fall due to lower consumption and lower export competitiveness.</p>
<p>The situation in the United States was satisfactory in the first quarter and there was no indication of a slowdown in the second quarter, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We think that the rate of growth is such that for the time being the intervention by the Fed is normal,&quot; he said. There was little risk of inflation, he added.</p>
<p>Automobile glass was relatively comfortable.</p>
<p>The insulation sector had seen a fairly favourable start to the year, with little negative to report for Europe or the United States.</p>
<p>Reinforcement fibres were in a difficult situation, with an erosion in prices, although this could improve in the second half, he said.</p>
<p>Building materials showed a favourable trend in Latin and North America, with a good start to the year even if there had been no significant increase on last year's good figures.</p>
<p>Containers, which includes glass packaging and bottles, saw difficult conditions in Europe and the company was continuing to cut costs. But the United States was improving.</p>
<p>Poliet saw a difficult start in January but there was a recovery in February, which should continue through March. Generally the situation was favourable.</p>
<p>Pipelines saw good exports, with a favourable situation in Latin America.</p>
<p>Ceramics saw good conditions and there was a recovery in abrasives.</p>
<p>-- Paris newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I24700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
