<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479410" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: U.S. stock error rattles European oilseed traders.</title>
<headline>U.S. stock error rattles European oilseed traders.</headline>
<byline>Tim Hepher</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>European oilseed traders, bitterly critical of a correction to U.S. government figures that sent soybean markets soaring, said on Tuesday the cut in reported stocks would tighten demand for meal and might lift cereals use.</p>
<p>Sellers on the European cash market disappeared after the U.S. Department of Agriculture confirmed it was correcting its March 1 soybean stock figure to 1.056 billion bushels from 1.078 billion given in a government report on Monday.</p>
<p>But on Europe's only oilseed futures exchange, the MATIF rapeseed contract in Paris, the market was flat to slightly higher and traders this sjhould be seen as very firm when compared with Chicago's previous closing levels on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no sellers on the cash market and if you want to trade an opinion in Europe you go to MATIF,&quot; private oilseeds trader Bernard Nicol said.</p>
<p>&quot;MATIF traded unchanged for November which is firm looking at last night, and that was in spite of a weaker dollar,&quot; Nicol, who also publishes oilseeds information service Infolea, said.</p>
<p>&quot;It means people are greedy to get the beans and everything else in their books and not in someone else's books,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In Project A electronic trading overnight, CBOT soybeans gained up to 12 cents on talk the USDA was preparing to correct its stock numbers for the first time in about 30 years.</p>
<p>July reached $8.70 a bushel or $1.72-1/2 more than November.</p>
<p>European traders were predicting before Chicago's Tuesday open that the same spread would soon penetrate two dollars -- &quot;I'd easily look for that in a week or two,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>When Chicago soybeans opened limit-up for front months at the market's official opening on Tuesday the same spread was up to $1.86. May also reached its highest point since August 1988.</p>
<p>&quot;This has made what we have seen with (demand) rationing on the old crop even more prominent,&quot; Nicol said. &quot;The market needs to do the rationing through the (July/November) spread.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders said the new stock figure, which was below original market expectations of 1.1 billion bushels, would exacerbate the tendency of soyoil to lose share against meal, the underlying source of the market's problems in the current campaign.</p>
<p>Some saw cereals benefiting from the move though only over a matter of months and barring any climatic problems.</p>
<p>Nicol and others who declined to be named said they were taken aback by the error and said it should not have happened.</p>
<p>&quot;This is an incredible mistake,&quot; Nicol said. &quot;Sowing intentions, yes, they can be out by 10 percent. They are an opinion. But stocks are there, they are a fact.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I can't ever remember this happening. A lot of people would be very upset,&quot; another European trader said before the USDA officially confirmed the correction on Tuesday.</p>
<p>European traders said some would be hit by losses after selling Project A on Monday and buying back on Tuesday, though they said such losses would be hard to prove or quantify.</p>
<p>Explaining the correction, the chairman of the U.S. Agricultural Statistics Board Rich Allen said on Tuesday it was due to an arithmetical error.</p>
<p>Errors were made computing the off-farm stocks figure for MIssissippi that inflated the state total. Allen said it had been about three decades since a stock report had been corrected. A standard review had failed to uncover the flaw.</p>
<p>But a European oilseeds trader said the error should still have been spotted. &quot;It was so big. It was obvious,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>--Paris newsroom +331 4221 5146</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100223">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
