<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479417" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: U.N. sleuth sees Iran advance on women's rights.</title>
<headline>U.N. sleuth sees Iran advance on women's rights.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A United Nations investigator said on Tuesday there was a &quot;climate for change&quot; in Iran on the status of women amid a growing public debate on the issue and the election of women to the country's parliament.</p>
<p>But the investigator, Canadian jurist Maurice Copithorne, said there was probably &quot;considerable opposition&quot; to further advance while in some areas movement had been retrogressive.</p>
<p>In a report for the U.N.'s Human Rights Commission, he implicitly rebuked Iran for maintaining a high rate of death sentences, for persecution of religious dissidents, for killings of dissenters abroad, and for new pressures on the press.</p>
<p>&quot;While the legal and practical difficulties faced by women in Iran have been well documented, it is now clear that some change has been effected in recent years and that there are a number of signs that further and substantive improvements may be on the way,&quot; Copithorne said.</p>
<p>There was, he declared, &quot;a climate for change in Iran concerning the status of women.&quot;</p>
<p>However, he added, &quot;there is probably considerable opposition to such a prospect both within and outside the government....Further, if and when significant change happens, it may be uneven.&quot;</p>
<p>Iran -- which has enforced its view of Islamic conduct for women since the overthrow of the Shah 17 years ago -- still had a considerable way to go &quot;to bring itself into compliance with international standards&quot; on women's rights.</p>
<p>&quot;But there are clear signs that this may be a time for progress to be made. The change must be real and the momentum must be sustained,&quot; declared Copithorne, who was once a senior Canadian diplomat.</p>
<p>His report was his third since his appointment in 1995 after the resignation of a previous Commission rights investigator for Iran -- in U.N. parlance a &quot;special rapporteur&quot; -- who was barred from the country for four years.</p>
<p>In an interim version last November, he said the rights situation in Iran &quot;may well have deteriorated&quot; during 1996. But this phrasing was missing from the final report.</p>
<p>Copithorne has been implicitly criticised by Iranian exiles for being &quot;soft&quot; on the Tehran government, but he argues that he presents the situation as he sees it.</p>
<p>However, the report revealed that he had been refused permission to go back to the country at the end of last year or early this year -- after a brief visit in February 1996 -- to gather fresh material for the new review.</p>
<p>An Iranian government reply to his request for clearance to go in which was cited in the report made clear Tehran had hoped the decision to admit him last February would lead to a more neutral stance by the 53-member Commission towards Iran.</p>
<p>But a few weeks later the body rejected a softer approach and adopted by 28 votes to eight with 17 abstentions a resolution backed by the United States and European countries condemning the Iranian government's rights record.</p>
<p>This had been &quot;detrimental to the renewed condifence and cooperation&quot; between Iran and the Commission, Copithorne's report quoted an oral message from Tehran delivered to him on December 30 as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;Hence, for the present, a further visit to the Islamic republic of Iran seems to be of little avail,&quot; the message added, according to the report.</p>
<p>The Commission is expected to pass a similar resolution this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
