<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479438" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India crisis clouds talks with Pakistan.</title>
<headline>India crisis clouds talks with Pakistan.</headline>
<byline>Nelson Graves</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India and Pakistan, fresh from upbeat peace talks, said on Tuesday a political crisis in New Delhi might delay efforts to resume substantive bilateral negotiations.</p>
<p>Pakistani Foreign Minister Gohar Ayub Khan said planned talks next week with his Indian counterpart, Inder Kumar Gujral, might be put off because of a looming vote of confidence in Indian Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>Deve Gowda on Sunday lost the pivotal support of the Congress party in parliament and must call a vote of confidence by April 11.</p>
<p>The two nations' foreign ministers had planned to meet during or after a meeting of foreign ministers of the Non-Aligned Movement (NAM) in New Delhi on April 7-8.</p>
<p>Pakistan's official APP news agency quoted Khan as saying the Indian crisis might &quot;cause some deadlock in the talks as Indian President Shanker Dayal Sharma had asked...Deve Gowda to take a vote of confidence from parliament&quot;.</p>
<p>Indian officials said the two foreign ministers were expected to meet during the NAM conference but might not attempt to press ahead with the talks, which resumed last week after a three-year standoff.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be a tete-a-tete, and exchange of views,&quot; one official said. &quot;The main focus will still be on NAM.&quot;</p>
<p>The four days of talks in New Delhi ended on Monday with a pledge by the two neighbours' foreign secretaries to meet again in Islamabad.</p>
<p>The two sides, which have fought three wars since independence in 1947, released a joint statement saying the talks had been &quot;frank, cordial and constructive&quot;.</p>
<p>A Foreign Ministry spokesman said the foundation had been set for more progress. &quot;Given the atmosphere, there is sufficient ground for further substantive discussions at whatever level in the near future,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Foreign policy analysts said the outcome of the latest talks was encouraging but the diplomats had been unable to set dates for a subsequent meeting partly because of political uncertainty surrounding Deve Gowda's government.</p>
<p>&quot;It is better that this hiatus be put behind us before substantive discussions take place,&quot; a Foreign Ministry official said. &quot;Let us put this political crisis behind us.&quot;</p>
<p>But a government official said New Delhi and Islamabad were still discussing the scope of any talks between Gujral and Khan.</p>
<p>&quot;The matter is still wide open,&quot; said the official, who asked not to be named. &quot;The situation is evolving.&quot;</p>
<p>Gujral has invited Khan to remain in New Delhi for two days after the NAM meeting, but the Pakistani foreign minister has not yet responded to the invitation, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>On Monday President Shankar Dayal Sharma asked Deve Gowda to prove his majority in the lower house of parliament by April 7.</p>
<p>But after the prime minister pointed out that his government would be hosting NAM foreign ministers that day, the president extended the deadline to April 11.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
