<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479495" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India says Pakistan talks must await end of crisis.</title>
<headline>India says Pakistan talks must await end of crisis.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India said on Tuesday that it would have to resolve a domestic political crisis before resuming &quot;substantive&quot; bilateral talks with Pakistan.</p>
<p>A Foreign Ministry spokesman said the two nations' foreign ministers would meet during or after a ministerial conference of the Non-Aligned Movement next week in New Delhi, but not hold &quot;substantive discussions&quot; on bilateral matters.  </p>
<p>&quot;It is better that this hiatus be put behind us before substantive discussions take place,&quot; the spokesman said. &quot;Let us put this political crisis behind us.&quot;</p>
<p>Indian Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda on Sunday lost the pivotal support of the Congress party in parliament and must call a vote of confidence by April 11.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral will meet his Pakistani counterpart, Gohar Ayub Khan, in the Indian capital next week, but the focus of their discussion will be on the Non-Aligned Movement, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>The foreign secretaries of India and Pakistan ended four days of talks on Monday, the first high-level bilateral negotiations in three years, and vowed to meet again in Islamabad. &quot;Given the atmosphere, there is sufficient ground for further substantive discussions at whatever level in the near future,&quot; the Indian Foreign Ministry spokesman said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
