<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479468" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India plans law for compulsory child education.</title>
<headline>India plans law for compulsory child education.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India, home to the world's largest child workforce, plans a law to make primary education compulsory to pull children out of factories and into schools, Labour Minister M. Arunachalam said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The government has committed (itself) to a law to make education compulsory in a short while,&quot; the minister told a meeting of child's rights activists and child workers. &quot;We will introduce a bill in parliament as soon as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Of course, as you know, the government is in a critical situation now -- how soon and whether we can fulfill it remains to be seen,&quot; Arunachalam added.</p>
<p>Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's government is fighting for survival after a key ally withdrew its crucial support on Sunday. Deve Gowda must prove his majority in parliament by April 11.</p>
<p>India officially prohibited the employment of children under 14 years in 1948 and, in 1986, banned 17 industries considered hazardous from employing children above 14.</p>
<p>While 14 Indian states aim to provide compulsory primary education, there are no federal government laws to enforce it.</p>
<p>Labour Ministry estimates show that India is home to some 20 million child slaves.</p>
<p>But child's rights activists say there are more than 55 million poor children working in labour-intensive industries like matches-making, quarrying, tanning, bangle-making, fireworks factories and carpet-weaving.</p>
<p>They say an estimated 1.2 million children work in carpet factories alone in India, Nepal and Pakistan. About 80 percent of India's child labourers work on farms and in roadside tea stalls, working to repay parents' debts to rural loan sharks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
