<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479579" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada T-bills open much weaker as dollar softens.</title>
<headline>Canada T-bills open much weaker as dollar softens.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian T-bills opened much weaker in moderate trade on Tuesday as further weakness in the Canadian dollar prompted expectations that the Bank of Canada will be forced to raise rates, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the currency weakness,&quot; said a T-bill trader with one bank-owned brokerage &quot;More than anything, it's the feeling that the soft currency will lead the Bank (of Canada) to raise rates.&quot;</p>
<p>Canada's three-month when-issued T-bill softened to yield 3.34 percent from 3.25 percent at Monday's close.  </p>
<p>Canadian T-bills weakened as the currency opened softer at C$1.3877 (US$0.7206), moving towards its two-year low of C$1.3910 (US$0.7189). Weighing on the Canadian dollar are expectations that the U.S. Federal Reserve will hike interest rates again in May. The most recent Fed rate hike weighed heavily on the Canadian dollar.</p>
<p>Dealers said there are growing expectations that the Bank of Canada will have to hike interest rates in order to offset the weakness in the currency and rebalance monetary conditions in Canada. The central bank's key bank rate of 3.25 percent is well below the U.S. Federal funds rate of 5.5 percent.  </p>
<p>In other prices, the six-month when-issued T-bill softened to yield 3.70 percent from 3.66 percent at Monday's close. The one-year when-issued T-bill softened to yield 4.26 percent from 4.14 percent.</p>
<p>The call loan rate traded at 3.05 percent, in the upper half of the Bank of Canada's 2.75-3.25 percent target range. The Bank of Canada yesterday intervened on the money market with three rounds of specials at 3.25 percent after the call loan rate traded at the top of the target range.</p>
<p>((Jeffrey Hodgson (416) 941-8105, e-mail: jeffrey.hodgson@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
