<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479578" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Bre-X says needs time to study assay report.</title>
<headline>Bre-X says needs time to study assay report.</headline>
<dateline>CALGARY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bre-X Minerals Ltd said on Tuesday that it will need more time to study a report from Kilborn SNC Lavalin containing data related to a check assay program at the Busang gold project.</p>
<p>&quot;This report is an extensive document which requires a more thorough review by Bre-X's technical team than initially anticipated,&quot; the Canadian exploration company said in a statement.</p>
<p>Bre-X said it received the report from PT Kilborn Pakar Rekayasa, a subsidiary of Kilborn SNC Lavalin, which is a unit of SNC-Lavalin Group Inc.  </p>
<p>&quot;Bre-X intends to conduct a detailed analysis of this report and correlate the relevant data therein with the information to be generated from Strathcona Minerals Services Limited, currently conducting an independent audit of the drilling, sampling and assaying at the Busang Gold Project,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Shares in Bre-X were halted on the Toronto Stock Exchange for the statement. When the trading halt was lifted around 1030 EST/1530 GMT, Bre-X opened 0.45 higher at 2.95 in heavy trading. The stock was up 1.00 at 3.50 on volume of 7.0 million shares by 1050 EST/1550 GMT.  </p>
<p>Bre-X has been under fire since test results from partner Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold Inc last week called into question Bre-X's claim that Busang, in the jungles of Borneo, was possibly the biggest gold find this century.</p>
<p>Investors slashed almost C$3 billion ($2.19 billion) off Bre-X's share price last week when the TSE ignored the company's initial request to postpone trading for several weeks, and re-opened trading late in the session.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, at least two class action lawsuits have been filed on behalf of Bre-X shareholders against the company, chief executive David Walsh and other insiders.</p>
<p>((Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8100))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CALGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
