<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479546" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan says Kashmir central to ties with India.</title>
<headline>Pakistan says Kashmir central to ties with India.</headline>
<byline>Aurang Zeb</byline>
<dateline>LAHORE, Pakistan 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistan on Monday stressed the &quot;centrality&quot; of its dispute with neighbouring India over Kashmir region as the two arch-rivals ended four days of peace talks in New Delhi.</p>
<p>Pakistani foreign ministry secretary Shamshad Ahmad said on return from New Delhi he and his Indian counterpart Salman Haidar had discussed &quot;all outstanding issues between India and Pakistan, including the core issue of Jammu and Kashmir&quot;.</p>
<p>Talking to reporters at Lahore airport in the Punjab province, he described the talks as frank and constructive and said the sides &quot;sought to explore common ground for evolving a mechanism&quot; to address these issues.</p>
<p>&quot;In our interactions, we emphasised the centrality of Jammu and Kashmir dispute in Pakistan-India relations,&quot; Ahmad said.</p>
<p>&quot;I stressed that without progress on the core issue of Jammu and Kashmir, meaningful cooperation in the economic and cultural fields between the two countries will be difficult.&quot;</p>
<p>Ahmad also said his delegation emphasised its deep concern at what he called &quot;represssive tactics of Indian occupying forces&quot; in the Indian-ruled two-thirds of Kashmir where New Delhi is fighting a separatist Moslem revolt.</p>
<p>Pakistan rules the remaining third of the Himalayan region, over which the two countries have fought two of their three wars since their independence from Britain in 1947.</p>
<p>Ahmad said that while in New Delhi, he also met the leadership of the umbrella All Parties Hurriyat Conference of anti-India Kashmiri groups and assured them that &quot;Pakistan will abide by its commitment to the Kashmir cause&quot;.</p>
<p>Pakistan denies Indian charges that it is training and arming the Kashmiri militants but says it gives them only moral and political support.</p>
<p>Earlier a joint statement issued in New Delhi said: &quot;The two foreign secretaries discussed all outstanding issues of concern to both sides in a frank, cordial and constructive manner.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The foreign secretaries decided to continue their discussions in Islamabad on dates to be mutually decided.&quot;</p>
<p>Salman Haidar and Shamshad Ahmad had previously kept an official silence on their talks, which began on Friday.</p>
<p>The negotiations were the first since a similar dialogue collapsed three years ago amid deep differences over Kashmir.</p>
<p>The latest meetings coincided with renewed violence in Kashmir and political turmoil in New Delhi, where the Congress party on Sunday withdrew support for Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's 10-month-old minority coalition government.</p>
<p>Pakistani leaders said before the talks they wanted &quot;some progress&quot; on Kashmir to enable the two sides to move forward on other matters. India made clear it wanted to put Kashmir on hold and focus on trade, economic cooperation and other areas.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAHORE, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
