<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479557" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - Oil slips as Nigeria resumes normal output.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Oil slips as Nigeria resumes normal output.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>World oil prices lost ground on Tuesday depressed by a return to normal operations in Nigeria and a weighty overhang on the North Sea spot market.</p>
<p>London futures for bellwether Brent blend by 1600 GMT were trading 30 cents down at $19.08 a barrel.</p>
<p>Oil giant Shell said its Nigerian production was on the path to full recovery on Tuesday after community unrest cut production by as much as 20 percent last week.</p>
<p>Shell said operations at a dozen crude flow stations brought to a halt by local political protests were being resumed in stages.</p>
<p>&quot;During the course of this week we expect to resume normal levels of production,&quot; a Shell official said.</p>
<p>Shell's 950,000 barrels a day (bpd) of Nigerian crude output was running little more than 50,000 bpd below capacity on Tuesday compared to a 210,000 bpd shortfall last week.</p>
<p>Militant villagers protesting against a merger of two communities and relocation of the capital of another council area last week disrupted Shell's operations across the Niger delta oil producing region.</p>
<p>Dealers said that unsold spot supplies in Atlantic Basin crude markets also were keeping a lid on crude prices.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm putting the situation as ample availabilities in my report,&quot; one North Sea crude trader said.</p>
<p>The supply overhang has increased discounts for spot crude cargoes to almost a dollar a barrel below futures prices for Brent scheduled to load in about 15 days time.</p>
<p>Traders said U.S. gasoline markets, normally a source of strength in the approach to the summer driving season, still were proving slow to get off the mark.</p>
<p>Forecasts of colder U.S. weather were seen by some as slightly supportive to distillates.</p>
<p>Independent forecasters Weather Services Corp said on Tuesday they saw temperatures in the key market of the northeastern U.S. eight to 14 degrees Fahrenheit below normal on Wednesday, but rising to slightly above normal on Friday.</p>
<p>Crude oil prices in dollars per barrel:</p>
<p>						   April 1     Mar 27</p>
<p>						 (1600 GMT)   (close)</p>
<p>    Dated Brent				$18.23	$18.52</p>
<p>    IPE London Brent Futures (May)     $19.08	$19.38</p>
<p>    NYMEX light crude futures (May)    $20.51	$20.75</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
