<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479567" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton asks for FCC study on curbing liquor ads.</title>
<headline>Clinton asks for FCC study on curbing liquor ads.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton on Tuesday asked the Federal Communications Commission to study ways to curb television liquor ads following the industry's decision to abandon its nearly half-century voluntary ban.</p>
<p>&quot;Liquor has no business with kids, and kids should have no business with liquor. Liquor ads on television would provide a message of encouragement to drink that young people simply don't need. Nothing good can come of it,&quot; Clinton said.  </p>
<p>Clinton, who had criticised the industry's decision last year to end the voluntary ban in effect for television since 1948 and radio since 1936, said at a White House ceremony he hoped the industry would rethink its position.</p>
<p>&quot;We're here today because parents now face a new hazard in raising their childen -- the advertising of liquor on television,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The distilled spirits industry has complained that there is no ban on beer and wine television advertising, but Clinton dismissed this as a rationale for liquor advertising, saying there should be no expansion of promoting the use of alcohol.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
