<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479504" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Political drama seen leaving Indian rupee untouched.</title>
<headline>Political drama seen leaving Indian rupee untouched.</headline>
<byline>Shyam Kumar</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's unfolding political drama is unlikely to infect the rupee as the central bank possesses more than enough muscle to dampen any speculative fever, foreign exchange dealers said.</p>
<p>India's currency markets were shut on Tuesday as banks finalised their year-end accounts.</p>
<p>But there little worry among dealers that they were missing any of the torrid action that has gripped the country stock markets since the Congress party withdrew support for Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's minority coalition government.</p>
<p>A shortlived blip weaker on Monday morning was the rupee's sole reaction to political upheavals that could culminate in a confidence vote by April 11.</p>
<p>Dealers said the central bank may not even have to sell a dollar to brake any impending slide in the rupee.</p>
<p>&quot;The RBI (Reserve Bank of India) can manage that even without actively intervening,&quot; said a foreign bank dealer.</p>
<p>The RBI has been the key factor influencing the dollar-rupee movement in recent months.</p>
<p>Dealers say the RBI's long-term strategy was a gradual depreciation of the exchange rate to reflect inflation trends.</p>
<p>But in recent months, it has had to buy dollars as the rupee threatened to appreciate on the back of large dollar inflows stemming from foreign direct investment, portfolio investment and overseas equity issues of Indian firms.</p>
<p>&quot;Yesterday (Monday) was the ideal day the rupee could have fallen sharply, but nothing much happened,&quot; said Ravi Kumar, chief forex dealer at ABN AMRO Bank in Bombay.</p>
<p>The rupee quickly recovered back to opening levels around 35.92 a dollar after initially weakening to 35.99.</p>
<p>Forward dollar premiums were attractive for companies to book their near-term requirements, but there was little demand, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Indian companies don't see the dollar rising above 36.10 level in the near term,&quot; said the treasury head of another bank.</p>
<p>&quot;They don't think the current (forward dollar) premiums are justified. And that is why they don't want to book forwards.&quot;</p>
<p>Last week, the RBI said its foreign currency reserves were at an all-time high of $21.16 billion as on March 21, which covers around seven months imports.</p>
<p>&quot;Building up reserves is crucial in RBI's plans to move towards full convertibility on the capital account,&quot; said a dealer. &quot;I doubt they'll be too keen to sell dollars.&quot;</p>
<p>Even if the rupee suddenly skidded beyond the 36 a dollar level, the RBI will only have to check prices for the market to calm down, a dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is so tentative and nervous at such levels,&quot; said a dealer. RBI in the past has said the objective of its intervention is to prevent sharp volatility in the market.</p>
<p>Some dealers said the RBI will be happy to see the rupee touch the 36 mark.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think RBI will sell at 36, They may, at 36.20, to arrest the (rupee's) fall,&quot; said Moses Harding, vice president and head of forex at the private IndusInd Bank.</p>
<p>NatWest Securities said in a recent report India sought to restrict the current account deficit to a sustainable level.</p>
<p>&quot;This could keep the rupee slightly overvalued in the long term, as that would encourage both imports and capital flows,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>-- Bombay newsroom +91-22-265 9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
