<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479531" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistani Senate passes presidential powers bill.</title>
<headline>Pakistani Senate passes presidential powers bill.</headline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Pakistani Senate unanimously passed a constitutional amendment on Tuesday to curb powers that allow the president to sack a government and parliament and appoint armed forces chiefs and provincial governors.</p>
<p>The 87-member house passed the constitution amendment bill by 79-0 votes. The bill must also be passed by the 217-memeber National Assembly (lower house) to become law.</p>
<p>The passage of the bill, announced by Senate chairman Wasim Sajjad, came hours after Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif's cabinet decided to move the amendment to restore supremacy of parliament.</p>
<p>The amendments make a dissolution of the National Assembly and consequential sacking of a prime minister, the appointment of armed forces chiefs and provincial governors by the president subject to mandatory advice from the prime minister.</p>
<p>The amendments are certain to be approved by the National Assembly, where Sharif's Pakistan Muslim League and its allies hold the two-thirds majority needed for amending the constitution.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
