<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479505" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's truck owners launch nationwide strike.</title>
<headline>India's truck owners launch nationwide strike.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The owners of more than two million trucks pulled their vehicles off India's roads on Tuesday in protest over a proposed service tax and higher insurance premiums, transport officials said.</p>
<p>Booking and delivery at nearly 60,000 transport companies across the country came to a standstill, S.P. Singh, a spokesman for All India Motor Transport Congress (AIMTC), told Reuters.</p>
<p>The nationwide strike started at midnight March 31, he said.</p>
<p>The congress represents owners of about two million heavy trucks, one million light and medium-weight trucks and some 60,000 booking and delivery companies.</p>
<p>&quot;About 2.2 million trucks have gone on strike,&quot; Singh said, adding that talks between government officials and the AIMTC had so far failed to break the deadlock.</p>
<p>Further talks were planned for later on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The AIMTC objected to a five percent service tax on road transport which Finance Minister P. Chidambaram proposed in the federal budget for the 1997/98 (April-March) financial year.</p>
<p>It also denounced a decision by state-owned insurance companies which the transport congress said would raise insurance premiums between 300 and 400 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Nearly 60 percent of goods are carried by roads. Hence any move to stop transport will adversely affect movement of goods and traffic,&quot; said a spokesman for a northern Indian chamber of commerce.</p>
<p>&quot;The strike should be deferred. Even if the truckers have some grievances it should be addressed when there is a stable government,&quot; the spokesman for Punjab, Haryana, Delhi Chambers of Commerce and Industry (PHDCCI) said.</p>
<p>Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's 10-month-old minority government is facing a political crisis after its key ally, the Congress party, withdrew support on Sunday.</p>
<p>Deve Gowda has been given until April 11 by President Shankar Dayal Sharma to face a confidence vote in the Lok Sabha, or lower house of the parliament.</p>
<p>Deliveries of aviation fuel to airports could also be affected by the national truck strike, another AIMTC official said.</p>
<p>He said dock workers at Nava Shiva, the port for Bombay, would refuse to load or unload ships. The strike started a day earlier than first planned, at midnight on Sunday, in the western state of Maharashtra.</p>
<p>Aviation fuel is delivered by private carriers or government-owned tankers from companies such as Indian Oil Corporation.</p>
<p>&quot;There will not be any immediate impact as inventories of aviation fuel are usually there for three, four days. We will not stop the government carriers from supplying,&quot; Singh said.</p>
<p>The AIMTC had two rounds of talks with government officials on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;We had two rounds of government (talks) which lasted for five to six hours but failed to yield any result,&quot; Singh said.</p>
<p>Truck owners said the ball was in the government's court and hoped officials would resolve the impasse soon.</p>
<p>Singh said the last time truck owners went on strike was in 1993, which lasted for 13 days.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
