<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479565" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. manufacturing surges, economy adds momentum.</title>
<headline>U.S. manufacturing surges, economy adds momentum.</headline>
<byline>Glenn Somerville</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Manufacturing gained steam in March, a key private-sector report released on Tuesday showed, yet there was no sign of troubling price pressures as financial markets were roiled again by fear of more interest rate rises.</p>
<p>The National Association of Purchasing Management, whose members buy raw materials for the nation's factories, said its index of manufacturing activity climbed to 55.0 in March -- the highest since February 1995 when it was also at that level -- from 53.1 in February.</p>
<p>A reading above 50 in the index shows expanding activity. March was the 71st straight month -- nearly six years -- in which the manufacturing index indicated growth.</p>
<p>The purchasing managers' summary was one of a trio of reports that further demonstrated the economy's vitality as it completed six years of steady expansion last month.</p>
<p>It was intensely awaited by analysts after two days of steep stock market losses since the Federal Reserve raised short-term interest rates last week as a preemptive strike against inflation. Its price index dropped to 50.9 percent from 55.1 percent, reflecting a slower rate of inflation.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, stock prices fell on Tuesday, though bond prices steadied.</p>
<p>Separately, the Commerce Department said spending on new construction increased in February at the briskest rate in nearly a year, up 2.3 percent to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $603.8 billion after a 0.3 percent January gain.</p>
<p>Milder-than-normal weather after a bitter January boosted building activity across the board for private and government-financed projects from new housing to offices and water treatment plants.</p>
<p>A third report from the Conference Board showed its broad-based index of leading indicators flashing a green light for steady growth as it rose 0.5 percent in February after a 0.3 percent gain in January.</p>
<p>The February rise in the index, which is designed to forecast economic activity six to nine months ahead, was the largest since a 0.9 percent rise last February, the business research group said.</p>
<p>&quot;The economy is showing solid growth with inflation still well-contained,&quot; said economist Lynn Reaser of Barnett Banks Inc. in Jacksonville, Fla.</p>
<p>&quot;But the economy, in terms of labour markets, is at full employment,&quot; Reaser added. &quot;The risk is still on the side of higher inflation rather than recession.&quot;</p>
<p>The Federal Reserve cited its concern about strong demand last week when it announced a quarter percentage point rise in short-term interest rates. Many analysts expect more rate rises later this year until the central bank is convinced that costlier credit is putting a brake on demand.</p>
<p>The purchasing managers' report showed gains in new orders, tighter supplier deliveries, rising employment and more export orders last month that suggest continuing momentum for the economy.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly these numbers are pointing to stronger growth through the second quarter,&quot; said economist David Jones of Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Co. in New York, possibly three consecutive quarters of expansion at a 3 percent to 4 percent annual rate.</p>
<p>&quot;That's far in excess of the economy's long-term potential,&quot; Jones added. The Fed has set a target of around 2 percent to 2-1/4 percent as its ideal level for sustained increases in national output without risking an inflationary flare-up in wages and prices.</p>
<p>The February leading index, seen as an indicator of the economy's direction, was broadly higher with nine of its 10 separate component measures turning up from January.</p>
<p>The largest contributors to the overall gain were fewer unemployment claims and slower deliveries, which suggested that suppliers were having a harder time meeting brisk demand.</p>
<p>The Commerce Department's finding that February construction picked up was anticipated because it was previously reported that there was a bulge in hiring for construction jobs during the month.</p>
<p>The size of the gain, however, was larger than anticipated. The department said it was the biggest surge in construction spending since a matching 2.3 percent rise in March of last year. The last time there was a bigger spending jump was nearly three years ago, in March 1994, when it gained 3.4 percent.</p>
<p>Privately financed building rose 1.8 percent to $456 billion a year in February after a 0.6 percent January gain.</p>
<p>Government spending on construction projects surged 4.1 percent to a rate of $147.9 billion in February after a 0.4 percent fall in January. Spending was up on public housing projects, for schools, highways and streets, sewers and water treatment plants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
