<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479545" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: INDIAN HEADLINE STOCKS - Factors to watch - April 1.</title>
<headline>INDIAN HEADLINE STOCKS - Factors to watch - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the main factors affecting Indian stock markets on Tuesday morning:</p>
<p>NEWS OUTLOOK:</p>
<p>**  Indian stocks will continue to head lower, shaken by sudden political crisis which erupted with Congress party's withdrawal of crucial support to ruling coalition, traders say</p>
<p>**  Shares across the country's bourses fall more than seven percent in nervous trade on Monday as investors struggle to come to grips with the unexpected bout of political uncertainty</p>
<p>**  Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda gets until April 11 to prove his majority in parliament, a near impossible task after his government loses support of its key ally</p>
<p>**  President Shankar Dayal Sharma's instruction to Deve Gowda to seek a vote of confidence by April 11 closes option to call snap polls, forcing him either to resign or seek a split in the fractious Congress party to gain a majority</p>
<p>**  Asked how Congress expected to form a government backed by the coalition it sought to topple, spokesman Vithal Gadgil said: &quot;In politics, certain things are not stated publicly.&quot;</p>
<p>**  Foreign investors in Hong Kong and London return to business after long Easter weekend. Traders say India's overseas listed global depositary receipts (GDRs) will see sharp fall during the day</p>
<p>**  India and Pakistan talks end with an agreement to meet again in the Pakistan capital Islamabad. No dates are set.  </p>
<p>**  Main opposition Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) says it will not seek to form a fresh government</p>
<p>**  Foreign investors despondent at India's sudden plunge into political crisis should watch and wait rather than take any drastic decisions, brokers say</p>
<p>They say it is too early to retreat from India or take advantage of cheap prices and jump in</p>
<p>**  Political leaders jockey for power ahead of confidence vote with United Front coalition swiftly closing ranks behind the Prime Minister</p>
<p>**  Commerce minister, shrugging off political setback to the government, unveils a new trade policy that lifts import controls on hundreds of items</p>
<p>Bolla Buli Ramaiah also said the rupee, riding on the strength of a surge in foreign exchange reserves, would remain stable despite the political uncertainty</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
