<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479568" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Consumers get new power against 'credit repair'.</title>
<headline>Consumers get new power against 'credit repair'.</headline>
<byline>David Lawsky</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Consumers with bad credit ratings won new power Tuesday to strike back and win money from companies that promise to fix their credit but do not, federal officials said.</p>
<p>A new federal law took effect that arms consumers who have been defrauded by the promise of credit repair with the power to go into federal court and win their money back -- along with attorney fees and unlimited punitive damages.</p>
<p>Consumers with bad credit -- often desperate for credit cards -- pay hundreds or even thousands of dollars to companies that claim to be able to &quot;repair&quot; their credit.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope that consumers who have been victimised by credit repairs have success in getting to court, getting damages and ultimately shutting these firms down,&quot; said David Medine, of the Federal Trade Commission's division of credit practices. &quot;An individual lawyer can be very effective in costing a clinic enough money to shut it down.&quot;</p>
<p>In addition, the FTC has been taking aggressive action itself against the firms and the new law permits state attorneys general to bring action in federal court.</p>
<p>The Federal Trade Commission estimates there are about 1,000 &quot;credit repair&quot; companies in the United States, but say none of them do what they promise.</p>
<p>&quot;While it's theoretically possible that there could be a legitimate service, the FTC has never seen a legitimate credit repair service,&quot; said Steven Baker, director of the FTC Chicago regional office, at a news conference.</p>
<p>FTC experts said flatly that no one can repair credit or wipe away truthful records of bad payment. Under the new law credit repair services are barred from taking any money at all from consumers before successfully repairing their credit.</p>
<p>Before any contract is signed, the credit repair companies must give consumers written disclosure explaining their rights, along with a precise schedule of what they will do. Consumers have three days to cancel the contract after singing. Any contract that fails to comply with those conditions is void.</p>
<p>Background information on credit repair is available on the FTC's World Wide Web site, http://WWW.FTC.GOV.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
