<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479517" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's overseas shares dive on political crisis.</title>
<headline>India's overseas shares dive on political crisis.</headline>
<byline>Priya Ramani</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign investors caught unawares by a sudden political crisis triggered during the long Easter weekend, marked prices of India's overseas listed equity sharply lower as they returned on Tuesday, traders said.</p>
<p>But they said though prices of global depositary receipts (GDRs) in Hong Kong were quoted at least 10-15 percent below Thursday's close, volumes were low and most investors were on the sidelines.</p>
<p>Prices in London were also expected to open sharply lower.</p>
<p>Largest private firm Reliance Industries was quoting at an indicative $15.25/15.75 in London, against its last close of $17.63/$18.38.</p>
<p>State Bank of India had been driven down to $19.25/19.50 from Thursday's close of $22.25/23.0.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices have been marked down by market makers by around 10-12 percent across-the-board but we are not advising clients to sell when the market is so easy,&quot; said a GDR salesman at a leading UK brokerage in London.</p>
<p>&quot;Most investors missed the opportunity to sell yesterday.&quot;</p>
<p>A sudden announcement by the Congress party on Sunday that it was withdrawing make-or-break support to the country's ruling coalition sent Indian stock markets into a tailspin on Monday.</p>
<p>Stocks across the country fell more than seven percent but Hong Kong and London markets -- where GDRs of top Indian firms are actively traded -- only reopened on Tuesday after the long Easter weekend.</p>
<p>India's newest GDR -- by state-run telecommunications firm Videsh Sanchar Nigam Ltd (VSNL) -- was quoting at $15.50/16.25 against its last close of $17.50/17.75 in London.</p>
<p>&quot;VSNL has fallen quite a bit considering the amount of strength the issue had and the way the stock traded last week,&quot; said the GDR salesman at the UK brokerage.</p>
<p>VSNL raised more than $500 million through an international equity issue late last month. The issue -- India's largest ever GDR offering and its first overseas equity issue this year -- was priced at $13.93 per GDR and traded just under $18 all of last week.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously prices have been marked down quite sharply,&quot; said Manoj Thakkar, subcontinent sales and dealing, at UBS Securities in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be a market completely driven by politics for the next few weeks with prices flying up and down on rumours,&quot; Thakkar said.</p>
<p>Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda has been given until April 11 to prove his majority in parliament, a near impossible task after his government lost the support of its key ally.</p>
<p>Thakkar said a sudden rally on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE) was unlikely to trigger buying in GDRs.</p>
<p>Bombay shares rebounded on Tuesday on news that the government was determined to approve the 1997/98 pro-business budget in parliament, despite the ongoing political crisis.</p>
<p>Bombay's benchmark stocks index was quoting 39.63 points, or 1.2 percent, higher at 3400.52 in afternoon trade.</p>
<p>The market was 2.3 percent higher at one stage, but a statement by the main opposition Bharatiya Janata Party that the budget would not be possible before the confidence vote curtailed the recovery.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
