<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479570" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: SBC completes Pacific Telesis merger.</title>
<headline>SBC completes Pacific Telesis merger.</headline>
<dateline>SAN ANTONIO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>SBC Communications Inc. said Tuesday it completed its $16.5 billion merger with Pacific Telesis Group.</p>
<p>The merger creates the nation's largest provider of local telephone services, with a territory that stretches from the Mississippi River to the Pacific Ocean and market value of $47.9 billion.</p>
<p>Its annual revenue of $23.5 billion ranks it among the top 30 publicly held U.S. corporations on the Fortune 500.</p>
<p>The closing of the merger followed Monday's approval of the deal by the California Public Utilities Commission, the last regulatory agency required to give its blessing, and subsequent votes by the two companies' boards of directors.</p>
<p>SBC agreed to the California regulators demand that it issue refunds totalling $341 million to California consumers over a five-year period beginning in 1998 to cover a portion of the short-term and long-term benefits of the merger.</p>
<p>&quot;Growth prospects for our business are outstanding,&quot;  said Edward Whitacre, SBC's chairman and chief executive officer.</p>
<p>&quot;Exploding demand for Internet access and high-speed data services, strong growth in wireless services, increased demand for basic wireline service and tremendous opportunities in long-distance and in markets outside the United States -- all point to an exciting future for the new SBC,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The merger of the two Baby Bell companies has met with stiff criticism from consumer groups and rival telephone companies, who argue that the combination of the two will slow the opening p of local exchange markets to competition.</p>
<p>&quot;There is little here for consumers to cheer about. A bigger monopoly is still a monopoly,&quot; said Rian Wren, AT&amp;T vice president for local services in the Southwest United States.</p>
<p>&quot;The real promise of the federal Telecommunications Act of 1996 is that consumers will have a choice in local phone service. This merger doesn't speed up anyone's ability to choose between local phone companies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The combined company, which will retain the name SBC Communications Inc. -- has nearly 110,000 employees, operating cash flow of nearly $10 billion, net income of more than $3 billion and a market value of over $47.9 billion.</p>
<p>The new SBC will provide 31 million access lines located largely in high-growth areas of the nation and reach more than 87 million potential wireless customers across the country.</p>
<p>SBC will serve the nation's most populous states -- California and Texas -- seven of the top 10 U.S. metropolitan markets and 16 of the top 50, and selected countries overseas, including Mexico, Chile, South Korea, Taiwan, France and South Africa. Other states it serves include Nevada, Oklahoma, Arkansas, Missouri and Kansas.</p>
<p>The $23 billion merger of Bell Atlantic Corp. and NYNEX Corp., which has been held up by anti-trust regulators, would surpass the value of the SBC-Pacific Telesis deal.</p>
<p>The combined Bell Atlantic would also become the largest local phone service provider by most basic measures.</p>
<p>&quot;This merger better positions SBC to be the telecommunications provider of choice at a time when all markets are opening to competition,&quot;  said Phil Quigley, PacTel's former chief executive and now SBC vice chairman.</p>
<p>While the corporate headquarters will be in San Antonio, the company will set up headquarters for its Internet, international, long distance and administration activities in California.</p>
<p>The merger involves an exchange of stock with current Pacific Telesis stockholders receiving SBC stock. Each Pacific Telesis shareowner will receive 0.73145 share of SBC for each share of Pacific Telesis they own.</p>
<p>After the merger, which qualifies as a tax-free exchange, SBC shareholders will have 64 percent of the combined company and Pacific Teleis holders the remaining 34 percent.</p>
<p>California's consumer-oriented utility commission had held up approval of the deal, demanding a series of concessions from the company, including rebates to the state's consumers, job growth guarantees and other requirements.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN ANTONIO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
