<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479509" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indianoil processes 25.1 mln t in 96/97.</title>
<headline>Indianoil processes 25.1 mln t in 96/97.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>State-run Indian Oil Corporation (Indianoil) said on Tuesday that its six refineries had processed 25.1 million tonnes of crude oil in fiscal 1996/97 (April-March).</p>
<p>It gave no comparative figure for the previous fiscal year.  </p>
<p>Indianoil's six refineries at Guwahati, Barauni, Gujarat, Haldia, Mathura and Digboi together processed 25.1 million tonnes in 1996/97, achieving 102.3 percent capacity utilisation in spite of lower crude oil supplies to Barauni, a comapny statement said.</p>
<p>It said in 1996/97 Indianoil sold 41.74 million tonnes of petroleum products, up from 39.85 million tonnes in the previous year.</p>
<p>During the year the company commissioned a state-of-the-art, 600,000-tonne liquified petroleum gas terminal at Kandla to augment product availability, the statement said.  </p>
<p>The statement said Indianoil was expected to complete projects valued at 100 billion rupees ($2.8 billion) during the next two years and had identified several new projects valued at 300 billion rupees.</p>
<p>Major projects likely to be completed during 1997/98 were the Panipat refinery in northern Haryana state and a catalytic reformer at Mathura in Uttar Pradesh state.</p>
<p>The company said during the next two years 25 LPG bottling plants would be set up in phases.</p>
<p>It said the proposed projects include a nine million tonnes grassroot refinery in collaboration with the Kuwait Petroleum Corporation at Paradeep on the east coast and an export-oriented refinery in southern India.  </p>
<p>Indianoil said it had entered into an understanding with Britain's Enterprise Oil to jointly develop oilfields.</p>
<p>The statement said its request for allocation of Bombay High offshore fields on nomination basis was awaiting government approval.</p>
<p>The company also intended to participate in deep water exploration projects of Oil and Natural Gas Corp (ONGC), it added.</p>
<p>--New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
