<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479644" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Atrix submits NDA for periodontal therapy.</title>
<headline>Atrix submits NDA for periodontal therapy.</headline>
<dateline>FORT COLLINS, Colo. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Atrix Laboratories Inc Tuesday said it submitted a New Drug Application to the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for marketing approval of its atridox drug product for the treatment of periodontal disease.</p>
<p>Periodontitis is a chronic and progressive condition affecting an estimated three out of four Americans over age 35.  </p>
<p>&quot;The atridox product represents an innovative, non-invasive approach to therapy that is faster, less painful and less costly than mechanical scaling and root planing, currently the standard treatment for periodontitis,&quot; said John Urheim, vice chairman and chief executive officer of Atrix.</p>
<p>&quot;Because it offers these important advantages without sacrificing therapeutic effectiveness, it is expected to capture a significant share of the periodontal treatment market in the years ahead.&quot;</p>
<p>He noted that the market for periodontal treatment currently totals $17 billion annually in the United States alone, and is likely to expand with the introduction of this innovative, less painful, localized antibiotic therapy.</p>
<p>Periodontal disease is an infection caused by a buildup of bacterial plaque, which leads to destruction of the soft tissue and bone that support the teeth.  Left untreated, the condition grows increasingly severe and is a major cause of tooth loss.</p>
<p>Pending regulatory approvals, the atridox product will be marketed in North America and certain European countries by Block Drug Co Inc, a major dental products company.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FORT COLLINS, Colo."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
