<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479675" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: John Alden to cut workforce by 725.</title>
<headline>John Alden to cut workforce by 725.</headline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>John Alden Financial Corp said it plans to cut its workforce by about 725 employees in 1997.</p>
<p>It said Monday it had made the decision after reviewing its operations in light of the sale of its annuity operations, a proposed sale of its credit business, and an anticipated group health premiums reduction.  </p>
<p>Among the job cuts, about 250 were in the discontinued annuity and credit operations, it said. Charges associated with these eliminations were part of a previously-announced $45 million net deferred gain.</p>
<p>The remaining 475 cuts represent about 20 percent of the full-time workforce of its continuing operations, the company said.</p>
<p>John Alden said it would take an after-tax charge of about $15 million in the first quarter related to continuing operations. It also said it would not fill an estimated 100 open jobs in these operations.  </p>
<p>John Alden, an insurance holding company, said its continuing operations include its group health business and Alden Risk Management Services.</p>
<p>&quot;Decisions like this are the most difficult to make but this is a necessary step in successfully positioning this company for the future,&quot; Chairman Glendon Johnson said.</p>
<p>&quot;While it will be challenging for us to reduce our expenses in line with the anticipated reduction in premium, we are committed to maintaining a competitive expense ratio on a long-term basis,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The company said it had closed the sale of its annuity business to SunAmerica Inc. The transaction included the sale of all common stock of John Alden Life Insurance Co of New York and the reinsurance of substantially all of the annuity business of John Alden Life Insurance Co.</p>
<p>((--New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
