<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479633" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Edison Brothers files reoganization plan details.</title>
<headline>Edison Brothers files reoganization plan details.</headline>
<dateline>ST. LOUIS, Mo. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Edison Brothers Stores Inc said Tuesday it filed its proposed disclosure statement with the U.S. Bankruptcy Court in Delaware, providing details regarding its plan of reorgnaization.</p>
<p>The plan includes a proposal that a combination of cash, new corporate debt, equity and other assets would be used to pay an estimated $0.92 on the dollar for its approximately $444 million in total unsecured claims.  </p>
<p>Edison Brothers also proposes warrants be distributed to its existing shareholders, entitling them to purchase 964,913 shares or about nine percent of new common stock of the reorganized company on a fully diluted basis.</p>
<p>Edison said the disclosure statement must be approved by the bankruptcy court after notice and a hearing.</p>
<p>If approved, the statement will be used to solicit acceptance of the plan, enabling the company to emerge from Chapter 11 bankruptcy reorganization.  If the process proceeded as expected, the company said it would emerge from Chapter 11 by mid-1997.  </p>
<p>Earlier, Edison Brothers, which sells apparel, footwear and accessories, reported a loss for the fourth quarter ended February 1 of $4.00 a share after $84.5 million in charges, compared with a year-ago loss of $4.83 a share after $97.8 million in charges.</p>
<p>&quot;Edison's fourth quarter 1996 operating results were an improvement over 1995, but they still reflect a company in the midst of a major restructuring effort,&quot; Alan Miller, chairman, said in a statement.  &quot;We are focused on continuing the sales momentum Edison gained at the end of 1996 and emerging from Chapter 11 this summer.&quot;</p>
<p>Edison previously reported same-store sales for the fourth quarter increased 0.6 percent.  Total sales for the quarter declined 21.8 percent to $308.2 million.  The company said the total sales decline was narrower than the 27.8 percent decrease in the average number of stores operated in the fourth quarter.</p>
<p>Edison said its cash position improved during 1996. The company had $204.1 million in cash and short-term investments at year-end, compared with $139.6 million as of February 3, 1996.</p>
<p>((Reuters Chicago Newsdesk (312) 408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ST. LOUIS, Mo."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
