<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479648" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Intl Alliance oks owner structure changes.</title>
<headline>Intl Alliance oks owner structure changes.</headline>
<dateline>CLEVELAND 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>International Alliance Services Inc (IASI) Tuesday said its board approved changes in its ownership structure.</p>
<p>Alliance Holding Corp, a major shareholder of IASI, plans to distribute its IASI common stock and warrants to its shareholders and certain debt holders of Alliance.</p>
<p>Under the terms of a lockup agreement covering such shares and warrants, the approval of IASI's board is required. The board of IASI granted its approval for the distribution subject to the condition that the shares and warrants remain subject to the lockup agreement.  </p>
<p>The distribution will require certain regulatory approvals that IASI expects to obtain. When the distribution is completed, most Alliance Holding Corp shares and warrants will be held directly or indirectly by the officers, management and key employees of IASI.</p>
<p>In addition, IASI's board acknowledged certain changes with respect to IASI shares now held by MGD Holdings Ltd. The board acknowledged the termination of the voting agreement between MGD Holdings and Alliance which will permit MGD and its successors to vote all IASI shares held by it. Further, the board acknowledged the proposed merger of MGD into Westbury (Bermuda) Ltd. As a result of this merger, Westbury will succeed to the shares of IASI held by MGD. Westbury and MGD are Bermuda companies controlled by Michael DeGroote, chairman of IASI.</p>
<p>The changes are expected to be consummated over the next several weeks. Following the consummation of these transactions, Westbury will be the largest stockholder of IASI, holding 14.2 million shares of the common and common share equivalents and businessman H. Wayne Huizenga will be the second largest stockholder holding 8.4 million common and common share equivalents outstanding.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CLEVELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
