<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479615" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Calif. regulators approve SBC, Telesis merger.</title>
<headline>Calif. regulators approve SBC, Telesis merger.</headline>
<byline>Adam Entous</byline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>California regulators Monday approved SBC Communications Inc.'s $17 billion merger with Pacific Telesis Group on condition that customers receive a $341 million refund.</p>
<p>The companies said they would review the decision and expected to make an announcement early on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The California Public Utilities Commission (CPUC) was the only regulatory body whose approval of the merger was still required. The Federal Communications Commission approved the merger plan earlier this year.</p>
<p>The California commission, which voted 4-1 for the merger, said its approval was conditional upon Pacific Telesis' Pacific Bell unit issuing the $341 million refund to customers over five years beginning in 1998 to reflect the short- and long-term economic benefits of the merger.</p>
<p>In present-value terms, the refund is worth about $248 million, half of the estimated economic benefits of the merger, the commission said.</p>
<p>California law requires the commission to share projected economic benefits of a merger between shareholders and ratepayers, with ratepayers receiving no less than half of the benefits.</p>
<p>The commission said the refund would be returned to Pacific Bell's customers through a rate reduction in their monthly bills for the next five years. The companies would also contribute funds to a program to improve telecommunications access for underserved communities.</p>
<p>SBC, the San Antonio, Texas-based parent of Southwestern Bell, and San Francisco-based Pacific Telesis plan to evaluate the commission's decision and decide whether to go through with the merger, a spokesman said.</p>
<p>CPUC officials who worked on the commission's final proposal said Monday they expected the companies to accept the final ruling.</p>
<p>The final CPUC decision was sharply lower than the $590.5 million refund over five years proposed by two administrative law judges, who make recommendations to the commission.</p>
<p>Another proposal before the CPUC called for Pacific Bell to refund $316 million in present value terms.</p>
<p>SBC and Pacific Telesis had urged the California commissioners to approve the merger without conditions, saying the benefits of the merger would flow to ratepayers in the form of lower prices for telecommunications services. They said the merger would also boost the California economy by creating new jobs.</p>
<p>At Monday's hearing, the commissioners touted the economic benefits of the proposed merger, saying the combination of the two companies would boost the economy and provide jobs.</p>
<p>&quot;This will afford California a significant opportunity,&quot; Commissioner Richard Bilas said. &quot;There will be many beneficiaries: the merged companies, the ratepayers, (and the) stockholders.&quot;</p>
<p>The commission said the merger was unlikely to hurt competition in California.</p>
<p>Consumer groups had called for refunds to customers of nearly $1 billion over five years. The groups blasted the CPUC decision after Monday's vote.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a very bad decision, a blow to competition, a blow to California's autonomy, and a decision that allows shareholders to pocket almost all of the huge cost savings from this merger,&quot; said attorney Thomas Long of the group TURN, The Utility Reform Network.</p>
<p>SBC and Pacific Telesis announced their merger plans last April. Shareholders from both companies approved the merger last summer.</p>
<p>The companies serve the nation's two most populous states -- California and Texas -- and seven of the nation's 10 largest metropolitan areas. Together, the two companies' 1996 revenues totaled $23.5 billion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
