<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479762" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: IPE Brent holds lower levels as U.S. seeks direction.</title>
<headline>IPE Brent holds lower levels as U.S. seeks direction.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>IPE Brent crude oil futures seesawed in a narrow range on Tuesday in reaction to a firmer but nervous NYMEX start that struggled to find direction, brokers said.</p>
<p>May Brent was at $19.13 a barrel at 1415 GMT, down 25 cents and in line with easier morning levels. June was 20 cents adrift at $19.28 a barrel.</p>
<p>May had touched a high of $19.22 before the NYMEX opening. But the contract retreated to a range of $19.10 to 19.20 while the New York market clung on to positive territory following a narrowly firmer opening supported by stronger heating oil.</p>
<p>&quot;Brent is struggling to break above $19.20. If it slides the other way below $19.00 we could see some fairly aggressive selling,&quot; a broker said.</p>
<p>&quot;NYMEX is moving in a fairly tight range despite its slight recovery. There are some signs of stability but no clear direction yet.&quot;</p>
<p>Dealers saw support for Brent at around $19.08/$19.09, followed by $18.90.</p>
<p>NYMEX heating oil was three cents firmer at 54.45 cents a gallon. May crude was $20.48 a barrel, seven cents higher.</p>
<p>April IPE gas oil was 25 cents easier at $166.50 a tonne.</p>
<p>Forecasts of colder U.S. weather were seen by some as slightly supportive to distillates.</p>
<p>Independent forecasters Weather Services Corp said on Tuesday they saw temperatures in the key market of the northeastern U.S. eight to 14 degrees below normal on Wednesday, but rising to slightly above normal on Friday.</p>
<p>Physical Brent looked weak. A cargo was traded on Monday at May Brent -96 cents, down from May -88 on Thursday.</p>
<p>Weekly U.S. inventory data was expected late on Tuesday and GNI said they expected crude, gasoline and distillate stocks all to be &quot;flat to a couple of million barrels lower.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
