<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479744" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Blair urges Britons to trust New Labour.</title>
<headline>Blair urges Britons to trust New Labour.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tony Blair on Tuesday urged the British people to put their trust in his revitalised Labour Party as he and Prime Minister John Major went out to meet the people ahead of the May 1 election.</p>
<p>On the first stop of a 60-town tour aimed at wooing crucial middle class voters, Blair sought to convince shoppers in the market town of Northampton that Labour had changed for the better after 18 years in opposition.</p>
<p>Speaking atop a new &quot;people's platform&quot; which unfolded from Labour's campaign tour bus, Blair told cheering crowds: &quot;Be strong, be of good courage, put your trust in us and we will repay that trust 1,000 times over in the years ahead.&quot;</p>
<p>The platform was intended to counter the battered wooden soapbox used by Prime Minister John Major to address crowds and sweep the Conservatives to a surprise fourth victory in 1992.</p>
<p>Both parties treated Tuesday as the start of their campaigns for the election. The first two weeks of electioneering has been low-key and dominated by allegations of &quot;sleaze&quot; in the ruling Conservative party.</p>
<p>Major is fighting an uphill battle against opinion polls, which show his party about 20 points behind Labour, and sex and money scandals within his Conservative Party. He told voters in suburban London he would like some light &quot;on the real issues&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The economy is booming,&quot; Major told shoppers in a Croydon DIY store. &quot;What we have to do is make sure nobody changes it.&quot;</p>
<p>Three Conservatives resigned their jobs last week over allegations of personal impropriety or involvement in a cash for questions row in parliament. Two more Conservative MPs are under under strong pressure to quit.</p>
<p>Major earlier backed Neil Hamilton, the MP at the centre of the sleaze storm, saying he should be allowed to stand at the election.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not going to bow to the witch-hunt mentality of saying that anyone who faces public charges must quit public life,&quot; Major told a news conference. Hamilton has denied accepting envelopes stuffed with cash from a businessman.</p>
<p>Major's campaign got a boost on Tuesday from former prime minister Margaret Thatcher, who launched a scathing attack on the &quot;boneless wonder&quot; of the revamped Labour Party.</p>
<p>In an article for the Daily Telegraph newspaper, Thatcher accused &quot;New Labour&quot; of turning its back on its beliefs to pander to pundits and pollsters. Blair has ditched much of Labour's socialist dogma and moved it to the centre of British politics.</p>
<p>&quot;The whole of Mr Blair's strategy in creating the boneless wonder that calls itself New Labour is to reassure the electorate in its illusion. But illusion it remains,&quot; wrote Thatcher.</p>
<p>Blair, bidding at 43 to become Britain's youngest prime minister this century, is keen to shake off the &quot;Phoney Tony&quot; label that has come with his slick management of New Labour.</p>
<p>He spoke on Tuesday of the reponsibility and humility he felt at being hot favourite for the premier's job.</p>
<p>&quot;It is in some ways quite a humbling experience because all those hopes and aspirations are with us,&quot; Blair told journalists.</p>
<p>The minority Liberal Democrats, who have almost been drowned out by the two main parties, urged an end to the knockabout politics of the past two weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;After the false start to the election campaign before Easter which saw Punch and Judy politics at its worst we would like both the other parties to join us in fighting honestly on the big issues,&quot; said Liberal Democrat leader Paddy Ashdown.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
