<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479765" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FUND VIEW-Invesco overweight in HK, Singapore.</title>
<headline>FUND VIEW-Invesco overweight in HK, Singapore.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gill</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fund manager Invesco said on Tuesday it was overweight in Hong Kong and Singapore as it focused on core equity markets amid uncertainty in the region.</p>
<p>Nigel Hale, executive regional director at Invesco based in Hong Kong, told Reuters that relatively cheap valuations and an obvious exposure to China were key reasons for its stance on Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;We are pretty upbeat on Hong Kong but we are not universally upbeat on the region,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At the end of February, Invesco was overweight in Hong Kong with a 28 percent weighting against a benchmark MSCI AC Pacific Free ex Japan index weighting of 23 percent.</p>
<p>Hale also said Invesco was slightly overweight in Singapore at 13 percent against 11.2 percent, but was neutral or underweight in other markets.</p>
<p>Singapore offered a haven in times of uncertainty with its solid economic fundamentals and good liquidity. &quot;It is a low risk market with a pretty stable policy. The economic fundamentals are just superb.&quot;</p>
<p>It would also benefit from a likely recovery in electronic components and finished goods prices.</p>
<p>&quot;The valuation of the market is looking quite good. It is on a prospective multiple for this year of under 20 times and a discount of around 15 percent to its long term average rating.&quot;</p>
<p>He was aggressively underweight in Taiwan and Thailand, with Taiwan looking extremely expensive having been driven sharply higher by liquidity rather than earnings growth in the past few months.</p>
<p>In Thailand, where Invesco has been significantly underweight at two percent against a benchmark four percent, he said some very selective situations were likely to appear in the next three months.</p>
<p>&quot;We have got an amber light flashing to warn us that we are approaching the time when we need to be putting our toe back into the water there.&quot;</p>
<p>In Korea, an aggressively underweight stance had been changed to neutral with much of the bad news, including labour unrest and a collapse in earnings, likely to be out of the way.</p>
<p>Korea's market is on a valuation of about 12 times 1997 earnings against almost forty times earnings five years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;This is at a cyclical low as well so there is double upside potential as earnings start to recover and the market gets rerated,&quot; Hale said.</p>
<p>Amid high U.S. stock valuations, Hale said there would be a growing trend by funds to invest in markets in Europe and Asia over the medium to long term.</p>
<p>Investors would look to economies at the bottom of their growth cycles where earnings growth was likely to accelerate and where valuations were more attractive than in the U.S.</p>
<p>&quot;There are many of those markets in Asia and there are also some of those markets in Europe and we see a net cash outflow from the U.S. into a number of these markets over the next 18 months or so.&quot;</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +171 542 5887</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
