<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479715" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Aasche cites one-time charges.</title>
<headline>Aasche cites one-time charges.</headline>
<dateline>SHANNON, Ill. 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Aasche Transportation Services Inc said its 1996 results were  hurt by several non-recurring one-time charges that totaled $1.9 million after taxes or $0.48 per share.</p>
<p>For the full year, it posted a loss of $0.67 per share compared to a 1995 loss of $0.34 per share.</p>
<p>The charge related to a writedown of Polar Express equipment, a Polar restructuring charge and a Polar litigation settlement.  </p>
<p>&quot;In addition, we wrote down the value of our equipment to better reflect the current used equipment market,&quot; said chief financial officer Leon Monachos in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe these writedowns should be sufficient to avoid any additional equipment writedowns in 1997,&quot; he added. &quot;We further believe we have taken the last of our non-operating writedowns associated with the Polar Express acquisition,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In a direct effort to address driver shortage problems, operating inefficiencies, asset utilization concerns and equipment debt issues that have plagued Polar Express over the course of 1996, the company entered into a purchase agreement to sell 68 Polar tractors and 141 Polar trailers for $4.6 million. The transaction is expected to generate $1.4 million in net cash proceeds to the company with no significant earnings effect expected in 1997.</p>
<p>Although the loss from the sale in connection with the writedown of Polar equipment to net realizable value was recorded in 1996, the transaction was completed on March 25, 1997.</p>
<p>For the year, Aasche posted a loss of $0.67 per share.</p>
<p>		((Reuters Chicago Newsdesk (312) 408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANNON, Ill."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
