<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479731" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: EMU MINOR ISSUE FOR FINNISH FOREST INDUSTRY - STUDY.</title>
<headline>EMU MINOR ISSUE FOR FINNISH FOREST INDUSTRY - STUDY.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Finland's decision for or against membership of European economic and monetary union will have a relatively minor long-term impact on the Finnish forest industry, economists said in a study published on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Although Finland's EMU decision will have many effects on the sector, its significance will be relatively minor alongside the other factors affecting the long-term development of the forest industry and forestry,&quot; the experts said.</p>
<p>The study was one of 15 in an interim report published on Tuesday by a government-appointed panel of experts investigating the pros and cons of possible Finnish membership of EMU.</p>
<p>&quot;From the point of view of the competitiveness of the Finnish forest industry, the significance of EMU is relatively small,&quot; wrote the authors of the report, from the Finnish Forest Research Institute (METLA).</p>
<p>Finland's decision whether to join the European single currency bloc, scheduled for start-up in January 1999, would have no effect on world demand for forest industry products, they said.</p>
<p>Sweden's decision on EMU would not be of major importance to the competitiveness of the Finnish forest industry, except for possible cyclical effects in the sawmill sector.</p>
<p>The report drew the following main conclusions:</p>
<p>* EMU membership would have no crucial impact on the regional structure of forest industry exports; regardless of EMU membership, an ever larger share of Finnish paper industry exports will go to non-EU areas with fast consumption growth.</p>
<p>* EMU is unlikely to have any effect on cyclical price fluctuations; prices of forest products have fluctuated more sharply in terms of EU currencies than in markka, and so the shift to the euro is unlikely to dampen cyclical swings.</p>
<p>* The balancing effect of exchange rates on the forest industry's profitability fluctuations would cease with EMU membership.</p>
<p>* EMU membership would weaken the Finnish forest industry's chances of competiting for market share, but would have little magnifying effect on profitability fluctuations.</p>
<p>* The single currency is seen making it easier for the forest industry to obtain debt financing and equity financing; the elimination of risk premiums in EMU would also reduce financing costs.</p>
<p>* With the onset of EMU, it will become more important for forest industry firms to secure stable and adequate financing without debt in order for companies to be able to surive weak profitabilty years, regardless of whether Finland joins.</p>
<p>* EMU membership would reduce the costs of borrowed capital via the reduced risks of creditors and it would remove the rate risks of Eurobonds and create more opportunity to seek competitive offers for financing across Europe.</p>
<p>* With Finland outside EMU, the forest industry's foreign-denominated exchange rate risks of loan capital would remain, with the risks accentuated by the fact that domestic inputs would be markka-denominated.</p>
<p>* The forest industry will have an even greater need for flexibility in wage costs (17 percent of total costs) than in raw wood costs (13 percent).</p>
<p>* EMU will add pressures for more even pricing of electricity between countries, which would likely mean slightly higher electricity prices in Finland and weaken the relative profitability of mechanical pulp versus chemical pulp. This trend can be expected regardless of whether Finland joins EMU.</p>
<p>* If companies see Finland encountering substantial adjustment problems in wages and other inputs, this must be seen as a negative effect of EMU from the point of view of industry's location in Finland; the common currency and the inflexibility of input costs would increase the risk of investment in Finland.</p>
<p>* If Sweden opts out of EMU, the Swedish crown -- which now accounts for over half of invoicing of sawn goods in Europe -- may retain its position as a pricing currency, possibly causing short-term adjustment difficulties for Finnish saw mills.</p>
<p>* If Sweden were to stay outside EMU and Finland were to join, the Finnish forest industry could enjoy a relative advantage in the form of lower capital costs and higher economic policy credibility, lower protectionism and lower costs of hedging against forex risks.</p>
<p>* On the image level, the forest industry evidently sees it as a bigger risk to remain outside EMU than to join, and so it would be easier in the future to invest in Finland as an EMU-member than as a non-member.</p>
<p>* Changes in markka exchange rates cannot be expected to solve the forest industry's problems.</p>
<p>--Helsinki Newsroom +358-9-680 50 235</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I46000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
