<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479791" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Funds wary after Dow dive, no meltdown seen.</title>
<headline>Funds wary after Dow dive, no meltdown seen.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gill</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A dive in U.S. stocks over the Easter weekend has raised concerns about a larger equity market reversal, but analysts said on Tuesday they were not recommending a major shift in portfolio strategy.</p>
<p>Many big funds have already moved large amounts out of the U.S. market in anticipation of a U.S. correction, picking up equities in other countries and more recently bonds.</p>
<p>But they say that global asset allocation strategies are still geared towards only a mild decline on Wall Street.</p>
<p>The Dow has fallen some 4.3 percent since Thursday, sparking losses in Europe and Asia on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Recent fund shifts have been into markets with a relatively high correlation with the U.S.. They are likely to offer minimised risk under the scenario of a mild Dow correction, but would most likely slide with the U.S. if prices there fell significantly.</p>
<p>Neil Honebon, head of global research at Flemings Investment Management, said if U.S. did not fall steeply, then acceptable returns could be achieved in markets with a relatively high U.S. correlation.</p>
<p>&quot;The idea of taking money from the U.S. into the Pacific and Latin America is crucially dependent on the argument that what will happen in the U.S. will not be a big event and therefore those high correlations will not hold,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Analysts said U.S. mutual fund inflows, a driving factor behind recent steep U.S. gains, would be the key to determining the extent of the fall.</p>
<p>A major slowdown, or reversal of those inflows into equities could spark a change in strategy, with bond market yields above seven percent attracting increased interest from concerned investors.</p>
<p>Already, inflows have slowed to aggressive growth funds, with a move into more conservative stock mutual funds and money market funds.</p>
<p>More earnings downgrades, and a possible shift within U.S. funds into bonds, would also be key factors, they said. But the U.S. market was likely to avoid a major setback.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it is a major reassessment of the U.S. outlook. We expected a set-back and now it's trickling through to Europe,&quot; Yamaichi international economist John Shepherd said.</p>
<p>He said the increase in U.S interest rates did not have far to go, and with a modest growth and low inflation outlook in the U.S. a disaster scenario was not expected.</p>
<p>Honebon said some shifts into bonds had been made, but price movements were likely to be limited.</p>
<p>&quot;We see the (equity) deterioration on a relatively shallow gradient, and the interest rate response will also be shallow.&quot;</p>
<p>He said bond yields above seven percent were clearly offering a lot more competition for fund flows. &quot;I don't think there is much doubt we will see a smaller proportion will go to equities in general.&quot;</p>
<p>BZW global market strategist Michael Hughes said it was difficult to have big bets in the markets currently, with insufficient evidence to justify holding big positions.</p>
<p>He said the degree of interest rate risk in the U.S., the uncertain European growth outlook, and emerging market uncertainty following recent gains, were all hampering allocation strategy.</p>
<p>He would not rush back into U.S. stocks at current levels, he said, especially with the relative attraction of bond yields at over seven percent. But the Dow at under 6,400 was likely to look more interesting.</p>
<p>Nigel Hale, Hong Kong-based executive regional director of Invesco, said the fact that fears of slower U.S. corporate earnings and expected interest rate increases had coincided had surprised many market players, and left valuations looking relatively expensive.</p>
<p>Analysts said on Tuesday they had not yet changed their forecasts for markets following the Dow decline.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +171 542 5887</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
