<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479727" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: EMU NOT OPTIMAL CURRENCY AREA FOR FINLAND - REPORT.</title>
<headline>EMU NOT OPTIMAL CURRENCY AREA FOR FINLAND - REPORT.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The countries of central Europe expected to be among the first to join the third phase of European economic and monetary union would not create an optimal currency area for Finland, Nordic economists said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Three studies, all part of an interim report by an expert group appointed by Prime Minister Paavo Lipponen to examine the pros and cons of Finnish EMU membership, by economists from Finland and Sweden saw risks for Finland in EMU, especially if Sweden did not join.</p>
<p>Some central points in the three studies:</p>
<p>* The group of countries believed to be part of the first phase of a future EMU, as well as the entire EU, does not constitute an &quot;optimal&quot; currency area for Finland.</p>
<p>* The central European countries are better suited to be founders of a single currency area.</p>
<p>* The cyclical fluctuations of the Finnish economy have differed considerably from fluctuations in major West European economies. The Finnish business sector structure also differs quite much from that in core-European countries.</p>
<p>* Differences between EMU member countries will remain also after the euro has been taken into use.</p>
<p>* Differences due to structural and institutional factors in particular will be fading only slowly.</p>
<p>* If Sweden and Finland joined EMU the efficiency benefits for Finland would increase since Sweden is among Finland's most important trading partners, but all benefits would not disappear even if Sweden remained outside.</p>
<p>* It would be important to safeguard the competitiveness of Finnish exports if Finland were in EMU and Sweden outside, and make sure Sweden could not get a temporary advantage by letting its currency weaken.</p>
<p>* An unfavourable trend in terms of trade, especially if Finland were in EMU and Sweden outside, could cause problems if the exchange rate of the euro proved inflexible.</p>
<p>* That potential problem would be partly alleviated by the fact that the traditional importance of the current account would cease and so give Finland more time to adjust to weaker terms of trade. Sweden, which could let its exchange rate weaken and run the risk of higher interest rates, would have less time to adjust.</p>
<p>* Sweden's EMU decision is one factor, but not the only one, affecting Finland's position as a member of the single currency bloc. The same would apply if Finland opted to remain outside while Sweden joined EMU.</p>
<p>* The economies of Finland and Sweden are quite similar compared to many other EU countries which underlines the importance for Finland and Sweden to conduct a similar exchange rate policy; either both inside EMU or both outside EMU, or that the two create their own currency union.</p>
<p>--Helsinki newsroom +358-9-680 50 245, e-mail news@reuters.fi</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
