<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479758" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: London Freight market difficult to gauge, trade low.</title>
<headline>London Freight market difficult to gauge, trade low.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brokers reported difficulty in assessing the freight market after the Easter break as very little news emerged about capers. Some noted good volume still unfixed, but there appeared to be widespread mild pessimism about Panamax prospects. Reported fixtures of modern types were generally a little softer, especially for round voyages in the Far East but many brokers felt it was premature to form an opinion of likely trends for April and May. The BFI fell 7 points to 1,507.</p>
<p>In a quiet handy market rates seemed to be generally unchanged. The Baltic Handy index slipped 2 points to 1,107.</p>
<p>Grain - European maritime carriers were reported to have booked Fareast Victory 70,003 dwt delivery US Gulf 7/15 April to cover their US gulf/Japan heavy grain stem at $15,000 daily plus $295,000 daily bonus. This compares with Pan Ocean's fixture at the end of last week of Atlantic Princess 73,565 dwt delivery early April for similar business at $15,250 daily plus $285,000 bonus.</p>
<p>Few grain fixtures were reported from Argentina and Brazil. Cabral were firm to over-age panamax tonnage for Paranagua/France at $17.50. There were rumours that Cargill fixed 20,000 wheat Plate/Tunisia for 3/10 April on private terms and that Comshipco booked a vessel for 20,000 pellets 54' Sao Francisco do Sul/Brake for 10/25 April.</p>
<p>Other handy-size grain reports suggested Blue Deck covered 20,000/10 wheat US gulf/Egypt on timecharter, and Sometra fixed the 1970-built Alkmini 26,739 dwt delivery northern France trip W Africa at $6,000 daily. In the far east Irisl were said to have taken an over-age 64,000 dwt vessel delivery S Korea first half April trip via Australia and Iran redelivery Muscat at $10,750 daily. These charterers were understood to be willing to repeat the business.</p>
<p>Other fresh orders included Contintal/Finagrain with 54,000 heavy grain US Gulf/Japan for any 10 days 1/25 April (alternatively Nopac/Japan 21 April/10 May), 1.9/2.2m cft US Gulf/E Med including Israel 7/14 April and 900,000 cft grain Nopac/Japan 19/24 April, Glencore 50,000 wheat Dunkirk/Aqaba 10/14 April, Tradigrain 25,000/10 heavy grain US Gulf/N Spain 10/25 April, and Lorico 20/28,000 corn US Gulf or Atlantic/Algeria 15/30 April.</p>
<p>MINERALS - Market rumours suggested Cobelfret fixed Mega Hill 118,712 dwt for co Richards Bay/Continent at about $7.00/7.25 and that Ostrako 127,907 dwt had been fixed privately for a Transatatlantic round. Anthia 81,796 dwt open continent was also fixed on private terms (by Kingston Maritime), and K Line booked Joyous Society 69,274 dwt on subjects delivery Santander early April trip via Narvik redelivery Cigading at $16,000 daily, option further trip Indonesia/Japan at $13,000 daily.</p>
<p>Tokai was said to have taken a 1989-built 69,000 dwt vessel delivery Hongkong trip v Indonesia redelivery Japan at $13,000 daily. In the far east Orange Phoenix 69,561 dwt was also fixed on subjects by K Line, delivery prompt Kakogawa trip via Port Kembla redelivery Taiwan at $11,800 daily. Samsun was to have fixed the 1980-built Ikan Beliak 64,957 dwt delivery far east mid-April for 5-7 months at $11,000 daily.</p>
<p>Handy-sizes  - in the Atlantic Safmarine fixed a 38,000 dwt bulker delivery Us Gulf trip S Africa at $10,500 daily plus $70,000 bonus, and Van Ommeren continued Taxiaharis p 39,013 dwt delivery prompt continent trip Boston-Galveston range at $8,000 daily. In the East Pan Ocean wase reported to have taken Sulu Warrior 33,000 dwt delivery prompt S Korea trip Vancouver-Manzanillo range at $6,300 daily.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
