<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479725" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: EMU WILL NOT SOLVE FINNISH JOBLESS PROBLEM -STUDY.</title>
<headline>EMU WILL NOT SOLVE FINNISH JOBLESS PROBLEM -STUDY.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Neither joining European economic and monetary union (EMU) nor opting out of the single currency bloc will solve Finland's unemployment problem, an economist said in a study published on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Unemployment will be a significant problem affecting the economy in EMU as well as outside of it,&quot; economics professor Jaakko Pehkonen said in the report. &quot;(Joining) EMU or staying out of it is not a solution to the current unemployment problem,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The study was one of 15 interim reports published on Tuesday by a government-appointed working group weighing the pros and cons of Finnish possible membership of EMU.</p>
<p>Following are some of the main points in Pehkonen's study:</p>
<p>* On the one hand EMU is an opportunity for faster and more stable economic growth, and therefore it can be a key to a faster improvement in employment.</p>
<p>* On the other hand, EMU is a risk because it will remove the possibility of using exchange rates to reduce the domestic cost level, and it will put more responsibility for employment and competitiveness on the labour market.</p>
<p>* It remains unclear how well the labour market will be able to meet the challenges of EMU and how monetary union will change the economic operating environment.</p>
<p>* In normal conditions, EMU would probably stabilise the labour markets; this would reduce both cyclical unemployment and structural unemployment.</p>
<p>* In crisis situations, EMU could make it difficult for the economy to find equilibrium. The slow adjustment of the labour market and unpredictable external disturbance factors could be a threat to stable employment in the early phase of EMU.</p>
<p>* That threat would recede if economic structures in the euro area became more uniform and the flexibility of national labour markets increased.</p>
<p>* Opting out of EMU would be a risk. Outside EMU, Finnish real interest rates could exceed the European level and uncertainty about interest rate fluctuations and exchange rates could create extra costs for Finnish companies.</p>
<p>* Staying outside EMU would weaken the credibility of the low inflation policy; this would probably mean that the sacrifices already made to qualify for EMU would fail to produce much of the expected benefits.</p>
<p>Another of the interim report's studies on the effects of EMU on Finland's labour market found that Finland would need to further reduce its inflation rate as wage increases have been a significant component of the &quot;traditional inflation-devaluation spiral.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;This need for adjustment lies ahead both in EMU and outside of it,&quot; economists Erkki Koskela and Juhana Vartiainen said in their study.</p>
<p>EMU membership would affect the speed at which inflation expectations adapt to the new situation and partly determine the seriousness of possible failure to adapt, they said.</p>
<p>The adjustment to EMU would be a historically important transition involving adjustment problems that could prove long-lasting, the economists said.</p>
<p>By international comparison, Finland is characterised by average real wage rigidity and high rigidity of nominal wages and prices, Koskela and Vartiainen said.</p>
<p>&quot;This means that the loss of independent monetary and exchange rate policy could in Finland's case potentially mean a weakening of the economy's ability to adjust,&quot; they said.</p>
<p>Assessing the need for wage adjustment, they found that -- within EMU -- reducing wage costs could be an alternative means of economic adjustment replacing the earlier possibility of adjusting exchange rates.</p>
<p>&quot;In the event of the worst, exceptional disturbances, the lowering of nominal wages should not be ruled out,&quot; Koskela and Vartiainen said, adding that such serious disturbances were however unlikely.</p>
<p>In monetary union, the profitability of export industries would face bigger fluctuations than now, as such swings could no longer be offset by devaluation, they said.</p>
<p>--Helsinki Newsroom +358-9-680 50 235</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
