<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479740" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Euro stocks sag under weight of Wall Street.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Euro stocks sag under weight of Wall Street.</headline>
<byline>Malcolm Davidson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stock markets plunged across Europe on Tuesday as investors wiped billions of dollars off share values following two days of heavy losses on Wall Street and fears that the long bull run had run its course.</p>
<p>The London, Paris and Frankfurt bourses all tumbled.</p>
<p>German stocks suffered one of their biggest one-day falls during bourse floor trade, while more than 19 billion pounds ($31 billion) was wiped off London's blue-chip FTSE 100 index at one point.</p>
<p>Wall Street was to blame for the bloodletting, having lost 157 points on Monday, when many other markets were closed for Easter, on top of its 140-point tumble on Thursday.</p>
<p>Europe edged back from its worst levels before Wall Street opened on Tuesday. The Dow Jones industrial average fell around 30 points immediately after reopening before recovering.</p>
<p>New York analysts had predicted that the Dow would rally at the start but said the market still had some way to go before the correction was over.</p>
<p>They said investors would scrutinise the National Association of Purchasing Management (NAPM) index due at 1500 GMT for signs whether U.S. interest rates were likely to rise again.</p>
<p>&quot;Is the big correction people have been warning about finally here? This could certainly be the start of it. The mood is very nervous,&quot; one London dealer said.</p>
<p>European bond markets fell with shares, dragged down by gloom in global bond markets, while the dollar weakened as traders returned to their desks in nervous mood after the falls in U.S. asset markets.</p>
<p>Some of Europe's smaller equity markets suffered even worse than the big bourses, with Amsterdam and Stockholm sliding more than four percent. In Asia, Tokyo fell only 0.74 percent but Hong Kong's Hang Seng index dropped 3.67 percent.</p>
<p>By mid-afternoon in Europe, most markets had struggled off their lows and were anxiously awaiting the NAPM index.</p>
<p>If the survey turned out stronger than expected, dealers said Wall Street could suffer further losses as concerns mount about the interest rate outlook.</p>
<p>Further out, the main focus of a potentially torrid weak was on U.S. non-farm payrolls data for March that will come out on Friday.</p>
<p>Despite the gloom, London dealers said they detected some support from the hope that Europe was decoupling from the U.S. market.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not going to escape the danger today but over the last few weeks the U.S. has struggled while European markets have held up reasonably well,&quot; said Roger Monson, strategist at Daiwa Europe in London. &quot;I think some of that divergence in performance will be restored after this sell-off.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders in Germany were not so sanguine after seeing the DAX index lose 3.88 percent of its value in floor trade and close at 3,295.93.</p>
<p>&quot;This has certainly been a very dramatic correction,&quot; said Bank Julius Baer chief economist Gerhard Grebe. &quot;Fundamentals apart, it shows the German market cannot decouple from the U.S. when things happen at this kind of speed.&quot;</p>
<p>Losses were spread across the board, with few blue chip stocks escaping the downward trend. Deutsche Bank AG, a solid performer in recent weeks, fell 4.45 marks ($2.66) to 89.45 marks.</p>
<p>Daimler-Benz AG dropped 6.50 marks to 126.90 marks while utility Veba fell 5.65 marks to 88.80 marks.</p>
<p>By 1415 GMT London's blue chip FTSE 100 index was down 1.97 percent at 4,228 points, having earlier plumbed 4,200.</p>
<p>&quot;The market seems to have found a level where we're finding some selective buyers,&quot; said one senior market maker. &quot;But liquidity is down from even last week's levels.&quot;</p>
<p>Bargain hunters, he added, were targeting the financial sector, as well as the historically defensive food and utility sectors.</p>
<p>Paris was down more than three percent but, like markets elswhere, the French bourse crawled off its lows.</p>
<p>Brokers said that there had been no panic selling and fund managers were waiting to see which way Wall Street jumped.</p>
<p>Alcatel Alsthom was down 1.77 percent at 666 francs. ITT said on Monday it sold its remaining 4.5 million shares in Alcatel Alsthom for approximately $530 million to an unnamed U.S. institutional investor.</p>
<p>The dollar softened in nervousness over the Dow's fall, which seemed unlikely to be changed much by the NAPM index.</p>
<p>Dealers said reasons for recent dollar weakness include disappointment at its inability to make new highs after last Tuesday's U.S. rate hike and concern over a repeat of 1994, when monetary tightening led to a slide in U.S. asset markets and a weaker dollar.</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 1415 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar was at 1.6682 marks and 123.46 yen, compared with 1.6763 and 123.48 in late European trade before the holiday on Thursday.</p>
<p>STOCK MARKETS AT 1415 GMT</p>
<p>LONDON - The FTSE-100 index was down 84.9 points, or 1.97 percent, at 4,228.0.</p>
<p>PARIS - The CAC-40 was down 80.91 points, or 3.05 percent, at 2,575.77.</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - The 30-share DAX index closed floor trade  down 133.12 points, or 3.88 percent, at 3,295.93. In later screen trade, the IBIS DAX index was down 131.24 points, or 3.85 percent, at 3,276.59.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold fixed little changed at $350.00 an ounce, versus $349.85 in the morning. Silver bounced off $5.00 support but was still eight cents down at $5.05.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
