<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479793" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: EMU delay could tip vulnerable US economy-analysts.</title>
<headline>EMU delay could tip vulnerable US economy-analysts.</headline>
<byline>Jennifer Scott</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-03-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Speculation about a delay to Europe's planned single currency may seem a distant rumble to the mighty U.S. economy now, but in just over a year's time it could sound a serious threat, some economists say.</p>
<p>A delay to monetary union would throw European economies into disarray, damage U.S. exports and potentially tip an already vulnerable U.S. economy over the edge.</p>
<p>&quot;If there were a chaotic postponement to EMU...it would be particularly awkwardly timed as far as the U.S. is concerned,&quot; said Alistair Barr, research fellow at the London Business School's centre for economic forecasting.</p>
<p>Talk of a delay to European economic and monetary union (EMU), the plan under which a single euro currency is to start in 1999, has captivated European markets since early this year.</p>
<p>But the subject has earned just a cursory glance in the U.S.</p>
<p>&quot;If it becomes apparent in 1998 that EMU is not going ahead, there would be a deal of turbulence in Europe such as rising long term interest rates,&quot; Barr said.</p>
<p>&quot;That would potentially have a knock-on effect on European growth at the same time the U.S. is vulnerable to a slow-down, so it would exacerbate the risks.&quot;</p>
<p>If the process runs wildly off course during 1998 and a muddled and woolly postponement occurs, global capital flows and shifting interest rates mean the U.S. will have to sit up and take notice, economists say. Barr predicts growth of 2.5 percent in the U.S. in 1997 and 2.0 percent in 1998 -- assuming EMU goes according to plan. He expects German and French growth in 1998 around 2.5 percent.</p>
<p>Research into the macroeconomic effects of EMU is not confined to academic circles. Commercial bank economists too are following every twist and turn in the single currency saga.</p>
<p>IBJ chief economist Stephen Hannah said the degree of fallout from a delay to the single currency project would depend on the nature of the postponement.</p>
<p>&quot;If it's just a technical issue with no more than a six month wait, then real economic behaviour would not be affected by rising long term rates...as they would be seen as just temporary,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But if the delay is more permanent with no guaranteed start date announced, then you could be looking, at least initially, at some negative effects.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the medium term impact would be more mixed depending on the extent of private sector corporate retrenchment.</p>
<p>&quot;In terms of the U.S., by 1998/99 they will be at a much later stage of the economic cycle,...so any disturbances in one of its major export markets...would accelerate its growth demise,&quot; Hannah said.</p>
<p>But as usual, the economic story is not so simple. The process would be labyrinthine, with more than one impact on the U.S.</p>
<p>An EMU delay may trigger a rush to buy German marks, leaving a weaker dollar and helping the U.S. export sector, which would offset some of the negative effects of shrinking markets.</p>
<p>&quot;But the exchange rate effect is not that clear-cut,&quot; said Hannah. &quot;A situation that threatens the European political establishment and the rational implementation of the single market project, may leave a European economy more fragmented and antagonistic than before.&quot;</p>
<p>This then could prompt a flight to dollars, undoing the boost to the export sector, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;So I would tend to take the view the U.S. (economy) would get more of a negative than positive effect from the change.&quot;</p>
<p>An indefinite delay could also allow European governments to relax fiscal policies -- which they had been tightening to meet EMU criteria. This would mean long-term interest rates in Europe would rise to reflect increased inflation risks, say economists.</p>
<p>Also, the possible rush to buy  marks would leave Germany to contend with a strong currency and the resulting negative effects on exports.</p>
<p>&quot;In Germany, the stronger mark wouldn't help the export sector and would have a dampening effect on economic growth,&quot; said Nomura International chief economist Bronwyn Curtis.</p>
<p>Other European countries may have the opposite problem. Weaker currencies would encourage exports, but may demand higher interest rates as authorities seek to deter currency speculators.</p>
<p>&quot;Softer currencies may help growth but would balloon out the budget side, particularly in a country like Italy where so much debt is funded off the shorter term,&quot; said Curtis.</p>
<p>-- International Bonds Unit +44 171 542 8682</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
