<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479763" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FORECAST -UK consumer credit to bounce back in Feb.</title>
<headline>FORECAST -UK consumer credit to bounce back in Feb.</headline>
<byline>Rosemary Bennett</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>British consumers had a busy February judging by the strong retail sales figures which suggest consumer credit will bounce back smartly in the month after January's lull, analysts said.</p>
<p>The Reuters consensus forecast suggests consumer credit rose 1.029 billion pounds in February compared with 853 million in January and 983 million in December. The Bank of England will release the data on Wednesday at 0830 GMT.</p>
<p>Robust figures released by the British Bankers' Association covering February suggested higher retail spending was financed by credit.</p>
<p>It said consumer credit rose by a record 626 million pounds, almost 50 percent above the the recent monthly average.</p>
<p>Jonathan Loynes said the BBA data and breakdown of retail sales both point to strong consumer credit in the month.</p>
<p>&quot;The BBA measure of card borrowing rebounded sharply in February, and the monthly rise in household goods and car sales both point to fairly robust non-card lending.&quot;</p>
<p>February retail sales data showed overall sales up 0.4 percent on the month with clothing and footwear up 1.5 percent and household goods up 0.8 percent.</p>
<p>Domestic demand has grown strongly in the last year, and credit data has shown that while borrowing is not racing ahead, it is robust.</p>
<p>&quot;The figures confirm that consumers' appetite for borrowing remains very healthy,&quot; said Loynes.</p>
<p>But other data due for release by the Bank on Wednesday are likely to show mortgage lending starting to slow.</p>
<p>&quot;Both the building societies and major retail banks reported a slight dip in mortgage loans in February, and we expect this to be confirmed in the overall figures,&quot; said Michael Saunders, UK economist at Salomon Brothers.</p>
<p>Figures for narrow money supply growth in March are also due. The Reuter poll forecasts a rise of 0.3 percent in the month for year-on-year growth of 6.4 percent, unchanged from February.</p>
<p>&quot;Excluding erratic movements on bankers' balances, there is evidence of a slowing down in the growth of notes and coins,&quot; said David Walton, UK economist at Goldman Sachs.</p>
<p>&quot;But it remains too strong for comfort.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the strength of monetary growth, adds to mounting evidence from the labour market and services sector that the economy may be overheating.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7715</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
