<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479749" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK leaders try to steer agenda away from sleaze.</title>
<headline>UK leaders try to steer agenda away from sleaze.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's political leaders took to their &quot;battle buses&quot; on Tuesday, vowing to move their campaigns for the May 1 election away from sleaze and back to bread and butter policies such as education and the economy.</p>
<p>Opposition leader Tony Blair set off on a pre-election tour that will take him to 60 towns and cities in a bid to woo crucial middle-class floating voters. Both parties are due to unveil their manifestoes this week.</p>
<p>&quot;Judge our policies on what they are, not on what the Tories (Conservatives) say they are. Our policies are mainstream, costed, sensible, better for Britain,&quot; Blair told a news conference before boarding his bus.</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Major, trailing Labour by 20 points in opinion polls, set off for north London eager to shake off the sex and money scandals in his Conservative Party that have dominated the first two weeks of Britain's longest election campaign.</p>
<p>Three Conservatives resigned their jobs last week over allegations of personal impropriety or involvement in a cash for questions row in parliament. Two more Conservative MPs are under under strong pressure to quit.</p>
<p>Labour has made great political capital out of the sleaze issue, saying it underlined the need for a change in British politics and the fact Conservatives had been warped by holding power for so long.</p>
<p>Major backed Neil Hamilton, the MP at the centre of the sleaze storm, saying he should be allowed to stand at the election. &quot;I am not going to bow to the witch-hunt mentality of saying that anyone who faces public charges must quit public life,&quot; Major told a news conference. Hamilton has denied accepting envelopes stuffed with cash from a businessman.</p>
<p>Major is credited with having turned around Conservative fortunes in the 1992 election campaign when he began giving impromptu speeches in Britain's streets from a battered soapbox.</p>
<p>Blair plans to match Major's soapbox by making speeches from a &quot;people's platform&quot; attached to his campaign bus.</p>
<p>Major's campaign got a boost on Tuesday from former prime minister Margaret Thatcher, who launched a scathing attack on the &quot;boneless wonder&quot; of the revamped Labour Party.</p>
<p>Blair, bidding to become Britain's youngest prime minister this century, has ditched much of Labour's socialist dogma in a move to the centre that has drawn praise from Thatcher.</p>
<p>But in an article for the Daily Telegraph newspaper, Thatcher accused &quot;New Labour&quot; of turning its back on its beliefs to pander to pundits and pollsters.</p>
<p>&quot;The whole of Mr Blair's strategy in creating the boneless wonder that calls itself New Labour is to reassure the electorate in its illusion. But illusion it remains,&quot; wrote Thatcher. Major kept up the attack, branding Labour's strategy a &quot;sham, con trick, and a fraud&quot;.</p>
<p>The Conservatives, he said, would spread opportunity and prosperity to every home in the country and stand up for Britain's national interests in Europe.</p>
<p>The minority Liberal Democrats, who have almost been drowned out by the two main parties, urged an end to the knockabout politics of the past two weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;After the false start to the election campaign before Easter which saw Punch and Judy politics at its worst we would like both the other parties to join us in fighting honestly on the big issues,&quot; said Liberal Democrat leader Paddy Ashdown.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
