<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479750" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - Evening Standard - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Evening Standard - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>PUNCH-UP FOR THE PRINCESS</p>
<p>Princess Diana has become embroiled in a row with police. Scotland Yard officers were furious with the Princess after it emerged that she encouraged a member of the public to help snatch a photographer's film as he took pictures of her emerging from her new gym in west London. A street brawl developed.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>WALL ST HAS SHARES RUNNING SCARED</p>
<p>A retreat Wall Street dominated overnight trading in the Far East. London shares were set to open lower today. A 2.3 pct drop by the Dow yesterday, on interest rate fears and a slowdown in corporate earnings was echoed in the Far East. On currency markets, as House Speaker Newt Gingrich sounded caution on Japan's trade surplus with the US, the dollar weakened.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>CLEAROUT AT NIPPON</p>
<p>As part of a restructuring exercise by Japan's Nippon Credit Bank, three affiliates of the bank filed for bankruptcy today. The three non-bank financial institutions have debts totalling 2.025 trillion yen (10.1 billion stg).</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BIG SWITCH-OFF BY VODAFONE CUSTOMERS</p>
<p>Britain's biggest mobile phones operator Vodafone is expected to reveal a near 50 percent cut in net new customers in the first quarter of this year to between 70,000 and 75,000 for the final three months of 1996.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>KKR IN QUEUE FOR 800 MLN HOSPITALS SALE</p>
<p>Kohlberg Kravis Roberts, the US venture capital group has joined in the auction for Compagnie Generale de Sante, one of Britain's biggest private hospitals chains. The company which comprises of 26 hospitals across Britain and also operates in France has been put on the market by French utilities group Compagnie Generale Des Eaux.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>109 MLN SHARES GLITCH AT MEDEVA</p>
<p>Medeva the pharmaceutical company has come clean about a 'regrettable technical hitch' that meant investors were left with 109 million stg of illegally issued shares. This week every shareholder will receive a revised notice of this month's annual meeting.</p>
<p>-- BMC +44 171 377 1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
