<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479786" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Vodafone says subcribers up 979,000 in year.</title>
<headline>Vodafone says subcribers up 979,000 in year.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Vodafone Group Plc, Britain's biggest mobile telephone operator, on Tuesday said worldwide subscribers grew by 979,000 in the year to March 31, and has now passed four million.</p>
<p>It said in a statement that in the UK, the subscriber base was more than 2.87 million, up 415,000 in the current financial year.  </p>
<p>Its 11 overseas networks, after adjusting for increased shareholdings in Greece and France, increased by the end of March to more than 1.15 million, up 564,000 on the year. Overseas subscribers now account for more than 28 percent of the group's total.</p>
<p>&quot;In the UK Vodafone remains the market leader both in turnover and in numbers of subscribers,&quot; chief executive Chris Gent said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;Progress during the financial year on both successfully migrating our analogue customers to our digital service and in winning new digital business has exceeded our best expectations&quot;.</p>
<p>He said that the digital base now represents over half of all the company's UK subscribers, helping slow the fall in average revenue per customer.</p>
<p>The company's overall churn rate is 27 percent, while its digital churn rate at 17 percent for the year is the lowest in the industry.</p>
<p>&quot;Overseas our businesses taken collectively are now profitable and are growing rapidly taking advantage of the strong world-wide demand for mobile telephony,&quot; Gent added.</p>
<p>International connections accounted for 57 percent of its our overall growth in the year.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 4017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
