<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479787" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Major promises &quot;booming Britain&quot; manifesto.</title>
<headline>Major promises &quot;booming Britain&quot; manifesto.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Prime Minister John Major said on Tuesday he would publish an election manifesto designed to keep Britain booming.</p>
<p>The ruling Conservative Party's manifesto for the May 1 election would contain pledges to keep public spending below 40 percent of national income and virtually eliminate public borrowing by the year 2000.</p>
<p>In a statement on the manifesto to be published on Wednesday, Major said the Conservatives would ensure that Britain maintained the lowest tax burden of any major European economy.</p>
<p>The party was committed to maintaining  an annual inflation target of 2.5 percent or less throughout the the five-year life of the next parliament.</p>
<p>Britain would also maintain its opt-out from the Social Chapter of the Maastricht Treaty on European Union.</p>
<p>&quot;Today Britain is booming. Tomorrow we will be publishing an election manifesto designed to keep it booming and to provide certainty in an uncertain world,&quot; Major said.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that sticking with these policies is the only way to be sure that our prosperity will last. Labour's policy of extending union power, increasing spending taxes and piling costs on business would blow it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
