<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479863" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turk PM attacks 'anti-Moslem' West after blazes.</title>
<headline>Turk PM attacks 'anti-Moslem' West after blazes.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's Islamist Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan on Tuesday strongly criticised the West for the deaths of Turks in a recent spate of fires in Europe, which he said were the result of anti-Moslem sentiment.</p>
<p>&quot;I call to the West, come to your senses. Stop this violence happening among you,&quot; Erbakan said in a speech to members of his Islam-based Welfare Party. &quot;You do nothing other than increase tension on earth and apply double standards.&quot;</p>
<p>On Tuesday, a Turkish man was injured after a fire broke out at his home in the central German town of Haigerseelbach and investigators were not ruling out the possibility of a racist attack, police said.</p>
<p>Six members of a Turkish immigrant family died in the Netherlands last week in an arson attack being investigated amid suspicions that it may have been motivated by racial hatred.</p>
<p>On Monday German police said three members of a Turkish family had died after a fire broke out in their apartment in the west German town of Krefeld. Investigators believe it was set deliberately but there is no word on whether it was racism.</p>
<p>Turkey's relations with Europe have been strained in recent months by Turkish frustrations at a perceived lack of progress in its bid to become a full member of the European Union.</p>
<p>Erbakan said the education of children in the West encouraged anti-Moslem feelings which led to racist attacks.</p>
<p>&quot;Television, novels and newspapers in your countries fan an Islam enmity campaign against Moslems every day and you just look on,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Turkish State Minister Lutfu Esengun and a group of parliamentarians were to travel to the Netherlands and Belgium on Wednesday to investigate human rights abuses against Turkish citizens, the foreign ministry said.</p>
<p>Erbakan attacked Western countries for not meting out adequate punishment for those guilty of racist attacks.</p>
<p>&quot;You have a big share of responsibility. You send the people who carry out these acts home after three days or do not punish them at all,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Five members of a Turkish family died in a racist arson attack in the German town of Solingen in 1993. Four Germans were sentenced to between 10-15 years in prison on counts of murder, attempted murder and arson.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
