<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479808" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Coloured beer and new job for Maggie -- Not!.</title>
<headline>Coloured beer and new job for Maggie -- Not!.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The date was the clue on Tuesday for British newspaper readers puzzling over stories about beer produced in the colours of top football clubs and a new job for Margaret Thatcher as ambassador to Washington.</p>
<p>April Fool's Day brought its traditional crop of weird and wonderful &quot;news items&quot; in the national media.</p>
<p>But with a general election campaign in full swing and much of the news almost beyond parody, it was harder than usual to tell the spoofs from the truth.</p>
<p>The story about former prime minister Thatcher being offered a job as ambassador to Washington in return for her endorsing opposition Labour Party leader Tony Blair was given prominence on the front page of The Independent.</p>
<p>It had a ring of truth, given persistent speculation about Thatcher's apparent impatience with her successor John Major.</p>
<p>But the game was given away by an alleged quote from President Bill Clinton, said to be &quot;more than happy&quot; to welcome to Washington the woman who was his predecessor's closest ally and whose party tried to undermine Clinton's election hopes.</p>
<p>More authentic was the &quot;Thatcher onslaught on Blair&quot; headline in the rival Daily Telegraph, which carried an article by the &quot;Iron Lady&quot; attacking Labour as a &quot;boneless wonder&quot;.</p>
<p>Traditional April Fool's Day fare was served up by the tabloid Mirror, which reported that scientists at a major brewery had managed to produce beer in the colours of every top-flight soccer club.</p>
<p>Wimbledon fans would be able to toast the &quot;Crazy Gang&quot; in blue beer, while followers of Newcastle United could sink a pint of black-and-white striped ale.</p>
<p>The rival Sun meanwhile came up with the &quot;scoop&quot; that former England soccer star Gary Lineker was planning to spend millions to buy his old club Leicester City with backing from the potato crisps company whose products he now advertises.</p>
<p>The story rather paled in its weirdness when put up against the paper's genuine front page &quot;exclusive&quot;, in which Diana Princess of Wales urged a passing stranger to snatch film from a photographer whose antics had angered her.</p>
<p>The Daily Mail ran a story, suspiciously larded with a reference to April 1, about how a monkey had stolen a wild-life photographer's camera in Africa and taken an award-winning picture of a snarling lioness.</p>
<p>Underneath, the tabloid ran an item on how to teach your pet to take photographs.</p>
<p>But was that any odder than the straight news story, which appeared on a number of front pages, about the election plans of a man called Swampy, an environmental protester best known for tunnelling under road and airport runway developments.</p>
<p>Swampy, whose real name is Daniel Hooper, was pictured emerging from a tunnel at Manchester airport to launch his &quot;Don't fly, don't drive&quot; manifesto for the May 1 election.</p>
<p>He had made reporters wait while he finished his favourite snack -- pot noodles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
