<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479822" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: US stocks in London up on limited bargain hunting.</title>
<headline>US stocks in London up on limited bargain hunting.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. shares were generally firmer but trading volumes were thin on Tuesday as European investors returned to their desks after a four-day Easter holiday break to find the Dow industrials nearly 300 points lower.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen a bit of bargain hunting but nothing too extraordinary. It's anyone's guess what Wall Street will do but we could see a firmer start today,&quot; one market maker said.</p>
<p>&quot;But if the NAPM figures are strong, we could easily see another round of selling.&quot;</p>
<p>The National Association of Purchasing Managers survey for March is due at 1500 GMT. The key U.S. data, the March U.S. unemployment figures, are scheduled for release on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Until we get the jobs numbers out of the way this market is going to be nervous. I can't see the Dow making too much headway,&quot; another dealer said.</p>
<p>Some technical analysts here expect the Dow, which has fallen 7.4 percent, or 528.62 points, over the past three weeks, to find some near-term support at around the 6,500 level.</p>
<p>&quot;I do suspect 6,500 will act as a support level, said Nick Glydon, chartist at Robert Fleming. &quot;People are very, very bearish - really terrified of this market. That is always a good sign that we are due for a bit of a bounce.&quot;</p>
<p>Glydon, who warned that the Dow was entering a bear phase, shortly before it hit a record high of 7,112.1 on March 11, believes any Wall Street bounce will be short-lived, however.</p>
<p>He noted that the S&amp;P 500 Index had closed below the 760 support level on Monday, ending at 757.12, down 16.76 on the day while the Nasdaq Composite had fallen below its 14, 25, 40 and 90 day moving averages -- all bearish signs for U.S. blue chips.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not looking too promising. We think the Dow has seen a(chart) double top and it looks like its going to have a few bad weeks,&quot; Glydon said.</p>
<p>A &quot;double top&quot; has formed on the Dow Industrials average -- a normally bearish technical sign.</p>
<p>After starting the year at around the 6,450 level, the Dow pushed above the 7,000 level but the rally temporarily stalled in late February, with the Dow slipping to around 6,850 in early March.</p>
<p>But upon seeing this dip, residual buyers, believing the Dow's uptrend was still intact, pushed the market back above 7,000. That advance ended on March 11 and previous support points have given way, creating a bearish double-top pattern on the Dow's chart.</p>
<p>Glydon believes the Dow will initially test the 6,300 support level before buyers are tempted to do any significant bargain hunting.</p>
<p>If the 6,300 level gives way, the next important Dow support is pegged at around 6,000.</p>
<p>Amongst individual shares, bellwether IBM Corp was up $1/4 to $137-5/8 while Philip Morris added $1/2 to $114-5/8.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, Intel Corp was up $3/8 to $139-1/2 while Digital Equipment Corp gained $1/4 to $27-5/8.</p>
<p>The June S&amp;P 500 futures contract was 3.00 to 761.00 while the June T-Bond rose 2/32 to 107-9/32. The yield on the 30-year cash long bond was standing at 7.10 percent by 1150 GMT.</p>
<p>--Dale Faulken, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
