<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479860" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: Jordan Housing Bank says new law expands role.</title>
<headline>Jordan Housing Bank says new law expands role.</headline>
<dateline>AMMAN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jordan's Housing Bank, the country's second largest bank, said on Tuesday a law widening its scope of operations will boost its future financing role.</p>
<p>A royal decree was published on Tuesday scrapping the bank's original law which set it up in 1973 as a real estate financial institution to provide below market rates credit for low income Jordanians.</p>
<p>The new law strips Housing Bank of a number of previous privileges including unconditional underwriting of its liabilities, but lifts restrictions on its commercial activities.</p>
<p>&quot;Housing Bank's ability to perform comprehensive commercial banking will allow it to consolidate its financing role to meet the development needs of Jordan in the coming years,&quot; Zuhair Khoury, the bank's chairman said in a statement sent to Reuters.</p>
<p>The bank in the past had to get special permission from the Central Bank for a growing amount of credit extended for commercial business activities, which since the late 1980s have outstripped the bank's real estate lending.</p>
<p>At least 60 percent of Housing Bank's outstanding loans portfolio of 661.1 million dinars at end of 1996 has been in commercial business.</p>
<p>Bank officials say Housing Bank's strategic focus is to expand into comprehensive banking away from dependance on its core real estate credit along with widening its investment and private banking business for its clients in capital markets.</p>
<p>Housing Bank's total assets stood at 1.136 billion dinars by the end of 1996 and its deposits stood at 918 million dinars.</p>
<p>Khoury said widening of its activties into comprehensive commercial banking will boost the bank's &quot;competitiveness&quot; and allow it to widen its exposure and activities in global financial markets.</p>
<p>The bank plans to launch soon a 20 million dinar investment fund in Jordanian bluechip and newly established companies which it has registered in Bahrain.</p>
<p>The fund, the first of its kind by a local financial insitution, will be managed by New York-based Alliance Capital.</p>
<p>The Jordan fund targets mainly foreign investors and Jordanian expatriates. It is to be listed on both the Amman bourse and the Bahrain Stock Exchange under a cross listing deal.</p>
<p>($1 = 0.7080 dinar)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMMAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
