<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479815" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Blair, humble but excited, hits UK campaign trail.</title>
<headline>Blair, humble but excited, hits UK campaign trail.</headline>
<byline>Alan Wheatley</byline>
<dateline>NORTHAMPTON, England 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Opposition leader Tony Blair, formally launching his campaign for the May 1 election, spoke on Tuesday of the responsibility and humility he felt at being hot favourite to be Britain's next prime minister.</p>
<p>Speaking to reporters aboard Labour's &quot;battle bus&quot; on the way to Northampton in central England, Blair said he was excited the campaign was finally under way after months of shadow boxing.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel the responsibility. It is in some ways quite a humbling experience because all those hopes and aspirations are vested in us,&quot; said Blair.</p>
<p>Labour leads Prime Minister John Major's Conservatives in opinion polls by about 20 percentage points.</p>
<p>&quot;But there's also a sense of excitement, of what we can achieve, of what we can do. The whole of my political life has been a preparation, if you like, for this period of time.</p>
<p>&quot;I came into politics as a doer, not a sayer. For 13 to 14 years -- all my adult life in politics -- I've been in opposition and we're anxious to start doing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Blair, accompanied by his wife Cherie and just a handful of close aides, again warned his party, in opposition for 18 years, not to be lulled into complacency by the polls.</p>
<p>The Conservatives, he said, would try to &quot;terrify people about the Labour Party&quot; in the run-up to polling day and Labour had to respond by putting across its own positive message.</p>
<p>Although Blair is keen to campaign on what he sees as the key issues of education and modernising Britain's economy, he accepts that to some extent voters will make their minds up on the personalities of the party leaders.</p>
<p>Asked what sort of person he was, Blair answered: &quot;I hope I've been very straight with people about what we can deliver.</p>
<p>&quot;All the way through I've been saying I don't promise a revolution, I don't say I can wave a magic wand and put the world to rights.&quot;</p>
<p>The first two weeks of the campaign since Major called the election have been relatively low-key, with the spotlight on so-called sleaze in the Conservative Party.</p>
<p>But the Conservatives and Labour launch their manifestoes this week and Blair began his &quot;meet the people&quot; tour on Tuesday. Labour has set up a high-tech campaign headquarters a stone's throw from parliament but Blair's bus, taking him on a tour of 60 towns and cities, is largely a throwback to the old days.</p>
<p>The only concessions to modern electioneering are a mobile fax machine and a telephone conferencing facility. But a &quot;people's platform&quot; will unfold from the rear of the coach to give Blair his equivalent to Major's famed soapbox.</p>
<p>The cramped coach, painted with the Union Jack flag on its roof, has been paid for by the media which have had to stump up 7,500 pounds ($12,250) for a seat on two accompanying press buses.</p>
<p>The press buses of the Conservatives and minority Liberal Democrats are also self-financing.</p>
<p>Labour strategists have a minutely prepared schedule of campaign stops for the next month, with fall-back plans in case last-minute changes have to be made.</p>
<p>In between meetings, Blair intends to concentrate on interviews with local and regional media, which aides believe exert enormous influence in election campaigns.</p>
<p>Blair says he does not feel stressed but admits the next four weeks will be tough.</p>
<p>Yet he adds: &quot;We are conscious the whole time that if we are elected, that's when the tough work begins. If we are successful in persuading people, May 2 is the date when we've got to get on with the business of delivering what we promised to do.&quot; ($1=.6124 Pound)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NORTHAMPTON, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
