<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479807" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Sterling locked in ranges in quiet European trade.</title>
<headline>Sterling locked in ranges in quiet European trade.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sterling was well-supported within tight ranges in quiet European trade on Tuesday as markets lulled after the long Easter holiday.</p>
<p>&quot;Sterling held up well despite the FTSE 100-point drop,&quot; BankAmerica economist Jeremy Hawkins said. &quot;People are looking for UK interest rates to move up in line with the U.S.&quot;</p>
<p>Sterling was quoted at 2.7420/30 marks by 1142 GMT compared to 2.7465/75 in late Europe on Thursday, with cable trading in a range at $1.6432/42 against $1.6450/60 on Thursday.</p>
<p>Fears of further hikes in UK interest rates are providing sterling with underlying support, according to economists.</p>
<p>&quot;The UK, which is expected to increase rates after the general election, is better placed to follow the Fed than most European countries which are looking to bring rates down,&quot; Hawkins said.</p>
<p>&quot;The dislocation in economic cycles between the UK and continental Europe continues to support sterling,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The pound ignored March UK Purchasing Managers Index data which showed purchasing managers reported a 10th consecutive monthly rise in output and new orders.</p>
<p>The overall PMI, however, edged slightly lower to a seasonally-adjusted 52.9 from 53.4 in February, largely due to a drop in manufacturing employment.</p>
<p>-- Simon Gardner, London Forex Desk +44 171 542 6762</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
