<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479848" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK March Purchasing Managers survey -- full text.</title>
<headline>UK March Purchasing Managers survey -- full text.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following is the full text of the March report on business (Purchasing Managers' Survey) of the Chartered Institute of Purchasing and Supply (CIPS):</p>
<p>PMI SIGNALS EXPANSION FOR TENTH CONSECUTIVE MONTH AS OUTPUT</p>
<p>AND ORDERS SHOW STRONG GROWTH</p>
<p>The seasonally adjusted Purchasing Managers' Index (PMI - a composite indicator designed to provide an overall view of manufacturing activity) indicated expansion for the tenth consecutive month as purchasing managers reported further strong growth of output and new orders in March.</p>
<p>The principal source of the growth of new orders was the UK market. Export orders also rose, and to a greater extent than in February, on the back of faster growth in European economies. However, the impact of the recent increase in the value of the pound continued to subdue export orders compared to the strong performance recorded in the latter half of last year.</p>
<p>The positive aspect of the pound's strength was, again, lower prices for imported raw materials and components. This led to a sharp fall in manufacturers' average input prices in March -- the seventeenth consecutive monthly decline.</p>
<p>Further evidence of subdued price pressures was provided by suppliers' delivery times. Although the time taken for suppliers to deliver goods to factories lengthened for the seventh month running in line with rising demand, the incidence of such delays and shortages remained relatively low.</p>
<p>To illustrate, despite the fact that the quantity of goods bought by purchasing managers showed the sharpest rise since December 1994, fewer than 9% of companies reported their suppliers to have had insufficient capacity to meet demand in March. This suggests that any inflationary effects associated with capacity constraints remain suppressed.</p>
<p>Stocks of both purchases and finished goods fell again. The decline in the latter was largely unintentional. For the third month in a row sales were reported to have grown faster than output, leading to a fall in finished goods stock. Stocks of purchases, on the other hand, generally fell as a consequence of deliberate destocking policies intended to reduce costs.</p>
<p>The need to reduce costs also affected employment, which fell marginally for the first time in ten months in March. A slightly higher number of firms cut staffing levels as part of efficiency-boosting rationalisation programmes, such as downsizing, than recruited new staff.</p>
<p>This drop in employment was a prime cause of a slight fall in the rate of growth of the PMI. Overall, the survey indicates a continuation of growth in manufacturing activity at sustainable levels.</p>
<p>The Purchasing Managers' Index (PMI) is a composite indicator designed to provide an overall view of activity in the manufacturing economy and acts as a leading indicator for the whole economy.  </p>
<p>The indicator is derived from individual diffusion indices which measure changes in output, new orders, employment, suppliers' delivery times and stocks of goods purchased. A reading of the PMI below 50 indicates that the manufacturing economy is generally declining; above 50, that it is generally expanding. The seasonally adjusted index may be subject to revision as improved estimation of seasonal adjustments occur with each month's new data.</p>
<p>OUTPUT</p>
<p>The seasonally adjusted Output Index, at a level markedly higher than the 50.0 &quot;no change&quot; level, signalled a further substantial rise in manufacturing production in March. Output has now shown significant growth for 10 consecutive months in response to continual improvements in order books over this period. Output of consumer, intermediate and investment goods all rose, with the latter showing especially strong growth.</p>
<p>NEW ORDERS</p>
<p>New orders rose for the 10th consecutive month in March, and at a slightly faster rate than in February. Orders from UK customers showed stronger growth than orders from overseas markets, but export orders continued to rise as faster economic growth in Europe partly offset the uncompetitiveness caused by the stronger pound. Orders for investment goods, such as plant and machinery, showed the largest rise.</p>
<p>QUANTITY OF PURCHASES</p>
<p>The Quantity of Purchases Index rose to 55.6 in March, reflecting the fastest rate of growth since December 1994. Over the past three months, firms have been buying increasing quantities of inputs to meet rising production requirements. However, the rate of growth of purchases continues to run slightly behind that of output as manufacturers attempt to keep stock levels under control for cost considerations.</p>
<p>PRICES</p>
<p>The seasonally adjusted Prices Index, at a level well below 50.0, continued to indicate sharply falling prices in March. As seen throughout this year so far, the reduced price of imported goods -- resulting from the continued strength of sterling -- was again the principal cause of a drop in input prices across all manufacturing industries.</p>
<p>SUPPLIERS' DELIVERY TIMES</p>
<p>The Suppliers' Delivery Times Index remained below 50.0 in March, indicating lengthening delivery times for the seventh consecutive month. The rate at which lead-times have been lengthening has shown very little change over the past six months, the index remaining just below 48.0. This suggests that suppliers have become increasingly busy over this period but that capacity constraints are not a significant problem.</p>
<p>STOCKS OF PURCHASES</p>
<p>Firms continued to concentrate on reducing costs in March and the continued widespread implementation of cost-cutting stock reduction policies led to a further marked drop in stocks of goods purchased by manufacturers. Purchasing managers also noted that a favourable outlook of continued low prices and good availability again reduced the risks involved with holding stocks as low as possible.  </p>
<p>STOCKS OF FINISHED GOODS</p>
<p>Stocks of finished goods fell again in March. In contrast to the situation reported throughout most of last year, when stocks were generally declining due to the widespread implementation of cost-cutting policies, the main cause of the decline in finished goods stock over the past three months has been the strength of sales growth, which has exceeded growth of factory output.</p>
<p>EMPLOYMENT</p>
<p>The seasonally adjusted Employment Index dropped below 50.0 in March, signalling the first drop in manufacturing employment since last May. The decline reflects increased concerns over rising costs, with marginally more manufacturers downsizing and rationalising production processes than recruiting new staff.</p>
<p>CONSUMER GOODS</p>
<p>The New Orders Index recorded continued growth in March as demand from UK customers remained buoyant. However, subdued overseas demand, arising from the strength of the pound, has weakened order book growth over the past two months and in March the New Orders index fell to its lowest level since last May. Output rose to meet the continued growth in orders, but also showed a dip in the rate of growth. Suppliers' delivery times lengthened as firms fought to meet demand, but price pressures remained muted. Prices paid for inputs in fact fell sharply again due to cheaper imports, but employment nevertheless fell for the first time since May last year as an increasing number of firms focused on rationalising production to reduce costs.</p>
<p>INVESTMENT/CAPITAL GOODS</p>
<p>The investment goods industries recorded the highest Output Index, signalling the greatest monthly rise, of all three market sectors in March (and the highest rise since January 1995). Order books also showed the strongest growth of all three sectors, in part because export demand has been less affected by the rise in the pound compared with consumer and intermediate goods, but also because UK demand for plant and machinery strengthened. The amount of inputs purchased rose sharply to rebuild stocks and cater for future growth in production, but the rise was met by suppliers with ease (delivery times actually shortened). Thus, in spite of the rising demand for goods, prices fell sharply as the cost of imported goods fell due to the exchange rate.</p>
<p>INTERMEDIATE GOODS</p>
<p>Both new orders and output of intermediate goods (mainly components) showed strong gains again in March, although the rate of growth moderated slightly. Orders from both UK and overseas markets rose with UK orders showing the strongest growth. The quantity of goods purchased by firms rose again to meet rising production requirements, but again the rate of growth dipped slightly.</p>
<p>Despite some evidence of UK suppliers' prices hardening in line with the continued growth of demand for raw materials, input prices fell again due to the lower cost of imported goods arising from the exchange rate. Costs continued to affect stocks and employment, however, both of which were deliberately reduced to improve efficiencies.</p>
<p>EXPORT ORDERS</p>
<p>Approximately 80 percent of the CIPS survey panel export to some degree and since January 1996 an additional question has been asked of these survey panel members. &quot;Please compare your export order books with the situation one month ago.&quot; This question is intended to supplement the New Orders Index, which monitors the overall state of total order books -- UK and overseas sourced. The data derived from this new question are published below. The charts show export performance over the past 15 months, as measured by the diffusion index derived from the percentages of respondents reporting an improvement, deterioration or no change in export order levels.</p>
<p>NEW EXPORT ORDERS INDEX</p>
<p>The unadjusted Export Orders Index rose to 54.9 in March, its highest level since last October, as nearly a quarter of all exporters reported growth. However, the rise was partly attributable to seasonal influences, especially the ordering of goods in advance of Easter closures, and after taking such seasonal influences into account the survey found only a modest increase in export orders, albeit to a slightly greater extent than reported in February. The seasonally adjusted index rose to 52.8, but this remains well below levels reported last summer and therefore indicates a significant decline in the rate of growth of export orders compared with last year.</p>
<p>THE IMPACT OF CHANGES IN EXPORT ORDERS ON TOTAL ORDER BOOKS</p>
<p>In general, the weaker export performance experienced so far this year has been linked to the rise in the value of the pound. The pound has risen by 15% since last August. Although dropping somewhat in March, the appreciation in the exchange rate has meant that UK goods have become less competitively priced in overseas markets. The resultant decline in the rate of growth of orders has clearly had an impact on the rate of growth of total order books which peaked in November. However, with domestic demand showing strong growth, order books continued to record significant growth in March despite the sluggish export demand.</p>
<p>EXPORT ORDERS BY MARKET SECTOR</p>
<p>Consumer Goods -- The volume of new export orders for consumer goods rose in March, having fallen in February. The seasonally adjusted index rose from 48.2 to 52.3. Despite the rise in the index the rate of growth remains sharply lower than that seen throughout last year and is almost wholly attributable to the rise in the pound.</p>
<p>Investment Goods -- After taking into account seasonal factors, overseas demand for investment goods was again less affected by the rise in sterling than the other two sectors. The seasonally adjusted index recorded the highest reading, 53.3, although the fall in the index from 56.1 reflected lost orders due to the strength of sterling.</p>
<p>Intermediate Goods -- Following a very small drop in export orders in February, producers of intermediate goods saw export orders rise after seasonal adjustment in March. The adjusted index rose from 49.6 to 52.7. The effects of the rise in the pound were reported to have been partially offset by faster economic growth in Europe.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 5109</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
