<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479868" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli parliament considers &quot;Who is a Jew&quot;.</title>
<headline>Israeli parliament considers &quot;Who is a Jew&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Heller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Debating &quot;who is a Jew&quot; while Middle East peace falters, Israel's parliament on Tuesday approved preliminary legislation which opponents said would alienate non-Orthodox Jews worldwide.</p>
<p>The bill, which passed the first of three readings, would enshrine in law a long-standing &quot;status quo&quot; whereby people converted in Israel to Judaism would be officially recognised as Jews only if the conversion was performed by an Orthodox rabbi.</p>
<p>Government officials said Israel would continue to accept as valid conversions done outside its borders by rabbis in the Reform and Conservative movements, the mainstream in the United States, home to the world's largest Jewish community.</p>
<p>But non-Orthodox politicians called the legislation -- part of a coalition deal between the ruling Likud party and religious factions -- divisive and an insult to Reform, Conservative and secular Jews who far outnumber Orthodox Jews in Israel and abroad.</p>
<p>&quot;The law limits itself to Reform and Conservative communities only here in Israel but we know...it is a first step towards making those abroad illegitimate,&quot; Hagai Merom of the main opposition Labour party said in a stormy debate.</p>
<p>The long-standing &quot;foreign conversion&quot; loophole allows all converts who immigrate to Israel to be listed as Jews on their identity cards.</p>
<p>Such a listing is essential for Jews who wish to be married or divorced in Israel, where only Orthodox rabbis are officially sanctioned to perform the ceremonies.</p>
<p>&quot;There is nothing new here. It is only setting into law an existing situation,&quot; Transport Minister Yitzhak Levy of the National Religious Party said about the proposed legislation.</p>
<p>Rabbi Eric Yoffie, president of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations, a Reform movement, said on Monday the legislation would cause &quot;anger, frustration and a split between Israel and the biggest and most important Jewish community in the world&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;If the Reform rabbis in Israel are not rabbis and our conversions (in Israel) are not conversions, it means our Judaism is not Judaism and we are second class Jews,&quot; he told Israeli Army Radio.</p>
<p>Yossi Sarid of the left-wing Meretz party said the legislation was indicative of what he called ultraorthodox hate of Reform and Conservative Jews, who are more flexible in interpretation and practice of Jewish ritual law.</p>
<p>&quot;The Conservatives and Reform in the world, especially in the United States, are the majority. They number four million Jews, if not more.</p>
<p>&quot;Today, they have been given a divorce decree and then (the Orthodox) will cry crocodile tears about assimilation and the disappearance of the Jewish people,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Coalition whip Michael Eitan said the preliminary legislation, approved by a vote of 51 to 32 with seven abstentions, would not be presented for its final readings until all efforts to hammer out a compromise draft were exhausted.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
