<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479804" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Investors seen opting for short end of bond market.</title>
<headline>Investors seen opting for short end of bond market.</headline>
<byline>Carolyn Cohn</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>International investors will look for returns at the short end of the bond markets in the current environment of plummeting stocks and spiralling yields, analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>U.S. stocks fell sharply on Monday while Europeans were continuing their Easter break -- adding to another big drop on Wall Street last Thursday -- and European stocks and bonds followed suit in morning trading on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The short end is the place which is being favoured,&quot; said Graham McDevitt, head of bond research at Paribas Capital Markets in London.</p>
<p>The U.S. long bond closed above seven percent on Monday and late last week after the Federal Reserve raised U.S. interest rates on March 25.</p>
<p>Bonds took their cue from the U.S. equity market, analysts said. The Dow industrials index lost 157 points to 6,583 on Monday after shedding 140 points last Thursday. The market was closed on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;If the equity market in the U.S. is responding to perceptions of weaker growth in its own right, that would be equity-unfriendly and bond-friendly,&quot; said Nigel Richardson, head of bond research at Yamaichi International in London.</p>
<p>&quot;But if the market is reflecting perceptions of further monetary tightening, that would be both equity- and bond-unfriendly.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts favour the latter view.</p>
<p>&quot;The U.S. market has been leading the way, because it is ahead of Europe in the interest rate cycle, and far ahead of Japan,&quot; said McDevitt.</p>
<p>The short end of the U.S. bond market is already discounting further U.S. rate rises and so provides a cautious resting place for international assets, analysts said.</p>
<p>The two-year note is currently yielding 6.419 against a federal funds target rate of 5.50 percent. The 30-year bond is yielding 7.101 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a fair amount of expectation of a couple more rate rises,&quot; said Sonja Gibbs, senior market analyst at Nomura International in London.</p>
<p>&quot;Seven percent at 10 years will be a target.&quot;</p>
<p>The 10-year note is yielding 6.902 percent.</p>
<p>In Europe, the absence of rate rise worries together with steep yield curves will send investors hunting for value in medium-term bonds, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a natural bid to the short end but we are probably going to see people further along the curve,&quot; said McDevitt.</p>
<p>Four-year German debt currently yields around 80 basis points (0.80 percentage point) more than two-year paper.</p>
<p>European bonds are also likely to outperform their U.S. counterparts, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;For European bonds, there is no reason to turn very bearish until the Bund future breaks below 99.28,&quot; said McDevitt.</p>
<p>The 99.28 level on the Bund future equates to a six percent yield in 10-year Bunds.</p>
<p>The June contract is currently trading around 99.44, 57 basis points below Friday's close.</p>
<p>Markets are likely to hover at current lower trading levels ahead of the release of key U.S. data this week, analysts said, starting with the March National Association of Purchasing Management (NAPM) index later on Tuesday and culminating with March employment data on Friday.</p>
<p>While the mood is cautious, Yamaichi's Richardson recommends skipping out of securities altogether.</p>
<p>&quot;People are going internationally to put their money into cash and go underweight in bonds.&quot;</p>
<p>Cash looks an attractive alternative to bonds and stocks until the next meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC) in May removes some rate uncertainty, Richardson said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
