<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479872" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel shares close lower in mixed trading. [CORRECTED 15:59 GMT]</title>
<headline>Israel shares close lower in mixed trading. [CORRECTED 15:59 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>TEL AVIV 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli shares closed slightly lower on Tuesday in very thin and mixed trading unaffected by Wall Street's plunge, traders said.</p>
<p>The benchmark Mishtanim index of the top 100 shares fell 0.25 percent, or 0.61 points, to 245.03 on low all-share turnover of 80 million shekels against 76 million shekels on Monday.</p>
<p>The Maof 25 blue chip index closed 0.11 percent lower at 253.70. (Corrects Maof figure from 245.03 to 253.70.)</p>
<p>&quot;Trading was very dull today and investors showed little interest in trading. The decline of the Dow on Monday had little impact on the market. The only reason for optimism is that there are more talks about a unity government,&quot; said Danniella Finn, head of sales at Batucha Securities and Investments.</p>
<p>On Monday, Wall Street added to Thursday's 140-point fall on the Dow Jones industrial average by losing another 157 points to 6,583.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said on Tuesday he was weighing the possibility of forging a unity government with the opposition Labour party, hoping to achieve a broad consensus for a final peace deal with Palestinians.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is dead and activity is minimal. Despite that, the fact that the market did not fall following the Dow's decline is a very positive indicator,&quot; said Danni Scahria, a broker at Capital Securities.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite the low volume the mood is still positive mainly because fourth-quarter earning reports were above expectations,&quot; Finn said.</p>
<p>Teva Pharmaceutical Industries, the most active share, fell 0.25 percent to 18,803 agorot on volume of 4.4 million shekels. Teva said on Tuesday it had won interim approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for its generic version of Glaxo Wellcome PLC's anti-viral drug Zovirax.</p>
<p>Bank Hapoalim, the second most active issue, gained 1.25 percent to 669 agorot on turnover of 3.7 million shekels. The bank said fourth-quarter 1996 net profit rose to 121.8 million shekels from 105.7 million a year earlier. Hapoalim also said it would increase its dividend for 1996 to 310.4 million shekels to reflect gains from the forced sale of excess holdings in non-bank companies.</p>
<p>Israel Chemicals closed unchanged at 359 on volume of 3.4 million shekels that made it the third most active stock.</p>
<p>($1 = 3.36 shekels)</p>
<p>- Dan Gerstenfeld, Tel Aviv newsroom, 972-3-537-2211</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEL AVIV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
