<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479867" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>KUWAIT: Kuwait mulls attracting more foreign investors.</title>
<headline>Kuwait mulls attracting more foreign investors.</headline>
<byline>Inal Ersan</byline>
<dateline>KUWAIT 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kuwait is considering several steps to attract foreign investment including easing ownership limitations in local firms, a minister said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have issued a decree to form a committee to study all matters in the area of foreign capital,&quot; Commerce and Industry Minister Jassem al-Mudaf told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The purpose is to encourage and attract foreign investors,&quot; said the minister adding that the committee would study changes to a trade law which limits foreign ownership in local firms to a maximum stake of 49 percent.</p>
<p>Trade in Kuwaiti shares is also restricted to nationals of Gulf Arab states. Any change to the law requires approval by parliament and the Emir Sheikh Jaber al-Ahmad al-Sabah.</p>
<p>&quot;Who would want to put his money in a third world country company without having a say in what it does with it?&quot; said an economist. &quot;Good economy signs are not the only ingredients to make money, regulations should be on your side.&quot;</p>
<p>Visiting officials often tell Kuwaiti counterparts that limitations on ownership discourages foreign investors.</p>
<p>The new committee is made up of investment, finance, industry and stock exchange officials, members of the chamber of commerce and two technical experts, Mudaf said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have pointed out that we want the results soon,&quot; he said when asked about a timeframe for the envisaged amendments.</p>
<p>Kuwait also plans to cut taxes imposed on foreign firms operating in Kuwait, officials earlier told Reuters. A foreign company with an annual profit of $1.25 million or more pays a maximum tax of 55 percent according to a three-decade-old law.</p>
<p>Mudaf would not say if the proposed changes would include allowing foreign firms a stake in the crude oil sector -- seen by economists as the most attractive for foreign investors.</p>
<p>&quot;The committee will determine the types of firms&quot; to be affected by the new measures, he added.</p>
<p>The state controls the strategic oil sector which is forecast in the annual budget to June 30 to bring in almost 90 percent of total revenues of three billion dinars ($9.9 billion) although it plans to privatise some local fuel stations and has allowed an American company a stake in a petrochemicals complex.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KUWAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
