<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479870" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Palestinian driver reconstructs Gaza explosion.</title>
<headline>Palestinian driver reconstructs Gaza explosion.</headline>
<byline>Taher Shriteh</byline>
<dateline>DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Moments before he was ripped apart by an explosion, a man dressed in a Palestinian police uniform was trying to hitch a ride from a car driving behind an Israeli army jeep in the Gaza Strip.</p>
<p>The off-duty Palestinian police officer who was driving his civilian car said he did not stop because the vehicle was full. He said he was paying particular attention to the Israeli jeep in front of him.</p>
<p>&quot;The Israeli soldier in the back was pointing a gun with something like a grenade or a rocket fitted to it,&quot; he said. &quot;Then there was a loud explosion.&quot;</p>
<p>The man at the side of the road not far from the Jewish settlment of Kfar Darom was blown to bits.</p>
<p>&quot;The Israeli jeep sped away while I slammed the brakes. Behind me, I saw the man on the ground in pieces,&quot; the witness, who spoke on condition he not be named, said.</p>
<p>Five passengers riding in a yellow Mercedes taxi behind the witness's vehicle were wounded by the blast.</p>
<p>The Israeli army says the dead man was the second of two Palestinian suicide bombers who tried to attack Israeli school buses on their regular routes from two isolated Jewish settlements to the main settlement block in the strip.</p>
<p>In the first incident 15 minutes earlier, another Palestinian was killed when he blew himself up near the Jewish settlement of Netzarim. No one was wounded in the blast.</p>
<p>No Israelis were hurt in either incident.</p>
<p>&quot;We doubt that they were suicide bombings and we are checking into the matter,&quot; said Major-General Abdel-Razek al- Majaydeh, director of the Palestinian security forces in Gaza.</p>
<p>One of the wounded taxi passengers, gesturing from his hospital bed, said: &quot;An Israeli military jeep came out of the Gush Katif (settlement block). There was one soldier in the back and he was acting weird. The car was swinging like this.</p>
<p>&quot;A settler car passed us and all of a sudden there was a huge explosion.&quot;</p>
<p>Palestinian officials said evidence and witness testimony indicate that an explosive charge was hurled from the Israeli army jeep, killing the man at the side of the road and wounding the seven taxi passengers.</p>
<p>Ahmed Abdel-Rahman, secretary-general of the Palestinian cabinet, told a news conference in Gaza:</p>
<p>&quot;In the area of Kfar Darom, an Israeli military jeep hurled a grenade or a bomb at (Palestinian) passers-by killing one and wounding others. This is information that we have ascertained from passers-by and victims.&quot;</p>
<p>Abdel-Rahman added that recent media reports have said Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has authorised Israel's secret police to resume work in areas under Palestinian self-rule.</p>
<p>Asked if he was accusing Israel of responsibility for the bombing, Abdel-Rahman said: &quot;It is premature to say that Mr Netanyahu has given a green light for operations of this kind. But if such an evidence comes up, I will say that.&quot;</p>
<p>His phrasing echoed Netanyahu who said before and after an Islamist suicide bombing in Tel Aviv on March 21 in which three Israelis were killed that Palestinian Authority President Yasser Arafat had given Palestinian militants the impression they had a &quot;green light&quot; to attack Israel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
