<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479821" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: New Algerian oilfields due on stream in 1997-OPECN.</title>
<headline>New Algerian oilfields due on stream in 1997-OPECN.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Algeria will bring new oil fields on stream in 1997 as part of plans to raise production capacity to one million bpd by the year 1999, the OPEC news agency OPECNA reported on Tuesday.</p>
<p>It quoted Algerian minister of energy and mines Amar Makhloufi as saying in an interview that Algeria would respect its OPEC quota as it built up capacity to a targeted 1.1-1.2 million bpd by the year 2000.</p>
<p>Makhloufi told OPECNA that Algeria had been holding talks with a number of foreign companies but that it did not intend to sign any new hydrocarbon deals for the time being but concentrate on evaluating the results of contracts signed in the past.</p>
<p>It quoted Makhloufi as saying the largest deposit to come on stream would be run by U.S.-based Anadarko Petroleum Corp while Italy's Agip SpA and the U.S. Atlantic Richfield Co (ARCO) would also develop new deposits, allowing for an increase in oil production &quot;while respecting our OPEC quota allocation.&quot;</p>
<p>Makhloufi said earlier this month that 1997 production capacity would be between 850,000 and 900,000 barrels per day (bpd) against a recent 700,000 bpd.</p>
<p>Its OPEC quota is 750,000 bpd and a Reuter survey pegged Algerian output at 840,000 bpd in February.</p>
<p>OPECNA said Makhloufi spoke in an interview in Tunis during a regional electricity conference last week.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 7630</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
