<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479851" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: PRESS DIGEST - Canada - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Canada - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the headlines from selected Canadian newspapers. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>THE GLOBE AND MAIL:</p>
<p>- Authority to buy Terminal 3: Sale to GTAA fuels speculation Ottawa hoping to end Pearson suit before election.</p>
<p>- Margin investors stung by Bre-X: Many thousands lost many millions.</p>
<p>- Teachers offered early retirement: Ontario proposal would allow some to leave without taking hit in their pension.</p>
<p>- Protest dogs grizzly hunt: Loss of habitat called a danger.</p>
<p>- Probes put care agencies on trial: Battered Ontario baby was CAS ward.</p>
<p>- Union reforms stay, Labour leader says: Party won't rescind Thatcher changes, Blair reassures British voters in letter.</p>
<p>- Wily Mobutu may buy off his rebel foes: Analysts expect Zairian leader will accept the fact he can't win the battle, and do the next best thing: bribe Kabila.</p>
<p>REPORT ON BUSINESS:</p>
<p>- Bre-X trading halted again: TSE awaits Busang information; firm faces billion-dollar lawsuits.</p>
<p>- Walsh cites complex ore body.</p>
<p>- Bears bite Toronto, U.S. stock markets: Interest rate, earnings fears spur sell-off.</p>
<p>- Scotiabank pushing deeper in South America: Spending C$200 million on expansion.</p>
<p>THE FINANCIAL POST:</p>
<p>- Bank, gold shares feel brunt of market anxiety.</p>
<p>- Bre-X set to battle it out: Beleaguered gold miner defends analysis of Busang ore samples and threatens to sue its critics - but U.S. lawsuits have already begun to accuse the company of fraud.</p>
<p>((Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8100))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
