<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479855" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: PLO says Israel behind second Gaza blast.</title>
<headline>PLO says Israel behind second Gaza blast.</headline>
<byline>Taher Shriteh</byline>
<dateline>DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israel said suicide bombers aiming to kill Jews were behind twin explosions in Gaza on Tuesday, but Palestinians said Israeli troops caused one of the blasts.</p>
<p>The Israeli army said two bombers died in separate attacks, one of which wounded five Arabs in a taxi. Palestinians conceded one of the dead men blew himself up, but said the other was killed by a bomb or grenade thrown from an Israeli jeep.</p>
<p>No Israelis were hurt in the incidents.</p>
<p>The blasts came against a backdrop of stalled Israeli-PLO peace talks and Israeli charges Palestinian President Yasser Arafat has failed to curb militants in areas of the West Bank and Gaza under his control.</p>
<p>In separate incidents, Israeli forces on Tuesday shot dead two Arabs in the West Bank, where clashes over Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem flared for a 13th straight day.</p>
<p>In a blast near Kfar Darom settlement, a Palestinian dressed in military uniform was ripped apart by an explosion on the main Gaza-Rafah road and five taxi passengers were wounded in the Tuesday morning blast.</p>
<p>An aide to Palestinian President Yasser Arafat said: &quot;In Kfar Darom area, an Israeli military jeep hurled a grenade or a bomb at (Palestinian) passersby killing one and wounding others. This is information that we have collected from passersby and victims,&quot; Ahmed Abdel-Rahman, secretary-general of the Palestinian cabinet, told Reuters.</p>
<p>An Israeli army spokesman rejected the Palestinian account.</p>
<p>&quot;It is absolutely incorrect. There were two suicide attacks and two bombs,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office quoted him as saying the blasts were proof that Arafat's &quot;Palestinian Authority has not yet taken the necessary efforts against terror. Terror organisations still understand that they have a green light to act against Israel and its citizens&quot;.</p>
<p>Earlier, Palestinian police officials said that a man with five kg (11 lb) of explosives on his back blew himself up on the side of the road at 7 a.m. (0400 GMT) about two km (1.5 miles) from the Jewish settlement of Netzarim south of Gaza City.</p>
<p>The second blast occurred about two km (1.5 miles) from Kfar Darom near the refugee camp of Deir al-Balah.</p>
<p>Both settlements, heavily armed Jewish enclaves in self-ruled Gaza, have been the focus of Palestinian attacks.</p>
<p>The Islamist militant group Hamas denied it was behind the explosions, accusing Israel of ordering the blasts to sour relations between Hamas and the Palestinian Authority.</p>
<p>&quot;This bombing was done by the Israeli intelligence and its (Palestinian) collaborators in an attempt to create an internal problem between the Islamic movement and the Palestinian Authority,&quot; Hamas official Sayed Abu Musameh told Reuters.</p>
<p>Last month Hamas claimed responsibility for a suicide bombing in Tel Aviv in which three Israeli women were killed.</p>
<p>Israeli-PLO ties have plunged to severe crisis since Israel broke ground on a new settlement in East Jerusalem last month.</p>
<p>Netanyahu has conditioned any further progress toward peace on a Palestinian crackdown on militants in self-ruled areas.</p>
<p>In the West Bank town of Nablus, undercover Palestinian policeman Haitham Mansour, 20, was shot dead by Israeli soldiers who opened fire at stone-throwing Palestinians near a checkpoint on the city's outskirts, witnesses said.</p>
<p>In another West Bank incident on Tuesday, a Palestinian youth was shot dead in Hebron. The Israeli army said soldiers spotted several Arabs engaging in theft. It said all but one fled in a car and that troops shot him as he fled on foot.</p>
<p>&quot;The suspect did not stop and soldiers fired at him,&quot; an army spokesman said.</p>
<p>Both Gaza explosions occurred around 7 a.m., about the time Israeli children leave two nearby Jewish settlements on buses for school, Jewish settlers said.</p>
<p>&quot;We can suppose that the operative goal at that hour was school buses or settler commuters who go to work at that hour,&quot; Israeli Southern Commander Shlomo Yanai said.</p>
<p>Settlers, enraged by the blasts, demanded Israeli troops invade PLO-ruled areas to uproot &quot;terror&quot;.</p>
<p>After the Tuesday blast at Netzarim, settlers hurled rocks at passing Arab motorists after the blast, witnesses said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
