<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479857" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>YEMEN: Yemen appeals court to rule on school gunman.</title>
<headline>Yemen appeals court to rule on school gunman.</headline>
<byline>Mohammad Sudam</byline>
<dateline>SANAA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Yemeni appeals court said on Tuesday it would announce its verdict on Wednesday against a Yemeni gunman condemned to death for killing four children and two adults in an attack at two schools.</p>
<p>The prosecutor general demanded that Mohammad Ahmad Misleh, 48, be executed by firing squad at a site between the two schools in Sanaa and his body crucified as an example to others.</p>
<p>A three-judge panel on Monday, after a three and a half hour session, found Misleh guilty of opening fire on hundreds of children in the two schoolyards, killing a headmistress, a teacher and three children.</p>
<p>The prosecutor general told the appeals court a boy, 16, who sustained serious injuries in Sunday's shootings, died early on Tuesday in hospital raising the number of dead children to four. He said 11 children were injured, four seriously.</p>
<p>Misleh had lodged his appeal after Monday's sentencing. He repeated in court on Tuesday that his shooting spree was an attempt to avenge the alleged rape of his daughter and the kidnappings of his daughter and son.</p>
<p>Two court-appointed lawyers defended Misleh, who heard the death sentence on Monday in a wheelchair behind the steel bars of a cage in the packed courtroom.</p>
<p>Relatives of the victims screamed in anger on Tuesday when one of the defence lawyers, Mohamamd al-Khatib, asked the judges for 10 minutes recess so he could talk to the defendant.</p>
<p>&quot;The proceedings are hasty, I need more time,&quot; said Khatib, sparking the anger of relatives who tried to attack him. Security forces intervened and pulled them away.</p>
<p>The gunman sustained a leg wound in an exchange of fire with police after he shot an assault rifle at hundreds of students aged six to 18 as they lined up for morning classes at the two neighbouring schools in a middle class suburb of Sannaa.</p>
<p>Misleh repeated to the court on Tuesday that he had intended to kill the headmistress' husband, alleging that they had approved the kidnap and rape of his daughter, 8, in 1995.</p>
<p>He said the kidnappers, with whom he had a feud over a plot of land, had also received the approval of the other school's administration to kidnap his son.</p>
<p>But the prosecutor general, who on Monday produced a medical examiner's report saying the girl was still a virgin and was not raped, questioned Misleh's nine-year-old son Badr, who denied he was ever kidnapped.</p>
<p>At the end of Tuesday's court session Misleh said he had worked in Saudi Arabia as a truck driver before he returned to Yemen two years ago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YEMAR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANAA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YEMEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
