<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479898" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Walls of mistrust go up between Arabs and Israel.</title>
<headline>Walls of mistrust go up between Arabs and Israel.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Wright</byline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The walls are going up again in the Middle East as the fragile bonds of trust between Arabs and Israelis snap under the strain of incompatible aspirations.</p>
<p>The Arab states, their patience exhausted after nine months of rightwing government in Israel, decided on Monday to deploy one of their last weapons short of war -- political and economic isolation of the Jewish state.</p>
<p>Advocates of political violence are gaining ground in Gaza and the West Bank, perhaps inadvertently giving Israeli leaders a new chance to divert attention from the bigger question of whose land it is and who will end up in control.</p>
<p>Talks between Israel and the Palestinians are close to collapse and even the United States, the mediator of first and last resort, does not seem about to patch them up again.</p>
<p>Egypt, the first Arab state to make peace and the most influential in Arab councils, is in angry mood, openly saying it does not trust Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.</p>
<p>&quot;By God, this is the worst situation in the peace process since 1977,&quot; Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak told the Israeli newspaper Maariv, citing the year Egyptian president Anwar Sadat went to Israel on the visit that led to the 1979 peace treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;You have succeeded in frightening the world,&quot; he said. &quot;You have pushed all of us into a very difficult situation.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We discover it (Egypt) is doing its utmost, I am sorry to say, in a pretty systematic way, to shut the gates of normalisation and openness,&quot; Netanyahu retorted.</p>
<p>He was reacting to Egypt's active support for Monday's Arab League resolution, which recommended that Arab states backtrack on normal relations with Israel, restore the economic boycott and withdraw from multilateral peace talks.</p>
<p>&quot;The parties have lost whatever faith or trust they ever had in each other...It does look very bad,&quot; one diplomat said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Arab resolution is the toughest language we have heard from the Arabs for a very long time. People (the Arabs) really are very angry,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The immediate cause of the anger is Netanyahu's decision to go ahead with a Jewish settlement at Jabal Abu Ghneim or Har Homa in Arab East Jerusalem, the part of the city Palestinians see as the capital of their future state.</p>
<p>For both sides, the hill in Jerusalem has become a symbol in the conflict over the shape of a final settlement -- where the borders of Israel will be and how much control the Palestinians will have of the areas they live in.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, in a statement likely to infuriate the Palestinians and other Arabs, stated his position in the conflict on Monday with great clarity.</p>
<p>&quot;We will not retreat to the 1967 borders, we are against a Palestinian state and we actively oppose the division of Jerusalem,&quot; he told parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;I recommend abandoning false dreams. What is needed today is lowering expectations on the Palestinian side so that the gap that remains becomes bridgeable.&quot;</p>
<p>But the Palestinians and Syrians, who want Israel to give back the Golan Heights, are not about to do Netanyahu's bidding and they say they have the documents to back their case.</p>
<p>Israel gave a commitment to the principle of &quot;land for peace&quot; at the Madrid peace conference in 1991 and by most accounts the previous Israeli government told Syria that complete withdrawal from the Golan Heights was a possibility.</p>
<p>&quot;He (Netanyahu) came and changed all the agreements...It's not acceptable. He is acting as if the Arab countries are just very marginal. This is a serious, serious miscalculation,&quot; Arab League Secretary General Esmat Abdel-Meguid said on Monday.</p>
<p>Most eyes are now on U.S. diplomacy and the United Nations, where the Arab states are trying to arrange a &quot;uniting for peace&quot; session in the General Assembly to bypass two U.S. vetoes of Security Council resolutions critical of Israel.</p>
<p>But diplomats in Cairo said the U.S. State Department appeared to be in disarray, especially after the failure of special envoy Dennis Ross's trip to the Middle East last month.</p>
<p>New Secretary of State Madeleine Albright has hardly touched the Middle East. By telling the Palestinians just to keep talking, regardless of what Israel does on the ground, she will not win friends among the Arabs.</p>
<p>&quot;What we need is James Baker,&quot; one Western diplomat joked.</p>
<p>Baker, secretary of state under former U.S. president George Bush, used loan guarantees to Israel as a diplomatic weapon and strongarmed the Israeli government into the Madrid conference.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARABST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SYRIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
