<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479816" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Summary of latest opinion polls on EMU.</title>
<headline>Summary of latest opinion polls on EMU.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a summary of findings from recent opinion polls about European economic and monetary union (EMU).</p>
<p>EUROPE, March 27 - Market expectations of a broad-based start to EMU in 1999 edged lower, with the perceived probability of Italy taking part dipping below 50 percent, according to the JP Morgan &quot;EMU calculator&quot;.</p>
<p>FRANCE, March 25 - A BVA survey for French radio BFM found that 64 percent of French adults believed both that France would be among those joining EMU from 1999 and that it was necessary that it do so.</p>
<p>SWEDEN, March 25 - Sixty-eight percent of Swedish market players expected EMU to start as planned in 1999, according to a March survey by pollster TEMO, compared with 80 percent in February. The poll also showed that seven percent of market players believed Sweden would join EMU from the start, down from 10 percent in February's survey.</p>
<p>GERMANY, March 20 - A survey by Manager magazine found that over four-fifths of 100 German executives questioned expected the launch of EMU to go ahead as planned. It also found that many companies planned to switch over to euros as a means of payment before it is issued notes and coins in 2002.</p>
<p>DENMARK, March 17 - A Gallup poll published in the Berlingske Tidende showed 41 percent of respondents believing Denmark should reverse its 1993 decision not to join EMU, compared to 46 percent in December. The survey, carried out between March 12 and 14, showed 49 percent in favour of maintaining the Danish 'no' to a common European currency, compared to 44 percent in December.</p>
<p>GERMANY, March 15 - The Infratest Burke financial research institute said only 37 percent of Germans accepted planned currency union, while 57 percent were against it, the Welt am Sonntag newspaper reported.</p>
<p>The poll, of 700 residents of the former West Germany with a monthly income of at least 5,000 marks, showed seven out of every 10 thought EMU, due to start in 1999, would happen, although only 40 percent thought Germany would fulfil the conditions laid out in the Maastricht treaty.</p>
<p>GERMANY, March 13 - Three-quarters of German voters think Europe's planned single currency should be delayed if member countries do not meet the Maastricht criteria. The Forsa survey in the weekly Die Woche said a mere 14 percent argued for softening the tough line backed by the Bundesbank and Finance Minister Theo Waigel in order to allow the launch to take place on schedule in 1999.</p>
<p>Die Woche also published two bank surveys showing widespread scepticism among business executives about the monetary union. Only 22 percent were positive about it and only 14 percent expected it to start on time.</p>
<p>BRITAIN, March 10 - Almost two-thirds of UK fund managers said EMU would significantly change their investment plans, but almost an equal number expect the start date for the single currency to be postponed, a monthly Gallup poll of fund managers showed. A majority of continental European fund managers, meantime, believe EMU will take place on time and only a third said it would change their investment plans.</p>
<p>GERMANY, March 6  - More than half of German voters want the strict economic criteria to qualify for Europe's planned single currency to be softened and only one-fifth think they should be applied strictly, according to a survey by the respected Allensbach Institute.</p>
<p>The poll also said 47.6 percent of the sample group opposed the euro, while 41.6 percent said they supported it. Only 10.8 percent were undecided. On the criteria, 55.2 percent said they should be softened, while 19.6 percent wanted to see them applied as laid down in the Maastricht Treaty, according to the poll.</p>
<p>AUSTRIA, March 5 - Nearly 50 percent of Austrians believe conversion to a European single currency, scheduled for 1999, will make their savings less valuable, a survey by market research institute Spectra showed. Nearly 40 percent expected the euro to be a disadvantage for Austria. Only 15 percent thought it would bring benefits.</p>
<p>FINLAND, March 3 - A Reuters poll found 22 of 23 dealers, analysts and economists surveyed at banks and corporate treasury departments believed Finland would be in the first group of countries to join stage three of EMU, if it started on time in 1999.</p>
<p>BRITAIN, Feb 27 - The UK retail banking sector is significantly behind its continental European competitors in preparations for introduction of the euro, Coopers &amp; Lybrand said in a survey. The survey found continental Europeans did not see UK banks as a threat &quot;largely because they do not believe that the UK will join the EMU at its outset.&quot;</p>
<p>-- London Polling Unit +44 171 542 5223</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
