<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479987" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pollen blankets U.S. South with sneezes, sniffles.</title>
<headline>Pollen blankets U.S. South with sneezes, sniffles.</headline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>As the Northeast dug its way out from under a heavy snowfall Tuesday, people across the Southern United States clutched their handkerchiefs and braced for a severe blizzard of pollen.</p>
<p>A string of unusually warm and sunny days, following a mild winter, has sent the daily pollen count skyrocketing for many Southern communities with trees, shrubs, grasses and flowering plants all reaching bloom at the same time.</p>
<p>The pollen count this week surged to the highest mark in metropolitan Atlanta since record-keeping began 15 years ago, according to the Atlanta Allergy and Asthma Clinic. Fine green dust coated cars and lawn furniture and allergy sufferers sniffled and sneezed.</p>
<p>&quot;It's been a very severe season,&quot; said the allergy and asthma clinic's Dr. Robert Berkowitz.</p>
<p>The latest count was 4,601 specks of sinus-infesting irritants in each cubic meter of air, up sharply from 2,000 pollen particles just last week. The old record was 3,474 last April.</p>
<p>The soaring count has become the bane of about 20 percent of the population who suffer from hay fever. But clinic officials also warned that pollen, whipped up by recent high winds, posed a problem for mild allergy sufferers as well.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
