<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479944" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ballot questions and bond referendums by state.</title>
<headline>Ballot questions and bond referendums by state.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a list of upcoming ballot initiatives and measures affecting municipal finance.</p>
<p>P - passed. D - defeated. NA - not available.</p>
<p>CALIFORNIA</p>
<p>June 3</p>
<p>--Two tax ballot issues to raise $60 million in Los Angeles County.</p>
<p>FLORIDA</p>
<p>April 1</p>
<p>--Broward County community of Bonaventure vote on whether to join City of Sunrise or City of Weston.</p>
<p>June 10</p>
<p>--Marion County, half-cent sales tax increase for schools.</p>
<p>June 17</p>
<p>--Oglethorpe County, five-year extension of special purpose one-cent sales tax increase.</p>
<p>Nov 4</p>
<p>--Up to $800 million of Broward County general obligation bonds for schools.</p>
<p>ILLINOIS</p>
<p>April 1</p>
<p>--Vote in Adams, McDonough, McLean, Shelby and Stephenson counties on property tax and general obligation bond limitations on local governments.</p>
<p>MISSOURI</p>
<p>April 1</p>
<p>--$100 million Kansas City GOs.</p>
<p>NEW JERSEY</p>
<p>April 15</p>
<p>--Northern Highlands Regional High School District, N.J., votes on three separate ballot questions: a $1.62 million bond issue for computers and technology improvements; a $395,600 bond for an all-weather track and auditorium upgrades; and a $636,600 bond for gym improvements and other upgrades.</p>
<p>May 6</p>
<p>--$6.6 million Caldwell School District, N.J., school general obligation bonds, for school renovations and technology improvements.</p>
<p>NORTH CAROLINA</p>
<p>May 6</p>
<p>--$71.5 million City of High Point GO bonds for streets and recreation.</p>
<p>--$4.5 million Hoke County water system bonds.</p>
<p>May 20</p>
<p>--$59.5 million Dare County GO bonds for schools.</p>
<p>OHIO</p>
<p>May 6</p>
<p>--Franklin County vote on 0.5 percent sales tax for sports complex.</p>
<p>SOUTH CAROLINA</p>
<p>May 3</p>
<p>--$61 million Lexington County School District 1, GO bonds for schools.</p>
<p>SOUTH DAKOTA</p>
<p>April 1</p>
<p>--$31 million GO bonds for Sioux Falls school district.</p>
<p>--U.S. Municipal Desk, 212-859-1650</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
