<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479947" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Bodies of suicide cult members sent home.</title>
<headline>Bodies of suicide cult members sent home.</headline>
<byline>Len Navarro</byline>
<dateline>SAN DIEGO, Calif. 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Officials on Monday held what they said was their last news conference on the mass suicide of 39 members of the Heaven's Gate cult, saying 11 more bodies had been released to family members.</p>
<p>Only two more families remained to be located, San Diego County Medical Examiner Brian Blackbourne said.</p>
<p>County sheriff's investigator Jerry Lipscomb disclosed that an autopsy of cult leader Marshall Applewhite showed no signs of cancer, refuting a theory that Applewhite led his followers to death because he was dying.</p>
<p>Lipscomb said there was nothing in the more than 11 computers found at the cult's rented mansion that indicated Applewhite had told his followers he had cancer.</p>
<p>The bodies of the cult members were found in a $1.6-million mansion in the exclusive San Diego suburb of Rancho Santa Fe on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Blackbourne said he believed the members died in batches, possibly starting as early as the previous Saturday. The group, which designed computer web sites, believed they would be transported to heaven by a UFO trailing the Hale-Bopp comet.</p>
<p>He said investigators were still looking for relatives of Alfonso Recardo Foster, 44, who was born in Detroit, Michigan, and has three sisters and a brother, and the family of Lindley Ayerheart Pease, 41, who was born in New Hampshire and was believed to have a sister in Palm Springs, California.</p>
<p>If the families cannot be found, the bodies will be cremated and their ashes buried in San Diego, Blackbourne said.</p>
<p>Blackbourne said the last two members to die had taken a drug called Vicodin, the trade name for hydrochordone, a semi-synthetic opiate. Tests on the other bodies so far had shown no trace of the drug.</p>
<p>He had previously said the two were the last to die because their bodies were the only ones not covered in shrouds. Members killed themselves in batches by eating pudding and applesauce laced with Phenobarbital and once they were dead, the living members had covered them in triangular purple shrouds.</p>
<p>The process was repeated until only the final two were left.</p>
<p>Lipscomb also said FBI computer experts had been called in to examine more than 100 computer disks found in the mansion. He said he expected the examination of the computers to take four to six weeks.</p>
<p>In addition, the sheriff's department asked for aid from the FBI's Special Cult Group in helping to learn more about Heaven's Gate and other groups.</p>
<p>Lipscomb discounted rumours that other cults were ready hold their own mass suicides, saying tips received by the county sheriff's department were &quot;bizarre&quot;.</p>
<p>He said his team of investigators were also probing the source of the massive amounts of Phenobarbital -- more than 1,000 pills -- that the cult members used to kill themselves, although he said he did not expect any criminal prosecution to arise from that investigation.</p>
<p>Blackbourne said the final toxicology reports on the victims would be ready on Friday and no official cause of death would be given until then, although he had previously indicated that initial results showed death from either Phenobarbital poisoning or suffocation.</p>
<p>He had said cult members assured death by putting plastic bags over their heads after taking the drug.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN DIEGO, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
