<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479903" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turk court to consider privatisation law objection.</title>
<headline>Turk court to consider privatisation law objection.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's constitutional court is this week to consider a request for the annulment of two articles in the country's privatisation law, state-run Anatolian news agency reported on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The petitition, to be discussed on Wednesday, seeks the cancellation of articles relating to the evaluation of companies slated for privatisation and to the format of sell-off tenders.</p>
<p>The annulment request, which also relates to the creation of evaluation commissions, was made by deputies from two leftist parties who seek alternative procedures.</p>
<p>A fresh draft amendment to the privatisation law has already been presented by the government to parliament for its approval.</p>
<p>On Monday evening, the parliamentary planning and budget commission approved the draft changes redefining the formation and work of evaluation commissions and sell-off tender procedures in detail.</p>
<p>The draft also changes the selection of members on the High Board of Privatisation to include the deputy Prime Minister.</p>
<p>Turkey's Islamist-led government has targeted the acceleration of the country's long-standing privatisation programme as a key element of plans to raise revenues. The constitutional court earlier this year rejected a bid to block the sell-off of Turk Telekom, the centrepiece of the privatisation programme.</p>
<p>-- Ankara newsroom +90-312-446 2940</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
