<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479960" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: February construction spending strongest in nearly a year.</title>
<headline>February construction spending strongest in nearly a year.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Construction spending shot ahead at the fastest rate in nearly a year during February, the Commerce Department said on Tuesday, as warm weather fostered  big gains in both private and publicly financed projects.</p>
<p>Spending jumped 2.3 percent to a record seasonally adjusted annual rate of $603.8 billion after a revised 0.3 percent January rise, when bitter weather slowed building activity. It far exceeded Wall Street economists' forecasts of a smaller 0.9 percent increase in February spending.</p>
<p>Department officials said February posted the strongest rise in monthly spending since a matching 2.3 percent rise in March last year. The last time there was a bigger spending jump was nearly three years ago, in March 1994, when it gained by 3.4 percent.</p>
<p>February construction spending was running nearly 11 percent above the February 1996 rate of $544.6 billion a year.</p>
<p>The government previously reported that January construction spending had risen by 0.4 percent, but it revised that down slightly.</p>
<p>The February pickup in construction activity was virtually across the board in both the private and government-financed sectors, offering further evidence of continuing solid economic growth in the first quarter.</p>
<p>Privately financed construction increased 1.8 percent to $456 billion a year in February following a 0.6 percent gain in January.</p>
<p>Spending on new housing was up 1.2 percent to a rate of $253.7 billion after a slight 0.1 percent rise in January. Construction of non-residential buildings like offices, hotels and hospitals climbed 2.5 percent to $158.5 billion following an even larger 3.2 percent increase in January.</p>
<p>Government spending on construction projects surged 4.1 percent to a rate of $147.9 billion in February after a 0.4 percent fall in January. Spending to build new public housing, schools, highways and streets, sewers and water treatment plants all picked up from January's pace.</p>
<p>After allowing for inflation, total construction spending increased 2.5 percent in February to a seasonally adjusted $522 billion annual rate following a 0.6 percent gain in January, the department said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E61">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E71">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
