<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479995" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Snow buries New England, thousands without power.</title>
<headline>Snow buries New England, thousands without power.</headline>
<byline>Leslie Gevirtz</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A rare spring blizzard buried New England in more than two-feet (0.6 metres) of snow on Tuesday, leaving more than 150,000 people without power and killing at least one person, officials said.</p>
<p>Massachusetts Gov. William Weld declared a state of emergency as roads remained impassable, public transport services were halted and schools closed.</p>
<p>Boston's Logan International Airport was closed indefinitely, stranding hundreds of passengers. Bradley International Airport in Hartford, Connecticut was also shut down because of the snow and poor visibility.</p>
<p>Boston was covered with 24 inches (61 cms) of snow, and at least 12 inches (30 cms) had fallen in parts of southern New Hampshire, Vermont and most of Connecticut and Rhode Island.</p>
<p>In the Catskill region of New York State, which got at least 18 inches (45 cm) of snow, a man aged 36 was killed in a traffic accident that police said was caused by the storm.</p>
<p>&quot;It is still quite a vicious storm and it is continuing,&quot; said Massachusetts Emergency Management Agency executive director Peter LaPorte.</p>
<p>New Hampshire's state Legislature closed for the day.</p>
<p>The National Weather Service reported that snow would continue throughout Tuesday in New England, with snow falling at about one inch (2.5 cm) an hour, along with sustained winds of up to 50 miles an hour (80 kph).</p>
<p>Utility crews worked to restore power service in areas where the heavy, wet snow brought down powerlines.</p>
<p>&quot;We've had a 100 crews on all night and we know 36 crews are headed here from Canada. We're also looking for help from New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Vermont,&quot; Boston Edison spokesman Mike Monahan said. He estimated it would take up to a week to fully restore service to some 50,000 customers.</p>
<p>Other utilities throughout the New England region reported another 100,000 customers without electricity.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
