<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479935" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton to ask FCC to study liquor ad limits.</title>
<headline>Clinton to ask FCC to study liquor ad limits.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton wants the Federal Communications Commission to review the possibility of banning or sharply curbing liquor advertisements on television, the White House said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Clinton, at an event scheduled for 1:15 PM EST (1815 GMT), planned to express concern over last year's decision by the liquor industry to remove a voluntary policy against TV advertising, White House spokesman Mike McCurry said.</p>
<p>Asked why Clinton was seeking a FCC review of the matter, McCurry said: &quot;Since it pertains to television advertising, that's the appropriate contact, and remember, all we're doing is asking them to look into the question.&quot;</p>
<p>Another White House official said Clinton would cast the issue as one of protecting young people from a potential health hazard. The president would ask the FCC to examine if the ads encouraged young people to try drinking, he said.</p>
<p>Clinton has previously advocated curbs on cigarette advertising as part of a concerted administration campaign to discourage young people from smoking.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
