<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479911" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Bank Hapoalim raises dividend for 1996.</title>
<headline>Bank Hapoalim raises dividend for 1996.</headline>
<dateline>TEL AVIV 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bank Hapoalim, Israel's biggest bank, said it would increase its dividend for 1996 to 310.4 million shekels to reflect gains from the forced sale of excess holdings in non-bank companies.</p>
<p>The dividend payment compares with 251.9 million shekels from the previous year.</p>
<p>The gain after taxes recorded by the bank from the sale of its holdings in 1996 was 135 million shekels.</p>
<p>The dividend payout includes these gains plus 26 percent of net profit from regular operations.</p>
<p>Hapoalim's net profit in 1996 totalled 812 million shekels, or 0.66 shekels a share, including the income from the asset sales. Earnings were up 9.2 percent and in line with analysts' expectations.</p>
<p>The bank's operating profit after taxes fell to 469 million shekels from from 543 million shekels in 1995. The decline was mianly due to a big increase in Hapoalim's tax provision to 655 million shekels from 562 million in 1995 and higher operating expenses.</p>
<p>Amiram Sivan, chairman of Hapoalim's managing board, said the bank's net profit accounted for 42.7 percent of the combined profits of Israel's five biggest commercial banks in 1996.</p>
<p>Hapoalim's net return on equity was 11 percent compared with 10.9 percent in 1995.</p>
<p>Profit from financing activities grew as a result of increased in activity in the foreign currency and inflation-linked sectors, forward transactions and other financial activities.</p>
<p>The bank said it increased its capital reserve fund to cover unidentified risks in keeping with its decision to accelerate the pace of these provisions and set aside the entire amount required, rather than spread it out over several years.</p>
<p>Operating and other income rose 3.2 percent as a result of increased customer activity, but income from capital market activity decreased due to the weak market.</p>
<p>Credit to the public increased by 3.7 percent in 1996 to 92.5 billion shekels while deposits rose 8.7 percent to 106.3 billion shekels from 97.8 billion.</p>
<p>Hapoalim attributed the increase in deposits to movement of money into bank accounts last year in the wake of the capital market crisis and to the high yields offered by the unlinked shekel sector.</p>
<p>Total consolidated assets grew 3.8 percent to 155.8 billion shekels.</p>
<p>Shareholders' equity rose 6.6 percent to 7.9 billion shekels at the end of the year.</p>
<p>Assets of the bank's mutual funds totalled 3.8 billion shekels while the assets of its provident funds were 32.7 billion shekels.</p>
<p>($1=3.36 shekels)</p>
<p>- Tel Aviv newsroom, 972-3-537-2211</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEL AVIV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
