<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479966" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Peoples Gas begins customer choice sign-up.</title>
<headline>Peoples Gas begins customer choice sign-up.</headline>
<dateline>PITTSBURGH 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Peoples Natural Gas Co said Tuesday as of today all customers can sign up to select the natural gas supplier of their choice.</p>
<p>Under the utility's Energy Choice Program, customers will be able to buy natural gas from a provider other than their local utility, then have the utility deliver the gas to their homes, the company noted.</p>
<p>Peoples Gas -- the Pennsylvania distribution utility of Consolidated Natural Gas Co -- provides natural gas service to over 317,000 residential, 29,000 commercial and 200 industrial customers in 16 counties in southwestern Pennsylvania.  </p>
<p>It emphasized that if a customer does not want to select another supplier, he or she may choose to continue to purchase natural gas from Peoples Gas.</p>
<p>Natural gas suppliers will begin contacting customers starting today through telemarketing campaigns, direct mailings and door to door solicitation, the company said.</p>
<p>For customers who sign up in April, service will begin in June, it noted.</p>
<p>Last week, State Representatives Frank Tulli Jr. and Mike Veon, along with State Senator Jeff Piccola, announced they were co-sponsoring legislation that would allow natural gas customers throughout the state to select their suppliers.</p>
<p>And earlier last month, the Pennsylvania Public Utility Commission voted in favor of a pilot program submitted by the City of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County to offer customer choice to all of its residents who currently use natural gas.</p>
<p>&quot;We see these efforts as complementary to our own Energy Choice program, and a major step towards bringing customer choice to the entire gas industry,&quot; Peoples Gas President Bill Fox said.</p>
<p>&quot;Since we first announced the Energy Choice Program in February,&quot; Fox said, &quot;our Customer Service Center has received over 1,800 telephone calls from customers interested in obtaining more information about how they can select their own gas suppliers.&quot;</p>
<p>To accommodate the increase in customer calls as well as to provide better customer service, Peoples' Customer Call Service representatives will be available to respond to customer calls from 0700 until 1900 local time Monday through Friday, and from 0800 until noon on Saturdays.</p>
<p>((-- New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610.))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PITTSBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
