<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479926" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ohio scientists create synthetic human chromosome.</title>
<headline>Ohio scientists create synthetic human chromosome.</headline>
<byline>Joanne Kenen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scientists in Ohio said on Monday they had made a synthetic miniature human chromosome, which could generate fresh approaches to the difficult field of gene therapy.</p>
<p>In the April edition of the journal Nature Genetics, a team from Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland and Athersys Inc. report that they were able to create a synthetic &quot;microchromosome&quot; out of elements found naturally in the human body. It is about one-fifth to one-tenth the size of a real human chromosome and contains less genetic material.</p>
<p>&quot;People have been so frustrated by gene therapy, which has not lived up to the hype. The key significance (of the artificial chromosome) is that it gives us a fresh approach to gene therapy,&quot; Huntington Willard, a Case Western geneticist and senior author of the study, said in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>Gene therapy requires introducing a specific gene to target cells to fix a defect, such as cystic fibrosis or a form of muscular dystrophy.</p>
<p>Most attempts so far have involved using an altered virus to carry the gene to the site, with little success. These viruses can sometimes produce an undesired immune response or the gene cannot produce consistently.</p>
<p>The hope is that a synthetic mini-human chromosome could eventually be used to shuttle the desired gene to the site needing repair, although Willard said this &quot;first generation&quot; discovery is only one step toward that goal and more has to be learned about chromosome formation.</p>
<p>Willard said the team was able to synthesize in the lab different DNA components that make up a chromosome. But the scientists did not try to assemble the pieces into a chromosome, but let the cell do that in the lab.</p>
<p>&quot;We let the cell glue the pieces together,&quot; he said, adding that scientists now want to learn how the pieces were assembled so they can customise them for future therapies.</p>
<p>&quot;This novel system is not perfect but it constitutes a major step in the right path to HAC (human artificial chromosome) construction,&quot; Melissa Rosenfeld, a scientist at the National Institutes of Health, wrote in an essay accompanying the journal report.</p>
<p>Chromosomes carry genes but they also contain other elements, including something called centromeres, which play a role in cell division. Willard said the team had created and incorporated centromeres in the artificial chromosomes where past efforts had failed.</p>
<p>&quot;We are already moving ahead to refine the system and begin building an efficient and versatile vehicle for the introduction and stable maintenance of therapeutic genes in human cells,&quot; Gil Van Bokkelsen, president and CEO of the privately-held Athersys, said in a statement.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
