<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="479945" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Telecast relays McVeigh trial to bomb survivors.</title>
<headline>Telecast relays McVeigh trial to bomb survivors.</headline>
<byline>Kieran Murray</byline>
<dateline>OKLAHOMA CITY 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Relatives of the 168 people killed in the Oklahoma City bombing watched a special telecast on Monday of the opening of Timothy McVeigh's trial, taking place about 600 miles (1,000 km) away in Denver.</p>
<p>While many said they were proud they had succeeded in forcing the U.S. judicial system to set up the telecast, they also feared the trial would reopen deep wounds and that their agony was still far from over.</p>
<p>&quot;It'll help, but nothing on earth is going to bring Julie back,&quot; said Bud Welch, whose 23-year-old daughter was among those killed by the huge truck bomb that wrecked the Alfred P. Murrah federal building on April 19, 1995.</p>
<p>Welch said he plans to watch a lot of the trial because he wants to be absolutely certain that McVeigh and fellow defendant Terry Nichols -- who is to be tried separately -- are guilty and, if so, that they acted alone.</p>
<p>He said watching McVeigh on the 26-foot (8-metre) wide screen had brought back memories of the defendant's first appearances at pre-trial hearings, when many victims were appalled by his easy confidence.</p>
<p>&quot;That steel-hard look is kind of piercing,&quot; Welch said.</p>
<p>When the trial last year was moved to Denver in order to guarantee McVeigh and Nichols a fair hearing, survivors and relatives of the victims complained bitterly that their own rights were being trampled on.</p>
<p>Congress responded by passing a law that, for the first time, would allow a closed circuit feed of a federal trial. The telecast was being shown inside a Federal Aviation Administration auditorium on the outskirts of Oklahoma City.</p>
<p>Almost 3,000 people are entitled to see the telecast although the auditorium only has space for about 330 with seats reserved two days in advance on a first-come first-served basis.</p>
<p>Just 62 people were there for Monday's proceedings and only 40 have reserved seats for Tuesday, but a full house is expected once jury selection ends and the trial begins.</p>
<p>Jim Denny, whose 5-year-old son Brandon suffered brain damage and other serious injuries in the bombing, said he will follow news reports on the trial but has no interest in seeing it himself.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if it was on television at our house, we'd be watching kids' videos and watching them dance and sing. That's our priority, that's what we do,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But other families see the painful memories as a price they will have to pay for seeing justice done. For some of those families, a closed circuit feed is not close enough.</p>
<p>&quot;I need to be in Denver. I want to see McVeigh's face when the evidence is introduced,&quot; said Jannie Coverdale, the grandmother of Aaron, 5, and Elijah, 2, who were both killed inside the children's day care centre at the federal building.</p>
<p>Counsellors will be on hand at the FAA auditorium to help family members cope with the emotional stress during the trial.</p>
<p>The fiber optic line which transmits the courtroom action from Denver to Oklahoma City has an encrypted signal to prevent pirating.</p>
<p>U.S. District Court Judge Richard Matsch has control of the two-way closed circuit feed and can shut it down at any time.</p>
<p>He has also hired a retired judge to keep order inside the auditorium, where the usual rules of a federal courtroom -- such as a ban on talking, electronic equipment, food and drink -- will apply throughout the trial.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OKLAHOMA CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
