<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480007" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - New York Times business - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - New York Times business - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York Times reported the following business stories Tuesday:</p>
<p>* The Dow Jones industrials, which lost more than 140 points on Thursday, sank 157.11 points to close at 6,583.48.</p>
<p>* The Supreme Court upheld a Federal law requiring cable television systems to carry local broadcast station signals.</p>
<p>* General Electric agreed to buy a stake in Cablevision's Rainbow Programming Holdings inc, which gives it a stake in Madison Square Garden properties.</p>
<p>* The U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation is examining agreements for Columbia/HCA to acquire some hospitals in northeastern Ohio.</p>
<p>* Personal income rose nine-tenths of one percent in February while personal spending rose three-tenths of one percent.</p>
<p>* Bre-X Minerals shares were halted again as many questions surrounding the company's gold find in Indonesia remained unresolved.</p>
<p>* Bermuda-based PartnerRE said it entered a definitive stock purchase agreement with Swiss Re to buy French reinsurer Societe Anonyme Francaise de Reassurances for $950 million.</p>
<p>* Equifax is expected to announce a deal to buy corporate investigative and consulting firm Kroll Associates.</p>
<p>* ITT said it sold its remaining 4.5 million shares in French telecommunications equipment maker Alcatel Alsthom for about $530 million.</p>
<p>* Ashland and USX-Marathon are seen close to a deal to combine their refining and marketing operations.</p>
<p>* Astoria Financial said it would buy Greater New York Savings Bank for $293 million.</p>
<p>* During the first quarter, average mutual fund investing in American stocks posted its worst performance in over two years.</p>
<p>* Market place: The stock market's tumble on Monday was wide and deep, as efforts to push it higher were crushed by sell orders.</p>
<p>* The U.S. Commerce Department issued a preliminary finding alleging Japanese computer makers NEC Corp and Fujitsu Ltd dumped supercomputers on the U.S. market.</p>
<p>* Entrepreneurs are trying to find ways to help corporate customers avoid high-priced airplane tickets associated with last-minute travel.</p>
<p>((New York newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
