<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480094" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Airlines wary of testing new EU open skies freedom.</title>
<headline>Airlines wary of testing new EU open skies freedom.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Chalmers</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>European airlines are wary of testing new freedoms to fly throughout the bloc since problems such as subsidies, airport congestion and a shortage of slots darken their horizon for now.</p>
<p>But airline executives and analysts expect the impact of more competition to be significant over time.</p>
<p>From Tuesday, carriers from the European Union's 15 countries and the European Economic Area's Norway, Iceland and Liechtenstein can operate domestic services in any of the other 17 without connecting flights from their home markets.</p>
<p>But airlines ranging from German giant Lufthansa AG to tiny Brussels-based Virgin Express play down the impact of the final stage in a decade of liberalisation of the EU aviation market, seeing it as one of many stopovers en route to fully open skies.</p>
<p>&quot;(Aviation) competition already exists. It cannot be expected that the world of European air traffic will totally change all of a sudden on April 1,&quot; said a Lufthansa report.</p>
<p>Lufthansa said airline subsidies, limited competition for airport ground-handling services, poor airport infrastructure, fragmented air traffic control systems and a shortage of landing and take-off slots were the greatest bars to truly open skies.</p>
<p>The removal of capacity restrictions for non-national carriers on others' domestic routes completes a decade of changes which have slashed through a maze of bilateral aviation accords criss-crossing western Europe.</p>
<p>Lufthansa said its domestic market was one of the most prone to the effects of Tuesday's changes.</p>
<p>&quot;The German market is interesting for competitors and is an ideal base for experiments because it is not only Europe's largest market but has a decentralised structure with attractive secondary markets such as Hamburg, Cologne, Duesseldorf, Berlin or Stuttgart,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Lufthansa should know, having seen its 1996 profits drop -- due in part, it said, to the downward pressure on fares from market liberalisation.</p>
<p>Air France plans to test the open skies regime from May 5, challenging a Lufthansa bastion with the launch of a Frankfurt-Berlin service. It also plans a British domestic link-up, possibly in partnership with Jersey European.</p>
<p>The pressure is likely to continue, with the European Commission singling out Germany, France and Italy last year as having domestic markets where scheduled fares remained stubbornly high.</p>
<p>While the Commission has grumbled of possible legal action on fares, European Transport Commissioner Neil Kinnock sees change coming via increased competition.</p>
<p>&quot;It should produce fare reductions in the same way that price cuts have come on main routes between member states when second or third companies and charter operators have offered a challenge,&quot; he told Reuters in a written statement on Tuesday.</p>
<p>But small, independent airlines, seen by many as the big hope for open skies, seem unlikely to rush in just yet.</p>
<p>&quot;I think in the medium term there will be some small opportunities,&quot; Virgin Express's chief executive officer, Jonathan Ornstein, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;But in the short term, we are committed for the rest of the year,&quot; he said, adding that among the &quot;small opportunities&quot; could be flights linking Barcelona and Madrid next year.</p>
<p>British Midland is also wary, seeing as a warning to others the mixed success of British Airways efforts to compete on domestic services using TAT in France and Deutsche BA in Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;We have no plans to do that at the moment. We would regard British Airways as a very formidable competitor and an efficient airline and we have noticed the experience they have had with these services,&quot; chairman Sir Michael Bishop said recently.</p>
<p>But Ornstein added that while European airlines might not be excited about April 1 itself, the longer-term effect was likely to be more turbulent for airlines than U.S deregulation in 1978.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the effect will be huge over time. While we had some inefficient carriers (in the United States) it was nothing compared with the extent of what there is here,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Asked whether deregulation would have an impact in the key French market, Chris Avery, airline analyst at Paribas Capital Markets, commented: &quot;In the medium term, yes. On Day One it's unlikely there will be any unleashing as occurred in the United States in 1978. But deregulation will continue to come and it's a tide that cannot be reversed.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I76400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
