<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480064" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Germans warned of BSE in asparagus in April fool joke.</title>
<headline>Germans warned of BSE in asparagus in April fool joke.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A newspaper played a particularly cruel April Fool's trick on nervous German consumers on Tuesday, when it reported that mad cow disease had crossed to the humble asparagus when a genetic experiment got out of hand.</p>
<p>Just as fears over bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE) in Germany looked set to die down, the Tageszeitung daily said asparagus plants thought to be infected with the disease had been stolen from a laboratory.</p>
<p>The paper said scientists had managed to grow &quot;turbo asparagus&quot; --- thicker and longer than normal -- by boosting plants with a cattle growth hormone.</p>
<p>It said three rats had died after eating the asparagus and that examination of their brains had shown signs similar to those seen in the brains of cows with BSE.</p>
<p>The paper said Stuttgart police had launched a search for 36 plants which had gone missing, and asked grocers to be on the lookout for particularly large asparagus.</p>
<p>It quoted consumer groups as advising Germans, who are particularly wary of genetically engineered foods, to buy only thin asparagus.</p>
<p>Germany took the toughest stance last year on the need to protect public health against BSE when the British government said it appeared humans could contracted a fatal brain illness, Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease, from eating infected beef.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
