<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480017" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Doctor espouses health despite modern medicine.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Doctor espouses health despite modern medicine.</headline>
<byline>Janie Gabbett-Lee</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Broccoli? Yes. Marijuana? Maybe. The evening news? No way.</p>
<p>That is the advice from Dr. Andrew Weil, whose latest book, &quot;8 Weeks to Optimum Health,&quot; became a No. 1 best seller a week after its March 14 launch. His previous book, &quot;Spontaneous Healing,&quot; has remained a top best seller since it was published two years ago.</p>
<p>Not bad for a Harvard medical school graduate who was denounced in the early 1970's by then Vice President Spiro Agnew for his views on illegal drugs in his book &quot;The Natural Mind,&quot; and whose book &quot;From Chocolate to Morphine&quot; was nearly banned from schools and libraries in the early 1980's.</p>
<p>But this is the 1990's. Weil no longer writes about drugs. He writes about health. And to him it is a seamless, even obvious, progression.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not in any way disown that stuff on drugs I wrote,&quot; Weil, who once wrote that alcohol was more dangerous than heroin, told Reuters in an interview. &quot;Drugs act as triggers or releasers of inner experiences. I think what I say now about healing is very analagous to that, that healing is something that is intrinsic.&quot;</p>
<p>On the debate over legalizing medicinal uses of marijuana, he said, &quot;I've studied marijuana for a very long time and it is so non-toxic relative to drugs we use in medicine that you may as well look for ways of using it medically.&quot;</p>
<p>TRAINING DOCTORS TO APPECIATE SPIRITUALITY</p>
<p>Weil, director of the Program in Integrative Medicine at the University of Arizona, the nation's first program to train doctors to integrate conventional and alternative medicine, said: &quot;All our problems come down to how we are training our doctors. We do not take account of human beings as mental, emotional, spiritual beings as well as physical bodies.&quot;</p>
<p>His eight-week program, which he guides volunteers through on his popular website (http://www.drweil.com), includes not only dietary, vitamin and exercise recommendations but also suggestions to breathe deeply, appreciate beauty, listen to your favorite music and spend time with people who make you feel happy. It does not recommend the nightly news.</p>
<p>&quot;Many people listen to the news addictively and unconsciously ... I think it often makes people feel very angry, powerless and frustrated and I also think people get addicted to that feeling,&quot; he said. By the eighth week, his program suggests a week long &quot;news fast.&quot;</p>
<p>Weil is a big fan of organically grown foods.  He warns against fruits and vegetables a nonprofit research group says are heavily contaminated with pesticides, including peaches, strawberries, bell peppers, spinach, cherries, celery, Mexican cantaloupes, apples, green beans, cucumbers and Chilean grapes. He adds to the list wheat, soybeans, potatoes and button mushrooms.</p>
<p>LONG LIST OF WARNINGS</p>
<p>He also warns against the harmful effects of chlorinated water, electric blankets, heating pads, electric clock radios, X-rays, computer monitors without protective screens, electric blow driers, living near power transmission lines, standing in front of the microwave oven while it is on and the sun.</p>
<p>There is some good news, however.  It turns out the best things in life really might be free and easy.  Weil's No. 1 suggestions for optimum health are: breathing and being happy.</p>
<p>His book includes a number of breathing exercises that he rates at the top of all his suggestions. He also sees positive relationships with others as extremely healthy.</p>
<p>&quot;I do know for sure that connectedness is necessary to well-being. You can eat as much salmon and broccoli as you can, take antioxidants for the rest of your life, breathe terrifically and walk all over the earth, but if you are disconnected you will not achieve optimum health.&quot;</p>
<p>Even the good doctor falls off the health food wagon occassionally. He admitted to lapses including pizza, Coca Cola and dark chocolate.</p>
<p>Blushing slightly around his full white beard after that confession, Weil added, &quot;I don't think it is healthy to be obsessive about health.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
