<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480042" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy defends navy, presses on with Albania force.</title>
<headline>Italy defends navy, presses on with Albania force.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy denied on Tuesday that its navy had rammed a boat crowded with Albanian refugees and said the sinking would not alter its plans to lead a multinational security force to the troubled Balkan country.</p>
<p>Defence Minister Beniamino Andreatta told parliament he had invited Albanian navy experts to join investigations into last Friday's disaster, in which Tirana says at least 83 people drowned, and promised a full and open inquiry.</p>
<p>But he dismissed claims in some newspapers and from some sources in Albania that the collision in the Adriatic happened because the corvette Sibilla bore down on the refugee boat, which had set out for Italy from the rebel-held port of Vlore.</p>
<p>&quot;It is absolutely shameful even to think that the Italian vessel had the deliberate intention of ramming the Albanian boat,&quot; Andreatta told a joint session of the defence and foreign affairs commissions of the Senate (upper house).</p>
<p>He said the boat had been badly overcrowded and had swung abruptly into the path of the Sibilla when the corvette moved alongside to order it to return to Albania.</p>
<p>The sinking entailed the first known loss of life since Italy began controversial naval interdiction patrols late last month after some 13,000 Albanians fled to Italian shores in an uncontrolled exodus from their country's armed upheaval.</p>
<p>It has cast a cloud over preparations by Italy to lead a security force to protect a European humanitarian relief mission to Albania, rocked by an uprising that has put rebels and lawless gunmen in control of towns throughout the south.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Romano Prodi reaffirmed on Tuesday that the sinking would not stop Italy from proceeding with the force despite threats to the safety of Italian soldiers expressed in Vlore and rumblings of political opposition at home.</p>
<p>&quot;The Albanian people know that Italy is an indispensable partner in rebuilding their own country,&quot; he told La Stampa newspaper. &quot;I know that the Albanians expect concrete help from us and we will give it to them,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Andreatta said he would meet Albanian Defence Minister Shaqir Vukaj in Rome later on Tuesday to discuss the sinking.</p>
<p>The talks will also focus on plans for the security force deployment ahead of a meeting in the Italian capital on Wednesday of senior defence officials from countries that have said they are ready to contribute men.</p>
<p>Andreatta said the force, expected to secure the ports of Durres and Vlore as well as Tirana airport for foreign aid deliveries, would consist of 4,000 to 6,000 men.</p>
<p>He said France, Spain, Portugal, Greece, Turkey, Austria, Romania, Hungary, Slovenia, Denmark and Sweden had all expressed a willingness to contribute.</p>
<p>The force, the bulk of it Italian, received United Nations Security Council approval last Friday and was given the go ahead by the Albanian parliament on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;Lack of prudence by public opinion and the press (about the sinking) has certainly aggravated the risks for the mission. That has meant committing more men and taking additional precautions,&quot; Andreatta said.</p>
<p>The Italian navy rescued 34 people in Friday's shipwreck and recovered four bodies. Albanian authorities said after talking to survivors that at least 79 more people were missing, most of them crammed below decks when the boat capsized and sank.</p>
<p>Andreatta said the aged coastal patrol craft had been stolen from the port of Sarande by &quot;criminals&quot; on March 26 and suggested it was crewed by unqualified seamen running an illegal emigration racket.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
