<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480015" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Spring blizzard batters northeast U.S., kills one.</title>
<headline>Spring blizzard batters northeast U.S., kills one.</headline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>A spring storm lashed the U.S. East coast on Monday, pummeling residents from Maine to Maryland with snow, rain, hail, and howling wind and leaving one dead and thousands without power.</p>
<p>More than 18 inches (45 cm) of wet snow fell in New York state, where the death of a 36-year-old man in a Catskill mountain region traffic accident was blamed on the storm.</p>
<p>Further south in Sussex County, New Jersey, more than a foot (34 cm) of snow blanketed the region and a painful mix of sleet, rain and snow pummeled New York City and Long Island as the storm slowly lumbered east toward the Atlantic.</p>
<p>Philadelphia reported 8 inches (20 cm) of snow and it continued to snow into the night in Wilmington, Delaware, and Baltimore, Maryland.</p>
<p>Power outtages plagued New England as the National Weather Service recorded winds of 65 mph (105 km) off the coast of Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Northeast Utilities reported 14,000 customers without power in Connecticut and another 4,000 without power in Western Massachsetts. Boston Edison said some 2,000 of its customers without power.</p>
<p>Public Service of New Hampshire also reported some 1,000 customers without power. Spokesmen for all three utilities said they expected the number of outtages to grow as the storm continued to pummel the region with heavy, wet snow bringing down powerlines.</p>
<p>Many schools in the region, which had closed early on Monday, said they would cancel classes on Tuesday as well as the storm showed no signs of abating.</p>
<p>Massachusetts, New Hampshire and New York State police reported dozens of traffic accidents due to the severe weather.</p>
<p>&quot;Cars are all over the place and there are lots of accidents,&quot; Trooper Andrew Lindeman said. &quot;The interstates are a mess and I am sure the back roads are too.&quot;</p>
<p>Bradley International Airport in Hartford, Conn. closed and Boston's Logan International Airport reported flight delays of up to an hour. Many airlines cancelled flights altogether, said a spokeswoman for Massport, which operates Logan.</p>
<p>Marine storm warnings were also in effect from Long Island to the Gulf of Maine as the weather service expected wind gusts to reach near hurricane force at times off-shore.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
