<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480027" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USDA sees possible record U.S. soybean crop.</title>
<headline>USDA sees possible record U.S. soybean crop.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said on Monday that good weather this growing season could push U.S. soybean production to an all-time record.</p>
<p>&quot;If we have normal weather, it could give us the highest production ever,&quot; Glickman said in a speech at an agriculture policy conference.</p>
<p>He spoke after the USDA announced estimates earlier Monday showing U.S. farmers plan to plant 68.8 million acres of soybeans this year, the most since 1980. &quot;Soybeans was perhaps the big surprise,&quot; Glickman said, adding that the USDA estimate was &quot;above and beyond&quot; any industry expectations.  </p>
<p>The report also showed that U.S. soybean stocks have fallen to a 20-year low, Glickman said.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices can be expected to remain strong although the prospects of a record crop could take some steam out of the market,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>U.S. farmers are responding to strong global demand for corn and soybeans and reducing their crops of wheat and cotton this year, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;By and large, things look pretty good out there,&quot; Glickman said, referring to the overall outlook for U.S. farm production this year.  </p>
<p>Glickman also said the sign-up for the Conservation Reserve Program, which ended last Friday, was &quot;very strong.&quot;</p>
<p>The department will announce later this week how many acres were bid for the program, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The new program will no longer be used to control supply and demand,&quot; he said. &quot;From here on out, it remains and is, a conservation program. It will focus on preventing soil erosion, protecting wildlife habitat.&quot;</p>
<p>On the controversial issue of downsizing the USDA, Glickman said he had not approved any additional reorganization plans. &quot;As I told Congress and others, there will be no surprises,&quot; he said. &quot;There has been nothing implemented or formally approved&quot; pending the budget negotiation process, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The bottom line here is to figure out functionally what we want these offices do before we decide how many and in what capacity they will be around,&quot; he said. USDA officials plan to meet with White House and congressional leaders during the next four to six weeks to talk about the role of USDA's farm offices throughout the nation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100223">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
