<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480077" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian Socialists on ropes, government hangs on.</title>
<headline>Belgian Socialists on ropes, government hangs on.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Lovell</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgium's Francophone Socialist Party (PS) is on the ropes after a former party president was charged with corruption, but analysts said on Tuesday they did not see an immediate threat to the country's ruling coalition.</p>
<p>The PS is part of Belgium's four-party centre-left coalition government that also includes Dutch-speaking Socialists and Christian Democratic parties.</p>
<p>Only if the bribery scandal that resulted in the charges of passive corruption against Guy Spitaels spreads to other members of the party hierarchy could the coalition find itself disintegrating, they added.</p>
<p>&quot;If the affair is confined to Spitaels then the PS will survive and so will the government,&quot; Lieven Dewinter, Professor of Political Science at Leuven Catholic University, said.</p>
<p>&quot;But if it goes any higher to (current PS president Philippe) Bousquin, then the party will be in a crisis and so will the government,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>The charges against Spitaels stem from kickbacks allegedly paid to the PS in the late 1980s by French aerospace firm Dassault in return for a contract to refit Belgian air force F-16s. Spitaels has denied any wrongdoing.</p>
<p>Several prominent PS officials have already been charged in connection with the alleged bribes, and in February Spitaels had his parliamentary immunity from prosecution lifted and he resigned as president of the Walloon regional parliament.</p>
<p>Bousquin has repeatedly denied any knowledge of the alleged bribes.</p>
<p>Some 30 million Belgian francs ($900,000) has been found in secret party bank accounts in Luxembourg.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no way this government is going to give up yet,&quot; Helmut Gauss, Professor of Political Science at Ghent University, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to get ready for the single European Union currency. In order to do that we have to have (Prime Minister Jean-Luc) Dehaene. No one else has the authority,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Both analysts said that if the PS went to the polls now it would be wiped out.</p>
<p>But national elections are not due until late 1999, and the party will cling to its position in the coalition in the hope that short voter memories and internal reorganisation will give it a new lease of life.</p>
<p>However, analysts agreed that the coalition is unlikely to last the whole of its term.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe there will be a general election in 1998,&quot; Dewinter said. &quot;The government cannot go to the polls now, it is empty-handed. In one year it will have the single currency decision and will be able to show progress in reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;Leaving it until 1999, even if it could, would mean holding four sets of elections at the same time -- national, regional, senate and European Parliament. That would be too much to handle and could cause real problems,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The analysts said it was possible that, if the Dassault scandal and an unrelated but similar affair concerning Italian helicopter manufacturer Agusta proved too much, Dehaene could evict the PS and bring in the francophone Liberals (PRL).</p>
<p>The PRL has already offered just this solution, but Dehaene has shown no interest.</p>
<p>However, the government is also coming under pressure from workers protesting at job losses and lack of employment creation as it, in common with other EU nations, tightens its budgetary belt in preparation for the start of the single money in 1999.</p>
<p>There have already been street protests, and more are planned. If they gather pace and become more focused they could threaten the currency project and even the government.</p>
<p>&quot;A mass movement could do it. The Socialists could see the possibility to regain face by backing the protests and bringing down the government,&quot; Gauss said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
