<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480057" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Calls emerge for new German &quot;Alliance for Jobs&quot;.</title>
<headline>Calls emerge for new German &quot;Alliance for Jobs&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Federation of German Trade Unions (DGB) and the labour wing of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian Democrats (CDU) called on Tuesday for renewed efforts to reach a broad pact to create jobs.</p>
<p>With 4.7 million people out of work, the highest level in Germany since 1933, they said it was time to put differences aside and resurrect a failed effort by government, industry and unions to work together to boost employment.</p>
<p>&quot;It is high time that all large social organisations and political parties live up to their responsibilities to reduce unemployment,&quot; Ursula Engelen-Kefer, DGB deputy vice president, told German Radio.</p>
<p>Trade unions initiated the &quot;Alliance for Jobs&quot; talks with an offer of wage restraint in exchange for job guarantees from employers. Talks collapsed early last year without results.</p>
<p>Engelen-Kefer said unions were still ready to play a constructive role in carrying out necessary social reforms, but rejected &quot;pure capitalist&quot; methods such as a recent failed hostile takeover bid by industry group Krupp for rival Thyssen.</p>
<p>Under intense political pressure to abandon its hostile bid, a rare move in Germany, Krupp agreed to settle for a merger of the carbon steel activities of the two companies.</p>
<p>But even the narrower steel merger would cost some 6,600 jobs over the next four years and add to the unemployment in the Ruhr industrial region, which at over 15 percent is already well above the national average.</p>
<p>&quot;As trade unions, we will take (in social reforms),&quot; Engelen-Kefer said. &quot;But not if it means simple reductions, restructuring on the backs of workers.&quot;</p>
<p>Should talks on an &quot;Alliance for Jobs&quot; resume, she said it would be up to employers to present concrete proposals to match the offer made by labour.</p>
<p>The CDA labour wing of Kohl's conservative CDU called for a &quot;social contract for full employment&quot; and in a 30-point proposal called for pay rises below inflation, more part-time work, and elimination of overtime.</p>
<p>It also urged measures to encourage hiring long-term unemployed at levels below starting salaries in existing wage contracts and called on industry to do more to develop new products and services.</p>
<p>Wolfgang Clement, Social Democratic (SPD) economics minister in North Rhine-Westphalia state, warned of social unrest should Germany's unemployment remain at record levels.</p>
<p>Clement also appealed in a newspaper interview to political parties to agree on a &quot;national alliance for jobs&quot;. He said &quot;concrete action&quot; was required, as a &quot;nice chat at the round table&quot; would not be useful.</p>
<p>-- William Boston, Bonn Newsroom, 49 228 26097 150</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
