<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480018" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Little houses, little houses make suburban history.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Little houses, little houses make suburban history.</headline>
<byline>Jon Kalish</byline>
<dateline>LEVITTOWN, N.Y. 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A half-century has passed since the first veterans of the Second World War moved into the rows of identical houses built on farmland 40 miles (65 km) east of New York City and created a community that become an internationally known symbol of suburbia.</p>
<p>While many elderly people living in Levittown complain of high property taxes today, they still say their homes were, as they were hyped at the time, &quot;the buy of the century.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It's been a great place to live. It really has,&quot; said Abe Selsky, who raised three children here with his wife Sue. &quot;It looked like a wilderness to me when I came out here from the Bronx. I was living in an apartment and it was a new experience to live in a private home. All of us veterans came to do the same thing: bring our children up as best we could.&quot;</p>
<p>Selsky bought the 4-1/2 room house for $8,400.  Like other residents, he expanded the house as his family grew.</p>
<p>Many old-timers here are struggling to remain because of local school taxes that have climbed from a few hundred dollars a year in the late 1940's to several thousand today. Still, Levittowners are in the midst of a year-long celebration of the community's 50th anniversary.</p>
<p>When it first opened, nay-sayers predicted it would become a blue-collar slum and lower property values in neighbouring villages in affluent Nassau County. But the severe housing shortage at the time convinced the local zoning board to allow the Levitt family to build homes without basements, a concept branded as &quot;unthinkable&quot; at the time.</p>
<p>COLD WAR PLAYED ROLE</p>
<p>The politics of the Cold War also had a role in the creation of Levittown, according to Barbara Kelly, a Hofstra University history professor who wrote &quot;Expanding the American Dream: Building and Rebuilding Levittown.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They were provided with housing, in part, to keep them from major protests and to keep them from becoming socialists at a time when the socialists were still trying to make inroads into American labour,&quot; Kelly said. &quot;And as William Levitt was fond of saying, 'No man who owns his house and lot can be a communist. He has too much to do.'&quot;</p>
<p>The Levitt family put up more than 17,000 Cape Cods and ranch houses between 1947 and 1951. The first houses were offered as rentals. When the homes were offered for sale, all it took was $100 in banking fees and the ability to handle a monthly mortgage payment of around $60.</p>
<p>Levitt is credited with revolutionising home building by using an assembly line process. It was a technique he learned building military housing during the war. Rather than the product moving, as it did in a factory, workers went down the block repeating the same 26 basic building tasks at every house. Each worker did one particular construction job, such as framing, roofing, flooring, plumbing or electrical work.</p>
<p>A statue of Levitt is to be erected in a park near the local library as part of the 50th anniversary celebration.</p>
<p>At a recent dinner that was part of the anniversary celebration, residents reminisced about the 1950's when neighbours took part in what was the suburban equivalent of a barn-raising: men would help each other put additional bedrooms and other extensions on their homes. Few of the original, unexpanded Levitt homes exist today. Most houses sell for around $150,000, although a few with extensive improvements go for as high as $300,000.</p>
<p>FEELINGS OF PRIDE MIXED WITH GUILT</p>
<p>Although there is much pride in the survival of this prototype for post-war suburban development, Levittown has long been stigmatized by a covenant that existed during its early years excluding sales of homes to African Americans.</p>
<p>The covenant, which was a common practice in the 1940's, was repudiated in the 1950's, but it &quot;has followed us through the years,&quot; concedes Louise Cassano, a life-long resident involved in 50th anniversary activities.</p>
<p>&quot;It was an unfortunate thing that took place at the time,&quot; Cassano said. &quot;We look back at it with regret. We're not proud of it but it was a part of our history.&quot;</p>
<p>Peter Hales, a cultural historian at the University of Illinois in Chicago who has studied Levittown, said that just as it was a &quot;celebrity community,&quot; enabling America to conceive of what it could be in the postwar, the town also became a symbol of what America did not want to become.</p>
<p>Although the covenant no longer exists, few African American families have settled in Levittown over the years.</p>
<p>During the late 1960's and early 1970's, Levittown residents were famous for their enthusiastic support of the Vietnam War. Like most of Nassau County, Levittown is overwhelmingly Republican today.</p>
<p>It is no small irony that a community that was made possible by federal programmes is politically opposed to government spending. And after two generations of Levittowners have benefited from a quality public school education, it is also ironic that local school taxes have left seniors in dire economic straits.</p>
<p>Some of the elderly rent out the attic dormers that their children grew up in to supplement fixed incomes. The annual rent on a one-bedroom apartment in Levittown now tops $7,000, about the same amount it took to buy a house 50 years ago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LEVITTOWN, N.Y."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
