<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480083" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy hard-left party opposes Albania mission.</title>
<headline>Italy hard-left party opposes Albania mission.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy's hard-left Communist Refoundation party, a key ally of Prime Minister Romano Prodi, said on Tuesday it opposed sending a multinational force to Albania and threatened to vote against the move in parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;The proposed military mission...would be absolutely mistaken in the current conditions,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>The party leadership said Italian troops, due to lead a multinational force to ensure security for aid shipments, faced hostility after a collision between an Albanian boat and an Italian military ship on Friday in which 83 Albanians died.</p>
<p>Italy has been patrolling the Adriatic between Albania and its shores to deter refugees after some 13,000 crossed in old and often unseaworthy ships to escape chaos sparked by the collapse of shady investment schemes.</p>
<p>Communist Refoundation said the patrols should now stop.</p>
<p>The international force, which has been approved by the United Nations but has not yet been assembled, could also give the impression of shoring up President Sali Berisha, it said.</p>
<p>Rebels in southern Albania, now largely outside government control, blame Berisha for the crisis and want his resignation.</p>
<p>&quot;For these reasons, if the (Italian) government digs in its heels and insists on setting up this military force immediately, Communist Refoundation will oppose it,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Parliamentary sources said they expected votes in both houses of parliament this week on the planned military mission, which Defence Minister Beniamino Andreatta said earlier could include forces from France, Spain, Portugal, Greece, Turkey, Austria, Romania, Hungary, Slovenia, Denmark and Sweden.</p>
<p>Prodi's centre-left government relies on Communist Refoundation for a majority in the lower house of parliament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
