<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480008" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Choosing Oklahoma bomb jury is slow process.</title>
<headline>Choosing Oklahoma bomb jury is slow process.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Croft</byline>
<dateline>DENVER 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Choosing 12 impartial jurors to decide the fate of the man accused of blowing up the Oklahoma City federal office building will be a long, slow process if the first day of the trial is any pointer.</p>
<p>Only six potential jurors were questioned by U.S. District Judge Richard Matsch and lawyers for both sides on Monday, the first day of the long-awaited trial of Timothy McVeigh in a heavily-guarded federal courthouse in Denver.</p>
<p>The 28-year-old Gulf War veteran could face the death penalty if found guilty of destroying the Alfred P. Murrah building with a massive truck bomb on April 19, 1995, killing 168 people and wounding more than 500 in the worst attack against civilians on U.S. soil.</p>
<p>Matsch and the attorneys spent up to an hour questioning each prospective juror from an initial pool of 1,000 about their exposure to the heavy publicity in the case, their views on the government and their position on the death penalty.</p>
<p>&quot;This may be a job you don't want,&quot; chief defence attorney Stephen Jones told one potential juror.</p>
<p>Jurors sat behind a screen and were identified only by a number to protect their privacy.</p>
<p>Defence lawyers fear that heavy media coverage of the bomb investigation has poisoned potential jurors against McVeigh and are expected to seek to disqualify those they think have already made up their minds.</p>
<p>Several potential jurors said they had been deeply moved by the tragedy. One said she was &quot;in shock&quot; when she saw pictures of the destroyed building on the day of the bombing and later sent a check to the Red Cross to help bomb victims.</p>
<p>But only one had heard of news accounts that McVeigh had allegedly confessed to his attorneys that he planted the bomb. McVeigh's attorneys unsuccessfully sought a delay in the trial last week because of the news stories which they have denied.</p>
<p>The federal courthouse in Denver, where the trial was moved because of doubts whether McVeigh could get a fair trial in Oklahoma City, was under tight security. Concrete barricades surrounded the building, police patrolled the area and visitors had to pass through two metal detectors. Hundreds of journalists prowled the courthouse complex.</p>
<p>The man at the centre of attention was seemingly oblivious to all the fuss. McVeigh, wearing blue shirt and khaki pants, looked relaxed as he read juror questionnaires and talked animatedly with his lawyers, smiling occasionally.</p>
<p>McVeigh is charged with the &quot;use of a weapon of mass destruction&quot; and the murder of eight federal officials. A second defendant, his former Army buddy Terry Nichols, will be tried separately later.</p>
<p>The start of the trial reopened emotional scars for survivors and relatives of the 168 victims, who included 19 children. Some relatives had reserved seats in court while others watched a telecast at an Oklahoma City auditorium.</p>
<p>Tom Kight, whose stepdaughter Frankie Merrell, 23, died in the blast, said the family was still haunted by her loss. &quot;Yesterday was a difficult day because it was Easter. We were recalling hiding Easter eggs when Frankie was small.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DENVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
