<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480096" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Germany sends 30 Bosnian children home to Sarajevo.</title>
<headline>Germany sends 30 Bosnian children home to Sarajevo.</headline>
<byline>Cordula Tutt</byline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany on Tuesday sent home 30 Bosnian children, brought out of the besieged city of Sarajevo five years ago, as the repatriation of thousands of Bosnian refugees gathered pace.</p>
<p>Although Germany has come under mounting criticism for the forcible repatriations, a United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) spokesman said he agreed with the return of the children.</p>
<p>&quot;From the refugee protection point of view we have no objections to the return of these Bosnian orphans,&quot; Stefan Teloeken, UNHCR spokesman in Germany, told Reuters Television. &quot;This is no deportation.&quot;</p>
<p>The children, some of them orphans, are aged between five and 10 and have been living in three children's homes in the state of Saxony-Anhalt. They were flown to Sarajevo, where they are to be accommodated for now in a children's home.</p>
<p>One other child, due to travel with the group, was suffering from pneumonia and will follow later.</p>
<p>Karsten Knolle, a member of the Saxony-Anhalt state assembly who brought the children to Germany at the start of the Bosnian civil war in 1992, said Bosnia was using the children as propaganda to show that everything had returned to normal there.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a scandal... The adults should have been sent home first and the children last,&quot; Knolle said.</p>
<p>But a spokesman for Saxony-Anhalt's social affairs ministry said the initiative for the return of the children had come from their guardians in Bosnia and not Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;They (the Bosnian guardians) have the same right as the parents have. Of course one could not deny the parents or guardians their right to bring their children back home,&quot; Adrian Teetz told Reuters Television.</p>
<p>Although UNHCR spokesman Teloeken defended the case, he still criticised Germany's policy of repatriating refugees without regard for where they came from in Bosnia.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of them (the Bosnians in Germany) are Moslems from the Bosnian Serb entity, the Republika Srpska. They cannot return home because of the situation there. But they also cannot return to other parts of the country because living conditions are not good enough,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>German officials have decided to send back single people and those without children first, but UNHCR says a refugee's home region should be the most important factor.</p>
<p>The interior ministries of Germany's 16 states are due to meet in June to discuss the issue.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel said on Saturday he would visit Bosnia to try to improve the way refugees were dealt with when they returned home.</p>
<p>Kinkel's predecessor, Hans-Dietrich Genscher, and other public figures appealed last Friday for changes in the practice of forcibly repatriating Bosnian refugees. They said the current policy could lead to increased tensions in Bosnia and was damaging Germany's international image.</p>
<p>They singled out for criticism the deportation last week of a group of Bosnian refugees, who they said included pregnant women and sick people, from Berlin and Bavaria.</p>
<p>Germany took in more than 340,000 Bosnian refugees, more than the rest of the European Union put together.</p>
<p>In the last few months around 20,000 have returned home of their own accord. Around 95 have been forcibly repatriated.</p>
<p>Over 60,000 more have received letters ordering them to leave, or will receive them in the next few days, according to figures provided by the federal states.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
