<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480052" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French capital markets closing report.</title>
<headline>French capital markets closing report.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>French bond futures failed to recover from a weak start on Tuesday and followed Bunds lower in a quiet but gloomy session and traders saw little prospect of significant gains ahead of key U.S. jobs data due on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's grey. There are no cash buyers and no-one can see why the market should climb,&quot; one trader said. &quot;The market will remain on the defensive until Friday.&quot;</p>
<p>The June bond future settled down 0.82 at 127.44 and dipped to 127.30 on GLOBEX after a stronger than expected rise in a U.S. purchasing managers hit bond markets. However a bounce in U.S. bonds provided brief respite, pushing it back to 127.50.  </p>
<p>Analysts said the drop in the prices paid index in the purchasing managers report to 50.9 from 55.1 mitigated the strength of the activity data, limiting bond declines.</p>
<p>The trader said, however, the generally pessimistic mood was based on the fact investors were still expecting the U.S. Federal Reserve to follow up last week's rate rise with stronger measures in the months to come to try and slow the pace of economic growth.</p>
<p>Traders said the next important support level for the June contract would be 127.24, the low hit on March 20, before a return to 127.00.  </p>
<p>The French market followed German bonds closely on Tuesday, the spread between 10-year French and German yields remaining stable at minus 11 basis points.</p>
<p>With the front of the curve providing relative sanctuary in current turbulent environment, the French yield curve continued to steepen. The gap between two and 10-year yields climbed six basis points on Tuesday.</p>
<p>June PIBOR was little changed at 96.61 while the franc remained solid against the mark at 3.3668 compared with 3.3667 late on Monday.  </p>
<p>The Treasury announced it would be selling 20 to 22 billion francs of OATs on Thursday which would be the smallest OAT auction so far this year. It also broadened the number of lines on offer to three for the first time this year.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't feel overly bearish and the smaller amount should make life reasonably comfortable, but it never bodes well when they spread the load so much,&quot; a bond analyst said.</p>
<p>The Treasury will be selling the benchmark 5.5 percent 2007 OAT, the 6.75 percent 2004 OAT and the 2009 TEC 10 variable rate bond. The 2004 OAT is the cheapest to deliver bond for both June and September French bond futures contracts.  </p>
<p>Iain Lindsay, senior bond analyst at Credit Lyonnais, said the heavy flow of coupon payments on OATs in April should also help the auction.</p>
<p>He said OAT coupon repayments during the month, including Ecu OATs, amounted to some 47 billion francs which was &quot;a meaningful figure&quot;.</p>
<p>Lindsay also said most of the coupon repayments were on OATs maturing from 2003 and natural holders of long dated bonds would be more likely to recycle flows at the long end of the curve.</p>
<p>-- David Clarke, Paris Newsroom +331 4221 5542</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
