<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480001" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Debt, equity underwriting over $273 bln in Q1 -SDC.</title>
<headline>Debt, equity underwriting over $273 bln in Q1 -SDC.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. stock and bond underwriting rose during the first quarter, with overall issuance of domestic debt and equity exceeding $273 billion compared to $244.9 billion in the year-ago quarter, according to Securities Data Co.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch was the leading underwriter of domestic debt and equity in the first quarter, Securities Data said. The firm took a 16 percent share of the domestic public underwriting business in the first quarter, responsible 312 issues with total proceeds of $44.4 billion, it said.  </p>
<p>Goldman, Sachs ranked second, after lead-managing $33.2 billion in debt and equity from 290 issues this quarter, while Salomon Brothers had the third highest level of underwritings, with over $29.8 billion, Securities Data said.</p>
<p>Straight debt issuance rose but common stock and initial public offerings fell, the company said.</p>
<p>Straight debt issuance rose more than 20 percent in the quarter, compared to year-ago period, Securities Data said.</p>
<p>In this area, Merrill Lynch was the lead manager with $22.4 billion from 111 deals in the quarter. J.P. Morgan placed second with over $21 billion from 167 issues.  </p>
<p>Domestic corporate bond high-yield debt issuance exceeded $8.2 billion in the current quarter, and Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette was the leading underwriter, it said.</p>
<p>But common stock underwriting fell seven percent to $21.2 billion from 303 deals in the first quarter, compared to nearly $23 billion on 328 issues in the year-ago first quarter, the company said.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch, which ranked fifth in equity underwriting during the first quarter of 1996, led the rest in this area during 1997's first quarter, it said.  </p>
<p>The firm was responsible for $3.65 billion in activity from 29 deals, Securities Data said.</p>
<p>IPO issuance declined by more than 30 percent from the first-quarter 1996 levels, to $5.9 billion from $8.26 billion, it said. Securities Data said this was the lowest level since the first quarter of 1995.</p>
<p>The average size of the deal also fell by more than 11 percent to $43 million from a year ago, it said.</p>
<p>Morgan Stanley was the first in IPO issuance with $886 million from 10 deals, it said.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch also posted the most disclosed fees in the first quarter, generating $336.4 million from 312 issues, it said. This compared to the firm's $261 million in fees in last year's quarter from 289 deals.</p>
<p>-- New York newsdesk 212-859-1610</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C313">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
