<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480082" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Austria's ATX slumps 2.6 pct on Wall St tumble.</title>
<headline>Austria's ATX slumps 2.6 pct on Wall St tumble.</headline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian shares took a battering on Tuesday, falling 2.6 percent in reaction to an overnight sell-off on Wall Street, traders said.</p>
<p>It was the worst setback the index has had since October 1995 when Austrian shares slumped 2.86 percent after the collapse of the government coalition.</p>
<p>Traders see next support at 1,180 points.</p>
<p>&quot;It's held well at that level,&quot; said one, noting a technical rebound was possible since Wall Street could close higher.</p>
<p>One or two days of gains could be in the offing but uncertainty over U.S. interest rates remained, one trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;The uncertainty will continue on that front,&quot; he said, speculating the index could drop as low as 1,164 points.</p>
<p>The ATX blue chip index dropped 2.6 percent or 31.75 points to 1,183.49. Among its constituents 17 fell, two rose and two remained unchanged.</p>
<p>Luxury hosiery maker Wolford led the decliners for second straight trading day, falling 8.7 percent to 1,205 schillings.</p>
<p>The leading gainer was Creditanstalt ordinaries, climbing 0.21 percent to 717.5 schillings.</p>
<p>Shares in Austrian beverage group BBAG ended unchanged at 743 schillings, after the company said its majority shareholders had rejected a takeover bid by drinks giant South African Breweries (SAB).</p>
<p>The April ATX future tumbled 43.0 points to 1,177.0 on heavy volume of 1,966 contracts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
