<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480016" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton says knee injury &quot;drives me nuts&quot;.</title>
<headline>Clinton says knee injury &quot;drives me nuts&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton, an avid golfer and frequent jogger, admitted to frustration on Monday over the knee injury that will keep him off the golf course and running trails for up to six months.</p>
<p>&quot;Drives me nuts,&quot; he said in an interview with CBS Eye on People, a new cable television channel.</p>
<p>Clinton said he had to be especially careful for the next six weeks as the tendon he tore on March 13 mends. Surgeons at Bethesda Naval Hopsital reattached the tendon and prescribed months of physical therapy for the president.</p>
<p>&quot;The idea that I'm going to miss spring and summer playing golf, after I suffered through all that cold weather ... it's amazing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Still, he said, he was not going to rush the recovery which requires two therapy sessions a day as well as exercise to keep the rest of his body strong.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to just, you know, settle down and live with the fact.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton found some solace in his enforced inactivity because it had allowed him to watch almost all of the NCAA basketball tournament and to spend more time around the White House.</p>
<p>&quot;Actually one of the benefits of my injury is that I've been laid up. I have seen the NCAA from the beginning. I've seen a huge number of the games ... I've gotten to see all this March Madness, it's been wonderful,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>With his wife Hillary and daughter Chelsea on a trip to Africa for the past 10 days, Clinton, who initially used a wheelchair and is now on crutches, said he had spent the time learning &quot;how to navigate with this injury because it changes everything.&quot;</p>
<p>With no golf or jogging, Clinton conceded he'd &quot;be around the house more&quot; and added that his wife was looking forward to that.</p>
<p>&quot;I think she thinks she'll like it, but I bet you in about two months she'll be sick of me,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton tore the tendon when he stumbled down dimly lit steps at the Florida home of Australian golfer Greg Norman. The president was to have played in a charity tournament with Norman the next day.</p>
<p>Instead, he returned to Washington for emergency surgery. Although he travelled to Finland for a long-planned summit with Russian President Boris Yeltsin a few days after the procedure, he has been forced to postpone several other scheduled trips.</p>
<p>White House officials said they were certain Clinton was watching the NCAA finals on Monday night, but they refused to say whether he was supporting Arizona, making its first-ever appearance in the championship game, or Kentucky, which was hoping to repeat last year's victory.</p>
<p>In the cable TV interview, Clinton broadly hinted at which team he thought might win.</p>
<p>&quot;Well you know, in the last couple of years Kentucky has played at a very soaring level at the end of the year and so you have to give them a little advantage ...it's very hard to repeat, but they're very good,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
