<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480026" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Nynex accepts N.Y. State merger terms.</title>
<headline>Nynex accepts N.Y. State merger terms.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nynex Corp. said Monday it would accept the conditions set by the New York State Public Service Commission last week when it gave its qualified approval for Nynex to merge with Bell Atlantic Corp. in a $23 billion deal.</p>
<p>On March 21, the three members of the N.Y. utility regulatory commission voted unamimously in favour of the deal, subject to a 10-point checklist of conditions to be met before final approval was given.</p>
<p>The regulators demands focused on improving customer service in New York, where consumer groups have berated Nynex for offering what they call the worst service in the nation.</p>
<p>The approval called on Nynex to accelerate spending to improve customer service, including hiring up to 1,000 new support staff by the end of 1997 in New York state.</p>
<p>In a statement issued late Monday, Nynex President Donald Reed said, &quot;We have carefully reviewed the PSC's conditions and find them generally in line with conditional approvals granted by other commissions in Nynex states.&quot;</p>
<p>In a letter dated March 31 to N.Y. regulatory officials from Nynex and Bell Atlantic, signed by Reed, the companies stated they had agreed to accept the 10 conditions, but continued to take issue with some PSC conclusions.</p>
<p>The letter disputed the state regulators' assertion of jurisdiction over the merger and cautioned the commission against leveling additional demands on the two companies.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the N.Y. state PSC could not be reached for a response to the joint Nynex/Bell Atlantic letter.</p>
<p>Among the conditions specified by N.Y. regulators in their March 21 order was that the company not relocate major operations located in New York state prior to the merger.</p>
<p>It also called on Bell Atlantic Corp., as the merged company will be known, to locate its headquarters in New York. Nynex is currently headquartered in New York while Bell Atlantic is based in Philadelphia.</p>
<p>New York was the last state in Nynex's six-state service region to approve the merger, which still faces hurdles from federal regulators.</p>
<p>The merger of the Baby Bells would create the nation's largest local telephone company serving customers in 12 Northeastern states and Washington.</p>
<p>The merger is being held up by federal regulators who are reviewing its competitive implications.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
