<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480090" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: St-Gobain actively seeks acquisitions.</title>
<headline>St-Gobain actively seeks acquisitions.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>French glass-maker Saint-Gobain will actively seek acquisitions in the coming years but will be selective by adding to core businesses and will look for areas which add growth, chairman Jean-Louis Beffa said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The acquisition strategy was &quot;active and selective,&quot; he told an analysts' meeting on its 1996 results published in January.</p>
<p>Saint-Gobain's acquisitions will be guided by its aim to be world leader or number two in a given sector, to increase growth, expand its geographical coverage and select areas complementary to existing expertise, he said.</p>
<p>Saint-Gobain's 1996 net cashflow totalled 10.7 billion francs. It had shareholders capital of 62.2 billion francs and net debt of 14.8 percent, giving it a debt/equiity ratio of around 30 percent, he said.</p>
<p>Saint-Gobain could &quot;easily&quot; raise its gearing to 40 percent to take advantage of any opportunities and did not envisage a capital increase, Beffa said.</p>
<p>He said the group acquired companies, such as Poliet bought from Paribas last year, whose growth rate were higher than Saint-Gobain's average rate, he said.</p>
<p>The group is holding to its growth target for Asia, with five billion francs in turnover by 2000 and 20 billion in 2005. That compared to one billion francs a couple of years ago.</p>
<p>Beffa said he had just returned from Latin America and was very confident about the Brazilian economy.</p>
<p>Acquisitions would respect the group's profitability goals. Saint-Gobain's target is operating profit of 20 percent of fixed assets and 10 percent return on equity, based on French accounting rules.</p>
<p>-- Pierre Tran, Paris newsroom +33 1 4221 5452 pnt</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I24700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
