<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480037" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy to press on with Albania force, patrols.</title>
<headline>Italy to press on with Albania force, patrols.</headline>
<byline>Paul Holmes</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy said on Tuesday that it would press ahead with plans to lead an international security force to troubled Albania despite mounting domestic pressure to think again after the fatal sinking of a crowded refugee boat.</p>
<p>Defence Minister Beniamino Andreatta said the Italian-dominated force, expected to number some 5,000 men, could start deploying in the Balkan country by April 10.</p>
<p>&quot;When you are good members of a community you have to make haste and do your duty,&quot; he said, adding that he saw &quot;no reason to hesitate&quot; because of internal factors.</p>
<p>He also insisted that the navy would continue controversial interdiction patrols of the Adriatic, where Albanian authorities say at least 83 refugees drowned last Friday when their boat sank after a collision with an Italian corvette.</p>
<p>&quot;The Adriatic patrols continue,&quot; Andreatta told reporters after addressing a joint session of the Senate (upper house) defence and foreign affairs commissions on the disaster.</p>
<p>Italy began the dissuasive patrols late last month after some 13,000 Albanians fled to Italian shores in an uncontrolled exodus from their country's armed upheaval.</p>
<p>Calls from some of the government's own supporters for a halt to the naval action, and for Italy to keep its troops out of Albania, grew on Tuesday in the wake of the disaster and reported threats from Albanians to the safety of Italian forces.</p>
<p>Hard-left leader Fausto Bertinotti, whose Communist Refoundation party ensures the government its lower house majority, said he was against sending a security force.</p>
<p>&quot;It would only aggravate the situation in Albania and expose (the mission) itself to all sorts of dangers,&quot; Bertinotti said.</p>
<p>The Greens, who are part of Prime Minister Romano Prodi's centre-left coalition, also expressed misgivings.</p>
<p>&quot;Our first request is to halt the patrols,&quot; Greens leader Luigi Manconi said. &quot;That is the...minimum precondition for approval of the international (security) mission.&quot;</p>
<p>The proposed multinational force, which has received the go-ahead from the U.N. Security Council and the Albanian parliament, will also require a vote of support from both houses of the Italian parliament.</p>
<p>It is designed to secure the ports of Durres and Vlore -- from where the boat that sank set out -- and Tirana airport for a planned European humanitarian relief mission to Albania following the impoverished state's slide into anarchy.</p>
<p>Andreatta was to meet Albanian Defence Minister Shaqir Vukaj in Rome on Tuesday to discuss last Friday's disaster.</p>
<p>Their talks will continue on Wednesday when senior defence officials from other countries meet in the Italian capital to discuss arrangements for the planned security force.</p>
<p>Andreatta told parliament he had invited Albanian navy experts to join investigations into last week's sinking and promised a full and open inquiry.</p>
<p>But he dismissed claims in some newspapers and from some sources in Albania that the collision happened because the corvette Sibilla bore down on the refugee boat, which had set out from Vlore, one of several southern Albanian towns in the hands of rebels.</p>
<p>&quot;It is absolutely shameful even to think that the Italian vessel had the deliberate intention of ramming the Albanian boat,&quot; Andreatta said.</p>
<p>He said the boat had been badly overcrowded and had swung into the path of the Sibilla when the corvette moved alongside to order it to return to Albania.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
