<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480084" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bunds plumb lower levels amid U.S. rate worries.</title>
<headline>Bunds plumb lower levels amid U.S. rate worries.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bund futures spent much of Tuesday drifting at markedly lower levels, awaiting with the rest of the global debt market any indication about the direction of U.S. interest rates.</p>
<p>Although Bunds are widely expected to outperform on any Treasury market weakness, traders said the fate of German debt is closely tied to the U.S. where the market is seen laden with downside risks.</p>
<p>&quot;We will spend the entire week chasing the U.S. and it does not look good,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>At 1331 GMT, the DTB Bund futures contract was down 46 basis points at 99.52, having traded as low as 99.34.  </p>
<p>Although Bunds were weak all day, chart support at 99.30 dampened selling in the futures contract. That level roughly corresponds to the six percent yield on the 10-year cash Bund.</p>
<p>With Treasuries pulling the Bund lower, the German yield curve steepened on the day and German debt strongly outperformed the U.S.</p>
<p>The Bund/T-note spread stood at around 105 basis points in the afternoon with some traders expecting it widening out toward 115 basis points in coming weeks.</p>
<p>The spread between two- and 10-year maturities widened six basis points to 228 basis points.  </p>
<p>&quot;Investors are looking for security and they are finding it only on the short-end,&quot; a trader at a German bank said.</p>
<p>With German economic fundamentals Bund-market supportive, traders were unsure about the market's direction, some seeing buying opportunities at current low levels, others seeing risks of further selling linked to the U.S.</p>
<p>With the Bundesbank widely expected to keep rates on hold at its regular council meeting Thursday, the major domestic event of the week is German industrial production data, due out Wednesday or Thursday.  </p>
<p>The data should shed light on recent signs that the German economy is starting to recover, potentially adding to the Bund market's problems.</p>
<p>&quot;It should be viewed as a negative sign that the 30-day moving average has cut downward through the 100-day moving average, thus generating a medium-term selling signal,&quot; wrote Trinkaus &amp; Burkhardt in a market commentary this afternoon.</p>
<p>The 10-year cash Bund fell to 99.94 in price from 100.47 to yield 5.99 percent.</p>
<p>--Frankfurt Newsroom + 49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
