<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480004" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: United Air to drop cargo fuel surcharge.</title>
<headline>United Air to drop cargo fuel surcharge.</headline>
<byline>David Gersovitz</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>United Airlines said Thursday it will drop its worldwide cargo fuel surcharge effective April 7, but several other large North American carriers say they will hold on to theirs.</p>
<p>Spokesmen for Northwest Airlines, American Airlines, Air Canada and Canadian Airlines International said they were aware of United's action, but had no plans to follow suit.</p>
<p>&quot;This has been a big debate internally as to whether we hold or not (to the surcharge), but we're going to hold on,&quot; says John Gibson, CAI's general manager of international cargo sales, told Reuters.</p>
<p>UAL introduced its $0.10 a kg surcharge on November 15 reflecting sharply higher jet fuel prices and similar action by competitor carriers.</p>
<p>Market sources said they understood that major transpacific carriers like Japan Air Lines also are trying to keep surcharge in place.</p>
<p>They said United's decision to drop the 10 cent a kilo fuel levy, which follows similar actions by Delta Airlines and Virgin Atlantic, may be motivated by the fact United is in the process of implementing rate increases which could mitigate the revenue loss.</p>
<p>They also note that April usually is a trough in the industry and that carriers like Delta and United may be trying to secure some discretionary traffic.</p>
<p>Officials for the holdout carriers, which right now constitute the majority in the industry, say fuel prices remain significantly higher than they were a year ago, and have not come off much from their peak in October, when the surcharges came into being.</p>
<p>&quot;We're benchmarking fuel prices to June '96, and we're probably about 15 percent over June '96 prices,&quot; Robert Thomson, head of Air Canada Cargo, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Thomson said Air Canada will continue monitoring market conditions to assess whether its surcharges should be removed.</p>
<p>Overseas, it will be influenced by what the major European and Asian carriers decide in their home markets, he said.</p>
<p>Domestically, Air Canada is likely to hang on to its surcharge, irrespective of what happens internationally, he said, adding: &quot;We don't want to pull it (the surcharge), but we will maintain our competitive in each of our market areas.&quot;</p>
<p>Thomson expressed disappointment at the fact some carriers are removing the surcharge without first seeing the extent of the usual April drop-off in market activity. --Reuters Air Cargo Newsroom Tel +44 171 542 7706 Fax 5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
