<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480078" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian-French group Dexia eyes expansion.</title>
<headline>Belgian-French group Dexia eyes expansion.</headline>
<byline>Nieck Ammerlaan</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian French bancassurance group Dexia said on Tuesday it had the means to make acquisitions, but had no specific victims in its sights.</p>
<p>&quot;We have ample assets, we are strongly capitalised, we are on the outlook for opportunities...both inside and outside Europe,&quot; Francois Narmon, chief executive officer of Dexia Belgium and management board chairman of Credit Communal de Belgique/Gemeentekrediet (CCB) told a news conference.</p>
<p>CCB is 50 percent owned by listed holding company  CCB Holding/Dexia Belgium and 50 percent by holding company CLF-Dexia France.</p>
<p>CCB and Credit Local de France (CLF) together form Dexia, a group mainly active in public sector lending.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to be number one in Europe (in public sector lending) and expand inside and outside Europe...we have achieved critical mass in Europe (by linking up with CLF),&quot; Narmon said.</p>
<p>Earlier he announced a 13.1 percent rise in group net profit to 19.4 billion Belgian francs ($562.6 million), a result which he called satisfactory.</p>
<p>Last year was the first book year for the combined group.</p>
<p>Narmon declined to be specific on where the group's ambitions lay, but made it clear it had no plans to move into retail banking outside of Belgium or Luxembourg. CLF too had no intention to become a retail bank in France.</p>
<p>For asset management and private banking the group regarded its Luxembourg-based Banque Internationale a Luxembourg as its international centre.</p>
<p>Narmon said Dexia had no plans to raise its 40 percent stake in Italy's  Crediop, bought recently from Italy's group Instituto Bancario San Paolo di Torino, in the months ahead.</p>
<p>&quot;But we have concluded a shareholders' agreement with San Paolo so that we are on an equal footing with San Paolo, so that we are not a minority shareholder,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He gave no details.</p>
<p>Narmon estimated Dexia had a potential war chest of 120 billion Belgian francs.</p>
<p>Dexia could halve its risk/asset ratio of 16.3 percent at June 30, 1996 -- before the Crediop purchase which the group funded from cash -- to eight percent, which amounted to 120 billion francs. &quot;But we will never go that low (eight percent)&quot;, he added.</p>
<p>Alternatively, Dexia could sell its stake of over 10 percent in Belgian Banque Bruxelles Lambert to raise cash.</p>
<p>&quot;Suppose we sell, the only possibility would be that we re-invest in OLOs (Belgian government bonds)? BBL is a good investment, we do not need the cash, we do not have a project to sell (the stake),&quot; Narmon said.</p>
<p>Prospects for Dexia in 1997 were favourable, he said, adding he foresaw public sector lending growth in Belgium and France.</p>
<p>Comparing net profit of 19.4 billion francs with shareholders' equity of 163.68 billion francs, Narmon put return on equity at 11.5 percent. &quot;In the next few years we want to do better and aim for 13 percent and 15 percent thereafter.&quot;</p>
<p>Apart from expansion, Dexia would strive to raise profit by curbing operating costs and lauching new products to satisfy client demand.</p>
<p>-- Brussels Newsroom +32 2 287 6810, Fax +32 2 230 7710 ($ = 34.48 Belgian Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150106">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
