<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480097" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: Greece slams attack on consul's house in Albania.</title>
<headline>Greece slams attack on consul's house in Albania.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greece said on Tuesday that gunmen had shot at the house of its consul in the southern Albanian town of Gjirokaster and described the attack as criminal and immoral.</p>
<p>Unknown attackers holed up in a nearby building fired eight shots at the consular residence in the rebel-held southern Albanian town late on Monday, the Foreign Ministry said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a foolish, immoral and criminal action which aims to harm Greek-Albanian relations and the operation of our general consulate in Gjirokaster,&quot; the ministry said.</p>
<p>It said general consul Nikos Kanellos was instructed to ask the Albanian authorities for additional security measures but did not say whether he was at home at the time of the attack.</p>
<p>The consulate in the rebel stronghold 30 km (20 miles) from the Greek border had come under attack first last Thursday by an armed crowd seeking visas to leave the impoverished Balkan country.</p>
<p>Greece, concerned with the chaos at its northern border, has promised to participate in a multinational force designed to restore order in Albania and has offered a favourable loan to help its people cope with an economic crisis.</p>
<p>Albania has been swept by violence since January when a number of popular investment schemes collapsed, wiping out millions of dollars in savings.</p>
<p>The anti-government riots and protests evolved into a full-scale uprising, with army depots looted and rebel committees running the south of the country.</p>
<p>Albanian Prime Minister Bashkim Fino, a former Socialist mayor of Gjirokaster, is expected in Greece on Wednesday for talks with Prime Minister Costas Simitis on the Albanian crisis.</p>
<p>Fino will be joined in Greece by Albania's ministers of finance, interior and foreign affairs for a two-day visit.</p>
<p>About 350,000 illegal Albanians work in Greece, having fled across the long border after the fall of communism. Greece also keeps an eye on a large ethnic Greek community in Albania.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
