<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480183" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: W. Europe pulp/paper/board output may rise in 1997.</title>
<headline>W. Europe pulp/paper/board output may rise in 1997.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Western Europe's total output of paper and board as well as of pulp may rise this year compared with 1996, the Confederation of European Paper Industries (CEPI) said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>CEPI, issuing regular production figures, said total paper and board output jumped 10.6 percent to 18.5 million tonnes in the fourth quarter last year compared with the same 1995 quarter.</p>
<p>Total pulp output also increased in the fourth quarter, up by 7.3 percent to 8.3 million tonnes.  </p>
<p>However, due to a weak start to the year, total paper and board output still fell 0.8 percent last year compared with 1995.</p>
<p>Pulp output also declined in 1996, down by 5.4 percent.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, CEPI said it did not expect any dramatic changes for paper and board production this year.</p>
<p>Most graphic grades would show a strong increase during the first half and a slowdown towards the end of the year, sanitary and household might continue with a slight increase and packaging grades might grow marginally, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;Altogether, 1997 could show a surplus over 1996 of between 1 to 2 percent,&quot; CEPI said in a report.  </p>
<p>Turning to the outlook for pulp in 1997, CEPI said:</p>
<p>&quot;...good 4th quarter results and at least slight growth expectation for paper production in 1997 leads to the assumption that 1997 total pulp production might exceed the 1996 results.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Brussels newsroom +32 2 287 68 11</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
