<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480128" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Wall Street prompts dramatic German share sell-off.</title>
<headline>Wall Street prompts dramatic German share sell-off.</headline>
<byline>Catherine O'Mahony</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>German shares plunged to one of their greatest one-day losses ever on Tuesday, as rattled investors stampeded to sell off their stocks in the wake of Wall Street's Easter tumble.</p>
<p>The 30-share DAX ended the bourse session down 133.12 points, or 3.88 percent, at 3,295.93 points -- its biggest one-day collapse since its 4.06 percent plunge on December 6 when Federal Reserve Chairman Alan Greenspan sparked global market chaos with warnings over &quot;irrational exuberance.&quot;</p>
<p>The December fall was the largest since a coup attempt against former Soviet Union leader Mikhail Gorbachev sliced some nine percent off German share prices in August 1991.</p>
<p>&quot;This has certainly been a very dramatic correction,&quot; said Bank Julius Baer chief economist Gerhard Grebe.</p>
<p>&quot;Fundamentals apart, it shows the German market cannot decouple from the U.S. when things happen at this kind of speed.&quot;</p>
<p>Dow industrials tumbled 157 points on Monday, bringing their losses in two days to more than four percent and alarming markets worldwide. U.S. shares are being buffeted by mounting concern that more interest rate hikes are in the offing.</p>
<p>But market players were at a loss to find a fundamental reason why Germany should react so dramatically. German interest rates have been latterly expected to remain stable for the time being and the outlook for corporate earnings is generally considered extremely rosy.</p>
<p>&quot;That's still the case,&quot; said Rainer Helbig, a trader at Baden Wuerttembergische Bank in Stuttgart. &quot;But it's a psychological thing. And it looks like the Germans have typically reacted very thoroughly.&quot;</p>
<p>Losses were spread across the board, with few blue chip stocks escaping the downward trend. Deutsche Bank AG, a solid performer in recent weeks, fell 4.45 marks ($2.66) to 89.45 marks.</p>
<p>Daimler-Benz AG dropped 6.50 marks to 126.90 marks while utility Veba fell 5.65 marks to 88.80 marks.</p>
<p>The next few days were expected to give a clearer picture as to whether the sell-off, on relatively strong volumes, marked a clear change in trend.</p>
<p>Dealers noted that the DAX had held above key points of technical resistance so far. One key support at 3,280 DAX points was briefly breached but the market recovered as dealings went on.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, the week ahead was expected to be a rocky one.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a long-overdue correction. It's healthy,&quot; said Julius Baer's Grebe.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically what we had in the first few months was the best of all worlds, low interest rates and a strong dollar. Now all of a sudden what have we got? -- a U.S. rate rise and the dollar's on the way down too.&quot;</p>
<p>Grebe said the DAX could touch off a lower technical resistance point at 3,080 points if Wall Street continues its losses, especially if the U.S. labour market data due on Friday appear to support the case for a U.S. rate hike.</p>
<p>The DAX has risen 14 percent this year, bypassing many analysts' forecasts for its end-of year target.</p>
<p>Dealers have noted of late an ever-more rapid switching between sectors on the DAX, often without a reasoned fundamental explanation. This, some say, is a clear sign that the market needs breathing space.</p>
<p>--Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
<p>($ = 1.670 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
