<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480185" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: RESEARCH ALERT - Greek telecom OTE rated &quot;buy&quot;.</title>
<headline>RESEARCH ALERT - Greek telecom OTE rated &quot;buy&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greek telecom OTE remains one of the top buys in the European telecoms sector based on impressive revenue growth and a price earnings (P/E) ratio at a 25 percent discount to the sector, HSBC James Capel said.</p>
<p>&quot;OTE remains one of our top buys in the European telecoms sector. In P/E terms it is one of Europe's least highly rated telcos on a 25 percent discount to the 1997 sector average. It has impressive top-line revenue growth,&quot; HSBC said in a report.</p>
<p>It said OTE's growth prospects are underpinned by the fact that Greece is easily the EU's least developed telecoms market and by a regulatory environment that will remain impervious to competition, except at the fringes, until the new millenium.</p>
<p>&quot;OTE's growth we believe is more secure than most European telcos facing the uncertainties of liberalisation from 1998. It may still have its blemishes -- an impoverished network, weak commercial organisation -- but this is the normal baggage of any telco in this position,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>OTE's free float, currently 8.0 percent, will rise after the planned second flotation whose details will be finalised at a Greek cabinet meeting this Friday.</p>
<p>In terms of return on equity, OTE was ahead of BT, KPN, Portugal Telecom, Tele Danmark, Telecom Italia, Telefonica, SPT and Deutsche Telekom with 27.2 percent in 1996, and 27.9 percent seen for 1997, HSBC James Capel said.</p>
<p>At 5,850 drachmas a share it had the lowest 1997 trading multiple at 11.9 times, 10.5 times for 1998. It ranked second to SPT in terms of three-year (1996-99) average net revenue growth among European telecoms with 11.6 percent.</p>
<p>OTE has strong regulatory protection, a market ripe for rapid development and a government which seems inclined to give it scope to facilitate change with respect to tariffs.</p>
<p>The question is, does OTE have the right recipe?</p>
<p>&quot;Technically and financially competent, commercially weak, OTE still has a lot to learn. However, the important thing is that the right start has been made and the company will enjoy near complete protection in its marketplace over the next four years,&quot; said HSBC.</p>
<p>While OTE has a large customer base it has also, until recently, made little effort to leverage it.</p>
<p>Consequently, it has probably the greatest potential to grow its revenue base of any operator in Europe which, of course, remains one of its main attractions as well as challenges, the report said. --George Georgiopoulos, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
