<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480126" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Uranium found on Italian plane wreck - agencies.</title>
<headline>Uranium found on Italian plane wreck - agencies.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scientists believe an Italian airliner which crashed in mysterious circumstances in 1980, killing 81 people, was carrying the radioactive nuclear fuel uranium, Italian news agencies reported on Tuesday.</p>
<p>They said nuclear scientists and chemists commissioned by investigating judge Rosario Priore to examine the wreckage of the plane, retrieved from the sea near the island of Ustica, had found trace elements of uranium in what had been the hold.</p>
<p>The ANSA agency said the scientists concluded that their findings showed &quot;that there was uranium in the hold&quot;. Investigators were not available for comment on the reports.</p>
<p>Uranium, a silvery-white metal, is used as a fuel for nuclear reactors.</p>
<p>Italian media have speculated that the passenger jet, a DC-9 belonging to the now defunct airline Itavia, was accidentally brought down by a NATO missile.</p>
<p>It crashed into the sea on a flight from the central city of Bologna to the Sicilian capital Palermo. Media reports have speculated that it was carrying uranium intended to be sent to Libya by sea.</p>
<p>Authorities have recently stepped up efforts to resolve the mystery of the crash, which happened on June 27, 1980 near Ustica, just north of Sicily.</p>
<p>NATO has submitted new data to Priore's investigation and set up a special committee to help probe the crash.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
