<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480135" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: FORECAST - One-year bill yields seen stable on Wed.</title>
<headline>FORECAST - One-year bill yields seen stable on Wed.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The yield on Spanish one-year Treasury bills at Wednesday's auction is expected to be little changed from 5.579 percent at the previous auction on March 19, dealers said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Dealers said they expected the yield to be set within a range of 5.55 to 5.60 percent, in line with grey-market rates, with the auction exciting little investor interest.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no expectations for changes, money market rates and grey-market rates are stable. I guess bids will be made at the same levels,&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>Yields on Treasury bills bottomed in February, coinciding with peseta exchange rate tension.</p>
<p>Although February inflation fell to a fresh low of 2.5 percent year-on-year, providing room for a rate cut at the following Bank of Spain repo auction, peseta tension and reduced prospects for further rate cuts in the future mean that lower T-bill and interbank rates are more difficult, dealers said.</p>
<p>Dealers are expecting bids of between 350 and 450 billion pesetas. On Friday April 4, 464.9 billion pesetas of one-year bills will mature.</p>
<p>-- Madrid newsroom +341 585 2160</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
