<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480121" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Brazil eyes European parallel bonds - traders.</title>
<headline>Brazil eyes European parallel bonds - traders.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil has asked banks for proposals to issue Eurobonds in several European currencies which would be fungible after the introduction of a single European currency, banking sources said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The sources said Brazil had asked for recommendations last week and wanted to receive bids by the middle of April.</p>
<p>&quot;They've gone to a number of banks, looking to issue in a number of European currencies so that when the euro comes in they will be fungible,&quot; a syndication manager said.</p>
<p>Another syndication manager said Brazil was looking at parallel bonds and had asked several institutions to come up with ideas and put in bids by the middle of April. He thought an offering in marks and two other currencies would be the most likely outcome.</p>
<p>A third syndication manager said Brazil had left the choice of currency up to the bidders but had suggested marks, guilders, francs and Austrian schillings as possible denominations.</p>
<p>&quot;But that doesn't mean the franc will be chosen, nor that the operation will take place quickly given the sharp decline in the market recently,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Another syndication declined to confirm whether Brazil was planning to issue bonds denominated in European currencies, but said there had been talk of a Brazilian issue in French francs for some time.</p>
<p>He added that the idea that Brazil would issue parallel bonds was perfectly plausible given that it was &quot;always very innovative&quot;.</p>
<p>Bond issues linked to the launch of a single European currency scheduled for January 1, 1999, have been in vogue this year, capturing 5.4 percent of total international bond issuance in the first quarter.</p>
<p>The first so-called parallel bond was launched by Austria in January. The five billion French franc issue included a clause making it fungible with existing Austrian schilling bonds, and future offerings by the same borrower with the same coupon and maturity date, if and when the single currency, or euro, is launched.</p>
<p>Since then there have been another 26 euro-related issues taking the total issuance in the first quarter to $10.7 billion, according to figures from Capital DATA Bondware.</p>
<p>Two issuers, Italy and the European Investment Bank have launched jumbo Eurobonds denominated in the euro itself, but most of the other issues have included a clause similar to the Austrian deal allowing redenomination of the bonds in euros.</p>
<p>One syndication manager said while there had been several issues from countries within the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development an issue from an emerging market such as Brazil &quot;would clearly be a first&quot;.</p>
<p>Four sovereigns -- Austria, Italy, Portugal and Spain -- have issued euro-linked bonds. The EIB has issued four 5.75 percent 2007 Eurobonds, in escudos, French francs, guilders and marks, with an aggregate value of around $1.8 billion.</p>
<p>-- David Clarke, Yann Le Guernigou, Paris Newsroom +331 4221 5542</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
