<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480118" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: EU team visits Algiers before Malta forum.</title>
<headline>EU team visits Algiers before Malta forum.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union (EU) officials on Tuesday arrived in Algiers, part of a working tour of south Mediterranean countries before a meeting of 27 foreign ministers in Malta this month, Algerian state-run radio said.</p>
<p>The European delegation, led by Dutch Foreign Minister Hans van Mierlo who is also EU council of ministers' chairman, will hold talks with Algerian officials on the Malta conference and Algeria's negotiations with the EU on an association accord, the radio said.</p>
<p>&quot;We will listen, talk and try to have Algeria's analysis on the evolution of Euro-Mediterranean cooperation and bilateral negotiations,&quot; said van Mierlo quoted by the official Algerian news agency APS.</p>
<p>The Malta meeting, on April 15 and 16, is a follow-up to the 1995 Barcelona conference which forged a partnership accord involving the 15 EU countries and 12 south Mediterranean ones.</p>
<p>Algeria in February began negotiating an EU association accord which will open the Algerian economy to competition in a Mediterranean free zone by the year 2010.</p>
<p>European Commission vice-president Manuel Marin was among the European delegation which started its tour in Morocco and is due to visit Tunisia, Malta, Egypt and Turkey, officials said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALTA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
