<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480117" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Lufthansa sees profit rebound in 97 - paper.</title>
<headline>Lufthansa sees profit rebound in 97 - paper.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Deutsche Lufthansa AG expects profits to rebound in 1997 to around levels seen in 1995 after a drop of around ten percent in 1996, chief executive Juergen Weber said in an interview on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Our aim is to reach the 1995 level. We are confident of achieving that,&quot; the German airline chief said in an interview in the Tuesday edition of the Financial Times.</p>
<p>In 1995 Lufthansa posted profit from ordinary activities of 756 million marks. The group has yet to report 1996 data, but has indicated that profits will be down around 10 percent.</p>
<p>The airline also said that 1996 revenues would be around five percent higher at around 21 billion marks.</p>
<p>Weber said that while productivity at Lufthansa had risen by around 50 percent since he took over as CEO six years ago, more still needed to be done.</p>
<p>Weber was confident that the group's proposed cost-cutting programme, which is seeking to save around 800 million marks by the end of the century, will be a success. &quot;I am certain we can do this,&quot; Weber said.</p>
<p>Weber also said that he saw exciting prospects in the Asia-Pacific region and that Lufthansa was holding &quot;promising talks&quot; on developing alliances in Asia. He said China and India were countries where it wanted to expand business.</p>
<p>--Clifford Coonan, Frankfurt Newsroom +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
