<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480130" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: UN bodies voice alarm on Afghan women, refugees.</title>
<headline>UN bodies voice alarm on Afghan women, refugees.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>United Nations agencies voiced mounting concern on Tuesday about the suppression of women's rights by Afghanistan's Taleban Islamic movement and a growing tide of refugees fleeing conflict in the country.</p>
<p>In separate reports, the U.N. Children's Fund UNICEF and the refugee agency UNHCR said the two developments were causing increasingly serious social problems across the war-devastated country and especially in the capital, Kabul.</p>
<p>&quot;The exclusion of girls and women from the public sphere has disastrous consequences for the entire nation, as well as being an affront to basic human rights,&quot; UNICEF Executive Director Carol Bellamy said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;Not only are they shut out of educational opportunities, but they are denied the right to contribute to their families' welfare and the country's economy,&quot; she declared.</p>
<p>Bellamy said the Taleban's education minister in Kabul had gone back on a promise to U.N. officials last month that girls up to the age of nine would be allowed to attend school when they reopened at the end of March.</p>
<p>Only boys were being allowed to go to school in the two thirds of the country controlled by the Taleban, which captured Kabul last September, ousting a more moderate Islamic administration whose forces it is still fighting.</p>
<p>Kabul University, where women accounted for 4,000 out of a 10,000-strong student body when it was closed by the Taleban last September, reopened last week without female teachers or students, UNICEF said.</p>
<p>In her statement, Bellamy rejected as &quot;implausible&quot; a Taleban argument that there were not enough funds to provide for the education of women, whom it has also banned from leaving their homes without wearing an all-covering Burqa veil.</p>
<p>The exclusion of girls from schools and women from the workforce, she said, was seriously undermining the country's prospects for economic and social development.</p>
<p>&quot;Afghanistan is a nation of widows. Women are not only vital members of the workforce but are frequently the only breadwinners in the family,&quot; Bellamy declared.</p>
<p>&quot;If they cannot earn a living they will not be able to feed their children. The consequences will be catastrophic.&quot;</p>
<p>UNHCR spokeswoman Pam O'Toole told a Geneva news briefing that the already &quot;debilitated and impoverished population&quot; of Kabul had been swollen by 10 to 15 percent since January by the arrival of displaced people from farming areas to the north.</p>
<p>The flow, which began at the end of December and grew after the Taleban took control of the Shomali valley from the capital to the foothills of the Hindu Kush in January, showed little sign of abating, she said.</p>
<p>Kabul, a city of around one million people out of a total Afghan population of 15 million, had had to accomodate a total of around 140,000 more since early January.</p>
<p>Over the past three weeks, an average of 800 people a day had been passing through the UNHCR checkpoint on the northern edge of the city -- most crowding into already occupied houses and apartments and others into schools and mosques.</p>
<p>Another source of concern, O'Toole said, was that the Shomali valley was an extremely import source of food for the capital, and with the departure of much of its population there were few people left for the spring crop sowing.</p>
<p>&quot;At this time of the year, the population should be planting their crops and pruning their fruit trees, not themselves struggling to find food,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Across the country, the northern third of which is controlled by an anti-Taleban alliance, some 250,000 people had been forced from their homes since last October, including 35,000 who had fled to the city of Herat from fighting between the two sides in the west of the country.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
