<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480168" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian steel workers delay high-speed train.</title>
<headline>Belgian steel workers delay high-speed train.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hundreds of protesting workers from bankrupt Belgian steel firm Forges de Clabecq blockaded a railway station on Tuesday, causing half-hour delays to the Brussels-Paris high speed train which had to be diverted.</p>
<p>&quot;Three Thalys (high speed trains) in each direction have been affected,&quot; a spokesman for the Belgian railways told Reuters.</p>
<p>Belgian media reported the action ended after three hours.</p>
<p>The spokesman said the station at Tubize where the Clabecq plant is situated, about 20 km (12 miles) southwest of Brussels, had been closed to all train traffic.</p>
<p>There were no reports of any violence among the workers, whose sit-in at the station followed a general workers assembly.</p>
<p>On Friday, 25 people were injured when nearly 1,000 Clabecq workers clashed with riot police as they tried to block the E19 motorway to Paris south of Brussels.</p>
<p>A small delegation of Clabecq workers also joined protesting colleagues at Renault's plant in Vilvoorde, near Brussels, on Tuesday morning.</p>
<p>Staff at the profitable Vilvoorde site are occupying their factory in protest at the French car group's decision to close it with the loss of 3,100 jobs.</p>
<p>The Renault workers are also planning a day of action in Brussels, Paris and Madrid on Friday, and there is due to be a general march for jobs in the southern city of Namur on Saturday.</p>
<p>A march for jobs in Brussels last month attracted between 50,000 and 100,000 participants from all over Europe in protest at the failure of governments to create work as they tighten their budgetary belts in preparation for the European Union's single currency in 1999.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
