<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480107" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Gold seen poised for upside gains in 1997.</title>
<headline>Gold seen poised for upside gains in 1997.</headline>
<dateline>DUESSELDORF 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The gold bullion price may be poised for gains towards $374 or $391 per ounce, WestLB bank said in a monthly market circular.</p>
<p>It cited continued short covering and positive chart signals after the market fell to three-year lows at $336 earlier in the year.</p>
<p>It said the projected price targets would only be threatened if the market dropped below the initial 1997 low.</p>
<p>But much hinged on possible sales from European central banks in a bid to meet convergence criteria ahead of currency union.</p>
<p>The report did not say whether the price targets, if reached, would be maintained for lengthy periods.</p>
<p>London gold fixed firmer at $349.85 on Tuesday morning after a four-day market holiday as weaker equity markets were seen providing support.</p>
<p>Silver might rise to 600 cents in 1997 because of a growing supply/demand gap, WestLB also said.</p>
<p>London silver on Tuesday fixed sharply lower at 503.50 cents/lb but remained supported at 500.</p>
<p>The bank noted stocks were at a 46-year low after the last seven years had generated new mining and recycling supply shortfalls against a background of steadily growing demand.</p>
<p>Sooner or later this imbalance would have to be regulated via higher prices since national banks held no silver reserves, WestLB said.</p>
<p>-Vera Eckert, Hamburg newsroom, +49-40-41903275</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUESSELDORF"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
