<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480180" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: FORECAST - ING year net seen up 22 pct.</title>
<headline>FORECAST - ING year net seen up 22 pct.</headline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dutch financial services group Internationale Nederlanden Groep NV is expected to announce an about 22 percent increase in 1996 net profit on Thursday, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts polled by Reuters expect net profits before preference dividends of between 3.17 billion and 3.36 billion guilders, averaging 3.22 billion, up from 2.65 billion in 1995.</p>
<p>They expect banking to have outstripped insurance for profit growth as buoyant markets boosted commission and trading income and investment bank Barings improved its contribution.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect them to be good numbers,&quot; Salomon Brothers analyst Matthew Czepliewicz said.</p>
<p>ING will also unveil its hidden reserves for the first time on Thursday, with forecasts ranging between 2.5 billion and 3.0 billion guilders.</p>
<p>After the first nine months of 1996, ING's net profit had risen 24.1 percent to 2.34 billion guilders.</p>
<p>Czepliewicz said the fourth quarter of last year was good for banks involved in trading and, although ING was not a major trading house, its operations in emerging markets had done well.</p>
<p>Andrew Goodwin of UBS said insurance would have outshone banking for profit growth in the final quarter because banking profits were strong in the last three months of 1995.</p>
<p>Others agreed, citing strong final quarter results from Dutch insurers Aegon and Fortis Amev.</p>
<p>F. van Lanschot Bankiers analyst Jean-Paul van Bavel said the final quarter results would have benefited from a stronger guilder and a continued improvement from non-life insurance.</p>
<p>Bart van der Feen of IRIS Research expected ING's banking profits to have grown 25 percent in 1996 with insurance profits up 16 percent up the previous year.</p>
<p>Within banking, he forecast increases of 14 percent in net interest income, 35 percent in commission income and 18 percent in other income, including trading income.</p>
<p>Van der Feen expected Barings, bought for 1.7 billion guilders in March 1995 after it collapsed from derivatives trading losses, to have just covered its interest costs.</p>
<p>Van Bavel said: &quot;But it's still disappointing and not generating the profits they would have expected when they took it over.&quot;</p>
<p>Tom Bennett of Paribas expected ING to have smoothed profits by making extra provisions in the fourth quarter for computer projects associated with the euro currency and the millennium.</p>
<p>The group set aside 275 million guilders in the first nine months of the year for these projects.</p>
<p>&quot;They should have had a stunning year of trading but they're in the process of hiding it away one way or the other,&quot; Bennett said.</p>
<p>In insurance, he said the Dutch life operations would have lifted profits due mainly to premium growth but he expected losses from the greenfields operations around the world.</p>
<p>-- Garry West, Amsterdam newsroom +31 20 504 5000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
