<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480166" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Austria insurers await details of holocaust suit.</title>
<headline>Austria insurers await details of holocaust suit.</headline>
<byline>Janet McBride</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian insurers were awaiting notification on Tuesday of a U.S. law suit filed against them by holocaust victims and their families but one of the firms said it believed there was no case to answer.</p>
<p>The suit, filed in Manhattan federal court on Monday, seeks class action certification and alleges that seven Austrian, Italian, German and French insurers withheld, concealed or converted the cash value and proceeds of policies sold before 1946.</p>
<p>Among the companies named are Vienna-based Wiener Allianz, part of Germany's Allianz group, and Der Anker Allgemeine Versicherungs AG, a unit of Swiss Helvetia.</p>
<p>The suit, which estimates the class could exceed 10,000 members, is targeting billions of dollars in damages for life, property and casualty insurance policies and annuities bought between 1920 and 1945.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't know anything about the suit or its contents,&quot; Wiener Allianz spokeswoman Elisabeth Rashid told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;What we can say is that Wiener Allianz only acquired that name in 1938 and only began selling life insurance in 1960.&quot;</p>
<p>Rashid suggested the firm may be a victim of mistaken identity and noted a company called Allianz and Gisela Verein operated in Austria prior to its annexation by Nazi Germany in 1938.</p>
<p>&quot;Wiener Allianz has no connection to this firm,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Der Anker declined comment before receiving details of the complaint but added that crucial company records went up in smoke in 1945 when allied bombs razed the firm's Vienna headquarters.</p>
<p>The suit claims the defendants &quot;with a reputation for confidentiality and professionalism&quot; encouraged European citizens fearful of Nazi persecution to deposit their assets and purchase insurance to safeguard their families' futures.</p>
<p>Members of the class who were unable to flee the persecution were arrested and their assets, including the insurance policies and numbers, were taken by the Nazis, the suit alleged. The policies were then improperly transferred, liquidated or cashed in, it claimed.</p>
<p>&quot;In many instances proceeds from the insurance policies of Holocaust victims were used to finance and extend the war or enrich Nazi war criminals,&quot; plaintiffs alleged.</p>
<p>Shares in Wiener Allianz, which controls around 20 percent of the Austrian insurance market, were 20 schillings down at 1,350 in Vienna on Monday. Der Anker is unlisted.</p>
<p>Other defendants in the case are: Assicurazioni Generali S.p.A. of Trieste, Italy; A.G.F. Assurances Generales de France Vie of Paris; Riunione Adriatica Di Sicurta S.p.A. of Milan; Allianz Group of Munich; and Bavarian Reinsurance Co of Munich.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
