<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480213" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss chocolate maker Lindt targets U.S.</title>
<headline>Swiss chocolate maker Lindt targets U.S.</headline>
<byline>Alice Ratcliffe</byline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swiss chocolate producer Lindt &amp; Spruengli AG aims to expand business in the U.S. where its sales now are comparatively small, but where it sees more chances for growth than in Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;America is a very big market,&quot; said Lindt's chairman and chief executive officer Ernst Tanner, speaking to journalists at a news conference to present 1996 results.</p>
<p>&quot;If all goes well, we would like to be market leader&quot; in the U.S. premium chocolate sector, he said, adding the current market leader has up to 18 percent. Lindt now has slightly less than three percent of the U.S. premium market, worth over $1 billion in annual sales.</p>
<p>Lindt already offers its products in the U.S. through its own outlets, comprising 20 businesses in New England. It plans to open another 20 by the end of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;Our plan for this year is to regionally expand the store concept, then at the end of this year and early next year to evaluate the results and further refine the concept,&quot; Tanner said. Lindt hopes to have retail outlets nationally in the U.S. within five years, eight years after opening its first retail shop in 1994 in Portsmouth, New Hampshire.</p>
<p>Overall group profit rose in 1996 by 10.4 percent to 46.8 million Swiss francs from 42.4 million in 1995. Sales rose 5.8 percent to 973 million francs in 1996 from 920 million in 1995. In local currencies sales rose 3.7 percent.</p>
<p>The company plans to raise its dividend to 275 Swiss francs per share from 250 on 1995 results.</p>
<p>&quot;These results were achieved despite the generally difficult market environment,&quot; Tanner said.</p>
<p>The company said that the first quarter of 1997 began well.</p>
<p>But price pressure in major European markets continued and Tanner sees little scope for Lindt to raise prices.</p>
<p>Sales in Germany, France, Switzerland and Italy together comprised 80 percent of total sales. Sales in Germany and Switzerland slipped, while sales grew in France and Italy.</p>
<p>Meanwhile Lindt's sales in the U.S. rose 15 percent to $29.5 million in 1996, Tanner said. &quot;This remarkable result reflects not only the positive consumer mood in the U.S., but also the targeted efforts to better service the world's largest market for confectionary,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He sees a significant growth trend in the U.S. for higher-quality products, whether coffee, clothing or chocolate.</p>
<p>With this in mind, Lindt will aim to open its stores in population centres with above-average per capita income.</p>
<p>As to the lengths Lindt will go to adapt to the U.S. consumer, Rudolf Mueller, Lindt's director of manufacturing and engineering, said the Swiss chocolatier is even offering peanut butter chocolates in the U.S., a flavour combination foreign to Swiss palettes but a popular choice in the U.S.</p>
<p>It is also expanding U.S. production, where it has made chocolates since 1989.</p>
<p>Mueller said that current U.S. capacity, based on a single-day production shifts, was currently 900 metric tonnes. Lindt will open new production facilities in the U.S. with a capacity of 1,800 tonnes in September.</p>
<p>Lindt shares on Tuesday were unchanged at 27,000 Swiss francs per share while the overall Swiss market was down roughly three percent following losses in U.S. shares.</p>
<p>-- Zurich Editorial, +41 1 631 7340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
