<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480214" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German TV network Sat1 reports March ratings jump.</title>
<headline>German TV network Sat1 reports March ratings jump.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>German television network Sat1 said on Tuesday it had jumped to second place behind RTL in viewer share thanks to momentum from Sunday soccer matches, in-house productions and a new scheduling strategy.</p>
<p>The private station, which in February was ranked fourth among German networks, said ratings from the GfK media research institute showed it with a 14.6 percent market share in March, up 2.3 points from the previous month.</p>
<p>Private channel RTL remained the ratings leader with a 16.4 percent overall market share. It had an 18.7 percent rating among viewers between 14 and 49 years old.</p>
<p>Sat1 said pushing back the start of its evening prime-time programming to 8.15 p.m. had shielded it from competition with a popular news broadcast which begins at 8 p.m. and had contributed growth of a half to a full percentage point.</p>
<p>Separately Munich-based station Pro Sieben said its broadcast of Steven Spielberg's Holocaust film Schindler's List on Good Friday was the movie which drew the largest audience over the hotly contested Easter weekend.</p>
<p>The station said the audience of 6.7 million viewers was 600,000 more than the number who bought tickets to see the movie in German cinemas.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
