<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480203" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India rulers face hurdles in bid to pass budget.</title>
<headline>India rulers face hurdles in bid to pass budget.</headline>
<byline>Narayanan Madhavan</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's embattled ruling coalition said on Tuesday it wants parliament to approve the budget for 1997/98 (April-March) before a vote of confidence in the government due by April 11.</p>
<p>But it faced hurdles in its efforts after the main opposition Hindu nationalists said they were open on the move to get the budget passed, but not before the vote.</p>
<p>Jaipal Reddy, a spokesman for Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's 15-party United Front alliance, said the coalition was exploring ways of ensuring passage of the budget before the test vote. &quot;We are making an effort,&quot; Reddy told Reuters.</p>
<p>For the budget to be passed, the government would have to work out an agreement with either the Congress party, which withdrew its vital support on Sunday, or the Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP).</p>
<p>President Shankar Dayal Sharma on Monday asked Deve Gowda to prove his majority in the lower house of parliament by April 11.</p>
<p>&quot;The budget would not be possible before the confidence vote,&quot; BJP vice-president K.R. Malkani told Reuters. &quot;I don't see how Congress or the BJP will agree with that.&quot;</p>
<p>But it could be considered later, Malkani said. &quot;The government has to approach us, then we can consider the matter,&quot; he said. &quot;Let them convene a meeting. Let them do it properly,&quot; BJP president L.K. Advani told Reuters at the party office.</p>
<p>The Congress spokesman was not available for comment.</p>
<p>The Bombay benchmark index had opened down 1.3 percent at 3,339.47 after dropping more than eight percent on Monday to 3,360.89 on fears linked to political uncertanty and the fate of the budget. After hitting a high of 3,438.27, it was quoted at 3,430.43 at 1000 GMT, up a provisional 2.07 percent from Monday's close.</p>
<p>Analysts pinned hopes on parliament passing the 1997/98 (April-March) budget regardless of the political crisis.</p>
<p>&quot;There might be minor changes but we're hopeful the budget will go through,&quot; said Vinay Motwani at brokerage KBS Capital Management.</p>
<p>Malkani said a vote on the budget cannot precede the confidence vote because spending proposals needed to be discussed by parliamentary panels.</p>
<p>&quot;They are trying to divert attention from a political crisis,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The market-friendly budget, presented by Finance Minister P. Chidambaram on February 28, proposed to slash corporate and personal income tax rates. Parliament had been originally scheduled to take up the budget after reconvening on April 21.</p>
<p>Analysts said key aspects of the budget may not be resisted by the Congress party because Chidambaram's main proposals only carried forward an economic reform programme launched by Congress party's former finance minister, Manmohan Singh.</p>
<p>&quot;Since both sides are not in disagreement in a broad sense, the problem is more on ego,&quot; said analyst B.G. Verghese of the Centre for Policy Research.</p>
<p>&quot;(But) the Congress could say if you (United Front) could quit gracefully, we can pass the budget,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Reddy said the United Front's Steering Committee, which held a meeting on Monday, was considering asking the speaker of the lower house, P.A. Sangma, to determine if Congress and the BJP would agree to pass the budget before the test vote.</p>
<p>Minor amendments would be allowed, Reddy said.</p>
<p>The United Front's 15 parties control 178 votes in the 545-seat lower house, and claim the support of another dozen outside deputies. Congress has 140 members and the BJP and its direct allies command the support of 193 deputies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
