<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480219" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Brussels blue-chip index seen taking cue from Dow.</title>
<headline>Brussels blue-chip index seen taking cue from Dow.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brussels Bel-20 index which closed down two percent on Tuesday was expected to take a cue from Wall Street in coming days, but traders said further falls in the U.S. were likely to trigger a major sell-off.</p>
<p>&quot;It's wait-and-see for investors, if the Dow closes in positive territory it will boost the Bel-20 in coming days, but if it closes negative we'll plunge,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>The Brussels blue chip Bel-20 closed down 1.96 percent, or 42.08 points, at 2,104.29 after earlier falling over three percent.</p>
<p>Wall Street has fallen over four percent in the last two days of trade due to fears of further interest rate hikes.</p>
<p>Traders said investors were also eyeing U.S. NAPM figures for for an indication on U.S. rates.</p>
<p>&quot;There's no panic in the market, a lot of players are on the sidelines but some market players are taking the opportunity to pick up cheap stocks,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>Financials were hardest hit as they are more likely to suffer from further U.S. interest rate hikes.</p>
<p>&quot;Financials were under pressure, because of interest rate worries in the U.S.,&quot; trader Paul de Lophem at brokerage Mignon, Hanart, Declerck said.</p>
<p>Belgium's fourth-largest bank BBL fell 4.38 percent to 7,420 francs and insurer Royale Belge dropped 4.32 percent to 8,420 francs.</p>
<p>Financial group Fortis AG ended down 4.07 percent at 5,900 francs.</p>
<p>Elsewhere holding company Groupe Bruxelles Lambert (GBL) closed up 0.7 percent at 5,010 francs.</p>
<p>GBL and its unit Electrafina benefitted from news that several shareholders of French company Cie de Suez wanted Suez to distribute some of its cash ahead of a possible merger with Lyonnaise des Eaux.</p>
<p>Electrafina, which closed up 0.6 percent at 3,490 francs, owns 8.3 percent of Suez.</p>
<p>&quot;GBL is positive because of the Suez story and the same stands for Electrafina,&quot; added de Lophem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
