<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480277" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Dollar softer in Europe, tracks weak U.S. assets.</title>
<headline>Dollar softer in Europe, tracks weak U.S. assets.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The  dollar  opened softer in Europe after a four-day Easter break with the market nervous after sharp falls in U.S asset markets, said analysts.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials index lost 157 points to 6,583 on Monday after shedding 140 points last Thursday, for an aggregate 4.3 percent decline.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks as if the Fed will be tightening again...But the buoyancy in the U.S. economy argues for a firmer dollar,&quot; said Tony Norfield, treasury economist at ABN AMRO.</p>
<p>He said the dollar was likely to remain nervous  ahead of key economic indicators on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>Norfield said U.S. data, due later on Tuesday, could reinforce market expectations of higher U.S. rates to cool the economy.</p>
<p>U.S. February leading indicators, construction spending and March National Association of Purchasing Management (NAPM) are due at 1400 GMT.</p>
<p>The key NAPM index is forecast to be stronger at 54.6 vs 53.1 in February.</p>
<p>At 0753 the dollar was at 1.6670/75 marks vs 1.6772/77 marks in late Europe on Thursday. Against the yen, the dollar was steady at 123.48/3.53 vs 123.48/53 in late Europe on Thursday.  </p>
<p>While a strong NAPM could knock the U.S. unit, as the market anticipates the effect of higher rates on U.S. stock and bonds markets, the effect on the dollar should be short-lived.</p>
<p>&quot;I think any negative impact will be short-lived,&quot; said Chris Turner, currency strategist at BZW, adding that medium and longe-term the U.S. unit will find support from a strong U.S. economy.</p>
<p>&quot;It is hard to see why, for economic or policy reasons, the dollar is sliding. Data from Germany remains weak and other core European countries look in pretty poor shape,&quot; said ABN AMRO's Norfield.  </p>
<p>The start of Japan's new fiscal year was having little immediate impact on dollar/yen rates in Europe and analysts said they expected dollar/yen to remain rangebound ahead of the Bank of Japan's quarterly Tankan corporate survey on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is awaiting the Tankan index...We are expecting a strong survey,&quot; said BZW's Turner.</p>
<p>Tokyo stocks ended moderately lower on the first day of the 1997/98 financial year, following Wall Street's tumble and renewed bank woes. The 225-share Nikkei average shed 133.81 points, or 0.74 percent to 17,869.59.</p>
<p>--Julia Meehan, London newsroom +4471 542 6701</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
