<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480287" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Monthly review - Unrest in Albania, Middle East.</title>
<headline>Monthly review - Unrest in Albania, Middle East.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>An insurrection in Albania and violent clashes between Palestinians and Israeli troops dominated the news in March.</p>
<p>The month ended with Israeli leader Benjamin Netanyahu saying &quot;false dreams&quot; were the reason for Arab anger over Israeli policies that led to an Arab League decision to suspend normal ties with the Jewish state.</p>
<p>Italy was preparing to deploy a multinational security force in lawless Albania. Much of southern Albania remained in rebel hands after protests against the collapse of pyramid investment schemes turned into open insurrection.</p>
<p>Here is a chronology of the main events of the month:</p>
<p>Mar 1 - Albania's government resigns in response to riots rocking the Balkan state. The next day parliament votes to declare an immediate state of emergency. On March 5, army and police secure roads to the flashpoint town of Vlore.</p>
<p>Mar 3 - German anti-nuclear demonstrators clash with police around Dannenberg during protests against a train carrying nuclear waste to Gorleben, east of Hanover. The train finally arrives on Mar 5.</p>
<p>Mar 3 - In Pakistan, 136 people die when a runaway passenger express train crashes after being switched to a dead-end line to avert a collision with another express.</p>
<p>Mar 5 - Two former East German border guards convicted of manslaughter for the 1962 killing of Peter Fechter, who was running towards an Allied checkpoint.</p>
<p>Mar 5 - In Turkey, Islamist Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan signs a statement agreeing to a crackdown on religious activism.</p>
<p>Mar 6 - Nepalese Prime Minister Sher Bahadur Deuba resigns following the defeat of his coalition in a vote of confidence.</p>
<p>Mar 6 - Albania's President Berisha suspends military action against armed insurgents in the south of the country. Twenty-four hours later, rebels in the south reject an amnesty offer.</p>
<p>Mar 6 - In eastern Sri Lanka, Tamil Tiger rebels attack Vaunathivu army camp in Batticola and an air force base in Trincomalee; at least 65 soldiers die and 200 rebels are killed.</p>
<p>Mar 8 - Albanian rebels seize the last southern government stronghold of Gjirokaster.</p>
<p>Mar 10 - A jobless journalist hijacks a Taiwanese airliner to China to request asylum -- the first defection from Taiwan to China since 1986.</p>
<p>Mar 11 - Presidents Leonid Kuchma of Ukraine and Petru Lucinschi of Moldova pledge to form an &quot;equal&quot; customs union.</p>
<p>Mar 11 - A fire and explosion at a nuclear reprocessing plant contaminated at least 35 workers in Japan's worst atomic accident.</p>
<p>Mar 11 - Bashkim Fino, an economist from the opposition Socialist Party, is appointed Albania's new prime minister.</p>
<p>Mar 11 - Jordan warns Israel it is pushing the Middle East into crisis by dictating the terms of its withdrawal from the West Bank and by building new settlements in east Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Mar 12 - Exiled Nobel laureate Wole Soyinka and 11 other dissidents charged with treason by Nigeria's military government over a spate of recent bomb blasts.</p>
<p>Mar 12 - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu ends his first visit to Russia, hailing a new era of better ties between the two countries.</p>
<p>Mar 13 - A Jordanian soldier shoots dead seven Israeli girls on a school trip to an area called &quot;The Island of Peace&quot; on the border with Jordan.</p>
<p>Mar 13 - Sister Nirmala is elected as the new Superior General of the Missionaries of Charity, succeeding Mother Teresa.</p>
<p>Mar 13 - The U.S. House of Representatives votes to censure Mexico over its lack of anti-drug efforts.</p>
<p>Mar 14 - Australia and Indonesia sign a sea boundary treaty establishing exclusive economic zones between the two nations.</p>
<p>Mar 14 - Gunmen go on a deadly rampage in a southern Egypt hamlet, killing 13 people.</p>
<p>Mar 14 - President Bill Clinton undergoes an operation to repair a knee tendon torn during a late-night stumble.</p>
<p>Mar 14 - Hundreds of Americans and Europeans are evacuated from Albania by land and sea as small arms fire crackles through the streets of Tirana.</p>
<p>Mar 15 - Zairean rebels seize the country's third city of Kisangani.</p>
<p>Mar 16 - Jordan's King Hussein meets Israeli leaders following the killing seven Jewish schoolgirls by a Jordanian soldier.</p>
<p>Mar 17 - Papua New Guinea Prime Minister Sir Julius Chan sacks the head of the country's defence force after he demanded that Chan quit within 48 hours. On March 26, Chan bows to pressure and steps aside temporarily.</p>
<p>Mar 17 - Prime Minister John Major launches Britain's longest general election campaign in 80 years when he confirms that polling day will be May 1.</p>
<p>Mar 17 - President Boris Yeltsin sets Russia on course for a new spell of profound economic and social change in his most dramatic government reshuffle in five years.</p>
<p>Mar 18 - Israel breaks ground for a Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem, defying world opinion.</p>
<p>Mar 18 - Hwang Jang-yop, the highest North Korean official to flee the Stalinist state, flies to the Philippines from China.</p>
<p>Mar 18 - Forty-six passengers and crew aboard a Russian AN-24 plane die when it crashes en route to Turkey.</p>
<p>Mar 18 - An Italian military court orders house arrest for former SS captain Erich Priebke, pending a re-trial for his role in Italy's worst World War Two atrocity.</p>
<p>Mar 18 - A munitions dump explosion kills or wounds more than 300 people in the eastern Afghan city of Jalalabad.</p>
<p>Mar 20 - The leader of the self-proclaimed Nagorno-Karabakh republic, Robert Kocharyan, is appointed Armenian prime minister.</p>
<p>Mar 21 - A suicide bomb attack in a cafe in Tel Aviv kills four people and wounds 42.</p>
<p>Mar 21 - Presidents Bill Clinton and Boris Yeltsin hail their summit meeting in Helsinki as a major breakthrough. They said they settled key arms accords but remained far apart over NATO.</p>
<p>Mar 21 - Zaire's ailing and embattled President Mobutu Sese Seko returns home from cancer treatment in Monaco.</p>
<p>Mar 21 - The Netherlands reports its first case of Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE), or mad cow disease.</p>
<p>Mar 22 - President Boris Yeltsin says Moscow wants to join the European Union as part of its attempt to end its Cold War-era isolation for good.</p>
<p>Mar 22 - Five members of the Solar Temple sect die in an apparent suicide pact in Saint Casimir, 37 miles (60 km) southwest of Quebec.</p>
<p>Mar 23 - Belarus arrests Serzh Alexandrov, first secretary at the U.S. embassy and asks her to leave the country within 24 hours. On Mar 25, the United States recalls its Belarus ambassador. The next day, the United States expels the Belarus first consul.</p>
<p>Mar 24 - Australian parliament overturns the world's first and only euthanasia law after it was introduced nine months ago in the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>Mar 24 - In Zaire, President Mobutu Sese Seko accepts the resignation of his prime minister Kengo wa Dondo.</p>
<p>Mar 26 - The bodies of 39 people belonging to the Heaven's Gate cult are found in a mansion outside San Diego after a mass suicide.</p>
<p>Mar 27 - The Dalai Lama ends his first visit to Taiwan.</p>
<p>Mar 27 - At least 1.8 million Russians protest in cities from the Pacific to the Baltic against unpaid wages and government policy.</p>
<p>Mar 28 - U.N. Security Council approves a multinational force for Albania with a mandate for three months. A refugee boat crashes into an Italian navy Corvette in the Adriatoc, killing more than 80.</p>
<p>Mar 29 - Sixteen people die in a car bomb explosion in a crowded bus station in the northern Indian city of Jammu.</p>
<p>Mar 29 - Israeli troops kill a Palestinian protester during clashes over Israeli settlements in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Mar 30 - In India, the Congress party withdraws its support from Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's government. On the 31st, Deve Gowda is asked to seek a confidence vote by April 11.</p>
<p>Mar 30 - A man with an assault rifle attacks hundreds of pupils at two schools in Sanaa, Yemen, killing six children and two others. He is sentenced to death the next day.</p>
<p>Mar 31 - Arab foreign ministers' meeting in Cairo approves a resolution seeking an end to normal relations with Israel and a restoration of the Arab boycott of Israel.</p>
<p>Mar 31 - Indian and Pakistani diplomats end four days of talks in New Delhi, the first for three years, and agree to a future meeting in Islamabad.</p>
<p>Mar 31 - Zairean rebels seize the southern rail city of Kamina, effectively cutting off the copperbelt province of Shaba from the rest of the country.</p>
<p>Mar 31 - Spanish authorities say 19 people were killed when a crowded passenger train was derailed near the city of Pamplona in northern Navarre province.</p>
<p>Notable Deaths in March included: Cheddi Jagan, President of Guyana (6th): Michael Manley, former prime minister of Jamaica (6); LaVern Baker, influential blues singer of the 1950s (10); Fred Zinnemann, U.S. director of films including &quot;High Noon&quot; (14); Willem De Kooning, U.S. artist and founder of &quot;Abstract Expressionist&quot; school (19); and veteran French Africa kingmaker Jacques Foccart (19).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
