<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480249" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: GERMANY AGAIN SAYS MAASTRICHT GOALS MUST BE MET.</title>
<headline>GERMANY AGAIN SAYS MAASTRICHT GOALS MUST BE MET.</headline>
<byline>Catherine O'Mahony</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-03-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany stuck to its hard line on monetary union over the Easter weekend, reaffirming its faith in a rigorous interpretation of the Maastricht Treaty amid fresh signs of extreme public scepticism about the project.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Theo Waigel argued that only strict adherence to the demanding budgetary goals set down in the treaty would secure the success of the single currency, scheduled to begin on January 1 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;Germans will only accept the common European currency if it is just as strong as the mark. Therefore I stand by my statement -- convergence determines the timetable,&quot; Waigel said in an interview with the Welt am Sonntag newspaper.</p>
<p>His comments came as a nationwide poll by the Bild am Sonntag newspaper showed nearly two thirds of Germans opposed the euro. An even larger number opposed any attempt to raise taxes or cut welfare benefits to ensure its success.</p>
<p>Top economic commentators, including a senior Bundesbank official, said there was a case for leeway on the budgetary goals set out in the treaty. Candidates for the single currency will be judged on the basis of their 1997 economic performance.</p>
<p>German leaders have always insisted on a strict interpretation of Maastricht to win over a sceptical public, who regard the deutschemark as a talisman and dread any possible dilution of their savings and spending power.</p>
<p>The treaty calls for debt to total no more than 60 percent of gross domestic product -- or at least to show significant progress in falling towards this level -- and for deficits to be three percent or less, except in exceptional circumstances.</p>
<p>The room for interpretation has become a hot issue. As Germany battles unemployment of 4.7 million, the highest number since 1933, its chances of meeting the Maastricht debt goals on the button this year are widely viewed as slim.</p>
<p>On Saturday, the DIW economic institute predicted that Germany's 1997 deficit to GDP level would be 3.5 percent, way off the target. But, it said, the Maastricht Treaty was flexible on this point.</p>
<p>&quot;Chancellor (Helmut) Kohl and Waigel should therefore not be more pope-like than the Pope, and use that leeway,&quot; DIW budget expert Dieter Vesper told the daily Neeue Osnabruecker Zeitung.</p>
<p>Commerzbank AG chief executive Martin Kohlhaussen told Reuters the Maastricht debt criteria did not have to be met &quot;exactly on the spot.&quot;</p>
<p>Bundesbank council member and euro-supporter Ernst Welteke weighed in to say he also saw room for manoeuvre on EMU debt goals, and questioned the importance of debt levels as an indication of stability.</p>
<p>&quot;The connection between public debt and stability is actually not that great: For example we will probably have an inflation rate of 1.5 percent this month, alongside rising public debt,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>On the treaty itself, Welteke said &quot;the fiscal criterion is described in such a way that the overall political situation is also taken into account.&quot;</p>
<p>Waigel, however, stuck by a tougher line. &quot;Strict adherence to the stability criteria is a decisive prerequisite for a strong euro,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Talk of laxity on the Maastricht criteria risked ruining confidence in the currency union, the finance minister said. In particular, speculation about delaying the euro launch disrupted financial markets.</p>
<p>Waigel also said he was still determined to achieve more cuts in social welfare spending. &quot;Budgetary consolidation is a very serious issue for me,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>This was &quot;not a duty exercise for Maastricht but is happening in our own interests&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>The Bild am Sonntag poll showed 83 percent of Germans opposed any cuts in social welfare spending that were designed to boost Germany's chances of joining the single currency.</p>
<p>A separate poll of chief economists of major companies, run in the Welt am Sonntag, showed 38.4 percent were confident Germany would fulfil the Maastricht criteria this year and only 15.3 percent supported a delayed start for the euro.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
