<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480248" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: PRESS DIGEST - GREEK FINANCIAL NEWS - APRIL 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - GREEK FINANCIAL NEWS - APRIL 1.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leading stories in the Greek financial press:</p>
<p>KATHIMERINI</p>
<p>--Countries participating in the Italian-led multinational protection force to Albania are making the final decisions on the make-up of the mission. Greece is expected to send a mobile battalion of 600-700 men - reinforced with armoured vehicles and tanks - to the region of Tirana.</p>
<p>--The government is considering reducing subsidisation of private investment by 38.0 percent or a total of 100 billion drachmas, unable to satisfy all the requests flooding into the national economy ministry and regional services. </p>
<p>--Education Minister Gerasimos Arsenis is confident an end is near to the dispute between the ministry and secondary school teachers and that the ministry's circular will be implemented. The teachers' union OLME however appears to disagree and plans a new rally in Athens today.</p>
<p>--A map depicting Greek islands in the eastern Aegean as Turkish caused red faces at yesterday's seminar on renewable sources of energy. European Commissioner Christos Papoutsis has called for an inquiry into the Brussels-drafted map.</p>
<p>ELEFTHEROTYPIA</p>
<p>--Defence Minister Akis Tsohatzopoulos has found 300 men to send to Albania as part of the multinational protection force and is now looking for another 500.</p>
<p>--Reliable sources say that recent conciliatory remarks by the Turkish chief of staff Hakki Karadayi can be attributed to reported marriage plans between his son and Prime Minister Costas Simitis's daughter Marilena.</p>
<p>TA NEA</p>
<p>--National Economy and Finance Minister Yannos Papandoniou is insisting that wage increases to public utility and organisation employees not exceed 7.0 percent.</p>
<p>--Former deputy foreign minister Christos Rozakis says communication between Athens and Ankara would be to the benefit of both sides.</p>
<p>--Ten air force cadets are being prosecuted over the vicious beating of a junior cadet.</p>
<p>ELEFTHEROS TYPOS</p>
<p>--Major changes to the pension system are hidden in recent statements by Labour and Social Security Minister Miltiades Papaioannou.</p>
<p>--Ruling party PASOK president and Prime Minister Costas Simitis is reportedly considering a cabinet reshuffle to deal with the forthcoming fresh New Democracy line-up, following the election of leader Costas Karamanlis last week.</p>
<p>--More than 4,000 devout Orthodox believers demonstrated outside Parliament yesterday against the Schengen treaty, causing traffic chaos in the city centre during peak hour.</p>
<p>--Turkish commandos will be stationed in southern Albania to guard the ethnic Greek minority, according to reports. </p>
<p>ETHNOS</p>
<p>--Unions in public utilties are threatening strikes if the government continues to insist on its income policy threshold of 7.0 percent.</p>
<p>--The Ambulance Service's new motorcycle service, ferrying doctors quickly through city traffic to casualties, officially begins today. --Maria Petrakis, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
