<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480217" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-UK manufacturing grows in March, but jobs go.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-UK manufacturing grows in March, but jobs go.</headline>
<byline>Rosemary Bennett</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's manufacturing sector expanded in March for the tenth month in a row but the pace of growth eased as firms axed jobs to cut costs, a leading business survey said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The Chartered Institute of Purchasing and Supply (CIPS) said its purchasing managers' index stood at a seasonally adjusted 52.9 in March compared with 53.4 in February.</p>
<p>The institute said the fall in the index was a result of a drop in manufacturing employment, the first since last May.</p>
<p>&quot;A slightly higher number of firms cut staffing levels as part of effiency-boosting rationalisation programmes, such as downsizing, than recruited new staff,&quot; the institute said.</p>
<p>A reading over 50 indicates expansion in the sector, with the small fall in the index level showing the pace of growth eased.</p>
<p>The survey said new orders registered higher growth in March with the principal source of demand coming from the home market.</p>
<p>And contrary to other business surveys, export orders also rose and at a faster rate than in February, largely due to faster growth in the economies of key European trading partners.</p>
<p>Manufacturing firms have complained recently that the pound's dramatic appreciation -- 15 percent on a trade-weighted basis since August -- is checking demand for British goods abroad.</p>
<p>Their concerns were strongly reflected in the Confederation of British Industry's latest monthly trends survey which said export demand in March fell to its lowest level since November 1993.</p>
<p>However, the CIPS survey said despite the slight increase in export demand in March, on a longer term basis firms were suffering from the pound's spirited rise.</p>
<p>&quot;The impact of the recent increase in the value of the pound continued to subdue export orders compared to the strong performance recorded in the latter half of last year.&quot;</p>
<p>The PMI is seen as a reliable barometer of activity in manufacturing. The snap shot it provides is often confirmed by subsequent official data.</p>
<p>The manufacturing recovery badly lags the lively activity seen in the services sector. Manufacturers were badly hit last year first by slow growth in key export markets, then by a massive appreciation in the pound.</p>
<p>Chancellor of the Exchequer Kenneth Clarke has used the pound's appreciation to justify leaving interest rates on hold at six percent.</p>
<p>But economists said the strength of the domestic economy looks like it is more than compensating for weaker exports, calling into question this decision.</p>
<p>&quot;The strength we're seeing in domestic orders and even in export orders suggests we should be worried about the growth outlook in the medium term,&quot; said Michael Dicks, UK economist at Lehman Brothers.</p>
<p>&quot;The currency strength clearly isn't hurting the manufacturing sector that much.&quot; And Michael Saunders, UK economist at Salomon Brothers, said while the PMI survey did not in itself put pressure on the authorities for higher rates, faster growth in the services sector will soon prompt a rate rise.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect base rates to rise by 50 basis points and possibly by as much as 75 basis points soon after the election, regardless of who wins.&quot;</p>
<p>The election will be held on May 1 and, if the opinion polls are correct, opposition Labour will soundly beat the ruling Conservatives and form the next government.</p>
<p>And CIPS will offer a detailed insight into the service industries on Thursday when it launches a new survey on the sector.</p>
<p>It will cover all service businesses, apart from retail and</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
