<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480297" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian bonds hold nerve against U.S. plight.</title>
<headline>Australian bonds hold nerve against U.S. plight.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>----------(Snapshot at 4.35 P.M./0635 GMT)------------------</p>
<p>FUTURES					  CASH YIELD</p>
<p>90-DAY BILLS  (JUN) 93.80  (- 0.03)    6.11    (UNCH)</p>
<p>3-YR T-BONDS  (JUN) 92.66  (- 0.06)    7.22    (+ 0.15)</p>
<p>10-YR T-BONDS (JUN) 91.765 (-0.140)    8.16    (+ 0.13)</p>
<p>AUD/USD  0.7870 (PREV 0.7858) US 30-YR  7.10   (7.10 NY)</p>
<p>---------------------(April 1)------------------------------</p>
<p>*Australian bond yields finished below their early highs as the market held its nerve in the face of jittery U.S. markets amid fears that the Fed will tighten policy again.</p>
<p>*U.S. March NAPM index due later today.  </p>
<p>Australian bond yields finished below their early highs as the market held its nerve in the face of jittery U.S. Treasuries.</p>
<p>Bond futures dropped to their lowest levels in six months on the return from the four-day Easter break as the market adjusted to the sell-off in the U.S. market amid fears that the Federal Reserve will tighten policy again.</p>
<p>A modest tick down in U.S. yields in Tokyo trading helped to stabilise the market, although local turnover was relatively light with less than 10,000 lots traded on the June 10-year bond futures contract.  </p>
<p>&quot;The market went into Easter reasonably flat which prevented a huge reaction here. Most of the action was in futures, with physicals fairly limited,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Signs of an expanding U.S. economy saw the U.S. 30-year bond yield spike through 7.0 percent on Thursday. Although the short end of the U.S. curve benefitted from further weakness in U.S. stocks on Monday, the market faces the March National Association of Purchasing Management index later today.</p>
<p>Reuters' survey of U.S. economists expects the index to rise to 53.6 from 53.1 in February and such a reading would heighten fears of continued strong U.S. economic growth.  </p>
<p>The Dow Jones index dropped 157 points on Monday after slumping 140 points on Thursday, the last day before Easter.</p>
<p>Locally, the Reserve Bank of Australia held its monthly board meeting today and although last week's 25 basis point tightening by the Fed is expected to have been on the agenda, economists unanimously do not expect the RBA to follow suit.</p>
<p>Expectations of a subdued Australian inflation report later this month and the prospect of further fiscal tightening in the May Federal budget should help the local bond market withstand some of the bearishness eminating from the U.S., analysts said.  </p>
<p>----------------------(SPREADS)---------------------------------</p>
<p> AUD VS   3-YR	   10-YR	* AUD 3-YR/10-YR SPREAD</p>
<p> USD	 66 (- 01)   128 (+ 02) * FUTURES   89.5  (+ 07.5)</p>
<p> CAD	183 (- 21)   141 (- 04) * CASH	95    (+ 06)</p>
<p> NZD	-73 (- 01)   +09 (UNCH) *</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>The local yield curve steepened with the short end protected by the prospect of the RBA maintaining its &quot;on hold&quot; rates policy stance at least until the fourth quarter.</p>
<p>The yield spread to the Canadian short-end narrowed sharply as the market there weakened with the Canadian dollar.</p>
<p>-------------------------(TECHNICALS)---------------------------</p>
<p>FUTURES	*SUP/RES     *SUP/RES 2ND *RSI    *MA-10 *MA-20</p>
<p>10-YEAR (JUN)*91.72-91.80 *91.65-91.85 *31 PCT *91.89 *91.97</p>
<p>3-YEAR  (JUN)*92.60-92.67 *92.50-92.75 *37 PCT *92.73 *92.76</p>
<p>90-DAY  (JUN)*93.80-93.86 *93.75-93.88 *39 PCT *93.82 *93.83</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>The 10-year bond contract broke down through a 2-1/4 year rising trendline just after the opening at 91.780, but the move lacked a sustained follow through and stopped just short of testing 91.710, a level tested twice in early September.</p>
<p>-- Colin Brinsden 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
