<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480298" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian stocks slump with Dow, but end off lows.</title>
<headline>Australian stocks slump with Dow, but end off lows.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>-----------------(Snapshot 4.20 p.m./0620 GMT)-----------------</p>
<p>AORD		 2352.2  -70.1    DJIA (close)  6583.48 -157.11</p>
<p>SPI Sycom	  2339.0  -74.0    US 30yr (close)  7.10   +0.10</p>
<p>10yrbond futs    91.780  -0.125   Gold NY 350.95 Prev cl 349.20</p>
<p>AUD	 $0.7872 (Thur $0.7860)  CRB Index	245.17   -0.92</p>
<p>NIKKEI (midpm)17,869.59 -133.81   FTSE cl	  4312.9  +11.4</p>
<p>S&amp;P500(Globex)   759.75  +1.75    NZSE40 (close)2207.48  -29.26</p>
<p>--------------------------(April 1)----------------------------</p>
<p>*Stocks end down 2.9 pct, but off lows on thin volumes, seen well-supported despite Dow slump. Volume 300.90 million, value A$729.91 million, 1,098 stocks traded, 168 steady, 94 up, 836 down.  </p>
<p>Australian stocks rode Wall Street's tattered coat-tails 2.9 percent lower on Tuesday, but ended a lightly traded day off its lows as brokers said sentiment remained resilient and the panic button untouched.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the mood was relatively relaxed -- there was no panic,&quot; said Hartley Poynton dealer Mark Macleod.</p>
<p>&quot;This correction had been signalled by Greenspan and it shouldn't have been a surprise,&quot; Macleod said.</p>
<p>Brokers said volumes were thin, reflecting the dearth of fund manager sell orders and the lack of genuine weakness. The All Ordinaries index ended down 70.1 points at 2,352.2.  </p>
<p>&quot;There was definitely no panic,&quot; said a senior Sydney broker.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically anyone with a buy order out there just withdrew it from the screens early on, waited for the prices to drop and then put their buy orders back in at lower levels,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Brokers said the overall market looked well-supported technically at around the 2,350 level, which had been a previous market high and is a key fibonacci retracement level.</p>
<p>&quot;I think even if the Dow drops another 20 to 30 points tonight, the market should hold up pretty well at these levels,&quot; said Macleod.  </p>
<p>BHP's 3.23 percent morning fall to an intra-day low of A$16.45 and then its rebound to A$16.52 by the close echoed the fortunes of the market overall.</p>
<p>Besides BHP, the other major stocks to take the brunt of the Dow-induced selloff included RTZ Corp Plc-CRA Ltd and Coca Cola Amatil, which fell two to three percent.</p>
<p>Banking stocks were also hit hard, falling on the Dow and the sharp rise in local and U.S. bond yields. Australian 10 year bond yields rose to 8.16 percent from 8.03 percent. National Australia Bank fell 44 cents to A$15.71 by the close, however, it too had bounced off its A$15.64 intra-day low.  </p>
<p>The All Ordinaries fell in morning trade to 2,342.4, its lowest level since the 2,331.7 intra-day low on December 20, 1996. Gold stocks fell sharply despite a rise in the gold price, reeling along with the Canadian market on concerns about the drilling results from Indonesia's Busang deposit.</p>
<p>Newcrest Mining fell 22.5 cents to A$3.955, helping to shove the gold index down 46.6 points or 2.80 percent to 1,619.9. Brokers said some feared that Canadian investors, who have helped underpin Australia's gold shares in recent times, would bail out of their overseas investments after being burnt so badly by the Busang controversy.  </p>
<p>------------------------(TECHNICALS)----------------------------</p>
<p>Short-term range    Support   Restnce   RSI-14  MA-10  MA-20</p>
<p>AORD   2340/2400     2330	2410	32.45   2398   2420</p>
<p>SPI    2330/2400     2320	2410	37.13   2385   2411</p>
<p>-------------------------KEY ACTIVES----------------------------</p>
<p>*BHP A$16.52 (-0.48) A$16.640/16.450 Vol: 4,194,693</p>
<p>*NAB A$15.71 (-0.44) A$15.891/15.641 Vol: 1,638,551</p>
<p>*CRA A$18.22 (-0.64) A$18.47/18.20 Vol: 2,196,634</p>
<p>*C-C Amatil A$11.92 (-0.21) A$11.95/11.650 Vol: 601,897</p>
<p>Major stocks selloff in line with Dow's dive, rising yields</p>
<p>*Century Drilling A$1.57 (+0.04) A$1.60/57 Vol:207,650</p>
<p>Century recommends acceptance of Downer's A$1.60 takeover offer</p>
<p>-- Bernard Hickey, Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1812</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
