<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480238" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FEATURE - ART SHOW RECALLS HAPPIER FRANCO-BELGIAN GOLDEN AGE.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - ART SHOW RECALLS HAPPIER FRANCO-BELGIAN GOLDEN AGE.</headline>
<byline>Paul Taylor</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>&quot;How do you shoot a Frenchman?&quot; goes an old Belgian joke. &quot;Aim above his head and you hit him right in the middle of his superiority complex.&quot;</p>
<p>Franco-Belgian relations sometimes seem like a caricature of the love-hate relationship between a big country used to throwing its weight about in the world and a smaller one with a nagging inferiority complex.</p>
<p>The French have long revelled in &quot;Belgian jokes&quot; that make their northern neighbours out to be slow-witted buffoons. The Belgians reciprocate with a caustic humour depicting the French as arrogant and too clever by half.</p>
<p>Relations have soured beyond a joke this year over French carmaker Renault's decision to close its only factory in Belgium, throwing 3,100 people out of work.</p>
<p>France is meanwhile shielding from Belgian justice a top industrialist, Serge Dassault, wanted in Belgium for allegedly bribing politicians to win a big aviation contract.</p>
<p>So a new exhibition at Paris's Grand Palais, which moves to Ghent in September, is a welcome reminder of a more harmonious period when Franco-Belgian cross-fertilisation and emulation inspired some of the greatest European art.</p>
<p>&quot;Paris-Brussels, Brussels-Paris&quot; chronicles the prolific artistic dialogue between the two countries in the second half of the 19th century -- the age of realism, impressionism, symbolism and art nouveau. FRENCH ARTISTS, WRITERS FOUND LIBERAL REFUGE IN BRUSSELS</p>
<p>French and Belgian artists, writers and composers were often first appreciated in each other's country before making a breakthrough at home.</p>
<p>Libertarian Brussels provided a welcoming political asylum for such French artists and intellectuals as the painter David, exiled for having voted to execute King Louis XVI, and later the writer Victor Hugo when they were undesirable in France.</p>
<p>Hugo fled Napoleon III's 1852 coup and settled in Brussels until he was expelled in 1871, the year of the Paris commune, when bourgeois Belgium feared being contaminated by revolution.</p>
<p>Belgium's intellectual avant-garde and thriving art market drew French painters whose works initially scandalised Paris, such as Courbet, Manet, the impressionists and the pointillists.</p>
<p>Among the most active Belgian artistic groups were the &quot;Cerle des XX&quot; and &quot;La Libre Esthetique&quot;, both created by Octave Maus, which exhibited modern French art and staged music by composers such as Massenet and Debussy.</p>
<p>French poets Baudelaire, Verlaine, Rimbaud and Mallarme were attracted both to the free living of Brussels and to the gothic mysticism of old Flemish towns.</p>
<p>French authors regarded as scandalous at home found publishers and patrons in Brussels, although Baudelaire was bitterly disappointed and wrote a diatribe against &quot;Poor Brussels&quot;, which was never published.</p>
<p>BELGIAN ARTISTS FOUND FAME FIRST IN PARIS</p>
<p>The sculptor Rodin spent six formative years in Brussels in 1871-77, where he decorated the wealthy city's booming Bourse and created his first masterpiece, the stunningly realistic male bronze nude &quot;L'age d'airain&quot;.</p>
<p>The exhibition shows how French scuptors such as Carpeaux, Dalou and Lambeaux drew inspiration from Rubens' monumental canvases of writhing pink flesh.</p>
<p>The Franco-Belgian exchange illustrated by curators Anne Pingeot of Paris' Musee d'Orsay and Robert Hoozee of the Museum of Fine Art in Ghent was not quite a dialogue among equals.</p>
<p>&quot;The receptiveness of Belgian circles did a lot for French art...Belgian interest in French creativity awakened in return a curiosity among the French about the Belgians. But Belgium never really had an artistic influence on France,&quot; Hoozee said.</p>
<p>The Belgian James Ensor was in his way as great a painter as Manet, but he did not exert the same international magnetism.</p>
<p>Yet Pingeot argues that Belgium did achieve that eminence at the turn of the 20th century, when Horta, Mucha and Van de Velde were the driving force of art nouveau, the high-point and probably the culmination of half a century of cross-pollination.</p>
<p>However she notes that many Belgian artists achieved fame first in Paris, citing the author Maeterlinck, whose play &quot;Pelleas and Melisandre&quot; inspired Debussy's opera, and the social realist Constantin Meunier.</p>
<p>The show, part of a Franco-Belgian season that includes two other travelling exhibitions -- one on Rodin in Belgium and one on the Belgian poet Emile Verhaeren -- stops at the eve of World War One, which effectively broke the privileged artistic links.</p>
<p>For much of the 20th century, France and Belgium have given the impression of living with their backs to each other, politically and artistically.</p>
<p>French people tend to think of Brussels, less than two hours away by high-speed train, as the capital of Europe rather than of Belgium nowadays.</p>
<p>There is something hauntingly topical about Meunier's giant paintings and sculptures of downtrodden working-class heroes at a time when a French employer is throwing Belgian workers on the dole.</p>
<p>If Meunier were alive today, he might well be painting the striking car workers of Vilvoorde, occupying their assembly plant in a doomed fight to save their jobs.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
