<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480234" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Emerging Europe Advertising &amp; Media Digest - Apr 1.</title>
<headline>Emerging Europe Advertising &amp; Media Digest - Apr 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>REUTERS EMERGING EUROPE PRESS DIGEST FOR ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA</p>
<p>--------------- April 1, 1997 ------------------</p>
<p>Weekly Press Digest from Central and Eastern Europe on Advertising, Marketing, the Media, the Internet, Brand-name Products and Consumer Trends</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>ADVERTISING &amp; MARKETING:</p>
<p>-- Poland's advertising market grew 34 percent in 1996 over 1995, according to a report by BR TVP SA, the state-owned television broadcaster. The corporate sector spent $700 million on advertising campaigns last year.</p>
<p>(Rzeczpospolita, March 24, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- Coca Cola, Marlboro and Lucky Strike advertisements are among the most popular with Bulgarian television audiences, a survey by the Alpha Research agency shows. The most successful advertisements were those broadcast in the popular satirical weekly television show Kanaleto, the survey reports. (Capital, March 24-30, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- A consortium of SKBH Kft Sawyer/Miller Group and the media and market research firm Szonda Ipsos Kft has been awarded a 123.7 million forint ($704,000) contract for a public relations campaign for public sector reform in Hungary. The campaign will include broadcast of a cartoon series on public service television and an advertising and press campaign.</p>
<p>(Vilaggazdasag, March 27,1997)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>MEDIA AND THE INTERNET:</p>
<p>-- Around 2.5 million households in Poland have subscribed to cable televison in the past few years, the Polish Cable TV Association reports. Polska Televizja Kablowa cable TV supplier will take over the Gosat network, and Aster City will merge with Porion cable television. (Gazeta Wyborcza, March 24, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- A group of media professionals and foreign investors have formed a production team named Gold Rush that will produce a series of promotional films about Bulgaria. The project aims to focus international investors attention on Bulgaria, and the films are expected to be broadcast on CNN, NBC, and BBC as well as the national television stations of Germany, France, Belgium and Greece. (Pari, March 26, 1997)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>BRAND-NAME PRODUCTS AND MARKETS:</p>
<p>-- Hungary's Opel plant has manufactured 62,000 Astras since starting production five years ago, with 45,000 of the total cars produced driven by Hungarians. Todays Opels are usually equipped with two airbags, an anti-lock brake system, central locks and air conditioning. (Napi Gazdasag, March 24, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- The French Cora supermarket chain will open a 13,000 square-meter hypermarket in the outskirts of Budapest on May 8. The hypermarket will be Cora's first in Eastern Europe. The site has parking space for 2000 cars and cost 7 billion forints. Cora and Profi supermarkets are operated by the Delhaize group.</p>
<p>(Vilaggazdasag, March 27, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- About 80,000 visitors attended the 1997 Budapest travel exhibition and fair Utazas 97, fewer than the number of visitors recorded last year. Hungarians still seem to be more interested in travelling abroad than discovering places in Hungary. (Vilaggazdasag, March 24, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- Poland's consumption of paint and lacquer grew seven percent in 1996, according to a report by IB Austria Securities. Imports, mostly from the EU countries, were worth $140 million and accounted for 30 percent of the market in terms of value and 10 percent in terms of volume. (Gazeta Wyborcza, March 24, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria will participate with a national stand at the Moscow International Travel and Tourism fair from March 26 to 29, the Tourist Committee says. Committee chairman Roumen Draganov says he expects the event would boost Bulgarias image as a holiday destination for foreign tour operators. (Pari, March 26, 1997)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>CONSUMER TRENDS:</p>
<p>-- Over 90 percent of Poland's washing powder market is controlled by international chemical concerns, a survey by the Chemical Industry Institute says.(Zycie, March 27, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- About 49 percent of Poles have no savings at all, whereas 34 percent save money through financial instruments offered by banks or invest in stocks, a recent survey by the PBS polling institute says. (Rzeczpospolita, March 24, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- Polish consumers rarely understand technological and chemical names of compounds used to make products, which are advertised on the media, though they trust the components' beneficiary qualities, a recent survey by the Demoskop firm says. (Nowa Europa, March 26, 1997)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>-- The average Pole goes to the theatre nine times in his lifetime, the culture ministry official Grzegorz Wisniewski says. The number of theatre-goers fell more than 30 percent in the years 1978 and 1993, Wisniewski says. (Nowa Europa, March 26, 1997)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>-- Reuters London Advertising Newsdesk +44 171 542 2792</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>See more stories on Central and Eastern Europe and the rest of the world on Reuters Advertising &amp; Media Briefing. Why not visit our Internet site at http://www.bizinfo.reuters.com?</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>($ = 175.7 Hungarian Forints)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
