<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480255" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - Financial Times - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Financial Times - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>-- HOSTILE BID RESTRICTIONS LIKELY</p>
<p>Senior figures from industry and the City are reported to be lobbying for reforms from regulators to make hostile takeovers more difficult by restricting a bidder's ability to buy shares in the market. The moves follow the takeover in December of Northern Electric by the US group CalEnergy, which many people believe was acquired too cheaply because the bidder was able to make large market purchases. Regulators are understood to have conceded privately that change looks likely.</p>
<p>-- LABOUR SEEKS CURBS ON NON-RESIDENT TAX BREAKS</p>
<p>A future Labour government would act to curb the substantial tax breaks enjoyed by entrepreneurs who sell their businesses while technically non-resident in the UK, party sources have confirmed. Labour's treasury team are understood to be planning an 'objective residence test' in order to stop companies being sold free of capital gains tax if the owner has been working abroad for a year. The present rules on residence date back to the 18th century.</p>
<p>-- SHAKE-UP AT WORLD BANK WINS UNANIMOUS APPROVAL</p>
<p>The member states of the World Bank have given unanimous approval to plans for a sweeping reorganization of the institution. The moves, designed to increase the Bank's efficiency, entail an additional 250 million dollars to the running costs of the Bank by 2000, and spending at least 60 million dollars on redundancies. The proposals had to be scaled down in order to secure the approval, after the UK, the US and France expressed concern about their cost.</p>
<p>-- EUROPEAN UNION FINALLY FREES ITS SKIES</p>
<p>The European Union will on Tuesday complete the liberalization of its aviation market, leaving European airlines free to operate domestic services in countries other than their own. The move is the final act in a process of liberalisation that began in 1987 with the easing of controls on air fares. However, industry experts do not expect a rush of companies starting domestic services in other countries, with Europe's most profitable carrier, British Airways, still to begin making money from its French and German operations.</p>
<p>-- CHIPS ARE DOWN AS EU ACTS ON DUMPING</p>
<p>The European Union is set to reimpose minimum prices on imports of the biggest-selling semiconductor chips from 14 Japanese and South Korean manufacturers. The move is the latest attempt to preserve the domestic industry in the EU's 5.76 billion dollar a year market for Dynamic Random Access Memory (D-Ram) chips. Japan and South Korean currently have 80 percent of the European D-Ram market, and the EU has had to balance the protection of the European interest with the needs of European users of the components, who have warned that costs will spiral if minimum prices are reimposed.</p>
<p>-- BUSINESS FAILURES POINT TO PATCHY UPTURN</p>
<p>Figures released on Monday by business information group Dun &amp; Bradstreet show that businesses are finding the economic recovery is still patchy and fitful in spite of rising output and increased consumer spending during the past 12 months. The figures reveal that the number of businesses collapsing fell by nearly 10 percent in the first three months of 1997. Separately, credit insurance group Trade Indemnity has said bad debts and business failures were up 10 percent in 1996.</p>
<p>-- BANKERS' FEARS ON EMU GROWS</p>
<p>A survey of City financiers, carried out by London-based think-tank the Centre for the Study of Financial Innovation, has found that European Monetary Union is seen as the fastest-growing danger to the banking industry. The study, which canvassed 170 bankers, lawyers, accountants and regulators, found concern that Emu would force a restructuring of the European banking industry and cause more general economic and political strains.</p>
<p>-- RACAL LOOKING FOR EQUITY PARTNER</p>
<p>Defence and electronics group Racal Electronics is looking to beef up its network services business with an alliance that could see one or more partner take a stake of up to 50 percent in the business. Racal is understood to be considering overseas telecoms groups and UK cable operators as equity partners in the business. The company involved, Racal Network Services, is the world's seventh largest managed data network group, and analysts believe an alliance could value RNS -- which includes the former British Rail telecoms business BRT -- in excess of 500 million stg.</p>
<p>-- BSKYB SEEKS UP TO 700 MILLION STG FOR DIGITAL VENTURE</p>
<p>Satellite broadcaster BSkyB is reported to be seeking funds of between 600 million stg and 700 million stg to establish its digital television joint venture with British Telecom. The funds, larger than the amount expected by many observers, would be used to subsidise the UK launch of digital television by reducing by up to 50 percent the price of the set-top boxes needed to receive programmes. BT is keen that the set-top devices include a modem that can be plugged into a telephone line, linking customers with service providers and allowing interactive applications such as home banking and shopping.</p>
<p>-- FRANCE TELECOM IN SHARE PLAN</p>
<p>Michel Bon, the chairman of state-owned telecoms group France Telecom, has proposed that the company institute a share option plan for up to 1,500 senior employees following May's partial privatisation. Bon views such a scheme as an important element in changing the company from a civil service operation to a more customer-orientated outfit. Full details of the scheme will not be decided until after the FFr30 billion to FFr50 billion ($5.3 billion to $8.9 billion) floatation.</p>
<p>For a full range of news monitoring services, phone BMC +44-171-377-1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
