<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480288" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - New lease of life planned for London's Thames.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - New lease of life planned for London's Thames.</headline>
<byline>Pratima Desai</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Throughout history, the Thames was the vital artery of one of the world's great trading cities and an inspiration for poets and artists.</p>
<p>But over the past 30 years Londoners have neglected their river. After London ceased to be Europe's biggest port in the 1970s, vast areas of dockland became derelict and it was used as a dumping ground for sewage and industrial waste.</p>
<p>Now, it is back in favour and officially recognised as one of the capital's greatest assets. After two years of consultation, the government has launched its first blueprint for the Thames, designed to bring it back to life.</p>
<p>&quot;The river Thames is one of the nation's major natural assets which, sadly, is often neglected or under-used. I want the river to be a focus for the capital, a living, working waterway,&quot; said Environment Secretary John Gummer at the launch.</p>
<p>From the royal town of Windsor, west of London, all the way to the sea, the framework emphasises quality of environment and aims to protect and enhance natural and historic sites.</p>
<p>Use of the river for leisure activities is to be encouraged with the completion of the Thames Path National Trail, a 180-mile (288-kilometre) walk, formally launched in July 1996.</p>
<p>Also under construction is the Thames Cycle Route running from Hampton Court, west of the capital, to Dartford in the east.</p>
<p>The London Planning Advisory Committe (LPAC) welcomed recognition of the Thames as London's most under-used resource.</p>
<p>But it warned that the new Strategic Planning Guidance does not identify the mechanics of financing and implementing its recommendations.</p>
<p>&quot;It's all very well getting the policies right, but if you don't make sure the necessary resources and powers are available, then you're wasting your time,&quot; said Robin Clement, Deputy Chief Planner at the LPAC.</p>
<p>&quot;If a London borough has been trying to develop a site for a long time, it will be difficult to turn down a proposal that creates employment but does not fit the quality guidelines.&quot;</p>
<p>Other environmental and heritage associations, including the London Rivers Association (LRA) welcomed the guidelines.</p>
<p>&quot;We particularly welcome moves to prevent further contraction of the port industry,&quot; said LRA chairman George Nicholson.</p>
<p>USING THE RIVER AS ALTERNATIVE TRANSPORT</p>
<p>Central to the government's plan is attracting people and freight companies to use the river as an alternative means of transport, reducing traffic and pollution in the crowded capital, home to about eight million people.</p>
<p>&quot;The river's potential for transporting both goods and people, and thereby removing traffic from London's congested roads, is enormous,&quot; said Gummer.</p>
<p>Statutory directives have been issued to safeguard 32 river wharves between Hammersmith in west London and Newham in the east. Proposals for alternative development of wharves, some of which been used for luxury flat developments, will also have to be referred to the Department of Environment.</p>
<p>The Walbrook Wharf in the capital's financial district was recently refurbished at a cost more than four million pounds ($6.5 million).</p>
<p>It is used to move the equivalent of 624 lorry-loads of waste per week out to landfill sites east of London, saving the capital road congestion and air pollution.</p>
<p>Planners will also have to take into account the &quot;look&quot; of London and architects have been warned the Thames will not be allowed to be marred by ill-matching buildings.</p>
<p>&quot;Dramatic visual statements and landmark buildings are not ruled out but they should be exceptional and of the highest quality,&quot; the document said.</p>
<p>A definition of good design is not specified, but a series of tests and principles are listed to ensure new developments fit into the environment and are acceptable to local communities as well as national heritage and environmental groups.</p>
<p>Also highlighted is the need for construction of more bridges across the Thames, particularly in east London.</p>
<p>New bridges will help the regeneration of derelict and declining areas along the river, as well as relieve congestion at other crossings.</p>
<p>&quot;Their visual impact should be considered and a high quality of design encouraged,&quot; the guidelines said. ($ = 0.614 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
