<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480268" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSTANT VIEW - UK March PMI survey.</title>
<headline>INSTANT VIEW - UK March PMI survey.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following is a list of reactions to UK PMI March survey published at 0830 GMT.</p>
<p>The survey showed Britain's purchasing managers reported their tenth consecutive month of expansion in March with strong growth of output and new orders.</p>
<p>JEREMY HAWKINS, BANK OF AMERICA</p>
<p>&quot;This is very favourable and suggests growth is holding up nicely. If I were the Chancellor, I'd say everything in the garden is pretty well rosy.&quot;  </p>
<p>MICHAEL DICKS, LEHMAN BROTHERS</p>
<p>&quot;I agree the short term outlook is pretty rosy, but I think the strength we're seeing in domestic orders and even in export orders suggests we should be worried about the growth outlook in the medium term, because the currency strength certainly isn't hurting the manufacturing sector that much, and what we don't know about today is what's happening in the service sector and that's where the economy's main problems lie.&quot;  </p>
<p>ANDREW CATES, UBS</p>
<p>&quot;On the export side there hasn't been any weakness in export orders balances, but given the strong domestic economy the total orders balance is still at a low level, and the reason for that is export orders continue to subdue it. Generally, the pound's strength has continued to affect prices and the prices paid index is still well below 50 showing inflation pressures are very subdued. The survey shows some expansion but its nothing to get excited about and the sector is a long way from overheating.&quot; --Catherine Bremer +44 171 542 2774--</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
