<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480262" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: United, utilities resilient to market trend.</title>
<headline>United, utilities resilient to market trend.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Utility stocks showed some resilience to overall London stock market falls on Tuesday with United Utilities bucking the trend to be the only gainer on the FT-SE 100 as they appeared a defensive play for the market, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen some buyers this morning and people with small books are covering their tracks,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>United Utilities was up two pence at 0900 GMT to 630 pence with Scottish Power unchanged at 353-1/2 pence as the overall market fell 2.21 percent.  </p>
<p>Scottish Hydro was up two pence to 363 pence while generator National Grid had edged down three pence to 206-1/2 pence.</p>
<p>The utilities were also being seen as a relatively defensive play in a sliding market, analysts said, helping to trim losses.</p>
<p>&quot;National Grid, for example, is quite a defensive stock and so it is not expected to move too far,&quot; one analyst said.</p>
<p>In addition, this analyst said, there could be hopes that the two Scottish firms might escape more lightly than their English counterparts from a proposed windfall tax from the opposition Labour party.</p>
<p>Labour, well ahead of the ruling Conservative party in polls ahead of a May 1 election, has vowed to levy a one-off tax on privatised companies if it wins power.</p>
<p>&quot;There is some hope that the Scottish companies might get away with the windfall tax better,&quot; the analyst said.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1610107">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I17000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
