<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480254" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - British business press - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - British business press - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>DAILY TELEGRAPH</p>
<p>-- ELECTION TAKES TOLL OF STOCK MARKET FLOATS</p>
<p>Figures published today by KPMG show that only 20 companies obtained full stock market flotations in the first quarter, compared with 39 in the previous three months. KPMG said the forthcoming general election was behind the fall. Money raised totalled only 246 million pounds stg, despite record stock market levels.</p>
<p>-- NATIONAL SAVINGS HITS 13 BILLION POUNDS AND MEETS</p>
<p>TREASURY TARGET</p>
<p>Thirteen billion pounds stg has been invested in National Savings in the current financial year. The savings body is thus ensured of reaching its Treasury target of providing finance for 4.5 billion pounds of the public sector borrowing requirement. However, withdrawals will also reach record levels beyond 10 billion pounds as three major savings certificates issues mature.</p>
<p>-- GROUPS FACE VAT BILLS AFTER CUSTOMS' AVOIDANCE RULING</p>
<p>Customs &amp; Excise have taken action to close tax avoidance measures, a move that is likely to cost banks and insurance companies dearly in VAT payments. The November Budget closed a loophole in taxation of telecoms providers, which had made services bought overseas exempt from VAT. Many customers paid in advance in the hope of a longer tax-free period, but the Customs rules now say payments before July 1 which have not yielded a service are taxable.</p>
<p>THE TIMES</p>
<p>-- BANK BAR ON VILLA BOARD MEMBERSHIP</p>
<p>Bank of England governor Eddie George is understood to have prevented chief economist Mervyn King from becoming a non- executive director of Aston Villa football club. He is understood to have told Mr King that being a director of a commercial organisation would provide a conflict of interest with Bank activities.</p>
<p>-- ROLLERCOASTER DOW RAISES FEARS FOR LONDON SHARES</p>
<p>Wall Street continued its rapid decline yesterday, leading to fears that London and other world markets would suffer knock-on effects. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 140 points in early trading before recovering to 120 points down. The first effects on the British markets will be seen today, after being closed for the Easter break.</p>
<p>-- AMP PUTS NPI ON SHOPPING LIST</p>
<p>AMP, Australia's biggest life assurance group, has indicated strong interest in British life assurer National Provident Institution. AMP, which already owns Pearl Assurance, said it would be resuming talks with several British life offices after its unsuccessful bid for Scottish Amicable.</p>
<p>THE GUARDIAN</p>
<p>-- WATCHDOG INVESTIGATES MERRILL DEALS</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch is investigating accounting irregularities in trading derivatives at its London operation. The brokerage, which took over Smith New Court two years ago, has denied rumours of problems, but The Guardian reports that a team of investigators has been sent from the New York head office. The Securities and Futures Authority has also begun an inquiry.</p>
<p>-- LABOUR WATERS DOWN RAIL PLANS</p>
<p>Labour yesterday stressed that its plans to be tough on defaulting rail franchise companies would not include franchise removal. The party said tough enforcement orders and fines would be imposed on companies like South West Trains, under attack for cancelling services.</p>
<p>-- RISE IN BUSINESS FAILURES REVERSED</p>
<p>Separate reports released yesterday revealed good economic news. Business information company Dun &amp; Bradstreet said company failures had fallen 10 per cent in the first quarter, while the Foundation for Manufacturing and Industry published a report stating that official figures had not taken account of changes in the ways companies operate and had led to the rise of the service sector being overstated at the expense of manufacturing.</p>
<p>THE INDEPENDENT</p>
<p>-- MYERS SET TO BUY IMRY OFF BARCLAYS</p>
<p>Martin Myers, one of Britain's leading property developers, is planning to buy property developer Imry from Barclays, eight years after selling it to Marketchief for a profit of 15 million pounds stg. Barclays, which lent Marketchief 20 million pounds for the sale, was left owning Imry after Marketchief collapsed. Myers' deal with Barclays includes an unspecified payment on the unwinding of Imry, which he has continued to manage.</p>
<p>-- GROCERS GRAB 15 PER CENT OF VIDEO AND CD MARKET</p>
<p>The latest issue of U.K. Retail Report says the big supermarket groups now hold 15 per cent of British music and video sales. The report, by retail consultants Corporate Intelligence, says the supermarkets could hold one quarter of the 2.9 billion pound stg market within three years.</p>
<p>-- ASCEND DESCENDS ON U.S. RIVAL IN 3.7 BILLION DOLLAR DEAL</p>
<p>U.S. network computers merger mania continued yesterday, when Ascend Communications agreed to buy its smaller rival Cascade Communications for US$3.7 billion. The enlarged company will retain the Ascend name. The market for computer linking equipment has grown quickly alongside the popularity of the Internet and private networks linking up with the World Wide Web.</p>
<p>For a full range of news monitoring services, phone BMC +44-171-377-1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
