<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480252" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Rolls-Royce signs deal with Continental Airlines.</title>
<headline>Rolls-Royce signs deal with Continental Airlines.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>British engineering group Rolls-Royce Plc said on Tuesday it had won an order worth up to $240 million to supply engines to power up to 16 additional Continental Airlines Boeing 757 aircraft.</p>
<p>If all options are exercised, the deal would give U.S. airline Continental a Rolls-Royce powered 757 fleet of 41 aircraft.</p>
<p>Rolls-Royce Commercial Aero Engines managing director John Cheffins said the deal was important for two reasons.</p>
<p>&quot;It expands our relationship with a valued customer and it adds Air Micronesia, a Continental affiliate, as yet another operator of the 535 engine,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Share analysts said the deal confirmed Rolls-Royce's grip on the 757 engine market.</p>
<p>&quot;It's quite a big deal and builds on their link with Continental. But they are the dominant force in 757s so it's no real surprise,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>Rolls-Royce shares were trading 3p lower at 225p at 0830 GMT on a London Stock Exchange which had suffered heavy losses on the back of Wall Street's fall.</p>
<p>Rolls-Royce said Continental had chosen its RB211-535 engine for the 757 passenger airliner because of its reliability and potential for cutting operating costs.</p>
<p>The deal also includes a repair and overhaul agreement between Continental and Rolls-Royce Canada which will provide the airline with an eight-year support package.</p>
<p>It also includes the purchase of over $45 million in spare engines from two Rolls-Royce units. That element is part of the potential $240 million overall value of the deal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
