<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480236" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Bombay shares end higher in day of political drama.</title>
<headline>Bombay shares end higher in day of political drama.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Blue chips at Bombay exchanges closed near the day's highs on Tuesday as domestic funds and some foreign players bought on dips during a day of wild swings wrought by the country's political crisis, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a lot of buying by local institutions at lower prices,&quot; said Sanjeev Choithani, chief dealer at brokers Pashupati Advani. Buying was seen after the Bombay index on Monday suffered its fourth largest plunge ever of 310 points.</p>
<p>The benchmark 30-share index of the Bombay Stock Exchange on Tuesday ended 69.54 points, or 2.07 percent, higher at a provisional close of 3,430.43.</p>
<p>Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's 10-month old minority coalition government faces a confidence vote by April 11 after the Congress party on Sunday withdrew its crucial support.</p>
<p>Analysts pinned hopes on parliament passing the tax cutting budget presented by Finance Minister P.Chidamabaram on February 28, regardless of the political crisis.</p>
<p>&quot;Our basic view is that the budget will remain intact,&quot; said Ajit Dayal, managing director of Quantum Financial Services which advises foreign and domestic clients.</p>
<p>&quot;There might be minor changes but we're hopeful the budget will go through,&quot;said Vinay Motwani at brokerage KBS Capital Management.</p>
<p>The ruling coalition needs the support of lawmakers from the Congress party or the main opposition, Bharatiya Janata Party to ensure passage of the budget.</p>
<p>&quot;The budget would not be possible before the confidence vote,&quot; BJP vice-president K.R. Malkani told Reuters. &quot;I don't see how Congress or the BJP will agree with that.&quot;</p>
<p>But it could be considered later, Malkani said. &quot;The government has to approach us then we can consider the matter,&quot; he said. &quot;Let them convene a meeting. Let them do it properly,&quot; BJP president L.K. Advani told Reuters at the party office.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda's United Front alliance said the coalition was exploring ways of ensuring passage of the budget before the test vote. &quot;We are making an effort,&quot; spokesman Jaipal Reddy said.</p>
<p>The NSE index rose 0.30 percent at 971.15 provisional close.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
