<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480220" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Europe bourses may outshine Dow once dust settles.</title>
<headline>Europe bourses may outshine Dow once dust settles.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Marshall</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>European bourses will be unable to escape further punishment if Wall Street's battering continues but they may get back on their feet more quickly than U.S. stocks once the storm subsides, analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>A 4.3 percent Easter plunge in the Dow Jones industrial average sent European shares reeling when trade resumed after the holiday.</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 index dived 2.5 percent, while the CAC-40 in Paris opened 2.69 percent weaker and Frankfurt's DAX plummeted 2.71 percent.</p>
<p>With several analysts predicting further pain for Wall Street, particularly if Friday's U.S. non-farm payrolls numbers are strong, Europe's performance may hang crucially on the extent to which it can shrug off the Dow's depressing influence.</p>
<p>&quot;This is going to be a test of just how decoupled these markets truly are,&quot; one London dealer said.</p>
<p>Some analysts are confident that, after an initial tumble, Europe can pick itself up and push higher.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not going to escape the danger today but over the last few weeks the U.S. has struggled while European markets have held up reasonably well,&quot; said Roger Monson, strategist at Daiwa Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;I think some of that divergence in performance will be restored after this sell-off.&quot;</p>
<p>Wall Street's pounding was provoked by fears of further interest rate rises and concern that the momentum of corporate earnings growth was slowing.</p>
<p>But supporters of the decoupling argument say the situation in Europe is completely different.</p>
<p>Economies in continental Europe are still struggling to emerge from recession. So the interest-rate outlook is more bullish for equities.</p>
<p>And corporate earnings in Europe are expected to be on an upward track in coming months, supporting equity markets.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, bond yields have risen less strongly than in the United States, making Wall Street much more vulnerable to switching into bonds than European share markets, analysts say.</p>
<p>&quot;The interest rate outlook for continental Europe is for steady rates, perhaps for another whole year,&quot; Monson said. &quot;And corporate earnings in Europe are likely to be rebounding to some extent this year and next after a period of weakness.&quot;</p>
<p>Monson said the valuation of Europe's equities compared to bonds looked less stretched than in the U.S. market, while the U.S. long bond's breach of the psychologically important seven percent yield had added to Wall Street's woes.</p>
<p>These factors could help Europe escape the worst of the damage from a Wall Street correction, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We think European fundamentals could justify some independent strength in the coming few months,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;European markets have a much greater correlation with the U.S. when the magnitude of change is large, preventing local fundamentals from having much influence. When markets settle, there may be room for divergence in performance.&quot;</p>
<p>Although Britain's economic cycle is closer to the U.S. one than continental Europe, analysts said British share valuations looked less stretched, thanks to bond market outperformance.</p>
<p>With much bad news already priced in, London's FTSE also had some scope to outperform Wall Street, they said.</p>
<p>But despite the possibility of further decoupling, analysts said Europe could not hope to fully escape the impact of a falling Wall Street.</p>
<p>&quot;The key issue for Europe is not what is going on in Europe, which is quite supportive, but the global context for Europe,&quot; said David Bowers, European strategist at Merrill Lynch.</p>
<p>&quot;We've got a stronger Japanese economy, worries about a stronger U.S. economy, pressure on global bonds and people having second thoughts about the dollar,&quot; he said. &quot;That's not a great environment for European equities.&quot;</p>
<p>Bowers said the strength of the dollar was crucial.</p>
<p>If it retreats from its current strong levels, Wall Street stocks will become cheaper relative to European equities and any benefits of decoupling will be blunted.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe's equity markets are incredibly correlated to what's happening to the currency,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The other main risk for European shares is a rise in European bond yields, Bowers said.</p>
<p>&quot;European bonds haven't sold off nearly as much as their U.S. counterparts but Europe is still at risk if European bond yields start to get dragged up in a U.S.-led global bond sell-off. That could make things very difficult for Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>Not all analysts agree that European fundamentals are supportive.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe has got an additional problem even beyond the interest rate cycle starting in the U.S., which is the onset of monetary union and the continuing tightening of monetary policy,&quot; said SocGen strategist Andy Hartwill.</p>
<p>&quot;So in terms of excess returns from Europe, I wouldn't hold your breath.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
