<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480257" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Princess Diana in scuffle over gym photos.</title>
<headline>Princess Diana in scuffle over gym photos.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Princess Diana was caught up in a street scuffle after reportedly asking a passer-by to snatch film of her from a photographer's camera.</p>
<p>The Sun newspaper on Tuesday carried three pages of pictures showing Diana, wearing a long black coat and trainers, first remonstrating with a photographer and then standing by as another man thrust him against a brick wall.</p>
<p>The Sun said Diana, the world's most photographed woman, had turned on the cameraman after he snapped her leaving a gym in London on Monday and demanded that he hand over the film.</p>
<p>Diana is shown talking to a stranger, who asked if she needed help, and then standing aside as the two men fought in the public street over the camera.</p>
<p>Police confirmed a confrontation had taken place but said no complaint had been made and it was not investigating the matter.</p>
<p>Photographer Brendan Beirne told the Sun; &quot;I am stunned she (Diana) did not step in and stop it. It was outrageous.</p>
<p>&quot;She knows I am not a stalker or a threat. I have taken photographs of her for 10 years.&quot;</p>
<p>Diana has cut down drastically on public appearances since her divorce last August from heir to the throne Prince Charles. Last year she succeeded in getting a court order against another freelance photogapher whom she accused of harassment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
