<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480250" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FRANCE'S JOSPIN PLEADS FOR SOUTH IN EURO CURRENCY.</title>
<headline>FRANCE'S JOSPIN PLEADS FOR SOUTH IN EURO CURRENCY.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>French opposition Socialist Party leader Lionel Jospin called on Germany on Monday to relax its hardline on the criteria for membership of the European single currency so that Italy, Spain and Portugal join in 1999.</p>
<p>Jospin told RTL radio it would be inconceivable that people from Dresden, in the former East Germany, be in the planned EU currency if Italy, a founding member country of the European common market, was left out.</p>
<p>&quot;The criteria were made to achieve the single currency, not to hamper it... We believe that the southern countries, Spain, Italy and Portugal must be in the single currency from the start,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Germany is believed to be reluctant to allow Italy, Spain and Portugal into the single currency when it is launched in 1999 for fear this would undermine the Euro's credibility.</p>
<p>&quot;Germany itself realises that it has some difficulty in meeting some criteria, such as debt and budget deficit. Under the circumstances, it could perhaps be a little more open,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Italy's centre-left government, insisting in joining the single currency from the start, approved last week a mini-budget in a final bid to get state accounts ready.</p>
<p>France's centre-right government has refused comment on speculation about Italy's membership, saying a decision will be made next year on which countries join in 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;Either (the single currency) is an episode without any interest and it may involve five or six countries, or it is a new stage for the whole of the European Union and it must involve the EU,&quot; Jospin said.</p>
<p>Jospin, who hopes to form a left-wing alliance for next year's general election, rejected a call from Communist potential allies for a referendum on the single currency.</p>
<p>He said voters should be consulted on whether to join the Euro, but a vote in the parliament elected next year would be sufficient since French voters had already approved the Maastricht Treaty on European monetary union in a 1992 referendum.</p>
<p>&quot;The new parliamentary majority just coming out of the ballot box will be the most adequate forum,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
