<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480243" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: EUROPE'S 500 BRIGHTENS EU UNEMPLOYMENT FUNK.</title>
<headline>EUROPE'S 500 BRIGHTENS EU UNEMPLOYMENT FUNK.</headline>
<byline>George Georgiopoulos</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>With joblessness emerging as the European Union's Achilles' heel in the drive towards EMU, the role of dynamic entrepreneurs at the helm of fast growing companies is becoming crucial in tackling unemployment.</p>
<p>Europe's 500 is the Association of Dynamic Entrepreneurs who run businesses of growing importance for the creation of wealth and jobs in Europe.</p>
<p>Founded on the back of a massive research project undertaken by the European Foundation for Entrepreneurship Research (EFER) in 1994, it is a pan-European association of job creators.</p>
<p>Its mission is to promote entrepreneurship and the interests of fast-growing companies throughout the continent's different cultural environments.</p>
<p>&quot;We aim to encourage entrepreneurship in society and assist policy makers in government at national and European levels to create a more favourable climate,&quot; Europe's 500 Vice-President Evangelos Zavliaris told Reuters.</p>
<p>Zavliaris, a civil engineer, is also the managing director of construction firm Etane which is going public this year. A specialist in prefabricated construction and rehabilitation of landmark buildings it is also a member of Europe's 500.</p>
<p>EFER's pioneering project identified the owners of 500 of the fastest growing companies in Europe and Europe's 500 was launched in May 1996 at a high profile meeting with EU Commissioner Christos Papoutsis.</p>
<p>Drawn from all countries and sectors, these are companies whose turnover grew at an annual average of 29 percent between 1989-1994. Their employment grew at 21 percent annually while exports amount to 44 percent of turnover.</p>
<p>And boosting job creation, helping member companies grow faster and persuading budding entrepreneurs to launch new businesses is one of the principal issues facing Europe these days.</p>
<p>&quot;The association aims to achieve this by building on the strengths of Europe's successful entrepreneurs - their skills and expertise will form the foundations of tomorrow's flourishing businesses,&quot; Zavliaris said.</p>
<p>Analysts say, tough budgetary discipline and the precondition of EMU have become closely linked in the mind of the European public with record unemployment levels, even in a country like Germany, so far Europe's economic locomotive.</p>
<p>But what is the role of dynamic entrepreneurs in job creation?</p>
<p>EFER honourary president and Europe's 500 founding father Bert Twaalfhoven claims there has been a poor rate of job creation in the private sector, averaging 0.3 percent per annum over the last 25 years.</p>
<p>Compare this to Japan's 1.0 percent and an even better 1.8 percent in the U.S. where the message is clear: employment in large companies is falling, jobs are created in small enterprises.</p>
<p>From a search of 10 million companies, EFER's study identified 500 fast growers which more than doubled their employment in five years at a time when the number of jobs fell across Europe as a whole.</p>
<p>As regards the make up of the typical rapidly growing company in Europe, Twaalfhoven says &quot;they typically adopt strategies that are offensive and outward looking, market-minded and customer focused.&quot;</p>
<p>Their strategy emphasises product differentiation with high quality and superior service rather than costs. Exports account for nearly half of their turnover.</p>
<p>&quot;Dynamic entrepreneurs consider that their governments create a number of obstacles for them. However, they have great belief in their ability to overcome these and at times to take advantage of them,&quot; he says.</p>
<p>Channelling together the views of entrepreneurs for decision makers will also help the Commission and EU members to recognise where their actions need to be adapted.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe's 500 are not the largest nor the most heavily capitalised companies. They are not the subject of speculation on European stock exchanges. They are simply the most enterprising,&quot; says EU Commissioner Papoutsis.</p>
<p>Already, Europe's 500 launched a four-year partnership with Boston's Babson College, Glasgow Caledonian University and Scottish Enterprise to form a prestigious learning environment composed of entrepreneurs at the helm of Europe's fast growing businesses and prominent academics.</p>
<p>The first four-day symposium is to be held in Scotland in July. --Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
