<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480294" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Broadcasting Corp Morning Update.</title>
<headline>Australian Broadcasting Corp Morning Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>NATIONAL HOLIDAY ROAD TOLL AT 16</p>
<p>The national road toll for the Easter holiday period stands at 16.</p>
<p>The number of fatalities is lower than last year's national toll of 28.</p>
<p>Western Australia and Victoria had the highest number of fatal crashes with four deaths each.</p>
<p>Three people died on New South Wales roads, and two each in</p>
<p>Queensland and the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>South Australia had one death, Tasmania and the ACT were fatality free.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>VICTIMS RIGHTS BILL AMENDMENT</p>
<p>in New South Wales, the Shooters Party's John Tingle is confident his amendment to the Victims Rights Bill won't lead to uncertainty among the judiciary.</p>
<p>The amendment, due to become law on Wednesday, requires judges in murder cases to hear and acknowledge a Family Impact Statement during sentencing.</p>
<p>Director of Public Prosecutions, Nicholas Cowdery Q-C, has raised concerns about the effect and interpretation of the amendment.</p>
<p>Mr Tingle says it's clear that judges are not forced to take the impact statement into account.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SHEARING INDUSTRY CODE FOCUSES ON HEAT STRESS</p>
<p>Acceptable temperatures for working in shearing sheds may be included in a proposed code-of-practice for the shearing industry.</p>
<p>The Australian Workers Union has launched the code, which it says aims to protect shearers from occupational health risks.</p>
<p>Yossi Berger, from the AWU's Workplace Health and Safety Section, says the code also restricts use of chemicals and seeks to improve work-place design, to reduce injury.</p>
<p>Dr Berger says while the union is looking at heat stress as a health risk across many occupations, it's an area of particular concern for shearers.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FOSTERS A TOP-SELLER IN LONDON</p>
<p>Fosters Brewing says its beer is now the top-seller in London.</p>
<p>The company sells around one million pints of beer in Britain every day.</p>
<p>Television commercials featuring comedians H.G. and Roy are said to have led to a 10 per cent increase in sales since December.</p>
<p>The commercials are said to emphasise the benefits of a &quot;laid-back Australian attitude, and an enjoyable beer, in a stressful world.&quot;</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CAR PRODUCERS GET MOST OUT OF TARIFFS: CHAMBER</p>
<p>The West Australian Chamber of Commerce and Industry says car producers are the big winners out of Australia's high vehicle tariffs.</p>
<p>The chamber's chief economist, Nicki Cusworth says it's unacceptable that in 1995 tariffs can be shown to have cost new car buyers almost four-thousand dollars per vehicle.</p>
<p>The tariff on imported cars is currently 25 per cent, and this is set to fall to 15 per cent in the Year two-thousand.</p>
<p>But the chamber says it strongly supports the Industry Commission's Draft Report on the Automotive Industry, which advocates further phased reductions in tariffs to five percent.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>LOST WOMAN AND CHILDREN FOUND IN GOOD HEALTH</p>
<p>West Australian police say a woman and 13 children are all in good health, after being lost for two days in the State's goldfields.</p>
<p>A trip to Bromus Dam, south of Norseman in W.A's south-east, turned into trouble for the group on Saturday when their 1976 station-wagon broke down in bush, more than 25-kilometres from the Norseman-Esperance road.</p>
<p>Six of the children walked more than 30-kilometres in the direction of the road before they were found by the search party this afternoon.</p>
<p>Mrs Schultz and the other seven children were located a short time later.</p>
<p>Their rescue followed a widescale search involving three planes, police, the State Emergency Service, and relatives of the missing people.</p>
<p>Police say the 14 people are healthy despite their two-day ordeal.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BUDDHIST TEMPLE AND UNI PLANNED</p>
<p>In New South Wales, a A$500 million dollar Buddhist temple and university is being planned for a site west of Shellharbour, just south of Wollongong.</p>
<p>A Chinese Buddhist group is understood to have bought 180 hectares of land on the Illawarra escarpment at Yellowrock, and is negotiating to buy another 60 hectares.</p>
<p>A delegation recently met with Shellharbour Council to discuss its plans, but no development application has yet been presented.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>NO SIGN OF MISSING MEN</p>
<p>In Tasmania, police have switched the focus of their search for three men missing since yesterday in rugged terrain west of Hobart.</p>
<p>The three left New Norfolk at 10.30 a.m. yesterday to drive the Jeffreys Track to Judbury.</p>
<p>Searchers in two four-wheel drives this morning drove the length of the track from Lachlan, but found no sign of the men or their vehicle.</p>
<p>Acting Sergeant Michael Barber says they are now re-evaluating their options.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>POLICE DOORKNOCK HOMES IN MACKAY MURDER HUNT</p>
<p>Mackay police are conducting a doorknock this morning in a hunt for clues to a fatal shooting in the north Queensland city last night.</p>
<p>Police say a 46-year-old man was shot in the back while attempting to flee from an intruder he disturbed in his backyard about 8.15 last night.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
