<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480293" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Bre-X faces two class action suits in U.S..</title>
<headline>Bre-X faces two class action suits in U.S..</headline>
<dateline>OTTAWA 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bre-X Minerals was hit on Monday by two class action suits in the United States.</p>
<p>The Canadian Press (CP) news agency said one suit was filed in U.S. District Court in New York, alleging Bre-X sold shares before damaging news emerged about its Busang project in Indonesia, and that material mis-statements were made.</p>
<p>Earlier on Monday a Houston-based law firm, Baker and Botts, said a group had filed a class action in Texas.</p>
<p>Bre-X has been under fire since test results from partner Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold Inc last week called into question Bre-X's report that its Busang property in the jungles of Borneo was possibly the biggest gold find this century.</p>
<p>Bre-X maintains its early estimates will be vindicated.</p>
<p>CP quoted the New York complaint as alleging: &quot;Before the truth about the company's Busang project was revealed, Bre-X's insiders ... sold over $22 million of Bre-X stock on the open market, benefiting from the belated disclosure of the above adverse facts.&quot; CP said its figures were in Canadian dollars.</p>
<p>The lawsuit was filed on behalf of an American investor who bought 4,000 Bre-X shares in February and early March, it said.  </p>
<p>The Houston-based law firm Baker and Botts said the lawsuit in Texas was on behalf of shareholders whom, it said, had been injured in buying or selling the stock over the last three years.</p>
<p>&quot;Beginning in 1994 defendants convinced the world that Bre-X owned 90 percent of a massive gold deposit, perhaps the largest ever discovered, located in the Busang area of East Kalimantan, Indonesia. This was false,&quot; the plaintiffs alleged in the suit.</p>
<p>The suit named Bre-X and its chief executive David Walsh among the defendants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OTTAWA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
