<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480218" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Madrid stocks tumble, Wall St rebound seen as key.</title>
<headline>Madrid stocks tumble, Wall St rebound seen as key.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Madrid stocks tumbled to close lower on Tuesday, depressed by falls in other stock markets and some traders said unless there was a rebound on Wall Street, stocks were heading for greater losses in the short term.</p>
<p>&quot;This is all down to foreign influences,&quot; said one dealer. &quot;Stocks are simply falling in line with other markets after Wall Street's fall on Monday, but are performing better than Germany and France for example.&quot;</p>
<p>The general index slipped 7.92 pesetas, 1.67 percent, to 465.14, while the Ibex-35 index fell 97.74 points, 1.8 percent, to 5,326.54. Turnover reached 70.3 billion pesetas, with Telefonica and BCH accounting for 33 percent of this.</p>
<p>&quot;The fall on Wall Street yesterday has affected the whole of Europe and will dictate the tendency in the short term,&quot; said one dealer. Wall Street fell 157 points on Monday. The Dow Jones industrial average had gained 14 points by Madrid's close.</p>
<p>Another dealer said the Ibex-35 could fall as low as 5,000 in the short term.</p>
<p>&quot;If we don't see a rebound in the U.S., stocks could continue to fall for the next two to three days,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We should then see a rebound if there are no other negative external influences,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>But others were more optimistic, and although they expected further losses in the short term, they said they would not be significant and Madrid stocks would outperform other key stock markets.</p>
<p>Among individual stocks, significant losers included Adolfo Dominguez which fell 310 pesetas to 5,210, but dealers noted that this has been a highly volatile stock since flotation.</p>
<p>Telefonica slighly underperformed the indices, falling 2.34 percent, or 80 pesetas to 3,335, while Repsol outperformed the market, falling 1.19 percent, or 70 pesetas, to 5,830.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
