<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480351" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean won ends lower as economy stays weak.</title>
<headline>S.Korean won ends lower as economy stays weak.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The won closed lower against the dollar on Tuesday as many dealers remained sceptical over the impact from the government's steps to attract foreign funds, traders said.</p>
<p>The finance ministry, saying it wanted to stop the won's fall, on Monday opened the local capital market wider to foreign investors and allowing state banks to borrow more from abroad.</p>
<p>Dealers said despite the official steps, there were few signs economic fundamentals improved.</p>
<p>The won ended at 896.50 against Monday's close of 895.00.  </p>
<p>The trade ministry said on Tuesday the country's trade deficit narrowed to $1.88 billion in March from $2.09 billion a month ago, briefly sparking dollar selling.</p>
<p>&quot;But many bought back dollars as the defict was still very big,&quot; a local bank dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;Market players understood the government was determined to stop the won's depreciation,&quot; said another domestic bank dealer. &quot;Furthermore, there will be no big amounts of commerical deals.&quot; He said the won/dollar rate would be range-bound this month.</p>
<p>Dealers put the won's mid-rate at 896.20 on Wednesday against 892.80 today. -- Yeom Yoon-jeong 727-5647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
