<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480367" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: U.S. would defend Taiwan against coercion - Gingrich.</title>
<headline>U.S. would defend Taiwan against coercion - Gingrich.</headline>
<byline>Linda Sieg</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. House Speaker Newt Gingrich said on Tuesday that Washington stuck to its one-China policy but added that he had told Beijing that in his view the United States would defend Taiwan from a mainland attack.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe in a one-China policy. That means that the process should be achieved voluntarily and through dialogue. There should not be coercion,&quot; Gingrich told a news conference here during a stay wedged between his visit to China and a trip to Taiwan. &quot;That is binding on Taiwan as well as on Beijing.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;What I've said consistently in Beijing and Shanghai was that the United States had a deep interest in the issue of voluntary, non-coercive dialogue, that we had indicated in the 1979 Defense of Taiwan Act that we regarded it as vital that Taiwan have the weapons to defend itself...and I said that in my judgment as a historian and as somebody who is pretty aware of the mood in the United States, we had so consistently indicated that we would defend Taiwan, that we would defend Taiwan.&quot;</p>
<p>The White House on Monday sought to play down Gingrich's earlier tough talk on China and to deflect suggestions that the Republican's hard-line stance had overshadowed a visit by Vice President Al Gore to Beijing.</p>
<p>White House spokesman Mike McCurry told reporters that Gingrich was &quot;speaking for himself&quot; and, when asked to elaborate on U.S. policy toward any Chinese attack on Taiwan, referred reporters to the Taiwan Relations Act of 1979, which does not commit Washington to defend the island Beijing regards as a renegade province.</p>
<p>Gingrich said on Tuesday that Chinese leaders &quot;took note of what I said and reminded me that they had not renounced the use of force, and we agreed that if they weren't using force, we wouldn't have to defend, and since they don't intend to use force, we won't have to think about defending.&quot;</p>
<p>Gingrich was the latest senior U.S. official to visit China amid what both sides say is a growing rapprochement after ties deteriorated in 1995 and 1996 over issues such as human rights, Taiwan and trade.</p>
<p>Gingrich, who will meet Taiwan President Lee Teng-hui in Taipei, said he would discuss a wide range of issues with the Taiwanese leader.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll certainly be sharing with him some of my discussions in Beijing and I look forward to hearing his views on the future evolution of relations across the state.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Hong Kong's future after reversion to Chinese sovereignty would have a major impact on the dialogue between Beijing and Taipei.</p>
<p>&quot;If Hong Kong is a key experiment, if the two systems in one country works in Hong Kong...then it seems to me they'll have a very different dialogue in four or five years than if they see Hong Kong fail,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Gingrich also cautioned against expectations that North Korea's impoverished Stalinist regime would necessarily collapse soon and said it was vital to give Pyongyang alternatives to either total breakdown or war.</p>
<p>&quot;I would not overestimate the speed of collapse nor underestimate the danger that North Korea might do something militarily if it does decide its future is limited,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We should cautiously and carefully try to open up dialogue and increase the potential that the regime will see alternatives to either total collapse or launching a pre-emptive war,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
