<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480335" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: TIFFE euroyen futures end lower on Ushio remarks.</title>
<headline>TIFFE euroyen futures end lower on Ushio remarks.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>April 1 settlement  prev settlement</p>
<p> TIFFE Euroyen 3M (Z)     99.00		   99.05</p>
<p>---------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Key December three-month euroyen deposit rate futures ended Tuesday's TIFFE day session lower after Jiro Ushio, head of the Japan Association of Corporate Executives, said Japan might change its easy monetary policy towards the middle of the year.</p>
<p>The December settled at an intraday low of 99.00. Earlier in the day, it rose as high as 99.10 following a sharp fall in Tokyo stocks, traders said.  </p>
<p>Day session turnover for the December was 48,038.</p>
<p>&quot;The December started out the day firmer on the Nikkei's falls, but fell into the negative territory in the afternoon as heavy selling emerged in reaction to Ushio's remarks,&quot; said a brokerage house trader.</p>
<p>The Nikkei 225 stock average ended down 133.81 points, or 0.74 percent, at 17,869.59, after falling as low as 17,529.05 in the morning.</p>
<p>Ushio told a news conference that he sees a possibility that Japan's easy monetary policy may change towards the middle of the year, a spokesman for the association said on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>Market participants were cautious ahead of the release of the Bank of Japan's (BOJ) key quarterly &quot;tankan&quot; corporate sentiment survey on Wednesday, traders said.</p>
<p>Economists polled by Reuters expect the March diffusion index (DI) for major manufacturers to rise slightly. Forecasts range from minus two and plus two in March, compared with minus three in November.</p>
<p>Traders said the market is more interested in the tankan's DI forecast for June to assess the possible impact of the consumption tax rise from April 1. Economists' forecasts for June DI forecast range from minus six to plus one.  </p>
<p>The BOJ injected 400 billion yen into the money market, supplying 300 billion yen more than the market needed to offset a fund shortfall for the second consecutive day.</p>
<p>However, the key unsecured overnight call rate failed to fall substantially. Its weighted average for Tuesday was likely to be near 0.60 percent, compared with Monday's 0.72 percent, traders said.</p>
<p>About 50 billion yen worth of three-month certificates of deposit (CDs) were issued at 0.55 percent, down from Monday's offer rate of 0.56 percent. One- and two-month CDs were offered at 0.55 percent. -- Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-3-3432-9780</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
