<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480304" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAPUA NEW GUINEA: PNG opens inquiry into Bougainville mercenary deal.</title>
<headline>PNG opens inquiry into Bougainville mercenary deal.</headline>
<dateline>PORT MORESBY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A public inquiry began in Papua New Guinea on Tuesday into a $36 million contract between the government and a British military firm for mercenaries and arms to crush the long-running rebellion on Bougainville island.</p>
<p>The mercenary deal last month sparked the worst political crisis in PNG's 22 years of independence and forced Prime Minister Sir Julius Chan to stand aside in the face of public and army opposition.</p>
<p>Some 70 foreign mercenaries arrived in PNG but were expelled before they could launch an assault on Bougainville. Their leader, retired British colonel Tim Spicer, remains in the South Pacific nation to face illegal firearm charges.</p>
<p>Chan himself set the terms of the inquiry before he stood down last Wednesday and a lawyer for sacked army chief Jerry Singirok, who led the campaign against Chan, applied on Tuesday for the inquiry to focus on the role of Chan and other senior ministers in the contract.</p>
<p>In a written submission to the inquiry, Singirok lawyer Peter Donigi said the terms of reference set by Chan were too general and would leave many questions unanswered.</p>
<p>Donigi asked that the inquiry, scheduled to last three weeks, should look into Chan's actions and those of his former finance minister Chris Haiveta and former defence minister Mathias Ijape.</p>
<p>Donigi said the inquiry should also investigate &quot;the share trading affair&quot; -- allegations of irregular trading in shares of listed PNG companies before the deal with Britain's Sandline International became public.</p>
<p>And he called for the investigation of other corruption allegations made against Chan, including that private security companies controlled by Chan might have profited from the Sandline contract.</p>
<p>Donigi's application to extend the terms of the inquiry was opposed by lawyers representing Chan, Haiveta and Ijape and by lawyers representing Sandline commander Spicer.</p>
<p>Spicer was expected to give evidence to the inquiry on Wednesday after judge Warwick Andrews, chairman of the commission of inquiry, rules on Donigi's application.</p>
<p>The British colonel, a former U.N. peacekeeper in Bosnia, faces trial on minor firearms charges on Friday.</p>
<p>Chan and the two other former ministers could also be called to give evidence to the inquiry.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAPNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORT MORESBY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAPUA NEW GUINEA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
