<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480352" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila says might shelter Korea defector for month.</title>
<headline>Manila says might shelter Korea defector for month.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Philippines said on Tuesday it was considering allowing top North Korean defector Hwang Jang-yop to stay in the country for a month.</p>
<p>Foreign Secretary Domingo Siazon said the government was holding talks with Chinese and South Korean officials on the length of Hwang's stay in the Philippines and that Manila might not announce Hwang's departure until after the fact.</p>
<p>Pyongyang's former top ideologue has been in a secret hideway in the Philippines since China spirited him into this country on March 18, nearly five weeks after Hwang defected to the South Korean consulate in Beijing.</p>
<p>Seoul and Beijing had agreed that the Philippines should serve as a third country transit point before Hwang, 73, is flown to South Korea, where he is expected to seek political asylum.</p>
<p>The Philippine detour is widely seen as intended to spare North Korea the indignity of having Hwang head straight for its bitter rival, South Korea.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the Republic of Korea has given a commitment to China that they would agree to 30 days,&quot; Siazon told reporters before attending a cabinet meeting chaired by President Fidel Ramos.</p>
<p>Asked if this was acceptable to Manila, Siazon said: &quot;That is still being considered ... We are in the process of considering 30 days, yes.&quot;</p>
<p>Ramos declared shortly after the North Korean arrived that he would be allowed to remain for &quot;as long as necessary and as short as possible&quot;.</p>
<p>The government has maintained an official news blackout on Hwang's location. Fears have been raised that Hwang, the most senior North Korean to defect, might be a target for Pyongyang hitmen.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't deal with details,&quot; Siazon said, when pressed on Hwang's whereabouts. &quot;Fortunately, so I can look straight into your eyes and say I don't know where he is.&quot;</p>
<p>Since Hwang's arrival, immigration officials have been on alert at airports and seaports around the country against the possible entry of any suspected North Korean assassins who might try to harm Seoul's prize diplomatic catch.</p>
<p>Asked if Hwang's continued stay might prove an embarrassment to Manila because of the danger that he might be assassinated, Siazon said, &quot;Did anyone tell you that he would be killed here?&quot;</p>
<p>He indicated that Hwang remained safe in his hideaway.</p>
<p>&quot;If there were something strange, they will report that to me. If everything is normal, I am not informed,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hwang has been variously reported to be under military protective custody in the mountain city of Baguio, at the former U.S. Clark airbase, now an industrial complex, at the Subic Bay freeport and in Manila.</p>
<p>But searches by dozens of Filipino, Japanese and South Korean journalists failed to yield any sign of him.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a stake in the stability of the Korean peninsula,&quot; Siazon said, defending Manila's decision to provide a haven for Hwang.</p>
<p>&quot;This is our contribution to the stability of Asia and that's why we have taken this particular role.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
