<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480301" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>New Zealand: NZ shares end 1.31 pct down after Wall St fall.</title>
<headline>NZ shares end 1.31 pct down after Wall St fall.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>* New Zealand share prices end sharply lower</p>
<p>* Local market suffers cumulative effect of Wall St falls</p>
<p>* Weakness spread across the board on moderate volume</p>
<p>---------------------------(April 1)---------------------------</p>
<p>Price movements at close</p>
<p>	    LAST CHG</p>
<p>  130   -4  * NZSE-40 cap index -29.26 at 2,207.48</p>
<p>  302   -3  * NZSC cap index -71.21 at 4,997.54</p>
<p>  286   -5  * NZSE-10 cap index -15.23 at 1,090.15</p>
<p>  342  nil  * Volume NZ$52 million. Futures -15 at 1,111</p>
<p>  650   -5  * Other movers - -11 -9</p>
<p>New Zealand share prices ended sharply lower on Tuesday after the long Easter holiday weekend, the market responding to the cumulative effect of sharp falls on Wall Street on Monday and Friday.</p>
<p>The NZSE-40 Capital Index ended 29.26 points (1.31 percent) down at 2,207.48, the index having earlier dipped to a low of 2,198.59. Turnover was moderate at NZ$52 million, inflated a little by some portfolio buying activity towards the close.</p>
<p>Brokers said it was a delayed reaction to Wall Street's fall, the local market having been closed for Friday and Monday.  </p>
<p>But Paul Nicolson at SBC Warburg said it was a surprisingly resilient market, given the four percent fall in the U.S. over the break.</p>
<p>It appeared Australia had fared worse, the All Ordinaries index losing 69.6 points (2.89 percent) to 2,352.4 in late trade.</p>
<p>Nicolson noted that Telecom finished locally at NZ$6.50, up 10 from its equivalent price in the U.S.</p>
<p>&quot;It was not a bad performance but one would imagine that it was because we've been one of the poorer performing markets in the last little while,&quot; Nigel Scott at BZW said.  </p>
<p>&quot;People have had opportunities to sell at levels higher than this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>New Zealand equities had also moved away from reacting to Wall Street's rises and falls over the last six months.</p>
<p>&quot;So the divergence really is shown out here today,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- James Gray 64 4 4734746</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
