<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480395" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China's Worldbest overbought securities - Shenyin.</title>
<headline>China's Worldbest overbought securities - Shenyin.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shanghai Worldbest Co Ltd spent too much money on short-term investments last year, especially in the securities markets, Shenyin &amp; Wanguo Securities Co said in a research report on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Worldbest's short-term investments amounted to 98 million yuan by the end of 1996, of which 80 percent was invested in the securities market, accounting for 17 percent of the company's total working capital, the report said.</p>
<p>Worldbest, a major producer of polyester, recently took on 50 million yuan in new long-term loans, 70 million yuan in short-term loans and issued five million yuan in three-year corporate bonds, the report said.</p>
<p>These extra debts had resulted in a surge in the company's interest payments.</p>
<p>&quot;We are puzzled why the company did not pay back their debts to lower interest payments but rather invested so much money in the risky financial markets,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>Worldbest last week reported that its 1996 net profit surged 135.69 percent to 79.087 million yuan from 33.555 yuan in 1995 based on international accounting standards, citing the company's good management.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I43000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
