<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480310" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia's Optus shake-up seen good for float.</title>
<headline>Australia's Optus shake-up seen good for float.</headline>
<byline>Kevin Morrison</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Telecommunications group Optus Communications Pty Ltd's takeover of its loss making associate, Optus Vision, and the litigation settlement with Seven Network Ltd augers well for its public float, analysts said.</p>
<p>However, they said on Tuesday the restructure is likely to cut Optus Communications' profit for the year to June 30, 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very positive for Optus Communications. The Seven litigation is out of the way, they appear to have got Optus Vision for a good price and it allows the float to go ahead,&quot; said Phil King, a telecoms analyst at Macquarie Equities.  </p>
<p>Under the Optus rejig, announced early on Easter Friday morning, Optus would acquire 100 percent of pay television group Optus Vision for an undisclosed amount.</p>
<p>The other shareholders in Optus Vision, US West Inc, with 46.5 percent, Kerry Packer's Publishing and Broadcasting Ltd (PBL) at five percent and Seven Network with two percent, would swap their holdings for stakes in Optus.</p>
<p>The long-awaited deal arose from litigation lodged by Seven against Optus Vision shareholders for breaking the Optus Vision shareholders agreement when they agreed to grant PBL an option to lift its stake in Optus Vision.  </p>
<p>The settlement gave the go-ahead for Optus Communications' float, expected around July-August, analysts said. The float had been delayed since last year due to Seven's legal action.</p>
<p>Analysts said Optus could be looking to raise up to A$1.5 billion with the bulk of the offer representing the sale by transport and healthcare group Mayne Nickless Ltd of its 26.1 percent stake in Optus.</p>
<p>&quot;It puts the Optus float ahead of the Telstra float, which is very positive,&quot; King said. However, analysts said the issue of shares to Seven, PBL and US West might reduce the amount of shares to be issued to investors through the proposed float.  </p>
<p>The government plans to sell a third of its 100 percent holding in telephone carrier Telstra Corp by the end of 1997 and raise over A$8 billion through a public share offer.</p>
<p>Analysts said Optus was keen to settle the Seven litigation and avoid any float clash timing with Telstra.</p>
<p>However, analysts said Optus and Telstra might get together and work out a deal to share each other's infrastructure for the delivery of their respective loss making pay-TV services some time this year, possibly before the planned Optus float.</p>
<p>Telstra jointly owns pay-TV group Foxtel with Rupert Murdoch's News Corp Ltd.  </p>
<p>Optus Vision has made losses of about A$330 million, while Foxtel losses add up to about A$270 million.</p>
<p>&quot;Telstra and Optus have already refered to sharing cables,&quot; said Andrew Mullholland, an analyst at Pru-Bache Securities.</p>
<p>&quot;On carriage, I think you will get some sort of deal between Optus and Telstra on cable and you may get some sort of deal on satellite,&quot; Mullholland told Reuters.</p>
<p>However, any deal between Telstra and Optus over pay-PV or sharing telecommunications infrastructure would need the consent of anti-monopolies body, the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (ACCC).  </p>
<p>The Optus rejig would reduce the equity exposure to Australia's pay-TV industry for US West and PBL, analysts said.</p>
<p>Under Optus' current ownership structure US West is not allowed to own more than five percent of Optus Communications as foreign companies also own half of Optus. BellSouth Corp and Cable &amp; Wireless Plc each own about 24.5 percent.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Continental Cablevision of Australia, a unit of US West, said it would receive cash and shares for its Optus Vision stake, but would not comment on how much the U.S. group would own in Optus Communications.</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
