<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480369" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean opposition backs Kim's bid to save economy.</title>
<headline>S.Korean opposition backs Kim's bid to save economy.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean opposition leaders on Tuesday agreed to bury political differences to support President Kim Young-sam's bid to revive an economy hit hard by a loans scandal and labour strife.</p>
<p>In a rare display of solidarity, Kim and the heads of two major opposition groups issued a seven-point agreement pledging joint efforts to overcome economic woes.</p>
<p>The agreement said a special parliamentary investigation and state prosecutors must reveal the whole truth behind a bribes-for-loans scandal involving failed Hanbo Steel Co.</p>
<p>But it added: &quot;We share the view that this issue should no longer pose a hurdle in the development of our economy.&quot;</p>
<p>Kim Dae-jung of the main opposition National Congress for New Politics and King Jong-pil of the United Liberal Democrats agreed with the president that a political crisis over the scandal had caused public anxiety.</p>
<p>&quot;In view of the current political situation, ruling and opposition parties will concentrate on reviving the economy and appeal to the people to share hardships,&quot; the agreement said.</p>
<p>Government economists say hopes for an economic turnaround this year have been dashed by wildcat strikes in January in protest at a controversial labour bill and the collapse of Hanbo Steel, the country's second largest steelmaker.</p>
<p>The government has revised downward its projection for this year's economic growth to 5.5 percent from an earlier forecast 6.4 percent.</p>
<p>This compares with growth of 7.1 percent in 1996 and 8.9 percent the previous year.</p>
<p>The opposition parties and President Kim's ruling New Korea Party agreed to form a special economic committee, which will also include representatives from various social groups, to deal with economic problems.</p>
<p>They also agreed to speed up banking reforms to prevent any repeat of the Hanbo crisis. Hanbo folded under debts of $5.8 billion provided by banks that did not secure enough collateral.</p>
<p>&quot;Our economy which was once an envy of the world is now pushed to the back in a race of global competition,&quot; the political leaders said in a joint statement.</p>
<p>&quot;Now is the time to join all forces to revive the economy.&quot;</p>
<p>The political leaders' meeting coincided with the release of figures showing the March trade deficit at $1.88 billion, a sharp jump from a shortfall of $446 million a year earlier.</p>
<p>The figure brought to $7.43 billion South Korea's trade deficit in the first three months of this year, representing more than half the $14 billion deficit targeted by the government for all of this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The most urgent task is to restore confidence by resolving public suspicions over the Hanbo incident and other pressing issues,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Ten people, including a former cabinet minister, and close associates of President Kim, are standing trial on bribery and embezzlement charges over the Hanbo scandal.</p>
<p>Prosecutors said they were also probing rumours of a kickback involving the president's second son, Hyun-chul, over a Hanbo deal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
