<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480350" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korea's monthly trade deficit narrows.</title>
<headline>S.Korea's monthly trade deficit narrows.</headline>
<byline>Yeom Yoon-jeong</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea said on Tuesday that its trade deficit dropped in March compared with February, sparking government optimism its shortfall target of $14 billion for the whole year could be met.</p>
<p>The trade ministry said the customs-cleared deficit eased to $1.88 billion in March from a shortfall of $2.09 billion in February and $3.47 billion in January.</p>
<p>But the March deficit gained 2.9 percent compared with a $446 million deficit a year earlier.</p>
<p>A ministry statement said the nation's trade deficit should continue to narrow month-on-month.</p>
<p>&quot;The trade figures show signs of improving, which means we will be able to meet our yearly target,&quot; Kim Sang-yeol, the trade ministry's director general for trade policy, told reporters.</p>
<p>The ministry said it expected the trade deficit to narrow to $14 billion this year from $20.63 billion last year.</p>
<p>However, the shortfall rose to $7.43 billion in the first three months of this year, up from $4.17 billion in the same 1996 period.</p>
<p>&quot;The government seemes to be too optimistic with its aggressive target,&quot; said Lim Choon-soo, head of research at Deutsche Morgan Grenfell Capital Markets Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;If export prices do not rebound, there's no way. It's up to global markets,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Although South Korean exports rose in volume terms last year, the country's trade deficit hit an all-time high, bloated by a sharp fall in prices of key exports. Economists said export prices fell by 15 percent year-on-year.</p>
<p>But Kim said a production cut by chipmakers had helped drive up semiconductor prices on world markets.</p>
<p>Semiconductors are South Korea's largest single export item. They have been largely responsible for the huge trade shortfall because of a sharp drop in export prices.</p>
<p>South Korea exported $3.50 billion worth of semiconductors in the first quarter, down 43 percent from $6.14 billion a year earlier.</p>
<p>Kim said the unit spot price of 16 megabit dynamic random access memory (DRAM) chips, used to make personal computers, was now heading for $11 from $10.50 in March.</p>
<p>A ministry statement said the price stood at $9 in February and $8 in January.</p>
<p>&quot;The price will rise further in April as Japanese chipmakers are expected to cut their output after finishing the fiscal year ending March,&quot; Kim said. &quot;This will help increase our exports.&quot;</p>
<p>Exports, excluding semiconductors, rose 5.4 percent in March on steady sales of other key export items, including steel and petroleum products.</p>
<p>The ministry said slowing imports of foreign products would also help ease the rising trade deficit.</p>
<p>Imports of capital goods, accounting for 60 to 70 percent of total imports, continued to fall in March as facility investment by South Korean companies slowed.</p>
<p>Those imports fell 3.2 percent in the first 20 days of March, compared with a 2.2 percent decline in the month of February and a 0.5 percent rise in January.</p>
<p>&quot;The economic slowdown has chilled investment sentiment among domestic companies and hurt domestic consumption. This will result in a sharp fall in import growth,&quot; said Lee Yong-man, an economist at LG Economic Research Institute.</p>
<p>He forecast facility investment by South Korean companies would fall 2.4 percent this year against a 8.2 percent rise a year earlier.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
