<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480363" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: China Zhuzhou Smelter says boosts 97 output plan. [Corrected 09:39 gmt]</title>
<headline>China Zhuzhou Smelter says boosts 97 output plan. [Corrected 09:39 gmt]</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's Zhuzhou Smelter said on Tuesday it had decided to increase its annual zinc output to 260,000 tonnes per year in 1997, from its previous target of 210,000 tonnes per year.</p>
<p>In a faxed statement, the smelter said the production increase was mianly due to a 100,000-tonne zinc production line which came onstream last year.  </p>
<p>The smelter said it planned to export 160,000 to 180,000 tonnes of zinc and zinc alloys in 1997, an increase of 300 percent compared to 1996 exports.</p>
<p>In the first quarter of this year, Zhuzhou had produced about 59,078 (corrects from &quot;50,078&quot;) tonnes of zinc and zinc alloy, a 30 percent increase over the same period last year.</p>
<p>In the first quarter of this year, Zhuzhou exported 40,497 tonnes of zinc and zinc alloy, a 174 percent increase from the same period last year, the statement said.</p>
<p>The smelter planned to ship its surplus zinc metal to London Metal Exchange (LME) warehouses at a rate of about 8,000 to 10,000 tonnes per month, starting in March, it said.</p>
<p>This was because zinc physical markets in Southeast Asia were declining slowly, the statement said.</p>
<p>The smelter was currently running at a capacity of about 900 to 950 tonnes per day of zinc. This figure included the processing of national zinc stocks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22471">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
