<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480399" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Asian traders tip LME copper, aluminium stock fall.</title>
<headline>Asian traders tip LME copper, aluminium stock fall.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Far East metals traders expected copper and aluminium stocks on the London Metal Exchange (LME) to fall on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Copper stocks were tipped to drop by 7,000-10,000 tonnes, and aluminium by 8,000 to 10,000 tonnes, one trading source in Singapore said.</p>
<p>Chinese buying, although long expected, was not necessarily behind the expected drop in LME copper stocks, he and other traders in the region said.</p>
<p>&quot;I haven't seen much (copper) coming out of Singapore,&quot; another source in Singapore said. &quot;I don't expect to see Singapore accounting for the fall.&quot;</p>
<p>North America was seen as the most likely destination, traders said.</p>
<p>Chinese buying has been expected to emerge for so long that many traders said on Tuesday they had given up waiting, and now saw China starting its import programme once the winter ended and construction returned to full swing in late April/early May.</p>
<p>LME zinc stocks were expected to rise, traders said, by 8,000 to 10,000 tonnes.  </p>
<p>Trading sources in China, Hong Kong and Singapore have said Chinese zinc is moving to Singapore warehouses so producers can take advantage of high world prices, now hovering around 4-1/2-year highs of $1,300 a tonne.</p>
<p>Traders have estimated Chinese zinc tonnages on the way to Singapore at 20,000 to 25,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>China is known to move zinc metal to Singapore to use as collateral for loans, so it does not necessarily show up on warrants.</p>
<p>Nickel stocks would also rise by about 800 tonnes, one trading source said.</p>
<p>-- Shanghai newstoom (86-21) 6279-8544</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
