<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480327" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: Computershare paid about NZ$19 mln for RMNZ.</title>
<headline>Computershare paid about NZ$19 mln for RMNZ.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Computershare Ltd said on Tuesday it paid around NZ$19 million for Registry Managers New Zealand Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;It's around...$19 million,&quot; Managing Director Chris Morris told Reuters by telephone from Melbourne.  </p>
<p>Computershare earlier announced that it had bought Registry Managers from Baycorp Holdings Ltd.</p>
<p>Baycorp bought Registry Managers in February this year for about NZ$22 million, including costs associated with capital raising.</p>
<p>Registry Managers are the largest suppliers of registry services to New Zealand companies, handling over 90 percent of the securities registration business for over 200 clients, including 26 of the top 30 companies listed on the New Zealand Stock Exchange.  </p>
<p>Morris said Registry Managers was a long term strategic investment for Computershare.</p>
<p>&quot;It fits fairly well with us, probably a lot better than with the other purchaser (Baycorp),&quot; Morris said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's totally in line with our core business and there's a lot of synergies we've got with the company that probably they didn't have.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a long-term investment and fairly strategic for us. We do a lot of work for New Zealand companies now in Australia and also a lot of New Zealand and Australian companies in the U.K., where we've got an office, so we can offer services between  </p>
<p>Morris said Computershare, in conjunction with the major Australian registrars, would now be able to offer registry and bureau services in Australia, New Zealand and Britain all linked via high speed communications accessing a central data base.</p>
<p>He said RMNZ would enhance Computershare's broker bureau business currently being established in Australia and New Zealand.</p>
<p>Opportunities also existed to provide unique services to New Zealand brokers by linking the back office to the registry data base.  </p>
<p>The cross border settlement system currently operated from Britain for Australian shares would be extended to include New Zealand stocks.</p>
<p>In conjuction with the major Australian registrars, Computershare now offered bureau and registry services to over 90 percent of all Australian and New Zealand companies, and the opportunity existed to establish a fully integrated registry system for cross-Tasman trading, Morris said.</p>
<p>-- Wellington Newsroom (64 4) 4734746</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83954">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
