<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480359" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Shanghai copper futures end up on short-covering.</title>
<headline>Shanghai copper futures end up on short-covering.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shanghai copper futures ended mostly up on Tuesday on short-covering, traders said.</p>
<p>The most active July 1997 contract ended at 24,050 yuan ($2,899) per tonne, rising 90 yuan. It opened at 24,010 yuan, hitting an intraday low of 24,000 and a high of 24,130.</p>
<p>April fell 10 to 23,500, May rose 90 to 23,690, June 80 to 23,880, August 120 to 24,070, September 170 to 24,070 and October 150 to 23,950.</p>
<p>Combined volume rose to 26,840 tonnes from 10,670.  </p>
<p>Copper opened slightly higher and moved at that level for most of the session with some investors continuing to liquidate their short positions due to the unclear short-term market trend, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Many investors wanted to stay on the sidelines due to a lack of direction from the London Metal Exchange,&quot; one trader said. &quot;Speculative buying dominated today's trading.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders said copper would find it hard to move out of the current narrow range around 24,000 yuan in the absence of market-moving news in the short term.  </p>
<p>Aluminium ended mixed. April was unchanged at 16,150, May fell 50 to 16,400 and June rose 50 to 16,750.</p>
<p>Combined volume fell to 710 tonnes from 1,480.</p>
<p>($1=8.2955 yuan)</p>
<p>-- Shanghai newsroom (86-21) 6279-7004</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
