<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480390" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Price war looms as Singapore deregulates telecoms.</title>
<headline>Price war looms as Singapore deregulates telecoms.</headline>
<byline>Chris Johnson</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore marked the deregulation of its cellular phone and paging markets on Tuesday by scrapping licence fees for mobile phones and with signs growing of price war between messaging companies.</p>
<p>Communications Minister Mah Bow Tan told a glitzy ceremony to launch one of the island's three new paging services that the government would remove licence fees for all portable phones, saving users between Singapore $50 (US$34.72) and S$100 a year. Total savings would be around S$23 million a year, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;This move, together with the new competition regime, will make mobile telecommunication services even more accessible to users,&quot; Mah said.</p>
<p>The Telecommunication Authority of Singapore (TAS) said in a statement the cut would affect 440,000 mobile phone users, 1,100 mobile data system users and 12,000 trunked radio users.</p>
<p>Singapore's mobile phone and paging markets were opened to full competition for the first time on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>State-owned Singapore Telecommunications Ltd (SingTel) has lost its monopoly and now faces one competitor, MobileOne, in the mobile phone market and three rival pager services.</p>
<p>Mah was officiating at the launch of Sunpage, a unit of the state-owned Singapore Technologies conglomerate.</p>
<p>Sunpage used a laser show, fireworks, giant balloons and psychedelic lighting to reveal the cheapest rates yet for basic paging services and a range of more sophisticated services to attack the growing messaging and secretarial paging market.  </p>
<p>Sunpage's rates start at Singapore $9.80 a month, against S$9.90 for new competitor Hutchison Paging and S$15 for SingTel. Sunpage general manager Yong Lum Sung told Reuters its low prices aimed at taking a third of a deregulated Singapore market he said could grow to around 1.5 million pagers.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very aggressive. We aim to get about 30 percent of the market in three to five years,&quot; Yong said in an interview.</p>
<p>Mah said Singapore had one of the world's highest pager usage rates with 34 pagers for every 100 people. He said the market was growing at 12 percent a year and some forecasts predicted penetration rates could rise to 50 percent.</p>
<p>But Yong said intense price competition in the new open market could mean all players would suffer, and warned his rivals not to risk setting off a full-blown price war.</p>
<p>&quot;People have to be careful,&quot; he said. &quot;I hope they don't keep (prices) going down. I hope everyone gets the message that we shouldn't compete on price after a certain level.&quot;</p>
<p>Hutchison Paging is a joint venture of Hong Kong group Hutchison Whampoa Ltd, Intraco Ltd and Teledata.  </p>
<p>The other new paging firm is MobileOne, a joint venture of Britain's Cable &amp; Wireless, Hong Kong Telecommunications, Keppel Telecom and Singapore Press Holdings.</p>
<p>Tan Guong Ching, the chairman of Singapore Technologies Telemedia (STT), told the Sunpage launch his company hoped to get a full basic telecommunications licence in Singapore when that market is opened in April 2000.</p>
<p>STT has joined with state-owned utility Singapore Power, British Telecommunications Plc and Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corp (NTT) to bid for a licence.  </p>
<p>Other foreign telecoms companies, including AT&amp;T, have said they may bid for a licence.</p>
<p>Mah has said the government will award one or two basic telecommunications licences to compete with SingTel next year.</p>
<p>MobileOne had to postpone a giant quayside party to launch its mobile phone and pager services on Monday evening after heavy rain drove the crowds away and high winds set off fireworks prematurely, The New Paper reported.</p>
<p>($1 = S$1.44)</p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom (65 8703199)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
