<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480380" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: FORECAST - Shanghai state debt prices see no change.</title>
<headline>FORECAST - Shanghai state debt prices see no change.</headline>
<byline>Graham Earnshaw</byline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chinese state debt spot contracts on the Shanghai stock exchange are not expected to move much over the next month with high yields offset by a bull run on the domestic A share markets, analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The seven listed spot contracts now have an average yield of around 10 percent per year, much higher than the 7.47 percent rate for one-year bank deposits.</p>
<p>But the A share bull run is sucking money out of the state debt spot market, they said. In the past six weeks alone, Shanghai's A share index has surged 23.5 percent.</p>
<p>In addition, an increasing number of new A share issues has attracted speculative funds away from the spot debt market, the analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The A share markets have been very active in the past few weeks, and that has caused a lot of speculative funds to leave the state debt spot market,&quot; one state debt trader said. &quot;Heavy new A share issues have made liquidity even tighter.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;But the yields of the existing countracts are high and this will prevent them from falling sharply,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;Market fundamentals are unlikely to change much in the next month on either the state debt or the stock markets,&quot; said a securities investment analyst. &quot;Prices of the state debt contracts will see little change as a result.&quot;</p>
<p>The Shanghai exchange accounts for over 95 percent of state debt trading in China and its prices quotations have a decisive impact on trading in other markets including on the Shenzhen stock exchange and the Wuhan Securities Trading Centre.</p>
<p>Since its establishment in 1992, the spot debt market has grown to become a barometer of China's monetary policy with prices surging or plunging on major policy changes. The contracts are nearly exclusively traded by institutions.</p>
<p>&quot;No fresh-market moving factors are seen in the near future, which is another reason for the contracts to move narrowly in the next month,&quot; the investment analyst said.</p>
<p>At the close of business on Tuesday, the market's most active 10-year bond that matures in June 2006, a market barometer, rose to 117.4 yuan ($14.14) from 116.29 yuan on a technical rebound after a few weeks of falls.</p>
<p>&quot;The 10-year bond is likely to move in a narrow range of 115 to 118 yuan in the next month,&quot; said a second state debt trader. &quot;Trading in the market is expected to be very dull if the A share markets continue their bull run.&quot;</p>
<p>But a lull on the secondary debt market will not affect China's record state debt issue this year, partly because Chinese retail investors focus almost exclusively on new issues, the analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Most investors have no time to trade on the secondary market and are very wary of the risks there,&quot; said one state debt analyst. &quot;But they will continue to buy state debt as it is issued. The good sales on the primary market so far this year prove that.&quot;</p>
<p>China plans to issue a record 248.596 billion yuan worth in state debt in 1997, the Finance Ministry has announced.</p>
<p>In contrast to the spot market, analysts said Shanghai's state debt repurchase market will continue to boom next month.</p>
<p>The repo market, whose rate movements are effectively governed by the performance of the A share markets, has been active in the past few weeks with interest rates for repo papers staying at high levels.</p>
<p>Analysts said they believed the annual rates for the most active seven-day contract would continue to move around a high 16 percent next month.</p>
<p>($1 = 8.3 yuan)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
