<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480340" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: ASIAN EXOTICS - Rupiah stable as new year begins.</title>
<headline>ASIAN EXOTICS - Rupiah stable as new year begins.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Indonesian rupiah made a slow start to the new financial year on Tuesday, remaining steady amid flush liquidity after a four-day break.</p>
<p>Dealers said trading was slow, with some Japanese players establishing new positions by selling outrights.</p>
<p>&quot;There is not much activity except some players trying to pull April 1 hoaxes that the central bank would hold a press conference this afternoon,&quot; a dealer in Singapore said.</p>
<p>Bank Indonesia said there was no press conference scheduled on Tuesday.</p>
<p>A European bank dealer in Singapore said earlier rumours of a band widening after the financial year end had failed to materialise and the market was largely neutral.</p>
<p>Dealers said there was some light selling in dollars but it could also be attributable to operators establishing fresh positions with the start of a new fiscal year.</p>
<p>&quot;I hear some Japanese names in the market opening new positions but volumes are not significant,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>Spot rupiah was at 2,400.00/1.00 at 0400 GMT against an opening of 2,400.50/1.50.</p>
<p>In Malaysia, fresh buying by Japanese and U.S funds boosted the ringgit.</p>
<p>&quot;Funds are selling both dollar/Sing and dollar/ringgit,&quot; said a U.S. bank dealer in Singapore.</p>
<p>He said this was part of the traditional Japanese funds outflow into Southeast Asian currencies at the beginning of their new financial year on April 1.</p>
<p>&quot;This should continue through this month. But it will be matched, I think, by Malaysian corporate demand for the dollar,&quot; a European bank dealer in Singapore said.</p>
<p>He said Malaysia was expected to buy a Boeing 777 this month and also raise funds for the Bakun hydroelectric project in the eastern Sarawak state.</p>
<p>Further south, the Singapore dollar firmed as U.S. names sold the U.S. unit and players remained wary of pushing the Singapore dollar down after the Monetary Authority of Singapore intervened for the first time in months last week.</p>
<p>&quot;I think dollar/Sing should be sold on rallies for it to come down to 1.4300 before seeing new highs. This is just a correction after it was overbought to 1.4520/30,&quot; said a European bank dealer.</p>
<p>She said dollar/Sing was likely to be supported around 1.4410 for the day and face resistance at 1.4450/55 and 1.4480.</p>
<p>The Singapore dollar dropped to an 18-month low last week on heavy selling by offshore funds following reports, later denied, that Malaysia had decided to freeze new ties with Singapore.</p>
<p>The Thai baht firmed on the dollar's decline against major currencies but ample domestic liquidity continued to prevent strong gains in the baht.</p>
<p>The baht was quoted at 25.955-25.960 to the dollar at 0400 GMT against 25.976-25.981 on Monday. The Bank of Thailand fixed the mid-rate at 25.96 against 25.97 on Monday.</p>
<p>The overnight interbank rate edged higher to 7.50-8.00 percent early from 5.75-6.00 late on Monday on higher demand for funds, dealers said.</p>
<p>But they said any upside in the interbank rate would be curbed by the entry of Government Pension Funds (GPF) worth a total of about 80 billion baht ($3 billion) launched last week, which will enter the market in stages.</p>
<p>-- Madhav Reddy in Kuala Lumpur (603-230 8911), Mantik Kusjanto in Jakarta (6221-384-6364), Anuchit Nguyen in Bangkok (662) 652-0642 and Sonali Desai in Singapore (65-8703090)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
