<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480388" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Jiang's offer exposes China-Taiwan divide.</title>
<headline>Jiang's offer exposes China-Taiwan divide.</headline>
<byline>Kevin Chen</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chinese President Jiang Zemin's offer to make a Taiwanese vice president if Taiwan accepts reunification with the mainland exposes the very dispute that divides the two rivals.</p>
<p>What China sees as a carrot, Taiwan sees as a stick.</p>
<p>While Jiang made what he appeared to regard as a generous overture in a meeting with Japanese Foreign Minister Yukihiko Ikeda, Taiwan sees his offer as the antithesis of the island's proudest achievement -- democracy.</p>
<p>&quot;A position like the vice presidency should be decided by people's choice, not by simply giving it out from the top,&quot; said Kao Koong-lien, vice chairman of the cabinet's policymaking Mainland Affairs Council.</p>
<p>Beijing apparently hoped to sweeten the terms of its &quot;one country, two systems&quot; model under which Taiwan would be allowed basically to run itself -- if it accepts Beijing's sovereignty.</p>
<p>Jiang told Ikeda on Sunday that Beijing would not only refrain from interfering in Taiwan's politics, but also dole out powerful central government posts to Taiwan officials.</p>
<p>&quot;For example, I am president now and it is possible to welcome a vice president from Taiwan,&quot; Jiang was quoted by Japanese diplomats as saying.</p>
<p>Rather than welcome Jiang's gesture, Taiwan's Republic of China government -- exiled on the island since losing a civil war in 1949 -- slammed it as an example of authoritarian ignorance of liberal democratic ideals.</p>
<p>&quot;The Republic of China seeks a democratic, free and mutually beneficial system,&quot; a presidential spokesman who declined to be identified told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;All government posts should be decided through the will of the people. No person should have the power to grant them.&quot;</p>
<p>The influential United Daily News on Tuesday branded Jiang's offer as a &quot;carrot with no attraction&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The dignity of the Republic of China cannot be bought by any tangible or intangible reward,&quot; it said in a commentary.</p>
<p>Reforms begun in the mid-1990s gradually broke the absolute power of Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek and his Nationalist Party, first enabling Taiwan's parliament to be chosen through free elections in 1992.</p>
<p>The greatest milestone was reached in March 1996 with the first popular presidential election in Chinese history.</p>
<p>Proud of Taiwan's achievement, President Lee Teng-hui, who won the election in a landslide, says the island cannot consider reunification before Beijing itself embraces democracy.</p>
<p>Taiwan's democratic renaissance and the yearnings for full independence that it has engendered have caused deep discomfort for Beijing, which sought to affect the 1996 vote by mounting what it acknowledged were intimidating war games.</p>
<p>The eight months of live-fire drills in the Taiwan Strait convinced many in Taiwan that Beijing's communists prefer to resolve disputes by force rather than by ballot.</p>
<p>Beijing attacked Taiwan's election not as a celebration of civil rights, but as an insidious scheme by Lee and other &quot;splittists&quot; to sever Taiwan forever from the &quot;motherland&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Lee Teng-hui has not brought real political democratisation to the Taiwan masses, but instead brought...Taiwan independence to accommodate anti-China foreign countries who want to split Taiwan and the mainland,&quot; the Communist Party mouthpiece People's Daily said in an election-day commentary.</p>
<p>China is tinkering with the ballot box. Village democracy, quietly launched in the mid-1980s, has brought electoral choice to nearly a million villages that are home to some three-quarters of China's 1.2 billion people, officials say.</p>
<p>Late paramount leader Deng Xiaoping said in the 1980s that China may be ready to embrace full-scale democracy in 50 years, rendering hope to Taiwan's vision of reunification.</p>
<p>China believes it can win Taiwan's trust by faithfully implementing the &quot;one country, two systems&quot; policy in Hong Kong when the capitalist British colony returns to Chinese rule on July 1.</p>
<p>&quot;This system which we now have for Hong Kong was originally meant for Taiwan,&quot; Jiang told Japan's Ikeda.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
