<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480344" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Chinese newspapers - April 1.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Chinese political and business stories in leading newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Beijing. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy. Telephone: (8610) 6532-1921. Fax: (8610) 6532-4978.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY</p>
<p>- Communist Party, State Council issue 13-point joint decision ordering all localities and departments to reduce burdens on farmers by cancelling all kinds of illegal levies.</p>
<p>- China releases white paper on progress in human rights cause in 1996.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>XINHUA DAILY TELEGRAPH</p>
<p>- Premier Li Peng tells visiting Australian Prime Minister John Howard that China and Australia should join hands in pushing forward development of bilateral relations</p>
<p>- Premier Li Peng urges young scientists to open minds and be adventurous in research to make greater contributions to development of science and technology and modernisation.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PEOPLE'S DAILY OVERSEAS EDITION</p>
<p>- China to open trading rights on imports of rubber, steel, wood, cashmere, acrylic fibre, plywood in three years</p>
<p>- China to control trade in wheat, crude oil, oil products, fertiliser, cotton, tobacco</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA SECURITIES</p>
<p>- Bank of China launches forward yuan-dollar trading to offset risks in forex trading</p>
<p>- Sichuan province to give special policies to support selected firms such as Sichuan Changhong</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>FINANCIAL NEWS</p>
<p>- Bank of China boosts management of loans in 1996</p>
<p>- Bank of Communications loans 600 million yuan to second line of Shanghai underground</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS DAILY</p>
<p>- China sets 33 percent income tax for foreign banks handling renminbi yuan business</p>
<p>- State Council approves Oriental Group to become major trading conglomerate after Sinochem</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA BUSINESS TIMES</p>
<p>- Vice Premier Zhou Jiahua says lack of controls leads to rampant use of farmland</p>
<p>- China's liquor production hits 6.5 million tonnes in 1996, causes grain shortages in Gansu province</p>
<p>- Inner Mongolia region lacks funds to build storage facilities for grain</p>
<p>- Guangxi border trade with Vietnam hit 3.136 billion yuan in 1996, up 17.9 percent</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BEIJING ECONOMIC DAILY</p>
<p>- Yanshan Petrochemical to stop produce leaded petrol from April 1</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CHINA DAILY</p>
<p>- China pledges to further improve living, studying and labour reform environment of prisoners by 2000, says official of Ministry of Justice</p>
<p>- Two Chinese vessels will soon embark for northeastern Pacific Ocean to prospect for natural resources.</p>
<p>- Safety authorities launch crusade against road accident deaths</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
