<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480368" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: SIMEX Nikkei futures recover to end near highs.</title>
<headline>SIMEX Nikkei futures recover to end near highs.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>SIMEX Nikkei futures shrugged off the steep overnight losses on Wall Street, recouped most of their morning losses and ended near their intraday high on Tuesday, dealers said.</p>
<p>The benchmark June Nikkei contract rallied to a high of 17,870 in the afternoon before ending at 17,830, down 45 points. Volume was 13,800 lots.</p>
<p>June fell to 17,530 in the morning on Wall Street's losses and disappointment over Japan's plans to boost land liquidity.  </p>
<p>Dealers said the Nikkei futures settlement prices reflected the market's attempt to stay neutral ahead of the Bank of Japan's tankan survey, scheduled for release on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The market is expecting the tankan to indicate a peak in Japan's economy in the first quarter of 1997. It also expects sentiment for the large-scale manufacturing sector to return to positive territory.</p>
<p>Dealers said the restructure and merger plans by troubled Nippon Credit Bank would be positive for the Nikkei market.  </p>
<p>&quot;Sure there will be short term pains like job cuts but in the medium to long term, it is good news for the banking sector. It shows they are grasping the nettle,&quot; said a dealer.</p>
<p>The April MSCI Taiwan index contract ended at 335.5 against its open at 320.0 on 1,758 lots.</p>
<p>-- Angela Tan (65 8703083)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
