<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480370" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: INTERVIEW - Fish and chips make the move to Asia.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - Fish and chips make the move to Asia.</headline>
<byline>Nick Edwards</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The chip, Britain's best known contribution to world cuisine, is alive and well and coming to Asia.</p>
<p>No longer wrapped in vinegar-sodden newspaper, the deep fried slice of potato has been repackaged for the 1990s and 'branded' for maximum marketing mileage.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a unique concept -- there's nobody else with a brand image in fish and chips,&quot; John Barnes, chairman of Harry Ramsden's plc, told Reuters in an interview in Singapore, where the company has just opened a restaurant.  </p>
<p>As former UK managing director of Kentucky Fried Chicken, Barnes is undaunted by the scale of competition Ramsden's faces.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically fish and chips is the world's first fast food and the world's first theme restaurant was probably opened in 1936 in Guisely, north of Leeds, called Harry Ramsden's,&quot; he said</p>
<p>Turning the chip into a branded commodity is no easy feat. To consumers, chips do not excite in quite the same way as designer labels might.  </p>
<p>At a Ramsden's restaurant there's not a soggy chip, tiled floor or formica table top to be seen. Instead there is a stage, plush carpeting, chandeliers, wood panelling and staff in traditional-style waiters uniforms.</p>
<p>And the chip is no different to other products said Barnes.</p>
<p>&quot;As long as you live up to the reputation and give customers friendly service and you add some different touches, you've got them because people no longer see you as fish and chips, they see you as Harry Ramsden's. That's what's worked.&quot;  </p>
<p>But why come to Asia? The company's first outlet in the region was opened in Hong Kong in 1992 and it was there that Barnes first noticed the potential for fish and chips.</p>
<p>&quot;The reaction in Hong Kong, where two thirds of the customers are Chinese, says it all: there is an affection for British fish and chips done well in a larger than life concept,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A historical link with Britain also helps: &quot;If there's a bit of British history somewhere, there's more you can tap into, but it's done with affection rather than anything that's cynical,&quot; he added.  </p>
<p>Singapore has been on the agenda since at least 1994, and if it proves successful, Malaysia, Indonesia and Thailand could follow in short order.</p>
<p>With a plan to open 10 restaurants a year between now and 2000, there could be as many as 60 Harry Ramsden's open by the millennium from the present 25.</p>
<p>The three most recent were opened in the space of a week -- in Oxford, England; Inverness, Scotland; and Singapore.  </p>
<p>For Barnes, the key to his success is showing people that &quot;all you've ever heard about British fish and chips are the wrong things. You walk through our door and say 'My God, what is this?' The perception of fish and chips immediately changes&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I66100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
