<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480302" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: WA industry group backs more tariff cuts for car industry.</title>
<headline>WA industry group backs more tariff cuts for car industry.</headline>
<dateline>PERTH 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tariff protection for Australia's car manufacturing industry should continue to be cut in line with the Industry Commission's latest draft report, Western Australia's Chamber of Commerce and Industry (CCI) said.</p>
<p>In a 39-page response to the report, CCI said further phased reductions beyond the current scheduled rate of 15 per cent by the year 2000 are justified not only from a national perspective but also from the point of view of sectional and regional interests.</p>
<p>&quot;It should be emphasised that, whichever direction tariff policy takes, there will be losers as well as winners,&quot; the submissions said.</p>
<p>&quot;If further tariff reductions are implemented then South Australia and Victoria (the principal car manufacturing states) could perhaps be net losers, at least in the short term.</p>
<p>&quot;But if relatively high protection is maintained, then the other States, and Western Australia in particular, will certainly be the losers.&quot;</p>
<p>The majority findings of the draft report support continued reductions in automotive tariffs until they match the general manufacturing protection rate of five per cent, with 2004 the date set for reaching this target.</p>
<p>CCI, the major industry lobby group in Western Australia, endorses the majority findings and estimates automative tariffs cost WA consumers at least A$190 million last year.</p>
<p>At the same time, it says, WA received &quot;only a tiny proportion of the benefits of tariff protection&quot;, making it probably the biggest loser nationally from the tariff policy.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PERTH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
