<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480323" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: INTERVIEW - SFE sees bigger future in energy, meat.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - SFE sees bigger future in energy, meat.</headline>
<byline>Michael Byrnes</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Listing an electricity futures contract on the Sydney Futures Exchange (SFE) would open the door for futures trading in the more difficult market of coal, Australia's biggest export commodity, SFE chief executive Les Hosking said in an interview.</p>
<p>Predicting a bright future for electricity contracts when they list on the SFE, Hosking said deregulation of Australian electricity was raising a knock-on effect for how coal may be priced and traded forward.  </p>
<p>Electricity was simply the end product of burning coal, he said.</p>
<p>Electricity contracts were expected to list on the SFE by mid-year, following deregulation of electricity supply and generation by Australian state governments.</p>
<p>Hosking's comments follow years of unsuccessful attempts to establish a transparent open market in Australian coal.</p>
<p>Efforts had been thwarted partly because of technical problems over quality grades between different types of coal, but particularly by silent opposition by Japanese customers and Australia's biggest coal exporters.  </p>
<p>Pricing of Australia's exported coal is set in private annual contract negotiations between Japanese customers and individual Australian exporters in a system which has aroused longstanding criticism because of its lack of transparency.</p>
<p>&quot;We are actively examining a coal contract. We could well be listing one (on a one-to-two year horizon),&quot; Hosking said.</p>
<p>Deregulation in the energy markets would produce greater pricing transparency.</p>
<p>&quot;One would suggest there's an inevitability (that) other markets in that sector, like coal, will also become more transparent,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>However, Hosking said the SFE would not cause radical changes to market places by listing a coal futures contract.</p>
<p>Electricity futures could be listed on the SFE after about two months' time, Hosking said. &quot;It's on a fast track,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Specifications of an electricity contract were still under investigation. Until that work was complete, it was hard to predict potential turnover.</p>
<p>&quot;(But) in the short end of the market, in the one to three day risk area, there is sufficient volatility to indicate that an electricity contract would be well-used,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Hosking predicted electricity futures would be much more active than agricultural commodities --- but he also revealed that SFE is investigating listing live cattle and meat futures.</p>
<p>The SFE already trades an electricity futures on the New Zealand Futures and Options Exchange, which it owns. Electricity futures in New Zealand currently trade about 60 lots a day.</p>
<p>Each contract is worth NZ$12,500 face value and represents 250 megawatt hours a month.</p>
<p>SFE was now working as quickly as possible to produce consensus on contracts designed for the Australian market and for subsequent approval by regulatory authorities, Hosking said.  </p>
<p>Hosking has also said the SFE was examining listing water and natural gas contracts with deregulation in the energy industry.</p>
<p>The possible listing of cattle and meat futures was under research and development and at least &quot;12 months out&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Cattle futures specifications would have to allow contracts to be used across the entire Australian east coast, while a problem in specifying a meat contract was the industry's transition from grassfed to grainfed beef, he said.</p>
<p>The SFE was not considering dropping the low-volume wheat contract, Hosking added.  </p>
<p>&quot;We will continue to list the contract regardless of turnover and continue to monitor government policy regarding the single (monopoly export) desk,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
