<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480360" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: SE Asia Grains - Indonesia snaps up 500,000T corn.</title>
<headline>SE Asia Grains - Indonesia snaps up 500,000T corn.</headline>
<byline>K.T. Arasu</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia is believed to have snapped up at least 500,000 tonnes of corn while Thai buyers are sniffing for 50,000 tonnes of soymeal, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Reaction by Southeast Asian grain and oilseeds buyers to the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) stock and plantings report released overnight was muted, however, as the trade waited to see how the report would affect prices, the dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;At least 500,000 tonnes of corn from China, the United States and South America have been ordered for delivery in early third quarter,&quot; a dealer in Indonesia said.  </p>
<p>In Thailand, feed producers have made inquiries for 50,000 tonnes of soymeal for May delivery. Other buyers, however, were cautious about the impact of the USDA report.</p>
<p>&quot;Most buyers seemed to pause to digest the USDA report before deciding what to do. They will come back to me and say what they think. My bet is they will still be cautious (about) short-term prices,&quot; said a Bangkok-based trader.</p>
<p>&quot;Local players will wait for at least one week to digest the USDA report before deciding on what to do,&quot; an Indonesian trader added. &quot;They will want to see how prices trend over one week.&quot;  </p>
<p>Prices of new crop corn futures on the Chicago Board of Trade (CBOT) drifted lower on Monday while soybean futures dived with the November contract shedding 20-1/2 U.S. cents end at US$6.99 a bushel.</p>
<p>China continued to offer corn at prices below that of U.S. and South American origins and for shipments in quantities as small as 10,000 tonnes, dealers said.</p>
<p>The Chinese were offering August corn at $154 a tonne C&amp;F against U.S. corn which was being quoted at $160 a tonne C&amp;F.  </p>
<p>&quot;China has an advantage because it can ship out smaller quantities and the sailing time is less when compared with the United States or South America,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>Another trader said Indonesian players were undecided on whether to enter the soymeal market following the USDA report.</p>
<p>&quot;Local buyers are wondering whether they should enter the market now or wait for another week or so,&quot; he said, adding that Indian soymeal was being offered at $340 a tonne C&amp;F.</p>
<p>In Thailand, buyers were dissapointed that CBOT nearby futures prices remained firm on ideas stocks were tight.  </p>
<p>&quot;Buyers seemed to be disappointed that the nearby months are still expensive. That's why we still cannot conclude deals for May soymeal,&quot; one of the traders said.</p>
<p>Another dealer from a major firm said he would rather wait for the USDA's April report to get a better picture of spring plantings of grains and oilseeds.</p>
<p>&quot;The spring planting picture could change if there are floods and too much spring rain,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Thai traders reported no fresh corn purchases, but believe buyers will enter the market soon.  </p>
<p>&quot;They will have to buy very soon to cover May/June demand. And I will bet the industry will need to import more than 200,000 tonnes,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>There has been market talk that some feedmills attempted to buy corn from China and tried to have the origin changed to Singapore to avoid tariff duties and surcharges.</p>
<p>&quot;I heard of that talk as well. But in reality, who would dare to do that? The cost could be high, so is the risk,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Soymeal prices edged up to 9.60-9.70 baht a kg while corn also rose to 4.50-4.65 baht a kg due to strong buying from feedmills who wanted to chase up the price.</p>
<p>Indian soymeal was quoted around $320 per tonne C&amp;F while South American origin was seen between $350-$360 a tonne C&amp;F.</p>
<p>In Malaysia, grain prices were little changed from last week, except for soymeal, which fell sharply on weak demand.</p>
<p>Traders reported almost no immediate impact from the USDA report. A flour mill manager estimated that up to 80,000 tonnes of corn was expected to arrive from China this month to satisfy purchases made last month.  </p>
<p>&quot;The market's pretty sluggish as it is, and well-stocked,&quot; the official said. &quot;There's no real urgency for anyone to buy. Each of us bought at least 10,000-15,000 tonnes of the Chinese corn.&quot;</p>
<p>The price of bulk corn, ex-factory/godown in the central region, was at 410 ringgit a tonne. Local and imported soymeal were both seen at 730 ringgit. Grade &quot;A&quot; wheat was at 860 ringgit a tonne. Local wheat was unchanged at 500 ringgit.  </p>
<p>    SOUTHEAST ASIAN GRAIN/MEAL PRICES:	April 1    March 26</p>
<p>Thailand - Corn/maize (baht/kg)		4.50-4.65    4.50</p>
<p>Thailand - Imported soymeal (baht/kg)	9.60-9.70  9.60-9.65</p>
<p>Malaysia - Corn (ringgit/tonne)		  410	 400-415</p>
<p>Malaysia - Grade A wheat (ringgit/tonne)     860	   850</p>
<p>Malaysia - Low grade wheat (ringgit/tonne)   500	   500</p>
<p>Malaysia - Local soymeal (ringgit/tonne)     730	   850</p>
<p>Malaysia - Imported soymeal (ringgit/tonne)  730	   845</p>
<p>Indonesia - Corn (rupiah/kg)		    410-415    410-415</p>
<p>Indonesia - Soymeal (rupiah/kg)		 830-840	830</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (65-8703305)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
