<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480321" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: ANZ says Beijing branch licence approved.</title>
<headline>ANZ says Beijing branch licence approved.</headline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (ANZ) said on Tuesday it had received approval to proceed with accreditation for a branch banking licence in Beijing.</p>
<p>The Beijing branch would be ANZ's second branch in China, complementing the existing branch in Shanghai.  </p>
<p>ANZ said the approval to proceed was granted during a visit to China by Australian Prime Minister John Howard, who was accompanied by a number of Australian business executives including ANZ chairman Charles Goode.</p>
<p>Goode said the approval to proceed reflected the bank's position as one of the leading financial institutions in the Asian region.</p>
<p>&quot;The establishment of an ANZ branch in Beijing will significantly enhance the bank's ability to provide financial services, particularly in the increasingly important commercial and industrial bases of Beijing and Tianjin,&quot; Goode said.  </p>
<p>ANZ opened its first branch in Shanghai in 1993 and has had representative offices in Beijing since 1986 and Guangzhou since 1993.</p>
<p>ANZ said it was the only Australian bank with a branch banking presence in China.</p>
<p>ANZ executive director Alister Maitland said in the statement having a branch in Beijing would give ANZ the opportunity to grow and develop a role in assisting trade and investment flows between Australia and China.  </p>
<p>The Beijing branch would offer a wide range of personal and business deposit and loan facilities and international trade finance services.</p>
<p>ANZ expected to receive the official branch licence within a month, after certain formalities were competed.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
