<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480320" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia industry group calls for more rate cuts.</title>
<headline>Australia industry group calls for more rate cuts.</headline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Metal Trades Industry Association of Australia (MTIA) said on Tuesday it believed there was still a strong case for further cuts to official interest rates.</p>
<p>&quot;While there are uncertainties in the immediate outlook that could justify a wait-and-see approach to interest rates for a short while, the case for further cuts remains strong,&quot; the MTIA said in a pre-budget submission to the Australian government.</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) board is meeting on Tuesday, but no monetary policy change is expected as a result.</p>
<p>A Reuters survey of 30 economists found on Tuesday that the overwhelming majority expected Australian interest rates to remain on hold for at least most of 1997 before rising as inflation pressures emerged.</p>
<p>But the MTIA said it believed the Australian economy could grow at more than four percent without posing a threat to the current low inflation environment.</p>
<p>&quot;Under present circumstances of high unemployment and excess capacity, the Australian economy is capable of growing at four percent plus for an extended interval without compromising the inflation objective,&quot; the MTIA said.</p>
<p>The RBA has set an underlying inflation rate target of two to three percent over the course of the economic cycle.</p>
<p>Australia's underlying inflation rate was at 2.1 percent between the December quarters of 1995 and 1996, while consumer prices rose 1.5 percent over that period.</p>
<p>The government has forecast a growth rate of 3.5 percent for the 1996/97 financial year.</p>
<p>&quot;Now is not the time for the central bank to hold back,&quot; the MTIA said.</p>
<p>&quot;Unpalatable fiscal action has been borne in the name of easier monetary policy conditions, yet they remain essentially unchanged.</p>
<p>&quot;The question must be asked whether our policy makers have become addicted to high real interest rates?&quot;</p>
<p>The RBA eased monetary policy three times between July and December last year, each time dropping its overnight cash rate by 0.5 percentage points. The bank now targets overnight cash at 6.0 percent.</p>
<p>-- Canberra Bureau 61-6 273-2730</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
