<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480329" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: AWB Report-Australian wheat market stays strong.</title>
<headline>AWB Report-Australian wheat market stays strong.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The cash market for wheat in the Australian state of Victoria remained strong in the past week, propped up by low-volume buying interest, the Australian Wheat Board (AWB) said in its weekly grain market report.</p>
<p>However, triticale and feed barley pricers fell in response to increased supply and in anticipation of reduced dairy demand during autumn/winter, it said.</p>
<p>Sorghum in the state of Queensland continued to move south into Victoria, but prices in Brisbane remained steady over the week at quotes of about A$145.00 a tonne.  </p>
<p>The AWB national indicator price moved above the AWB's national pool estimate for the first time this season during the past week, AWB pointed out.</p>
<p>The national indicator is a cash contract fob price offered by the AWB on a delivered port basis and represents the AWB's assessment of the current state of the world market.</p>
<p>AWB wheat shipments totalled 351,069 tonnes in the past week, bringing total shipments this year to 9.96 million tonnes against 6.80 million tonnes in the same period last year.  </p>
<p>The AWB confirmed that Egypt had purchased 150,000 tonnes of wheat in the past week, with 50,000 tonnes U.S./Australian wheat for April shipment and 100,000 tonnes of Australian wheat for May/June shipment.</p>
<p>The AWB did not disclose price but said non-AWB sources indicated prices ranged between US$155.00 and US$162.50 a tonne fob for May/June and around $173.00 a tonne for the April tonnage, it said.</p>
<p>Wheat Shipping:</p>
<p>		  Latest Week     Year to Date     Previous Year</p>
<p>    (tonnes)  351,069	    9,964,213	  6,803,448</p>
<p>NOTE: Shipping year starts October 1.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
