<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480498" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: New Hokkaido bank aims for &quot;super-regional&quot; status.</title>
<headline>New Hokkaido bank aims for &quot;super-regional&quot; status.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A new bank to be formed through a merger between Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd and Hokkaido Bank Ltd will aim to become a &quot;super-regional&quot; bank, Hokkaido Takushoku vice president Chuji Ohno said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are trying to become a super-regional bank based in Hokkaido,&quot; Ohno told a news conference.</p>
<p>A super-regional bank is generally regarded as one based outside of a major money centre but which can rival big city counterparts in terms of size and profitability.</p>
<p>The new merged bank, based in Hokkaido, Japan's northernmost main island, is aiming to become a powerful regional presence as well as operating a strong domestic network outside the region.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku, Japan's 10th biggest commercial bank, currently owns 63 outlets on Japan's main island of Honshu, where Tokyo is located, and the bank does not plan to withdraw from operations in Honshu, he said.</p>
<p>Outlets in the Tokyo metropolitan area are profitable and many of the customers there actively engage in business in Hokkaido, the bank said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Withdrawal from Honshu would be like committing suicide and it is not a reasonable idea,&quot; Ohno said.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku and the smaller regional bank announced earlier on Tuesday that they plan to merge in April 1998.</p>
<p>Both are headquartered in Sapporo, the largest city in Hokkaido.</p>
<p>He said the Long-Term Credit Bank of Japan Ltd (LTCB) had agreed to help Hokkaido Takushoku withdraw from overseas operations but it did not mean that LTCB would buy Hokkaido Takushoku's overseas assets.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku plans to introduce its customers of its securities subsidiaries in Switzerland and London to LTCB, he said.</p>
<p>After withdrawing from overseas business, Hokkaido Takushoku hopes to obtain information on overseas markets from LTCB, he said.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku currently has 20 overseas offices, including six branches and five subsidiaries.  </p>
<p>Ohno also denied a report on Tuesday by Japan's Nihon Keizai Shimbun business daily that Hokkaido Takushoku would sell assets to the Hongkong &amp; Shanghai Banking Corp.</p>
<p>Ohno said that Hokkaido Takushoku and Hokkaido Bank had agreed to merge in order to survive in an era of &quot;Big Bang&quot; financial reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;To survive this era, it is important for us to clarify our identity, taking account of our financial strength, human resources and financial expertise,&quot; Ohno said.</p>
<p>&quot;The way (for us) to survive is by strengthening and stabilising our core banking business, rather than by expanding our business globally,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The major purpose of the merger is to streamline our operations and cut costs while keeping a certain level of assets,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Asked whether the merger decision was triggered by low international credit ratings and fears of business difficulties, Ohno said that these were one factor.</p>
<p>&quot;The sense of crisis has brought the agreement,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ohno said that the two banks' financial health had weakened due to massive problem loans, which grew during the bubble economy era of late 1980s.</p>
<p>He also said business efficiency at the two banks was not necessarily good as they had been competing with each other.</p>
<p>If the two banks left the situation as it is, they could not help to invigorate the local economy in Hokkaido, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
