<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480414" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Seoul stocks close lower, ceiling hike discounted.</title>
<headline>Seoul stocks close lower, ceiling hike discounted.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>An early rally among blue chips in response to Monday's announcement of a rise in the foreign investment ceiling fizzled out, and the index ended Tuesday lower on profit-taking.</p>
<p>After the market closed on Monday the finance ministry announced the ceiling would rise to 23 percent from 20 percent starting May 1.</p>
<p>&quot;Stocks have risen on hopes for the hike, and the actual announcement sparked selling today to take profits,&quot; said Park Sang-woon of Seoul Securities.</p>
<p>The index slid 4.35 points to close at 672.99.  </p>
<p>The ceiling for Pohang Iron and Steel Co and Korea Electric Power Corp will rise to 18 percent from 15 percent. Pohang gained 3,400 won to close at its daily limit of 46,500 while Korea Electric closed flat at 26,000.</p>
<p>Other blue chips ended mixed. Samsung Electronics closed 100 won higher at 60,000 while SK Telecom fell 4,000 won to end at 491,000.</p>
<p>Brokers forecast the expanded ceiling would bring in between $500 million and $600 million, against the government's estimate of about $3 billion.  </p>
<p>Analysts say the local currency's steep depreciation, as a result of a widening current account deficit, was a major factor discouraging foreign investment.</p>
<p>Dainong Corp, Woo Sung Food and Chung Won all closed limit-low on a stock exchange caution that they could become candidates for delisting next year due to poor reserve ratios. Dainong was down 360 won to 4,260, Woo Sung 2,900 won to 34,500 and Chung Won 530 won to 6,170.</p>
<p>Brokers said a correction was now due after the index gained about 10 percent in the week to Monday.</p>
<p>--YOO CHOON-SIK (822) 727 5646</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
