<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480462" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan FTC to study bank merger monopoly risk - paper.</title>
<headline>Japan FTC to study bank merger monopoly risk - paper.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's anti-monopoly watchdog is planning to study the merger of Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd and Hokkaido Bank Ltd to assess any risks of the new bank monopolising the market in Hokkaido, the Nihon Keizai Shimbun said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The Fair Trade Commission (FTC) was not immediately available for comment on the report in the leading Japanese business daily.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku, Japan's 10th-largest commercial bank, and the smaller regional bank said earlier on Tuesday that they planned to merge in April 1998. Both of them are based in Sapporo, the largest city in Hokkaido, Japan's northernmost main island.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku and Hokkaido Bank are the largest and the second largest banks in Hokkaido, the Nihon Keizai Shimbun said in its report, which appeared in its evening edition.</p>
<p>They currently hold combined deposits of more than seven trillion yen, about two-thirds of the total deposits of about 11 trillion yen in Hokkaido, the paper said.</p>
<p>The FTC will study whether other banks in Hokkaido can compete with the merged bank and if there is a possibility that the new bank will unfairly dominate the market, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>After completing the study, the FTC may tell the new bank to transfer some of its deposits or branches to other banks, the newspaper said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
