<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480471" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean Red Cross to ship new $1 mln aid to North. [CORRECTED 06:55 GMT]</title>
<headline>S.Korean Red Cross to ship new $1 mln aid to North. [CORRECTED 06:55 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea's Red Cross will send more than $1 million worth of food and vegetable seed to North Korea on Thursday, the second aid shipment in a week, a Red Cross spokesman said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>It will be the largest food delivery by the South Korean National Red Cross to the impoverished North since such shipments began in November 1995, he said.</p>
<p>On Monday (corrects from &quot;Last Wednesday&quot;), the Seoul government lifted a ban on private organisations providing rice to Pyongyang and allowed local business groups to join food aid programmes for the North.</p>
<p>Previously, only local religious and human rights groups and individual South Koreans could ship non-rice food aid to the North. Seoul had banned shipments of rice fearing it could be diverted to the military.</p>
<p>&quot;We will soon be able to begin shipping rice to North Korea,&quot; Red Cross spokesman Lee Jong-geun said.</p>
<p>The latest relief comprises 1,650 tonnes of potatoes, 10 tonnes of powdered milk and 11.2 tonnes of turnip and cabbage seeds, a Red Cross statement said. The total value was one billion won ($1.12 million).</p>
<p>This compares with a total two billion won worth of supplies shipped by the group on 13 past occasions.</p>
<p>Lee said this week's relief was not related to Monday's announcement by the government, which has made several goodwill gestures recently in an apparent bid to lure the North to proposed peace talks among the two Koreas, China and the United States.</p>
<p>The talks, jointly proposed by U.S. President Bill Clinton and South Korean President Kim Young-sam last April, are aimed at securing a peace treaty to replace a truce that ended the 1950-53 Korean War and left the two Koreas technically at war.</p>
<p>The South Korean Red Cross is the only channel for private-level food aid by South Korea.</p>
<p>Famine is looming over North Korea after two consecutive years of devastating floods and economic collapse, but Seoul has ruled out a large-scale official food aid until Pyongyang agrees to the peace talks.</p>
<p>Seoul officials said North Korea offered its first formal response to the proposal for talks last Wednesday, demanding substantial food aid at a working-level meeting in New York.</p>
<p>Washington and Seoul insist there can be no preconditions but food aid could be discussed during the talks. They have said, however, they would continue to join international relief programmes on humanitarian grounds.</p>
<p>South Korea has pledged $6 million and the U.S. $10 million after the United Nations World Food Programme (WFP) launched the latest appeal for food aid for the Stalinist state. The first shipment of the $41.6 million WFP aid is scheduled for May.</p>
<p>International aid agencies say North Korea is weeks away from famine and faces a grain shortage of between 1.5 million tonnes and three million tonnes. ($1=892.80 won)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
