<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480497" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: China's PLA troops in Hong Kong in April - paper.</title>
<headline>China's PLA troops in Hong Kong in April - paper.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Hong Kong newspaper said on Tuesday up to 200 Chinese soldiers were likely to move into the British colony this month, ahead of China's July 1 handover, but the British garrison said there was no agreement on this.</p>
<p>The Chinese-language daily Ming Pao, quoting an unidentified source, said the advance party of up to 200 People's Liberation Army (PLA) troops would be unarmed and would abide by Hong Kong laws.</p>
<p>Britain hands Hong Kong back to China at midnight on June 30, when the PLA will replace the British garrison.</p>
<p>The Sino-British Joint Liaison Group (JLG), which is haggling over handover details, including China's demand to send in a PLA advance party to prepare for the future garrison, failed two weeks ago to reach an agreement on the troops issue.</p>
<p>&quot;There can be no question of advance parties arriving in Hong Kong until there is an agreement within the JLG,&quot; British Armed Forces spokesman Roger Goodwin told Reuters when asked about the Ming Pao Report. &quot;And the last JLG meeting announced no such agreement.&quot;</p>
<p>Ming Pao said details of the advance party had been agreed in principle by China and Britain, but had yet to be finalised by London.</p>
<p>China believed Britain was stalling over the troops in a bid to wrest last-minute concessions from Beijing on other issues, such as the right of abode in Hong Kong, the newspaper said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
