<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480487" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China trains speed up to attract passengers.</title>
<headline>China trains speed up to attract passengers.</headline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's rail system entered the marketplace on Tuesday when trains started to run faster to try to win back passengers who have switched to buses and planes for speed and comfort.</p>
<p>Trains on three major lines -- between Beijing and the southern boomtown of Guangzhou, between Beijing and Shanghai, and Beijing and northeastern Harbin -- will run at a maximum speed of 140 kph (84 mph), the Ministry of Railways said.</p>
<p>Trains on other lines will reach a maximum speed of 120 kph (72 mph), the ministry said.</p>
<p>The move accelerates the average speed of China's lumbering trains from the current 48.1-54.9 kph (28.8-33 mph) and the maximum speed of long-distance passenger trains from 97.6 kph (58.5 mph), it said.</p>
<p>Ticket prices will remain unchanged.</p>
<p>The move was part of a campaign to win back travellers, many of whom in recent years have changed to buses and airlines for speed and comfort, the ministry said.</p>
<p>A train journey from Beijing to Shanghai will now take about 15 hours, compared with the previous 17-1/2 hours, officials said.</p>
<p>Trains, once the transport of choice among millions of Chinese, have lost out in recent years to rapidly developing bus and airline services.</p>
<p>China's trains carried only 942 million passengers last year, a 12.3 percent drop from the previous year. Air travel boomed</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
