<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480425" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Ghost from past haunts Indonesia's Suharto.</title>
<headline>Ghost from past haunts Indonesia's Suharto.</headline>
<byline>Jim Della-Giacoma</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ghost of Indonesia's founding president Sukarno still haunts his successor, Suharto, who is intent on stressing the legitimacy of his rise to power 30 years ago, political analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Suharto has approved an official seminar this month on Sukarno's last major speech in which he denied prior knowledge of a 1965 coup attempt blamed on the Indonesian Communist Party (PKI).</p>
<p>Suharto, now 75, took over power from Sukarno in March 1966 amid rising public discontent in the aftermath of the coup bid. He was elected provisional president a year later and president in 1968.</p>
<p>The seminar is officially aimed at giving &quot;accurate&quot; information to Indonesians, particularly the country's youth, on Sukarno's January 1967 speech to the Provisional People's Consultative Assembly (MPRS) in which he denied prior knowledge of the coup bid that sparked massive bloodshed across the nation.</p>
<p>The seminar issue led Suharto to stress publicly last week that he had not come to power through a coup d'etat.</p>
<p>&quot;In old age, perhaps, a lot of things haunt you from the past,&quot; an Indonesian historian, Onghokham, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The MPRS, whose members had been appointed by Suharto, stripped Sukarno of all his titles, including president for life, in March 1967 and elected Suharto acting president.</p>
<p>Historians give little weight to Sukarno's speech, as by then he had already been effectively pushed aside after signing a letter the previous March transfering executive power to Suharto.</p>
<p>Suharto, then chief of the army's strategic reserve command, was one of the few senior generals not killed in the 1965 coup bid led by troops from Sukarno's palace guard and the air force.</p>
<p>Suharto quickly re-asserted army control and later organised the crushing of the now-banned PKI in a series of bloody army-backed pogroms. Sukarno's links to the coup attempt have never been clear.</p>
<p>Political analysts said it was not clear why Suharto wanted to revisit the subject, but they speculated it could be linked to his decision last year to back the removal of Sukarno's daughter, Megawati Sukarnoputri, as head of the Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI).</p>
<p>They said Megawati's rising popularity was seen as a possible threat to Suharto at the March 1998 presidential election when he is expected to run for a seventh five-year term.</p>
<p>Megawati was ousted at a government-funded special congress in June 1996 and together with her supporters has been excluded from contesting a general election due at the end of May.</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps he wants to blacken a bit his historical rival and his daughter as he was troubled by the growing popularity of Sukarnoism,&quot; a Jakarta-based diplomat said.</p>
<p>Analysts note that Suharto's 30-year rule has brought stability and high economic growth to Indonesia, which was in a constant state of economic chaos and political turmoil during Sukarno's 20 years in power.</p>
<p>Despite this, Indonesia's first president remains a popular figure among the young and his speeches are still sold on cassettes at street corners across the country.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
