<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480496" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Amid defence debate, Taiwan tests U.S. missiles.</title>
<headline>Amid defence debate, Taiwan tests U.S. missiles.</headline>
<byline>C.C. Yao</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan test-fired two U.S. Hawk missiles in the Taiwan Strait on Tuesday, punctuating a debate over whether American forces would defend the Nationalist-ruled island in the face of attack by communist China.</p>
<p>The advanced short-range ground-to-air missiles successfully intercepted two target planes, destroying them in the Taiwan Strait off Tanshui on Taiwan's northwestern coast.</p>
<p>Officers said Taiwan was a pioneer in deploying the latest version of the U.S. missile and U.S. military officials were on hand to view the test.</p>
<p>&quot;This was the first time the third-generation Hawk missile has been tested outside of U.S. soil,&quot; an army missile unit officer told a news briefing.</p>
<p>The Hawk missiles, together with the locally developed medium-range Sky Bow I and Sky Bow II missiles, would strengthen Taiwan's medium-to-low air space defence, the officer said.</p>
<p>The state-funded Central News Agency said on Tuesday the United States had agreed in mid-March to sell Taiwan 54 AGM-84A Harpoon missiles and 21 Super Cobra attack helicopters armed with Hellfire missiles, but rejected Taiwan's request to buy submarines -- something that would have angered China.</p>
<p>Washington recognised Beijing's communist government in 1979, breaking off ties with Taiwan's exiled Republic of China to do so, but maintains a right to arm the capitalist island.</p>
<p>Beijing regards Taiwan as a rebel-held province that must be brought under Beijing's control, by force if necessary.</p>
<p>Whether U.S. forces would come to Taiwan's defence if China attacked has been a hot topic in Beijing, Washington and Taipei since U.S. House of Representatives leader Newt Gingrich told China's leaders that the United States would do so.</p>
<p>U.S. officials have strenuously played down the comment, saying Gingrich was representing himself, not U.S. policy.</p>
<p>The 1979 Taiwan Relations Act commits Washington to arm the island for defensive purposes, but does not explicitly commit the United States to defend Taiwan.</p>
<p>In an unambiguous warning, Washington sent two aircraft carriers to the region when Beijing mounted what it acknowledged were intimidating war games in waters near Taiwan during the island's March 1996 presidential election.</p>
<p>Taiwan's test-firing of two Hawk missiles on March 19 ended a year-long suspension of major live-fire drills ordered in March 1996 to avoid exacerbating the tensions with China, the island's arch rival since a civil war split them in 1949.</p>
<p>Beijing said the eight months of missile tests, mock landings and other war games it mounted from mid-1995 aimed to ensure Taiwan did not set a course towards independence and abandon its policy espousing eventual reunification.</p>
<p>Taiwan officials have brushed off speculation that the resumption of live-fire tests was related to unconfirmed large-scale manoeuvres that a Taipei newspaper said Beijing was planning for April in three Taiwan Strait provinces.</p>
<p>Military officials said the drills had been publicised in advance in Taiwan newspapers to ensure public safety, adding that the defence ministry had not detected any signs that China was preparing for major military drills.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C331">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
