<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480486" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan stocks dodge Wall Street hit, close higher.</title>
<headline>Taiwan stocks dodge Wall Street hit, close higher.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Late buying on electronics pushed Taiwan share prices to a sharply higher close on Tuesday as the market dodged the reverberations from Wall Street's big downturn that rattled other major Asian exchanges.</p>
<p>The benchmark index jumped to a higher open after giant Formosa Plastics made peace with Taiwan's government with a Monday pledge to drop a big China power plant investment if Taipei -- as is virtually certain -- denies a permit.</p>
<p>The index rose through the day to close at its intraday high of 8,163.41 for a gain of 159.21 points or 1.99 percent.</p>
<p>Turnover was a brisk T$128.2 billion.  </p>
<p>Formosa said on Saturday it already was building the US$3 billion China project in defiance of Taiwan policy, sparking worries to send Taiwan stocks down 1.42 percent on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Since Formosa has reached agreement with the economics ministry to back off from its China project, investor worries have eased,&quot; said HSBC James Capel analyst Alex Chen.</p>
<p>Late buying focused on electronics, which rose 3.71 percent on a sound outlook entering the second quarter.</p>
<p>Semiconductor packaging firm A.S.E. rose the daily seven percent limit to T$107 and motherboard maker Asustek was limit up to T$666.  </p>
<p>Brokers nonetheless cautioned that overconcentration on the dazzling electronics sector was skewing the wider market.</p>
<p>&quot;Electronics, despite their solid sales and profit performance, simply have been overheated,&quot; said Jardine Fleming Securities fund manager George Hou.</p>
<p>Car shares rose 4.64 percent as Yulon Motor and China Motor reported good recent sales. Yulon was limit up to T$57.5 and China Motor surged T$3.5 to T$68.</p>
<p>Constructions rose 2.87 percent on reports of good March sales in the beleaguered property market and hopes for a better April, with Pacific Construction up T$1.6 to T$31.4.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
