<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480400" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Thai gasoline export dwindles as demand catches up.</title>
<headline>Thai gasoline export dwindles as demand catches up.</headline>
<byline>Marguerita Choy</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Growing Thai gasoline demand is catching up with the surplus created by the country's burst of refinery expansions last year and is stemming exports of spot cargoes, industry sources said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Thai Oil Co Ltd, the operator of the country's biggest refinery with a capacity of 220,000 barrels per day (bpd), has stopped exporting gasoline on a spot basis, a source familiar with the refinery said.  </p>
<p>Thai Oil refinery is 49-percent owned by PTT, 15 percent by Royal-Dutch Shell and five-percent by Caltex, itself co-owned by Chevron Corp and Texaco Inc.</p>
<p>Last July, Thai Oil started its first exports of two to three 250,000-barrel cargoes of 95-octane gasoline per month.</p>
<p>That made Thailand a major gasoline exporter in Asia with refining capacity boosted to 760,000-bpd with the commissioning of the 145,000-bpd Rayong refinery and the 130,000-bpd Star refinery.  </p>
<p>The Rayong refinery is jointly owned by the Petroleum Authority of Thailand (PTT) and Shell. Star refinery is a joint-venture between PTT and Caltex.</p>
<p>For the first time, Rayong and Thai Oil concluded one-year term contracts during the third quarter of last year to export 240,000-barrels per quarter.</p>
<p>A third refiner, Bangchak Petroleum Plc started suppling 125,000 to 170,000 barrels of gasoline a month to Vietnam.</p>
<p>But no new term export contracts have been concluded since then, according to a source close to PTT.  </p>
<p>&quot;I am not sure whether we can fix on term,&quot; the source said. &quot;Demand is catching up and there is no guarantee of a constant surplus to export.&quot;</p>
<p>Said a source close to Thai Oil: &quot;There are two reasons there is nothing to export. Demand is growing a lot, and the start up of the new mixed xylene plant in mid-February is taking all the surplus reformate.&quot;</p>
<p>Reformate is an oil product which is used to produce either gasoline or petrochemicals. Thai Oil is now using the mixed xylene plant to produce petrochemicals, the source said.  </p>
<p>Last year, gasoline consumption in Thailand grew a hefty 9.5 percent to 119,000 bpd, according to PTT statistics.</p>
<p>Exports began faltering in January with gasoline being absorbed in Thailand during the high demand season in the first quarter of the year, coupled with refinery maintenance and unscheduled shutdowns.</p>
<p>&quot;Until July, demand is strong...and there are long holidays in April which should boost petrol consumption,&quot; a trader said.  </p>
<p>Instead of using its surplus reformate to produce gasoline, Thai Oil is processing it into petrochemical feedstock, mixed xylene with its new 300,000 tonnes-per-year plant, located near its refinery in Sri Racha, a source said..</p>
<p>The Rayong and Star refineries, the other two exporters, could still export spot cargoes, with one cargo for April lifting available, sources at PTT said.</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3086)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
