<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480401" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shenzhen B index ends lower on profit-taking.</title>
<headline>Shenzhen B index ends lower on profit-taking.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shenzhen's B shares zig-zagged to a lower close on Tuesday as investors took profits from gains earlier in the session but the market mood remained positive, analysts said.</p>
<p>The B index edged down 0.07 points or 0.04 percent to end the day at 162.50 points. Turnover was a thin HK$73.3 million compared with HK$88.4 million last Thursday before the market closed in line with Hong Kong's Easter holiday.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors took profits after the B index went up in the morning on optimism over China's economic prospects,&quot; an analyst at China Guotai Securities said.  </p>
<p>China's State Statistical Bureau said China's economy would grow by 10 percent in 1997 with the inflation rate around five percent, according to Monday's Shenzhen-based Securities Times.</p>
<p>&quot;Although the index ended lower, investors are optimistic,&quot; the Guotai analyst said.</p>
<p>Traders said the absence of a market clampdown widely rumoured last month had also buoyed the market mood.</p>
<p>&quot;No regulatory news is good news in the short term,&quot; a trader at Central-South Securities said.  </p>
<p>Analysts said investors were reluctant to place large orders ahead of the April 30 deadline for listed companies to publish their 1996 annual reports.</p>
<p>Only three out of 44 B share companies listed in Shenzhen have so far made their results public.</p>
<p>Shenzhen Tellus Machinery &amp; Electronics Co Ltd was the worst performer and hit its 10 percent limit-down at HK$3.38 on volume of 690,000 shares.</p>
<p>The B share market resumed trading on Tuesday after closing for the past two sessions in line with Hong Kong's Easter holiday.  </p>
<p>However, some trading took place on Friday morning due to what the Shenzhen stock exchange said was a technical error, and the transactions were carried over to Tuesday, a stock exchange statement said.</p>
<p>The A share index gained 1.28 points or 0.28 percent to 459.76 points on turnover of 10.1 billion yuan against Monday's 10.8 billion yuan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
