<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480457" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Meralco 1997 sales growth seen up 9.5 pct.</title>
<headline>Meralco 1997 sales growth seen up 9.5 pct.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Electricity distributor Manila Electric Co (Meralco) said on Tuesday it expects its sales to grow by at least 9.5 percent this year from a year ago.</p>
<p>In 1996, Meralco reported a 12.2 percent increase in kilowatt-hour sales to 17.81 billion kwhs from 15.88 billion kwhs in 1995.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect our sales to grow by 9.5 percent in 1997 or even better,&quot; Meralco president and chief executive officer Manuel Lopez said in a annual letter to shareholders.  </p>
<p>Meralco said it expected higher power demand this year on prospects that the country would sustain its solid economic growth of 6.8 percent in 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;We remain optimistic that the country can sustain the economic growth (it) had started and we foresee that this growth will be even better in the Meralco franchise area,&quot; Lopez said.</p>
<p>Meralco, the country's largest power distributor, services Metro Manila and nearby provinces.</p>
<p>&quot;We add at least 150,000 customers every year and since the franchise area includes provinces around the urban center of Metro Manila, the growth in customers will continue at a strong level as these areas develop further,&quot; Lopez said.</p>
<p>In 1996, Meralco added 208,000 customers, ending the year with 2.9 million customers.</p>
<p>Meralco posted net income of 5.064 billion pesos in 1996 against 4.411 billion the previous year mainly due to higher-than-expected growth in sales.</p>
<p>--Manila newsroom (632) 841-89-36, fax 817-62-67</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
