<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480458" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: RESEARCH ALERT - Negara report seen helping stocks.</title>
<headline>RESEARCH ALERT - Negara report seen helping stocks.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The economic outlook provided by Bank Negara in its annual report for 1996 was positive for Malaysia's stock market this year, research firm W.I. Carr said in a research report on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Strong growth momentum, ample liquidity and prospects of a currency appreciation create a positive outlook for the equity market until fourth quarter of 1997,&quot; W.I.Carr's regional economist in Singapore, Dilip Ratha said in the report.</p>
<p>He said in the fourth quarter of this year, overheating concerns may re-emerge and damp sentiment.</p>
<p>The positive trend established last year by slowing growth, cutting the current account deficit, lifting long-term capital inflows and reducing public sector spending, was expected to continue for most of 1997, Ratha said.</p>
<p>However, economic growth was stronger than the 7.8-8.2 percent forecast by Bank Negara, the country's central bank, particularly in the construction sector, the research report said.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall GDP growth, therefore, should not be less than 8.5 percent in 1997,&quot; it said.  </p>
<p>It said that Bank Negara's imposition of a limit of 20 percent of total loan outstandings on lending to the construction sector was &quot;merely to tell the financial markets that the authorities are aware of the mess in Thailand&quot;.</p>
<p>Contrary to Bank Negara's assertion that its tight monetary policy stance would continue, Ratha said interest rates were likely to fall from the second quarter of 1997 due to the high liquidity in the system.</p>
<p>He forecast a drop of 40-50 basis points in interest rates by the end of 1997.</p>
<p>Later this year, with a forecast recovery in the electronics industry, there would be stronger growth in exports, which would in turn trigger a sharp increase in imports of intermediate goods.</p>
<p>In addition, there would be the sharp rise in labour costs to contend with as Malaysia imported skilled workers to bridge the shortage in labour supply. &quot;External payment obligations, therefore, will begin to outstrip current account receipts later this year,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>Bank Negara's 1996 annual report was published on Friday.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-230 7509)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
