<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480499" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asia Products Outlook - Diesel dips on arb cargoes.</title>
<headline>Asia Products Outlook - Diesel dips on arb cargoes.</headline>
<byline>Ramthan Hussain</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asian diesel prices were set to soften as cargoes from Russia and the Middle East started to arrive and were being aggressively offered, overwhelming the number of buyers, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>But some traders noted that despite some concerns of an oversupplied market, prices were holding quite well, shaving off only a few cents from last week.</p>
<p>Traders attributed the firmness to large purchases from a Singapore oil trading firm, who has taken about 6.8 million barrels of diesel since early March.  </p>
<p>The market remained embroiled in a nervous guessing game as to whether or not the local trader would continue to support demand with some traders saying the trader concerned has almost run his course.</p>
<p>Since last Thursday, the trader has bought at lower prices of around $26.50 per barrel free-on-board (basis) for end April lifting cargoes, compared with over $28.00 for prompt cargoes two weeks ago.  </p>
<p>&quot;There are still a lot of cargoes coming in,&quot; a western trader said. &quot;Between April 20 and May 5 as much as 500,000-700,000 tonnes will hit the scene which remained unsold. But at the moment, the market are still holding.&quot;</p>
<p>Overall, over 1.6 million tonnes of Russian and Middle Eastern cargoes were expected to arrive in Asia in April and May. &quot;The Singapore trader is like a magnet and everyone is hoping that he would absorb more cargoes,&quot; one trader with arbitrage cargoes said.</p>
<p>On Monday the trader bought 600,000 barrels of arbitrage cargoes from three western traders.  </p>
<p>But others said when the trader finally withdrew amid the arrival of these cargoes, prices could plunge to the $25.00-support.</p>
<p>They said the market would also cautiously welcome a fall in prices as this might encourage China to emerge to buy more. China continued to bid at around $200 a tonne cost-and-freight southern China.</p>
<p>Traders also noted that some arbitrage cargoes would be placed into India which has bought about 870,000 tonnes in its tender for May arrival.  </p>
<p>Indonesia's gas oil demand in April was also not expected to be high as their large imports in March were causing &quot;logistical problems&quot;, one source said.</p>
<p>Indonesia's jet fuel demand was also expected to be thin as its monthly spot purchases have slipped following its annual term contract to buy 55,000 tonnes from Kuwait every 40 days.</p>
<p>But some demand for May has emerged from Nepal and Taiwan while India was expected to buy two or three cargoes in its tender for that month, compared with only one cargo per month in March and April, traders said.  </p>
<p>Gasoline prices for April came under pressure on high stocks in Singapore and aggressive offers from a Swiss trader who pushed prices down by more than $1.00 a barrel on Monday.</p>
<p>But the market remained supported for May amid healthy regional demand, trader said.</p>
<p>Refinery shutdowns in Japan and Australia have created demand which would remain supported during the U.S. summer driving season in May, traders said.</p>
<p>Regional supplies have also thinned as growing demand in Thailand was catching up with surplus brought on last year by refinery expansions and curbed exports, sources said.  </p>
<p>The market was also seeking support from Taiwan's demand for 500,000 tonnes of leaded and unleaded gasoline in its tender for early May delivery. The hikes in wholesale prices have pushed Singapore retail gasoline prices to one of Asia's  highest.</p>
<p>Traders said naphtha demand, especially from Japan, was also strong enough to absorb the 400,000 tonnes scheduled to arrive in April and May from the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>After a recent lull and a downward pressure on prices amid the arrival of Mediterranean cargoes, the fuel oil market was boosted by Chinese, Indian and South Korean demand. China recently bought at least three cargoes from from a local trader.  </p>
<p> FOB SIN (EXCEPT *)		MAR 31	MAR 21   PRICE CHANGE</p>
<p> NAPHTHA (D/B)		     24.15	  24.80     -0.65</p>
<p>NAPHTHA* C-AND-F TOKYO(D/T)  224.50	 223.20     +1.30</p>
<p> GASOLINE 95 UNL (D/B)	   27.10	  28.45     -1.35</p>
<p> JET/KEROSENE (D/B)		25.45	  27.00     -1.55</p>
<p> GAS OIL 0.5% S (D/B)	    26.70	  28.10     -1.40</p>
<p> LSWR* FOB INDONESIA (D/B)     17.35	  17.45     -0.10</p>
<p> FUEL OIL (180 CST) (D/T)     100.00	 102.50     -2.50</p>
<p> FUEL OIL (380 CST) (D/T)	94.00	  96.50     -2.00</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3084)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
