<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480565" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: BOJ provides ample funds for 2nd consecutive day.</title>
<headline>BOJ provides ample funds for 2nd consecutive day.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bank of Japan (BOJ) injected 300 billion yen more than the market needed to offset a fund shortfall for the second consecutive day on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The BOJ injected 400 billion yen into the money market in its regular 9.20 a.m. (0020 GMT) operation. The market was in deficit of 100 billion yen going into the day.</p>
<p>On Monday, the central bank supplied 300 billion yen more than required by the market in its regular operation for the first time since late July 1996.</p>
<p>Key unsecured overnight call money was traded at around 0.55 percent after the BOJ operation on Tuesday morning, down from Monday's weighted average of 0.72 percent.  </p>
<p>&quot;Under the current market conditions, the overnight rate is unlikely to fall much. The BOJ is likely to continue its accommodative stance in the coming days. Without it, the overnight rate could jump,&quot; said a regional bank trader.</p>
<p>Banks' tendency to concentrate their fund-raising in shorter-term funds was responsible for the higher overnight rate, traders said.</p>
<p>This tendency is based on the belief that the central bank will maintain its nearly 19-month commitment to keep the average of the overnight rate below its 0.5 percent official discount rate (ODR).  </p>
<p>&quot;Judging from the market trend, it looks very difficult to expect the average of the overnight rate to be below 0.5 percent in the current reserves reporting period (ending on April 15),&quot; the trader said.</p>
<p>Bids for overnight call money edged higher by late morning to around 0.63 percent.</p>
<p>Traders said the weighted average for Tuesday is difficult to predict at the moment as trade volume is thin.</p>
<p>-- Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-3-3432-9780</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
