<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480582" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: PRESS DIGEST - Philippine newspapers - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Philippine newspapers - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in Manila newspapers on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>- The family of a Chinese-Filipino kidnap victim has chosen to pay a 30 to 40 million peso ransom rather than cooperate with police authorities, southern police district sources say. (PHILIPPINE DAILY INQUIRER)</p>
<p>- Lakas congressman Jose Zubiri calls on all presidential aspirants to identify their funding sources to assure electorate that big businesses and foreign agents are not out to buy any favour. (ALL PAPERS)</p>
<p>- Withholding taxes paid by employees of the House of Representatives and other government agenices were being diverted by a syndicate to unauthorised accounts, the Bureau of Internal Revenue says. (MANILA TIMES)</p>
<p>- An Air Force attack plane crashes into a house in southern Davao del Sur, injuring three residents, including two boys. (TODAY)</p>
<p>				 +++++++++</p>
<p>BUSINESS STORIES</p>
<p>- The government is projecting a trade deficit of $14.7 billion this year from an earlier forecast of $9.5 billion. (BUSINESSWORLD)</p>
<p>- The Central Bank has appealed to the finance department to spare its reverse repurchase agreements from the imposition of the 20 percent withholding tax. (BUSINESS DAILY)</p>
<p>- The Securities and Exchange Commission is looking into companies suspected for having violated full disclosure rules, but SEC chairman Perfecto Yasay declines to name the firms. (TODAY)</p>
<p>- Selecta Dairy Products Inc has firmed up an agreement with American giant Hershey's Food Corp to exclusively distribute Hershey's confectionery products in the Philippines (MANILA TIMES)</p>
<p>- Manila newsroom (632) 841 8938</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
