<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480591" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: 2 Gaza suicide bombers miss target, wound 5 Arabs.</title>
<headline>2 Gaza suicide bombers miss target, wound 5 Arabs.</headline>
<byline>Taher Shriteh</byline>
<dateline>DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two Palestinians blew themselves up in the Gaza Strip on Tuesday in what the Israeli army said were apparent separate suicide attacks aimed at killing Jews.</p>
<p>A Palestinian hospital said five Palestinians in a passing taxi were the only ones wounded in one of the attacks.</p>
<p>&quot;There were two suicide bombers,&quot; said an Israeli army spokesman. &quot;There were no injuries to Israeli forces. There are a number of Palestinian injuries.&quot;</p>
<p>In one instance, witnesses said, the body parts of the bomber were scattered over the road.</p>
<p>Brigadier-General Saeb al-Ajaz, Palestinian police commander of the northern Gaza Strip, told Reuters: &quot;Somebody carrying five kilograms on his back blew up.&quot;</p>
<p>Other Palestinian officers said the other man was a suicide bomber who stood beside the road.</p>
<p>But Major-General Abdel-Razik Majaida, commander of the Palestinian police forces in the Gaza Strip, told Reuters: &quot;We doubt that they were suicide bombings and we are checking the two explosions. No Israelis were in the area and there are no holes in the ground.&quot;</p>
<p>Both explosions occurred around 7 a.m., about the time Israeli children leave two nearby Jewish settlements on buses for school, Jewish settlers said. But none was hurt.</p>
<p>There was no explanation for why the two explosions occurred when they did, far from any Israeli soldiers or civilians. Israeli radio stations suggested that two suicide bombers had mistakenly blown themselves up before their intended time.</p>
<p>In a separate incident, Israeli police said a Palestinian ran into a policeman with his car at an Israeli roadblock near the West Bank Jewish settlement of Kiryat Arba. They said the policeman opened fire, wounding a passenger. Palestinians said he later died. Clashes erupted nearby.</p>
<p>Palestinians said earlier the passenger had died in clashes.</p>
<p>Israeli-Palestinian relations have plunged into crisis since Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu broke ground on a Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem last month.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers have clashed for 13 straight days with Palestinian stone-throwers in the West Bank and a Palestinian suicide bomber last month killed three Israeli women at a Tel Aviv cafe.</p>
<p>Israeli security sources said the two apparent suicide bombings took place about 15 minutes apart near the Jewish settlements of Netzarim and Kfar Darom</p>
<p>Palestinian police officials had said that in the first blast, around 7 a.m. (0400 GMT), about two km (1.5 miles) from Netzarim, the suicide bomber carried some five kg (11 lb) of explosions on his back and stood beside the road when he blew himself up.</p>
<p>In the second blast about two km (1.5 miles) from Kfar Darom near the Palestinian refugee camp of Deir al-Balah, the bomber was also standing beside the road, Palestinian police said, adding the five Palestinians were wounded in this explosion.</p>
<p>The bomber's body parts were strewn all over the road, witnesses said.</p>
<p>In the past both Jewish settlements have been the focus of Palestinian attacks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DEIR AL-BALAH, Gaza Strip"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
