<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480523" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Banking, property stocks lead HK losses.</title>
<headline>Banking, property stocks lead HK losses.</headline>
<text>
<p>HONG KONG, April 1 - Hong Kong property and banking stocks dragged the market downwards in morning trade on Tuesday after losses on Wall Street last week and on Monday, analysts said.</p>
<p>The finance sector index was down 3.68 percent and the property index was off 5.44 percent in mid-morning trade compared with the 4.11 percent drop to 12,018 points in the blue-chip Hang Seng Index.</p>
<p>With the Hong Kong market closed on Friday and Monday for the Easter holiday, Tuesday morning's session was the first chance local players had to react to the drop in the Dow industrials, analysts said. &quot;U.S. banking stocks were down substantially,&quot; said ING Barings banking analyst Carmel Wellso, who expected interest rate sensitive property and banking sectors to fall further.</p>
<p>But she predicted a recovery by Hongkong and Shanghai Banking Corp Ltd, which led the falls in early trade, because it was becoming such an attractive stock at current levels.  </p>
<p>Nomura Research Institute's Robin Fox said HSBC's purchase of Banco Bamerindus de Brasil was also helping to pull down HSBC's share price.</p>
<p>HSBC was down HK$6.00 at HK$174.00 and Hang Seng Bank was off HK$3.25 at HK$76.75.</p>
<p>In the property sector, Cheung Kong Holdings slipped HK$3.75 to HK$64.50 and Henderson Land was down HK$3.25 to HK$61.00. The Dow industrials fell 157 points to 6,583 on Monday after losing 140 points on Thursday.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6441</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
