<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480599" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>KUWAIT: Kuwait says 98 pct of private sector workers expats.</title>
<headline>Kuwait says 98 pct of private sector workers expats.</headline>
<dateline>KUWAIT 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign workers constitute 98.4 percent of the workforce in Kuwait's private sector, a minister was quoted on Tuesday as saying.</p>
<p>Planning Minister Ali al-Zmei'a said 9,828 Kuwaitis are employed by the private sector while 606,087 foreigners, 44 percent of whom unskilled workers, work for private businesses.</p>
<p>The minister gave the figures in a response to a parliamentary question, al-Rai al-Aaam newspaper reported.</p>
<p>Parliament has voiced concern over the jobs of Kuwaitis working in the public sector when the government privatises heavily subsidised utilities which are also used as employment centres for Kuwaitis.</p>
<p>Zmei'a said government plans include &quot;encouraging the national workforce to join private business and support the private sector&quot;.</p>
<p>About 92.4 percent of Kuwait's national workforce is hired by the state which spends about two thirds of its annual oil revenue on wages of over 1.25 billion dinars ($4.18 billion) in the cradle-to-grave welfare state of about 720,000 Kuwaitis.</p>
<p>There are some 1.2 million foreigners in Kuwait.</p>
<p>Experts say Kuwaitis are difficult to employ in the private sector because the state guarantees them higher wages and generous benefits which private firms find hard to match.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KUWAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
