<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480529" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Mobil says suspends maintenance at aromatics plant.</title>
<headline>Mobil says suspends maintenance at aromatics plant.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mobil Singapore, a unit of Mobil Corp of the U.S. said on Tuesday it has suspended maintenance work at its aromatics plant following a gas leak.  </p>
<p>The 280,000 barrels-per-day refinery has been shut down for scheduled maintenance since March 15. The work was due to last for up to six weeks.</p>
<p>A Mobil spokesman said Mobil personnel and contractors were carrying out maintenance work at a unit in the aromatics plant when they were overcome by fumes on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;The cause of the leak is under investigation and all works on the aromatics complex have been suspended,&quot; the spokesman said.  </p>
<p>The Singapore Civil Defence Force said in a separate statement that one man died and six were injured after the gas leak. One casualty was seriously injured, Mobil said.</p>
<p>The refinery also had a flash fire on March 25, which was extinguished in a few minutes. The SCDF said there was also another fire earlier today which was brought under control after 27 minutes.</p>
<p>The SCDF said it suspected the gas leak was hydrogen sulphide. It said there were six casualties other than the man who died.</p>
<p>--Singapore Newsroom (+65 870 3081)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
