<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480587" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Hokkaido Takushoku to brief media on withdrawal.</title>
<headline>Hokkaido Takushoku to brief media on withdrawal.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd said on Tuesday that it plans to hold a news conference in Tokyo at 10.30 a.m. (0130 GMT) on a merger with Hokkaido Bank Ltd as well as its planned withdrawal from overseas operations.</p>
<p>This would follow a separate news conference at 10.00 a.m. (0100 GMT) by the two banks in Sapporo, northern Japan, to formally announce their merger deal.  </p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku also said it would unveil revised earnings forecasts for the financial year which ended on March 31 at 10.00 a.m. (0100 GMT) on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Japanese media reported late on Monday that Hokkaido Takushoku, the country's 10th-largest commercial bank, had agreed to merge with the smaller regional bank.</p>
<p>The reports said the new entity would focus on becoming a regional powerhouse on Japan's northernmost main island of Hokkaido. Both banks are headquartered in the Hokkaido city of Sapporo.</p>
<p>The merger, to take the form of a stock swap, was aimed at streamlining the domestic operations of both banks while shedding Hokkaido Takushoku's overseas dealings, the news reports said.</p>
<p>The larger Hokkaido Takushoku will be the surviving entity, and the two banks will close overlapping branches in Hokkaido, the media reports said.</p>
<p>A senior official with Japan's Ministry of Finance, which supervises the banking sector, said late on Monday he was aware the two banks were in merger discussions but said he could not confirm that a deal had been reached.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
