<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480527" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan MOF asks banks, insurers to help NCB reform.</title>
<headline>Japan MOF asks banks, insurers to help NCB reform.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Ministry of Finance (MOF) has asked banks and insurers to help support Nippon Credit Bank in its restructuring efforts, a senior MOF official told reporters on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>Sei Nakai, deputy director-general of the ministry's banking bureau, told reporters that the ministry had explained what it knew of NCB's restructuring plan this morning to 12 banks and about 30 insurance companies.</p>
<p>He said that NCB will later brief the banks and insurers on detailed plans on how they could provided financial support. He did not go into detail about the form that help could take.</p>
<p>Nakai also said that the ministry had requested the use of 80 billion yen from a special fund originally designed to deal with bad loans at the nation's failed housing loan firms, or &quot;jusen&quot;, to help resolve the problems at NCB.</p>
<p>He said he was sure that the banks would consider the proposed moves very seriously. However, no deadline has been set for the banks to respond to the request.</p>
<p>NCB, one of Japan's long-term credit banks, is working on a restructuring plan that it has said will be unveiled soon. The Finance Ministry said earlier on Tuesday it expected the troubled bank to hold a news conference later in the day but an NCB spokesman said there was no such plan for now.</p>
<p>NCB also said on Tuesday that three non-bank financial affiliates of NCB had filed for bankruptcy at the Tokyo District Court.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
