<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480573" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan's NCB to brief on restructuring today - MOF.</title>
<headline>Japan's NCB to brief on restructuring today - MOF.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Nippon Credit Bank Ltd is expected to hold a news conference later today on its restructuring plans, Finance Minister Hiroshi Mitsuzuka told a news conference on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>He said he hoped that the markets would evaluate NCB's efforts to restructure its business in a positive way.</p>
<p>Concerning the merger of Hokkaido Takushoku Bank and Hokkaido Bank, Mitsuzuka said he had not received any formal reports on their plans.</p>
<p>However, he said he expects to be formally notified today and after that he is planning to hold a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;I realise the merger was reported on the front page of every newspaper. I believe that key banks have an important responsibility for solving financial uncertainties,&quot; Mitsuzuka said.</p>
<p>&quot;They also have a responsibility to maintain credibility at home and also have a responsibility to the international financial system,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Mitsuzuka said if the merger was as reported, he would like to express praise for the banks' difficult decision to be reborn as a new bank serving the Hokkaido region of northern Japan and depositors.</p>
<p>&quot;The ministry will cooperate and support the banks' efforts and help to make them bear fruit,&quot; Mitsuzuka said.</p>
<p>Asked about his meeting with U.S. Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin in Tokyo on Friday this week, Mitsuzuka said there had been no change in the Group of Seven (G7) nations' basic stance on foreign exchange since their last meeting in Berlin in February.</p>
<p>Mitsuzuka also said he would like to discuss Japan's bad loan problem with Rubin. The Finance Ministry will give its utmost support and expertise to large and small banks to help them carry out restructuring programmes based on their individual responsibility, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I have received reports that the problem loans are steadily decreasing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said he would also like to discuss Japan's deregulation plans, including its &quot;Big Bang&quot; financial reforms. The deregulation would help to correct Japan's high cost structure and spur domestic demand, he said.</p>
<p>Mitsuzuka said he would ask the United States to support Japan's reform efforts in the spirit of friendly cooperation that exists between the two countries.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
