<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480562" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: FEATURE - Chinese learn benefits, chaos of democracy.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Chinese learn benefits, chaos of democracy.</headline>
<byline>Scott Hillis</byline>
<dateline>BEIXING, China 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>On a bright March day in northern China's Beixing village, local officials rounded up nearly all the adult residents and locked them in a schoolyard hung with bright red banners bearing political slogans.</p>
<p>Welcome to democracy -- Chinese style.</p>
<p>Some 2,000 sun-baked farmers sat patiently on small stools, listening to campaign speeches by candidates running for village chief, deputy chief and seats on the local council.</p>
<p>Poll officials, eager to ensure a smooth balloting process, took no chances on fraud or procedural disorder, clapping lock and chain on the gates of the schoolyard, where makeshift plywood polling booths stood in the dirt.</p>
<p>The enfranchised residents of the village in northern Hebei province waited for more than six hours before they were let out after the final count. They said they didn't mind.</p>
<p>&quot;Once we started these democratic elections and we could choose someone we trusted, the village started developing and the economy started picking up,&quot; Beixing pear farmer Liu Ruifa said.</p>
<p>&quot;Democratic elections let you choose someone from your own village and lead the village into prosperity,&quot; Liu said.</p>
<p>SEEDS OF DEMOCRACY SEEN BEARING FRUIT, IN TIME</p>
<p>Village democracy, quietly launched by the Ministry of Civil Affairs in the mid-1980s and complete with multi-candidate polls and mostly-secret balloting, has spread to nearly a million villages that are home to some three-quarters of China's 1.2 billion people, officials say.</p>
<p>Candidates who do not belong to the ruling Communist Party compete and often win against card-carrying party members who have traditionally wielded ultimate local power.</p>
<p>Officials boast the grassroots political freedom has helped to bring economic growth to villages and say democracy will spread, in time, to the county, provincial and national levels.</p>
<p>&quot;China will develop its democracy,&quot; said Wang Zhenyao, deputy director of the office of basic-level democracy under the Ministry of Civil Affairs. &quot;But our experiences conclude that promotion of democratic elections should not be too fast.&quot;</p>
<p>Wang gave no timetable for the spread of democracy to the most senior levels but made clear that changes would be a long time in coming.</p>
<p>Some Western analysts say the Communist Party, which still holds a firm grip on power and is far from sharing the political pie, will eventually have to brave deeper political reform if it wishes to haul China into the modern age.</p>
<p>&quot;Until the election process begins to work its way up, there aren't going to be any dramatic changes in people's lives,&quot; said U.S. China analyst Anne Thurston.</p>
<p>POLLS WON ON ROADS AND INCOMES</p>
<p>Most voting villagers, like those in Beixing, fret more about practical, mundane matters close to home rather than over national policy hammered out in distant Beijing.</p>
<p>&quot;When it rains the road is all muddy and you can't get pesticides on the trees in time,&quot; said 29-year-old resident Song Huanju of the village's main concern.</p>
<p>Winners of polls are often innovative, entrepreneurial types who promise to seek out new markets for local goods or who have the connections and know-how to start up new lines of business.</p>
<p>The party, looking to fill its ranks with more creative and pragmatic officials, has tried to recruit non-members who can win elections, Thurston said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's also a way of sort of boosting the legitimacy of the party at the local level,&quot; Thurston said, adding that some 40 percent of non-communists elected later sign on with the party.</p>
<p>Beixing's incumbent village chief and party member Liu Qinxue won re-election to the three-year post with his pledges to repair the road, wipe out school fees and improve the village electricity network.</p>
<p>DISORDERLY VOTERS HAMPER REFORM</p>
<p>Teaching China's potential voters about election procedures, monitoring for poll fraud and ensuring smooth transfers of power were just some of the problems facing expansion of elections, said Wang of the civil affairs ministry.</p>
<p>&quot;The technical difficulties involved in holding elections even at the county level mean it is still too early and we need to wait a bit longer,&quot; Wang said.</p>
<p>Another problem was getting people to follow simple rules of order, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;How to get the farmers to queue up? We know how difficult it is to get city dwellers to queue up, what about farmers?&quot; he asked.</p>
<p>Villagers in Beixing seemed unconcerned with proper polling procedures. Many voters chatted noisily about the choices as they filled in ballots, often letting friends or family vote for them or choosing more than one candidate for the same post.</p>
<p>&quot;Certainly the Chinese have a long, long way to go,&quot; said Thurston. ($1 = 8.3 yuan)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIXING, China"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
