<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480559" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: FEATURE - Disney turns to Japanese cartoonist for new look.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Disney turns to Japanese cartoonist for new look.</headline>
<byline>Nao Nakanishi</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Giant sci-fi beetles, bare-bottomed heroines on gliders, and a pigman aviator are not exactly classic Disney cartoon material.</p>
<p>Yet Walt Disney is bankrolling the global release of the next cartoon from Hayao Miyazaki, the Japanese director from whose fertile imagination the images sprang.</p>
<p>Miyazaki has as quirky a view of his new employer as some of his characters.</p>
<p>&quot;They are boring,&quot; Miyazaki said of his Disney partner's films at an interview at his studio in suburban Tokyo.</p>
<p>&quot;Though I have friends there and they seem to like my work,&quot; he adds.</p>
<p>Miyazaki believes that Disney films have lost the dignity they once had and do not address broad human issues any more.</p>
<p>&quot;I despise films made purely for entertainment. It is not enough to make people laugh,&quot; Miyazaki said. &quot;Like other arts ... film should give a glimpse into the world's secrets.&quot;</p>
<p>BEATING DISNEY</p>
<p>Miyazaki's last two films were smash hits in Japan.</p>
<p>Cinema industry figures show that domestic distribution income from &quot;Porco Rosso&quot; and &quot;Whisper of the Heart,&quot; surpassed that of Disney's &quot;Beauty and the Beast&quot; and &quot;Pocahontas&quot;.</p>
<p>His new cartoon film, &quot;The Princess Mononoke&quot;, is the first from Miyazaki's Studio Ghibli to be distributed globally by Walt Disney since the two struck a cooperation deal last year.</p>
<p>Around 100 artists are working to complete about 125,000 pictures for &quot;The Princess Mononoke&quot; which is planned for release in July.</p>
<p>Miyazaki said the film might be his last.</p>
<p>FIFTEEN-YEAR PROJECT</p>
<p>He has staked everything, including the future of himself and the studio, on the two-billion yen ($16 million) film he has been working on for more than 15 years.</p>
<p>&quot;I wouldn't mind too much if I cannot make films any more. I've lived long enough. I would love to retire,&quot; said the 56-year-old director.</p>
<p>Studio Ghibli's films, at least technically, have the air of the early Walt Disney at his most detailed and inventive.</p>
<p>In a Miyazaki cartoon, the eye is captured not only by the main action, which is often the only moving part of a standard cartoon, but also by a group of subplot actions and events in a precise three-dimensional space around it.</p>
<p>Miyazaki and his colleague Isao Takabatake have captured a strong following by attention to detail, colour, and movement in space.</p>
<p>FLYING PIG</p>
<p>One recurrent theme in a Miyazaki cartoon is aviation in the 1920s and 1930s, which provides plenty of opportunity to display those traits. &quot;Porco Rosso&quot;, featuring an aviator with a human body and the head of a pig, is essentially a violent aerial ballet in cartoon.</p>
<p>&quot;In those days, planes often crashed and people were killed. I like men and women who give up living an ordinary life on earth and vanish in the air,&quot; said Miyazaki.</p>
<p>Asked if he made films differently since the cooperation with Walt Disney, Miyazaki said: &quot;No. We can make films only our way. We live in Japan and we see things from here.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the U.S. film giant had also accepted his way of making films and did not regard Studio Ghibli as its subcontractor.</p>
<p>&quot;Disney has grasped that the Japanese market is different. They now think there might be some other markets that like films made for a Japanese audience,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Japanese animation, which generally favours dark and violent worlds as a theme, has already made an international impact.</p>
<p>Films such as the post-nuclear fantasy &quot;Akira&quot; have global cult followings.</p>
<p>Miyazaki's themes, in comparison, are gentler.</p>
<p>The new film is about the environmental and spiritual impact of human encroachment on nature.</p>
<p>&quot;'The Princess Mononoke' is our attempt to confront the largest problem of our time,&quot; Miyazaki said.</p>
<p>And if he can make another film, Miyazaki wants it to be about worms: tiny worms, ugly worms, poisonous worms which fight for their existence in a world full of exhausts.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be wonderful if children didn't kill bugs after seeing the film,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
