<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480592" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Albright urges new thinking for Mideast peace.</title>
<headline>Albright urges new thinking for Mideast peace.</headline>
<byline>Ian Simpson</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright called on Arabs and Israelis to give up &quot;old thinking and old habits&quot; and oppose terror to forge a Middle East peace.</p>
<p>Albright said late on Monday that although Israel, the Arab states and the Palestinians had accomplished much, the &quot;future is not yet at hand.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There remain those who cannot bring themselves to accept peace, and those who cannot or will not free themselves from old thinking and old habits,&quot; she said at a dinner honouring King Hussein of Jordan with a prize for his peace efforts.</p>
<p>She spoke as the peace process lurched into a new crisis with Arab states voting to stop normal relations with Israel.</p>
<p>Palestinians also staged a 12th straight day of street protests at Israel's decision to start a Jewish housing project in Arab East Jerusalem. Hussein will meet President Bill Clinton on Tuesday to discuss the crisis.</p>
<p>Hussein said peace in the Middle East was the only worthy objective of Arabs and Israelis.</p>
<p>&quot;We are passing through difficult phases, because those who want to destroy peoce will continue to try,&quot; said Hussein, who unexpectedly made peace with Israel in 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;But we must be stronger and more determined and more committed. And we will come through in the end.&quot;</p>
<p>Hussein was awarded the Ruth Ratner Miller Seeds of Peace Prize, named for the mother of Aaron Miller, deputy to U.S. Middle East envoy Dennis Ross. The Seeds of Peace organisation seeks to foster understanding between Arab and Israeli youths.</p>
<p>Albright hailed Hussein as a man who understood peace and had taught others that reconciliation among peoples begins at the individual level.</p>
<p>&quot;The process of creating confidence, forging agreements and meeting commitments can be painstaking and painful,&quot; she said. &quot;It requires a steadfast adherence to principle and steadfast opposition to terror. And it deserves the support of governments and citizens from around the globe.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
