<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480556" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: PRESS DIGEST - Thai newspapers - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Thai newspapers - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Thai press on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>TOP STORIES</p>
<p>- The Tancharoen family has suffered another setback when the Counter Corruption Commission (CCC) resolved that land ownership papers for plots belonging to them on Chumphon's Samet Island should be revoked because they were unlawfully issued. However, the CCC ruled that former deputy interior minister Suchart Tancharoen, who has also been accused of involvement in the Nong Khai land-grabbing case, had not done anything wrong in the Samet scandal. (THE NATION) (BANGKOK POST)</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Chavalit Yongchaiyudh has defended his decision to revive a military pension for Colonel Narong Kittikachorn, the infamous son of former dictator Thanom Kittikachorn, despite growing opposition from several groups including New Aspiration Party (NAP) members. As the controversy threatened to escalate into a big political storm, Chavalit maintains that Narong, who was believed to be directly involved in the killing of protesters during the October 1973 anti-Thanom uprising, has over the past decade embraced democracy by running successfully in elections. (THE NATION) (BANGKOK POST)</p>
<p>- A unanimous decision has been reached in the disciplinary investigation of deputy central bank governor Jaroong Nookhwun and two other officials of the bank for failing to bring former Bangkok Bank of Commerce (BBC) executives to court. But the members of the investigative committee have not disclosed the decision, which they say clearly states whether Jaroong and the two other officials are responsible for the collapse of a banking law case against three former BBC exectuves. (THE NATION)</p>
<p>	 + + + +</p>
<p>BUSINESS</p>
<p>- A plan for the investment of 9.57 billion baht by the Petroleum Authority of Thailand (PTT) has been suspended on the orders of the Screening Committee on Economic Affairs. This latest cut in PTT's budget was not included in the previous cut of this year's fiscal budget and will contribute to an even larger reduction of 1997's fiscal budget. (BUSINESS DAY)</p>
<p>- With Vilaiphan Euarchukiati the only member of her family left on the Bank of Asia board, the Phatraprasit family has finally seized control of the bank. The result of yeaterday's shareholders' meeting signalled the start of a new era for the family-owned bank. (BANGKOK POST)</p>
<p>- The government is making steady progress at upgrading the services provided by 66 state enterprises, with an aim to allow greater private sector participation and reduce the influence of state monopolies. To demonstrate its commitment to the task, Prime Minister General Chavalit Yongchaiyudh will personally chair a committee studying privatisation policy. (THE NATION)</p>
<p>-- Bangkok newsroom (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
