<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480552" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Hokkaido Takushoku sees larger profit after merger.</title>
<headline>Hokkaido Takushoku sees larger profit after merger.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd said on Tuesday that the new bank to be created through a merger with Hokkaido Bank Ltd would post an annual operating profit of 60 billion yen to 100 billion yen.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku posted an operating profit of 60.75 billion yen in the year to March 31, 1996. The bank announced its latest earnings forecast for fiscal 1996/97 earlier on Tuesday but did not include its outlook for operating profits.  </p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku will try to cut costs by 40 billion yen per year through steps such as closing overlapping branches in Hokkaido, northern Japan, after the planned merger with Hokkaido Bank, Hokkaido Takushoku vice president Chuji Ohno told a news conference.</p>
<p>A total of 100 branches, mainly in Hokkaido, will be closed, he said. But the merged bank will not withdraw from business on Japan's main island of Honshu, he said.</p>
<p>The new bank will also cut at least 2,000 workers in the course of the merger, Ohno said.</p>
<p>The two banks will discuss details of how to handle their problem loans, Ohno added.  </p>
<p>Ohno said that restructuring can be done without external support.</p>
<p>The new bank will follow domestic capital adequacy requirements, not using the Bank for International Settlements (BIS) ratio in the future.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku, Japan's 10th-largest commercial bank, and the smaller regional bank Hokkaido Bank said earlier on Tuesday that they plan to merge in April 1998.</p>
<p>Both are headquartered in Sapporo, Hokkaido's largest city.</p>
<p>Hokkaido Takushoku will be the surviving entity after the merger. Hokkaido Takushoku said it withdraw from overseas operations by March 1998.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
