<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480578" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China sets 33 pct tax for foreign bank business.</title>
<headline>China sets 33 pct tax for foreign bank business.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>China has set the income tax rate for foreign banks doing local currency business at 33 percent, the Beijing-based International Business Daily said on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>Foreign banks are currently taxed at a rate of 15 percent on the foreign exchange business they conduct.</p>
<p>The newspaper said the differential in tax rates between foreign banks and Chinese banks had become more of an obvious problem since the central bank in December gave approval to foreign banks to do yuan business.</p>
<p>As a result, the State Council, the cabinet, recently decided to lower income tax for all Chinese banks, insurance firms and other financial institutions to 33 percent from 55 percent, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;It has also decided that foreign banks doing Chinese yuan business must pay 33 percent income tax as well,&quot; the newspaper said. &quot;This puts Chinese and foreign banks on the same level as far as income tax (on local currency business) is concerned.&quot;  </p>
<p>China has given approval to eight foreign banks to do local currency business. Among the eight, the Hong Kong &amp; Shanghai Banking Corp and the Industrial Bank of Japan formally started yuan business last Thursday.</p>
<p>A third bank, the Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi, became the first foreign bank to place a deposit in China's local currency interbank market on Monday, a bank official said.</p>
<p>The deposit of 10 million yuan was placed on 18-day deposit at an annual rate of 10.98 percent, the official said.</p>
<p>The newspaper said another five or six foreign banks are expected to win approval to do yuan business this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
