<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480596" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Netanyahu says he considering unity government.</title>
<headline>Netanyahu says he considering unity government.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said on Tuesday he was weighing the possibility of forming a national unity government to achieve a broad consensus for a final peace deal with the Palestinians.</p>
<p>&quot;I am definitely considering it but I have not taken any decision on the matter,&quot; he told Israeli Army Radio.  </p>
<p>Netanyahu said he was certain Israel and the PLO would overcome their current crisis over Jewish settlement in Jerusalem and negotiate a permanent peace accord &quot;once the Arab side realises Israel will not surrender to its demands&quot;.</p>
<p>The right-wing Israeli leader said a &quot;wide national front&quot; would have to be formed in the Jewish state once final-status talks got under way but it was unclear whether a unity government would be the answer.</p>
<p>&quot;The big question is whether a unity government would create such a front or break it. Would it be a government of unity or two governments,&quot; Netanyahu said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu's Likud bloc and the main opposition Labour party last joined in a unity government in 1988 but the coalition fell apart two years later over differences on peace moves.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
