<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480551" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Belle slips on dilution concerns.</title>
<headline>Belle slips on dilution concerns.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gaming firm Belle Corp slipped on Tuesday by 4.0 centavos, or 4.76 percent, to 8.00 pesos in heavy early trading as some investors sold their holdings on fears a warrant issue will dilute the stock's valuation, brokers said.</p>
<p>Belle was one of the most actively traded stocks with four million shares traded so far.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be a dilution in its valuation if the warrants would be exercised,&quot; Edser Trinidad, an analyst at Peregrine Securities, said.</p>
<p>The Securities and Exchange Commission recently approved the warrant issue, which can be exercised after one year.  </p>
<p>Belle chief financial officer Eric Recto, however, said that shareholders should not be concerned because they would get additional shares if they exercise the warrants.</p>
<p>&quot;It's like a stock rights. There should be no dilution ... There are two ways of looking at things,&quot; Recto told Reuters.</p>
<p>Belle shareholders are entitled to one warrant for every five shares held. The exercise price was set at 8.50 pesos per share.</p>
<p>The company is set to announce within the week the record date for shareholders to be eligible for the warrants.</p>
<p>Ana Candelaria, analyst at Eastern Securities, said that the company's fundamentals remain solid.</p>
<p>She said the release of first quarter results in the coming weeks should change the market's perception on the company.</p>
<p>- Manila newsroom 63 2 8418938 Fax 8176267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
