<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480586" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: PHILIPPINE STOCKS - factors to watch - April 1.</title>
<headline>PHILIPPINE STOCKS - factors to watch - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are views on the direction of Philippine stocks on Tuesday and main factors likely to affect trading.</p>
<p>* Shares are expected to trade in a narrow range on Tuesday with investors remaining cautious as a result of Dow Jones' sharp 157-point overnight drop, Anscor Hagedorn Securities Inc research head Noel Reyes says.</p>
<p>* Value turnover is expected to improve, reaching a peak on Thursday with the listing of Equitable Bank, says Sun Hung Kai Securities (Phil) Inc in its daily market outlook.  </p>
<p>* Dearth of market moving news in the domestic arena will keep the market looking at Wall Street for direction, says Abacus Securities research manager Erwin Tan.</p>
<p>* The Dow Jones fell 157.11 points on Monday or 2.33 percent to 6,583.48. Philippine Long Distance Telephone's American Depositary Receipt was unchanged at $59-7/8.</p>
<p>* On Monday, the Philippine Stock Exchange composite index settled a shade down by 0.16 points to 3,222.98.</p>
<p>* Euro-med Laboratories Phil Inc said it will offer to the public 401 million shares to raise 1.235 billion pesos to 1.764 billion pesos.</p>
<p>* MUSIC Semiconductors Corp said it is pushing through with plans to list the company's shares in the U.S. on the NASDAQ stock exchange.</p>
<p>* Selecta Dairy Products Inc said it has firmed up an agreement with American giant Hershey's Food Corp to exclusively distribute Hershey's confectionery products in the Philippines.</p>
<p>* Inquirer and Malaya says Globe Telecom will remain unprofitable until 1999.</p>
<p>* Newspaper BusinessWorld says Central Bank expects inflation rate for March to remain very close to the 4.4 percent registered in February.</p>
<p>* The benchmark 91-day Treasury bill rate slipped to an average of 9.498 percent at the regular weekly auction from 9.724 percent last week, the Bureau of Treasury said.</p>
<p>* The peso closed higher at 26.363 to the dollar vs 26.364</p>
<p>* The Philippine interbank call loan average was unchanged at 9.9375 percent.</p>
<p>- KATHERINE ESPINA  63 2 841-8939 Fax 8176267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
