<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480620" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: F.O.Licht - Daily coffee report.</title>
<headline>F.O.Licht - Daily coffee report.</headline>
<text>
<p>The following is a direct contribution from commodity statistician F.O. Licht in Ratzeburg, Germany. Please address any queries to Helmut Ahlfeld on +00 49 4541 88920.</p>
<p>COFFEE - World market for March 31, 1997</p>
<p>Arabica futures in New York ended mainly higher boosted by commission house buying. However, interest in the market was fairly light, with the London market still closed for the Easter holiday. May closed 1.35 cents/lb higher at 191.15 cents/lb, while July added 1.60 cents/lb to close at 174.15 cents/lb. Market sources said the commitments of traders report showed, as expected, that speculators have largely excited from the market. However, the outlook remains constructive, with the tightness of arabica supplies likely to persist.</p>
<p>FUNDAMENTALS</p>
<p>UNITED STATES - US certified coffee stocks remained unchanged at 83,578 60-kg bags as of March 27. There were no bags pending grading, the exchange said.</p>
<p>UNITED STATES - For the week ended March 22, coffee roastings totalled approximately 260,000 60-kg bags, down from 325,000 bags the previous week and compared with 265,000 bags in the corresponding week one year ago, Complete Coffee Coverage said. Cumulative roastings totalled 4.205 mn 60-kg bags, versus 4.070 mn bags the same year ago period.</p>
<p>COLOMBIA - Colombia's National Coffee Growers Federation cut domestic coffee prices by 8.38 per cent to 333,250 pesos per 125-kg load on March 31. The new price is the second cut since December 5 when the internal coffee price was set at 221,500 pesos. The price has been raised 6 times since then under the terms of a new sliding scale system introduced by the federation to calculate payments to growers. The price is normally set every seven days and is based on the average international trading price of Colombian coffee.</p>
<p>NORWAY - Norway imported 64,100 bags of coffee in January 1997, 24 per cent less than was imported the same month the previous year. Total imports in calendar year 1996 rose by 9 per cent to 719,900 bags. The main suppliers of green coffee in January 1997 were Brazil (25,000 vs 32,500 bags) and Colombia (14,300 vs 20,000 bags).</p>
<p>NEW ZEALAND - New Zealand imported 15,400 bags of coffee in January 1997, 14 per cent more than was imported the same month the previous year. Total imports in calendar year 1996 dropped by 9 per cent to 162,900 bags. New Zealand gets most of its coffee from Indonesia, Vietnam and Papua New Guinea.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
