<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480695" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: At least 21 killed in Spanish train disaster.</title>
<headline>At least 21 killed in Spanish train disaster.</headline>
<byline>Pablo Sanchez</byline>
<dateline>HUARTE ARAQUIL, Spain 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>A crowded passenger train was derailed in northern Spain on Monday night, killing at least 21 people, injuring 89 and trapping screaming travellers in the wreckage, officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>It was Spain's deadliest train disaster in nearly two decades. A spokesman for Spanish railway company RENFE said it was &quot;very possible&quot; the death toll would rise to as high as 26 as rescue crews pulled more bodies from the twisted metal.</p>
<p>Miguel Sanz, president of Navarre province, ruled out sabotage. RENFE officials said an investigation was under way and it was too early to determine the cause of the derailment.</p>
<p>The train, carrying 248 passengers, was travelling from Barcelona to Irun on Spain's border with France when three of its four carriages slid off the track and rolled over in the village of Huarte Araquil, about 32 km (19 miles) northwest of the city of Pamplona.</p>
<p>There were moments of sheer terror in the overturned carriages as passengers, many returning home from a long holiday weekend, struggled to crawl out from beneath piles of glass, baggage and broken seats.</p>
<p>&quot;The people inside were screaming. It was horrifying,&quot; one woman passenger told reporters.</p>
<p>Dozens of ambulances rushed to the scene from surrounding towns and survivors were pulled free.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Navarre regional government confirmed there were 21 dead and 89 injured. The injured, 18 of whom were listed in serious condition, were taken to half a dozen hospitals in Navarre province.</p>
<p>Outside a Pamplona hospital, a mother wailed with grief and collapsed in the arms of relatives after being told her 23-year-old son had died in the derailment. &quot;My son! My son!&quot; she cried.</p>
<p>At the crash site, there were so many wounded to attend to that emergency crews had to leave many of the bodies alongside the tracks draped in blankets. A makeshift morgue was set up in a nearby park.</p>
<p>Spain's King Juan Carlos expressed his condolences to the victims' families, and Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar pledged to provide whatever assistance was necessary.</p>
<p>The derailment occurred when the train, called the &quot;Miguel de Unamuno&quot;, was changing tracks as it entered the station, officials said. The train's schedule called for it to pass through Huarte Araquil without making a stop.</p>
<p>&quot;I was thrown from my seat...and luggage went flying through the air,&quot; said Maribel Burgui, who was travelling with her husband and son.</p>
<p>Calling it a &quot;great miracle&quot; that they all survived, she said: &quot;We saw everyone running. We started to comfort others. We took out clothes to cover some people because it was such a cold night.&quot;</p>
<p>Mariano Arduenza, a local official who rushed to the scene, said: &quot;One car went over on top of another. People were trapped.&quot;</p>
<p>In the search for bodies, huge cranes were brought in to lift heavy pieces of twisted metal.</p>
<p>It was Spain's deadliest train crash since 1980 when 27 people were killed in the Mediterranean coastal province of Valencia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HUARTE ARAQUIL, Spain"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
