<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480682" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: PRESS DIGEST - Germany - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Germany - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the main stories from Tuesday morning's German newspapers:</p>
<p>FRANKFURTER ALLGEMEINE ZEITUNG</p>
<p>- Three members of a Turkish family die after fire in their apartment in the west German town of Krefeld. Investigators believe the blaze was started deliberately.</p>
<p>- Christian Democrat (CDU) parliamentary leader Wolfgang Schaeuble says opposition Social Democrats (SPD) deeply divided over tax policies and, as such, hardly capable of negotiating with the ruling coalition over planned tax reforms.</p>
<p>- German trade unions want the SPD to name Lower Saxony state premier Gerhard Schroeder as its candidate to challenge Helmut Kohl for the chancellorship at next year's general election.</p>
<p>- Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel says relations between Germany and Russia are largely problem free after weekend visit by Russian counterpart Yevgeny Primakov.</p>
<p>HANDELSBLATT</p>
<p>- Health Minister Horst Seehofer confirms he wants to introduce special flat rate for recipients of social aid, which would save the state an annual 250 million marks.</p>
<p>- Media group Kirch says financial situation not as alarming as had been suggested in earlier reports.</p>
<p>- European businesses could save around 90 billion marks annually with the introduction of the planned single currency, the Ifo institute says.</p>
<p>- Head of Krupp group Gerhard Cromme says his company has prepared the way for a change in Germany, although the country was not yet ready for mass takeovers with its attempt to takover Thyssen AG.</p>
<p>- Unions call on SPD to name Schroeder as candidate to fight Kohl for chancellorship.</p>
<p>- Daimler Benz AG wants to use reserves of up to eight billion marks more efficiantly, says head of finance Manfred Gentz.</p>
<p>SUEDDEUTSCHE ZEITUNG</p>
<p>- Russia's Primakov says realistic over the expansion of NATO, despite continued official opposition to the plan.</p>
<p>- Finance Minister Theo Waigel says workers can only secure their jobs only through a loosening up of wage contracts.</p>
<p>- Former German economics minister, Otto Lambsdorff, says the power of the banks should be limited following Krupp's attempt to takeover Thyssen AG.</p>
<p>DIE WELT</p>
<p>- Leading politicians and church leaders warn against the dismantling of the welfare state.</p>
<p>- Moscow's resistance to NATO expansion weakens as Primakov signals Russia ready to compromise on the issue.</p>
<p>- President Roman Herzog says Germany still not turning inventions into marketable products quickly enough.</p>
<p>- Unions want SPD to nominate Schroeder as candidate for chancellorship.</p>
<p>-- Bonn Newsroom +49 228 26097160</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
