<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480684" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: PRESS DIGEST - Austria - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Austria - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the main stories from Tuesday morning's Austrian newspapers:</p>
<p>DER STANDARD</p>
<p>- A mere 27 percent of Austrians are in favour of the introduction of Europe's planned single currency, while as many as 50 percent are outright against it, a new study says.</p>
<p>- Surfing the internet is more expensive in Austria than in any other European country because of high telephone charges, a study by the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) shows. Experts now hope cable TV operators may provide cheaper access to cyberspace.</p>
<p>- Austria's net payments to the European Union should be reduced between the years 2000 to 2006 once the bloc has completed its eastward expansion, a parliamentary working group said in a paper.</p>
<p>- Economic research institute IHS said the government should increase subsidies for research and development by almost a third in order to match the amount of money spent on R&amp;D by the majority of developed nations.</p>
<p>- Austria celebrates its number-one tennis player Thomas Muster's victory in Key Biscane, where he was badly injured eight years ago.</p>
<p>DIE PRESSE</p>
<p>- Road accidents in Austria over the Easter weekend claimed nine lives, police said.</p>
<p>- Government negotiations over the 1998/99 budget have begun.</p>
<p>- The governmet plans a new initiative to ward off increasing number of corporate insolvencies.</p>
<p>- Brewery holding BBAG denies reports of a possible sale of its unit Brau AG to drinks giant South African Breweries.</p>
<p>KURIER</p>
<p>- Education Minister Elisabeth Gehrer says she plans to make teachers' working hours more flexible in order to reduce overtime.</p>
<p>- Car insurance premiums are likely to rise as insurere now have to pay for the full cost of hospital treatment for victims of car accidents.</p>
<p>SALZBURGER NACHRICHTEN</p>
<p>- The Vienna bourse already has five candidates for its new &quot;fit&quot; market segment for middle-sized businesses, scheduled to be launched during the summer.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
