<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480672" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: PRESS DIGEST - Finland - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Finland - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are some of the leading stories in Finnish papers this morning.</p>
<p>HELSINGIN SANOMAT</p>
<p>- The cost of school education varies largely between municipalities and turned higher last year after years of cost-cutting.</p>
<p>- It is insane to price pulp based on market pulp -- that is only the tip of the production iceberg, says Metsa-Botnia's UPM1v.HE managing director Erkki Varis.</p>
<p>- Trade in farming equipment is becoming livelier after a crash during recession. @</p>
<p>- Poaching in Lapland has become a systematic million markka business rather than just hunting for own needs.</p>
<p>- Return traffic after Easter was calm without accidents or traffic jams.</p>
<p>- Actors are teaching medicine students how to meet patients.</p>
<p>- Political parties have failed to reach suburbs, which are the suffering parts of large cities, study shows.</p>
<p>- Ministry of social affairs and health is pondering ethical and social problems related to spotting genetic diseases. @</p>
<p>- Helsinki apprenticeship office crowded amid strong demand for the form of learning.</p>
<p>- Second Finance Minister Arja Alho says voluntary pension insurances' tax exemptions are questionable and should be cut.</p>
<p>KAUPPALEHTI</p>
<p>- Harri Hollmen, managing director and partner of Merita Corporate Finance and partner of Merita's brokerage and fund management companies, got 417,000 markka in dividends for last year on top of his salary. @</p>
<p>- Plastics industry is suffering from rally which has boosted raw materials prices by up to 75 percent in 14 months, industry lobby says.</p>
<p>- HK-Ruokatalo is concentrating its sausage production in Vantaa.</p>
<p>- Changes in Finnair's board will not affect the airline's operations, CEO Antti Potila says.</p>
<p>- Taxi transport is increasing, approaching peak levels reached in 1989 and 1990. @</p>
<p>- Dismantling of holding company Lanor -- set up in 1989 by Neste and Asko to defend Asko against hostile takeovers -- started with the sale of 220,000 Asko shares and made Lanor virtually debt-free, Asko CEO Jarmo Rytilahti says.</p>
<p>- Margins in truck sales are being squeezed amid tough competition, indistry says.</p>
<p>- Insurer Pohjola's plans to take over mutual Suomi would not affect associated pension insurer Ilmarinen, CEO Kari Pura says. @</p>
<p>AAMULEHTI</p>
<p>- Flexible wages alone will not save Finland's economy in economic and monetary union and the single currency area may be problematic for Finland, interim report from government-appointed EMU committe says.</p>
<p>- Four under-age youngsters in stolen car tried to run over a police officer.</p>
<p>TURUN SANOMAT</p>
<p>- Economic interests played a part in sparking the winter war against Russia, Finnish historian says. @</p>
<p>- Non-smoking should be a recruitment criterion for healthcare jobs in Uusimaa, committee proposes.</p>
<p>HUFVUDSTADSBLADET</p>
<p>- Education minister Olli-Pekka Heinonen is the most popular minister in cabinet, and his friends and political opponents agree he is far from the top of his career.</p>
<p>-- Helsinki Newsroom +358-9-680 50 242, news@reuters.fi</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
