<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480691" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: FEATURE - Pope marks 19th Easter season looking tired, frail.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Pope marks 19th Easter season looking tired, frail.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>When the start of Pope John Paul's Easter Sunday mass was delayed by 15 minutes, some people in the crowd in St Peter's Square worried and reporters in the Vatican press room became nervous.</p>
<p>In an institution so steeped in precise pageantry and ritual, even a short unexplained delay can seem like an eternity.</p>
<p>The anxiety among the media was heightened further because Italian state television RAI had told European broadcasters minutes before that there was a &quot;possibility&quot; the Pope might not be able to say the mass that morning.</p>
<p>A tired-looking Pope finally appeared before some 100,000 people and celebrated the two-hour mass, broadcast live to millions around the world.</p>
<p>SIGNS OF FATIGUE</p>
<p>He showed signs of fatigue during the ceremony and the Vatican did not say what caused the delay. The Pope, who in October marks the 19th anniversary of his election, also appeared tired at an appearance on Easter Monday.</p>
<p>Sunday's incident once again illustrated the attention that has focused on his health in recent years and the speculation on who might eventually succeed history's most travelled and well-known Pontiff.</p>
<p>Vatican officials do not like to talk about a Pope's health. An old Roman saying goes: &quot;The Pope is in fine health until he dies.&quot;</p>
<p>While it is clear that the Pope's body is only a shadow of its former, energetic self, Vatican officials express irritation at what they see as excessive media attention on what they consider a private matter.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no other world leader who has to stay before the television cameras three, four hours at a time. All this scrutiny sometimes borders on the pathetic,&quot; one official said.</p>
<p>Indeed, in four days from Holy Thursday to Easter Sunday, the Pope presided at some 18 hours of ceremonies, with the world's cameras trained on his face for signs of frailty.</p>
<p>AIDES SAY POPE'S MIND IS STILL RAZOR SHARP</p>
<p>Aides say it is only natural for a 76-year-old to look and feel tired after four days of engagements. An Easter eve service of nearly four hours kept him up until after midnight.</p>
<p>Yet, while insiders say his mind is still razor sharp, even the most loyal Papal aides acknowledge that his frailty has become ever more evident in the past five years.</p>
<p>&quot;It is understandable that some people are astonished at how much he has aged, but they don't see him every day and they are comparing him to the vibrant, mountain-climing, skiing Pope of yesteryear,&quot; a Church source said.</p>
<p>&quot;He clearly is not that way anymore but that doen't mean he is at death's door,&quot; the source added.</p>
<p>The Pope's health began its visible, unlucky decline in 1992 when he underwent surgery to remove a large tumour in the colon that doctors said was starting to turn malignant.</p>
<p>He has not walked properly since April 28, 1994, when he slipped in his bath at the Vatican and broke his right thigh. He underwent bone replacement surgery the next day.</p>
<p>The Pope, who once left aides breathless, has had to lean on them for help in negotiating unfamiliar ground and steps.</p>
<p>A series of fevers raised alarm for his health in 1995 and 1996. Vatican officials said they were caused by an inflamed appendix, which was removed in an operation last October.</p>
<p>His left hand shakes, often uncontrollably. The Vatican has not denied media reports that this is caused by a form of Parkinson's disease.</p>
<p>Papal aides say the Pope is still fully in charge and that he still puts in punishing days of audiences and paper work as supreme monarch of Vatican City and spiritual leader of the world's some 960 million Roman Catholics.</p>
<p>SIX FOREIGN TRIPS PLANNED FOR THIS YEAR</p>
<p>The Pope has six foreign trips planned for this year -- Sarajevo, Prague, Beirut, Poland, France and Brazil.</p>
<p>Insiders say he is determined to lead his flock into the third millennium of Christianity in the year 2000. Most believe he will make it.</p>
<p>A number of Vatican insiders believe that a new papacy is so far off that John Paul's successor may well be a bishop or archbishop who has not yet even been made a cardinal.</p>
<p>Cardinals choose a Pope from among their number in secret &quot;conclaves&quot; in the Vatican, where they are locked until a new Pope is chosen.</p>
<p>Pope John Paul has now appointed more than 90 percent of the cardinals under 80 years old who would be eligible to enter a conclave choose his successor.</p>
<p>This would almost certainly make his successor a conservative in his own stamp, one who would not change his controversial rulings such as the bans on contraception and women priests.</p>
<p>VATICAN RUMOUR MILL IN HIGH GEAR WITH EVERY WOBBLE</p>
<p>Still, each time the Pope appears unwell or wobbly, speculation about possible successors abounds, the Vatican rumour mill is thrust into top gear and punters lay their bets.</p>
<p>For years the hope of liberal Catholics has been 70-year-old Cardinal Carlo Maria Martini of Milan. Believed to be the most progressive of candidates, he supports &quot;healthy pluralism&quot; within the church.</p>
<p>Lucas Moreira Neves, 71, of Sao Salvador da Bahia in Brazil, is a leading conservative candidate. He comes from the developing world, where the church is growing fastest and he has also had administrative experience at the Vatican.</p>
<p>Some Church observers consider them, and other candidates, too old. Pope John Paul was only 58 when he was elected in 1978.</p>
<p>A leading African candidate is Cardinal Francis Arinze, a 64-year-old respected Nigerian who has been the Vatican's point man for relations with Islam. He would be the first black Pope.</p>
<p>Trying to predict who could become a Pope has always been fraught with risks.</p>
<p>Pope John Paul, the former Cardinal Karol Wojtyla of Krakow, Poland, was himself a dark horse candidate in the 1978 conclave that elected him.</p>
<p>Another famous Roman saying says: &quot;He who enters a conclave as a (future) Pope, leaves it as a cardinal&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
