<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480622" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Two train crashes in Spain kill 21, injure 110.</title>
<headline>Two train crashes in Spain kill 21, injure 110.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two people were killed in a train derailment on the outskirts of Madrid on Tuesday only hours after a devastating train crash in northern Spain claimed the lives of 19 passengers, officials said.</p>
<p>Investigators combing through the wreckage at both crash sites -- 280 km (175 miles) apart -- ruled out sabotage, but the accidents raised questions about the safety of Spain's national rail system.</p>
<p>Authorities continued the grim task of identifying mangled bodies pulled from the wreckage of the &quot;Miguel de Unamuno&quot; train, which was derailed on Monday night in the northern town of Huarte Araquil in Spain's worst train disaster for nearly two decades.</p>
<p>&quot;Some bodies were completely destroyed, so it is very difficult to identify them,&quot; Navarre regional president Miguel Sanz told reporters.</p>
<p>Ninety-four of the train's 248 passengers were injured in the crash, 18 of them seriously. People trapped in the wreckage screamed for help, and rescue crews worked through the night combing through the twisted metal for the last of the victims.</p>
<p>Officials of the Spanish rail company RENFE said &quot;excessive speed&quot; was the most likely cause of the crash. They said the train approached the station at 137 km (85 miles) per hour when it should have slowed down to 30 km (20 miles) per hour.</p>
<p>Less than 10 hours after the Huarte Araquil crash, a train travelling from Barcelona to Malaga with 54 passengers on board was derailed before dawn while changing tracks near Azuqueca de Henares, about 30 km (20 miles) northeast of Madrid.</p>
<p>A conductor was pronounced dead at the scene, and a French woman passenger died on the way to a local hospital, officials said. Sixteen people were injured. The cause of the derailment was under investigation.</p>
<p>Spanish television stations flashed back and forth between the two crash sites with live broadcasts, and authorities sought to calm the public's fears.</p>
<p>&quot;Trains are the safest mode of transportation (despite) the dramatic events that have occurred in less than 10 hours,&quot; Deputy Prime Minister Francisco Alvarez Cascos told state-run radio.</p>
<p>In the first accident, three of four carriages of a train travelling from Barcelona to Irun on Spain's border with France tumbled off the track in Navarre province about 32 km (19 miles) northwest of Pamplona.</p>
<p>There were moments of sheer terror in the overturned carriages as passengers, many returning home from a long holiday weekend, struggled to crawl out from beneath piles of shattered glass, baggage and broken seats.</p>
<p>&quot;The people inside were screaming. It was horrifying,&quot; one woman passenger told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;I was thrown from my seat...and luggage went flying through the air,&quot; said Maribel Burgui, travelling with her husband and son.</p>
<p>Calling it a &quot;great miracle&quot;  they all survived, she said: &quot;We saw everyone running. We started to comfort others. We took out clothes to cover some people because it was such a cold night.&quot;</p>
<p>Dozens of ambulances rushed to the scene from surrounding towns and survivors were pulled free. Early unofficial death counts rose as high as 26, but authorities said on Tuesday 19 people had been killed.</p>
<p>Outside a Pamplona hospital, a mother wailed with grief and collapsed in the arms of relatives after being told her 23-year-old son had died in the derailment. &quot;My son! My son!&quot; she cried.</p>
<p>Emergency crews at first had to leave bodies alongside the tracks draped in blankets. A makeshift morgue was set up in a nearby park, and bodies were later taken to Pamplona for identification.</p>
<p>In the search for bodies, huge cranes were brought in to lift heavy pieces of twisted metal.</p>
<p>The Huarte Araquil derailment was Spain's deadliest train crash since 1980, when 27 people were killed in the province of Valencia.</p>
<p>Spain's King Juan Carlos expressed his condolences to the victims' families. Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar pledged to provide assistance and sent Development Minister Rafael Arias Salgado to Navarre on Tuesday to help coordinate the relief effort.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
