<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480621" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: F.O.Licht - Daily sugar report.</title>
<headline>F.O.Licht - Daily sugar report.</headline>
<text>
<p>The following is a direct contribution from commodity statistician F.O. Licht in Ratzeburg, Germany. Please address any queries to Helmut Ahlfeld on +00 49 4541 88920.</p>
<p>SUGAR - World market for March 31, 1997</p>
<p>Raw sugar futures in New York ended slightly lower after a late-session bout of commission house selling pushed prices below unchanged. Refiner pricing on a scale-down basis kept prices steady for most of the day, but speculative selling in the May/July spread and commission house selling in the May contract put pressure on the market. May lost 2 points to close at 10.79 cents/lb, while July gave up 1 point to close at 10.58 cents/lb. London was closed for the Easter holiday, which kept activity in New York light.</p>
<p>FUNDAMENTALS</p>
<p>THAILAND - Thailand produced 5.547 mn tonnes of sugar, raw value, in November/March 26, 1996/97, slightly more than the 5.489 mn tonnes produced the same period in 1995/96. The rise in production is the result of the higher volume of cane crushed which reached 52.070 mn tonnes, up from 50.134 mn tonnes the previous year. However, the extraction rate this season is with 11.63 per cent significantly down on last year's figure of 12.07 per cent. Among sugar producers there is still no agreement on the eventual size of this season's crop. Some said the country could see a record crop this year while others maintained that 1996/97 production would not meet the official target of 6.28 mn tonnes, tel quel. It is believed, that the total cane harvest this year will be not more than 58 mn tonnes, less than the official forecast of 60.32 mn tonnes.</p>
<p>UNITED STATES - The area sown to sugar beet in 1997 is expected to reach 1.45 mn acres, 6.4 per cent more than the 1.37 mn acres sown last year and up on the 1995 figure of 1.44 mn acres, USDA said. It was added an ample snow pack in the Colorado and Wyoming mountains should translate into adequate irrigation water supplies for the season. North Dakota could realize a record high acreage if planting intentions are met. Growers in Ohio intend to plant no sugar beets in 1997 because the major sugar factory in the state was shut down.</p>
<p>MADAGASCAR - Sugar production in Madagascar in 1997 could reach 102,000 tonnes, raw value, up from 91,560 tonnes produced in 1996 and 94,779 tonnes produced in 1995. Molasses production in 1997 is expected to reach 40,000 tonnes, up from 36,409 tonnes in 1996 and 43,896 tonnes in 1995. Sugar consumption in 1997 is forecast to reach 85,000 tonnes, up from 83,600 tonnes in 1996 and 78,383 tonnes in 1995.</p>
<p>PHILIPPINES - Philippine sugar production in calendar year 1996 reached 1.895 mn tonnes, raw value, nearly 56,000 tonnes less than was needed for the domestic market. All the same the country exported 297,993 tonnes of sugar to the United States in 1996. The gap had to be covered by imports estimated at around 1 mn tonnes. Molasses exports in 1996 reached 43,776 tonnes of which 13,150 tonnes were exported to Taiwan, 24,326 tonnes to South Korea and 6,300 tonnes to Japan.</p>
<p>ZIMBABWE - Sugar production in Zimbabwe in 1996 reached 336,731 tonnes, raw value, while consumption was of the order of 286,859 tonnes. The country imported 2,468 tonnes of raw sugar from Zambia in 1996. Exports in 1996 reached 148,012 tonnes. Main destinations in 1996 were the United States (36,228 tonnes), the EU (62,985 tonnes) and Russia (20,000 tonnes).</p>
<p>TENDERS</p>
<p>Sri Lanka floated a tender to buy 12,500 tonnes of sugar for delivery in Colombo in the first half of June, trade sources said.</p>
<p>Syria's General Foreign Trade Organization for Chemicals and Foodstuffs (GEZA) has bought 13,000 tonnes of raw sugar at $290 per tonne from French trade house Lorico for delivery between April 15 and May 15. The buying tender for 13,000 tonnes of white sugar was cancelled as price offers did not meet GEZA's conditions.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
