<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480651" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: German coal row shows decline of EU industry.</title>
<headline>German coal row shows decline of EU industry.</headline>
<byline>Fredrik Dahl</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fierce protests by German coalminers against cuts in subsidies have put the spotlight on the rapid decline of an industry which played a key role in bringing about closer European integration after World War Two.</p>
<p>Over the last three decades, the coal industry -- which fuelled Europe's industrial revolution in the 18th and 19th centuries and its reconstruction after 1945 -- has been forced to close numerous pits and slash production.</p>
<p>Producing coal at costs well above world market prices, the sector continues to shrink despite huge state support.</p>
<p>In the 15-nation European Union, the industry last year received direct state aid of roughly 7.5 billion European currency units ($8.6 billion), most of it in Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;The European coal industry has been making increasing losses for the last 30 years,&quot; one industry expert said.</p>
<p>Reflecting continuing hard times, miners virtually besieged Bonn's government quarter for three days last month to protest against plans to reduce subsidies.</p>
<p>Under a March 13 compromise deal, the government agreed to provide more aid than planned for the next few years, but stuck to its original goal to slash subsidies from nine billion marks ($5.3 billion) now to 3.8 billion by 2005.</p>
<p>HUGE DROP IN PRODUCTION AND STAFF</p>
<p>However, even under this deal layoffs would total 46,000 by 2005, continuing a downward trend in Europe.</p>
<p>In 1955 the coal industry in Britain and the six countries that were to form the nucleus of the EU employed about 1.8 million people. Today, only 140,000 work in the sector.</p>
<p>At the same time production has plunged to 130 million tonnes from almost 500 million and an increasing share of Europe's needs for coal is met by imports from more competitive countries such as Australia, South Africa and the United States.</p>
<p>In the early 1950s, Belgium, the Netherlands, Germany, France and Britain were all producing coal.</p>
<p>Since then, Germany, Britain and France have sharply cut output while production has ceased completely in Belgium and the Netherlands. The last Belgian mine closed in 1992 and France is to stop production in 2005.</p>
<p>COAL'S DECLINE MARKED BY LABOUR UNREST</p>
<p>This decline has been accompanied by outbreaks of labour unrest, such as the bitter strike in Britain in 1984-85 as the country cut its coal output to less than 50 million tonnes from 228 million in the early 1950s.</p>
<p>&quot;The main reason for this massive contraction throughout the European Union has been the high cost of production,&quot; said Christian Cleutinx, a senior official at the European Commission.</p>
<p>The trend was expected to continue, he said in a speech last year. &quot;In the early years of the new century, total production could well be below 100 million tonnes, compared to current estimates of around 128 million for 1996.&quot;</p>
<p>This is because the cost of extracting coal is clearly uncompetitive in most EU countries compared to the world market price of $40 per tonne, due partly to geological difficulties and high wage costs.</p>
<p>The cost ranges from as much as $175 per tonne in Germany to $59 in Britain, which is by far the most competitive coal-producing country in the EU, according to 1994 figures.</p>
<p>The outlook for the industry seemed very different in 1950.</p>
<p>Reflecting the strategic importance of coal and steel, six European countries - - desperate to avoid disastrous new wars -- formed the European Coal and Steel Community (ECSC) in 1951.</p>
<p>By placing the two sectors under a common supranational authority, war would be &quot;not only unthinkable, but materially impossible,&quot; according to Robert Schuman, the French foreign minister and author of the Schuman Plan which led to the ECSC.</p>
<p>This was to be the first key step towards what is now the 15-nation European Union -- a giant single market which is planning to launch a single currency in 1999 and where renewed warfare is virtually unthinkable.</p>
<p>The coal industry was &quot;terribly important&quot; back then and it was a good place to start closer European cooperation, said Keith Richardson, secretary-general of the European Round Table of industrialists.</p>
<p>&quot;But Europe has to move on, to move forward,&quot; he said. &quot;Money spent on subsidising a declining industry is of course money that could be spent in developing new industries.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
