<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480602" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: IMF to offer little comfort to Turkish economy.</title>
<headline>IMF to offer little comfort to Turkish economy.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Lyons</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign and domestic investors, nervously eyeing Turkey's economic high-wire act, can expect little comfort from the arrival of a delegation from the International Monetary Fund.</p>
<p>Turkish markets and political leaders are looking to the IMF's two-week visit, beginning on Tuesday, for some glimmer of support for the government's economic policies.</p>
<p>But economists, business leaders and even some officials say the financial mandarins from Washington will find their interlocutors hamstrung by political concerns and unable to address the Fund's desires for structural reform.</p>
<p>The very terms of the treasury's invitation to the IMF -- routine consultations known as Article Four talks rather than discussion of a reform package -- reflect the political pressures on the coalition of Islamists and conservatives.</p>
<p>&quot;Why did they invite them for Article Four?&quot; said a senior foreign economist based in Turkey.</p>
<p>&quot;It strikes me that they made it quite clear that they were not in a position politically to discuss a programme,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Turkish officials confirm that politics -- not economic fundamentals -- bars consensus on tackling the underlying causes of runaway inflation and yawning public deficits.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a matter of economic conditions. The first condition for an (IMF) accord is a political one,&quot; Necati Ozfirat, head of the State Planning Office, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;When the government says it intends to sign an accord and implement it, then it's possible to make a deal,&quot; Ozfirat said.</p>
<p>Another senior official was more direct: &quot;There is no harmony between the coalition partners on an accord with the IMF. We have not received any order from the political leadership to work for the establishment of...an IMF agreement.&quot;</p>
<p>For its part, the IMF is not expected to change its past stance and endorse the economic status quo.</p>
<p>That will certainly disappoint bankers, investors and businessmen at home and abroad, virtually all of whom agree Turkey cannot hope to defy the economic laws of gravity forever.</p>
<p>And it will do nothing to ease the high costs of foreign borrowing, free up funds for neglected public investment or ease growing maldistribution of income.</p>
<p>Year-on-year inflation is running at 78.6 percent, a level it has held since 1984. Public sector borrowing totals over eight percent of GNP, compared with the 12 percent that helped touch off a financial crisis in April of that same year.</p>
<p>Turkey's real interest rates, meanwhile, are roughly 20 percent, among the world's highest. Last month's auction of inflation indexed bonds carried a risk premium of 25 percent.</p>
<p>Five rating agencies recently downgraded Turkish debt to sub-investment levels, largely citing lack of confidence in the political leadership to address structural weaknesses.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most striking example is the tottering state pension system. Current estimates say the Social Security Administration will have a debt of $10 billion by the year 2000 if reforms, such as raising retirement ages, are not imposed.</p>
<p>So far the weak coalition government has moved warily, unwilling to take on the powerful labour unions.</p>
<p>Large agricultural price supports, key to political clout in a country that still boasts a big rural economy, are also largely off-limits.</p>
<p>Instead, say analysts, the government has relied on one-off measures and &quot;financial engineering mechanisms&quot; to meet its target of a balanced budget for 1997. An earlier IMF delegation, here last October, has already poured cold water on the figures.</p>
<p>Critics point out the 1997 budget includes a hefty jump in tax receipts without imposing any new tax mechanisms to capture revenues from the huge unreported economy.</p>
<p>It also counts on a five-fold increase in non-tax revenues from schemes such as selling off electrical power distribution networks and dumping public lands and other property.</p>
<p>In the near-term, Turkey has yet to show any visible ill-effects.</p>
<p>Share prices in dollar terms are up about 45 percent since the start of the year, while the government has managed to lengthen average maturities of domestic paper.</p>
<p>On Monday the state statistics institute announced the economy grew by nearly eight percent in real terms last year, raising fears of overheating but casting some doubt on the textbook relationship between rampant inflation and growth.</p>
<p>In fact, Turkey's ability to rack up impressive growth for the second year running -- after dropping six percent in the crisis of 1994 -- raises questions about the traditional macro-economic tools favoured by the IMF and other institutions.</p>
<p>&quot;Where does that leave you with Turkey? It just seems to continue with inflation that people say is not sustainable and continues to have some kind of growth,&quot; said the senior foreign economist. &quot;It makes analysing it tough.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
