<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480625" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spanish train disaster kills 19, injures 89.</title>
<headline>Spanish train disaster kills 19, injures 89.</headline>
<byline>Sergio Perez</byline>
<dateline>PAMPLONA, Spain 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spanish authorities said on Tuesday 19 people were killed when a crowded passenger train was derailed near the city of Pamplona in northern Navarre province.</p>
<p>Officials said earlier 21 people had been killed in Spain's worst train disaster in nearly two decades. But they revised the figure after further examination of the mangled remains of the victims.</p>
<p>Navarre regional government president Miguel Sanz ruled out sabotage in Monday night's derailment in the village of Huarte Araquil. A spokesman for Spanish railway company RENFE said an investigation was under way.</p>
<p>Eighty-nine people were injured in the disaster, 18 of them seriously. Passengers trapped inside the wreckage screamed for help.</p>
<p>&quot;Some bodies were completely destroyed, so it is very difficult to identify them,&quot; said Sanz.</p>
<p>RENFE said the five victims identified so far were Spaniards.</p>
<p>The train, carrying 248 passengers, was travelling from Barcelona to Irun on Spain's border with France when three of its four carriages came off the track and overturned in Huarte Araquil, about 32 km (19 miles) northwest of Pamplona.</p>
<p>There were moments of sheer terror in the overturned carriages as passengers, many returning home from a long holiday weekend, struggled to crawl out from beneath piles of glass, baggage and broken seats.</p>
<p>&quot;The people inside were screaming. It was horrifying,&quot; one woman passenger told reporters.</p>
<p>Dozens of ambulances rushed to the scene from surrounding towns and survivors were pulled free.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Navarre regional government confirmed there were 21 dead and 89 injured. The injured were taken to half a dozen hospitals in Navarre province.</p>
<p>Outside a Pamplona hospital, a mother wailed with grief and collapsed in the arms of relatives after being told her 23-year-old son had died in the derailment. &quot;My son! My son!&quot; she cried.</p>
<p>There were so many injured to attend to that emergency crews had to leave many of the bodies alongside the tracks draped in blankets. A makeshift morgue was set up in a nearby park.</p>
<p>Spain's King Juan Carlos expressed his condolences to the victims' families. Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar pledged to provide whatever assistance was necessary and sent Development Minister Rafael Arias Salgado to Navarre on Tuesday to get a firsthand account of the disaster.</p>
<p>The derailment occurred when the train, called the &quot;Miguel de Unamuno&quot;, was changing tracks as it entered the station at Huarte Araquil, officials said. The train's schedule called for it to pass through the village without making a stop.</p>
<p>&quot;I was thrown from my seat...and luggage went flying through the air,&quot; said Maribel Burgui, who was travelling with her husband and son.</p>
<p>Calling it a &quot;great miracle&quot; that they all survived, she said: &quot;We saw everyone running. We started to comfort others. We took out clothes to cover some people because it was such a cold night.&quot;</p>
<p>In the search for bodies, huge cranes were brought in to lift heavy pieces of twisted metal.</p>
<p>It was Spain's deadliest train crash since 1980 when 27 people were killed in the province of Valencia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PAMPLONA, Spain"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
