<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480698" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian shares ease, traders differ on down trend.</title>
<headline>Russian shares ease, traders differ on down trend.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leading Russian shares eased at the opening on Tuesday and traders said the short-term future of the market depended on domestic support as Westerners, worried U.S. interest rates could rise further, refused to buy.</p>
<p>The Russian Trading System 23-share index opened slightly down at 301.23 on Tuesday after 301.30 previously.</p>
<p>&quot;We're expecting a further drop in blue chips. Western operators have joined us again (after the Easter holidays) and their worries about a further rise in interest rates are being reflected in the market,&quot; said Alexander Gritskevich, head of trading operations at Trinfiko.</p>
<p>Despite recent heavy falls on Wall Street, Russian securities have rallied over the last few days, mainly on domestic support, traders say.</p>
<p>But at 1315 GMT regional utility Irkutskenergo  IRGZ.RTS had fallen to $0.253 from Monday's $0.257 close. National power company UES  EESR.RTS was off at $0.1900 after $0.1917 on Monday. Both had recovered slightly from opening lows.</p>
<p>Some dealers saw the market hovering at current levels on continuing domestic support.</p>
<p>&quot;The world climate is not good right now but the Russian market has held up surprisingly well,&quot; said ING Baring's chief equity trader Peter Kizenko.</p>
<p>&quot;The market will not rally strongly but will be around the same levels, maybe a bit down in sympathy with the rest of the world.&quot;</p>
<p>But other traders said leading Russian shares would ease further in the next few days.</p>
<p>&quot;I think prices will fall back to the levels they were at before the recent rise, Russian investors can't keep up the pressure,&quot; Gritskevich said, adding that there were no aggressive domestic purchases to offset profit-taking.</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
