<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480661" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: PRESS DIGEST - Sweden - April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Sweden - April 1.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the leading stories in the Swedish papers this morning. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAGENS NYHETER</p>
<p>- A 39-year-old man fooled about 260 people into investing at least 42.5 million crowns in raw materials on international bourses. The man will go to court on Tuesday, charged with fraud.</p>
<p>- A technical investigator of the three-nation committee looking into the sinking of the Estonia ferry in 1994 said the committee would not reveal who installed the weak parts of the ship. Investigator Borje Stenstrom wrote in a December 1996 letter to the wharf that built the ship that the committee would &quot;remain silent&quot; on the issue. Stenstrom died of cancer in early March.</p>
<p>- Denmark's largest bank Den Danske Bank, which recently bought Swedish regional bank Ostgota Enskilda Bank, could make further Nordic acquisitions, its managing director Knud Sorensen said in an interview. &quot;Norway looks most accessible immediately, while it is more difficult to see the options on the Finnish market,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>SVENSKA DAGBLADET</p>
<p>- Swedish men are leaving the teaching profession because of low salaries, poor working conditions and poor career opportunities.</p>
<p>- Biotechnology group Pharmacia Biotech, held by Swedish/U.S. drugs company Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn, is not for sale but looking for a partner, its chief executive Arne Forsell said in an interview.</p>
<p>DAGENS INDUSTRI</p>
<p>- Investment group Industrivarden, drugs company Astra and mining and rubber group Trelleborg are the three big companies that are most in need of new leaders, according to a survey of market players by Eureka Research. The poll found 21 percent of respondees said Industrivarden's Clas Reuterskiold should leave his position.</p>
<p>- Stuart Pettifor takes over today as the managing director of Sweden's Avesta Sheffield which is partly owned by British Steel.</p>
<p>-- Stockholm newsroom +46-8-700 1017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
