<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480690" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: U.N. Council increases police monitors in Bosnia.</title>
<headline>U.N. Council increases police monitors in Bosnia.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.N. Security Council late on Monday increased the international police force in Bosnia by 186 plus 11 civilian personnel for the northeastern Bosnian city of Brcko.</p>
<p>But the council took no immediate action on another 120 police U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan wanted for investigating human rights abuses in the rest of the country. It said it would &quot;consider expeditiously&quot; his recommendations.</p>
<p>The strategic town of Brcko, located on the Sava River, is under international supervision for another year. It was captured by Bosnian Serbs in May 1992 and straddles the Posavina corridor, which connects the two parts of the Serb-controlled territory in Bosnia.</p>
<p>Before the war Moslems and Croats made up a majority of the town's population. But an international arbitration in February left open the decision of who eventually would control the town and asked for U.N. monitors as well as NATO-led troops to patrol the area.</p>
<p>The task for the U.N. police was to restructure and retrain the mainly Bosnian Serb police in Brcko area, including placing one monitor in very police patrol.</p>
<p>The United Nations is currently fielding 1,605 police in Bosnia as part of an International Police Task Force, known as the IPFT.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
