<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480693" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: King Hussein said to be hopeful on Middle East peace.</title>
<headline>King Hussein said to be hopeful on Middle East peace.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-03-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jordan's King Hussein is reasonably hopeful there was still a basis for moving the Middle East peace process forward, United Nations Secretary-General Kofi Annan said on Monday.</p>
<p>The king, who will visit President Bill Clinton in Washington on Tuesday, spent several hours with Annan at his residence, first at a lunch with Queen Noor that was hosted by Nane Annan, wife of the secretary-general, and then in private discussions.</p>
<p>&quot;He felt we could get over this bump and move the process forward,&quot; Annan told Reuters. &quot;And of course he has demonstrated his leadership and has managed to maintain a posture that gives him credibility with the Arabs and the Israelis.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Therefore, he is a very good interlocutor for both sides,&quot; he added. &quot;We are lucky to have someone like him involved.&quot;</p>
<p>Shortly after seeing Hussein, Annan conferred with U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright on her first visit back to the United Nations since assuming her new post. She served as U.S. ambassador to the world body for nearly four years.</p>
<p>Annan pecked Albright on the checks a few times before their meeting and she said it was &quot;very nice&quot; to be back, adding, &quot;I miss it.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if he would go to the Middle East herself, she said: &quot;I will be going at some stage and the issue is for me to determine what is the best time to go to get the peace process back on track.&quot;</p>
<p>She said she agreed with Annan, who told reporters, &quot;I think the peace process is in a difficult phase and we are doing whatever we can to get it back on track. I would appeal to all sides to avoid any initiatives that would jeopardise the process further. So I hope we will find ways and means of de-escalating the tensions.&quot;</p>
<p>Israeli-Palestinian talks have been frozen since Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu two weeks ago broke ground for new Jewish settlements in Arab East Jerusalem, triggering West Bank violence that continued on Monday for a 12th day.</p>
<p>Palestinians say the project violates an Oslo peace accords commitment to decide Jerusalem's future in final status negotiations. The crisis deepened following a March 20 suicide bombing at a Tel Aviv cafe that killed three Israelis.</p>
<p>A White House official said Clinton and the Jordanian monarch would explore ideas for reviving the peace process. He also predicted Clinton would single out Hussein's bended-knee request for forgiveness from the families of the murdered schoolgirls as the kind of &quot;personal reaching across the divide&quot; needed to restore momentum to negotiations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-03-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
