<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480669" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: PRESS DIGEST - Italy - Tuesday April 1.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Italy - Tuesday April 1.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the top headlines in leading Italian newspapers.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>TOP POLITICAL STORIES</p>
<p>* Italy pressed on with preparing a multinational security force to deploy in Albania and tried to ease strained relations by calling for a joint Rome-Tirana inquiry into the sinking of a refugee boat in which around 90 Albanians are feared drowned. Grief and anger cast a shadow over Italy's plan to lead a force of about 2,500 troops or police to protect deliveries of food and medicine in the Balkan state (all).</p>
<p>* In an interview, opposition leader Silvio Berlusconi said Italian government's indifference is responsible for Albanian tragedy. In another interview, prime minister Romano Prodi said he is in favour of a bilateral Italo-Albanian effort to clarify the facts, as the government wants to clear up what happened so that no shadow of a doubt remains (La Stampa).</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>TOP BUSINESS STORIES</p>
<p>* Italian treasury minister Carlo Azeglio Ciampi said the government's mini-budget approved by cabinet last week was only one of two steps in cleaning up state accounts and ought not to be judged on its own. The 15.5 trillion lire of deficit-cutting measures have been designed to help Italy join the first group of European monetary union, but measures really affecting the quality and the stability of the state accounts will start only with new talks over welfare reforms. Ciampi was replying to a letter by Nobel Prize-winning Franco Modigliani, one of the latest critics to the mini-budget. Modigliani wrote to Ciampi saying the additional budgetary measures were damaging and should be withdrawn (all).</p>
<p>* In an interview, trade union federation leader Sergio Cofferati said he was ready to discuss welfare state reforms with the majority coalition but pension reforms can only be discussed in 1998 (Corriere della Sera).</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and cannot vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>--Milan bureau +39266129450</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
