<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480722" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: MARKETS-EUROPE-STOCKS.</title>
<headline>MARKETS-EUROPE-STOCKS.</headline>
<byline>Dan Lalor</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>European bourses were set for a lively opening on Tuesday morning with big price falls forecast after U.S. stocks dropped sharply in consecutive sessions.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials index lost 157 points to 6,583 on Monday after shedding 140 points last Thursday, for an aggregate 4.3 percent decline. The market was closed on Friday.</p>
<p>London-based analysts said the drop was more than ample to send shivers down the spine of European traders, most of whom have not been at their desks since last Thursday because of the Easter break.</p>
<p>BZW UK equity strategist Steve Wright saw prices suffering heavily on the back of the shakeout in U.S. stocks.</p>
<p>&quot;Normally you'd say the market would go along with 50 percent of what Wall Street does,&quot; said one equity analyst at a British bank. &quot;But as we've all been waiting for a correction of some sort we could easily see the FTSE-100 lose three percent.&quot;</p>
<p>The FTSE-100 index ended last Thursday at 4312.9.</p>
<p>In early Japanese trading on Tuesday, the 225-share Nikkei average was down 277 points, or 1.5 percent, to 17,726.</p>
<p>Schroders equity strategist Paul Walton said: &quot;Taking all of Europe, those that were first will be last and vice versa. Peripheral countries which have benefited most on convergence plays will be correspondingly harder hit on a sell-off.</p>
<p>&quot;So you'd be looking at Italy and Spain and perhaps Portugal. Then there's some huge PEs (price/earnings ratios) now in Scandinavia.&quot;</p>
<p>By comparison to those markets,&quot;Britain has almost been a laggard, and Germany and Switzerland,&quot; Walton said.</p>
<p>He, nevertheless, was looking for sharply lower opening levels.</p>
<p>Looking past the opening, analysts said the performance of U.S. Treasuries would be key prior to Wall Street opening.</p>
<p>Wright at BZW said the stock market may take some comfort from the fact the U.S. long bond, whose yield has been near seven percent for some while, was reasonably calm on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Markets are very much interest rate driven and bond yields will be key,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The U.S. long bond lost just 1/8 point to 94-5/32 for a 7.10 percent yield. Its yield rose above seven percent last Thursday when it lost 1-9/32 points.</p>
<p>Fears that rising rates would leave equities overvalued relative to bonds and spell the end for the bull run in U.S. stocks was the driving force behind the Dow's losses, New York-based analysts said.</p>
<p>The U.S. Federal Reserve's policy-making arm nudged short-term U.S. interest rates higher last week with a 0.25 point rise in the fed funds target rate to 5.50 percent.</p>
<p>The ongoing tone for long-term yields will be set later this week when the latest U.S. employment report, the grand-daddy of all economic data releases, is published on Friday.</p>
<p>The jobs report is consistently the cause of the U.S. Treasury market's wildest gyrations.</p>
<p>In stock market terms, Monday's 157 points decline ranked as the sixth largest one-day loss in absolute terms whereas, in relative terms, the 2.33 percentage points fall was less rare.</p>
<p>Britain, France, Germany and most other European countries were closed both on Friday and Monday.</p>
<p>European trading ended last Thursday with one German banker forecasting: &quot;The share market will see stronger volatility in the coming weeks&quot;.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 8863</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
