<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480707" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian rulers want budget passed before test vote.</title>
<headline>Indian rulers want budget passed before test vote.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's ruling coalition said on Tuesday that it wants parliament to approve the budget for the 1997/98 (April-March) fiscal year before a vote of confidence in Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda due by April 11.</p>
<p>Jaipal Reddy, a spokesman for Deve Gowda's 15-party United Front alliance, said the coalition was exploring ways of ensuring passage of the budget before the test vote. &quot;We are making an effort,&quot; Reddy told Reuters.  </p>
<p>On Monday President Shankar Dayal Sharma asked Deve Gowda to seek a vote of confidence in the lower house of parliament by April 11. The test vote was triggered by the Congress party's surprise decision on Sunday to withdraw support for Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>Reddy said the United Front's decision-making Steering Committee discussed the proposed budget at a meeting on Monday. He said it was considering asking the speaker of the lower house, P.A. Sangma, to determine if Congress and the Bhartiya Janata Party (BJP) would agree to pass the budget before the test vote. Minor amendments would be allowed, Reddy said.</p>
<p>&quot;The United Front has decided to find a way of getting the budget passed before a vote of confidence due by April 11,&quot; United Front Steering Committee member Sitaram Yachuri told Reuters. &quot;If that does not work out, President Shankar Dayal Sharma will ask the Lok Sabha (lower house) to meet and debate the bill after the trust vote.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
