<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480718" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Hong Kong stocks plummet in early trade.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong stocks plummet in early trade.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong stocks plunged in early Tuesday morning trade as investors and traders left the market following Wall Street's Easter holiday slide, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a reaction to the Dow's 300-point fall,&quot; said Peter Lai, associate director of OCBC Securities. &quot;Hong Kong always reacts more vigorously.&quot;</p>
<p>The Hang Seng was trading 494 points lower at 12,040 after bouncing off 12,029.39, the morning's low and the lowest point the market has traded this year.</p>
<p>Turnover was a healthy HK$1.42 billion after 30 minutes of trade.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials posted their sixth largest point drop in history on Monday, sliding 157.11 points or 2.33 percent to 6,583.48, after falling 140 points on Thursday.</p>
<p>The April Hang Seng Futures contract hit a low of 11,850 at the open, then bounced back slightly to trade 508 points lower at 11,955 on trade of 7,000 contracts.</p>
<p>The May contract was 485 points at 11,975 but on very little turnover.</p>
<p>&quot;In the short term, we are likely to remain at the 12,000 for a while,&quot; said Lai.</p>
<p>Properties led the market down, with the sector index down 5.38 percent. Finance followed with a drop of 3.81 percent.</p>
<p>Cheung Kong Holdings slipped HK$4.00 to HK$64.25, off 5.9 percent and Henderson Land shed HK$3.50 to HK$60.50, off 5.45 percent.</p>
<p>Index heavyweight HSBC Holdings plummeted HK$7.50 or 4.2 percent at HK$172.50 and Hang Seng Bank slid HK$3.75 at HK$76.25, off 4.70 percent.</p>
<p>Valiantly bucking the trend at the open was COSCO Pacific which rose HK$0.05 to HK$10.25 before easing HK$0.10 to trade at HK$10.00</p>
<p>China Merchants Hai Hong slipped HK$0.25 to HK$5.25. The company will report final results on Tuesday.</p>
<p>-- Kathleen Kearney (852) 2843 6933</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
