<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480723" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ahmanson cites consent support, Great Western responds.</title>
<headline>Ahmanson cites consent support, Great Western responds.</headline>
<byline>Sue Zeidler</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES, Calif.</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hostile bidder H.F. Ahmanson and Co. said Monday that most of the biggest investors in Great Western Financial Corp. favoured a proposal calling for the California savings and loan to start talks with Ahmanson.</p>
<p>Ahmanson, the parent of Home Savings of America, said Monday that 19 of the savings and loan's 20 biggest investors have voted for or indicated they would vote yes on a consent proposal to pressure Great Western to start negotiations.</p>
<p>Ahmanson initially launched a hostile bid in mid-February for Great Western and has been tenaciously fighting to complete the deal despite Great Western's rejection and its merger agreement, announced March 6, with white knight Washington Mutual Inc.</p>
<p>Both Ahmanson's and Seattle-based Washington Mutual's bids are stock exchanges based on their shares and were each valued at about $6.1 billion Monday.</p>
<p>Chatsworth, Calif.-based Great Western reacted to Ahmanson's statement Monday, by saying hostile suitor Ahmanson's effort to solicit shareholder consents had fallen &quot;far short&quot; of a majority of the outstanding shares.</p>
<p>Ahmanson, which is based in Irwindale, Calif., said more than 80 percent of &quot;voted&quot; Great Western shares supported its proposals, but did not say what percentage of the outstanding 139 million shares were received.</p>
<p>Ahmanson initially set a March 27 deadline, but may continue soliciting consents until about May 12.</p>
<p>A few of the major institutional investors confirmed there was a favourable reaction towards the solicitation and the notion of Great Western opening up negotiations with Ahmanson.</p>
<p>&quot;The consent was a free vote. Voting against it would be silly. Of course it would be advantageous to us if they opened up negotiations, but it will come down to which offer is the best at the end of the day,&quot; said one institutional investor.</p>
<p>&quot;I think you'll find that most voted in favour (of the consent),&quot; said another institutional investor.</p>
<p>But analysts noted the outcome of the consent solicitation does not mean the investors favour one bid over another.</p>
<p>&quot;My read of the institutional holders is still that its a a toss-up at best,&quot; said UBS Securities Gareth Plank.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not getting an overwhelming sense whether Ahmanson or Washington Mutual is winning,&quot; said Plank.</p>
<p>&quot;There's still a bit of time to play it out,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A source familiar with Great Western said a shareholder vote on its merger agreement with Washington Mutual is expected to be scheduled at the end of May or early June.</p>
<p>The past few weeks has seen an almost daily stream of press releases containing accusations and rebuttals  between the dueling parties.</p>
<p>&quot;They can keep putting out all the press releases they want, but I don't think any major investors have yet decided or are paying that much attention with all the other stuff going on in the market,&quot; said Campbell Chaney of Sanford Bernstein. By &quot;other stuff&quot;, Chaney was referring to the recent Federal Reserve's rate hike and overall market volatility.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
