<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480719" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore shares hit new low, further falls likely.</title>
<headline>Singapore shares hit new low, further falls likely.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore shares plumbed new 1997 lows in early trade on Tuesday with dealers desperate for positive news to prevent a deepening downside setting in.</p>
<p>In early trade the key Straits Times Industrials Index hit a 1997 low of 2,055.41 before recovering to 2,064.52 at 0245 GMT.</p>
<p>&quot;I see a major downside coming because the big question is what's going to happen now? Are we going to do better in our economy or not? If it stays down, so will the market,&quot; one dealer with a local institution said.</p>
<p>An overnight fall of 157 points on Wall Street kicked Singapore shares off to a bad start, another dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's pretty gloomy out there today,&quot; he commented.</p>
<p>With 212 losing issues decimating 22 gainers, the sentiment was clearly echoed.</p>
<p>Early volume was a thin 33.0 million shares. The most active counter was Roly International which fell US$0.03 to US$0.53 on volume of 1.5 million units.</p>
<p>Singapore Press foreign stock took the biggest early hit, down Singapore $0.30 at S$26.00 with Total Access Communication close behind, down US$0.25 at US$6.00.</p>
<p>Creative Technology was the leading early gainer, up S$0.30 at S$13.40.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
