<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="480708" id="root" date="1997-04-01" xml:lang="en">
<title>BAHRAIN: Saudi plans to offer some SABIC shares.</title>
<headline>Saudi plans to offer some SABIC shares.</headline>
<dateline>MANAMA 1997-04-01</dateline>
<text>
<p>Saudi Arabia is considering plans to offer 30 percent of the state holdings in the industrial giant Saudi Basic Industries Corp (SABIC) to the public, SABIC officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>They quoted Saudi Industry and Electricity Minister Hashem bin Abdullah Hashem Yamani as saying &quot;a ministerial committee is studying a plan to offer part of the government's holdings in SABIC to the public.&quot;</p>
<p>Yamani, who is also chairman of SABIC, was speaking after a SABIC shareholders' meeting in the Saudi capital Riyadh on Sunday, one official told Reuters by telephone from Riyadh.</p>
<p>Yamani said the offering, if it goes ahead, could reach 30 percent of a 70 percent stake the government currently holds in SABIC. Thirty percent of SABIC's shares are already traded on the Saudi stock market.</p>
<p>Oil-rich Saudi Arabia is actively reviewing privatisation options to reduce the state's dominant role in the economy and raise revenues after more than a decade of big budget deficits.</p>
<p>Shareholders of SABIC on Sunday approved a 2.5 billion riyal ($666.7 million) dividend for 1996.</p>
<p>SABIC, which accounts for around five percent of the world's petrochemical production, posted a net profit of 4.412 billion riyals in 1996, down from 6.281 billion riyals in 1995.</p>
<p>It controls and operates 16 complexes with Western and Japanese companies, producing mainly petrochemicals, plastics, fertilisers and steel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BAHRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-01"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-01"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANAMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BAHRAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
