<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522499" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: GOLF-IRWIN RUNS AWAY FROM FIELD AT PGA SENIORS' CHAMPIONSHIP.</title>
<headline>GOLF-IRWIN RUNS AWAY FROM FIELD AT PGA SENIORS' CHAMPIONSHIP.</headline>
<dateline>PALM BEACH GARDENS, Florida 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Defending champion Hale Irwin fired a 7-under-par 65 Friday to open a seven-stroke lead midway through the $1.2 million PGA Seniors' Championship -- the second major event of the year for golf's elder statesmen.</p>
<p>Irwin took the lead from a faltering John Bland with four consecutive birdies on the front nine. Through 36 holes Irwin was at 10-under-par 134, seven shots better than Bob Charles and eight ahead of Gibby Gilbert.</p>
<p>&quot;Don't think this is a common occurrence,&quot; said Irwin, who came within two shots of the course record. &quot;I had a remarkable day and the rest of the field didn't. I'll try to approach the next two days like I'm even with everyone else.&quot;</p>
<p>Former champion Jack Nicklaus carded an even-par 72 and was tied for fourth with John Morgan, Gil Morgan and Larry Gilbert at 1-under 143.</p>
<p>Bland, who held a two-stroke overnight lead, suffered three double-bogeys, including back-to-back doubles at 16 and 17 to fall nine shots behind Irwin at even-par 144.</p>
<p>&quot;I pulled my second shot on 16 and landed in someone else's pitch mark and couldn't manoeuvre it onto the green and then three-putted,&quot; Bland said.</p>
<p>&quot;On 17, I put my tee shot into the left-hand bunker and the ball was plugged. I then blew it out and into the water.&quot;</p>
<p>Irwin was two shots back at the start of the day, but caught fire at the par-4 fourth hole, where he sank a 15-foot birdie putt. He hit a 5-iron within 10 feet to set up another birdie at number five, then landed a sand wedge six feet from the cup for his third bird in a row.</p>
<p>Irwin rolled in a 12-foot birdie to make it four straight at number seven, dropping him to 7-under. He made his only mistake at the ninth hole, hitting it over the green and settling for his second bogey of the tournament.</p>
<p>The 51-year-old Irwin didn't need much time to recover, draining a seven-foot birdie putt at number 10.</p>
<p>He moved to 9-under with a spectacular eagle on the par-4 13th hole, holing a pitching wedge from 155 yards out. The two-time U.S. Open champion put an exclamation point on his round with a four-foot birdie on 18.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll stay focused on the task at hand,&quot; Irwin said.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll be aggressive when I have to and back off at times. That's the lesson I learned last year,&quot; said Irwin, who can become the first player to repeat as champion in this event since the Senior Tour was started in 1980.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PALM BEACH GARDENS, Florida"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
