<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522496" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: MOTORCYCLING-JAPAN'S OKADA TAKES POLE POSITION IN 500CC.</title>
<headline>MOTORCYCLING-JAPAN'S OKADA TAKES POLE POSITION IN 500CC.</headline>
<dateline>SUZUKA, Japan 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Tadayuki Okada earned his second pole position of the season on Saturday to start on the front row for Sunday's Japanese 500 cc Grand Prix.</p>
<p>The Honda rider, clocked two minutes 7.952 seconds during the second qualifying practice session at the 5.864 km (3.644 miles) Suzuka circuit.</p>
<p>Okada was just 0.065 seconds ahead of team mate and world champion Michael Doohan, while Spain's Alex Criville came in third.</p>
<p>&quot;Although I am in pole position again, things were not perfect for me as the course condition was not so good...I'll do as much as I can to hang in there,&quot; Okada said.</p>
<p>Doohan, who took the provisional pole on Friday by clocking two minutes 12.908 seconds in the rain, said he was not so concerned about finishing second.</p>
<p>&quot;The pole would have been better...But my basic concern was to be on the front row,&quot; Doohan said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think tomorrow will be a close race of about six people...it will come down to the last five laps,&quot; Doohan said.</p>
<p>Japan's Tetsuya Harada clinched the pole position for the 250cc race, while Japans Noboru Ueda will start in front for the 125cc race.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SUZUKA, Japan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
