<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522486" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER SHOWCASE-UNITED CLOSE TO FOURTH TITLE IN FIVE YEARS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER SHOWCASE-UNITED CLOSE TO FOURTH TITLE IN FIVE YEARS.</headline>
<byline>Mike Collett</byline>
<dateline>LIVERPOOL, England 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Manchester United moved to within five points of the English premier league title and effectively ended Liverpol's challenge when they deservedly beat their arch-rivals 3-1 at Anfield on Saturday.</p>
<p>The clash between the top two teams in the table before the start of play saw United dominate a Liverpool side who defended abysmally and were undermined by another woeful display from out-of-form goalkeeper David James, who gifted United their third goal which made the game safe for the defending champions.</p>
<p>All four goals came from headers with Gary Pallister scoring twice for United and Andy Cole adding the other. John Barnes briefly gave Liverpool some hope with a rare header which cancelled out Pallister's opener.</p>
<p>The victory moved United to 69 points with four matches remaining. Liverpool have 64 points with three matches to play, as do Arsenal, who were surprisingly held to a 1-1 home draw against Blackburn.</p>
<p>Despite the comprehensive nature of the victory, United manager Alex Ferguson was taking nothing for granted afterwards.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a massive result for us, very big win, a very important victory. Although we have three home matches left, we still have a lot to do.</p>
<p>&quot;To be champions you have to come here where they know a lot about title-winning sides and do well. I think if we win the title we will deserve it, but nothing is settled yet.&quot;</p>
<p>Pallister, who set United on the way to victory with the opening goal after 13 minutes, then scored again to put them 2-1 up three minutes before the break and was delighted with the result.</p>
<p>&quot;That's the first time I have ever scored two goals in a match,&quot; he said, &quot;and it was the perfect time to do it.&quot;</p>
<p>Liverpool manager Roy Evans said: &quot;We won't throw the towel in and say it's all over, but it's a very tall order for us now. We still have to be positive and get our heads up because second place is very important for the (European Cup) Champions' League next season. But we are desperately disappointed.&quot;</p>
<p>Former Liverpool captain Emlyn Hughes, who captained the club to championship and European Cup success in the 1970s, did not mince his words.</p>
<p>&quot;That's it for Liverpool, they can't win the title now,&quot; he said. &quot;They had to win this one to stand any chance and that chance has gone now.&quot;</p>
<p>United, who had won only once in the league at Anfield in the last nine seasons, were put on the way to their biggest away victory over Liverpool since 1969 when Pallister, unmarked at a David Beckham corner, powerfully headed home from close range.</p>
<p>Barnes equalised in the 19th minute when he directed his header from a Stig Inge Bjornebye corner wide of Peter Schmeichel. The Danish goalkeeper got his hand to the ball but could not stop it going in.</p>
<p>Pallister restored United's lead with another header from a corner after he had been left unmarked again. His goal came just seconds after James had made his best save of the match from Ronnie Johnsen, who also had a clear header from a corner.</p>
<p>James, who nervously came for balls when he should have remained on his line, and stayed when he should have come out, gifted United their third in the 63rd minute.</p>
<p>He completely missed a cross from Gary Neville, leaving Cole to direct an unchallenged header into the empty net to make it 3-1.</p>
<p>Eric Cantona and Cole twice -- once in the last minute when he had a great chance to make it 4-1 -- went close to increasing the victory margin.</p>
<p>United will meet Borussia Dortmund in the second leg of the European Cup semifinal at Old Trafford on Wednesday in a far happier frame of mind than Liverpool will be when they play Paris St Germain in the return of their Cup Winners' Cup semifinal at Anfield on Thursday.</p>
<p>Both sides are going into those games behind on aggregate, but while United look to have a fair chance of overturning their 1-0 first-leg deficit, Liverpool will have to show a huge improvement to overturn their 3-0 first-leg loss.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIVERPOOL, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
