<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522483" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SNOOKER-HENDRY MAKES GOOD START TO DEFENCE.</title>
<headline>SNOOKER-HENDRY MAKES GOOD START TO DEFENCE.</headline>
<dateline>SHEFFIELD, England 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stephen Hendry made a successful start to what many have predicted would be a difficult defence of his world snooker title on Saturday with a 10-6 victory over Englishman Andy Hicks.</p>
<p>The Scottish champion and top seed, bidding for a record seventh title, led 6-3 after the morning session against the 1995 semifinalist and was never threatened in the evening.</p>
<p>He got to the brink of victory at 9-4 before Hicks resisted briefly by winning two frames before Hendry sewed it up.</p>
<p>Hicks, unseeded this year, was swamped in the first three frames which he lost 73-48, 85-0 and 90-43 before taking the fourth with a break of 74. But the holder took the next two with a breaks of 82 in the fifth and good safety play in the sixth.</p>
<p>Hicks reminded the six-times champion of his fighting qualities by taking the next two frames to make it 5-3, but Hendry had the last word as a 69 break earned him the final frame of the session.</p>
<p>Welshman Mark Williams, who dealt Hendry his worst-ever defeat in a final when he whipped him 9-2 in the British Open two weeks ago, moved some way towards a repeat meeting with the champion in the next round.</p>
<p>He led veteran and former champion Terry Griffiths 5-4.</p>
<p>Peter Ebdon of England, the third seed, made a bad start against compatriot Stefan Mazrocis, a qualifier, and trailed 6-2.</p>
<p>Englishman Dave Harold, ranked 11th, trailed 5-4 to Welsh newcomer Lee Walker after falling behind 4-1 early in their match.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHEFFIELD, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
