<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522490" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: SOCCER-BAYERN EXTEND LEAD AFTER DRAW WITH DORTMUND.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BAYERN EXTEND LEAD AFTER DRAW WITH DORTMUND.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gray</byline>
<dateline>DORTMUND, Germany 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bayern Munich and Borussia Dortmund fought out a 1-1 draw on Saturday in a highly charged game which saw Bayern extend their lead at the top of the Bundesliga to six points.</p>
<p>Dortmund, who face Manchester United in the second leg of their European Cup semifinal on Wednesday, took the lead in the second minute. Karlheinz Riedle headed home a perfectly weighted free kick from Andy Moeller.</p>
<p>But Bayern struck back just a minute later. Alexander Zickler shrugged off a challenge from Martin Kree to break down the right and sent in a cross which Ruggiero Rizzitelli headed past Stefan Klos.</p>
<p>After an evenly-balanced first half, Dortmund piled on the pressure in the second in a desperate attempt to cut Bayern's lead at the top of the table and increase their own chances of winning a third consecutive Bundesliga title.</p>
<p>&quot;We had a bit of luck,&quot; acknowledged Bayern coach Giovanni Trapattoni. &quot;We didn't quite show enough initiative but we've acheived a success, if not a victory.&quot;</p>
<p>The draw moved Dortmund into second, ahead of both Bayer Leverkusen and Stuttgart who face each other on Sunday. A win for Leverkusen would cut Bayern's lead to three points.</p>
<p>Dortmund coach Ottmar Hitzfeld, deprived of libero Matthias Sammer and defender Stefan Reuter who failed fitness tests, was disappointed his side could not take three points from Bayern but insisted they could still win the title.</p>
<p>&quot;The goal gave us a great advantage which we just gave away a minute later,&quot; he said. &quot;But we're convinced we'll still get our chance to be champions.&quot;</p>
<p>Hitzfeld said Sammer was struggling with a groin injury and was also doubtful for Wednesday's clash in Manchester. The European Player of the Year missed Dortmund's 1-0 win in the first leg due to suspension.</p>
<p>Schalke, Germany's other remaining representatives in European competition, suffered a blow in the build-up to Tuesday's UEFA Cup semifinal second leg with Tenerife. The Gelsenkirchen side lost 1-0 away to struggling Hamburg.</p>
<p>Promoted Bochum increased their chances of taking part in next season's UEFA Cup, defending their fifth place with a fine 1-0 win away to 1960 Munich.</p>
<p>The tense nature of the Dortmund game, billed as a title decider which the home side could not afford to lose, was evident as early as the first few minutes when German internationals Moeller and Mario Basler almost came to blows.</p>
<p>Both players were shown the yellow card and a further four were booked in the course of the match.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a game characterised by battles with lots of drama.&quot; said Hitzfeld, who had four strikers on the field for much of the second half. &quot;We really wanted to win and we risked a lot.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DORTMUND, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
