<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522488" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-BOKSIC BRINGS SMILES BACK TO JUVENTUS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BOKSIC BRINGS SMILES BACK TO JUVENTUS.</headline>
<byline>Alan Baldwin</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A first-half goal from Croat striker Alen Boksic gave Juventus a precious 1-0 win at Bologna on Saturday and temporarily restored the league leaders' six-point cushion at the top of serie A.</p>
<p>Italy coach Cesare Maldini was in the stands to watch Boksic, a disappointment for much of the first half, score his 41st minute goal with a diagonal shot at the far post after weaving past three Bologna defenders.</p>
<p>That put the European Cup holders on 55 points, ahead of second-placed Parma on 49.</p>
<p>The goal also restored shaken confidence after a 3-0 thrashing by a 10-man Udinese at home last weekend.</p>
<p>And it brought back the smiles ahead of the holders' European Cup semifinal second leg in Turin on Wednesday against Ajax, the team they beat on penalties in last year's final.</p>
<p>It also delighted the money men, with a crowd of around 38,000 spectators and record takings at the gate of 1.8 billion lire ($1.1 million).</p>
<p>Parma, who now have the pressure on them to win, have a tricky home match against Udinese on Sunday with third-placed Inter snapping at their heels.</p>
<p>Inter, who play a UEFA Cup semifinal second leg against Monaco in France on Tuesday, made clear that the battle for the coveted second place spot that brings a place in the European Cup next season was far from over.</p>
<p>They moved to within one point of Parma after beating Cagliari 2-1 in Sardinia but coach Roy Hodgson was far from happy, saying they had lost concentration at the end as has happened so often this season.</p>
<p>&quot;In the last 20 minutes we played badly. Another five minutes and we would have conceded the equaliser,&quot; the Englishman said.</p>
<p>Inter were without French international striker Youri Djorkaeff who remained in Milan where his three-year-old son is in hospital with a chest complaint.</p>
<p>Chile's Ivan Zamorano and England midfielder Paul Ince supplied the goals for Inter either side of half time.</p>
<p>Ince set Zamorano up for the first in the 42nd minute and the Chilean repaid the compliment in the 50th.</p>
<p>Cagliari's Sandro Tovalieri pulled a goal back in the 79th for his 10th of the season but the result left the Sardinians in deeper danger of relegation than ever.</p>
<p>&quot;What can I say,&quot; said Parma coach Carlo Ancelotti after the matches. &quot;I take note. But it would have been the same for us whoever had won in Bologna...we have to beat Udinese.</p>
<p>&quot;And that won't be easy...the fact remains that a team that can beat Juventus 3-0 in Turin with 10 men has to be going through an excellent run of form,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A total of three fixtures were brought forward a day due to European club commitments next week and all three hopefuls, who all have good chances of reaching the finals, won.</p>
<p>Fiorentina, who host Barcelona in a Cup Winners' Cup semifinal second leg on Thursday, beat Roma 2-1 in a mid-table clash thanks to two first-half goals.</p>
<p>Anselmo Robbiati scored Fiorentina's first in the seventh minute and Fiorentina then went 2-0 up thanks to an own-goal deflected in by Roma defender Fabio Petruzzi.</p>
<p>Argentine striker Abel Balbo scored a consolation goal for the visitors in the 76th minute.</p>
<p>The defeat was the third in succession and second since 74-year-old Swedish coach Nils Liedholm, who took Roma to their only postwar title in 1982-83, was drafted in to help the club after Argentine coach Carlos Bianchi was fired.</p>
<p>Roma were beaten 1-0 by Parma last weekend.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
