<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522481" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: GOLF-PRICE TAKES TWO-SHOT LEAD INTO FINAL ROUND AT HERITAGE.</title>
<headline>GOLF-PRICE TAKES TWO-SHOT LEAD INTO FINAL ROUND AT HERITAGE.</headline>
<dateline>HILTON HEAD ISLAND, South Carolina 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nick Price moved closer to his first PGA Tour victory in three</p>
<p>years by taking a two-stroke lead after three rounds at the</p>
<p>$1.5 million Heritage Classic  Saturday.</p>
<p>Price birdied the final hole in a stiff breeze whipping</p>
<p>off Calibogue Sound to card a respectable two-under-par 69 on</p>
<p>the tight Harbour Town course.</p>
<p>The Zimbabwean posted a 10-under 203 total with one round</p>
<p>left. American Brad Faxon (70) was second at 205, British Open</p>
<p>champion Tom Lehman (67) was three shots back, while</p>
<p>eight-time major winner Tom Watson (70) joined Lennie Clements</p>
<p>(73) five shots off the pace.</p>
<p>&quot;I hit the ball very solidly all day,&quot; said Price. &quot;The</p>
<p>wind switched today, which made it a little tougher to read. I</p>
<p>made a couple of mistakes through wrong club selection or</p>
<p>misreading the wind.</p>
<p>&quot;The dropped shots I'm making are coming from mental</p>
<p>mistakes, not physical mistakes. When I did make a mistake I</p>
<p>chipped well or holed a putt. It was a very positive day for</p>
<p>me. There's nothing better than playing well under pressure.</p>
<p>That's the ultimate kick.&quot;</p>
<p>Price, winner of three major titles, has not trimphed on</p>
<p>the PGA Tour since the Canadian Open in September, 1994, but</p>
<p>he has won five times in Africa since then, including twice</p>
<p>against good fields at the Dimension Data Pro-Am and South</p>
<p>African PGA Championship in South Africa in February.</p>
<p>&quot;The win I had at Sun City was very satisfying, because I</p>
<p>kept going away from the field,&quot; Price said. &quot;There was no</p>
<p>slacking off. It's nice when you haven't won in 14 months to</p>
<p>win going away.&quot;</p>
<p>Price, 39, was ranked number one in the world at the end</p>
<p>of 1994, but he dropped out of the top dozen late last year</p>
<p>before climbing back to his current ranking of ninth.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't hit a lot of good iron shots into the greens,&quot;</p>
<p>Faxon said, &quot;but I did a great job putting and scrambling for</p>
<p>pars.&quot;</p>
<p>Faxon, who won in New Orleans two weeks ago, said he is</p>
<p>&quot;really psyched about playing with Nick. The last round we</p>
<p>played together was the third round at Turnberry at the</p>
<p>British Open when he won (in 1994). We both played great that</p>
<p>day.&quot;</p>
<p>Third-placed Lehman said: &quot;I feel more focused than I have</p>
<p>been for a while. There have been times this year where I have</p>
<p>hit a shot and I wasn't even thinking about that shot. This</p>
<p>week I have been more tuned in.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HILTON HEAD ISLAND, South Carolina"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
