<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522489" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: ATHLETICS-PEREZ AND STANKINA TAKE WORLD CUP TITLES.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-PEREZ AND STANKINA TAKE WORLD CUP TITLES.</headline>
<dateline>PODEBRADY, Czech Republic 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ecuador's Olympic 20 km walk champion Jefferson Perez added to his gold medal collection by winning the World Cup over the same distance on Saturday.</p>
<p>Perez moved away from the rest of the seven-man group who entered the final two-km lap together to win in a national record one hour 18 minutes 24 seconds and take the $20,000 first prize.</p>
<p>China's Mingjun Tan and Mexico's Bernardo Segura crossed the line in second and third place but were both disqualified.</p>
<p>Mexico's Daniel Garcia and Russia's Ilya Markov were eventually presented with the silver and bronze medals, clocking 1:18:27 and 1:18:30 respectively.</p>
<p>Russia took the men's 20 km team title with Belarus second and Mexico third.</p>
<p>Russian Olympiada Ivanova set off at world record pace in the women's 10 km event but began to tire after the halfway mark.</p>
<p>She was overtaken by her compatriot Irina Stankina at 7,500 metres and the reigning world champion strode away to win in 41 minutes 52 seconds.</p>
<p>Ivanova hung on for second in 41:59 with China's Gu Yan third in 42:15.</p>
<p>Russia took the women's team gold medals with Italy second and China third.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PODEBRADY, Czech Republic"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
