<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522570" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: SWIMMING-WORLD RECORD SPREE AT SHORT-COURSE MEET.</title>
<headline>SWIMMING-WORLD RECORD SPREE AT SHORT-COURSE MEET.</headline>
<byline>Derek Parr</byline>
<dateline>GOTHENBURG, Sweden 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Americans Misty Hyman and Jenny Thompson each set a world record in the same race and Claudia Poll romped to her second world mark in 24 hours at the world short-course swimming championships on Saturday.</p>
<p>China made it four world records on an exciting night in the 25-metre custom-built tank in the Scandinavium indoor arena, beating their own women's 4x100 metres freestyle relay mark.</p>
<p>Hyman won the opening skirmish in the women's 100 metres butterfly, turning at the 50-metre mark in 26.55 seconds to slice 0.01 seconds from the world short-course record set by Australia's Angela Kennedy in Sheffield, England, on February 12, 1995.</p>
<p>But Thompson won the battle and claimed the 100 butterfly world mark and the title in 57.79 as the three medallists all swam inside the old standard.</p>
<p>Poll obliterated an East German record which had stood for 10 years with an immense performance in the women's 400 metres freestyle.</p>
<p>The imposing Costa Rican left her rivals for dead, winning by nearly six seconds in four minutes 0.03 seconds and consigning the 4:02.05 set by Astrid Strauss in Bonn on February 9, 1987, to world record history.</p>
<p>&quot;Great,&quot; said Poll, amazed to have come so close to breaking the four-minute barrier and slicing more than two seconds off the old mark. &quot;I knew I could go under 4:05. We had planned to break the record, but never 4:00.&quot;</p>
<p>Poll, who lowered her own 200 freestyle world mark by more than a second on Friday, matched the golden double she achieved at the last world short-course championships in Rio de Janeiro in 1995.</p>
<p>Thompson also claimed a title double and embellished it with her world record in the women's 100 metres butterfly.</p>
<p>All eyes were on fellow American Hyman and the stunning submarine style in which she turns on her side after the dive and swims almost all the first length of the 25-metre pool under water.</p>
<p>Hyman led for most of the race, much of it spent below the surface, and earned herself the 50-metre world record. But Thompson's more traditional style stole the day and Hyman had to settle for her third bronze of the championships.</p>
<p>Thompson (57.79), silver medallist Cai Huijue of China (57.92) and Hyman (57.95) all bettered the 58.24 world short-course mark set by Japan's Ayari Aoyama in Tokyo on March 28.</p>
<p>&quot;I was really fired up before the race. I felt really good this morning and knew that I could go faster tonight,&quot; said Thompson, who had already won gold in the 100 freestyle and silver in the 50 freestyle.</p>
<p>China brought the evening to a superb climax, prevailing in a thrilling duel with Germany as both went under the old world mark in the women's 4x100 metres freestyle relay.</p>
<p>Le Jingyi, Chao Na, Shan Ying and Nian Yin clocked 3:34.55 and the German quartet 3:34.69 to improve on the 3:35.97 set by China at the inaugural world short-course championships in Palma de Mallorca on December 4, 1993.</p>
<p>Le's lead-off leg of 53.32 would have given her the gold ahead of Thompson in Thursday's individual event and Nian's gutsy riposte after Sandra Voelker had edged Germany in front midway through the anchor leg sealed a famous victory.</p>
<p>Kristy Ellem emulated training partner Samantha Riley's 1995 breaststroke double by adding the 100 crown to the 200 she gathered on Friday.</p>
<p>But, like every Saturday winner except Poll, she endured a close-run contest in contrast to her runaway victory on Friday.</p>
<p>Victory over Poland's Alicja Penzak by just 0.06 seconds enabled Ellem to bag Australia's seventh gold and maintained the team's lead in the medals table with one day of the four-day championships to come. A mere 0.14 seconds separated the top four.</p>
<p>Venezuela's Francisco Sanchez, 50 freestyle winner in 1995, captured the 100 freestyle title in 47.86.</p>
<p>Olympic medallist Gustavo Borges had to settle for his third successive silver in the event in 48.16, while fellow Brazilian Fernando Scherer, winner of the two previous editions, failed to make the final.</p>
<p>Alexander Goukov of Belarus squeezed out the evening's narrowest victory in the men's 200 breaststroke, overhauling Russia's Andrei Korneev at the last gasp to beat the Olympic bronze medallist by 0.03 seconds in 2:09.25.</p>
<p>Britain's James Hickman finished with similar panache to beat Ukrainian Denis Silantiev and Australian defending champion Scott Goodman and take the men's 200 butterfly gold in 1:55.55.</p>
<p>They all profited from a lacklustre Gothenburg showing by Russia's double Olympic champion Denis Pankratov, who failed to make the finals of both the 100 and 200 events.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GOTHENBURG, Sweden"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
