<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522538" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: RUGBY UNION-AUCKLAND RUN RIOT AGAINST GAUTENG.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-AUCKLAND RUN RIOT AGAINST GAUTENG.</headline>
<dateline>AUCKLAND 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Auckland Blues ended the Gauteng Lions' two-year dominance over them with a resounding 63-22 win against the South Africans in a Super 12 rugby game on a wet Eden Park on Saturday.</p>
<p>The Blues started slowly but once they settled they were irresistible in a 10-tries-to-three victory to atone for their failure to beat Gauteng in their previous two encounters.</p>
<p>Auckland are unbeaten in the competition and retake the lead briefly taken by the ACT Brumbies on Friday.</p>
<p>Gauteng stunned the Super 12 champions with a fierce start which earned them two tries in the first 15 minutes, the first to flanker Warren Brosnahan and the second to an intercept by halfback Johan Roux.</p>
<p>Between the two, the Blues set up two quick rucks for halfback Ofisa Tonu'u to dart under the crossbar for a try which Carlos Spencer converted.</p>
<p>Roux converted his the try and then kicked a penalty from 23 metres to take Gauteng out to a 15-7 lead.</p>
<p>Auckland stormed back, first from a pushover try in the 21st minute to Zinzan Brooke which was converted by Spencer to narrow the gap to 14-15, and then from a series of rucks inside the Lions 22 where Brooke again ploughed over for a converted try.</p>
<p>Disaster struck Gauteng in the 32nd minute captain Kobus Wiese landed heavily and appeared to suffer a neck injury when attempting to tackle Lee Stensness.</p>
<p>Play was halted for seven minutes as a neckbrace was applied on Wiese, who was carried from the field on a stretcher.</p>
<p>Spencer goaled a penalty when play restarted before Auckland sent young lock Leo Lafaiali'i scampering over for his side's fourth try, which secured the bonus point before the halftime break.</p>
<p>Leading 29-15 at halftime, Auckland needed just three minutes in the second spell before adding to their tally when Brooke sent Tonu'u over for his second try of the game from a five metre scrum to make.</p>
<p>From there on, Auckland's superior speed told.</p>
<p>Tries by Joeli Vidiri, Spencer, replacement Dylan Mika, who came on for Lafaiali'i, flanker Michael Jones and finally replacement winger Jeremy Stanley all added to the Lions' humiliation.</p>
<p>Teams -</p>
<p>Auckland Blues: 15-Shane Howarth, 14-Joeli Vidiri, 13-Eroni Clarke, 12-Lee Stensness, 11-Brian Lima (Jeremy Stanley), 10-Carlos Spencer, 9-Ofisa Tonu'u, 8-Zinzan Brooke (captain), 7-Mark Carter, 6-Michael Jones, 5-Jim Coe, 4-Leo Lafaiali'i (Dylan Mika), 3-Craig Dowd, 2-Sean Fitzpatrick,1-Paul Thomson.</p>
<p>Gauteng Lions: 15-Dawie du Toit, 14-Jannie van der Walt, 13-Japie Mulder, 12-Riaan van Jarsveld, 11-James Moss, 10-Hennie Le Roux, 9-Johan Roux, 8-Andre Vos, 7-Ian MacDonald, 6-Warren Brosnihan, 5-Hannes Strydom, 4-Kobus Wiese, 3-Kapstock van Greuning, 2-Chris Roussouw, 1-Balie Swart.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AUCKLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
