<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522596" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: TENNIS-COSTA BEATS MOYA TO TAKE BARCELONA OPEN FINAL PLACE.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-COSTA BEATS MOYA TO TAKE BARCELONA OPEN FINAL PLACE.</headline>
<byline>Richard Bastin</byline>
<dateline>BARCELONA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albert Costa celebrated his imminent arrival in the world's top 10 of tennis with a straight-sets victory over Carlos Moya on Saturday which earned him a place in the final of the Barcelona Open.</p>
<p>Costa's impressive 7-6 (8-6) 7-5 victory over the only other top-ranked Spaniard came the day after he had guaranteed himself a place in the top 10 in next week's revised rankings.</p>
<p>Costa could yet overtake Moya if he earns extra bonus points by winning the final against Alberto Berasategui, who was playing Albert Portas, also of Spain, in the other semi final later in the day.</p>
<p>&quot;It's difficult to play with a friend. We know each other so well, that at times you make mistakes trying to trick him,&quot; said Costa after a match in which 11 games had gone against serve.</p>
<p>The match was delayed half an hour by rain, and as the wet conditions dampened the sting of Moya's serve, both players tried to break up each other's baseline game with drop shots.</p>
<p>&quot;Normally he serves well, perhaps it's because we know each other that there were so many breaks,&quot; said Costa. &quot;It was a bit of a strange match.&quot;</p>
<p>The match turned on the first-set tie-break, in which Australian Open finalist Moya looked unusually nervous.</p>
<p>Moya was able to force his way back from 2-5 down, but Costa held his nerve to take the tie-break 8-6 after double-faulting on his first set-point.</p>
<p>Costa kept the upper hand in the second set, despite allowing Moya to break back twice.</p>
<p>Costa lost a third chance to break after seeing a drop shot clip the top of the net and bounce back into his court with Moya left for dead.</p>
<p>The point brought shouts of appreciation from a crowd eager to see the hotly-contested clash go into a third set.</p>
<p>But their hopes were dashed when Costa took advantage of a poor service game by Moya, who acknowledged he was a 'bit sad' after the game.</p>
<p>&quot;I really hoped to play a final here, which is practically my home,&quot; said Moya &quot;But I'm 20 and I have an opportunity in the future.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BARCELONA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
