<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522555" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: ATHLETICS-DEFENDERS FACE TOUGH TASK IN 101ST BOSTON MARATHON.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-DEFENDERS FACE TOUGH TASK IN 101ST BOSTON MARATHON.</headline>
<byline>Michael Ellis</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The venerable Boston Marathon begins its second century on Monday with defending champions Moses Tanui of Kenya and Germany's Uta Pippig, who is seeking a record fourth consecutive victory, facing stiff competition in their quests to repeat.</p>
<p>Tanui, 31, who thwarted compatriot Cosmas Ndeti's attempt at a fourth successive victory last year, leads a  strong entry of Kenyans in the 101st running of the world's oldest continuing marathon.</p>
<p>The Kenyans, who have dominated Boston for the last six years, will be challenged by a pair of elite Mexican distance runners this time around.</p>
<p>German Silva, 28, a two-time winner of the New York City Marathon, and 31-year-old Dionicio Ceron, a three-time winner in London, will each be making his Boston debut Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;This race, this year, is more than the Olympics because all the top runners from the world are here,&quot; Tanui told reporters. &quot;Here we have everybody.&quot;</p>
<p>The introspective Tanui said he will simply, &quot;try my best to do my best.&quot;</p>
<p>The much more vocal Ndeti, who focuses on Boston like no other race and even named his son after the city following his course record-setting victory in 1994, seems sure he can return to the winner's circle.</p>
<p>&quot;I am still confident. God can still renew my strength and I can still win,&quot; Ndeti said.</p>
<p>Pippig, whose leg injuries kept her from finishing the Olympic marathon in Atlanta and derailed her training for five months, said she is in good health now but still considers herself an underdog this year.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not too much pressure for me because I'm not the top favourite, and for me it gives me more space and it gives me maybe more energy for the race,&quot; said Pippig, whose winning smiles and blown kisses to fans have made her a crowd favourite in Boston.</p>
<p>South African Elana Meyer, who broke Pippig's record for a half-marathon this year and has placed third and second in Boston the past two years, feels she is ready to overtake the German -- a breakthrough worth $75,000 to the winner.</p>
<p>&quot;It may be third time lucky,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The strong women's field also includes Ethiopian Olympic champion Fatuma Roba and top Japanese marathoner Junko Asari, each making her Boston debut.</p>
<p>Asari won the the 1995 Tokyo Women's International and the 1993 Osaka Ladies International Marathons.</p>
<p>Roba said through an interpreter that she had been running hills in preparation for the infamous stretch of the Boston race known as &quot;heartbreak hill.&quot;</p>
<p>But Greg Meyer, the last American to win the men's division in Boston in 1983, said it is difficult to prepare for heartbreak hill, which comes at around the 20-mile (32-km) mark, without have experienced it first hand.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the first timer here is at a definite disadvantage,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
