<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522548" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NHL ICE HOCKEY-ROY'S SHUTOUT STREAK ENDS BUT COLORADO WINS AGAIN.</title>
<headline>NHL ICE HOCKEY-ROY'S SHUTOUT STREAK ENDS BUT COLORADO WINS AGAIN.</headline>
<dateline>DENVER 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Patrick Roy's remarkable post-season shutout streak finally came to an end but he tied the NHL record for career playoff victories as the Colorado Avalanche beat the Chicago Blackhawks 3-1 on Friday.</p>
<p>Mike Keane and Sandis Ozolinsh scored 73 seconds apart in the first period to give the defending Stanley Cup champions a two games to none lead in the best-of-seven first-round Western Conference playoff series.</p>
<p>Roy made 24 saves for his 88th career post-season win, tying him with former New York Islander Billy Smith.</p>
<p>Roy fell about 18 minutes short of the longest shutout streak in playoff history. Roy took a shutout streak of 213 minutes and 11 seconds -- dating back to last year's Stanley Cup Finals -- into Friday's game.</p>
<p>The streak ended at 231 minutes and four seconds when James Black took a pass from Jeff Shantz and flipped a wrist shot into the open side of the Colorado goal at 17:53 of the first period. The longest shutout sequence in playoff history is 248 minutes, 32 seconds by Detroit's Norm Smith in 1936.</p>
<p>&quot;I played with Patrick (Roy) in Montreal and he is one tough goalie in the playoffs,&quot; said Chicago defenceman Chris Chelios.</p>
<p>Claude Lemieux, who has won Stanley Cups with three different teams, restored the two-goal Avalanche lead by beating Jeff Hackett at 7:30 of the second period.</p>
<p>&quot;We came out hard and set the tone early and that was the key,&quot; said Lemieux.</p>
<p>Hackett made 30 saves for the Blackhawks.</p>
<p>In Detroit, Red Wings fans breathed a sigh of relief when their team tied its series with the Blues at one-game each to avoid going to St Louis down 2-0.</p>
<p>Kris Draper and Larry Murphy scored in a 3:04 span of the third period as Detroit, which was shut out in Game One, posted a 2-1 victory over St Louis.</p>
<p>Draper had a short-handed goal for the Red Wings, who killed all seven St Louis power plays, including a 5-on-3 advantage for 76 seconds late in the third period.</p>
<p>Mike Vernon finished with 22 saves for Detroit.</p>
<p>&quot;We had to get this win. You can feel the pressure lift,&quot; said Detroit coach Scotty Bowman. &quot;This will be a long series, maybe seven games.&quot;</p>
<p>Marc Bergevin scored for St Louis just 4:24 into the game for a 1-0 lead that the Blues carried into the third period.</p>
<p>St Louis goalie Grant Fuhr blanked the Red Wings for the first 100 minutes of the series, but Detroit finally got to him with Draper's short-handed tally at 4:05 of the third.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there was elation and a lot of relief,&quot; Murphy said of Draper's goal. &quot;We said, 'Hey, we can actually score against this guy.'&quot;</p>
<p>The Red Wings took the lead at 7:09 of the third when Fuhr coughed up a rare rebound on a shot by Martin Lapointe and Murphy pounced on the puck and buried it in the St Louis net.</p>
<p>Fuhr finished with 31 saves for St. Louis.</p>
<p>&quot;Grant Fuhr was spectacular,&quot; Blues coach Joel Quenneville said. &quot;He shut them out for five periods, but we've got to score some goals ourselves.&quot;</p>
<p>In Dallas, Curtis Joseph stopped 25 shots for his third career post-season shutout as the Edmonton Oilers blanked the Stars 4-0 to even their series at one game apiece.</p>
<p>Mike Grier gave Joseph all the support he needed with a first-period powerplay goal, converting a perfect cross-slot pass from Doug Weight with 5:09 left.</p>
<p>Mariusz Czerkawski tallied in the second period and Ryan Smyth and Boris Mironov added third-period goals for Edmonton.</p>
<p>Joseph, whose nickname is Cujo, faced just two shots in the first period but had to make 14 saves in the second and nine in the third.</p>
<p>He was at his best early in the second period when Dallas had a 5-on-3 powerplay. &quot;Cujo came up huge when we were down on that 5-on-3,&quot; Oilers coach Ron Low said. &quot;I counted three huges saves that he had on the power play that kept them from getting any momentum.&quot;</p>
<p>The Oilers killed off all seven Dallas power plays.</p>
<p>&quot;Now we go home for two games with this as a confidence booster,&quot; said Weight, who also assisted on Mironov's powerplay goal. &quot;We can win this series.&quot;</p>
<p>In Anaheim, J.J. Daigneault scored twice, including the go-ahead goal with 6:24 remaining, as the Mighty Ducks beat the Phoenix Coyotes 4-2 to take a two games to none lead in their best-of-seven first-round series.</p>
<p>Daigneault put the Ducks ahead to stay when he skated around the back of the Phoenix net and scored on a wraparound while Coyotes' goalie Nikolai Khabibulin and his defencemen were busy watching the dangerous Teemu Selanne in front.</p>
<p>Selanne sealed the victory by scoring into an empty net with seven seconds remaining.</p>
<p>Daigneault's first goal at 7:03 of the second broke a 1-1 tie. Dmitri Mironov had the other goal for the Ducks, who have not lost in their last 16 home games.</p>
<p>Teppo Numminen, who gave Phoenix an early 1-0 lead and Keith Tkachuk, who led the league with 52 goals this season, tied it, 2-2 at 3:55 of the third period for the Coyotes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DENVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
