<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522502" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-WENGER SAYS ENGLISH TITLE RACE IS OVER.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-WENGER SAYS ENGLISH TITLE RACE IS OVER.</headline>
<byline>Gideon Long</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Arsene Wenger watching his Arsenal side concede a late equaliser at home to Blackburn on Saturday and then conceded the English title race was over.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Manchester United are champions tonight,&quot; the Frenchman told BBC Radio after Arsenal caved in with two minutes remaining at Highbury and had to settle for a 1-1 draw.</p>
<p>&quot;They are five points ahead with four matches left to play and I can't see how they can lose it.</p>
<p>&quot;They are the new champions of 1997 and I think they deserve it because I thought they were the best team... There's no chance for us now.&quot;</p>
<p>Arsenal's surprise setback capped a wonderful day for United, who virtually ended Liverpool's title hopes by beating them 3-1 at Anfield in a morning match.</p>
<p>Not only are United five points clear of both Liverpool and Arsenal, they have a match in hand on both sides and play three of their remaining four league fixtures at Old Trafford.</p>
<p>Alex Ferguson's side now turn their attentions to their European Cup semifinal second leg match against Borussia Dortmund at home on Wednesday, secure in the knowledge they are just five points away from their fourth league title in five years.</p>
<p>Not that Ferguson was taking anything for granted after his side's momentous victory on Merseyside.</p>
<p>&quot;Although we have three home matches left, we still have a lot to do,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;To be champions you have to come here where they know a lot about title-winning sides and do well. I think if we win the title we will deserve it, but nothing is settled yet.&quot;</p>
<p>That was before Arsenal's slip-up, and only the foolhardy would now bet against United clinching their 11th English championship.</p>
<p>Wenger's graciousness in praising Ferguson's side as the best in England could help heal a rift between the two over the end-of-season fixture backlog.</p>
<p>Wenger had derided as &quot;ridiculous&quot; Ferguson's appeal for an extension to the league season to allow United more time between matches.</p>
<p>Ferguson responded by saying Arsenal and Liverpool had conspired to deny United the extra time they had requested.</p>
<p>Attention in England will now centre on the all-important battle for the league runners-up spot which guarantees a place in the expanded European Champions' League next season.</p>
<p>Arsenal and Liverpool both have three matches left to play. Newcastle are four points behind them both but have a game in hand.</p>
<p>At the other end of the table anything could happen with just eight points separating the bottom eight clubs.</p>
<p>Coventry, who have mastered the art of escaping relegation during their 30 consecutive seasons in the top flight, fought back from 2-0 to steal a 2-2 draw at fellow strugglers Southampton.</p>
<p>&quot;A couple of weeks ago I thought the players were just living off the old Coventry reputation (for avoiding relegation)... and they needed a kick up the backside,&quot; player-manager Gordon Strachan said.</p>
<p>&quot;They needed to know that they have to play positively if they are to survive.</p>
<p>&quot;The previous managers have done a great job at keeping Coventry up for the last 30 years. We hope to be able to keep that up.&quot;</p>
<p>Sunderland manager Peter Reid was equally pleased after his side's 1-0 victory at neighbours Middlesbrough -- a result which keeps Bryan Robson's side anchored in the relegation zone.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel for Bryan because it was a massive game for both of us, but we desperately needed the three points,&quot; Reid said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
