<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522560" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: CURLING-CANADIAN RINK CLAIM RECORD THIRD TITLE.</title>
<headline>CURLING-CANADIAN RINK CLAIM RECORD THIRD TITLE.</headline>
<dateline>BERNE, Switzerland 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sandra Schmirler led Canada to an 8-4 win over Norway in the final of the world curling championships on Saturday to become the first women's rink to claim three titles.</p>
<p>Schmirler's Regina foursome, winner of back-to-back crowns in 1993 and 1994, broke open a tight contest in the fifth end scoring five to jump ahead 6-1.</p>
<p>Norway's Dordi Nordby, the only other woman to win back-to-back titles, began to chip away at the lead taking one in the sixth then stealing singles in the seventh and eighth to narrow the deficit to 6-3.</p>
<p>But that would be as close as the Norwegian rink would come, as Canada scored two in the ninth to clinch their fourth title in five years.</p>
<p>With the win Canada become the early gold medal favourite in Nagano where curling will have full medal status for the first time.</p>
<p>&quot;I've never been at an Olympics nobody has so I don't know what the pressure will be like,&quot; said Schmirler, who is five months pregnant and expecting her first child in August. &quot;I think we are very lucky. Whichever team goes I think Canadians have to be realistic.</p>
<p>&quot;Other countries know how to play this game and they're getting stronger and stronger.&quot;</p>
<p>In the bronze medal match Denmark beat Japan 7-6.</p>
<p>The men's final on Sunday will see Sweden take on Germany.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERNE, Switzerland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
