<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522594" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-JUVENTUS REGAIN SIX-POINT LEAD IN ITALY.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-JUVENTUS REGAIN SIX-POINT LEAD IN ITALY.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A first-half goal from Croat striker Alen Boksic gave Juventus a precious 1-0 win at Bologna on Saturday and temporarily restored the league leaders' six-point cushion at the top of serie A.</p>
<p>Boksic's 41st minute goal put the European Cup holders on 55 points, ahead of second-placed Parma on 49.</p>
<p>Parma have a tricky home match against Udinese, who beat Juventus 3-0 in Turin last weekend, on Sunday.</p>
<p>The match in Bologna was one of three league fixtures brought forward a day due to European club commitments next week and all three of the Italian hopes won.</p>
<p>Third-placed Inter, who play a UEFA Cup semifinal second leg against Monaco on Tuesday, moved to within one point of Parma after beating Cagliari 2-1 in Sardinia.</p>
<p>Chile's Ivan Zamorano and England midfielder Paul Ince supplied the goals for Inter either side of half time with Cagliari's Sandro Tovalieri pulling one back in the 79th.</p>
<p>Fiorentina, who host Barcelona in a Cup Winners' Cup semifinal second leg on Thursday, beat Roma 2-1 in a mid-table clash thanks to two first-half goals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
