<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522536" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RUGBY UNION-QUEENSLAND STUN NEW SOUTH WALES.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-QUEENSLAND STUN NEW SOUTH WALES.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Struggling Queensland upset the form book and badly dented New South Wales' semifinal hopes with a committed 26-16 win in the Super 12 competition on Saturday.</p>
<p>Queensland, who went into the game languishing at the bottom of the table with only one victory to their credit, scored three tries to one in a spirited encounter at the Sydney Football Stadium between Australia's two traditional provincial powers.</p>
<p>The visitors gave an inspired defensive display to silence a partisan home crowd of 30,106, New South Wales' highest attendance of the season.</p>
<p>Number eight Mark Connors and wingers Ben Tune and Damian Smith crossed the line as Queensland exploited a succession of errors by a hesitant New South Wales outfit.</p>
<p>The victory was even more remarkable given that Queensland were reduced to 13 men at one stage during the second half after flanker David Wilson and flyhalf Elton Flatley were sent to the sin bin for separate professional fouls.</p>
<p>New South Wales' failure to exploit their numerical advantage highlighted a indecision and lack of inventiveness in attack.</p>
<p>The defeat leaves them facing an uphill task to lift themselves out of mid-table and qualify for the Super 12 semifinals by finishing in the top four on the table. Three of their last four games are away from home.</p>
<p>With local reputations and pride at stake, the match was fiercely contested. Tempers flared on several occasions and several ugly clashes erupted between the players.</p>
<p>In the worst incident, Queensland prop Dan Crowley was penalised for throwing several punches at opposition flanker Michael Brial, who was forced to leave the field for several minutes for treatment.</p>
<p>Connors earlier exploited a lapse in concentration by the New South Wales forwards when he broke from back of the scrum close to the line to cross unchallenged for the opening try after 13 minutes.</p>
<p>Four minutes later, Tune brushed past a feeble tackle by fullback Matt Burke before sprinting 40 metres to dive over in the corner.</p>
<p>Smith, whose transfer request to join New South Wales was refused by Queensland before the start of the season, sealed the victory with a breakaway try against a tiring defence with 10 minutes remaining.</p>
<p>Queensland's resistance was finally broken in the last minute when referee Wayne Erickson awarded a penalty try against them for a succession of professional fouls as they defended their line against a fierce late onslaught.</p>
<p>Queensland second rower John Eales landed a conversion and three penalties, a kicking performance equalled by Burke for the home side.</p>
<p>&quot;We really prided ourselves on our defensive performance tonight. It was a big occasion for us,&quot; Queensland fullback and captain Tim Horan said.</p>
<p>Teams:</p>
<p>Queensland - Tim Horan (captain), Ben Tune, Daniel Herbert, Jason Little, Willie Carne, Elton Flatley, Brett Johnstone, Mark Connors, David Wilson, Toutai Kefu, Matt Cockbain, John Eales, Glen Panoho, Michael Foley, Dan Crowley.</p>
<p>New South Wales - Matthew Burke, Alistair Murdoch, Graeme Bond, Richard Tombs, David Campese, Scott Bowen, Sam Payne, Fili Finau, Stuart Pinkerton, Michael Brial, Sam Domoni, Tim Gavin (captain), Andrew Heath, Mark Bell, Richard Harry.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
