<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522556" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: SOCCER-U.S. TO FACE FORMER COACH IN WORLD CUP QUALIFIER.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-U.S. TO FACE FORMER COACH IN WORLD CUP QUALIFIER.</headline>
<dateline>PROVIDENCE, Rhode Island 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. national soccer team faces its former coach and a formidable challenge when the Americans host Mexico in a CONCACAF zone World Cup qualifier at Foxboro Stadium on Sunday.</p>
<p>The United States, which has struggled in its campaign to return to the World Cup finals, aims to bounce back from last month's disappointing 3-2 loss to Costa Rica, which left the two nations tied in the CONCACAF standings.</p>
<p>Unfortunately that task comes against the region's best team, a Mexico squad coming off last week's 6-0 drubbing of Jamaica.</p>
<p>Mexico is on form to qualify for its 12th World Cup next year in France, leading the group with seven points from three matches. The United States and Costa Rica have four points each, but Costa Rica has played one less match than the United States, which must finish at least third in the region to advance.</p>
<p>El Salvador, Canada and Jamaica round out the group with one point each.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a do-or-die match, but it's important for us to play well,&quot; said U.S. coach Steve Sampson before a training session at Brown University on Friday.</p>
<p>Former U.S. coach Bora Milutinovic, who now leads Mexico, was looking forward to resuming a relatively young rivalry.</p>
<p>&quot;The moment when you have a rivalry, it cannot be friendly,&quot; said Milutinovic, who guided the United States to the second round of the 1994 World Cup. &quot;In sport, rivalry is indispensable.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't want to be pretentious, but I think when we (U.S.) beat Mexico 2-0 in the CONCACAF Gold Cup in 1991, that's when this rivalry started. Now I am on the other side,&quot; Milutinovic said.</p>
<p>Previous meetings between the two nations have been characterised by extremely physical play.</p>
<p>&quot;My philosophy hasn't changed,&quot; said Sampson. &quot;We want to go forward, we want to play an attractive, attacking style and we want to score goals.</p>
<p>&quot;We also have to defend more diligently,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PROVIDENCE, Rhode Island"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
