<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522564" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-BERLUSCONI JUMPS TO DEFENCE OF SACCHI.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BERLUSCONI JUMPS TO DEFENCE OF SACCHI.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>AC Milan president Silvio Berlusconi came to the aid of coach Arrigo Sacchi on Saturday amid speculation that his days were numbered.</p>
<p>&quot;I have never kicked out anybody,&quot; Berlusconi said after visiting Turin's fire-damaged cathedral when asked by reporters whether he intended to fire the coach.</p>
<p>&quot;Do you think I could do it to a friend like Sacchi whom I admire and to whom I wish well?&quot;</p>
<p>Sacchi took over as Milan coach late last year after Uruguayan coach Oscar Washington Tabarez handed in his resignation. Tabarez had himself taken over at Milan from Fabio Capello, who moved to Spain's Real Madrid.</p>
<p>Sacchi was in charge at the start of Milan's glory years, helping them win the European Cup twice. Capello continued the work with another Cup and four league titles.</p>
<p>Milan, the reigning champions, are now 12th and Italian newspapers have increasingly speculated that Berlusconi wants to bring Capello back to Milan from Spain.</p>
<p>The coach, who is due to visit Italy early next week, said this week that he would not discuss his future plans until the middle of May at the earliest.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
