<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522563" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: SOCCER-LEAGUE LEADERS PSV PULL CLEAR OF FEYENOORD.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-LEAGUE LEADERS PSV PULL CLEAR OF FEYENOORD.</headline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>PSV Eindhoven pulled clear at the top of the Dutch first division on Saturday by hammering Graafschap Doetinchem 5-0 as Feyenoord dropped two precious points in a 4-4 draw against Fortuna Sittard.</p>
<p>The two main contenders for the championship had started the day level on points but with only five games to go PSV now have 65 points and Feyenoord 63 from 29 matches.</p>
<p>PSV rapidly asserted their authority over Graafschap with a three-goal blitz in the first 15 minutes.</p>
<p>Philip Cocu struck the opening goal in the first minute after connecting with a cross from Zeljko Petrovic.</p>
<p>Luc Nilis scored from the penalty spot after five minutes and 10 minutes later he curled a free kick around a wall of Graafschap defenders to claim his 17th goal of the season.</p>
<p>PSV eased back a gear after establishing their early lead but Jaap Stam popped up to head home a corner two minutes before halftime and after the break Wim Jonk converted another penalty.</p>
<p>Feyenoord came back from behind three times after Fortuna took a second minute lead through Michael Jeffrey.</p>
<p>Goalkeeper Arjan Van der Zwam saved a penalty from Feyenoord sweeper Ronald Koeman in the 55th minute but Koeman converted a second penalty nine minutes later to level the score at 3-3.</p>
<p>Pablo Sanchez put Feyenoord ahead for the first time with a well executed diagonal shot and a broken Fortuna appeared to be heading for defeat before before Fernando Ricksen headed home a late equaliser from a free kick.</p>
<p>Ajax Amsterdam scored a morale-boosting victory ahead of Wednesday's European Cup semi-final second leg against Juventus, whipping NEC Nijmegen 5-0 on Friday.</p>
<p>Coach Louis van Gaal could hot have hoped for a better dress rehearsal for the Juventus match following Ajax's 2-1 defeat in the first leg 10 days ago and a 2-0 defeat by PSV last weekend.</p>
<p>Van Gaal was upbeat, even though midfielder Winston Bogarde and Nigerian striker Tijani Babangida left the pitch injured. &quot;It was a fabulous result with superb goals,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bogarde scored twice with Dani, Ronald de Boer and Kiki Musampa also getting their names onto the score sheet.</p>
<p>Attacker Peter Hoekstra made a long-awaited comeback after sustaining a serious knee injury last September.</p>
<p>Despite the impressive victory Ajax remain fourth in the table, trailing the leaders PSV by 14 points with six matches left to play.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
