<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522578" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: SOCCER-GUINGAMP REACH FIRST FINAL.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-GUINGAMP REACH FIRST FINAL.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Small town side Guingamp stood on the threshold of their first major honour on Saturday when they reached the French Cup Final by beating Montpellier 2-0 after extra time.</p>
<p>Guingamp, who had never previously reached the French Cup semifinals, meet the winners of Sunday's other semifinal between Nice and second division Laval in the May 10 final in Paris.</p>
<p>Liberia striker Christopher Wreh broke the deadlock four minutes into the second period of extra time with a cheeky goal, his third of the competition.</p>
<p>Wreh slipped his marker to get behind the defence and turn a free kick from the left by midfielder Stephane Carnot past Montpellier's veteran former France goalkeeper Bruno Martini.</p>
<p>Man-of-the-match Carnot lobbed the ball over Martini from the right edge of the penalty area and into the top far corner of the net for the second goal in injury time.</p>
<p>Carnot also hit Martini's near post with a free kick from the left two minutes from the end of normal time.</p>
<p>Montpellier, looking to reach their third final this decade, came close to taking the lead in the 20th minute when veteran midfielder Franck Sauzee had his free kick tipped over the bar by Guingamp goalkeeper Angelo Hugues.</p>
<p>Early in the second half, Montpellier's 20-year-old Ivory Coast striker Ibrahim Bakayoko beat the advancing Hugues with a low shot from a tight angle on the left but watched the ball run across the front of an open goal.</p>
<p>Guingamp, who played in the UEFA Cup in only their second season in the first division after qualifying through the Intertoto Cup last summer, needed extra time for the third time in five rounds of the French Cup to go through.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
