<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522565" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: SWIMMING-THOMPSON FINDS LESS PRODUCES MORE.</title>
<headline>SWIMMING-THOMPSON FINDS LESS PRODUCES MORE.</headline>
<byline>Steve Weizman</byline>
<dateline>GOTHENBURG, Sweden 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jenny Thompson has found less produces more at the world short-course championships.</p>
<p>On Saturday the 24-year-old pre-med student upstaged fellow-American Misty Hyman with a world record of 57.79 seconds in the women's 100 metres butterfly.</p>
<p>Two days ago, Thompson won gold in the 100 metres freestyle followed on Friday by a silver in the 50 metres freestyle.</p>
<p>&quot;Since the Olympics I've been not having a normal, real tedious, workout schedule. I've been training a lot of the time just once a day, I don't really worry about practice too much,&quot; Thompson said.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm just having a lot of fun and my performance here shows that maybe I don't need to train that much.&quot;</p>
<p>Underwater exponent Hyman had been widely fancied in the 100 metres final.</p>
<p>She eventually finished third, but along with second-placed Cai Huijue, of China, bettered the previous mark of 58.24 seconds set in 1982 by Japan's Ayari Aoyama, another submarine swimmer.</p>
<p>Thompson, who does not use the style, says that she no longer finds it intimidating in competitors, but thinks that a rule limiting the underwater portion of backstroke races to 15 metres at a time should be extended to other strokes.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it used to make me uncomfortable a little bit because they get such a lead in the beginning, but I know that it hurts them in the end of the race, because the lactic acid buildup is a lot more,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;I've had good success swimming on top of the water, so I guess I'm just old school. I've started using a little bit of underwater, more than I had, but I don't think I'll ever do the sort of swimming that they do,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Of Saturday's triumph she said that the energy of more than 6,000 enthusiastic spectators gave her a boost, even though she knew that the mostly home crowd were cheering Sweden's Johanna Sjoberg.</p>
<p>&quot;I was really fired up before the race because the crowd was going crazy and I knew it was for the Swedish girl but I was trying to use that energy and pretend that they were cheering for me,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GOTHENBURG, Sweden"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
