<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522655" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgarians vote for reform in parliamentary poll.</title>
<headline>Bulgarians vote for reform in parliamentary poll.</headline>
<byline>Elisaveta Konstantinova</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgarians voted on Saturday in parliamentary elections expected to launch their Balkan country on the path of reform already travelled by many of their east European neighbours.</p>
<p>The Union of Democratic Forces (UDF) is expected to capitalise on the support it won from month-long protests which toppled the former Socialist government in February, and the main question is how big their parliamentary majority will be. &quot;I appeal to all Bulgarians to vote because we need as many votes as we can get,&quot; said UDF leader Ivan Kostov, voting in the mountain village of Dragalevtsi on the outskirts of Sofia.</p>
<p>An interim cabinet led by Sofia's UDF mayor Stefan Sofianski has run the country since February, sealing a deal with the International Monetary Fund and kicking off the reform process the new government must continue.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing that the government will do after the elections is introduce to parliament the package of laws required for the implementation of the reforms agreed with the IMF,&quot; said Kostov, who walked to the polling station with his wife Elena.</p>
<p>A restrictive fixed exchange rate regime is due to be introduced in June to instil monetary discipline and restore confidence in the national currency, which went into freefall at the beginning of the year while Bulgaria was without effective government.</p>
<p>The lev has now stabilised, but annual inflation was more than 2,000 percent in March and the overhaul of communist-era state firms will add to unemployment already at 14.5 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;I am equally disappointed with all politicians in Bulgaria but I am voting in the hope of putting an end to what is happening now. This misery cannot continue for ever,&quot; said accountant Mario Ivanov.</p>
<p>Salaries, typically $40 or $50 a month, have failed to keep up with soaring prices. Grain and petrol almost ran out last month before the interim government secured new supplies.</p>
<p>The interior minister has launched a high-profile campaign against organised crime, which has soared unchecked since the end of communist rule, helped by an inadequate legal system.</p>
<p>&quot;I am voting for a new Bulgaria, for a Bulgaria without crime, without corruption, and with clear rules for doing business,&quot; said architect Hristo Genchev in Sofia's middle-class Lozenets district.</p>
<p>After communist leader Todor Zhivkov was toppled in 1989, leading communists renamed their party Socialist and continued in government. The UDF won elections in 1991 but their government lost a no-confidence vote after only 11 months.</p>
<p>One elderly couple, Stoyan and Ivana Georgiev, said they had voted Socialist in the previous general election in 1994 but would not be backing the former communists this time round.</p>
<p>&quot;Then we thought they had changed, now we know we were wrong, but unfortunately the price we all paid for this mistake was very high,&quot; Ivana said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
