<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522676" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin on holiday complains about weather - Tass.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin on holiday complains about weather - Tass.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin is unhappy about the weather in the Black Sea resort of Sochi where he is taking a short holiday, Itar-Tass news agency said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;It is raining, the temperature has dropped to five degrees Celsius (41 degrees Fahrenheit). The president has spent the morning in his residence and has not even ventured out for a walk,&quot; Tass quoted a well-informed source as saying.</p>
<p>Yeltsin arrived in his favourite holiday resort on Friday after a three-day visit to Germany.</p>
<p>Tass said Yeltsin's stay in Sochi was not a proper holiday because he would continue to work on government papers and to meet officials. He will also briefly interrupt his rest to host Chinese President Jiang Zemin in Moscow next Tuesday.</p>
<p>Chief Kremlin doctor Sergei Mironov told Tass on Friday that the 66-year-old leader's rest was &quot;not linked to medical necessity&quot; and no special medical treatment was planned.</p>
<p>He would go on many walks and, weather permitting, swim, Mironov said. But he did not mention tennis, Yeltsin's favourite sport.</p>
<p>Yeltsin, who had major heart surgery in November and pneumonia in January, looked pale and tired after talks on Thursday with Chancellor Helmut Kohl, his personal friend and political ally, in the spa resort of Baden-Baden.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
