<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522611" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: CRICKET-MUSHTAQ DOUBLE BLOW CHECKS SRI LANKA.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-MUSHTAQ DOUBLE BLOW CHECKS SRI LANKA.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leg-spinner Mushtaq Ahmed struck a double blow for Pakistan by snapping up both Sri Lanka openers just before lunch on the first day of the first test at the R.Premadasa stadium on Saturday.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka were 63 for two at the interval, Sanath Jayasuriya and test debutant Russel Arnold having shared a first wicket partnership of 61 on a slow pitch after their captain Arjuna Ranatunga won the toss and decided to bat.</p>
<p>Jayasuriya lived dangerously while making 31 off 65 balls. He was dropped on four by Salim Malik at first slip, and departed eight minutes before lunch when he was bowled attempting to cut a Mushtaq leg-break.</p>
<p>Fellow left-hander Arnold, making his test debut at the age of 23, batted steadily for 24 in nearly two hours before he fell in the final over of the morning session.</p>
<p>Attempting an ambitious drive, Arnold played through the wrong line and was comprehensively bowled by Mushtaq. His 118-minute innings included a superb sweep for six over square leg off the wrist spinner.</p>
<p>Arnold replaced regular opener Roshan Mahanama, who failed a fitness test on his injured left toe just before the start.</p>
<p>Marvan Atapattu and Aravinda de Silva negotiated the remaining balls from Mushtaq before lunch.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
