<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522684" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: US, Colombia seek extradition of accused drug lord.</title>
<headline>US, Colombia seek extradition of accused drug lord.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombia added its voice on Saturday to calls by the United States for the extradition of a reputed Colombian drug lord caught in Venezuela.</p>
<p>Justo Pastor Perafan, allegedly the wealthiest man in Colombia with a personal fortune estimated at $12 billion, was arrested in Venezuela near the Colombian border on Friday and flown to Caracas where he is currently being held.</p>
<p>&quot;We received Colombia's request this morning, and the United States' late yesterday,&quot; Venezuelan Foreign Minister Miguel Angel Burelli told Reuters in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>Burelli said U.S. ambassador to Venezuela John Maisto had formally filed a petition for Perafan's detention on Friday evening -- the first step towards an extradition. Perafan, who proclaims his innocence and says he has never set foot in the United States, is wanted on drugs charges in New York.</p>
<p>Colombia, meanwhile, has asked Venezuela to either deport or extradite Perafan. A Foreign Ministry release said Venezuela would decide in the next few days whether to proceed &quot;with extradition or deportation to the country where the individual is most guilty and has the longest standing claim.&quot;</p>
<p>Both petitions will be forwarded to the Supreme Court on Monday, Burelli said. The court will make the final decision.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't believe that this could lead to a conflict between Colombia and the United States,&quot; Burelli said. &quot;If we're all fighting for the same, why should there be a fight?&quot;</p>
<p>Perafan, 50, had been sought in Colombia for more than a year. After the arrest of the Rodgriguez Orejuela brothers and most other Cali drug Cartel leaders in 1995 and 1996, he was allegedly the top Colombian drug lord still at large.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
