<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522632" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Manitoba to raise dikes against Red River flooding.</title>
<headline>Manitoba to raise dikes against Red River flooding.</headline>
<dateline>WINNIPEG 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Manitoba's government was coordinating efforts Saturday to raise dikes around six towns facing the worst flood of the Red River forecast this century.</p>
<p>&quot;Natural Resources staff are currently working with the communities of St. Adolphe, St. Jean, Morris, Dominion City, Letellier and Emerson to raise ring dikes by as much as two feet to prevent against wave action from flood waters,&quot; Natural Resources Minister Glen Cummings said.</p>
<p>Some 100 Canadian Armed Forces troops were to aid in shoring up the dike around Richer, Manitoba Emergency Management Organization executive coordinator Harold Clayton told reporters.</p>
<p>Natural Resources revised its outlook Friday to say this flood would at least be one foot higher than the worst of the century and 800 square miles of farmland may be under water.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1979, 400 square miles were flooded and we may be looking at significantly greater than that, perhaps double,&quot; Manitoba Natural Resources director Larry Whitney said.</p>
<p>A higher than expected Red River flood level in Grand Forks, North Dakota, Friday forced the revision, he said.</p>
<p>Hundreds of people in East Grand Forks are being evacuated.</p>
<p>Seeding of Manitoba grains and oilseeds usually begins May 7 but 1996's April 20 crest delayed Red River seeding to May 29.</p>
<p>Manitoba Water Resources branch officials drilled holes in ice to speed up its breakup of the Red River and the Portage Diversion at the mouth of Lake Manitoba, Cummings said.</p>
<p>The technique worked in past weeks and Water Resources planned to do the same north of Winnipeg to prevent ice jams from holding back water and causing higher crests downstream.</p>
<p>Manitoba Agriculture worked closely with the Canadian Wheat Board to move grain out of the Red River Valley and assisted farmers in moving livestock to higher ground, Cummings said.</p>
<p>Manitoba Environment contacted firms in flood prone areas to secure or move pesticides, propane and gasoline.</p>
<p>Flood updates will be issued daily when flooding begins, he said.</p>
<p>((Gilbert Le Gras, Reuters Winnipeg bureau 204 947 3548))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WINNIPEG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
