<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522693" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>NICARAGUA: Nicaraguan ends four-day national strike.</title>
<headline>Nicaraguan ends four-day national strike.</headline>
<byline>David Koop</byline>
<dateline>MANAGUA 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sandinista leaders on Friday called off a four-day national strike that had disrupted traffic in Nicaragua after the government agreed to a national dialogue to heal the country's rifts.</p>
<p>After grueling four-hour negotiations between strike leaders, led by former Sandinista President Daniel Ortega, and President Arnoldo Aleman, accompanied by his top ministers, Ortega called on pro-Sandinista protesters to abandon the barricades they set up on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;We call on the thousands of Nicaraguans who are awaiting these results in the different territories, in the protest areas, to suspend the road blockages, to end the barricades, so that this negotiating process can begin,&quot; Ortega told a news conference.</p>
<p>The strike against Aleman's right-wing government had interrupted traffic flow in Nicaragua, especially on rural highways, and had led to fears of shortages in Managua if the strike continued for much longer.</p>
<p>Business leaders had repeatedly warned that a return of barricades and burning tires to Nicaragua's streets just when it was trying to sell itself as a politically stable country after civil wars, would scare away investors.</p>
<p>&quot;These conversations have contributed to the easing of tensions and the return to normality in the life of the country starting today,&quot; Aleman said.</p>
<p>To get Ortega to call off the strike, Aleman agreed to a national dialogue, starting on Monday, offering to create working groups with Sandinista and government members to negotiate a solution to Nicaragua's many problems.</p>
<p>The parties agreed to negotiate labour stability for Nicaragua, addressing the Sandinistas' fear of mass layoffs of civil servants under Aleman's austerity programme.</p>
<p>They also agreed to hammer out a definitive resolution to Nicaragua's bitter property dispute, with a deadline of 30 days to produce concrete results.</p>
<p>At issue in the property dispute are an estimated 200,000 houses, farms and businesses confiscated by the 1979-1990 Sandinista government, many of which are being reclaimed by their former owners.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NICG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANAGUA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NICARAGUA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
