<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522681" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil's Cardoso invites land radicals to talks.</title>
<headline>Brazil's Cardoso invites land radicals to talks.</headline>
<byline>William Schomberg</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazilian President Fernando Henrique Cardoso offered an olive branch to the militant Landless Movement (MST) on Friday, proposing talks and the possibility of widening his land reform program.</p>
<p>But MST leaders, who met with the president one day after staging Brazil's biggest demonstration in recent years, said they would not give up their campaign of massive and often violent invasions of unused farmland.</p>
<p>MST director Jose Rainha said the movement would seek to increase the number of families occupying private land to 200,000 from about 45,000 now.</p>
<p>&quot;The promises of the government are not going to solve the problems of land reform,&quot; Gilmar Mauro, another MST director, said. &quot;We will paint the cities of this country red with the flags of the Landless Movement.&quot;</p>
<p>The MST has emerged as a new left-wing force in Brazil by turning the country's long history of unfair land distribution into a major political issue.</p>
<p>More than 25,000 demonstrators marched in Brasilia on Thursday for faster land reform and against the government's polices to cut public spending and open up Brazil's once-closed economy.</p>
<p>Hoping to capitalize on the momentum created by the march, a delegation of about 20 MST leaders, accompanied by an Indian chief sporting a feathered headdress, a famous samba singer and trade union leaders, met with Cardoso on Friday.</p>
<p>The president proposed to set up a commission which would study the possibility of settling 500,000 landless families in the next two years, one of the MST's demands. The government has pledged to settle 280,000 families during its four-year term.</p>
<p>But Cardoso insisted the land invasions must stop. &quot;I particularly stressed the aspect of the law because without democracy it will be much harder to make concrete progress,&quot; Cardoso told reporters. &quot;The time has come for convergence in order to make progress.&quot;</p>
<p>A presidential spokesman said Cardoso also proposed signing decrees that would bring into law several land reform bills stuck in Congress. The president would first consult with leaders of political parties, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>MST members said they would consult with the movement's collective leadership before deciding whether to accept the invitation to talks. &quot;We're neither satisfied nor disatisfied,&quot; MST leader Joao Pedro Stedile said. &quot;We had an open meeting and a chance to talk.&quot;</p>
<p>Brazil has one of the world's most unfair land distribution ratios with about half arable land in the hands of just two percent of landowners.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
