<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522667" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgarian Moslems vote on festival weekend.</title>
<headline>Bulgarian Moslems vote on festival weekend.</headline>
<byline>Liliana Semerdjieva</byline>
<dateline>KARDZHALI, Bulgaria 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>For Bulgaria's Moslems, elections on Saturday coincided with an Islamic festival weekend made one of the leanest in memory by economic devastation.</p>
<p>In this ethnic Turkish area in the mountainous south of the country, residents turned out in warm sunshine both to cast their votes and to stock up on lamb for the Feast of Sacrifice -- if they could afford it.</p>
<p>Religious festivals were hardly celebrated during Bulgaria's decades of hardline communism, and ethnic Turks were the victims of a campaign to force them to take Slavic names that led to a mass exodus to Turkey in 1989.</p>
<p>Counting for only about one tenth of the national population, Moslem Turks outnumber Slavs in the Kardzhali region. Recent elections there have been marred by allegations of ballot-rigging and deliberate stirring of ethnic tensions.</p>
<p>But in 1997, like other Bulgarians, the Turks are afflicted more by poverty than discrimination. Townspeople flocking to Kardzhali's dilapidated market on Saturday were more interested in festival food and gifts on sale than in Turkish-language literature promoting election candidates of the ethnic Turks' Movement for Rights and Freedoms (MRF).</p>
<p>Adding to hardship caused by roaring inflation for all goods, the price for a traditional festival sheep had risen to 120,000-200,O00 levs, ($80-130), up from 60,000 levs before the holiday.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not have anything to eat as my pension is only 3,900 levs a month and I cannot afford to buy anything for the feast,&quot; said Azeze Mustafa Mute, 47, retired with a crippled husband and three grandchildren to look after.</p>
<p>&quot;We were happy to receive three kg of flour from the Red Cross&quot;, she said with tears in her eyes.</p>
<p>She said she had voted for MRF leader Ahmed Dogan, standing in Kardzhali.</p>
<p>&quot;We get along well with the Bulgarians, we are sisters and brothers but the politicians try to separate us,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The MRF, with 15 seats in the last 240-seat parliament, has played a role in government since the overthrow of communism. Like other parties it has been discredited in the eyes of some by the country's decline and cannot count on the votes of all Turks.</p>
<p>Hikmet Ramadan Osman, a cashier, voted for the reformist Union of Democratic Forces (UDF), which led winter unrest against the then ruling ex-communist Socialists and forced them to agree to early elections.</p>
<p>&quot;I voted for the UDF because I believe that they can attract foreign investment. I did not support the MRF because Dogan has done nothing in the last seven years and I do not think he will do anything in the future,&quot; Osman said.</p>
<p>Sebim Mehmed Shavan, a tailor, lives with her husband and three children in a single rented room. &quot;Young people should leave this country as it is very hard to find a job here,&quot; she added. &quot;I voted for the UDF as I think that they can improve the situation.&quot;</p>
<p>One of Bulgaria's rare breed of capitalist entrepreneurs saw signs of hope in planned economic reforms, key to which is a strict &quot;currency board&quot; system proposed by the International Monetary Fund to quell inflation of more than 2,000 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope that the situation will improve after the elections and with the introduction of a currency board as it is very hard to sell to poor people,&quot; said Sulnai Hadti, the gold jewellery-wearing owner of food stores and a bar.</p>
<p>&quot;They used to buy goods in kilograms and now they are buying in grams. Still I think that now people are getting used to working harder. People are cultivating every piece of arable land, even in the city.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARDZHALI, Bulgaria"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
