<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522695" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Ex-head of Australia retail group guilty of fraud.</title>
<headline>Ex-head of Australia retail group guilty of fraud.</headline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brian Quinn, former chief executive of Australia's largest retailing group, Coles Myer Ltd, was found guilty on Saturday of defrauding the company of millions of dollars to pay for renovations on his home.</p>
<p>Quinn, 60, had pleaded not guilty to defrauding the company of A$4.46 million (US$3.43 million) between 1982 and 1988, most of which went into renovating his Melbourne mansion.</p>
<p>The former executive, described by the prosecution during the trial as &quot;the boss hog sticking his snout in the trough&quot;, was remanded in custody to await a plea hearing on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The court was told Quinn had conspired with the head of the company's maintenance department to charge Coles Myer for the work by making it appear it had been done on company properties.</p>
<p>However, Quinn's lawyers had told the Supreme Court of Victoria that Quinn himself had been a victim of a fraud by a corrupt maintenance department.</p>
<p>The former head of the maintenance department, Brian Lanyon, pleaded guilty to fraud in 1994 and served four months in jail.</p>
<p>Quinn, who rose from a junior store assistant to the top of the Australian retailing industry, was chief general manager of G.J. Coles in 1980, then managing director in 1983 before becoming chief executive of the newly-merged Coles Myer group in February 1986. He resigned from Coles Myer in 1991.</p>
<p>Prosecutor Paul Coghlan had told the court during the trial that the case was about excesses in many ways.</p>
<p>&quot;But most of all it is a case about greed. It is a case about having your employer pay for your excesses,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Work on the house included adding another storey, building a tennis court and building an eight-car garage. Interior work included installation of a mirror worth A$15,000.</p>
<p>Quinn, who has been free on bail, has repaid all but about A$1 million of the money. The jury began deliberations on Thursday after a two-month trial.</p>
<p>Coles Myer is Australia's largest retailing group with annual sales approaching A$20 billion.</p>
<p>(A$=US$0.77)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I6560002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
