<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522672" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgarians go to polls, reformists expect victory.</title>
<headline>Bulgarians go to polls, reformists expect victory.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Roche</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgarians vote on Saturday in elections expected to launch them down the path of economic reform taken by most of their east European neighbours years ago.</p>
<p>The results of the parliamentary elections are largely a foregone conclusion. The biggest question is how big an absolute majority will be won by reformists who led a winter of unrest which forced the ruling ex-communists to call the polls two years early.</p>
<p>Two opinion polls on Friday gave the Union of Democratic Forces (UDF) 47 and 56 percent support, easily enough to secure a clear majority in the 240-seat parliament, and the ex-communist Socialists between 19 and 24 percent. UDF leader Ivan Kostov is expected to become the new prime minister.</p>
<p>For the first time since the fall of communist dictatorship in 1989, the incoming government should enjoy clear support for market reforms of the still state-dominated economy from across the political spectrum -- even from the Socialists, long blamed for obstructing change.</p>
<p>A $1.2 billion credit package from international lenders is conditional on the introduction of strict monetary controls and mass privatisation, a painful cure for economic collapse. Under an interim government formed in February, the first steps have already been taken.</p>
<p>Previous governments over the past seven years have paid lip service to change but reforms have remained mainly on the drawing board, held up by political wrangling.</p>
<p>The Socialists, who won 1994 elections, stand accused of economic mismanagement that has fuelled inflation of more than 2,000 percent a year. But they still command loyalty among many old people who lived most of their lives under communist rule.</p>
<p>Support for the UDF, in contrast, is concentrated among the under-40s.</p>
<p>Among three smaller coalitions likely to break the threshold of four percent support needed to win a place in parliament are monarchists who want the return of exiled King Simeon, representatives of Bulgaria's ethnic Turkish minority, and defectors from the Socialists.</p>
<p>A total of 4,448 candidates are standing in the polls. Under a proportional representation system, parties and coalitions put up lists of candidates in each of 31 electoral districts.</p>
<p>Polling stations open at 6 a.m. (0300 GMT) and close at 7 p.m. (1600 GMT) and first results are expected on Saturday evening.</p>
<p>The election has failed to ignite the passions of a demoralised public who in January and February besieged the Socialist-dominated parliament and took to the streets to demand early elections.</p>
<p>Bulgarian newspapers said on Friday they expected a turnout of some 70-75 percent, compared with 61 percent in the final round of presidential polls in November.</p>
<p>Some 72 percent say, however, they have not bothered to read the rival parties' election campaign programmes, according to Bulgarian pollsters Sova-5. REUTER  182212 GMT apr 97</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
