<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522683" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexican rebels say could talk to left-wing government.</title>
<headline>Mexican rebels say could talk to left-wing government.</headline>
<byline>Razhy Gonzalez</byline>
<dateline>SAN PEDRO YOLOX, Mexico 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Mexican guerrilla group the Popular Revolutionary Army (EPR) said late on Friday they could enter into a dialogue with the government if left-wing politicians win Congress in July elections.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to respect the elections and will not give any reason for the government to call it a vote of terror so that the people can take part,&quot; guerrilla leader Ruben told local residents gathered in the town square.</p>
<p>Heavily armed members of the guerrilla group invaded this small mountain town in the southern state of Oaxaca, calling for a truth commission and saying they would respect the key mid-term election to be held in July.</p>
<p>About 25 armed rebels entered the town late on Friday, saying they were looking for a dialogue with the community. About 50 natives gathered around the square to see the rebel leader, Ruben, read his statement by the light of a lantern.</p>
<p>The EPR first appeared in the state of Guerrero last June, calling for the overthrow of the government of President Ernesto Zedillo. Since then the rebels have carried out attacks in at least five other central and southern states.</p>
<p>Observers of Mexico's political scene have expressed concern that EPR attacks could disrupt the elections, which are seen as a key test for the long-ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI).</p>
<p>The EPR has blunted its armed attacks but has continued to spread propaganda for its Marxist cause.</p>
<p>&quot;Our message to the people is this: to everyone who is going to vote, we say we will respect your choice, but we also ask that you fight to the last breathe to demand that the government respect your decision,&quot; Ruben told the gathered crowds in this small isolated town, where most people farm corn or make a living by cutting trees.</p>
<p>The left-wing Party of the Democratic Revolution is ahead in recent polls in the race for mayor for Mexico City, but most analysts predict that either the ruling PRI or the opposition National Action Party (PAN) will control the Congress after the July electins.</p>
<p>Ruben also said the rebel movement would not lay down its arms.</p>
<p>&quot;The Mexican left has made large advances recently, and we are expecting good results, but neither are we going to lay down our arms,&quot; Ruben said.</p>
<p>In answer to a question from one of the gathered Zapotec Indians, the guerrilla leader said the group still backed an armed rebellion &quot;because we have understood that the government is not ready to leave power by peaceful means.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN PEDRO YOLOX, Mexico"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
