<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522617" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK Conservatives seize on firefighters' strike.</title>
<headline>UK Conservatives seize on firefighters' strike.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's embattled Conservative Party on Saturday seized on a strike by firefighters just 11 days before national elections to invoke the spectre of industrial strife under a new Labour government.</p>
<p>Some 1,000 firefighters in eastern England went on a 24-hour strike in protest at budget cuts by their local council which unions say will axe 52 jobs and hit spending on training, recruitment and equipment. Further strikes are planned for Monday and Wednesday.</p>
<p>The Conservatives, some 20 points behind the opposition Labour Party in opinion polls, said the stoppage was a preview of what life would be like if Labour won the May 1 election.</p>
<p>&quot;If the summer dawns with a Labour victory, it will end with a new winter of discontent,&quot; Deputy Prime Minister Michael Heseltine told a news conference.</p>
<p>Labour, out of power for 18 years, is still haunted by memories of the industrial chaos that signalled its last few months in power in 1979 when the dead went unburied and parks became unofficial garbage dumps during a wave of strikes by public sector workers.</p>
<p>Labour, which has since ditched much of its socialist dogma and distanced itself from its old trade union allies, said the firefighters' strike was &quot;unnecessary&quot; and refused to support it.</p>
<p>&quot;We think the strike is unnecessary and shouldn't be happening. No fire stations are closing, no fire officers are being made redundant and no engines are being lost,&quot; said Labour social security spokeswoman Harriet Harman.</p>
<p>Labour leaders shrugged off suggestions that the strike was an embarrassment to their party, whose election campaign has been noted for its slickness and high organisation.</p>
<p>&quot;The Labour Party will not be hijacked by any group at any time,&quot; economics spokesman Gordon Brown told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody knows that the way we will approach the question of trade unions is no favours and fairness to everybody and the general public as a whole,&quot; Brown said.</p>
<p>But the Conservatives claimed that Labour would blow the economic recovery underway in Britain and that a resurgence of union power under an administration led by Tony Blair would threaten the country.</p>
<p>Blair has moved Labour sharply to the right so that many of its policies are virtually indistinguishable from those of the Conservatives.</p>
<p>But unlike the Conservative government, Labour has pledged to introduce a minimum wage and to adopt the European Union's Social Chapter on working conditions.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
