<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522651" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgarians back reform in general election. [CORRECTED 07:20 20/4]</title>
<headline>Bulgarians back reform in general election. [CORRECTED 07:20 20/4]</headline>
<byline>Galina Sabeva</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgarians voted on Saturday in parliamentary elections likely to give a mandate for belated economic reforms intended to enable their impoverished country to catch up with its east European neighbours.</p>
<p>The Union of Democratic Forces (UDF) is expected to win a majority, building on the month-long protests it led to oust the former Socialist government in February and the efforts since of its ministers in the interim cabinet to tackle the crisis.</p>
<p>&quot;I am going to vote for the UDF because this is why we spent so many days on the streets and nights on the barricades -- to topple the communists,&quot; said Boyan Roussev, one of the students whose inventive daily street theatre formed the backbone of the campaign against the ex-communist Socialists.</p>
<p>&quot;But if they lie to us, I promise I will be the first to go back on the streets.&quot;</p>
<p>For Bulgaria's minority Moslems voting coincided with Bairam, the Feast of the Sacrifice, while Christian villages marked the traditional spring festival of St Lazarus.</p>
<p>President Petar Stoyanov, voting in Sofia's Darvenitsa (corrects from Draganitsa) district, was greeted at the polling station by girls in traditional costume who offered him bread and salt in a gesture of welcome.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no time to waste. We lost the chance we had with the fall of the Iron Curtain and now we must catch up,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>An interim cabinet led by Sofia's UDF mayor Stefan Sofianski has run the country since February, winning pledges of $1.2 billion from international lenders and kicking off the reform process the new government must continue.</p>
<p>A restrictive fixed exchange rate regime is due to be introduced in June to instil monetary discipline and restore confidence in the lev currency, which went into free fall in January while Bulgaria was without effective government.</p>
<p>The lev has now stabilised, but annual inflation was more than 2,000 percent in March and the planned overhaul of communist-era state firms will add to unemployment already at 14.5 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Regardless of the colour of the ballot paper we should vote for reforms at an acceptable social price,&quot; said Socialist leader Georgi Parvanov.</p>
<p>Salaries, typically $40 or $50 a month, have failed to keep up with soaring prices. Grain and petrol almost ran out last month before the interim government secured new supplies.</p>
<p>The interior minister has launched a high-profile campaign against organised crime, which has soared unchecked since the end of communist rule, helped by an inadequate legal system.</p>
<p>This week the government made its first major arrest, detaining a mafia boss in the southern town of Kardzhali and sacking local tax and interior ministry officials accused of connections to his organisation.</p>
<p>After communist leader Todor Zhivkov was toppled in 1989, leading communists re-emerged as the Bulgarian Socialist Party (BSP) and continued in government. The UDF won elections in 1991 but their government collapsed after only 11 months.</p>
<p>Both opinion polls and comments from voters at the booths on Saturday showed most would be backing the UDF.</p>
<p>But especially among the elderly who have lived most of their lives under hardline communism, a few were sticking with the left.</p>
<p>Gypsy sisters Vera and Lilka Yonkova were not sure what kind of elections were being held, but said they would back the Socialists because they lived better under communism.</p>
<p>&quot;Life was easier then, prices were low and we had enough food for our children,&quot; Vera said.</p>
<p>Pensioner Mihail Koev said he was supporting the tiny rump communist party. &quot;I have spent all my life building socialism and now if I support the UDF or the BSP I may have to spend the rest of my life building capitalism,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
