<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522605" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: SWIMMING-OLYMPIC CHAMPION PANKRATOV DIPS OUT AGAIN.</title>
<headline>SWIMMING-OLYMPIC CHAMPION PANKRATOV DIPS OUT AGAIN.</headline>
<dateline>GOTHENBURG, Sweden 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Double Olympic champion Denis Pankratov capped a disappointing week at the world short-course swimming championships when he failed to make his second final on Saturday.</p>
<p>The Russian, who holds all the men's short-course and long-course butterfly records, led for the first 50 metres of his 200 butterfly heat but was then passed by defending champion Scott Goodman of Australia and Germany's Thomas Rupprath.</p>
<p>Pankratov, who did not manage a place in the 100 butterfly final on Thursday, could not respond to the challenge and finished one place and 0.31 seconds behind Rupprath, the eighth and slowest overall qualifier for the evening's finals.</p>
<p>The blond Russian, swimming without his customary black cap, clocked one minute 58.22 seconds, more than five seconds outside the 1:52.64 world mark he set in Gelsenkirchen, Germany, in February.</p>
<p>He did not seem unduly concerned about the outcome and appears to be concentrating his season on next August's European long-course championships in Seville, for which he will compete in Russian trials in May.</p>
<p>Most of the Russian team came to Sweden direct from France where they had trained for seven weeks, including four weeks at high altitude in the Pyrenees.</p>
<p>American Misty Hyman gave fans in the Scandinavium arena a display of her remarkable underwater technique and came close to the world record in the women's 100 butterfly heats.</p>
<p>Hyman turned on her side after diving in at the start and swam almost all the first length of the 25-metre pool under water, emerging only for one obligatory stroke above the surface before the turn.</p>
<p>The American emerged for five strokes on the second length, six on the third and seven on the fourth and touched in a championship record 58.32.</p>
<p>Hyman, bronze medallist in the 200 butterfly and 100 backstroke at these championships, set a world mark of 58.29 last December but that was lowered to 58.24 on March 28 by Japan's Ayari Aoyama.</p>
<p>Aoyama is not competing in Gothenburg but her record was bound to be under threat in evening's finals.</p>
<p>American Jenny Thompson, with a 100 freestyle gold and 50 freestyle silver already in her possession, was second-fastest overall in 58.67.</p>
<p>Claudia Poll, who broke her own 200 freestyle world mark on Friday, faced a battle against 15-year-old Australian Natasha Bowron in the final of the women's 400 freestyle.</p>
<p>Bowron, gold medallist in Friday's 800 freestyle, led qualifiers in four minutes 8.72 seconds to sound her challenge to the Costa Rican defending champion and world record-holder.</p>
<p>Poll, who won the Olympic 200 freestyle title in Atlanta, won her heat in the second-best overall time of 4:08.93.</p>
<p>Venezuela's Francisco Sanchez, who won the 50 freestyle at the 1995 world short-course championships, led qualifiers in the men's 100 freestyle with a time of 47.85.</p>
<p>Defending champion Fernando Scherer of Brazil failed to qualify, finishing 17th overall in 49.57.</p>
<p>American Amanda Beard, double breaststroke Olympic silver medallist, failed to make the women's 100 breaststroke final, finishing ninth overall nearly a second outside a final place in 1:09.72.</p>
<p>South Africa's Joanne Russell led the women's 100 breaststroke qualifiers in 1:08.14 and Russia's Andrei Korneev topped the men's 200 breaststroke qualifiers in 2:09.82.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GOTHENBURG, Sweden"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
