<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522625" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Major savages Blair in UK election campaign.</title>
<headline>Major savages Blair in UK election campaign.</headline>
<byline>Lyndsay Griffiths</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister John Major is attacking Labour leader Tony Blair with ever more personal jibes -- likening his rival to a dummy, a fly and a grasshopper as he struggles to make up ground before Britain's May 1 election.</p>
<p>The increasingly acerbic tone of Major's taunts drew criticism from across the political spectrum, especially after the Conservative British premier embroiled other European leaders in his domestic point-scoring.</p>
<p>On Friday, the Conservatives created a storm of protest with an advertisement that depicted Blair as a ventriloquist's dummy perched on the knee of German Chancellor Helmut Kohl.</p>
<p>&quot;Don't send a boy to do a man's job,&quot; it read, implying Blair was not up to negotiating for Britain in Europe.</p>
<p>The advert was the latest in a line of attacks designed to show Blair as untrustworthy while Major paints himself as a man of honour with years of high office behind him.</p>
<p>Yet the same Major is taunted daily by opponents as a weak leader beholden to noisy factions in his own party, whereas Blair has largely silenced the Labour trouble-makers.</p>
<p>Seeking to still the internal revolt, Major has moved ever closer to the Euro-sceptic wing of his party, with the Kohl poster just the latest sop to those on his right.</p>
<p>Major took a huge gamble this week by switching the focus of his campaign onto Europe, hoping to put the spotlight on Blair's lack of experience of international negotiations.</p>
<p>But he has taken off the gloves in an effort to claw back support -- and plenty of his fellow statesmen don't like it.</p>
<p>Liberal Democrat peer Roy Jenkins, the only Briton to have held the presidency of the European Commission, said: &quot;I think it is very doubtful bringing in foreign statesmen -- whoever wins the election is going to have to work with Kohl.&quot;</p>
<p>Former Conservative foreign secretary Lord Geoffrey Howe expressed sadness that Major, trailing by 20 points in the polls, had &quot;gone against his natural instincts&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Britain would be a loser outside Europe...We should be leading Europe, not leaving it,&quot; said a cross-party letter to The Times, signed by Howe.</p>
<p>Pro-European members of Major's government were said to be fuming about the latest turn of events, talking of a party on the verge of collapse and in preparation for opposition.</p>
<p>&quot;The increasingly crude and desperate language now used by John Major will inevitably rebound on him. The public will be contemptuous of him and his own party will become increasingly embarrassed,&quot; said deputy Labour leader John Prescott.</p>
<p>Nor did Major show any sign of letting up his attacks, hoping to sow doubt among the electorate about so-called New Labour and win a record fifth Conservative victory.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Blair changes his mind as often as a grasshopper jumps,&quot; Major said in a campaign speech on Friday night.</p>
<p>He accused Blair of &quot;naivete and inexperience&quot; and said that sending the Labour leader to negotiate Britain's ties with the European Union would be like sending &quot;a fly to a spiders' convention&quot;. REUTER  182334 GMT apr 97</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
