<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522685" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Colombian truckers to begin nationwide strike.</title>
<headline>Colombian truckers to begin nationwide strike.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of Colombia's main truck drivers' union said a nationwide strike would begin at midnight on Saturday after 11th-hour talks with the government failed to produce agreement over key demands.</p>
<p>&quot;The strike begins at zero hour,&quot; Javier Suarez, leader of the Colombian Truck Drivers' Association (ACC), told Reuters in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;The strike will go forward no matter what,&quot; he added, dismissing reports of a possible delay in the work stoppage set to begin at 12 a.m. (0500 GMT) Sunday. The ACC represents about 80 percent of Colombia's truck drivers.</p>
<p>Suarez spoke after he and other union officials held marathon talks with Transportation Minister Carlos Hernan Lopez that broke down shortly after midnight on Friday without any definitive agreements on ways of averting the job action.</p>
<p>A new round of talks had tentatively been scheduled for Saturday in a bid to iron out a final accord. But Suarez said he and other negotiators saw no point in returning to the bargaining table since the government had been unable to convince the owners of transportation companies to attend and hammer out an agreement increasing highway freight rates.</p>
<p>The ACC called the strike in March on grounds that the government, and private companies alike, had violated terms of a pact that ended a crippling 11-day ACC strike last October.</p>
<p>That strike, which brought most highway freight to a standstill and wreaked havoc with exports of coffee, sugar and other commodities, ended with a pledge to increase freight rates by 18 percent in January.</p>
<p>No such increase has been implemented so far, and the ACC says most of its rank-and-file members are on the verge of bankruptcy because of soaring operating costs.</p>
<p>Defense Minister Gilberto Echeverri Mejia issued a statement early on Saturday reiterating government threats to declare the ACC strike illegal and urging its membership &quot;to think about the implications it would have for the country and the economy in general.&quot;</p>
<p>The statement said sanctions, including possible arrest and confiscations of property, would only be imposed against drivers who seek to block motorists and public transportation companies from circulating freely across the nation's highways, however.</p>
<p>Transportation Minister Lopez has voiced fears that leftist guerrillas may seek to take advantage of the ACC strike to add to Colombia's pressing law-and-order problems but Echeverri did not refer to that threat.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
