<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522604" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: SOCCER-BLATTER SPEAKS OUT AGAIN AGAINST WORLD CUP FENCES.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BLATTER SPEAKS OUT AGAIN AGAINST WORLD CUP FENCES.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>FIFA are still unhappy with France's decision to retain perimeter fencing at its venues for the 1998 World Cup finals.</p>
<p>&quot;You put wild beasts or prisoners behind bars. You can't have a party behind bars,&quot; Sepp Blatter, general secretary of world soccer body FIFA, said.</p>
<p>&quot;One ought to be able to find a solution between 2.40 metre high fences ... and protections behind the goal zones,&quot; he told reporters in Toulouse, one of the 10 venues, on Friday.</p>
<p>Blatter, who ended a tour of southern venues including Marseille and Montpellier, said FIFA wanted to take up the perimeter fencing debate again with the French national Olympic Committee and Football Federation.</p>
<p>Former France captain Michel Platini, joint head of France's World Cup organising committee, said the decision lay with the French Interior ministry.</p>
<p>Interior Minister Jean-Louis Debre said in February that fences would remain in place for the World Cup finals.</p>
<p>FIFA have campaigned to abolish perimeter fencing in the aftermath of several stadium tragedies, including one in Sheffield, England, in 1989 at the Hillsborough ground where 96 people were crushed to death in an over-crowded, fenced-in section of terracing during an F.A. Cup semifinal.</p>
<p>The call for the removal of fencing was renewed when more than 80 people were killed in an incident chillingly similar to Hillsborough before the start of a World Cup qualifier in Guatemala late last year.</p>
<p>Blatter said he was pleased with the work on the three World Cup stadiums he visited and had no worries over the organisation of the tournament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
