<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522648" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Agencies aid Albanians, troops ready escorts.</title>
<headline>Agencies aid Albanians, troops ready escorts.</headline>
<byline>David Brough</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Relief agencies distributed emergency food and medicines to Albanian hospitals and orphanages on Saturday as troops from a multinational security force prepared to protect aid convoys.</p>
<p>The International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) delivered the aid to a psychiatric and general hospital and three orphanages in the rebel-held port city of Vlore 150 km (90 miles) south of the capital Tirana, a spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Extremely thin patients at Vlore's psychiatric hospital, some with hollow cheeks, helped Red Cross officers to carry bags of rice, flour and soap from a truck, witnesses said. Many patients had no shoes and socks and wore torn clothes.</p>
<p>&quot;These patients have received very little food in recent weeks,&quot; said Red Cross officer Barbara Jaggi.</p>
<p>Conditions were better at the orphanages, where children aged up to six years old benefited from the aid.</p>
<p>The state's deliveries of food and medicines to hospitals, orphanages and homes for the handicapped and elderly have been severely disrupted since Albania slid into near-anarchy earlier this year after the collapse of get-rich-quick savings plans.</p>
<p>Some 300 people have been killed in violence since an armed insurrection in late February.</p>
<p>The first supplies of United Nations food for Albania's poor and needy were handed out to a flotilla of cars that ferried the aid across the small Balkan state.</p>
<p>Without waiting for a multinational security force to provide armed escorts, the U.N. World Food Programme started passing out sacks of wheat flour, beans and vegetable oil at the port of Durres, 40 km (25 miles) west of Tirana.</p>
<p>Small vans and cars from 20 orphanages, hospitals, and homes for the elderly and handicapped drove into the decrepit port on Saturday to pick up the aid.</p>
<p>Some institutions have been targets of banditry.</p>
<p>&quot;All of our food was stolen six weeks ago,&quot; said Mark Nyberg, collecting supplies for an orphanage in Vlore. &quot;Our concern is not so much getting it to Vlore, but keeping it once we get there. The situation is far from stable,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>ICRC spokeswoman Nina Winquist-Galbe said that one Red Cross team distributing aid this week in northern Albania, near the town of Krume, had visited hospitals which employed more armed guards than doctors in an effort to keep away gunmen.</p>
<p>Albania has been full of guns since the uprising. Angry Albanians ransacked arsenals deserted by troops and police, flooding the country with weapons. Rebel committees blaming President Sali Berisha for the failure of the investment schemes have taken control of much of the south.</p>
<p>The ICRC, which has already made two deliveries to Vlore institutions since mid-March, does not use military escorts despite the arrival this week of the Italian-led multinational force whose mission is to protect humanitarian aid convoys.</p>
<p>Italian military spokesman Paolo Bianchi told a briefing for journalists he expected the multinational force to start escorting aid convoys from next Thursday.</p>
<p>He said the immediate priority of troops was to secure the roads and plan routes in cooperation with relief agencies.</p>
<p>Bianchi said more than half of the multinational mission, which will eventually number 6,000, had arrived in Albania.</p>
<p>Italian military spokesman Lieutenant Gianfranco Scalas said 490 Italian soldiers landed by sea in Durres on Saturday and another 550 Italian troops were due on Sunday.</p>
<p>He said he expected the foreign troops to conduct joint patrols with Albanian police when protecting aid convoys.</p>
<p>Albanian Prime Minister Bashkim Fino dismissed Deputy Interior Minister General Agim Shehu, who is Albania's police chief, Fino's office said.</p>
<p>&quot;The government decided to dismiss Shehu after a proposal of Fino was voted for by the majority of his ministers,&quot; a statement said.</p>
<p>Political analysts said Shehu's removal was due to a roadside hold-up by about 15 gunmen barring Fino's convoy of cars from entering the northern town on Shkoder earlier this month. They said Fino held Shehu responsible for the event.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
