<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522657" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgarian voters give UDF mandate for reform.</title>
<headline>Bulgarian voters give UDF mandate for reform.</headline>
<byline>Thalia Griffiths</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1996-04-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgaria's reformist Union of Democratic Forces (UDF) scored a resounding victory in parliamentary elections, cementing a political transformation which began with presidential polls last November.</p>
<p>Partial official returns released early on Sunday gave the UDF and their coalition allies 57.62 percent of votes.</p>
<p>UDF leader Ivan Kostov said the new government's four main priorities would be carrying out reforms agreed with the International Monetary Fund, fighting organised crime and corruption, opening secret police files of public figures, and bringing Bulgaria into the European Union and NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;Difficulties are still ahead but don't be afraid, we shall overcome them,&quot; President Petar Stoyanov told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;Don't believe that Bulgaria will be sold out, that it has no future. On the contrary, we have already chosen our path.&quot;</p>
<p>Stoyanov, elected on the UDF ticket last November, indicated that he expected the UDF parliamentary group to nominate Kostov, a former finance minister less popular than the interim premier, as prime minister.</p>
<p>&quot;In every country after a decisive victory of a certain political force its leader becomes prime minister,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Moreover, Ivan Kostov with his activity in the democratic sector of political life has shown something very important -- willingness for dialogue and to place national interests above narrow party interests.&quot;</p>
<p>UDF supporters, who turned out for daily rallies during a winter of unrest which forced the former Socialist government to agree to polls two years early, celebrated into the night.</p>
<p>&quot;We will be a constructive opposition and will continue to represent the ideas of reason and agreement, especially when it comes to the structural reform and financial stabilisation of the country,&quot; Socialist leader Georgi Parvanov told reporters.</p>
<p>Three smaller groups were set to enter parliament. The Union for National Salvation (UNS) will bring monarchist organisations seeking the return of exiled King Simeon into parliament for the first time, in coalition with ethnic Turks.</p>
<p>They are joined by the Euroleft, a new party set up by Socialist dissidents, and the Bulgarian Business Bloc, led by maverick populist George Ganchev.</p>
<p>Partial results with about 20 percent of votes counted gave the Socialists 19.38 percent and smaller scores for the others.</p>
<p>An interim cabinet led by Sofia's UDF mayor Stefan Sofianski has run the country since February, winning pledges of $1.2 billion from international lenders and kicking off the reform process the new government must continue. Sofianski has said he wants to complete his mandate as mayor, but is expected to return to national politics at a later date.</p>
<p>&quot;The victory is expected,&quot; said Valentin Vassilev, a senior UDF official. &quot;But for us the end of the campaign does not mean the end of difficulties, as we have to govern a country ruined by the Socialists.&quot;</p>
<p>A restrictive fixed exchange rate regime is due to be introduced in June to instil monetary discipline and restore confidence in the lev currency, which went into free fall in January while Bulgaria was without effective government.</p>
<p>After communist leader Todor Zhivkov was toppled in 1989, leading communists re-emerged as the Bulgarian Socialist Party and continued in government. The UDF won elections in 1991 but their coalition with the ethnic Turkish party collapsed after only 11 months.</p>
<p>This time, the UDF has a secure majority. In addition, the Euroleft has pledged its support for their programme, while the UNS favour a coalition and the Business Bloc say they back Stoyanov and Sofianski but will not support a Kostov cabinet.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
