<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522614" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: BULGARIANS VOTE IN PARLIAMENTARY ELECTION.</title>
<headline>BULGARIANS VOTE IN PARLIAMENTARY ELECTION.</headline>
<byline>Elisaveta Konstantinova</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Voting got under way in Bulgaria on Saturday in parliamentary elections called after month-long protests toppled the former Socialist government in February.</p>
<p>Early turnout was low but was expected to pick up during the day. Polling stations close at 7 p.m. (1600 GMT) and first indications from exit polls are expected in the early evening.</p>
<p>&quot;I will vote for change and for the new Bulgaria, so that the young people have a better future,&quot; said retired teacher Ivanka Petrova in Sofia's Dragalevtsi suburb.</p>
<p>&quot;I voted for the UDF so that I and my generation have a future here, so that we can make a decent living here and not be forced to emigrate,&quot; said 20-year-old physics student Marin Petrov, heading off for a day's skiing after casting his ballot.</p>
<p>The Union of Democratic Forces (UDF), which led daily street protests in January and February, is seeking a mandate to carry out economic measures agreed with the International Monetary Fund and other lenders.</p>
<p>Final opinion polls published on Friday showed the UDF winning a majority in the 240-seat parliament with the Socialists as the biggest opposition party.</p>
<p>A $1.2 billion credit package from international lenders is conditional on the introduction of strict monetary controls and wide-ranging privatisations, a painful cure for economic collapse. Under an interim government formed in February, the first steps have already been taken.</p>
<p>The new government will be Bulgaria's 10th since the end of one-party rule in 1989.</p>
<p>The Socialists, who won the last parliamentary elections in December 1994, saw their support fade as the economy worsened but still command loyalty among many old people nostalgic for the communist era when food was cheap and crime rates were low.</p>
<p>Bulgaria has 2.3 million pensioners in a population of 8.4 million.</p>
<p>Among three smaller coalitions likely to break the threshold of four percent support needed to win a place in parliament are monarchists who want the return of exiled King Simeon, representatives of Bulgaria's ethnic Turkish minority, and defectors from the Socialists.</p>
<p>&quot;I am going to vote for the King but I don't know which is his ballot. I hope they'll tell me,&quot; said one elderly woman confused by the large number of monarchist parties.</p>
<p>A total of 4,448 candidates are standing in the polls. Under a proportional representation system, parties and coalitions put up lists of candidates in each of 31 electoral districts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
