<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522635" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Kabila urges army on to Kinshasa to topple Mobutu.</title>
<headline>Kabila urges army on to Kinshasa to topple Mobutu.</headline>
<byline>Douglas Hamilton</byline>
<dateline>LUBUMBASHI, Zaire 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laurent Kabila called on the young men of Shaba province on Saturday to join his rebel army, march on the capital Kinshasa, and put an end to the dictatorship of President Mobutu Sese Seko.</p>
<p>In a speech to some 10,000 people at a football stadium in the dusty Kenya township outside Lubumbashi, Kabila rammed home his message that there will be no compromise: Mobutu and his hangers-on must go.</p>
<p>&quot;It won't take long. We'll be in Kinshasa very soon. We're only 200 km (120 miles) away from Kinshasa. Now join the army and fight like men so we can finish this thing,&quot; he said in a two-and-a-half hour speech in Swahili mixed with French.</p>
<p>&quot;In Bas Zaire province, 100,000 young men have joined our cause,&quot; he said to cheers, in an address studded with anecdotes aimed at exposing the manipulations of the Mobutu regime and the lessons of his seven-month-old war to topple it.</p>
<p>He called on the government army to put down their weapons - - a suggestion already taken up by garrisons in many towns captured by the rebel forces but one which in Kinshasa could avert the bloodiest battle of the civil war.</p>
<p>Speaking for the first time to the people of the largest city so far captured by the rebels, Kabila drilled home the lesson that Mobutu had plundered the country for the past 32 years while holding supreme power through a policy of divide- and-rule, larded with corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;We can't celebrate yet,&quot; he said. &quot;We haven't finished our job. Kinshasa is not taken yet.&quot;</p>
<p>Kabila bore down on Zaire's opposition parties, telling the people his Alliance for the Democratic Liberation of Congo-Zaire (AFDL) would not pause in its mission simply to accomodate people who effectively collaborated with Mobutu.</p>
<p>&quot;What have the opposition political parties liberated? They haven't even liberated themselves,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He depicted the ex-governor of Shaba province as a pretend opponent of Mobutu who was in reality merely a puppet to the dictator -- a line which drew calls of dissent from sections of the crowd in what was a stronghold of the populist governor.</p>
<p>Now in control of over half of Zaire, a country as big as all of Western Europe, the AFDL forces are on a roll, picking up the support of disaffected government troops and taking on fresh recruits as they advance west from town to town.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to put all of Mobutu's people out of power so they can never raise their heads again,&quot; Kabila said.</p>
<p>Rejecting speculation that he might be ready to find compromise with Mobutu if the two meet next week in South Africa, Kabila repeated that all he was ready to do for Mobutu was assure his safety, once he has &quot;signed his resignation.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Our job is to liberate this country with weapons. Because our enemies have weapons...we should get ready. We need a lot of young people from this region so we'll have enough soldiers to take Kinshasa,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Once the war was over and Mobutu safely confined to his home town of Gbadolite, the AFDL would form an interim government and set about getting back the billions of dollars stolen by Mobutu and banked overseas, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;He won't go into exile. He'll have to stay here so he can watch and see what we will do for the country, what he couldn't do.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;When stability and the rule of law had been established, there would be open elections in which every party could run for office -- except individuals who 'stole with Mobutu'.</p>
<p>&quot;But first we must fight Mobutu, nothing else.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUBUMBASHI, Zaire"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
