<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522645" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Five more killed in Nigerian ethnic clash.</title>
<headline>Five more killed in Nigerian ethnic clash.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Five people died on Friday in the midwestern Nigerian oil town of Warri where there have been running clashes between militant youths of feuding tribes, local newspapers reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>The independent Guardian newspaper said the latest killings took place when the village of Ugbuwagbwe was burnt down. Among the victims were a man and his wife who had been out fishing.</p>
<p>This brought to 50 the number of people reportedly killed in renewed hostilities in the area since April 12.</p>
<p>A man was shot dead and the main market in Warri set ablaze on Thursday while 44 people, mostly from Ijaw tribe were killed a week ago when their Ikpokpo village was razed by armed men.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation here is still tense,&quot; said a journalist by telephone from Warri, about 300 km (190 miles) from Lagos.</p>
<p>An officer at the Warri police station, who was also reached by telephone from Lagos, refused to comment on the situation.</p>
<p>Warri has seen trouble since March 22 when clashes broke out over the relocation of the local council headquarters from an Ijaw town to a town belonging to the rival Itsekiri tribe.</p>
<p>A dusk-to-dawn curfew imposed in Warri in the wake of the March clashes was lifted early this week.</p>
<p>At the height of the crisis, armed Ijaw tribesmen occupied oil facilities of the Nigerian unit of Royal Dutch Shell Group, holding 127 of their Nigerian staff hostage and disrupting oil production.</p>
<p>The hostages were released in batches following delicate negotiations and oil output has since resumed.</p>
<p>Shell officials were not available to comment on the renewed clashes.</p>
<p>Similar clashes have erupted in several other parts of multi-ethnic Nigeria over a recent creation and restructuring of some of the more than 770 local government councils.</p>
<p>Government officials say the action is being reviewed by the federal authorities in the capital Abuja to correct what one called &quot;glaring anomalies in the exercise.&quot;</p>
<p>Colonel John Dungs, the military administrator of Delta state of which Warri is a part, met community leaders there on Wednesday and told them to call their people to order or the government would be forced to take tough measures.</p>
<p>--Lagos newsroom +234 1 2630317</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
