<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522671" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: ABB consortium to manage Kazakhstan's power grid.</title>
<headline>ABB consortium to manage Kazakhstan's power grid.</headline>
<dateline>ALMATY 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kazakhstan awarded a contract on Saturday to the ABB Power Grid Consortium Ltd to manage the former Soviet republic's national power grid for 25 years.</p>
<p>Under the agreement, the ABB consortium will pay wage arrears to the sector's employees, develop a power pool and invest a minimum $200 million over the next three years.</p>
<p>The Swedish consortium will receive the remainder of the net profits and a performance-linked management fee.</p>
<p>The Kazakh government, which has ruled out privatising the network despite its need to raise cash to top up hard-hit state coffers, will receive 85 percent of the grid's net profits.</p>
<p>On April 14, Kazakh economy minister Umirzak Shukeyev told Reuters that Kazakhstan was negotiating exclusively with Britain's National Grid Group for the contract, although there were questions on tariffs, royalty payments and the investment programme. He said then the government reserved the right to approach another company if the negotiations did not work out.</p>
<p>&quot;This concession agreement is a significant step forward in establishing reliable electricity transmission for the Republic of Kazakhstan by bringing modern management techniques and investment into the sector,&quot; the government said in a statement.</p>
<p>Sarebai Khalmurzaev of the Kazakh finance ministry told reporters after the signing ceremony that the agreement would help create an effective regional market in electricity.</p>
<p>Kazakhstan's national grid totals 16,000 km (10,000 miles).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALMATY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
