<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522637" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Mobutu's fate in balance as Zaire rebels press on.</title>
<headline>Mobutu's fate in balance as Zaire rebels press on.</headline>
<byline>William Wallis</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Loyal political allies rallied to the side of embattled President Mobutu Sese Seko on Saturday following calls by Western powers for him to surrender power to prevent civil war reaching Zaire's teeming capital.</p>
<p>The president of Mobutu's FPC political alliance, Idambituo Bakato, directed his attack mainly at Zaire's former colonial ruler Belgium and the United States, which on Friday ordered dependents of its embassy staff in Zaire to leave.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not for Western countries to decide who rules Zaire,&quot; he told a news conference in Kinshasa.</p>
<p>&quot;To this day the FPC has one candidate for presidential elections who is called Mr. Mobutu and you know that we're the largest party in this country,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Mobutu's fate has hung in the balance since rebel leader Laurent Kabila suggested his forces were ready for a final advance on Kinshasa, the last stronghold of Zaire's ragged army. Rebels now hold about half the sprawling country.</p>
<p>South Africa finally persuaded Mobutu to meet Kabila for direct negotiations the rebel leader has long demanded as a way of ending the six-month war. But diplomats are sceptical about Kabila's genuine interest in reaching any compromise given his overwhelming military advantage on the ground.</p>
<p>Mobutu's associates urged Western powers to use their influence to win a ceasefire to pave the way for elections instead of pressing Mobutu to step aside.</p>
<p>While Mobutu's camp is pushing for elections, even some of his supporters doubt his health would allow him to prolong his 32-year rule. Mobutu had cancer surgery in Switzerland last August and is still undergoing treatment.</p>
<p>His supporters appear to be pushing for free elections as the main issue at planned talks as a way of providing the president with a dignified way out.</p>
<p>The rebels insist he must step down unconditionally.</p>
<p>Although the United States military has been prepared for weeks for the possible evacuation of about 450 Americans from Zaire, no order to do so had been issued, U.S. officials said.</p>
<p>However, the U.S. State Department's announcement that it had ordered dependents of U.S. embassy personnel to leave reflected growing U.S. concern about the situation in Zaire.</p>
<p>Embassy officials said there were only seven dependents left but that they had no immediate plans to leave.</p>
<p>Latest assessments by diplomats and military analysts this week placed the rebels around 600 km (380 miles) from Kinshasa at the diamond trading centre of Tshikapa.</p>
<p>Military analysts say the rebels are likely to continue building pressure on Mobutu to go by overrunning towns in the province of Bandundu, which neighbours Kinshasa on its Western flank and supplies most of the capital's food.</p>
<p>Around half of Kinshasa's population originates from Bandundu, and analysts say the capture of towns such as Kikwit, 350 km (200 miles) away could have a dramatic psychological effect on the capital's inhabitants.</p>
<p>Since taking up arms last October the rebels have seized Zaire's key cities and the richest mineral-producing provinces.</p>
<p>The rebels captured the copper centre of Lubumbashi last week, leaving Kinshasa as the only important city in the hands of Mobutu's ragged army.</p>
<p>Kabila has predicted his forces will be in Kinshasa in three weeks and has ruled out any negotiations or a ceasefire agreement at the planned meeting with Mobutu.</p>
<p>In rebel-held areas, aid workers returned to Rwandan Hutu refugee camps south of the Zairean rebel-held city of Kisangani on Saturday. Protesters had blocked their way on Friday and attacked aid vehicles.</p>
<p>Rebel soldiers secured the jungle road to Biaro and Kasese camps under an agreement with the United Nations. Torrential rain cleared the streets.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
