<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522639" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Zaire rebel leader urges young men to join fight.</title>
<headline>Zaire rebel leader urges young men to join fight.</headline>
<byline>Douglas Hamilton</byline>
<dateline>LUBUMBASHI, Zaire 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zairean rebel leader Laurent Kabila on Saturday urged thousands of young men in the country's second city -- which his army seized about a week ago -- to join his forces in its advance on the capital Kinshasa.</p>
<p>He appealed to the young men among the crowd of about 10,000 at a rally in Lubumbashi to help him drive ailing President Mobutu Sese Seko, who has ruled the country for over 30 years, from power.</p>
<p>But he said it was too soon to celebrate.</p>
<p>&quot;We've not yet finished the job. The war is not finished. Kinshasa is not yet taken. We have to push this war and go on with our struggle against Mobutu to the end.&quot;</p>
<p>When Kabila urged parents to send their sons to his army and asked who was ready to join, hundreds of hands shot up.</p>
<p>On Friday Kabila ruled out protracted talks with Mobutu, saying he would only attend a short ceremony on the transfer of power. He said his forces would march on Kinshasa if Mobutu declined to give up power.</p>
<p>The rebel leader flew back to Lubumbashi on Thursday from an overnight trip to South Africa, where he had held a new round of peace talks with President Nelson Mandela in an attempt to reach a peaceful solution to the six-month-old war against Mobutu.</p>
<p>Unlike Monday, the day of Kabila's triumphant return to his native province, crowds lining the city's main streets on Thursday simply stared after his convoy of vehicles, without waving or cheering.</p>
<p>The thrill of revolution which last week gripped the once elegant city, formerly known as Elisabethville, was diluted by uncertainty, which locals said would not be dispelled until Kabila appeared in public.</p>
<p>Many of Kabila's soldiers are foreigners here, either from distant parts of sprawling Zaire, or from other African countries widely believed to be covertly helping the revolution that aims to topple Mobutu.</p>
<p>Advance men for Kabila's Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire (AFDL) arrived on Sunday and promptly upset the influential regional UFERI party by firing governor Kyungu wa Kumwanza and announcing the appointment of an interim governor who has lived in Belgium since the 1970s.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUBUMBASHI, Zaire"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
