<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522692" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peruvians honor captive priest on his birthday.</title>
<headline>Peruvians honor captive priest on his birthday.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dozens of Peruvian teachers and students on Friday marked the 65th birthday of a priest who turned down the chance of freedom to stay with the 72 hostages in Lima, saying his courage set an example.</p>
<p>The teachers and students from the university where Father Juan Julio Wicht teaches, attended a Mass for the priest who chose to stay with the hostages who have been held under the gun by Marxist rebels for 122 days.</p>
<p>They then marched to within a few blocks of the Japanese ambassador's residence, site of the crisis, where they sang happy birthday to Wicht.</p>
<p>&quot;He is an example to us, as not just anyone would have done this and risked their life this way,&quot; said 18-year-old student Fiorella Lizama, one of the marchers.</p>
<p>A Jesuit priest and economics professor, Wicht was offered a chance to leave the residence in late December along with 225 hostages but chose to stay.</p>
<p>&quot;I prefer to remain to help the hostages spiritually. I don't have any family,&quot; the priest was quoted as saying by former hostages.</p>
<p>Despite their ordeal, the captives are in reasonably good health and keep in touch with their families through twice- weekly written messages and special radio broadcasts.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, shuttle diplomacy to persuade the 20-odd heavily armed Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement (MRTA) guerrillas to give up their fight and free their captives continued on Friday.</p>
<p>Archbishop Juan Luis Cipriani and Canadian Ambassador Anthony Vincent, both members of a three-man commission overseeing talks, held talks with government representative Domingo Palermo. There was no comment on the negotiations.</p>
<p>The main sticking point remains the MRTA demand for the release of hundreds of jailed comrades. President Alberto Fujimori has publicly ruled out this demand although sources close to the talks suggest the government may be prepared to free some lesser MRTA prisoners to avoid bloodshed.</p>
<p>In a surprise move, the Red Cross said Minnig's number two, Jean Pierre Sharer, was asked by the Peruvian government to leave the country this week.</p>
<p>The reasons for the decision were not clear and senior Red Cross officials will come to Peru next week to demand an explanation from the authorities, he said said spokesman Steve Anderson.</p>
<p>The Red Cross has supplied food and medical help for the captives, most in their 40s and 50s, imprisoned in the squashed, sweltering confines of the house since it was seized by the guerrillas Dec. 17.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
