<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522633" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Mobutu's allies urge elections, Kabila urges war.</title>
<headline>Mobutu's allies urge elections, Kabila urges war.</headline>
<byline>William Wallis</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Loyal political allies rallied to the side of embattled President Mobutu Sese Seko on Saturday after calls by Western powers for him to surrender power to prevent civil war reaching Zaire's teeming capital.</p>
<p>Mobutu's associates urged Western powers to use their influence to win a ceasefire to pave the way for elections instead of pressing Mobutu to step aside.</p>
<p>But rebel leader Laurent Kabila told a rally of some 10,000 people in second city of Lubumbashi that there would be no compromise: Mobutu and his hangers-on must go.</p>
<p>&quot;It won't take long. We'll be in Kinshasa very soon. We're only 200 km (120 miles) away from Kinshasa. Now join the army and fight like men so we can finish this thing,&quot; he said in a two-and-a-half hour speech in Swahili mixed with French.</p>
<p>In the capital the president of Mobutu's FPC political alliance, Idambituo Bakato, directed his attack mainly at Zaire's former colonial ruler Belgium and the United States, which on Friday ordered dependents of its embassy staff in Zaire to leave.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not for Western countries to decide who rules Zaire,&quot; he told a news conference in Kinshasa.</p>
<p>Mobutu's fate has hung in the balance since Kabila suggested his forces were ready for a final advance on Kinshasa, the last stronghold of Zaire's ragged army. Rebels now hold about half the sprawling country.</p>
<p>South Africa finally persuaded Mobutu to meet Kabila for direct negotiations the rebel leader has long demanded as a way of ending the six-month war. But diplomats are sceptical about Kabila's genuine interest in reaching any compromise given his overwhelming military advantage on the ground.</p>
<p>As part of ongoing efforts by Zaire to win regional support, Benin's President Mathieu Kerekou was due to meet Mobutu on Sunday, presidential aides said. In Lome, the capital of Togo, Zaire's Foreign Minister Kamanda Wa Kamanda was still pressing for negotiations.</p>
<p>Meanwhile in Lubumbashi, Kabila spoke for the first time to the people of the largest city so far captured by the rebels, drilling home the lesson that Mobutu had plundered the country for the past 32 years while holding supreme power through a policy of divide-and-rule, larded with corruption.</p>
<p>Kabila bore down on Zaire's opposition parties, telling the people his Alliance for the Democratic Liberation of Congo-Zaire (AFDL) would not pause in its mission simply to accommodate people who effectively collaborated with Mobtutu.</p>
<p>&quot;What have the opposition political parties liberated? They haven't even liberated themselves,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Rejecting speculation that he might be ready to find compromise with Mobutu if the two meet next week in South Africa, Kabila repeated that all he was ready to do for Mobutu was assure his safety, once he has &quot;signed his resignation&quot;.</p>
<p>While Mobutu's camp is pushing for elections, even some of his supporters doubt his health would allow him to prolong his 32-year rule. Mobutu had cancer surgery in Switzerland last August and is still undergoing treatment.</p>
<p>Military analysts say the rebels are likely to continue building pressure on Mobutu by overrunning towns in the province of Bandundu, which neighbours Kinshasa on its Western flank and supplies most of the capital's domestic food needs.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
