<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522666" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: Late Ukraine budget risks aid,investor confidence - Sachs.</title>
<headline>Late Ukraine budget risks aid,investor confidence - Sachs.</headline>
<byline>Irene Marushko</byline>
<dateline>KIEV 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A top economic adviser to Ukraine warned on Saturday the country could lose confidence of Western funding bodies and investors and even risked economic collapse if it did not pass its budget and tax reform package quickly.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that the president, parliament and government could agree to work every day around the clock to fix this crisis,&quot; Jeffrey Sachs, director of the Harvard Institute for International Development, told a news conference.</p>
<p>The tax reforms and budget, which was due January 1 and would pave the way for a $2.5 to $3 billion long-term credit from the International Monetary Fund (IMF), has been stuck between government and the largely conservative parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope everyone understands this kind of waiting game is vary dangerous for the country. It's not true that Ukraine has all the time in the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Harvard professor, who has advised the Polish and Russian governments on market reforms, was speaking a week before the former Soviet republic of 52 million people was due to start a nine-day holiday declared by the government.</p>
<p>Sachs said failure to adopt tax reforms and the budget could halt and even reverse some $3.5 billion in Western funding aid agreed last year with the IMF and donor nations, on condition that President Leonid Kuchma's 1994 reform programme move ahead.</p>
<p>&quot;The current financial crisis, which is terrible enough, would get worse,&quot; Sachs said.</p>
<p>Nearly six years after independence Ukraine has yet to report economic growth, foreign investment has totalled only $1.4 billion, the shadow economy has expanded, there are few exports, and a $3.1 billion debt owed to workers is growing.</p>
<p>&quot;The economic situation is terrible,&quot; Sachs said, adding the sole &quot;glimmers of progress&quot; were slowed inflation, forecast at about 25 percent this year from 39.7 percent in 1996, and successful introduction of the new hryvnia currency last year.</p>
<p>He said successful passage of the tough budget, whose delays led reformist Viktor Pynzenyk to quit as deputy prime minister in charge of the economy this month, could lead to growth -- forecast at one percent this year after the economy contracted 10 percent in 1996.</p>
<p>Sachs said its delay was also reversing a recent trend of foreign investor confidence which started late last year, when international buyers purchased an estimated $500 million on the Treasury bill market as they expected an injection of IMF funds.</p>
<p>Foreign investor complaints about an unwelcoming investment climate in Ukraine have grown recently.</p>
<p>&quot;I meet more foreigners leaving Ukraine than I do coming into Ukraine right now,&quot; Sachs said. &quot;There are too many bribes, too many taxes, and too much instability.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
