<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522772" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. budget pact possible next week, leader says.</title>
<headline>U.S. budget pact possible next week, leader says.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Clinton administration and Congress might agree on balancing the U.S. budget by mid-week, the House Budget Committee chairman said Saturday, but if not the Republican majority &quot;will proceed forward with our own program.&quot;</p>
<p>Chairman John Kasich said on CNN's &quot;Evans and Novak&quot; program that an agreement would make it easier for Republicans to achieve goals like tax cuts.</p>
<p>Kasich, an Ohio Republican, compared the budget negotiations to the back-and-forth, offer and counteroffer involved in selling a house.</p>
<p>&quot;And we're kind of in the middle of each other's offers, and I will tell you that we will have a decision, I believe, by the close of business on Wednesday or early Thursday,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;If not, we will proceed forward with our own program.&quot;</p>
<p>Negotiators had set an informal deadline of this week for a pact, but agreed Thursday to allow more time for the two-week-old discussions.</p>
<p>Talks were to resume Wednesday and include the thorny issues of slowing the growth of the cost of Medicare and Medicaid health programs and the gap between Republican and Democratic tax-cut proposals.</p>
<p>&quot;The progress we've made so far is encouraging, and I'm hopeful that a bipartisan balanced budget agreement can be reached,&quot; Clinton said at the start of a brief White House news conference Friday.</p>
<p>White House and congressional negotiators are trying to reach agreement on spending cuts that would bring the federal deficit to zero by 2002. The deficit was $107 billion last year.</p>
<p>With a budget pact, Kasich said, Republicans &quot;would get a sizable part of our agenda through.</p>
<p>&quot;If in fact we don't, then I think we will not get as much through in the area, for example, of tax cuts as I believe we could if we had an agreement.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
