<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522764" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Most of Grand Forks flees as Red River floods.</title>
<headline>Most of Grand Forks flees as Red River floods.</headline>
<byline>Greg Frost</byline>
<dateline>GRAND FORKS, N.D. 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rising floodwaters of the Red River forced most of this city's 50,000 citizens from their homes Saturday and residents were told that they will not be allowed to return for up to two weeks.</p>
<p>Emergency efforts were complicated by a fire that tore through a multi-story structure Saturday in swamped downtown Grand Forks. Officials said they had to evacuate 20 people from the building -- people who were supposed to have already left the area but had stubbornly remained.</p>
<p>&quot;The Fire Department cannot get to the building. Currently it's free-burning. The flames are coming out of the roof,&quot; said Jim Campbell of Grand Forks Emergency Operations.</p>
<p>Thick black smoke could be seen billowing from the structure, but it was not immediately known if anyone had been injured in the fire.</p>
<p>Officials said an unspecified number of residents in the mandatory evacuation areas have remained in their homes too long, making evacuation efforts more difficult and more dangerous.</p>
<p>Grand Forks Mayor Pat Owens imposed a curfew over mandatory evacuation areas and said police and National Guard troops would arrest any unauthorised people in those zones.</p>
<p>&quot;We urgently ask residents to leave voluntarily before they are in an emergency situation,&quot; Owens said. &quot;We have not lost any lives in this flood so far, and we desperately want to keep it that way.&quot;</p>
<p>Authorities estimated that the cold, murky water covered more than half of the city by Saturday afternoon. The Grand Forks water treatment plant was among the buildings flooded out, leaving the city without clean drinking water.</p>
<p>North Dakota Gov. Ed Schafer said he had asked the National Guard to bring in fresh water and purification systems.</p>
<p>&quot;Lack of services is going to make life difficult and perhaps dangerous for residents throughout the city, even those who are not inundated with water,&quot; Owens said. &quot;We urge residents to pack up their families and be prepared to leave the city for as much as two weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>A U.S. Air Force base 10 miles west of town was set to take in as many as 10,000 evacuees. Other shelters were open at three eastern North Dakota colleges, the closest of which was 35 miles to the south. Long lines of traffic headed west out of the city.</p>
<p>Seventy-five miles (100 km) upstream at Fargo, Mayor Bruce Furness said approximately 500 homes would wind up on the wrong side of a new flood dike and could be swamped. Furness asked citizens in this area to remain calm, but there were reports of angry homeowners threatening a court injunction to stop construction of the contingency dike.</p>
<p>But city officials said later in the day that thousands of people had responded to calls for volunteers to work the dikes.</p>
<p>In Grand Forks, Tom Powers, 42, was among those forced out of his home by the floodwaters in the darkness of Saturday morning. He said water was up to the door of his truck as he drove away.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm unemployed. I have no insurance,&quot; Powers said as he gazed out at the still, brown water that has invaded half the city. &quot;I guess one of the good things is that I didn't own the house. I rent.&quot;</p>
<p>Witnesses said waist-high water was lapping up against storefront businesses in the flooded-out downtown area.</p>
<p>The flood shut all three bridges connecting Grand Forks to its sister city, East Grand Forks, Minnesota. The bridge closures meant that the Red River was impassable for vehicles between Fargo, North Dakota and the Canadian border -- a distance of about 150 miles.</p>
<p>The floods, unleashed by the thaw of a record winter snowfall, have covered thousands of acres in the valley of the Red River of the North along its flat and gently sloping course toward Canada.</p>
<p>The Red River rose to about 53 feet Saturday at Grand Forks, nearly three feet (one metre) above a record set in 1897 and more than 24 feet (seven meters) above flood stage.</p>
<p>The National Weather Service said it now expects the Red River to crest Saturday in Grand Forks at 54.0 feet.</p>
<p>At least one group of people took a small degree of satisfaction from the disaster. University of North Dakota President Kendall Baker cancelled the rest of the school's academic year Saturday, sending approximately 11,000 students on an early summer vacation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GRAND FORKS, N.D."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
