<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522706" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Seoul police fire tear gas to end street protest.</title>
<headline>Seoul police fire tear gas to end street protest.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>About 3,000 South Korean students clashed violently with riot police in central Seoul on Saturday as they tried to march toward the presidential Blue House, demanding the resignation of the president, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Riot police fired tear gas at the protesters to disperse them. Students fought back with rocks.</p>
<p>The students gathered in downtown Seoul to protest against a corruption scandal that has shattered President Kim Young-sam's reputation and implicated his second son, Hyun-chul.</p>
<p>&quot;Overthrow Kim Young-sam. Arrest his son, Hyun-chul&quot; students shouted, waving banners.</p>
<p>Witnesses saw riot police chasing and beating dozens of students before dragging them away to a police station.</p>
<p>Citizens on the street protested against the police beatings and tried to prevent a police bus with arrested students from passing, witnesses said.</p>
<p>The clash came on the anniversary of massive demonstrations in 1960 that toppled the nation's first president, Syngman Rhee. The anniversary is often marked by violent protests from students.</p>
<p>Several of President Kim's closest aides are on trial for corruption in connection with a loans-for-kickback scandal surrounding the collapse in January of Hanbo Steel Co, the country's second-largest steelmaker.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
