<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522748" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: U.S. pilot in Egypt on way to recreate Earhart trip.</title>
<headline>U.S. pilot in Egypt on way to recreate Earhart trip.</headline>
<byline>Christine Hauser</byline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. pilot Linda Finch on Saturday started the Egypt leg of her trip to recreate Amelia Earhart's 1937 attempt to fly around the world.</p>
<p>Wearing angel medals on her shoulders and with her daily prayers said, she braved thunderstorms over the Atlantic and made stops including Spain, Tunisia and Senegal before touching down in Luxor, the ancient capital of temples and monuments.</p>
<p>&quot;I always wanted to fly older airplanes,&quot; said the pilot of more than 20 years. But she said she was also inspired by Earhart, the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
<p>&quot;I think so many people don't do the things they are capable of doing. That it's easy to get habits and not take chances, to step out, do something different,&quot; she told Reuters by telephone. &quot;This is a good way to reinforce the message.&quot;</p>
<p>Finch spoke to Reuters on Saturday from Luxor, where late on Friday she landed her 1935 Lockheed Electra 10E.</p>
<p>The restored airplane is the same model used by Earhart, who completed 35,400 km (22,000 miles) of her journey before vanishing on the leg from New Guinea to Howland Island.</p>
<p>Just days after her 46th birthday, Finch left California in March to try to retrace a route similar to that of Earhart, whose memory inspired Finch most as she crossed the Atlantic.</p>
<p>&quot;It was long. It took us almost 13 hours. We had thunderstorms that we circumnavigated,&quot; she said. &quot;It was very dark. There was a little bit of moon but there was no way to tell the difference between the water and the sky. It was like we were in a black hole.</p>
<p>&quot;I guess the thing that struck me was thinking of Amelia flying across the Atlantic. You know when there are thunderstorms around, the plane doesn't fly straight and stable and you actually have to hand fly it carefully to make altitude and heading,&quot; the Texas businesswoman said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was so dark and alone, with nobody else there,&quot; she said of Earhart's ocean flight. &quot;And to think of her hand-flying the airplane for more than 13 hours -- and she had fuel problems.</p>
<p>&quot;To think about how hard that flight must have been ..and to have done it anyway to prove to others that they could do things too, that's when that thought really struck me.&quot;</p>
<p>Engine makers Pratt &amp; Whitney paid $4.5 million for aircraft restoration, an education programme and the &quot;World Flight 1997&quot; trip, a 48,000-km (30,000-mile) journey to 20 countries in five continents expected to take two and a half months. Finch is due to leave on Thursday for Dubai and return to California in May.</p>
<p>She spent part of her first day on the ground in Egypt organising flight permits for the rest of her journey. During her stay in Egypt Finch will fix a flat tyre, sight-see in Luxor, and organise satellite communications to transmit photographs to the journey's Web site.</p>
<p>In the air it's a different story. Finch and her navigator during the flight monitor fuel, engine gauges and temperatures and talk on the radio. &quot;Of course on the Atlantic there's not a lot of people to talk to,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Pre-flight preparations include reading the Bible in the morning. In the cockpit she wears two angel pins given to her by her grandmother and one of her three children, and carries a memento from her church and photographs of her family.</p>
<p>&quot;I really do trust God every day. And I certainly miss my children terribly,&quot; Finch said. &quot;I feel like they're forever away and it will be forever before I see them again.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I never thought that I might not make it,&quot; she said. I've always thought it would succeed.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
