<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522753" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SAUDI ARABIA: Pilgrims mark end of Haj in Saudi Arabia.</title>
<headline>Pilgrims mark end of Haj in Saudi Arabia.</headline>
<byline>Abbas Salman</byline>
<dateline>MECCA, Saudi Arabia 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hundreds of thousands of Moslems in white robes prayed on Saturday at the Grand Mosque, marking the end of the annual haj pilgrimage in which a blaze killed at least 343 people and injured 1,537.</p>
<p>They shuffled shoulder-to-shoulder seven times around the black, cube-shaped Kaaba covered by gold-embroidered black silk at the centre of the mosque, Islam's holiest shrines.</p>
<p>Many who could not find a place inside the crowded mosque for the ensuing farewell sermon, prayed outside the gates of the multi-million dollar premise under blazing sun. Moslems around the world face the Kaaba when praying.</p>
<p>Earlier, pilgrims hurled stones at three pillars symbolising the devil in Mena, 11 km (seven miles) off Mecca and site of the fire that swept through a vast pilgrim camp on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Some 535 of the pilgrims who were injured in the inferno took part in the final haj rituals, Saudi Health Minister Osama bin Abdul-Majid Shobokashi told the official news agency SPA.</p>
<p>He said only 25 of the 1,537 injured men and women were still at hospitals receiving medical treatment. The rest were all discharged.</p>
<p>The stoning was the final ritual of haj, which reached its climax on Wednesday at Mount Arafat where the Prophet Mohammad gave his last sermon 14 centuries ago.</p>
<p>Police helicopters kept vigil as thousands of cars and busses ferried pilgrims from Mena for final prayers at the Grand Mosque.</p>
<p>Later, many clutching their belongings left for Jeddah airport on the Red Sea to take flights back home while others headed to nearby Medina to visit Prophet Mohammad's mosque.</p>
<p>Some two million Moslems, half of them who came to Mecca from various parts of Saudi Arabia, performed this year's haj which ended on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Our transport plan was 100 percent successful,&quot; said one police officer.</p>
<p>But diplomats reached by telephone said they were still waiting for Saudi Arabia to list victims of the fire as officials were still struggling to track down the missing and indentify the dead, many of them burnt beyond recognition.</p>
<p>They said most of the dead were from the Indian subcontinent. The fire, which consumed 70,000 tents, engulfed the Iranian, Syrian, Lebanese, Egyptian, Sudanese, Yemeni and Moroccan sections of the encampment.</p>
<p>The blaze was the latest tragedy to strike the pilgrimage to Mecca, which able-bodied Moslems are obliged to perform at least once if they can afford it. In 1990, 1,426 pilgrims were crushed in a stampede in a tunnel and in 1994, another 270 people died in a stampede.</p>
<p>Riyadh has given no cause for Tuesday's blaze apart from saying it was an accident, but diplomats and witnesses said it was caused by gas cylinders.</p>
<p>In an annual joint message to pilgrims on Friday, King Fahd and Crown Prince Abdullah told Moslems that the kingdom was committed to comprehensive Middle East peace.</p>
<p>They said Saudi Arabia had repeatedly condemned Israel's building of settlements in Arab East Jerusalem and any moves against the rights of its inhabitants.</p>
<p>They also called on Moslems to look to the Koran to settle their differences and urged the Islamic world to boost cooperation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MECCA, Saudi Arabia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SAUDI ARABIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
