<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522780" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton says U.S. will never forget &quot;tragic day&quot;.</title>
<headline>Clinton says U.S. will never forget &quot;tragic day&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton told Oklahoma City on Saturday that America will never forget &quot;the tragic day&quot; two years ago when a truck bomb blew up a federal building there and killed 168 people.</p>
<p>As Oklahoma City observed the two-year anniversary of the bombing with 168 seconds of silence for the victims, the White House released an April 14 letter from Clinton to the Oklahoma City Memorial Foundation.</p>
<p>&quot;Our nation will never forget that tragic day...when we first learned of the bombing of the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building in Oklahoma City, and we will always remember the courage shown by the citizens of your strong and united city during that dark time,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>He said that &quot;in uniting around the citizens of Oklahoma City, our nation proved once again that no force of hatred or terrorism can ever defeat the American spirit.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton said he backed efforts by the foundation to establish a memorial at the bomb site to remember the victims as well as &quot;those whose lives were changed forever on April 19, 1995.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I know that, by honouring our fellow Americans in this way, we can help to further the healing and restore hope for a brighter, more secure future,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>White House spokesman Mike McCurry said the White House and other federal agencies had taken &quot;appropriate and necessary&quot; security arrangements in light of the anniversary.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a greater attention to security and reminders about the need to be vigilant and alert,&quot; he said on Friday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
