<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522744" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SAUDI ARABIA: Pilgrims seek clues on relatives after haj blaze.</title>
<headline>Pilgrims seek clues on relatives after haj blaze.</headline>
<byline>Abbas Salman</byline>
<dateline>MENA, Saudi Arabia 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Throngs of Moslems performed on Friday the final rituals of this year's tragic haj pilgrimage in which a ravaging blaze killed 343 people and injured 1,290.</p>
<p>But some pilgrims were still struggling to find relatives who went missing in the mayhem.</p>
<p>&quot;Four of my relatives travelled here from the United States to perform haj. I saw them before the fire but now I can't find them,&quot; said Elias, a 35-year-old Pakistani.</p>
<p>He and other pilgrims were seeking clues on the whereabouts of relatives who went missing after Tuesday's fire which swept through 70,000 tents at a haj compound outside the holy city of Mecca in Saudi Arabia.</p>
<p>&quot;I miss him. I have been looking for him since the fire,&quot; said one Indian woman desperate for information on her husband.</p>
<p>In Tehran, Iranian head of judiciary Ayatollah Mohammad Yazdi said the pilgrims' own negligence might have caused the fire but added that it was &quot;the duty of the (Saudi) government to protect the lives of pilgrims and their safety&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;We say to Saudi leaders that we ought not every year witness such accidents...in the house of God and the safe sanctuary of the divine shrine,&quot; said Yazdi in a Friday prayer sermon broadcast on Tehran radio.</p>
<p>Iran said none of its 72,000 pilgrims were hurt in the fire.</p>
<p>Police helicopters flew overhead while pilgrims in seamless white robes hurled stones at three pillars symbolising the devil on the outskirts of Mecca -- the last ritual of haj which climaxed on Wednesday at Mount Arafat where the prophet Mohammad gave his last sermon 14 centuries ago.</p>
<p>Some two million Moslems celebrated the Eid al-Adha feast at the end of the haj pilgrimage this year.</p>
<p>Trucks delivered bottles of water and milk to pilgrims, many of them carrying umbrellas to ward off the scorching sun.</p>
<p>Ambulances ferried to hospitals pilgrims hit by illness and fatigue from hours of walking between holy sites in the heat.</p>
<p>Tense relations between Saudi Arabia and Iran usually take a turn for the worse every year over the staging during haj of a political rally by Iranian pilgrims.</p>
<p>Radical Shi'ite Iran says Moslems should air their grievances during haj, mainly through rallies to denounce Israel and the United States as enemies of Islam. Conservative Sunni Saudi Arabia says the pilgrimage is purely religious and should not be politicised and bans all political activities during haj.</p>
<p>Iran has said pilgrims twice held the rallies this year. There was no word from Saudi authorities on the report.</p>
<p>On Thursday, a small fire broke out but was quickly extinguished in the same pilgrim tent city where the earlier blaze erupted.</p>
<p>The Saudi civil defence authority said the fire, which was extinguished in minutes, caused no damage at the encampment in Mena, 11 km (seven miles) from Mecca.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MENA, Saudi Arabia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SAUDI ARABIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
