<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522791" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mafia figures indicted in Indian gaming operation.</title>
<headline>Mafia figures indicted in Indian gaming operation.</headline>
<dateline>SAN DIEGO 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three reputed organized crime figures and seven others have been indicted on federal charges for allegedly trying to gain control of gambling on the Rincon Indian reservation near San Diego, the U.S. government announced Friday.</p>
<p>The indictments were announced jointly by U.S. Attorneys Alan Bersin in San Diego and Frederick Thieman in Pittsburgh. Three of the five indicted in Pittsburgh were among the eight indicted in San Diego.</p>
<p>According to the Pittsburgh indictment, Henry Albert Zottola and Pasquale Ferruccio are reputed members of the Pittsburgh organized crime family and Dominic Strollo is alleged to have a strong connection to the family.</p>
<p>Referring to Zottola and Ferruccio, Assistant U.S. Attorney Mitchell Dembin, in charge of the San Diego investigation, said, &quot;These are very significant players. They are of 'capo' level.&quot;</p>
<p>Also named in the indictments were Ruth Calac, a tribal member who, according to the charges, was bribed to help members of the crime family gain access to the reservation, and John Francis Conley of San Diego, who supplied the equipment. Others indicted allegedly worked for Conley.</p>
<p>According to the indictments, an organization known as the Columbia Group Inc. used money from illegal gambling activity in Pennsylvania and Ohio to invest in video poker and other equipment on the reservation beginning in 1991.</p>
<p>The indictments also charge the group got a written agreement from the Rincon tribe to operate the casino in Valley Center, 45 miles north of San Diego, while keeping its connection to organized crime a secret.</p>
<p>The group brought in more than 400 slot machines. However, a civil lawsuit in 1995 by the U.S. Attorney's Office, challenging the use of the equipment, eventually closed down the casino.</p>
<p>Bersin said the indictments were &quot;a message loud and clear to these remnants of organized crime who seek to infiltrate San Diego County. You will be identified, you will be apprehended, you will be prosecuted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The San Diego indictments charge the group with bribery, conspiracy to defraud the United States, money laundering, unlawful transportation of gambling devices, witness tampering and obstruction of justice.</p>
<p>The Pennsylvania indictment says three of those charged concealed their connections from the National Gaming Commission. The indictment also charges them with witness tampering, three counts of filing false tax returns and conspiracy to launder $2.1 million.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN DIEGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
