<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522765" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: North Korea shuns peace talks for second day.</title>
<headline>North Korea shuns peace talks for second day.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>For the second straight day, North Korea failed on Saturday to resume scheduled talks with the United States and South Korea on a Korean peninsula peace proposal; the future of the discussions was uncertain.</p>
<p>In an effort to keep their initiative from collapsing, the Americans and South Koreans persuaded the North Koreans to hold lower-level contacts aimed at getting the crucial senior-level dialogue back on track.</p>
<p>But that three-hour effort was unsuccessful and a U.S. spokesman announced &quot;there will no meeting at the heads of delegation level today.&quot;</p>
<p>The chief U.S. negotiator, Charles Kartman, flew back to Washington. However, some of his assistants remained in New York to continue working-level contacts with the North Koreans.</p>
<p>There is &quot;some possibility&quot; senior negotiators from the three sides would meet on Monday but &quot;nothing has been agreed at this point,&quot; the U.S. spokesman said.</p>
<p>He would not discuss the substance of the delay. &quot;The bottom line is they (North Koreans) don't feel they are in a position yet to come and meet at the delegations' heads level and provide their response,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Han Song Ryol, minister-counsellor at North Korea's mission to the United Nations, told Reuters his delegation was awaiting directions from Pyongyang.</p>
<p>Interagency-consultations in Pyongyang and the fact that it is the weekend, when officials cannot easily be reached, are the reason for the delay, he said.</p>
<p>Han said his delegation proposed holding another meeting on Monday, but he did not know if South Korean negtotiators, who originally planned to return to Seoul on Friday night, would stay on. The South Koreans were not immedately available to comment.</p>
<p>The three delegations, headed by senior negotiators, first met on Wednesday to hear the North's formal response to a year-old U.S.-South Korean proposal for four-party peace talks that would finally close the books on the 1950-53 Korean War by replacing the fraying armistice with a peace treaty.</p>
<p>Although the discussions were inconclusive, negotiators reported &quot;encouraging progress&quot; and agreed to resume talks on Friday. But the North Koreans, saying they awaited instructions from Pyongyang, never showed for Friday's meeting, which was re-set for Saturday. The North Koreans again failed to appear.</p>
<p>U.S. officials privately have said Pyongyang essentially accepted the peace talks proposal on Wednesday but then tied its acceptance to demands for additional food assistance.</p>
<p>On Thursday, however, U.S. officials ruled out the possibility Washington or Seoul would announce new food aid before Pyongyang conclusively answered the peace proposal.</p>
<p>All negotiations between the United States and North Korea since the two sides began intensive contacts in 1993 have been difficult.</p>
<p>Pyongyang's Stalinist regime has been preoccupied with increasingly severe food shortages. Two years of floods have worsened systemic economic problems and the impoverished North has insisted on more and more international help.</p>
<p>After some scepticism, it has been widely accepted that the North has a serious problem that could soon reach famine stage.</p>
<p>Experts say the country may need 2.3 million tons of food this year. The U.N. World Food Programme appealed for 200,000 metric tons of food, with Washington offering one-quarter of that amount, including $15 million pledged last Monday.</p>
<p>But U.S. officials have said Pyongyang cannot expect massive assistance until it enters peace talks and begins to defuse tensions on the volatile Korean peninsula.</p>
<p>Peace talks, if accepted by Pyongyang, might not begin until June or July. China would be the fourth participant along with the United States, South Korea and North Korea.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
