<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522746" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SAUDI ARABIA: Pilgrims start leaving Saudi Arabia at end of Haj.</title>
<headline>Pilgrims start leaving Saudi Arabia at end of Haj.</headline>
<byline>Abbas Salman</byline>
<dateline>MECCA, Saudi Arabia 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hundreds of thousands of white robed Moslems left Saudi Arabia on Saturday at the end of the annual haj pilgrimage in which a blaze killed at least 343 people and injured 1,537.</p>
<p>Diplomats said they were still waiting for Saudi Arabia to list victims of the fire as officials were still struggling to track down the missing and identify the dead, many of them burnt beyond recognition.</p>
<p>About 535 of those injured in the fire took part in the final haj rituals, Saudi Health Minister Osama bin Abdul-Majid Shobokashi told the official news agency SPA.</p>
<p>He said only 25 of the 1,537 injured were still at hospitals receiving medical treatment. The rest were all discharged.</p>
<p>To mark the end of the haj many pilgrims prayed at the Grand Mosque, before leaving for Jeddah airport on the Red Sea to fly home.</p>
<p>They shuffled shoulder-to-shoulder seven times around the black, cube-shaped Kaaba, Islam's holiest shrine covered by gold-embroidered black silk at the centre of the mosque.</p>
<p>Many who could not find a place inside the crowded mosque for the farewell sermon prayed outside the gates under a blazing sun.</p>
<p>Earlier, pilgrims hurled stones at three pillars symbolising the devil in Mena, eleven kms (seven miles) from Mecca and site of the fire that swept through a vast pilgrim camp on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The stoning was the final ritual of the haj, which reached its climax on Wednesday at Mount Arafat where the Prophet Mohammad gave his last sermon fourteen centuries ago.</p>
<p>Police helicopters kept vigil as thousands of cars and buses ferried pilgrims from Mena for final prayers at the Grand Mosque. Traffic moved at a snail's pace.</p>
<p>Many then left for Jeddah airport, while others headed to Medina to visit the mosque of the Prophet Mohammad.</p>
<p>Officials said 1.8 million Moslems performed the pilgrimage this year, more than 1.2 million of them from abroad.</p>
<p>Most of those killed in the fire were from the Indian subcontinent. The blaze destroyed 70,000 tents and engulfed the Iranian, Syrian, Lebanese, Egyptian, Sudanese, Yemeni and Moroccan sections of the encampment.</p>
<p>It was the latest tragedy to strike the haj, which able-bodied Moslems are obliged to perform at least once if they can afford it.</p>
<p>In 1990, 1,426 pilgrims were crushed in a stampede in a tunnel and in 1994, another 270 people died in a stampede.</p>
<p>Riyadh has said nothing about the cause of the fire apart from saying it was an accident. Diplomats and witnesses said it was caused by gas cylinders.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MECCA, Saudi Arabia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SAUDI ARABIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
