<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522754" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Arafat to renew security contacts with Israel.</title>
<headline>Arafat to renew security contacts with Israel.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Palestinian President Yasser Arafat has agreed to resume security contacts with Israel severed last month when the Jewish state broke ground on a new settlement in Arab East Jerusalem, a PLO official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;President Arafat agreed to renew security coordination with Israel,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The official, who did not want to be identified, said the decision was taken during the visit of U.S. special envoy Dennis Ross to the region this week.</p>
<p>The PLO cut off security contacts with Israel when it began work on a Jewish settlement in East Jerusalem, dealing the peace process one of its most serious setbacks since its launch in 1991.</p>
<p>The construction sparked widespread clashes between Palestinian stone-throwers and Israeli troops in the West Bank. Three days after the building began a Palestinian bomber killed three Israeli women at a Tel Aviv cafe.</p>
<p>Arafat had said earlier he would renew security cooperation only after Israel agreed to freeze the settlement plan.</p>
<p>Ross, who is on his way back to Washington, managed to get Israeli and Palestinian security chiefs to meet to discuss security cooperation.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton said on Friday it was vital to keep pressing ahead to bring the sides together.</p>
<p>&quot;The important thing is we get this security cooperation up and going and then we just keep plugging ahead,&quot; Clinton told reporters at a briefing in the White House.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
