<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522702" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai PM says Burma's leader may resign-paper.</title>
<headline>Thai PM says Burma's leader may resign-paper.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Thai newspaper on Saturday quoted the country's Prime Minister Chavalit Yongchaiyudh as saying his Burmese counterpart General Than Shwe was considering giving up his top position.</p>
<p>Chavalit said he believed Than Shwe -- who is also chairman of Burma's ruling State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) -- did not want to stay on in the position and was thinking of retiring, according to the report in The Nation newspaper.</p>
<p>Chavalit, who is also defence minister, is known to have close ties to SLORC leaders.</p>
<p>Burmese government officials were not immediately avaiable for comment on the report.</p>
<p>But commentaries in the official media said the SLORC was strong and united.</p>
<p>&quot;The SLORC is one with the people though it is a military government,&quot; the commentary said.</p>
<p>&quot;(SLORC leaders) are united, have mutual love and discipline with their hands firmly linked, and respect and uphold their responsibilities for the nation and people,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The Thai prime minister was quoted as saying Than Shwe could not yet quit due to problems with a reshuffle in the lower-level Burmese military hierarchy.</p>
<p>&quot;He (Than Shwe) is thinking of retiring, but there are some hitches at the lower level which require the further rearrangement of officials,&quot; Chavalit said.</p>
<p>&quot;General Than Shwe does not want to stay on in his position, which is somewhat like the case of General Saw Maung. These people are not bad people,&quot; he said on Friday during a visit to Kanchanaburi near Thailand's western border with Burma.</p>
<p>General Saw Maung headed the SLORC when it took power in September 1988 after crushing pro-democracy protests in which thousands were killed or imprisoned. But he quit as SLORC's top general in 1992.</p>
<p>In late 1988, Chavalit visited Burma to meet the country's top generals despite an internationally-imposed isolation of the country when the military seized power.</p>
<p>The Thai premier plans to visit Burma in the near future, the Nation said without giving further details.</p>
<p>Some analysts and diplomats have speculated that there might be a split within the secretive SLORC between hardliners and moderates which could lead to a restructuring of Burma's leadership in the future.</p>
<p>Than Shwe is considered a moderate leader within the SLORC, diplomats said.</p>
<p>Burmese military sources have denied rumours of any split.</p>
<p>Burma has recently been hit by religious unrest and a bomb attack at the home of the SLORC's hardline Secretary Two, General Tin Oo, which killed his daughter.</p>
<p>The country has also been fraught with image problems as it continues to curb the pro-democracy movement led by opposition leader Aung San Suu Kyi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BURMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
