<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522768" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Defense witnesses testify in U.S. Army rape case.</title>
<headline>Defense witnesses testify in U.S. Army rape case.</headline>
<byline>Deborah Funk</byline>
<dateline>ABERDEEN, Md. 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>A military judge Friday denied a defence request to dismiss 17 of 19 rape charges against Army Staff Sgt. Delmar Simpson, saying a jury should determine whether he is innocent or guilty.</p>
<p>The judge, Col. Paul Johnston, granted a request to dismiss four lesser charges, leaving Simpson facing 55 counts of sexual misconduct as his lawyers began to present their defence.</p>
<p>In denying the request to dismiss 17 of the rape counts, Johnston found that as a drill sergeant Simpson was in a position of authority over trainees, much like a parent, when the alleged acts occurred. &quot;He tells them when to get up, where to go, what to wear...,&quot; Johnston said.</p>
<p>Prosecutors argued Simpson's rank and authority allowed him to force female trainees to submit to him sexually against their will, even though some did not specifically resist.</p>
<p>While not a child, Johnston said, a trainee is a young adult conditioned to follow drill sergeants' orders or be subject to discipline. He said prosecutors had presented sufficient evidence to allow the charges to go to the jury.</p>
<p>But a visibly angry and frustrated defence attorney Frank Spinner argued that the women did not demonstrate a lack of consent essential to meet the definition of rape. He said the definition had been diluted and Simpson's position of authority and 6-foot, 4-inch stature made it easier for prosecutors to argue that he intimidated them into submission.</p>
<p>&quot;A woman in her own mind can think anything she wants and later claim it's rape. How is a man supposed to defend himself against that?&quot; Spinner asked.</p>
<p>&quot;Are the women so weak that they can't even open their mouths and say no?&quot; he went on. &quot;Has the law of rape become so paternalistic toward women so that now they don't even have to say no? Are trainees so ignorant that they can't distinguish between a drill sergeant telling them to run up a hill and lay down on a bed?&quot;</p>
<p>The defence presented its first witnesses in the afternoon and tried to prove that women trainees had nothing to fear in the Army if they filed complaints through the chain of command.</p>
<p>All five defence witnesses said that during training, soldiers knew that sex with a drill sergeant was not permitted and that they knew how to report complaints to a chain of command.</p>
<p>Defence witness Sgt. Maj. Mary Kyser said one of the alleged victims in the case had demonstrated in the past that she knew how to use the chain of command.</p>
<p>Two of the defence witnesses, who are also Simpson's victims, said he made advances toward them but they refused him and never reported the incident.</p>
<p>One of these witnesses also testified that one women Simpson is charged with raping would return from her trips to his office where the alleged assaults took place appearing happy.</p>
<p>Simpson, 32, has been charged with 19 counts of rape and 36 other counts including indecent exposure, battery and maltreatment involving 13 women. He has pleaded innocent to those charges but guilty to 11 counts of improper sexual intercourse with trainees and five of propositioning.</p>
<p>His is the first jury trial among 12 soldiers charged in the military's biggest sex scandal since the Navy's 1991 Tailhook affair and he has been charged with the most crimes. Four other cases were resolved through plea agreements or administrative proceedings.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ABERDEEN, Md."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
