<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522769" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Defense says police lack evidence in Cosby killing.</title>
<headline>Defense says police lack evidence in Cosby killing.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police investigating the murder of entertainer Bill Cosby's only son have little hard evidence against the accused killer, lawyers for the man charged in the killing said on Friday.</p>
<p>They said police have no recognisable fingerprints on the murder weapon and the only witness to the late-night shooting could not identify the suspect -- Mikhail &quot;Michael&quot; Markhasev -- in a lineup.</p>
<p>&quot;If they had a fingerprint and they had a (positive) lineup (identification), we'd be in worse shape,&quot; said lead defence attorney Charles Lindner. &quot;Obviously it's better for our case - the question is, what else have they got?&quot;</p>
<p>Lindner spoke before a hearing called by Los Angeles Superior Court Judge John Reid to discuss &quot;discovery&quot; -- the sharing of evidence between defence and prosecution.</p>
<p>After the hearing, lawyers on both sides declined to talk to reporters, saying Judge Reid had imposed a &quot;gag-order&quot; barring them from discussing the facts of the case.</p>
<p>Earlier, Lindner accused prosecutors of acting &quot;unethically&quot; by not sharing evidence. &quot;If this had occurred in federal court, the U.S. Attorney would be facing very serious sanctions for failure to comply with a judge's discovery order.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked why prosecutors had chosen to charge Markhasev after a secret grand jury hearing as opposed to a public preliminary hearing, Lindner said: &quot;Obviously the reason is what any defence attorney already knows -- you don't want to expose your witnesses to cross-examination.&quot;</p>
<p>Markhasev, an 18-year-old Ukrainian immigrant, has been charged with murdering Ennis Cosby on Jan. 16. The only son of Bill Cosby was shot by the side of a southern California freeway while he was changing a flat tire. Markhasev is due in court again on May 1 for continuation of his arraignment.</p>
<p>Another member of Markhasev's defence team earlier told reporters the prosecution appeared to have no hard evidence.</p>
<p>&quot;In any capital case, before you speak of executing somebody, you'd better make damn sure you've got the right guy,&quot; attorney Darren Kavinoky told a news conference. &quot;The caveat is -- we have not been provided with all discovery material.&quot;</p>
<p>The Los Angeles District Attorney's office declined to comment, saying it would try the case in court, rather than outside. It also said the defence had been given copies of all evidence in the case.</p>
<p>Commenting on reports that police found no usable fingerprints on the .38 calibre revolver police say is the  murder weapon, Kavinoky said: &quot;It's a critical piece of evidence -- or lack of evidence.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
