<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522751" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Turkish Cypriots make pilgrimage in divided Cyprus.</title>
<headline>Turkish Cypriots make pilgrimage in divided Cyprus.</headline>
<byline>Michele Kambas</byline>
<dateline>LARNACA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hundreds of Turkish Cypriots crossed the barbed wire dividing Cyprus on Saturday for their first pilgrimage to an Islamic mosque in Cyprus's south since a Turkish invasion in 1974.</p>
<p>Some 430 Turkish Cypriots took part in the pilgrimage to the Hala Sultan Mosque in the southern coastal town of Larnaca in the island's Greek Cypriot populated south, marking the Moslem celebration of Eid al-Adha.</p>
<p>Tight police security measures were taken throughout the day trip, organised by the Cypriot government as a goodwill gesture. The Hala Sultan Mosque was built in memory of Umm Haran, an aunt of the Prophet Mohammad.</p>
<p>In a reciprocal move by the Turkish Cypriots, a similar number of Greek Cypriots are due to visit the Apostolos Andreas Monastery on the north east tip of the island next week to celebrate the Greek Orthodox Easter. The event will also be a first.</p>
<p>&quot;UNFICYP welcome such operations and we are glad to assist them,&quot; said Waldemar Rokozsewski, a spokesman for the U.N. peacekeeping force in Cyprus. &quot;We believe what is scheduled for next week will go nicely as well.&quot;</p>
<p>Greeks and Turks on the island have been living apart since Turkey invaded Cyprus's north in 1974 in the wake of a brief Greek Cypriot coup in capital Nicosia engineered by the military ruling Greece.</p>
<p>Attempts to reunite the island under a federal umbrella have failed and the stalemate remains a source of tension between NATO partners Greece and Turkey.</p>
<p>The United Nations, which has maintained a presence on the island since shortly after the outbreak of bicommunal violence in 1963, is pushing for the resumption of direct talks between the two sides this summer.</p>
<p>Black clad Greek Cypriot women whose relatives have been missing since the invasion clambered onto the buses ferrying the Turkish Cypriots south with olive branches.</p>
<p>Turkish Cypriots responded by clapping and waving at the small crowd which gathered to watch them cross through the U.N.- controlled checkpoint.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not have anything against the Turkish Cypriots. Our grievance is with the occupation,&quot; said Greek Cypriot refugee Yiannoula Leondi, 65, referring to the presence of 30,000 Turkish troops based in northern Cyprus.</p>
<p>After praying at the mosque, Turkish Cypriot adults picnicked or collected salt which dried on the plain of a salt lake nearby as their children played in the shade of olive and palm trees.</p>
<p>&quot;Those of us who belong to the older generation want something good to happen but I don't know about these youngsters,&quot; said Turkish Cypriot pilgrim Mehmet Ali, 70, referring to younger generations on both sides who have never lived together.</p>
<p>Although the pilgrims appeared happy enough, some complained that the mosque was in a state of neglect, while others were angered after seeing, they said, a Greek Cypriot inside the mosque with his shoes on.</p>
<p>&quot;We are religious and this is not right,&quot; said Fatma Hussein, 64. &quot;These things here are not sacred just to the Turkish Cypriots but to all the world's Moslems.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LARNACA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
