<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522717" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: WEEK AHEAD-Asia stocks seen cautious, ignoring U.S..</title>
<headline>WEEK AHEAD-Asia stocks seen cautious, ignoring U.S..</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asian stocks are expected to trade quietly in the coming week, with little fallout forecast from a nervous Dow Jones Industrial Index, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;In Asia sentiment will remain cautious regardless of the Dow,&quot; said one head trader. &quot;Even if the Dow moves up, I don't think Asia will follow in a big way.&quot;</p>
<p>Hong Kong was the only Asian market expected to react to sudden moves on Wall Street in the coming week, with most other markets expected to stick to their ranges.</p>
<p>Hong Kong is considered the best bet in Asia this week, with red-chips -- companies active in China but managed and listed in Hong Kong -- offering lots of opportunity.</p>
<p>But many foreign funds said they were avoiding the action, which was locally driven and highly speculative.</p>
<p>The two most interesting regional markets, apart from Hong Kong, are those offering the least exposure to the uncertain U.S. rate outlook. However, markets in both Taiwan and South Korea are also the most inaccessible to foreign investors.</p>
<p>&quot;Both are at 28 times earnings and certainly not cheap, but within that there are some interesting opportunities,&quot; said Richard Nicholas, managing director at Hambro Pacific Fund Management in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>India also rated a mention at 12 times 1997 earnings. &quot;Forget the politics and buy the market,&quot; Nicholas advised.</p>
<p>Funds also said they had turned marginally less bearish on Thailand, which appears to be bottoming out.</p>
<p>However, the prospect of any company managing to increase earnings by more than five percent is remote, although some growth is possible from the current round of mergers and acquisitions in the troubled finance and banking sector -- a process dubbed the Bangkok Big Bang by one fund manager.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>TOKYO - Tokyo stocks are expected to test the upside cautiously in the coming week, backed by investor demand in a wider range of issues, including steel and chemical shares.</p>
<p>But profit-taking pressure is still strong, which could slow any rise in the key index above 18,500, brokers said.</p>
<p>On Friday, the 225-share Nikkei average closed at 18,352.14, up 505.16 points or 2.8 percent from its close on April 11. It had advanced for four consecutive days.</p>
<p>&quot;The firm tone will continue and the Nikkei 225 is likely to test 19,000,&quot; said Hiroyuki Nakai, chief investment strategist at Nikko Securities Co Ltd.</p>
<p>But Kazuo Shiogai, deputy branch manager at ING Baring Securities (Japan) Ltd, said there would be a line of selling above 18,000.</p>
<p>&quot;The Nikkei 225 would have to survive solid selling above 18,000,&quot; he said. &quot;It would trade in a narrow range between 17,500 and 18,500 for another week,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HONG KONG - Hong Kong stocks are seen trending in a broad range with a slight downward bias in the coming week, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;I am wary of being too bearish at this time,&quot; said David Robinson, regional investment strategist at HSBC James Capel. &quot;But I also think there will be a chance to buy blue chips at cheaper prices in a few weeks time.&quot;</p>
<p>The Hang Seng Index closed 24.95 points higher at 12,541.18 on turnover of HK$6.88 million on Friday. Activity was focused on only a handful of blue chips and a wide range of red chip China plays and second line issues.</p>
<p>Over the week, the Hang Seng Index added just 24.58 points, or 0.2 percent.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>TAIPEI - Taiwan share prices are seen consolidating in the coming week on worries over state financial policy, including selling of state-run commercial banks, brokers said.</p>
<p>Share prices could be hit by a flood of state bank equity, they said.</p>
<p>Another negative factor was the central bank's vow to look more closely at investment flows to ensure Taiwan capital is not being channelled illegally to rival China and that local banks' holdings are not improperly invested in stocks, they said.</p>
<p>A trading range of 8,000-8,400 is seen for next week.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>KUALA LUMPUR - The Dow's strong finish on Friday may help stretch the recovery in Malaysian stocks, dealers said. But they said sentiment was still bruised from three weeks of sharp selling following stricter lending guidelines on property and share purchases announced at the end of March.</p>
<p>&quot;It's difficult to identify the market's bottom,&quot; said Patrick Zecha, head of research at South Johor Securities. &quot;Everybody is a bit emotional.&quot;</p>
<p>For the holiday-shortened week, the Composite Index of 100 large capitalised stocks closed 33.78 points or 2.97 percent lower from Friday a week ago. On Thursday, the index ended up 16.80 points or 1.54 percent to 1,104.58. The market was closed on Friday for the Moslem Eid al-Adha festival.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MANILA - Philippine shares were expected to continue suffering the brunt of the troubled property sector and fears over a rise in U.S.interest rates could only exacerbate a fall.</p>
<p>On Friday, the main index rose 17.11 points to 2,944.48 but week-on-week, the stock market's barometer fell by 31.8 points, or 1.07 percent, from 2,976.78 points the previous Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The bias will continue to be downwards as there will be the same concerns as in the past weeks. Everybody is still worried about the property and banking sector, nerves have to be calmed,&quot; said Erwin Tan, research director at Abacus Securities Corp.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BANGKOK - Thai stocks are seen advancing slightly in the week ahead with local investors expected to return to the market in full force after enjoying nearly a week of holidays for the Thai traditional New Year, brokers said.</p>
<p>The Stock Exchange of Thailand (SET) index dropped 1.88 percent in the week to 700.23 points on Friday from a week ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The outlook of the SET next week will depend on releases of first quarter earnings of finance companies due on Monday and the country's economic indicators due for release by the central bank on Thursday. Most investors expect that earnings of finance firms during the period will be poor,&quot; said Supavat Saicheua, vice-president of Krungthai Thanakit Plc.</p>
<p>Foreign investors are also waiting to accumulate stocks which they think have become cheap and this could help the index rise next week, brokers said.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SEOUL - Stocks are expected to fall in consolidation early in the coming week and rebound towards the end, brokers said.</p>
<p>Financial troubles at the Jinro Group will continue to weigh on the market, while the planned expansion of the foreign stock ownership limit next month will help improve sentiment.</p>
<p>&quot;The composite index will move between 680 to 710 next week,&quot; said Na Min-ho of Daishin Securities.</p>
<p>The index ended at 700.65 on Saturday, up 3.7 points or 0.53 percent, from 696.95 last Saturday.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Singapore stocks look poised for further falls in the coming week after the benchmark Straits Times Industrials Index (STII) hit a 25-month low last week of 2,017.11 points.</p>
<p>Dealers said technical resistance at around 2,030-35 appeared to have been broken and it was probably only a matter of time before the index tested new lows around 2,000.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot will depend on New York. Sentiment is fragile and a couple of big falls would crush any buying,&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SYDNEY - Australian shares were seen rising steadily providing no news upsets a prevailing view that economic fundamentals are ripe for further capital gains.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we are going to see gradual gains on the back of fundamentals here,&quot; said Scott Healy, a dealer at Brisbane broker, Wilson HTM.</p>
<p>The All Ordinaries index closed at 2,442.4, up 1.21 percent, from Thursday and 2.6 percent firmer over the week.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>WELLINGTON - New Zealand shares are expected to trade slightly higher after a series of slight gains in moderate turnover in the past week.</p>
<p>Brokers also said they expect the market could gain on hints as to what Treasurer Winston Peters will reveal in his first budget scheduled for June.</p>
<p>&quot;The market will react with interest rate and currency news,&quot; said Nigel Scott at BZW. &quot;I don't think corporate news is going to change the market in the near term. It's been a solid week's trading on moderate volumes. Look out for more of the same.&quot;</p>
<p>The index finished at 2,257.31, up 5.3 points on Thursday's close and a gain of 24.33 point or one percent over last Friday's close of 2,232.98.</p>
<p>&quot;Hopefully we can get a kicker from interest rate movements,&quot; said Nigel Scott at BZW.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
