<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522741" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli police clash with ultra-Orthodox protesters.</title>
<headline>Israeli police clash with ultra-Orthodox protesters.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two Israeli policemen were injured on Saturday in clashes with ultra-Orthodox Jews trying to close a Jerusalem street that Israel's High Court said should remain open to traffic on the sabbath, a police spokesman said.</p>
<p>Witnesses said police held back thousands of religious Jews in traditional black garb who tried to block traffic on Bar Ilan street, a main Jerusalem thoroughfare.</p>
<p>&quot;Two policemen were injured and seven people have been arrested so far, some of them for stone throwing,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Police increased their presence on the street on Saturday after the High Court ruling last Sunday to keep Bar Ilan open on the sabbath.</p>
<p>The ruling ended an unofficial eight-month truce along the street and drew threats from members of the ultra-Orthodox community to renew weekly Saturday protests against the road being open.</p>
<p>The ruling cancelled last year's decision by Transportation Minister Yitzhak Levy, an Orthodox Jew, to close Bar-Ilan street during prayer times on the sabbath and Jewish holidays.</p>
<p>Ultra-Orthodox Jews had suspended their protests pending the court's decision on left-wing appeals against Levy's edict.</p>
<p>Jewish ritual law forbids the operation of machinery, including automobiles, on the sabbath which runs from Friday night to Saturday night.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
