<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522727" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: N.Korea seeks to join Asia Development Bank - daily.</title>
<headline>N.Korea seeks to join Asia Development Bank - daily.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>North Korea has applied to join the Asian Development Bank (ADB) as part of efforts to raise funds to cope with severe food shortages, a Japanese newspaper reported on Saturday, quoting the head of the ADB.</p>
<p>The ADB will soon begin discussing Pyongyang's application with the Manila-based bank's 16 members, whose approval is required for new admissions, the Asahi Shimbun quoted ADB President Mitsuo Sato as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;North Korea has shown strong interest in joining the ADB,&quot; Sato said in an interview with the Asahi in the western Japanese city of Fukuoka, site of the ADB's annual convention next month.</p>
<p>Sato said North Korea, believed to be on the brink of famine after two years of devastating floods, had made overtures to the ADB in February and March.</p>
<p>Food experts and humanitarian groups have said North Korea is facing serious food shortages that are likely to reach famine proportions in the next two months.</p>
<p>North Korea is due to respond to a joint U.S.-South Korean proposal for four-nation peace talks, which include China, in a meeting with the United States and South Korea on Saturday in New York.</p>
<p>The peace talks aim to secure a lasting peace on the Korean peninsula to replace a truce agreement that ended the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150106">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
