<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522799" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USWC spot gasoline edges up, distillates seen weak.</title>
<headline>USWC spot gasoline edges up, distillates seen weak.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spot markets for U.S. West Coast refined product were quiet late Friday, with gasoline prices edging up with the NYMEX, traders said.</p>
<p>Wholesale unleaded gasoline prices rose between 0.50 and 1.00 cent a gallon Friday, but talk was thin as traders left the market early for an industry function.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a lack of participation in today's market,&quot; said a trader for a California refinery.</p>
<p>A moderate rise in NYMEX energy futures tugged up California spot prices, with crude oil for May delivery up 49 cents a barrel on heavy technical and refinery buying.  </p>
<p>CARB cleaner-burning gasoline was pegged between 71 and 72 cents a gallon in Los Angeles, up 0.50 cents from Thursday.</p>
<p>Conventional gasoline in L.A. gained one cent ot 65.50/66.50 cents.</p>
<p>Despite a notional 0.50 cent rise, many sellers came into the market for &quot;EPA,&quot; or low sulphur diesel. Traders said a surplus of the fuel would weaken prices short-term.</p>
<p>They assessed &quot;EPA&quot; at 61/62 cents.</p>
<p>Jet fuel ended the day flat at 60.50/61.50 cents, but was seen weakening as talk of an arriving cargo, traders said.</p>
<p>((David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau +1 213 380 2014))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
