<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522731" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: N.Korean defector to arrive in S.Korea on Sunday.</title>
<headline>N.Korean defector to arrive in S.Korea on Sunday.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior North Korean defector taking refuge in the Philippines will arrive in South Korea on Sunday, ending his 68-day odyssey, South Korean government sources said.</p>
<p>Hwang Jang-yop, the most senior Pyongyang official to flee the North, would be flown to South Korea on a special plane, the sources said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;You can expect an announcement tomorrow morning after Hwang Jang-yop leaves the Philippines,&quot; a government source said. &quot;There will, of course, be another announcement after he arrives in our country.&quot;</p>
<p>Hwang was flown to a hideout in the Philippines on March 18 after arriving in South Korea's consulate in Beijing on February 12.</p>
<p>His exact whereabouts in the Philippines have remained a closely guarded secret since he was spirited out of Beijing after more than a month of negotiations between South Korean diplomats and Chinese officials.</p>
<p>Hwang, chief architect of North Korea's governing ideology of &quot;juche&quot;, a creed of self-reliance, is expected to issue a statement on his arrival in Seoul, security officials here said.</p>
<p>Diplomats have said China, which fought alongside North Korea in the 1950-53 Korean War, tried to save face for its ally by demanding that Hwang stay in the Philippines for about one month.</p>
<p>Tensions between North and South Korea remain high, more than four decades after their war ended in a truce.</p>
<p>Seoul has indicated Hwang would arrive in a glare of publicity. South Korean information officials have told reporters they are arranging facilities for the media, including foreign journalists, to cover Hwang's arrival.</p>
<p>Hwang is seen by some Western officials as a man who might provide an insight into the state of Pyongyang's military and government as it grapples with an economic catastrophe.</p>
<p>Seoul officials said Hwang's departure from the Philippines would not be affected by the outcome of a meeting in New York where U.S. and South Korean diplomats have tried to win Pyongyang's unqualified agreement to join landmark four-nation peace talks, which include China.</p>
<p>North Korea failed to resume discussion with the United States and South Korea on Friday on a proposal for the talks, forcing the meeting to be delayed until Saturday.</p>
<p>The New York meeting was arranged to hear Pyongyang's formal response to a year-old U.S.-South Korean proposal for peace talks that would finally close the books on the 1950-53 Korean War by replacing the armistice with a peace treaty.</p>
<p>U.S. and South Korean delegates remained hopeful the North would respond positively to the talks.</p>
<p>Diplomats from the United States and the two Koreas held an an inconclusive day-long meeting on Wednesday.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said privately Pyongyang essentially accepted the peace talks proposal on Wednesday but then tied its acceptance to demands for additional food assistance.</p>
<p>Both Washington and South Korea maintain large-scale aid can be discussed once Pyongyang sits at the peace table.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
