<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522773" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Scientists prepare for Alaska oil reserve studies.</title>
<headline>Scientists prepare for Alaska oil reserve studies.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Plans for oil development on part of a huge federal reserve on Alaska's North Slope may be moving too quickly to allow for adequate study of environmental impacts, said scientists attending a special symposium that ended on Friday.</p>
<p>The U.S. Interior Department's Bureau of Land Management plans to issue an environmental impact statement by next summer for possible oil and gas leasing in the northeast corner of the 23 million acre (9.3 million hectare) National Petroleum Reserve - Alaska.</p>
<p>Leasing on the 4.6 million acre (1.8 million hectares) northeast section could occur in 1998.</p>
<p>But the 18-month environmental study period represents &quot;world-record speed,&quot; said Ted Swem, a U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service bird specialist.</p>
<p>Tom Allen, Alaska director for the Bureau of Land Management, conceded that meeting the deadline would be difficult.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't know if it's possible for anyone to say with certainty what's too fast and what's too slow,&quot; Allen said on Friday. &quot;Certainly 18 months is going to be a challenge.&quot;</p>
<p>The reserve, west of the Prudhoe Bay oil complex, was set aside by President Warren Harding in 1923. It has been explored for oil and gas since the 1940s. The last federal oil and gas lease sale was held in the early 1980s.</p>
<p>New exploration technology and the oil industry's failure to gain government permission for drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge east of Prudhoe Bay has caused attention to shift to the petroleum reserve.</p>
<p>Interest in the area was further heightened after Arco Alaska Inc. last fall announced discovery of the 300 million barrel Alpine oil field just over the eastern border of the petroleum reserve.</p>
<p>The reserve is also important to wildlife, the subject of this week's symposium, which ended on Friday.</p>
<p>It is home to three migrating caribou herds, moose, muskoxen and other animals. And it is the breeding ground for birds that migrate from as far away as Chile and Argentina.</p>
<p>Among them are the spectacled eider, a duck listed as threatened under the Endangered Species Act, and the Steller's eider, a duck likely to be listed soon.</p>
<p>A specialist in protecting endangered species said biologists will be pressed to come up with suitable mitigation recommendations.</p>
<p>&quot;If it were my job to go out there and survey spectacled eider habitat, yeah, I'd feel pressured,&quot; said Greg Balogh, a biologist with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.</p>
<p>Half of Alaska's approximately 250 pairs of Arctic peregrine falcons -- an endangered species, until recent recovery -- nest in the petroleum reserve, Swem said. Of those, about half reside in the northeast study area, he said.</p>
<p>He warned that gravel extraction for drill pads could cause erosion of the high river bluffs that the birds use</p>
<p>Others recommended studies of oil development's cumulative effects on traditional Inupiat Eskimo hunting and fishing</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
