<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522705" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Chinese sailors allowed to tour Taiwan.</title>
<headline>Chinese sailors allowed to tour Taiwan.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Chinese crew will be allowed to tour the southern Taiwan city of Kaohsiung after their ship arrives there on Saturday, Taiwan's state-funded television reported.</p>
<p>The expected late-night arrival at Kaohsiung by the mainland-owned but St Vincent-registered Sheng Da would complete the first direct Taiwan-China crossing since 1949, when a civil war split Nationalist Taiwan from the communist mainland.</p>
<p>&quot;The port authorities have given the green light for the mainland crew to leave their ship and tour Kaohsiung city on Sunday,&quot; Taiwanese television reported, quoting a Transport Ministry official.</p>
<p>Taiwan would normally require the Chinese crew to stay on board the vessel.</p>
<p>The official did not elaborate the policy shift but said the Chinese crew could not make individual trips and must travel in a group in the company of the Taiwan harbour police.</p>
<p>Mainland cargoes are not allowed to enter Taiwan customs but will be processed at Kaohsiung's new &quot;offshore transshipment centre&quot; for onward passage to third countries.</p>
<p>Likewise, Taiwan cargoes at Kaohsiung cannot be put aboard ships planning to cross directly to the Chinese mainland.</p>
<p>Taipei gave the green light on April 11 to an initial batch of mainland shippers to cross the heavily militarised ideological divide and Beijing reciprocated on Thursday with unprecedented approvals for six Taiwan carriers.</p>
<p>Kaohsiung port authorities said on Saturday they had received formal notice from the Sheng Da that it was en route and expected to enter port as early at 8:30 pm (1230 GMT).</p>
<p>A second mainland ship, Far East Glory, would reach port on Sunday, a Kaohsiung duty officer said.</p>
<p>The first Taiwan vessel for China was expected to cross on April 24, a Chinese port official said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
