<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522777" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Oklahoma City marks second anniversary of bombing. [CORRECTED 08:25 GMT 20/4]</title>
<headline>Oklahoma City marks second anniversary of bombing. [CORRECTED 08:25 GMT 20/4]</headline>
<byline>Omar Gallaga</byline>
<dateline>OKLAHOMA CITY 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The pealing of church bells broke 168 seconds of silence, one second for each of the dead, on Saturday as hundreds of mourners gathered to mark the second anniversary of the Oklahoma City bombing.</p>
<p>Family members and survivors bowed their heads and wept as they remembered those who died in the April 19, 1995 blast that ripped apart the Alfred P. Murrah federal building.</p>
<p>The period of silence began at 9:02 a.m. CDT (1402 GMT), the moment when the massive truck bomb exploded in the worst civilian bombing attack in U.S. history.</p>
<p>The second anniversary of the bombing came just a few days before opening arguments were expected to begin in the trial of bombing suspect Timothy McVeigh in federal court in Denver.</p>
<p>Prosecutors charge that McVeigh and former army buddy Terry Nichols blew up the Murrah building to avenge the deaths of an estimated 80 Branch Davidians in an FBI siege at their Waco, Texas compound exactly two years before. The two were said to hate the U.S. government.</p>
<p>The silence at the ceremony was interrupted by the chilling sound of an ambulance racing through downtown Oklahoma City. A flyover of military jets soared across the brilliant blue sky in the missing man formation.</p>
<p>Mourners placed flowers on the grassy field where the Murrah building once stood as the names of the dead were read one-by-one in a grim reminder of the human toll of the attack.</p>
<p>This year's ceremony was more subdued than that of the first anniversary in 1996, with fewer people in attendance and less media coverage. But family members said their sense of loss was undiminished.</p>
<p>&quot;We feel a need to mark this day. We need this; we need the hugs,&quot; said Kathleen Treanor, whose daughter and parents-in-law (corrects from parents and son) were killed in the blast.</p>
<p>Janie Coverdale, whose grandsons, Aaron and Elijah, were among 19 children who died in the bombing, said sometimes she still thinks that the two boys are alive. &quot;It will take a long time (to heal)...We have to keep this alive in other people's minds,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>For others, the memories of the tragedy brought back by the ceremony were too overwhelming. Stephen Hull, who helped give emergency treatment to bombing victims, walked away while the names of the dead were read.</p>
<p>&quot;I just can't listen. I thought I could come down here after two years and deal with it a little bit more. I thought I was stronger than this,&quot; he told Reuters. &quot;It's just a tough, tough day.&quot;</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton sent a letter to the family members and survivors in which he said the nation &quot;will never forget that tragic day&quot; and praised the courage of the people of Oklahoma City.</p>
<p>In the bombing's aftermath, he said, &quot;our nation proved once again that no force of hatred or terrorism can ever defeat the American spirit.&quot;</p>
<p>Oklahoma Gov. Frank Keating, in a speech at the ceremony, said the trial would &quot;reopen old wounds for many, but it will also mark an end. Today, we pray for justice.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OKLAHOMA CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
