<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522776" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton, Gore celebrate &quot;Net Day&quot; at White House.</title>
<headline>Clinton, Gore celebrate &quot;Net Day&quot; at White House.</headline>
<byline>Steve Holland</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton used a computer in the White House on Saturday for a video conference with students to promote their goal of hooking up all U.S. schools and libraries to the Internet by 2000.</p>
<p>The two leaders were celebrating the second annual &quot;Net Day&quot; in which volunteers in 40 states wired more classrooms to cyberspace. To date, 65 percent of U.S. schools have a Net connection and 14 percent of classrooms are connected.</p>
<p>&quot;Net Day is a great example of how America works best when we all work together,&quot; he said in a radio address. &quot;It's like an old-fashioned barn-raising, neighbour joins with neighbour to do something for the good of the entire community.&quot;</p>
<p>In the weekly radio address, Clinton:</p>
<p>-- Announced $11.8 million in technology literacy grants for 10 states and territories to use as seed money for linking schools with the Internet.</p>
<p>-- Urged the Federal Communications Commission at a May 6 vote to approve a plan to provide up to $2.25 billion in annual discounts for schools and libraries to use for on-line services and telecommunications costs.</p>
<p>-- Issued a directive to federal departments and agencies to develop educational Internet services targeted to young people, such as the way NASA lets students interact with space shuttle astronauts via computer.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to do everything we can to make technology literacy a reality for every child in America,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>After the radio address, he and Vice President Al Gore made use of new video and computer technology set up for the first time in the Oval Office to talk to student volunteers.</p>
<p>&quot;Hi, students!&quot; Clinton said to Barrett Elementary School in Los Angeles. &quot;Hi, Mr. President!&quot; they replied.</p>
<p>Then Clinton pressed a button to talk by computer video to students in Hartford, Connecticut.</p>
<p>Clinton, who has a laptop computer in a side office near the Oval Office, admitted to the volunteers that he is not as computer literate as he would like to be.</p>
<p>&quot;So those of you who have good skills are helping those who need it, right? Yeah, well maybe you could send me a volunteer, I need some help down here,&quot; he said to laughter.</p>
<p>Both Clinton and Gore stressed that it is just as important to train teachers and students in how to use computers as it is to hook up classes to the Internet.</p>
<p>&quot;We sometimes get so focused on making sure that all the classrooms in the country are hooked up, that we forget that the hookup is worthless unless the teachers and the students are trained to use it,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Gore said the technology literacy grants provide money for training teachers how to incorporate the Internet into their lesson plans, as well as to purchase software, computers and modems. States have been awarded $57 million in these grants this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
