<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522781" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton in tough battle for chemical treaty.</title>
<headline>Clinton in tough battle for chemical treaty.</headline>
<byline>William Scally</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>With his credibility at stake on a major foreign policy issue, President Bill Clinton is lobbying hard for Senate approval of a treaty outlawing chemical weapons in the face of fierce opposition from conservatives.</p>
<p>As the Senate prepared to debate the Chemical Weapons Convention on Wednesday, supporters were putting prospects of approval at no better than 50-50, with Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott and undecided Republicans holding the key.</p>
<p>The pact was negotiated by the Ronald Reagan and George Bush administrations but Clinton has made it a cause of his own.</p>
<p>In his Friday appearance before reporters, Clinton called for defeat of amendments that would dilute the treaty.</p>
<p>He said while there was no such thing as perfect verifiability, the treaty's tough standards would detect militarily significant cheating. He denied the treaty would require the United States to share its advanced chemical defense technology with countries such as Cuba or Iran.</p>
<p>But the treaty faces some barriers constructed by archfoe Jesse Helms, chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, in the shape of provisions that would effectively bar U.S. participation in the treaty when it goes into effect on April 29, with or without the United States.</p>
<p>Treaty supporters will try to strip out these so-called killer amendments but by doing so they could lose vital votes needed to approve the resolution by a two-thirds majority.</p>
<p>The treaty was signed in 1993 during the Bush administration. More than 70 countries have ratified it.</p>
<p>Submitted to the Senate by Clinton in November 1993, the treaty languished until last September when it was brought up for debate, only to be withdrawn when Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole opposed it, endangering chances of passage.</p>
<p>The long delay allowed opponents to marshall their forces and Helms has been parading critics before his committee. The argument over whether the treaty is in U.S. interests has created unusual splits between former high officials.</p>
<p>Supporters include former presidents and top military officers; four former Republican defense secretaries are among the opponents.</p>
<p>Helms, who likes to say &quot;the United States never lost a war or won a treaty,&quot; found 33 specific objections to the chemical weapons pact but agreed to work with his committee's top Democrat, Sen. Joseph Biden of Delaware, to try to get some of them ironed out.</p>
<p>Hours of arduous bargaining brought an agreement on 28 amendments that leave the treaty intact, leaving five in dispute -- four of them regarded as &quot;killers.&quot;</p>
<p>They would:</p>
<p>- Bar U.S. participation in the treaty until Russia ratifies it and complies with an earlier agreement to destroy its poison gas stocks.</p>
<p>- Block U.S. ratification until so-called &quot;rogue states,&quot; such as Iraq and Libya sign on.</p>
<p>- Strike out treaty provisions that would require exchange of information between countries, including information on protection against chemical weapons.</p>
<p>- Raise standards for verification against cheating, including requiring the ability to detect as little as one metric ton of a chemical weapons agent.</p>
<p>A fifth amendment in dispute that Biden calls &quot;stupid&quot; rather than a killer, would bar inspectors of U.S. chemical facilities under the treaty if they were nationals of states designated as supporters of international terrorism.</p>
<p>Biden says this provision would result in retaliatory bans on U.S. inspectors.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
