<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522710" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Hungary, Singapore upgrade trade, diplomatic ties.</title>
<headline>Hungary, Singapore upgrade trade, diplomatic ties.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungarian Prime Minister Gyula Horn said on Saturday a four-day visit to Singapore had established the framework for stronger ties.</p>
<p>The visit resulted in trade, tax and investment deals, and Hungary announced its commercial office in Singapore would be upgraded to an embassy.</p>
<p>Citing the agreements, Horn told a news conference: &quot;I can say that the framework is already granted&quot; for building a stronger relationship.</p>
<p>The two countries agreed during the week to avoid double taxation and guarantee investments.</p>
<p>Singaporean and Hungarian companies signed three commercial agreements, including an acquisition deal between trading-based Thakral Group and Hungary's Yuganskorionneftegaz Kft.</p>
<p>Thakral acquired 77 percent of the Hungarian firm, which makes consumer and telecommunications products. Thakral will invest US$7 million in the Hungarian company, which had sales of $10 million in 1996.</p>
<p>The Singapore Confederation of Industries and the Federation of Hungarian Industrialists also signed an agreement to promote businesses between the two countries.</p>
<p>&quot;Investment activity of Singaporean countries in Hungary is not yet impressive,&quot; Horn said, speaking through a translator, but he added that there were indications that would change.</p>
<p>Singapore leaders were increasingly looking at eastern Central Europe for trade and investment, and expected to use Hungary as the gateway to the region, Horn and other officials at the news conference said.</p>
<p>They said a delegation from the Government of Singapore Investment Corporation was expected to visit Hungary soon, as would Singapore Prime Minister Goh Chok Tong.</p>
<p>&quot;The present visit will be returned within the not too distant future,&quot; Horn said.</p>
<p>Trade between Hungary and Singapore was Singapore $125 million (US$87 million) in 1996, up 50 percent from 1995.</p>
<p>Horn was scheduled to leave Singapore later on Saturday for a two-day visit to Malaysia before returning to Hungary, his press secretary said.</p>
<p>($1 =S$1.44)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
