<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522715" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: China ship embarks on historic Taiwan voyage.</title>
<headline>China ship embarks on historic Taiwan voyage.</headline>
<byline>Lawrence Chung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The first ship to sail directly to Taiwan from rival China in 48 years left the mainland port of Xiamen on Saturday for the 18-hour passage of the Taiwan strait, one of the world's great political divides.</p>
<p>The expected late-night arrival at Taiwan's southern port of Kaohsiung by the mainland-owned, St Vincent-registered, Sheng Da would complete the first such crossing since 1949, when a civil war split Nationalist Taiwan from the communist mainland.</p>
<p>Analysts said the crossing held symbolic importance and fuelled hopes for further liberalisations, but was only a timid first step that would have little economic impact.</p>
<p>Kaohsiung port authorities said on Saturday morning they had received formal notice from the Sheng Da that it was en route and expected to enter port by 10 p.m. (1400 GMT) on Saturday.</p>
<p>A second mainland ship, Far East Glory, had filed notice and would reach port on Sunday, a Kaohsiung duty officer said.</p>
<p>The first Taiwan vessel to embark for China was expected to cross on April 24, a Xiamen port official said.</p>
<p>Taipei on April 11 gave a green light to an initial batch of mainland shippers to cross the heavily militarised ideological divide and Beijing reciprocated on Thursday with unprecedented approvals for six Taiwan carriers.</p>
<p>The crossing comes amid deep uncertainty about the fate of far more important existing routes between Taiwan and Hong Kong after July 1, when Hong Kong returns to Beijing's control after more than a century as a British colony.</p>
<p>Negotiators have yet to meet to sort out prickly sovereignty issues such as whether Chinese-administered Hong Kong will give berth to ships flying the flag of the Republic of China on Taiwan, which Beijing does not recognise.</p>
<p>Analysts said the straits crossing could not rank as a breakthrough because Taipei will forbid direct cargo exchanges so as not to undermine its longstanding ban on direct links with the island's political adversary.</p>
<p>&quot;Because both sides are quite constrained by political tensions, neither side seems willing to make the first necessary concessions to establish true direct shipping links,&quot; China-watcher Chung Chin of Taiwan's Chunghua Institution for Economic Research told Reuters.</p>
<p>Mainland cargoes will not be allowed to enter Taiwan customs but can be processed at Kaohsiung's new &quot;offshore transshipment centre&quot; for onward passage to third countries.</p>
<p>Likewise, Taiwan cargoes at Kaohsiung cannot be put aboard ships planning to cross directly to the Chinese mainland.</p>
<p>Shipping analysts estimate that because of the restrictions, only about 200,000 20-foot equivalent units (TEU) of cargo would enter Kaohsiung for China transshipment per year -- tiny when compared to the annual five million TEU handled by Kaohsiung.</p>
<p>Diplomats in China said the establishment of restricted direct links was seen by Beijing as too little, which they said explained why the communist government was doing little or nothing to publicise the Sheng Da's inaugural crossing.</p>
<p>Beijing, which will allow the direct crossings only from the relatively small Fujian province ports of Xiamen and Fuzhou, has long demanded full resumption of direct shipping, aviation, mail, telecommunications and trade links with Taiwan.</p>
<p>Taiwan has refused to avoid undermining its exiled Republic of China government, which took refuge on the island after being routed from the mainland by the communists in 1949.</p>
<p>Beijing will permit 10 sailings a week from Xiamen and five from Fuzhou, the Xiamen port official said. Kaohsiung was expected to run the same number of routes a week into the two, which are the mainland ports closest to Taiwan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
