<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522779" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Republicans want liability limits for volunteers.</title>
<headline>Republicans want liability limits for volunteers.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Republicans believe legislation is needed to protect volunteers from liability lawsuits, Rep. John Porter of Illinois said Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;Although they are rarely sued successfully, volunteers acting in good faith are increasingly named in lawsuits -- dragged into court -- for nothing more than being present at the scene of an accident,&quot; Porter said in the Republican response to President Clinton's weekly radio address.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of these risks, many would-be volunteers are simply turning away. Fear of lawsuits has adversely affected recruitment of direct service volunteers and members of nonprofit boards,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Porter has introduced a bill to protect individual volunteers of nonprofit organizations from being sued except in cases of willful or wanton misconduct. The bill would allow the organizations themselves to be sued.</p>
<p>&quot;Now, with the enthusiastic support of House and Senate Republicans and many Democrats as well, we hope to pass the Volunteer Protection Act and send it to President Clinton,&quot; Porter said.</p>
<p>Porter said his bill was endorsed by groups such as the American Red Cross, the Little League and the Salvation Army.</p>
<p>Clinton last year vetoed a broader bill passed by Congress that would limit punitive damages in product liability suits. Supporters of the bill said Clinton was acting on behalf of the trial lawyers, who had heavily supported him.</p>
<p>&quot;Before the president decides to side with the trial lawyers yet again, we hope that he will take a close look at the modest protection we're seeking and listen to the hundreds of volunteer organizations across America who are supporting the bill,&quot; Porter said.</p>
<p>&quot;I urge you to contact the White House and to urge President Clinton to sign the Volunteer Protection Act when it reaches his desk.</p>
<p>&quot;This legislation is a positive Republican initiative, but the values it embraces -- service to others, compassion, giving something back to our communities -- cross all political boundaries,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
