<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522790" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US WCoast Line 63 falls, pressured by LATAM grades.</title>
<headline>US WCoast Line 63 falls, pressured by LATAM grades.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. West Coast Line 63 prices were talked lower Friday, under pressure from several offers of Venezuelan Oriente crude, which last week forced down the price of Alaska North Slope (ANS), traders said.</p>
<p>Two major producers and one refinery offered large parcels of Line 63. Two were sized at 4,000 barrels-per-day (bpd) for May, and a third for 5,000 bpd.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is very weak,&quot; for Line 63, said a trader who was offered the parcels. &quot;A lot of traders claimed they can't find a home for it.&quot;  </p>
<p>The barrels were offered for 70 cents over Buena Vista grade crude, 30 cents under the last reported deal.</p>
<p>On a notional basis, Line 63 was talked $2.37/2.27 under May West Texas Intermediate/Cushing (WTI). The grade rarely trades off WTI.</p>
<p>South American crudes on offer included a Colombian South Blend (29, 0.8) and four cargoes Ecuadorean Oriente (28.8, 1.02) cargoes.</p>
<p>BP Oil, the dominant seller of ANS, last offered at 95 cents below May West Texas Intermediate/Cushing (WTI) but refiners said the price remained out-of-synch with supply and demand.</p>
<p>Traders said about four cargoes of Oriente were being offered at competitive prices of $1.40 to $1.50 under ANS, delivered to the West Coast.</p>
<p>An asphalt-making refinery in the Northwest said a 340,000 barrel cargo of Venezulan Tia Juana Heavy (12.3 API gravity, 2.82 sulphur) was delivered last week, but a company official declined to say how much it cost.</p>
<p>West Coast benchmark Alaska North Slope (ANS) last traded a week ago at $1.32 below West Texas Intermediate/Cushing (WTI), which compared with a week earlier at $1.05 below.</p>
<p>--David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau, +1 213 380 2014</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
