<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522750" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Iran dismisses report of link to Saudi blast.</title>
<headline>Iran dismisses report of link to Saudi blast.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iran on Saturday dismissed as &quot;lies&quot; a U.S. newspaper report that one of its officials was involved in the bombing of a U.S. military compound in Saudi Arabia last year.</p>
<p>The move came two days after a U.S. official said his country has not concluded that Iran was behind the truck bombing that killed 19 U.S. servicemen but will take action if it does.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not the first time that America embarks on telling lies about the Islamic Republic of Iran,&quot; the Iranian News Agency IRNA quoted Major General Mohsen Rezaei, Commander of Iran's Revolutionary Guards, as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;Usually after such an incident, American and Zionist officials and media try to attribute the incident to the Islamic Republic of Iran without producing any evidence.&quot;</p>
<p>The Washington Post said last week an Iranian official was linked to the blast.</p>
<p>The newspaper quoted U.S. and Saudi officials as saying Brigadier Ahmad Sherifi, a senior Iranian intelligence officer, met two years before the blast with Hani Abd Rahim Sayegh, a Saudi Shi'ite arrested in Canada last month as &quot;a direct participant&quot; in the June 25 bombing.</p>
<p>It said U.S. officials disagreed whether the link was strong enough to require U.S. retaliation against Iran.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
