<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522743" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel awaits decision on Netanyahu indictment.</title>
<headline>Israel awaits decision on Netanyahu indictment.</headline>
<byline>Amy Michaels</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli opposition leader Shimon Peres ruled out on Saturday a national unity government following a police recommendation to indict Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in a government corruption scandal.</p>
<p>Israel's attorney-general is expected to announce on Sunday whether Netanyahu and three other top officials will be indicted as recommended by police earlier in the week.</p>
<p>&quot;As the situation stands today, there is no basis for a national unity government,&quot; Peres, leader of the Labour party, told Israel Army radio.</p>
<p>An indictment against Netanyahu, the first for an Israeli prime minister, could topple his Likud-led government. Prosecutors could ignore the police recommendations made after a probe over the short-lived appointment in January of Likud activist Roni Bar-on as attorney-general.</p>
<p>&quot;I've already decided,&quot; State Attorney Edna Arbel told Israel Radio on Saturday without elaborating. She said the matter was now in the hands of the attorney-general.</p>
<p>Peres, who helped engineer the Israel-PLO 1993 peace deals but lost to Netanyahu in elections last year, has said in the past he would consider joining a national unity government which he believes is the only way to save faltering Israeli peace moves with the Palestinians and other Arab partners.</p>
<p>&quot;If the conclusions are that this government stays put then in my opinion the peace process will have almost lost its chance,&quot; Peres said.</p>
<p>Netanyahu, 47, elected 11 months ago by less than a percentage point, has described the influence-peddling scandal as &quot;nonsense&quot; and rejected calls to resign.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton said in Washington that the crisis was an internal Israeli matter and must not be allowed to derail stalled Middle East peace efforts.</p>
<p>&quot;They are a great and vibrant democracy and they'll deal with that in their way,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>&quot;We just can't allow anything, anything to derail the peace process and I don't believe we will.&quot;</p>
<p>Newspaper opinion polls published on Friday showed a majority of Israelis believe Netanyahu must step down if charged or convicted.</p>
<p>The police probe was sparked by a Channel One television report in January which alleged that a Netanyahu ally on trial for corruption, politician Aryeh Deri, pushed Bar-On for the job in the hope of winning a plea bargain.</p>
<p>Channel One speculated on Friday that only Deri would be indicted.</p>
<p>&quot;According to today's likely trend, the decision at the state attorney's office is to issue an indictment against Aryeh Deri alone,&quot; said Channel One television reporter Amnon Abramovich.</p>
<p>But even if the prime minister is not indicted, a scathing report on the scandal by the state attorney could crumble his ruling coalition of mainly right-wing and religious parties.</p>
<p>Netanyahu is under no legal obligation to quit if indicted, but High Court judges have ruled in the past that ministers under indictment must step down. Opposition legislators have already said they would petition the court for a similar ruling.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
