<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522752" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Iran says petrol bomb hurled at its Paris consulate.</title>
<headline>Iran says petrol bomb hurled at its Paris consulate.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>An attacker has hurled a petrol bomb at Iran's consulate in Paris, the Iranian news agency IRNA said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Friday's attack caused no damage or injuries, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;The assailant, who is said to be an Iranian, was reportedly arrested by French police minutes after the attack,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>IRNA quoted a French Foreign Ministry official as saying he knew nothing about the incident. &quot;But he stressed that France condemns any attack against diplomatic missions on its soil,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>French Foreign Minister Herve de Charette was quoted on Friday as saying that European Union nations will soon send back ambassadors to Tehran after they were recalled in a row over political slayings in Europe.</p>
<p>EU nations, except Greece, withdrew their envoys from Iran after a German court ruled last week that Iran's rulers ordered the killing of four Kurdish dissidents in Berlin. Tehran has repeatedly denied any involvement.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
