<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522786" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pennsylvania execution halted, awaits court ruling.</title>
<headline>Pennsylvania execution halted, awaits court ruling.</headline>
<dateline>PHILADELPHIA 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The scheduled execution early Saturday of convicted murderer Gary Heidnik was halted by the Pennsylvania Supreme Court, leaving it up to the U.S. Supreme Court to decide whether the death sentence should go forward.</p>
<p>Heidnik, convicted of murdering two women among six that he had kidnapped and tortured a decade ago, was due to be executed at 2 a.m. EDT on Saturday. Death penalty opponents have fought the action each step of the way, arguing that the murderer is insane.</p>
<p>The state Supreme Court late Friday issued a stay blocking the execution, leading state authorities night to appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court so the execution could be carried out.</p>
<p>Prison officials said early Saturday morning that a High Court decision was expected at around 2 p.m. EDT.</p>
<p>The last-minute legal wrangling Friday began with a ruling by a U.S. Appeals Court to stay the execution. The court found Heidnik incapable of making a rational decision.</p>
<p>The matter then went to the U.S. Supreme Court, which lifted that stay, only to have another one imposed by the state Supreme Court.</p>
<p>Convicted of kidnapping and torturing six women and killing two of them, Heidnik would be the third person to die since the state reinstated the death penalty. His death warrant expires at midnight Saturday.</p>
<p>Heidnik, now 53, claimed insanity at his 1988 trial, but a jury convicted him and sentenced him to death.</p>
<p>The case came to public attention hours after Josefina Rivera escaped from a North Philadelphia row house on March 24, 1987.</p>
<p>She had been shackled with five other women in the cellar, which Heidnik had converted into a torture chamber where he enticed streetwalkers into his home to make them his sex slaves. One was killed, and a second died of starvation and mistreatment.</p>
<p>Deborah Dudley's body was found near a rural road in New Jersey. She had been electrocuted. Sandra Lindsay's body was found carved into parts in a basement refrigerator. Heidnik had cooked some parts and fed them to his captives, mixed with dog food, they later testified.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHILADELPHIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
