<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522767" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. orders Embassy dependents to leave Zaire.</title>
<headline>U.S. orders Embassy dependents to leave Zaire.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States on Friday ordered dependents of its Embassy staff to leave Zaire and strongly urged all Americans to depart the war-torn central African country.</p>
<p>Although the United States military has been prepared for more than three weeks for the possible evacuation of about 450 Americans from Zaire, no order to do so has been issued, officials said late on Friday.</p>
<p>However, the State Department's written announcement that it had &quot;ordered the departure of dependents of U.S. Embassy personnel&quot; reflected growing U.S. concern about the situation in Zaire where rebels have captured almost half of the country in the past six months.</p>
<p>On March 20, the department &quot;strongly encouraged&quot; Embassy dependents to leave and warned Americans to defer travel to Zaire.</p>
<p>The Clinton administration last week sent the assault ship Kearsarge, with more than 1,000 Marines aboard, to replace the helicopter landing ship Nassau, which had been stationed off the west coast of Africa for the past two weeks in case a rescue operation became necessary.</p>
<p>In addition, the Pentagon has moved a detachment of Marines into Brazzaville, the capital of the Congo, to coordinate a possible evacuation.</p>
<p>France, Belgium and Britain also have troops in Brazzaville to evacuate their citizens should the civil war lead to anarchy in Zaire's capital Kinshasa.</p>
<p>Rebels, who have been fighting since October 1996 to topple Zaire's ailing President Mobutu Sese Seko, now control the country's second city, Kisangani, but the unrest has not yet reached Kinshasa.</p>
<p>The United States, which has maintained a decades-old alliance with Mobutu, signalled last week that he should step down.</p>
<p>But Mobutu appears far from yielding to demands that he relinquish power. His son and spokesman, Nzanga Mobutu, said on Friday while his father was willing to meet rebel leader Laurent Kabila, his departure as president would leave &quot;a vacuum at the top&quot; and bring chaos to Zaire.</p>
<p>In its order to U.S. Embassy dependents, the State Department noted &quot;the uncertain political and security situation and the potential for unrest throughout the country.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The Department strongly urges U.S. citizens in Zaire to depart the country...(and) warns U.S. citizens to defer all travel to Zaire,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Earlier, a U.S. official discounted claims by Zairean rebels that Mobutu had ordered the massacre of all expatriates in Kinshasa.</p>
<p>&quot;We have approached Mobutu's people about this and they've said it's absolute nonsense. It would make no sense,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;Give it no credence. We're discounting it,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>An aide to Kabila told reporters in Lubumbashi that Mobutu had ordered security forces to kill all expatriates in the Zairean capital in order to provoke foreign intervention and avert his downfall.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
