<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522719" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Seoul prepares to welcome defector, aid to North.</title>
<headline>Seoul prepares to welcome defector, aid to North.</headline>
<byline>Moon Ihlwan</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea put the finishing touches on Saturday to a plan for ending a 68-day odyssey by the highest-ranking North Korean official to flee the impoverished nation.</p>
<p>A Seoul government official told Reuters that Hwang Jang-yop, who defected in Beijing on February 12 and is now taking refuge in the Philippines, would be flown to South Korea on Sunday on a special plane.</p>
<p>Another government official said Seoul had decided to offer about $10 million in fresh food aid to the famine-threatened North but the exact amount would depend on Pyongyang' response to a peace proposal</p>
<p>&quot;The amount could be reduced by a couple of million dollars if we are not happy with the North's response,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The new aid through the World Food Programme is in addition to $6 million Seoul had already donated to the U.N. body before it raised an aid appeal to $95.5 million from an earlier $41.6 million. Washington has pledged $25 million to the programme.</p>
<p>Some Western officials say Hwang could give an insight into the state of Pyongyang's government and military as it grapples with an economic catastrophe.</p>
<p>His scheduled arrival in Seoul comes at a sensitive time as the United States and South Korea try to persuade Pyongyang to join landmark four-nation peace talks, which include China.</p>
<p>In a separate development, North Korea on Saturday agreed to hold Red Cross talks with South Korea on food aid.</p>
<p>The South Korean Red Cross said its North Korean counterpart accepted a proposal for &quot;speedy and smooth&quot; delivery of food and other relief materials. The North suggested their first meeting take place in Beijing on May 3.</p>
<p>The South Korean Red Cross on Friday called for a meeting as soon as possible at the Korean border village of Panmunjom and it has not yet agreed to Beijing as the venue.</p>
<p>The South Korean Red Cross has made 14 relief shipments since November 1996 to North Korea. Religious and other civic groups in South Korea have pledged to raise about $20 million to ship 110,000 tonnes of corn to the communist state.</p>
<p>In New York, the United States and the two Koreas are due to resume discussions later on Saturday, delayed from Friday at North Korea's request.</p>
<p>The meeting was arranged to hear Pyongyang's formal response to a year-old U.S.-South Korean proposal for peace talks that would finally close the books on the 1950-53 Korean War by replacing the armistice with a peace treaty.</p>
<p>Delegates from the three nations held an inconclusive meeting on Wednesday. U.S. and South Korean officials remained optimistic the North would respond positively to the talks.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said privately Pyongyang essentially accepted the peace talks proposal on Wednesday but then tied its acceptance to demands for additional food assistance.</p>
<p>Both Washington and South Korea maintain large-scale aid can be discussed once Pyongyang sits at the peace table.</p>
<p>Seoul officials said Hwang's departure from the Philippines would not be affected by the outcome of the New York meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;You can expect an announcement tomorrow morning after Hwang Jang-yop leaves the Philippines,&quot; an official said. &quot;There will, of course, be another announcement after he arrives in our country.&quot;</p>
<p>Hwang was spirited to a hideout in the Philippines on March 18 after arriving in South Korea's consulate in Beijing on February 12. His exact whereabouts in the Philippines have remained a well-kept secret.</p>
<p>Hwang, chief architect of the North's governing ideology of &quot;juche&quot;, a creed of self-reliance, is expected to issue a statement on his arrival in the South, Seoul officials said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
