<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522815" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: EU, ACP states begin shaping new Lome Convention.</title>
<headline>EU, ACP states begin shaping new Lome Convention.</headline>
<dateline>MAASTRICHT, Netherlands 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union and its main trading partners in the developing world on Saturday wrapped up a two-day meeting in the southern Dutch town of Maastricht with a call for a deepening of economic relations.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a call for a broader agreement, particularly in the economic field, on the relationship between trade and aid,&quot; Dutch Overseas Development Minister Jan Pronk told a news conference.</p>
<p>Political and economic ties between the EU and the seventy African, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) states, most with colonial ties to EU countries, are enshrined in the Lome Convention, a framework for trade and aid which expires in the year 2000 after 25 years.</p>
<p>The Dutch government, as current EU President, says the convention needs to be amended &quot;because of the essential changes which have taken place on the world stage in the last 10 years.&quot;</p>
<p>But some the hottest trade issues facing the two groups remain unresolved.</p>
<p>The European Union's banana regime, which has sparked a war of words between Brussels and Washington is one such case. The regime favours imports from mainly Caribbean countries but was recently found by a World Trade Organisation dispute panel to violate open trading rules.</p>
<p>In an interim ruling the WTO found in favour of a complaint by the United States and four Latin American countries that the EU regime which permits the duty-free import of 875,000 tonnes of ACP-grown bananas discriminated against their companies.</p>
<p>If a final WTO decision goes against the EU, Brussels may have to pay compensation to the United States, Ecuador, Mexico, Guatamala and Honduras for their lost export revenue.</p>
<p>But Pronk said he did not expect the EU to drop its system of granting preferential trade protocols to ACP states.</p>
<p>&quot;I expect there will not be an outcome of negotiations that will lead to the withdrawl of preferences,&quot; he said, adding he thought they could be continued in some form within WTO rules.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEVGCO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MAASTRICHT, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
