<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522823" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Telekom,Kirch eye ending TV fight - magazine.</title>
<headline>Telekom,Kirch eye ending TV fight - magazine.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>German telecommunications group Deutsche Telekom AG and media group Kirch Group have moved closer to breaking a deadlock over the use of Telekom's cable television network, newsmagazine Der Spiegel reported.</p>
<p>In a summary of an interview with Telekom chief executive Ron Sommer, to be published in next week's edition, the magazine said Sommer and Bavarian media mogul Leo Kirch had made considerable progress in reaching an agreement.</p>
<p>The magazine quoted Sommer as saying, &quot;I am very optimistic and expect a positive result when we get together with other cable television providers in May.&quot; He declined further comment on the exact nature of the rapprochement however.</p>
<p>Telekom's previous refusal to endorse Kirch's decoder technology had been one of the obstacles to the distribution of Kirch's DF1 television programme via Telekom's cable television network.</p>
<p>Kirch has blamed the lack of access to the Telekom network for the sluggish sales of his DF1 programme.</p>
<p>Sommer had earlier also signalled a deadlock in Telekom's negotiations with Kirch and other broadcasters regarding programming for its 150 digital channels could be reached.</p>
<p>Talks have been stuck over pricing for inclusion in the Telekom cable television network, which connects around 16.7 million homes.</p>
<p>In the Spiegel interview Sommer said Telekom would not offer its own programmes but said &quot;we do want to excercise more influence over the programming in digital cable television since we have to make profits in the cable business.&quot;</p>
<p>Digital technology allows broadcasters to squeeze more channels into cable and satellite networks and to show films in CD-like quality. It also allows new media forms such as video on demand, home-shopping and possibly interactive games.</p>
<p>Separately German newsmagazine Focus reported in a summary of an article in next week's edition that Kirch planned to produce soap operas in the German state of North Rhine- Westphalia, securing some 200 jobs.</p>
<p>Kirch's son Thomas plans to invest some 80 million marks in Berlin's struggling television network FAB, the magazine reported.</p>
<p>--Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
