<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522804" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Uneasy Italian govt allies skirmish ahead of polls.</title>
<headline>Uneasy Italian govt allies skirmish ahead of polls.</headline>
<byline>Alan Baldwin</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy's uneasy centre-left coalition allies skirmished on Saturday, with Foreign Minister Lamberto Dini and the hard-left questioning each other's behaviour and motives ahead of local polls.</p>
<p>&quot;In the coming weeks the government will have to make difficult decisions to allow Italy to take part in European monetary union from the start,&quot; Dini, a centrist, said in northern Italy.</p>
<p>&quot;The majority must be united and Communist Refoundation (the former Communist Party) must consider Europe as a great opportunity for the growth and development of the country,&quot; he said as politicians stepped up campaigning for the April 27 local elections.</p>
<p>They are the first solid tests of sentiment since Prime Minister Romano Prodi's centre-left coalition won national polls one year ago.</p>
<p>Communist Refoundation hold the balance of power in the lower house of parliament and last week voted against their allies on sending an Italian-led force to Albania. The vote was carried only with help from the centre-right opposition.</p>
<p>Refoundation, with the trades unions, is also implacably opposed to any changes in welfare spending, and in Italy's costly pensions system, before 1998.</p>
<p>Dini said it was important to convince &quot;our friends from Refoundation...that they must overcome ideological intransigence to join the great objective that is Europe. This is indispensable because there is not much time.&quot;</p>
<p>Dini said earlier in an interview with the daily Corriere della Sera that the government must set out its social reform plans by June or consider modifying the coalition.</p>
<p>&quot;The government must define soon, before the summer, a proposed reform of the welfare state undersigned by the entire majority and then negotiate on that basis with the interested parties,&quot; Dini told the newspaper.</p>
<p>He said that otherwise Prodi &quot;must have the political honesty to admit promptly -- without waiting until 1998 -- that we are not in a position to take part in the single currency.</p>
<p>&quot;At that point the possibility of broadening the majority to include other centrist forces must be looked into,&quot; Dini said, adding that this would be a last resort.</p>
<p>The main Democratic Party of the Left (PDS) within the coalition ruled out changes in the coalition while Refoundation leader Fausto Bertinotti questioned Dini.</p>
<p>Prodi's administration has drawn up a 15.5 trillion lire ($9 billion) supplementary budget in a sustained effort to ensure Italy can join European economic and monetary union (EMU).</p>
<p>That measure was rejected 25 to 24 by a lower house commission on Friday after two centre-left deputies, both former members of Dini's group, voted against the government. The package now goes to parliament for approval.</p>
<p>Bertinotti, whose members also backed the government in the commission vote, said Dini's party &quot;looks more and more like a bridge to the centre-right (opposition)&quot;.</p>
<p>Treasury Minister Carlo Azeglio Ciampi has said the government would set out &quot;strategic lines&quot; for pension reforms in its annual document of three-year rolling economic targets (DPEF) to be presented in May.</p>
<p>But Dini told the daily Corriere that the DPEF needed to contain more than guidelines.</p>
<p>&quot;When we ask for an agreement by June we are not doing it for the pleasure of making ultimatums but because time is limited,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Talks with the unions and employers can only start when a proposal by the entire majority has been defined.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
