<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522833" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Kinkel reassures Germans on Iran suicide threats.</title>
<headline>Kinkel reassures Germans on Iran suicide threats.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel said on Saturday Bonn was taking seriously threats by a radical Islamic group in Iran to unleash suicide attacks against Germany but assured Germans they were safe.</p>
<p>Kinkel's remarks were quoted in a ministry statement a day after the leader of hardline Ansar-e Hizbollah said his followers were ready to die as martyrs against Germany if ordered by Iran's supreme leader.</p>
<p>Iranian officials have said they are committed to protecting foreign residents and Kinkel said he had no reason to doubt the 530 Germans in Iran were safe.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course we are taking the latest threats by the extremist Ansar-e Hizbollah to unleash suicide commandos seriously,&quot; Kinkel was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;At the same time, no-one in Germany has anything to fear since these suicide commandos apparently only act on orders from the (Iranian) government,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The suicide threats came amid a diplomatic row sparked by a Berlin court verdict that jailed an Iranian and three Lebanese for the murder of Kurdish dissidents and accused Tehran of ordering the killings.</p>
<p>The Berlin verdict not only prompted official protest from Iran's leadership but also unleashed a wave of protests in Tehran where thousands of people took to the streets and fundamentalist students tried to storm the German embassy.</p>
<p>The court said Iranian leaders, including the state president and the religious leader, had ordered the killings. But it only mentioned Intelligence Minister Ali Fallahiyan by name. Iran has repeatedly denied all involvement.</p>
<p>The verdict was the first time a European court had clearly attributed political responsibility for any of the dozens of assassinations of Iranian opposition figures abroad since the Islamic revolution in Iran in 1979.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
