<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522841" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's Gujral seen as next premier - agencies.</title>
<headline>India's Gujral seen as next premier - agencies.</headline>
<byline>Sambit Mohanty</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's caretaker Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral appeared likely to be named the leader of the United Front coalition and a new centre-left government, news agencies said on Saturday.</p>
<p>United News of India, citing United Front sources, said Gujral, 77, had been chosen to succeed caretaker Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>The Press Trust of India said there were &quot;indications that the External Affairs Minister, Mr I.K. Gujral, was the likely choice&quot; to replace Deve Gowda at the head of the 15-party alliance.</p>
<p>United Front leaders were meeting in the capital to select a new leader. An announcement was expected at about 1500 GMT.</p>
<p>Gujral was waiting in a nearby guest house where he was summoned earlier in the day by Andhra Pradesh chief minister Chandrababu Naidu, who has spearheaded the search for a new leader, alliance officials said.</p>
<p>Farooq Abdullah, chief minister of Jammu and Kashmir state, told reporters as he entered the United Front meeting that there would be no deputy prime minister, the Press Trust of India said.</p>
<p>Earlier on Saturday, there were reports that caretaker Defence Minister Mulayam Singh Yadav would be named deputy prime minister.</p>
<p>United Front officials said strong support for Gujral as a consensus candidate had built up during the day as alliance leaders held hectic talks to end a three-week political crisis.</p>
<p>Gujral, who has served twice as foreign minister, is widely respected but has little political base -- considered an advantage in the current highly politicised atmosphere.</p>
<p>Deve Gowda resigned on April 11 after losing a vote of confidence in the lower house of parliament.</p>
<p>The Congress party, which provoked his downfall by withdrawing support, said on Friday that it would back a new United Front leader at the head of a centre-left government.</p>
<p>The choice of a new United Front chief would put an end to three weeks of political uncertainty which have rocked financial markets and raised the prospect of the second general elections in a year.</p>
<p>But neither the 15-party United Front nor Congress want mid-term polls which opinion surveys show could put the rightwing Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) within striking distance of power.</p>
<p>Their common opposition to the BJP, more than shared principles, has kept the United Front and Congress from rupturing ties despite mounting acrimony which resulted in Deve Gowda's downfall.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
