<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522862" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's Gujral - urbane scholar in rustic alliance.</title>
<headline>India's Gujral - urbane scholar in rustic alliance.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Verma</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Inder Kumar Gujral, India's prime minister-in-waiting, is a suave foreign policy scholar who stands out from many rustic socialists in his centre-left United Front alliance.</p>
<p>Gujral, like his predecessor H.D. Deve Gowda, might have been seen by his colleagues as the right choice because he is so different.</p>
<p>Many believe the softspoken, two-time foreign minister was chosen on Saturday to lead the next centre-left government because he is regarded as a pliable moderate and has a reputation for honesty.</p>
<p>He has no power base to speak of and, at 77, is seen as having little political ambition left.</p>
<p>&quot;I bow my head to the people of India,&quot; the bespectacled Gujral told reporters after the decision was announced. &quot;I promise them to the best of my capacity to give a clean government, a government that serves them.&quot;</p>
<p>With no real enemies, Gujral was regarded as acceptable to not only the 15 parties of the United Front but also its key ally, the Congress party.</p>
<p>Gujral cut his political teeth in Congress, which helped to topple Deve Gowda's government but now is ready to support another centre-left coalition led by the United Front.</p>
<p>He served a first stint as foreign minister from 1989 to 1990 under prime minister V.P. Singh.</p>
<p>Foreign minister again in the outgoing government, the mild-mannered, white-goateed Gujral put his distinctive stamp on foreign policy, establishing in a mere 10 months what diplomats refer to as the &quot;Gujral Doctrine&quot;.</p>
<p>This holds that as the largest nation in South Asia, India can afford to offer concessions to its neighbours in the interests of regional harmony.</p>
<p>In December, India ended years of dispute with Bangladesh over a prickly river water-sharing arrangement by signing a pact under Gujral's stewardship. He struck another water deal with Nepal.</p>
<p>Also in December, India and China, which fought a brief war in 1962, signed an accord to reduce troops along their Himalayan border. This year, India and archrival Pakistan resumed peace talks after more than three years of tense silence.</p>
<p>Bucking bitter international opposition, Gujral led India's campaign last year to reject the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty to prohibit nuclear test blasts. His stand drew Washington's ire, but he did not flinch.</p>
<p>Foreign Ministry officials say Gujral is well-informed, remarkably courteous and receptive to new ideas.</p>
<p>&quot;But for someone so educated, he can also be extremely parochial, which is where his bluntness takes you by surprise,&quot; one diplomat said.</p>
<p>Born in 1919 in the city of Jhelum, located in modern day Pakistan, Gujral was jailed in 1931 and 1942 for taking part in India's struggle for freedom from British rule.</p>
<p>With the blood-stained partition of the subcontinent into India and Pakistan at independence in 1947, Gujral and his family migrated to India.</p>
<p>He joined parliament as a lawmaker of the Congress party in 1964, and held important ministerial posts between 1967 and 1976 as a close ally of then prime minister Indira Gandhi.</p>
<p>Between 1976 and 1980, the dapper politician was India's ambassador to the Soviet Union, with which New Delhi nurtured close ties during the Cold War.</p>
<p>Gujral later drifted away from the Congress party and joined the socialist Janata Dal, now the largest constituent of the United Front.</p>
<p>Conspicuously urbane, Gujral lives in a posh south Delhi suburb and lists his hobbies as &quot;writer and commentator&quot; in his official resume. He is also associated with various cultural organisations.</p>
<p>He is married to Shiela, a poet and author, and has two sons. His brother, Satish, is a prominent artist.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
