<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522855" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - April 19.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - April 19.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Indian business and political stories in leading newspapers prepared for REUTERS by Business News and Information Services Pvt Ltd, New Delhi Tel:3324842, 3351006, 3761233 Fax:+91-11-3351006 Internet: biznis@giasbm01.vsnl.net.in</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>		   -------oo0oo-------</p>
<p>			TOP STORIES</p>
<p>The Hindustan Times</p>
<p>CONGRESS CHIEF'S LETTER CLEARS HURDLE</p>
<p>The Congress party hastened the search for a new prime minister by informing the president that it was ready to support the United Front (UF) to form the next government if it elected a successor to Deve Gowda. The Congress chief's letter followed an appeal from UF leaders urging him to help the Front constituents to start the search for a new leader by at least modifying the Congress claim before the president, if he could not withdraw it without loss of face. The letter, however, made it clear that if the UF failed to find a new leader, the Congress claim to form the next government would be valid.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Indian Express</p>
<p>POWER STRUGGLE IN UNITED FRONT OVER LEADERSHIP</p>
<p>A consensus over the new leader eluded the United Front (UF). Indications were that a major power struggle had broken out within the UF, with both Defence Minister Mulayam Singh Yadav and Railway Minister Ram Vilas Paswan throwing their hat in the ring, further confusing the picture. If differences within the coalition persisted, some of the partners may join hands with the Bharatiya Janata Party.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Economic Times</p>
<p>INFLOW OF DOLLARS ON INVISIBLE ACCOUNT UP AT 4.5 BLN</p>
<p>The net inflow of dollars on the invisible account touched a high of $4.5 billion in 1996/97 (April-March), an increase of over $1 billion over 1995/96. In 1995/96, the net invisible inflows were $3.4 billion. Invisible inflows were largely constituted by private transfers on the current account by Indians living abroad. This was netted against outflows in respect of current account payments. In 1995/96, private transfer of dollars into the country was to the tune of $7.4 billion and the outflow on account of interest, dividend and other payments was $4.4 billion.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT APPROVALS TAPER OFF</p>
<p>Approvals of foreign direct investment (FDI) have started tapering off, even as the inflow in dollar terms ($2.41 billion in 1996) continued to grow at a healthy pace. Official estimates showed the government approved foreign projects worth $4.52 billion in 1994. This figure skyrocketed to $10.21 billion in 1995 -- an increase of $5.69 billion. But FDI approvals for 1996 were pegged at $10.34 billion, a paltry increase of $13 million. ----</p>
<p>CEILING ON POST-TAX RETURNS OF POWER COMPANIES PLANNED</p>
<p>The government decided to introduce a ceiling on the post tax returns to be earned by private power producers. Returns net of tax would be limited to 16 percent on equity. Any earnings beyond this on account of better plant management would be taxed. Private power generating companies are allowed a post tax return of 16 percent on their equity at 68.5 percent plant lead factor. However, it was not clear whether power companies could pass off their taxes payable on incentives, depreciation or better heat rate management to the state power utilities. As a result, the first batch of projects were given an incentive of earning a rate of return on equity net of tax.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Financial Express</p>
<p>ICICI PLANNING PENSION FUND WITH UK FIRM</p>
<p>Industrial Credit and Investment Corporation (ICICI) planned to float a pension fund. ICICI was likely to zero in on Prudential Corporation, the largest British insurance company, to form a joint venture to float the pension fund. Unit Trust of India (UTI) was also planning to float a pension fund, but is yet to identify an overseas partner. ICICI would sign a memorandum of understanding with the British company to enter the life insurance sector, as and when it was opened up. Sources said the proposed joint venture with Prudential would be limited to life insurance only for the time being.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>REGULATOR CONSENTS TO INTERCONNECTED MARKET SYSTEM</p>
<p>The Interconnected Market System (ICMS), sponsored by the Federation of Indian Stock Exchanges, was set to get a fresh lease on life with the bourse regulator putting its might behind the project. After much deliberation and particularly weighing expert opinion from Price Waterhouse on the feasibility of the project, the market watchdog consented to the implementation of the ambitious project to link most of the regional bourses in the country. As a sequel, other bourses, which were initially reluctant to join, accepted invitations to participate in the ICMS's deliberations.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>WILL RELIANCE PROVE ANALYSTS WRONG?</p>
<p>Even as some analysts predicted a fall in Reliance Industries' (RIL) net profit for 1996/97 (April-March), brokers seemed to be optimistic. The market keenly awaited RIL's results which would be announced on Tuesday. For 1995/96, RIL announced a net profit of 13.04 million rupees on 62.7851 billion rupee net sales. As petrochemical prices have been declining since the second quarter of 1996, analysts expected the company to announce lower sales compared with the previous year despite an improvement in volumes. RIL managed to maintain its operating profit margin for the first six months of 1996/97 because of higher volumes.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Standard</p>
<p>MUTUAL FUND IPOS MOP UP 4.26 BLN RUPEES MORE</p>
<p>Contrary to popular perception, collections by mutual funds through initial public offerings (IPOs) increased by 4.26 billion rupees in 1996/97 (April-March). According to a study by a research outfit, the industry collected a total of 26.893 billion rupees in the year as against 22.63 billion in 1995/96. The increase in collections was mainly on account of debt schemes, as most companies chose to launch fixed income schemes.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>SPECULATION OVER CHANGE IN ACC EQUITY STRUCTURE</p>
<p>The top brass of blue chip cement major Associated Cement Companies (ACC) fear the possibility of a change in the company's equity structure. The fears emanated from reports of some merchant banks' plans to approach Shapoorji Pallonji Mistry, the ACC deputy chairman, to ascertain if the latter was swapping part of his 18 percent holding in Tata Sons with the 11.2 percent stake jointly held by Tata Tea and Tata Chem in ACC. If the swap did take place, it would enable Mistry to substantially raise his stake in ACC.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>COCA-COLA SEEKS APPROVAL FOR FOUR BOTTLING UNITTS</p>
<p>Coca-Cola South Asia Holdings has proposed setting up four downstream bottling subsidiaries under its two fully owned holding companies. The soft drink giant was willing to divest up to 49 percent of the equity of the four companies within five years of commencement of operations in favour of Indian equity. The total equity investment in these companies add up to 11.9 billion rupees in the first phase, with Coca Cola holding 51 percent of the equity and the balance 49 percent being held by Indian shareholders. The application was deferred pending comments from the Food Processing Ministry.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>SHELL TO BID FOR REVIVAL OF OIL AND NATURAL GAS CORP FIELD</p>
<p>The Royal Dutch Shell group planned to team up with Oil and Natural Gas Corporation to help revive production at the Neelam oil field of the state owned company. Against the initial projection of 3.5 million tonnes a year, production remained confined to two million tonnes. Shell was keen to participate in the venture and would make a bid once tenders were floated. The bid would mark the beginning of an expansion move by the $168 billion oil multinational, which already has three companies in India through which it was eyeing upstream as well as downstream projects in the country.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>CELLULAR FIRMS MULL LICENCE SURRENDER</p>
<p>Most mobile telephone service providers may surrender their licences if the Telecom Regulatory Authority upheld the tariff hike for fixed to cellular calls. In such an eventuality, the loss of licence fee to the national exchequer was estimated at 80 billion rupees over a 10 year period. Besides, it would also mean a loss of two million expected job opportunities and affect the flow of investments into infrastructure.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>GAS AUTHORITY SELLOFF NEXT, DECISION ON INDIAN OIL DEFERRED</p>
<p>The government was likely to commence disinvestment of its holding in Gas Authority of India (GAIL) soon after the Videsh Sanchar Nigam (VSNL) disinvestment process was completed. However, the decision to divest government stake in Indian Oil Corporation (IOC) was deferred until clearance of the oil sector policy. IOC was identified by the core group of secretaries for the second tranche of disinvestment in 1996/97, after VSNL. Although the VSNL global depository rights issue received a good response, the divestment process would be complete only after a VSNL public issue.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Observer</p>
<p>REJECTED RAIL PROJECTS GET NOD FROM CCEA</p>
<p>Succumbing to political pressure, the Cabinet Committee on Economic Affairs (CCEA) cleared four railway projects which were rejected by the expanded board of secretaries as these were considered unviable. The expanded board comprises secretaries of the departments of expenditure, programme implementation, planning as also members and the chairman of the Railways Board. The projects, estimated to cost around 9.69 billion rupees, related to laying of three new railway lines and gauge conversion in the states of Bihar, Rajasthan, Madhya Pradesh and Maharashtra.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Line</p>
<p>60 PCT DROP IN CELLPHONE CALLS SINCE TARIFF HIKE</p>
<p>Cellular telephone operators built up a strong case for scrapping the increased fixed-to-cellular phone tariff for telecom circles. The operators' said the order had contributed to a 60 percent drop in number of calls, 40 percent fall in new subscribers, a 20 percent cancellation of bookings and even a fall in airtime usage by over 50 percent between cellular and fixed service. The operators said the utility of mobile phones was greatly reduced and circle cellular business rendered unviable. Moreover, foreign investors refused further investments while banks and investors have refused to finance cellular projects.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
