<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522866" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Mill owners say Karachi wheat flour crisis over.</title>
<headline>Mill owners say Karachi wheat flour crisis over.</headline>
<byline>Amir Zia</byline>
<dateline>KARACHI, Pakistan 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A flour shortage that sparked unrest in the southern port city of Karachi is almost over, the Pakistan Flour Mills Association said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;The markets will be flooded with flour when they reopen after Eid al-Adha holidays,&quot; Naeem Malik, the association's vice chairman, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The flour crisis struck Karachi ahead of a four-day holiday for the Moslem feast of Eid al-Adha, which began on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Some 16,000 tonnes of wheat has already arrived in Karachi from interior Sindh, while another 24,000 is due by Sunday evening,&quot; Malik said.</p>
<p>Karachi, the capital of Sindh province, needs about 4,000 tonnes of wheat a day to feed its estimated 12 million people.</p>
<p>&quot;Flour will be available in the city, initially at slightly higher prices as farmers are selling wheat at higher rates. But the prices will gradully come down,&quot; Malik said.</p>
<p>Police guarded mills and bakeries earlier this week to prevent attacks by crowds of angry shoppers and looters.</p>
<p>&quot;The flour shortage has dampened our Eid festivities,&quot; said Inam Khan of Orangi Town.</p>
<p>Flour shortages have provoked violence in several cities in recent weeks, but Karachi had previously been spared.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif's government blames the previous caretaker administration for failing to arrange timely wheat imports, but Malik faulted the government for a ban on the movement of wheat within Pakistan and price controls.</p>
<p>&quot;Now this ban has been lifted and mills can buy wheat from the interior of Sindh. The government has also promised us a share of imported wheat being unloaded at Port Qasim,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Pakistan imported 1.8 million tonnes of wheat in July-March 1996/97 compared to 1.5 million in the year-ago period.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARACHI, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
