<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522801" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Midcontinent Group Three diesel diffs ease.</title>
<headline>U.S. Midcontinent Group Three diesel diffs ease.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Midcontinent Chicago diesel fuel differentials eased Friday as rainy weather in recent days lowered spot agricultural demand, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Agricultural demand slowed down quite a bit,&quot; a trader in the U.S. Gulf said, attributing the sluggish demand to recent rainy weather.</p>
<p>Chicago low sulphur diesel for prompt delivery was talked 3.50 to 3.75 cents a gallon over the NYMEX May heating oil, or 0.25 cents lower than Thursday. Low sulphur for later timings was priced the same.  </p>
<p>Group Three low sulphur differentials ended the day flat at 5.50/5.75 cents a gallon over the print, after rising to around 6.25/6.50 cents on news that a major Canadian pipeline, the Interprovincial, shut four lines briefly on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;That created a little excitment,&quot; a trader said, noting that unconfirmed rumors of refinery problems at Amoco's Texas City, refinery and Tosco's Bayway refinery in New Jersey, had operational problems.</p>
<p>Chicago unleaded was bid up 0.25 cents a gallon, to 0.50 cent a gallon over the print, with premium barrels edging up 0.25 cents a gallon to 0.50 cents a gallon higher.</p>
<p>-- David Brinkerhoff Los Angeles bureau ((213 380-2014))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
