<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522829" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac set on snap election, liberal swing-reports.</title>
<headline>Chirac set on snap election, liberal swing-reports.</headline>
<byline>John Follain</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Jacques Chirac has decided to call an early general election, and may do so as early as Monday, French newspapers said on Saturday as strong speculation continued unabated.</p>
<p>The well-informed daily Le Monde said the ruling centre-right coalition would campaign on a swing towards more liberal economic policies than those pursued so far.</p>
<p>There was no comment from Chirac's office on the reports, which follow days of rumours that he may call a snap June poll to renew his centre-right majority and clear the decks for a crucial year in European integration.</p>
<p>Le Monde quoted unnamed ruling coalition members as saying Chirac had decided to dissolve the National Assembly, probably with a televised broadcast on Monday evening. It said the two-stage election could take place on May 25 and June 1.</p>
<p>Liberation said Monday was the most likely as other evenings were taken up by European Cup soccer matches.</p>
<p>&quot;The nature of a politician is that he must always be ready,&quot; Prime Minister Alain Juppe told France 3 television. &quot;I see much agitation. So people should calm down a little. This decision is entirely up to the President.&quot;</p>
<p>Michel Pericard, head of Chirac's RPR Gaullist party in the Assembly, said that a dissolution was the most likely option.</p>
<p>&quot;The country is in some form of crisis, or rather it is up against a wall...and Chirac must make a strong gesture to give public opinion a say and unblock the situation,&quot; Pericard told Europe-1 radio.</p>
<p>Le Monde quoted an unnamed official as saying the ruling coalition was considering three policy options -- &quot;frenzied liberalism&quot; as advocated by sacked finance minister Alain Madelin, &quot;a more moderate liberalism&quot; as pressed by Juppe, or &quot;tougher austerity&quot; as urged by Finance Minister Jean Arthuis.</p>
<p>If he called a vote, Chirac was expected to argue that it was needed to prepare for a vital year of European integration. The European Union is due to decide early in 1998 which countries attain predetermined criteria to join the single currency due to be launched in 1999.</p>
<p>Arthuis has denied reports that the government was facing problems in meeting Maastricht treaty budget criteria and so might be forced to introduce unpopular spending cuts.</p>
<p>Socialist Party chief Lionel Jospin, leader of France's biggest opposition force, planned to &quot;hit hard&quot; at the ruling coalition and accuse Chirac of breaking his promises in a television interview due on Sunday at seven p.m. (1700 GMT), an aide said.</p>
<p>The Paris stock market's CAC 40 index tumbled 2.59 percent on Friday on fears of a period of political uncertainty and perhaps a new round of fiscal austerity to help France qualify for the EU's planned single currency.</p>
<p>The National Assembly's five-year term expires in March 1998. Speculation of an early election has gained ground over rumours that Chirac may be considering a less dramatic cabinet reshuffle.</p>
<p>Commentators have singled out June 1 and 8 as the most likely dates for a two-stage election, after Chirac returns on May 21 from a trip to China and before he attends the June 15 European Union summit in Amsterdam.</p>
<p>Recent opinion polls have predicted a close battle but differed on whether the centre-right or the left would win.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
