<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522816" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Most French voters would welcome early poll-survey.</title>
<headline>Most French voters would welcome early poll-survey.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most French voters are dissatisfied with President Jacques Chirac and Prime Minister Alain Juppe, and would welcome Chirac's rumoured decision to call snap general elections, opinion polls showed Saturday.</p>
<p>An IFOP survey for the weekly Journal du Dimanche said 56 percent gave Chirac the thumbs down (against 55 a month ago) and 31 percent approved of him (against 32 in March).</p>
<p>Juppe was credited with 61 percent of negative opinions (against 60 percent in March) and 27 percent of favourable opinions (against 29 percent). The poll was carried out on April 10-18 and sounded out 1,849 people.</p>
<p>Another IFOP poll for the weekly showed that 59 percent of voters would approve a possible decision by Chirac to call early general elections for May-June. Thirty-eight percent would disapprove.</p>
<p>The survey was carried out on April 15-16 with a sample of 1,003 people.</p>
<p>The newspaper Le Monde reported on Saturday that Chirac would call an early election on Monday.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for Chirac refused to comment on whether he had decided to call a snap poll, after days of strong speculation that he may try to renew his majority and clear the decks for a crucial year in European integration.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
