<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522846" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's United Front struggles to find new leader.</title>
<headline>India's United Front struggles to find new leader.</headline>
<byline>Jawed Naqvi</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's United Front coalition on Saturday ran into difficulties in selecting a leader to head a new centre-left government as contenders stepped up hectic lobbying, officials said.</p>
<p>A senior official said differences had cropped up among the alliance's 15 parties over who should succeed caretaker Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda, jeopardising efforts to form a government this weekend.</p>
<p>But he said the United Front remained hopeful a consensus candidate would emerge on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope to clinch it by this evening,&quot; the official, who asked not to be identified, told Reuters.</p>
<p>On Friday, United Front officials had said they were confident the alliance would select a new leader on Saturday and that a new government would be formed by Sunday.</p>
<p>But splits quickly emerged between supporters of southern regional leader G.K. Moopanar, caretaker Defence Minister Mulayam Singh Yadav from the northern state of Uttar Pradesh and other contenders from the populous northern Hindi belt, officials said.</p>
<p>On Saturday morning, the senior United Front leader said the prospect of agreeing on a new leader had deteriorated.</p>
<p>But later in the day he said the outlook had brightened after the convenor of the United Front's decision-making Steering Committee, Chandrababu Naidu, held hectic discussions with alliance leaders.</p>
<p>&quot;Things are looking slightly better than a few hours back,&quot; the United Front official said.</p>
<p>A United Front news conference that had been scheduled for 4:30 p.m. (1100 GMT) was postponed indefinitely but would probably be held later in the day, spokesman Jaipal Reddy said.</p>
<p>United Front officials said the Steering Committee might meet on Saturday evening to endorse a new leader.</p>
<p>On Friday, the way appeared to have been cleared for the selection of a leader after the Congress party lifted a roadblock that had threatened to scuttle efforts to form a government without snap elections.</p>
<p>Congress, which had undercut Deve Gowda by withdrawing its vital support for his coalition on March 30, sent a letter to President Shankar Dayal Sharma on Friday saying it would back a new United Front leader if it were not Deve Gowda.</p>
<p>Head of the Tamil Maanila Congress party in Tamil Nadu state, Moopanar has been a front-runner in the race to succeed Deve Gowda, whose 10-month-old government fell on April 11 in a parliamentary vote of confidence.</p>
<p>Moopanar, a former Congress member, has the backing of southern parties that make up a large segment of the United Front's 178 votes in the 542-member lower house.</p>
<p>But he has been opposed by left-wing parties because of his close ties to Congress, which the leftist bloc distrusts.</p>
<p>Emerging as a strong rival to Moopanar was Mulayam Singh Yadav, the strong-willed former chief minister of the populous northern state of Uttar Pradesh.</p>
<p>Yadav's backers said he would be able to lead the fight against the right-wing Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) in the increasingly likely event the next government fails to survive until the end of parliament's term in 2001.</p>
<p>Lurking in the backdrop was caretaker Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral, who supporters said could emerge as a consensus choice as he had no strong political enemies and was respected.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
