<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522825" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Arafat in interview slams US on Israel support.</title>
<headline>Arafat in interview slams US on Israel support.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Palestinian President Yasser Arafat criticised the United States for continuing to support the Israeli government while it plunged &quot;the whole region into catastrophe&quot;, a German magazine reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton has been working to revive the Middle East peace process, which ground to a halt after Israel went ahead with a controversial housing project in Arab East Jerusalem that prompted Palestinian protests.</p>
<p>Arafat told Focus news magazine the United States was not using its influence enough to help the peace process get back on track and he could not rule out war in the region as a consequence of current Israeli policies.</p>
<p>&quot;The Americans are indeed in a position to put pressure on the Israelis. But they are not doing this,&quot; Arafat said in an interview released ahead of publication on Monday.</p>
<p>Clinton's Middle East mediator Dennis Ross got Israeli and Palestinian security chiefs to meet to discuss cooperation during a mission to the region this week, but Ross returned to Washington leaving major gaps between the sides.</p>
<p>&quot;The Americans have supported Israeli policy...in a spectacular way by vetoing United Nations condemnation of the construction of the (Jewish) Har Homa settlement in East Jerusalem on the U.N. security council,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>When asked if he ruled out renewed war in the region, Arafat said: &quot;No. At present the Israeli government is leading the whole region to catastrophe&quot;.</p>
<p>Arafat said the Palestinians were doing their best to prevent more suicide attacks against Israeli citizens.</p>
<p>&quot;No one in the whole world can guarantee they will catch individuals who try to disrupt the peace process with their attacks. But I guarantee we are trying 100 percent to stop the terror,&quot; Arafat said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
