<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522871" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's United Front having trouble finding leader.</title>
<headline>India's United Front having trouble finding leader.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's United Front coalition may be unable to form a new centre-left government this weekend because of difficulties selecting a leader, a senior alliance official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>The official, who asked not to be identified, said the 15-party United Front was struggling to agree on a leader to replace caretaker Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda. Asked if a government would be formed by Sunday, he told Reuters: &quot;It will be rather difficult.&quot;  </p>
<p>On Friday, United Front officials had said they were confident the alliance would select a new leader on Saturday and that a new government would be formed by Sunday.</p>
<p>But differences have cropped up between supporters of southern regional leader G.K. Moopanar, caretaker Defence Minister Mulayam Singh Yadav from the northern state of Uttar Pradesh and other contenders from the populous northern Hindi belt, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is far from over,&quot; the senior United Front leader said. &quot;It is quite a sensitive phase.&quot; Asked if the coalition was still confident a new leader would be selected on Saturday, he said: &quot;I underestimated the difficulties.&quot;</p>
<p>He said no meeting of the United Front's decision-making Steering Committee had yet been scheduled to take up the leadership question.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
