<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522860" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India industry welcomes new leader, broods on budget.</title>
<headline>India industry welcomes new leader, broods on budget.</headline>
<byline>Hari Ramachandran</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian industry on Saturday welcomed the governing United Front coalition's naming of a new leader, but there were worries about the budget because the party to which the former Finance Minister belongs has opted out of the government.</p>
<p>Care taker Prime Minister H. D. Deve Gowda told reporters on Saturday that the United Front's Steering Committee had unanimously chosen Inder Kumar Gujral, foreign minister in the outgoing government, to lead the 15-party coalition.</p>
<p>Deve Gowda's 10-month old government was defeated in a vote of confidence in parliament on April 11.</p>
<p>Minutes later, the Tamil Manila Congress (TMC), to which outgoing Finance Minister P. Chidambaram belongs, said it would not participate in a new government, though it would continue to support it.</p>
<p>TMC leader G.K. Moopanar had been considered a front-runner for leader of the coalition.</p>
<p>&quot;For the present the impasse seems to be over,&quot;  V. Raghuraman, secretary general of the Associated Chambers of Commerce and Industry (ASSOCHAM), told Reuters.</p>
<p>Raghuraman said that although the TMC has decided to stay out of the government and although Chidambaram may no longer be Finance Minister he felt the general budget for 1997/98 (April-March) presented on February 28, would get parliament's approval.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think they (the government) will disown the budget. It is a UF (United Front) budget,&quot; said Raghuraman. &quot;Otherwise they will have no credibility.&quot;</p>
<p>Technically, the 1997/98 (April-March) budget, handed down in February, is a piece of legislation from the former government.</p>
<p>It must still be agreed by parliament. Approval is widely seen as a test of politicians' commitment to economic reforms, despite underlying philosophical differences, analysts said.</p>
<p>The United Front's tax-cutting measures and steps to boost investment have won favour with India's other political parties.</p>
<p>The President of the Confederation of Indian Industry (CII) Shekhar Datta said Gujral was a mature leader and industry expected him to bring back stability.</p>
<p>Datta said if a new government was formed before Monday or Tuesday then it might ask for discussion on the budget to be postponed.</p>
<p>&quot;Legally speaking it is not the same government. If you change the leader you will have to have a new government,&quot; Datta said.</p>
<p>&quot;The new government has to own the budget,&quot; Datta said. &quot;We will have to wait and see.&quot;</p>
<p>D.H. Pai Panandhikar, economist and advisor to the RPG group of industries, said the budget was now the property of parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;Being Chidambaram's budget, TMC will support it and with the Congress support, it should go through,&quot; Panandikar said.</p>
<p>It was still a United Front government though one of its constitutents had decided to stay out, he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
