<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522876" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: Sri Lanka to unveil new mineral policy soon.</title>
<headline>Sri Lanka to unveil new mineral policy soon.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sri Lanka will shortly unveil a new mineral policy that will give private enterprises the prime role in commercial exploration and mining, an Industries Ministry official said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe commercial exploration and exploitation should be done by the private sector,&quot; said the official, who declined to be identified.</p>
<p>Companies with proven experience can apply for an exploration licence and will be given the sole authority to explore a given area as well as priority over others in mining any minerals which may be found, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The government does not have the money nor the technology for large scale commercial exploration and mining,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The government will do a limited amount of exploration and mining mostly for geological mapping, he said.</p>
<p>Under the policy, the government will also encourage the setting up of value- added mineral industries, he said.</p>
<p>The draft policy also tightens environmental measures as well as standards to protect the health of workers, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The minerals industry can sometimes have a devastating impact on the environment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bureau officials said several multinational firms have sought exploration rights to look for gold and minerals in the Indian Ocean island.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka has deposits of mineral sands, quartz and phosphate among other minerals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I23000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
