<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522834" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Amid uproar, decisions on U.N. parking delayed.</title>
<headline>Amid uproar, decisions on U.N. parking delayed.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-04-18</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States on Friday deferred all new plans to punish United Nations diplomats for unpaid parking tickets, saying it needed to negotiate further with New York Mayor Rudolph Giuliani.</p>
<p>In turn the chairman of a U.N. committee, which has had vitriolic debates on the subject, said he would delay an earlier decision to take the issue to the full 185-nation U.N. General Assembly. The controversy has become a public relations disaster for the world body.</p>
<p>Contrary to reports that a deal had been struck between the State Department and the United Nations, U.S. delegate Victor Marrero said all new parking plans &quot;had been deferred.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We need more time to consider ideas that we brought to the city and discussed with the U.N. legal counsel,&quot; he told reporters. &quot;We need to go back to see if other alternatives are feasible.&quot;</p>
<p>At issue are regulations announced last month by Giuliani, with the State Department's approval, These would remove the special license plates of diplomats who routinely ignore parking tickets and other violations.</p>
<p>The U.N. legal counsel, Hans Corell, said parts of the plan violated international law. As an alternative, the State Department proposed that it would deny foreign missions concerned a new plate next time they applied for one, which usually happens annually due to the rotation of personnel.</p>
<p>This would punish the mission but not necessarily the same diplomat who received the tickets, according to outlines of the proposal announced by the State Department last week.</p>
<p>Cypriot ambassador Nicos Agathocleous, chairman of the U.N committee on relations with the host countreand diplomatic way.&quot;</p>
<p>An angry Giuliani on Friday conceded he could do little to change the mind of the State Department, which issues the plates. But he said he would remove some of the 111 parking spaces he had reserved for diplomats and publish lists of unpaid tickets run up by foreign missions.</p>
<p>&quot;They had agreed with us to take the license plates of diplomats away if they didn't pay their tickets,&quot; he told reporters. &quot;The State Department has now backed off this.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They are willing to take away registrations but not license plates. We think they should fight it out. We think they shouldn't back down to the United Nations threatening them. But the State Department has a different view of it.&quot;</p>
<p>Giuliani, once a supporter of the United Nations that brings about $3.3 billion in revenue and goods and services to New York, last week suggested the world body could move elsewhere. His comments were ridiculed by many but welcomed by numerous residents who resent the diplomatic plates.</p>
<p>Sensing a good fight, city police, according to several diplomats, stepped up issuing tickets, including towing diplomatic cars parked legally in reserved spots. The main target is the large Russian mission, which is located near a police precinct and has more than 30,000 unpaid parking ticket</p>
<p>City officials claim diplomats ignored 134,281 tickets last year, each costing a minimum of $55. REUTER 182210 GMT apr 97</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-18"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
