<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522809" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Boeing to compensate for Dominican crash - lawyer.</title>
<headline>Boeing to compensate for Dominican crash - lawyer.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A lawyer representing 70 relatives of German tourists who died in a Boeing 757 plane crash in the Caribbean last year said on Saturday that Boeing Co. was prepared to pay compensation.</p>
<p>Lawyer Heiko Van Schyndel told Reuters the U.S aircraft manufacturer wanted to avoid a law suit by the victims' families after a report showed the probable cause to be the crew's confusion over the aircraft's system.</p>
<p>&quot;Boeing recognized the claims of the relatives at the beginning of this month and said it was prepared to pay compensation,&quot; said Van Schyndel who works for a law firm in Berlin representing 70 relatives of victims.</p>
<p>In Seattle, Boeing Co. spokesman John Dern said the plane company was involved in discussions with the representatives of the victims' families, but had not reached any settlement.</p>
<p>&quot;Because the discussions are on-going, it is inappropriate for me to go into specifics,&quot; he told Reuters. &quot;We haven't reached any conclusions yet.&quot;</p>
<p>Dern would not comment on the lawyer's version that Boeing had set aside $18 million. &quot;I just can't go into that.&quot;</p>
<p>The 757 leased to the Dominican airline Alas Nacionales by Turkish carrier Birgenair plunged into the sea on Feb. 9 shortly after taking off from the Dominican resort of Puerto Plata. All 189 people on board, mostly German tourists, died.</p>
<p>Van Schyndel said that victims' lawyers would meet Boeing's lawyers at the company headquarters in Seattle in June to discuss the details of the payments.</p>
<p>&quot;Boeing wants to prevent a law suit against them to claim for maintenance and compensation for personal suffering. We said we would not rule out filing a suit if we do not reach an agreement with them,&quot; Van Schyndel said.</p>
<p>&quot;Boeing wants to avoid the negative publicity,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Spiegel news magazine reported that Boeing was prepared to pay relatives compensation in cases where maintenance was required, for example, to children who lost their parents.</p>
<p>An official report last October year said the plane crash off the Dominican Republic was probably due to human error.</p>
<p>In the report, the Dominican office of Civil Aviation and the U.S. National Transportation Safety Board said the probable cause of the crash was the crew's &quot;confusion and lack of knowledge&quot; of the aircraft's systems.</p>
<p>Spiegel said Boeing had since made amendments to the instructions in the 757's cockpit handbook for pilots.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
