<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522838" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Gujral named to head new Indian government.</title>
<headline>Gujral named to head new Indian government.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's United Front alliance named outgoing Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral on Saturday as its leader to head a centre-left government but a key partner decided to pull out of his coalition.</p>
<p>The choice of Gujral, a 77-year-old scholar who enjoys a spotless reputation, ended a three-week political crisis that shook financial markets and threatened to plunge India into its second general election in a year.</p>
<p>&quot;I bow my head to the people of India,&quot; Gujral told reporters after the decision was announced. &quot;I promise them to the best of my capacity to give a clean government, a government that serves them.&quot;</p>
<p>Gujral, an erudite socialist, has held seven ministerial portfolios dating back to 1967 and was ambassador to the former Soviet Union from 1976 to 1980.</p>
<p>He is widely respected but has no strong political power base, which could prove an advantage in the current highly-politicised atmosphere.</p>
<p>Caretaker Prime Minister H.D. Deve Gowda told reporters the 15-party coalition's decision-making Steering Committee unanimously chose Gujral to lead the alliance.</p>
<p>But Finance Minister P. Chidambaram's Tamil Maanila Congress (TMC) said it would not join the new government. It said it would support the alliance from outside, thus not prevenintg the government from functioning.</p>
<p>The TMC, a powerful regional party from the southern state of Tamil Nadu, had three other ministers in the outgoing 10-month-old United Front government, which lost a parliamentary vote of confidence on April 11.</p>
<p>The party's withdrawal could raise doubts over the fate of the 1997/98 (April-March) budget which Chidambaram presented in February and was due to be debated in a special session of parliament from Monday to Wednesday.</p>
<p>TMC leader G.K. Moopanar had been regarded as a front-runner for Deve Gowda's job, but analysts said he was rejected because he was considered too close to the Congress party. The TMC was formed in 1996 by members of a breakaway Congress group.</p>
<p>Congress, which provoked Deve Gowda's downfall by withdrawing its crucial parliamentary support last month, had said it would back the coalition under a new leader.</p>
<p>Congress chief Sitaram Kesri, quoted by the Press Trust of India (PTI), said Gujral's election was the &quot;biggest triumph&quot; for his party.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Gujral has earlier been in Congress. He is not anti-Congress,&quot; Kesri said. &quot;Gujral is not Deve Gowda.&quot;</p>
<p>Neither the United Front nor Congress wanted mid-term elections which opinion surveys show could put the right-wing Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) within striking distance of power.</p>
<p>Their common opposition to the BJP, more than shared principles, has kept the United Front and Congress from rupturing ties despite the mounting acrimony which resulted in Deve Gowda's downfall.</p>
<p>Gujral said his first aim was to take steps to alleviate poverty, backwardness and problems of social justice.</p>
<p>&quot;India can be held together by secularism. Again I say with humility as a humble man (I will) serve the nation in the 50th year of independence,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The coalition leaders will meet President Shankar Dayal Sharma on Sunday to convey the alliance's decision.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that the new government will last a little longer than the one headed by H.D. Deve Gowda,&quot; United News of India quoted BJP leader Atal Behari Vajpayee as saying.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
