<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522869" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan still awaits word on haj fire victims.</title>
<headline>Pakistan still awaits word on haj fire victims.</headline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>Anxious Pakistanis are still waiting for Saudi Arabia to list victims of a fire that ravaged a pilgrim encampment near Mecca, an official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;The Saudi government has told us it will furnish the latest list tonight,&quot; said the official at an emergency information cell set up near Islamabad after Tuesday's blaze which Saudi authorities say killed 343 people and injured 1,290.</p>
<p>&quot;We have received about 80,000 calls in the past three days,&quot; the official said. &quot;We are working 24 hours a day.&quot;</p>
<p>Confusion persisted over the casualty toll.</p>
<p>The official, who asked not to be named, said 13 of an unknown number of Pakistani fatalities had been identified.</p>
<p>Pakistan's ambassador to Saudi Arabia Shahid Amin said on Thursday that 35 Pakistanis were missing from the haj tents, but did not confirm that they had died in the fire.</p>
<p>Saudi Arabia's Pilgrimage Affairs and Religious Endowments Minister Mahmoud bin Mohammad Safar told Amin on Friday night the Pakistani toll might be higher than first reported, the official news agency APP said.</p>
<p>&quot;He (Safar) informed the ambassador that on the basis of circumstantial evidence and the number of dead bodies already recovered from Pakistani haj camps and the streets surrounding them, the actual figure of casualties among Pakistani nationals may be higher than reported earlier,&quot; APP said.</p>
<p>&quot;However, given the stampede that took place in haj camps after eruption of fire, it cannot be said with authenticity that the dead bodies recovered from Pakistani camps are necessarily those of Pakistani nationals,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>APP said Safar had set up a committee at the Pakistani government's request to provide more definite information about Pakistani fire victims, but this &quot;may take some more time&quot;.</p>
<p>Diplomats in Saudi Arabia said most of the dead were from the Indian subcontinent. The fire also engulfed the Iranian, Syrian, Lebanese, Egyptian, Sudanese, Yemeni and Moroccan sections of the encampment at Mina, near Mecca.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
