<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522824" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Boeing ready to pay crash compensation-report.</title>
<headline>Boeing ready to pay crash compensation-report.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>A German magazine reported on Saturday Boeing Co. was prepared to pay compensation to the families of 189 victims, mainly German tourists, of a Boeing 757 plane crash in February 1996 off the Dominican Republic.</p>
<p>Spiegel said Berlin lawyer Elmar Giemulla representing 70 relatives of crash victims' said the U.S. airline manufacturer said on April 2 it was prepared to pay compensation in cases where financial support was needed &quot;for humanitarian reasons&quot;.</p>
<p>The company said this would apply to children who lost their parents for example, Spiegel said in a report released ahead of publication on Monday.</p>
<p>Giemulla said he would meet Boeing's lawyers at their headquarters in Seattle to discuss the details of the payments, Spiegel said.</p>
<p>It said Boeing spokesman John Dern had declined comment on the size of the payments but said sources close to the victims' families cited payments of 18 million dollars.</p>
<p>A joint U.S. and Dominican report put the accident down to human error in a report last October.</p>
<p>In the report, the Dominican office of Civil Aviation and the U.S. National Transportation Safety Board said the probable cause of the crash was the crew's &quot;confusion and lack of knowledge&quot; of the aircraft's systems.</p>
<p>The 757 leased to the Dominican national airline Alas Nacionales by Turkish carrier Birgenair plunged into the sea on February 9 shortly after taking off from the Dominican resort of Puerto Plata. All 189 people on board died in the disaster.</p>
<p>Spiegel said that since then Boeing had made amendments to the instructions in the 757's cockpit handbook for pilots.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
