<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522810" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: IMF said critical of Italy mini-budget -news agency.</title>
<headline>IMF said critical of Italy mini-budget -news agency.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-04-19</dateline>
<text>
<p>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) has criticised the Italian government's proposed mini-budget for lacking structural reform measures, the Italian news agency ANSA reported from Washington on Saturday.</p>
<p>The agency, quoting excerpts from &quot;confidential IMF documents obtained by Ansa&quot;, said the Fund believed the mini-budget to be &quot;less than what might have been desirable&quot; and aimed primarily at meeting European economic and monetary union (EMU) targets.</p>
<p>It quoted executive director Thomas Bernes as saying that Italy was putting too much emphasis on qualifying for European economic and monetary union (EMU) from the outset rather than tackling much-needed structural reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;In Italy there seems to be too much emphasis on participation in EMU as an end in itself rather than the challenges that Italy must face independently of whether it joins the first group or not,&quot; Ansa quoted him as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;These include the high level of unemployment concentrated in the south, the burden of public debt and the balancing of the budget, a relatively inflexible labour market and a fragile banking system,&quot; Bernes added.</p>
<p>Ansa said the IMF had said the Italian government &quot;should look to internal motivation for the improvement in public accounts and structural reforms&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;In this way, the risk of reforms stopping should Italy be excluded initially (from EMU) would diminish,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Bernes was also quoted as saying that financial markets would react more favourably to &quot;a solid programme carried out over a longer period of time than to a series of ambitious but debatable measures.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Such as the supplementary budget which does not contain structural measures on welfare spending,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi's administration has drawn up a 15.5 trillion lire ($9 billion) supplementary budget in a sustained effort to ensure Italy makes the first wave of European economic and monetary union (EMU) from January 1999.</p>
<p>But there have been doubts as to the sustainability of the deficit-cutting measures. Both industry and the opposition have criticised the mini-budget for not addressing structural reforms.</p>
<p>The government was also embarrassed on Friday when a lower house budget commission rejected the measure, helped by two centre-left deputies who voted against it.</p>
<p>Prodi is now expected to have to resort to a parliamentary confidence vote to force the mini-budget through.</p>
<p>Innocenzo Cipoletta, director general of the employer's federation Confindustria which has asked for the mini-budget to be withdrawn, reacted to the Ansa report on Saturday by saying his body was in full agreement with the IMF.</p>
<p>&quot;More than a new budget we need a budget that allows us to reduce structurally the deficit,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Businesses have complained about one section of the mini-budget which aims to raise 1997 revenue by bringing forward tax payments due on companies pools of severance payment funds.</p>
<p>Prodi, speaking to reporters in Milan on Saturday, did not comment directly on the report but repeated his insistence that Italy must be in the single currency from the start.</p>
<p>&quot;While respecting the mathematics, we believe Europe to be something else,&quot; he said, referring to social, security and enlargement issues. &quot;I am convinced that a strong and united Europe cannot exist without the Latin countries.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
