<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="522858" id="root" date="1997-04-19" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India coalition prepares for power under Gujral.</title>
<headline>India coalition prepares for power under Gujral.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Verma</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1996-04-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's United Front alliance prepared on Sunday to form a government under a new leader, whose nomination ended three weeks of political turmoil but sparked a rift within the 15-party coalition.</p>
<p>Inder Kumar Gujral, a scholarly 77-year-old socialist who is India's outgoing foreign minister, was due to meet President Shankar Dayal Sharma at 11 a.m. (0530 GMT) to formally claim power as the new head of the centre-left coalition.</p>
<p>Caretaker prime minister H.D. Deve Gowda, ousted as the head of the 10-month-old coalition in a vote of confidence on April 11, said on Saturday that Gujral was the alliance's unanimous choice.</p>
<p>But the goateed leader's nomination swiftly soured relations with a powerful regional partner in the coalition, the Tamil Maanila Congress (TMC), which pledged to pull out of the government minutes after he was named as its leader.</p>
<p>The TMC's withdrawal raised questions over the fate of outgoing finance minister P. Chidambaram's budget for 1997/98 (April-March), presented in February and due to be discussed by parliament later this week.</p>
<p>Chidambaram, the coalition's most outspoken free-trader, was one of the four TMC ministers in Deve Gowda's cabinet. His market-friendly budget contained a battery of proposals to slash taxes and lower import tariffs.</p>
<p>TMC leader G.K. Moopanar had been considered a favourite for Deve Gowda's job but was apparently rejected because the party, formed last year by a breakaway faction of the Congress party, was considered too close to Congress.</p>
<p>Congress, which triggered Deve Gowda's downfall last month by withdrawing vital support to his government, has already withdrawn its claim to form a new administration, clearing the decks for Gujral's bid to install a new government.</p>
<p>Gujral, an erudite socialist who has held seven ministerial posts since 1967, promised on Saturday to provide a clean government and strengthen national unity.</p>
<p>His reputation as an mild-mannered, uncontroversial moderate with no real political base nudged him ahead of Moopanar and others in the race for leadership.</p>
<p>Gujral now faces the ticklish task of juggling the demands of the United Front, which loosely groups socialists, regional parties, communists and free-traders, without irritating Congress, which props the coalition up in parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;How he will walk the tightrope is something that remains to be seen,&quot; said Mahesh Rangarajan, political analyst at New Delhi's Centre for Contemporary Studies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-19"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-19"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
