<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="523132" id="root" date="1997-04-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FEATURE-Sydney Opera House development sparks protests.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Sydney Opera House development sparks protests.</headline>
<byline>Richard Pullin</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-04-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>To many in Sydney and around the world, the view of the Australian city's famed, white-sailed Opera House is part of the magic which makes Sydney's harbour one of the world's most beautiful.</p>
<p>But plans to build a series of multi-storey apartment blocks close to the Opera House have threatened to mar that view permanently, sparking a fiery public outcry.</p>
<p>&quot;It's just a terrible mistake,&quot; said Jack Mundey, a former union leader who led a five-year campaign in the 1970s to preserve an historic district on Sydney's Circular Quay, which cradles the harbour.</p>
<p>Critics of the plan say the apartment blocks will be a blot on one of the city's most scenic and well-known waterfront sites. The area is a key attraction for tourists and will form the backdrop for the 2000 Olympics, when the eyes of the world will be on the city.</p>
<p>Work on the first 15-storey building on the eastern arm of the Quay has prompted two demonstrations on the steps of the Opera House. Newspapers and radio stations have been flooded with caustic criticism of the project.</p>
<p>Opponents have urged the New South Wales state government to halt the A$700 million (US$550 million) project, either by buying back the site, offering a land swap, or pushing for a single high-rise tower set well back from the Opera House.</p>
<p>The developers argue that the site has housed commercial buildings since 1807, and the development will be lower than the 1950s high-rise buildings that once lined the Quay.</p>
<p>OPPONENTS SAY DEVELOPMENT WILL BLOCK VIEWS</p>
<p>But opponents say the development, which will include a two-storey covered walkway to the Opera House with cinemas and cafes, will be too high and too wide.</p>
<p>They say that will mean an end to views from the Quay of the nearby botanical gardens and will block many of the approach views of the Opera House.</p>
<p>The building, which perches on the tip of Bennelong Point jutting out onto Sydney harbour, is famous world-wide for its unique design, often likened to a series of overlapping white sea-shells or sails.</p>
<p>&quot;The Opera House is one of the most three dimensional buildings in the world,&quot; said Sydney architect Neville Gruzman, who heads the East Circular Quay Committee.</p>
<p>&quot;It depends a great deal for its magic on the way the views of the shells change as you move towards it.&quot;</p>
<p>PROTESTS TAKE OFF AS WORK BEGINS</p>
<p>Public protests kicked off earlier this year when work started on the first apartment block nearest the Opera House.</p>
<p>&quot;The public have suddenly seen this disastrous building,&quot; Gruzman said. &quot;They couldn't imagine what it was going to be like.&quot;</p>
<p>About 3,500 people turned out for the second rally on the steps of the Opera House earlier this month and more than 30,000 signatures have been collected opposing the project.</p>
<p>But the government has already ruled out purchasing the site, arguing that the A$800 million needed to buy it could be better spent on schools and hospitals.</p>
<p>Gruzman said the most practical alternative would be a 40-50 storey tower at the end of the site furthest from the Opera House.</p>
<p>DEVELOPERS STAND FIRM ON PROJECT</p>
<p>But developers say they will not consider any changes to the project, which is on schedule for completion in 1999. Approval for the current design was given in 1994 after years of tortuous negotiations.</p>
<p>Most of the site is now owned by luxury hotel and property group Hongkong and Shanghai Hotels Ltd, with the southernmost site being built by local property developer and manager Mirvac.</p>
<p>&quot;All this ballyhoo now is just ridiculous because it went through five years of discussions,&quot; said Mirvac general manager Robert Hamilton.</p>
<p>&quot;We have got legal valid approval, we have sold all our units, the excavation is completed and the crane goes in in the next few weeks,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hongkong and Shanghai Hotels was still considering the possibility of building a hotel rather than just apartments, but said it will work within the approved guidelines.</p>
<p>&quot;We've always thought a hotel would be a better option because it's such a superb site,&quot; said a spokeswoman for Hongkong and Shanghai Hotels.</p>
<p>Both Mirvac and Hongkong and Shanghai Hotels say a plan for a 50-storey tower was rejected years ago as it would block views over Sydney harbour for many other buildings and cast a shadow over the botanical gardens.</p>
<p>But opponents still hoped for compromise.</p>
<p>Gruzman said the first building in the new project has shown how much of the area's character will be lost when the now vacant site is again covered by buildings.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't take much imagination to see it's going to be a disaster,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$0.78)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I5010022">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I66500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
