<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="523378" id="root" date="1997-04-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Timothy Leary to take ultimate trip -- into space.</title>
<headline>Timothy Leary to take ultimate trip -- into space.</headline>
<byline>Merissa Marr</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>Timothy Leary, the 1960s guru of LSD and 1990s icon of the Internet, will take the ultimate trip on Monday when his ashes are blasted into space with a Spanish satellite.</p>
<p>The cremated remains of Leary, whose final request before dying was for &quot;one last far-out trip&quot;, will be launched into orbit with those of &quot;Star Trek&quot; creator Gene Roddenberry and 22 other space enthusiasts for the world's first space funeral.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a way for people with a fascination with outer space to participate in the opening of the frontier and connect with the star-filled night sky&quot; said Chan Tysor, president of Celestis, the Texan company organising the venture.</p>
<p>The ashes, secured in sealed vials, will piggyback a mission to send Spain's first satellite into orbit via a Pegasus rocket to be launched over the Canary Islands on Monday.</p>
<p>The lipstick-sized capsules containing seven grams (0.25 oz) of remains will be released into space and will orbit the earth for anywhere between 18 months and 10 years before gravity pulls them back into the atmosphere where they will burn up in a flash of light.</p>
<p>Family and friends accompanied the ashes of their loved ones to Madrid on Friday before they were transported to the Canary Islands for take-off.</p>
<p>&quot;Timothy had always been a space pioneer and wanted to travel into space and now he has the opportunity,&quot; said Carol Rosin, a close friend of Leary who was by his side when he died of prostate cancer aged 75.</p>
<p>In an article shortly after the death of the former Harvard professor last year, Rosin said Leary, weak with illness, had been overjoyed when she showed him a promotional video of the proposed space funerals.</p>
<p>&quot;He was so excited that he would finally go into space, and with other space pioneers, that he jumped up and down in his wheelchair. I know that is the moment he decided it was time to die,&quot; she wrote.</p>
<p>Leary, who urged a generation of Americans to get high on LSD so they could &quot;turn on, tune in and drop out&quot;, was fired from Harvard in 1963 for involving students in his mind-bending drug experiments. Former U.S. President Richard Nixon branded him &quot;the most dangerous man in America&quot;.</p>
<p>He later became an early devotee of the Internet, calling it the LSD of the next century. In his final days, he planned to commit suicide while broadcasting it on the worldwide computer network but never had a chance and died peacefully in his bed.</p>
<p>The journey into space will begin on a Pegasus rocket, carried aloft by a Lockheed L-1011 jetliner from Gran Canaria and launched in airspace above the island, Spain's Defence Ministry said.</p>
<p>The rocket will be released from the aircraft at 11,000 metres (36,000 feet), where it will fall until its engines ignite, powering it into space.</p>
<p>At 600 km (370 miles) the rocket will first deploy the Minisat, the first satellite entirely designed and constructed in Spain, which will remain in orbit for two years.</p>
<p>Soon after, the part of the rocket storing the containers of human ashes will break away into space.</p>
<p>&quot;Eventually they will re-enter the atmosphere ... blazing like a shooting star in final tribute,&quot; said Tysor.</p>
<p>Celestis said they planned a second launch in September aboard a Taurus rocket from California with room for 150 passengers each paying $4,800 for the journey. The company intends to make three launches a year.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think this will ever replace the traditional funeral but there is a huge demand from those who want to connect with their interest in expanding our presence in space,&quot; said Tysor.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
