<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="523321" id="root" date="1997-04-20" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: &quot;Anaconda&quot; and Carrey remain tops at U.S. box office.</title>
<headline>&quot;Anaconda&quot; and Carrey remain tops at U.S. box office.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-20</dateline>
<text>
<p>&quot;Anaconda&quot; and &quot;Liar Liar&quot; retained the top two positions at the U.S. weekend box office according to studio estimates released Sunday.</p>
<p>Three movies opened in the top 10, but none of them showed much promise. The highest debut was at third, &quot;Murder at 1600,&quot; a White House murder mystery starring Wesley Snipes. The movie earned about $8.0 million.</p>
<p>Additionally, &quot;Chasing Amy&quot; reached the top 10 after two weeks in limited release. The boy-meets-lesbian comedy from &quot;Clerks&quot; writer/director Kevin Smith vied for the final spot with an estimated take of $1.6 million.</p>
<p>For the second consecutive weekend, Columbia Pictures' &quot;Anaconda&quot; held its grip at the top by swallowing about $12.2 million. Its 10-day total rises to $39.2 million. The movie, about a 40-foot snake on the loose in the Amazon, slipped just 27 percent from its opening round, and its per-screen average of $4,967 was the highest in the top 10. Columbia is a unit of Sony Corp..</p>
<p>Jim Carrey's &quot;Liar Liar&quot; followed with $10.2 million, which took its 31-day total to $133.6 million. Falling 30 percent from last weekend, the movie averaged a sturdy $3,505. It is released by Universal Pictures, a unit of Seagram Co. Ltd..</p>
<p>&quot;Murder at 1600&quot; averaged $3,717. A Variety poll of critics in New York, Los Angeles and Washington DC showed that five liked it, 11 did not and 13 were mixed. The movie is released by Warner Bros., a unit of Time Warner Inc..</p>
<p>The other debuts were Tom Arnold's bawdy big-screen version of &quot;McHale's Navy,&quot; which was seventh-equal with $2.1 million and a per-screen average of $1,130. Universal did not screen the film in time for many critics' deadlines. However, Variety described it as a &quot;fitfully amusing lark that quickly runs aground.&quot;</p>
<p>Joe Pesci's dark comedy &quot;8 Heads in a Duffel Bag&quot; opened in ninth with $1.8 million, and an $1,158 average. Variety's poll showed that one critic liked it, 13 did not and six were mixed. It is released by Orion Pictures, a unit of Metromedia International Group Inc..</p>
<p>One movie to overcome bad reviews has been Paramount Pictures' &quot;The Saint,&quot; which slipped a notch to fourth this weekend with about $7.3 million. The Val Kilmer/Elisabeth Shue thriller has earned $41.4 million after 17 days. Down 32 percent this weekend, it averaged $2,920 per screen. Paramount is a unit of Viacom Inc..</p>
<p>Holding steady at fifth was Walt Disney Co.'s &quot;Grosse Pointe Blank,&quot; with $4.9 million in its second weekend. Its 10-day total is 13.8 million. Down 29 percent, the John Cusack romantic comedy averaged $3,964 per screen, the second highest in the top 10.</p>
<p>Disney also owns Miramax Films, which released &quot;Chasing Amy.&quot; Expanding to 519 screens from 25 last week when it ranked 26th, the movie averaged $3,083. Its three-week total rises to $2.1 million, good going for a movie that cost about $200,000 to make.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34540">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I42400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-20"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-20"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
