<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="524194" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Absence of judge stalls Nigerian musician's trial.</title>
<headline>Absence of judge stalls Nigerian musician's trial.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>The absence on Monday of a judge prevented the trial in Nigeria of maverick musician Fela Anikulapo-Kuti on drug charges, witnesses said.</p>
<p>The tribunal's registrar did not give a reason for the absence of chairman Judge Yusuf Tanko Usman and adjourned the case to Wednesday.</p>
<p>Witnesses said many of Fela's fans thronged the venue, while a pale-looking Fela acknowledged their cheers.</p>
<p>Fela, as he is widely known, faces a minimum of 15 years in jail if convicted of possessing and using cannabis.</p>
<p>Fela, 59, was arrested on April 9 with 107 other people at his &quot;The Shrine&quot; nightclub in a working class district of Lagos for alleged possession of cannabis.</p>
<p>The National Drug Law Enforcement Agency (NDLEA) has since freed most of the others arrested with him.</p>
<p>Fela filed a suit last week at a Lagos court claiming 100 million naira ($11,765) in damages from the NDLEA for alleged violation of his human rights and a high court judge ordered that he should be released by the agency.</p>
<p>His lawyer Femi Falana, a human rights activist, said on Monday: &quot;This tribunal is a law court and a high court has set Fela free, so the tribunal should obey the court order.&quot;</p>
<p>There is no bail for drug offences in Nigeria.</p>
<p>The Afro-beat superstar is no stranger to controversy -- or to the jail cell. A past critic of Nigeria's military rulers, he has a reputation for openly smoking marijuana and dressing only in his underpants.</p>
<p>($1=85 naira)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
