<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525009" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Russian treasures tied up in Washington legal knot.</title>
<headline>Russian treasures tied up in Washington legal knot.</headline>
<byline>Robert Kearns</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>An exhibition of treasures from Russia's imperial past was stranded in a truck and in a museum's vault on Monday as lawyers wrangled over control of the priceless show.</p>
<p>The collection, including art works, costumes and some of the world's biggest gems, was due to be shown in several U.S. cities thoughout this year, starting with a successful show at Washington's Corcoran Gallery of Art, which has just ended.</p>
<p>But Russia now says it wants the treasures back for Moscow's 850th birthday celebration in May, according to the Corcoran.</p>
<p>The American organisers of the exhibition refuse to deliver them to the Russian Embassy, citing a contract with the Russian government.</p>
<p>&quot;This needs to be decided by a court,&quot; said David Levy, president and director of the Corcoran Gallery.</p>
<p>Levy has locked away the Romanov jewels in a vault and is sitting tight until he gets a court order or a written agreement about where they go next.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope it doesn't get to that,&quot; worries James Symington, head of the Washington-based American Russian Cultural Cooperation Foundation, which raised $550,000 to mount the exhibition. &quot;My hope is to get this rascal back on track.&quot;</p>
<p>Jack and Marcy Eschenbach hope so too. Hired to bring the exhibition to Houston for the next stop on a planned tour, they have been sleeping in their moving van on a side street near the gallery since last Wednesday.</p>
<p>Cars manned round-the-clock by drivers from the Russian Embassy blocked them in until Monday, when agreement was reached to drive the truck to a more secure parking area where it can be better guarded, museum officials said.</p>
<p>Symington said Moscow representatives are appealing to &quot;the highest levels of government&quot; to restore the seven-museum tour that his organisation has contracted to provide.</p>
<p>&quot;It was the Russian's idea for the tour,&quot; he said. &quot;It's not ours.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It was a sensation at the Corcoran,&quot; he said, noting that &quot;Jewels of the Romanovs: Treasures of the Imperial Court&quot; drew over 80,000 visitors during a stay that ended last week.</p>
<p>That's when the trouble began.</p>
<p>Symington attributes it to a dispute over revenue, not to Moscow's need for the jewels back home.</p>
<p>He said the deal with Russia's Culture ministry was to split revenues after expenses were paid, but said Russian officials were now telling him that that arrangement was not acceptable. &quot;It doesn't satisfy them,&quot; Symington said.</p>
<p>But John Millian, a lawyer retained by the Russian Embassy, denied that profits were the motive.</p>
<p>&quot;The issue is not money,&quot; he said. &quot;The issue is shared responsibility to manage the project. The foundation has refused to enter into an agreement for joint control.&quot;</p>
<p>All sides in the dispute spent the weekend trying to arrange a meeting of their lawyers.</p>
<p>Symington said it was a good sign when he could not reach his lawyer on Monday morning. &quot;Maybe she is talking to someone about this,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
