<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525108" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Six Koresh cult members lose US High Court appeal.</title>
<headline>Six Koresh cult members lose US High Court appeal.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Supreme Court Monday let stand the convictions of six followers of cult leader David Koresh for the deadly 1993 gun battle with federal agents at the Branch Davidian compound near Waco, Texas.</p>
<p>The high court rejected appeals by the cult members who were convicted after a jury trial of voluntary manslaughter of federal officers, using a firearm in a crime of violence and possessing machineguns and a grenade.</p>
<p>The charges stemmed from the Feb. 28, 1992 raid by the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, which led to a shootout that killed four agents and wounded more than 20. Three cult members also were killed in the confrontation.</p>
<p>The raid, carried out by 76 agents, was designed to arrest Koresh and conduct a search of the compound but he was tipped off and gunfire erupted from the compound when the agents tried to approach. A 51-day standoff followed, ending April 19, 1993, when FBI agents mounted an armoured assault.</p>
<p>A fire then engulfed the compound, killing Koresh and about 80 followers. The government charged that Koresh and his followers set the fire while surviving cult members said it began when federal tanks knocked over lanterns as they battered down walls to insert tear gas into the building.</p>
<p>Those appealing to the Supreme Court were Jamie Castillo, Kevin Whitecliff, Brad Branch, Renos Avraam, Graeme Craddock and Paul Fatta. They received sentences ranging from 15 years to as much as 40 years in prison.</p>
<p>A U.S. appeals court last year affirmed their convictions but ordered new sentencing for four sect members who had been given a 30-year prison term just for carrying a weapon during a violent crime.</p>
<p>A total of 12 cult members initially had been charged in the case. Four were acquitted on all charges in 1994 while two others did not appeal their convictions.</p>
<p>In appealing to the Supreme Court, the six made various arguments including that Congress had exceeded its power in making it a federal offence to possess a machinegun and that the jury should have been told that self-defence or the defence of others was a defence to voluntary manslaughter.</p>
<p>But the high court sided with the Justice Department and denied the appeals without any comment or dissent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
