<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525260" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Bardot slams Moscow for &quot;planned animal massacre&quot;.</title>
<headline>Bardot slams Moscow for &quot;planned animal massacre&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former screen goddess turned animal rights activist Brigitte Bardot slammed Moscow city authorities on Monday for what she said was a &quot;planned massacre&quot; of stray animals during the Russian capital's 850th anniversary.</p>
<p>&quot;I am absolutely shocked and horrified to learn that preparations for the celebrations include a massacre of all the city's strays,&quot; Bardot said in a letter to the municipality and which was released in Paris.</p>
<p>&quot;The millions which will be spent to buy poison (to kill) the animals and thus 'clean' the streets would be better spent helping those poor people who each day (in Moscow) come to the aid of animals in distress,&quot; Bardot wrote.</p>
<p>She called on Moscow authorities to scrap any animal-killing programme and replace it by sterilisation measures.</p>
<p>Stray dogs have become a big problem in recent years in Moscow, hit like the rest of the country by deep economic crisis. Many owners, faced with a sharp fall in their living standards, have been forced to abandon their pets while city authorities lack funds to control the number of stray dogs.</p>
<p>A Moscow official told Reuters on Monday that city authorities had not launched any new large-scale campaigns to clear the city of stray dogs. But he said the municipal government would have to tackle the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to find more humane ways of reducing the number of stray dogs in the city, perhaps by setting up special centres so that owners would have an alternative for their pets,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bardot, who is active on many animal defence fronts, is currently in renewed trouble with French human rights groups for her most recent attacks on Moslem ritual slaughter of animals.</p>
<p>A leading French anti-racist group said last week it would take her to court for saying the sacrifice of sheep by Moslems in France during the current Aid-el-Kebir festival &quot;will bloody the land of France.&quot;</p>
<p>She was cleared by a court in January for earlier statements in which she said France was being &quot;invaded&quot; by (Moslem) sheep-slaughterers.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
