<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525331" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian Haj pilgrims return home to tearful reunion.</title>
<headline>Indian Haj pilgrims return home to tearful reunion.</headline>
<byline>Clarence Fernandez</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian Moslems returned to Bombay on Monday after narrowly escaping a devastating fire on the pilgrimage to Mecca and were joyfully greeted by anxious relatives, officials said.</p>
<p>Indian officials estimate that 179 Indians are missing after the fire swept through a tent complex at a key pilgrimage site in Saudi Arabia last Tuesday, killing 343 people and injuring Many victims were burned, others suffocated from fumes and still more crushed in a stampede, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Many of the 375 returning Indians said they were overjoyed to find themselves on home soil once again.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm so glad to be back in my country,&quot; said Munshi Attari Begum, 65, sobbing uncontrollably. Dressed in white, she spoke breathlessly through a long gauze scarf that covered the lower half of her face.</p>
<p>&quot;These are tears of happiness,&quot; she added, after embracing waiting relatives at Bombay's international airport. &quot;It was so terrible there. There was chaos for many days. But I'm glad to finish my Haj peacefully.&quot;</p>
<p>India's ambassador to Saudi Arabia said 179 Indians were still missing after the fire on the plain of Mena, about 11 km (seven miles) from the Islamic holy city of Mecca.</p>
<p>&quot;Some 179 are missing and 123 are injured,&quot; Mohammad Hamad Ansari told Reuters in Dubai by telephone.</p>
<p>Ansari said there was still no exact figure for the number of Indians killed in the fire. Embassy teams were contacting mortuaries and hospitals in attempts to fix the count, he added.</p>
<p>About 80,000 Indians are estimated to have performed the Haj this year.</p>
<p>Ali Shamshi, 55, said he and his wife walked for four hours to the nearest habitation after they escaped the blaze.</p>
<p>&quot;The fire started from local tenements, not from the pilgrims' tents,&quot; Shamshi said. &quot;We started running. But those who ran towards the hills nearby couldn't make it. They got caught in the stampede.</p>
<p>&quot;We walked for 20 km (12.5 miles) without food or water,&quot; he added. &quot;It took four hours to reach the nearest people.&quot;</p>
<p>A woman in her 20s wept on seeing her family. &quot;I don't know what to say,&quot; she cried. &quot;I'm just so happy to be back in my country and see my relatives again. I thought I would never see my family again.&quot;</p>
<p>Fifity-year-old Mushtaq Ali said he wished he had died in the fire.</p>
<p>&quot;We Moslems believe that if you die on the Haj, it is the best thing that could happen. You go straight to heaven.&quot;</p>
<p>Air-India said in a statement that nearly 1,600 Indian pilgrims had been flown home from Jeddah on four flights on Monday, one each to Bombay and the southern city of Madras, and two to the capital, New Delhi.</p>
<p>The state-run firm will airlift a total of 55,000 pilgrims, running four or five flights a day until May 21, the statement added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
