<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525794" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: Iraq to send helicopters into West's no-fly zone.</title>
<headline>Iraq to send helicopters into West's no-fly zone.</headline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraq has decided to send helicopters to pick up Iraqi Moslem pilgrims from the Saudi border in the south despite a U.S. and allied ban on flights by Iraq in the area, the Iraqi News Agency reported on Monday.</p>
<p>It said the decision was announced after a meeting of Iraqi leaders headed by President Saddam Hussein in which they warned the United States against any attempt to intercept the helicopters.  </p>
<p>&quot;Any American practice threatening the safety of the helicopters and the pilgrims will be met with an appropriate action,&quot; the news agency INA said, quoting an authoritative source.</p>
<p>Iraq flew a civilian plane to Saudi Arabia on March 9 carrying 104 elderly and sick pilgrims to Mecca for the haj pilgrimage despite U.N. sanctions. The plane returned home the same day.</p>
<p>The U.N. Security Council issued a statement calling on Iraq not to fly more planes without its consent, but stopped short of regarding the flight as a breach of the embargo.</p>
<p>INA said &quot;practical reasons&quot; prevented Iraq from sending the plane back to transfer the pilgrims home.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
