<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525890" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - Daily Variety - April 21.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Daily Variety - April 21.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following stories appeared in Monday's Daily Variety:</p>
<p>* Columbia's &quot;Anaconda&quot; maintained its grip on the national box office, dropping just 27 percent to $12.2 million and taking the top spot for the second time.</p>
<p>* MGM co-owner Kirk Kerkorian is in talks with billionaire John Kluge to acquire Kluge's Metromedia Entertainment Group, which includes Orion Pictures and the Samuel Goldwyn Co, according to sources close to both companies. But no deal has been struck.</p>
<p>* Nielsen and the television networks last week agreed to start the fall season on September 22, a week later than last year and three full weeks after Labor Day.</p>
<p>* An investor group including Bain Capital Partners and Richland, Gordon &amp; Co. signed a definitive deal to buy video distributor Live Entertainment Inc for $93 million, Live said Friday.</p>
<p>* News Corp's Fox Broadcasting has canceled &quot;Married... With Children,&quot; the longest-running television comedy on the air and the show that put Fox on the map 10 years ago. Fox produces the series with Sony Corp's Columbia TriStar Television.</p>
<p>* Australia's Village Roadshow Pictures and London-based Intermedia Film Equities are pooling their international sales efforts in a joint venture called Village Intermedia Pictures.</p>
<p>((New York newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
