<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525990" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Rocket heads for space with Timothy Leary ashes.</title>
<headline>Rocket heads for space with Timothy Leary ashes.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ashes of 1960s LSD guru Timothy Leary and &quot;Star Trek&quot; creator Gene Roddenberry went into space on Monday on board a rocket carrying Spain's first scientific satellite.</p>
<p>The Pegasus rocket was launched from a Lockheed L-1011 jetliner 11,000 metres (36,000 feet) over the Canary Islands, in the Atlantic off North Africa, with observers watching via a satellite link-up from an escort plane.</p>
<p>After the rocket enters space, it will deploy the minisat, the first satellite to be entirely built and designed in Spain.</p>
<p>The cremated remains of Leary, a former Harvard professor who scandalised the U.S. establishment by advocating the use of drugs to the 1960s &quot;flower power&quot; generation and whose final request before dying was for &quot;one last far-out trip&quot;, will then go into orbit with those of Roddenberry and 22 other space enthusiasts for the world's first space funeral.</p>
<p>They will remain in orbit attached to the remains of the rocket for anywhere between 18 months and 10 years before they re-enter the atmosphere and burn up.</p>
<p>The satellite will participate in scientific studies, looking at ultraviolet, gravity and low energy gamma rays.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
