<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="525901" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Rocket with Timothy Leary ashes goes into orbit.</title>
<headline>Rocket with Timothy Leary ashes goes into orbit.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ashes of 1960s LSD guru Timothy Leary and &quot;Star Trek&quot; creator Gene Roddenberry were launched into orbit on Monday on board a rocket that also deployed Spain's first scientific satellite.</p>
<p>The Pegasus rocket was launched at 1200 GMT from a Lockheed L-1011 jetliner 11,000 metres (36,000 feet) over the Canary Islands, in the Atlantic off North Africa, with observers watching via a satellite link-up from an escort plane.</p>
<p>The rocket entered space some 10 minutes later and deployed the minisat, the first satellite to be entirely built and designed in Spain.</p>
<p>The cremated remains of Leary, a former Harvard professor who scandalised the U.S. establishment by advocating the use of drugs to the 1960s &quot;flower power&quot; generation and whose final request before dying was for &quot;one last far-out trip&quot;, joined those of Roddenberry and 22 other space enthusiasts for the world's first space funeral.</p>
<p>The ashes, secured in lipstick-sized capsules, will stay in orbit attached to the remains of the rocket for anywhere between 18 months and 10 years before gravity pulls them back into the atmosphere where they will burn up.</p>
<p>Family and friends who accompanied the cremated remains of their loved ones to Madrid on Friday said the space burials would fulfil, albeit posthumously, a lifelong dream.</p>
<p>&quot;Timothy had always been a space pioneer and wanted to travel into space and now he has the opportunity,&quot; said Carol Rosin, a close friend of Leary who was by his side when he died of prostate cancer aged 75.</p>
<p>The satellite, which cost 4.5 billion pesetas ($31 million), was designed and managed by Spain's National Institute of Aerospace Technology (INTA). Construcciones Aeronauticas-CASA built the platform and other state-owned companies contributed to different systems on the satellite.</p>
<p>&quot;So far everything has gone very well,&quot; Spain's State Secretary of Defence Pedro Morenes told a news conference after the launch. &quot;We now have to wait until it (the minisat) makes a full turn of the earth to confirm that everything is functioning well in orbit.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pegasus rocket was built by U.S.-based Orbital Sciences Corp, which had problems with a similar launch last November in which its two cargoes failed to separate.</p>
<p>An INTA official looked relieved when he received news that a tracking station on the island of Antigua in the Caribbean had spotted two separate bodies in orbit after Monday's launch.</p>
<p>Officials said they were waiting for confirmation from the main tracking station in the Canary Islands before calling the mission a success.</p>
<p>The minisat starts its scientific studies, looking at ultraviolet light, gravity and low energy gamma rays in two weeks' time.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
