<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="526093" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German media summit begins to take shape.</title>
<headline>German media summit begins to take shape.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>A high-level summit of German media and telecoms executives, politicians and media regulators will take place next month in a bid to break a deadlock that has held up the cable television industry for over a year, industry sources said on Monday.</p>
<p>Chaired by Deutsche Telekom chairman Ron Sommer, the meeting will be attended by leading media executives such as Bavarian media mogul Leo Kirch, Bertelsmann AG chairman Mark Woessner and heads of major public and commercial TV networks.</p>
<p>Also in attendance will be the economics ministers from Germany's 16 federal states and the heads of the state cabinet offices, who under German law carry the responsibility for regulating the media.</p>
<p>The meeting will take place on May 20 and is expected to be the first of several that will aim to break a deadlock between cable operators and media companies that has blocked the start of broad-scale digital TV and expansion of cable networks.</p>
<p>&quot;The issues are developing a common strategy for the future development of the television industry and the expansion of the cable TV networks in both analog and digital,&quot; said one industry source who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing that will happen is that Deutsche Telekom will finally reveal its own strategy for its cable network.&quot;</p>
<p>Deutsche Telekom declined to comment on the meeting.</p>
<p>The media summit is the result of an invitation by Deutsche Telekom as a way of bringing all interested parties together to try to overcome differences over digital and cable TV in order to introduce digital programming by Christmas.</p>
<p>-- William Boston, Bonn Newsroom, 49 228 26097150</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
