<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="526216" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - &quot;Girl Power&quot; puts Britain's Spice Girls on record.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - &quot;Girl Power&quot; puts Britain's Spice Girls on record.</headline>
<byline>Nicholas Winning</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>They are multi-millionaires, take former prime minister Margaret Thatcher as their role model and tell women to buck up and get &quot;Girl Power&quot;.</p>
<p>They are the feisty pop quintet &quot;Spice Girls&quot;, who have sold almost 10 million copies of their first album.</p>
<p>They are the first group ever to top the British charts with their first four singles, have done the same in 31 countries and even outdid the Beatles by getting their first single &quot;Wannabe&quot; to number one in the United States.</p>
<p>The 1990s saw the meteoric rise of the &quot;boy band&quot;, with &quot;Take That&quot; leading the way until they split up last year, breaking the hearts of thousands of adoring teenage girls across Europe.</p>
<p>The Spice Girls followed hot on the trail of this manufactured band phenomenon, having to audition for places in the group which blended feminism and catchy tunes. They have already earned $15 million each, media reports say.</p>
<p>In their first official book &quot;Girl Power&quot;, Melanie Chisholme, Victoria Adams, Emma Bunting, Melanie Brown, and Gerry Halliwell, said they wanted to become household names.</p>
<p>&quot;The future is female,&quot; they say. True to Frank Sinatra's classic song &quot;My Way&quot;, they are eager to stress they are doing everything their way and it is working a treat.</p>
<p>SPICE GIRL PHILOSOPHY</p>
<p>In their first single &quot;Wannabe,&quot; they spell out their philosophy of life.</p>
<p>&quot;Yo I'll tell you what I want, what I really really want/ So tell me what you want, what you really really want/...I wanna really really really wanna zigazig-ha.&quot;</p>
<p>The last word is one of the group's invented private words, Emma said in the book, but the popularity of the song was so great that it prompted British finance minister Kenneth Clarke to quote them in a speech about the economy.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll tell you what I want, what I really really want... healthy, sustainable growth,&quot; Clarke told businessmen.</p>
<p>He could well have been thanking the girls for their support after they lambasted opposition Labour leader Tony Blair and told the weekly magazine The Spectator that they saw Margaret Thatcher as the original Spice Girl.</p>
<p>&quot;When I said Thatcher was the first Spice Girl I wasn't claiming I was a Tory...I just admire people with ideals,&quot; Geri said in the book.</p>
<p>Rarely a day passes without a Spice Girl appearing in the tabloid press. Geri has faced the most exposure after topless photos from her pre-Spice days reappeared.</p>
<p>Geri said girl power was simply a matter of taking control of your own destiny irrespective of your physical attributes.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm an expressive person, very outspoken, I feel like a freedom-fighter trying to give girls the right to express themselves,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Mel C, known as Sporty Spice, said she had girl power because she plays football even though people turn their noses up at it. Victoria said she had it because she had broken off an engagement.</p>
<p>&quot;Girl power is when...You and your mates reply to wolf whistles by shouting 'Get your arse out'...You don't wait around for him to call...You believe in yourself,&quot; the girls said.</p>
<p>Mel B said the Spice Girls were not like normal pop stars.</p>
<p>&quot;The pop star life is all about stereotypes and fitting into a bracket and we don't want to do that,&quot; she said. &quot;I really think we should do whatever the hell we like in this band.&quot;</p>
<p>The big question is one of longevity, with some inevitably feeling their success is a flash in the pop music pan.</p>
<p>But if work rate is anything to go by, the band's 14-hour days, endless globetrotting and jam-packed daily promotions make them pretenders to James Brown's crown as the &quot;Hardest working man in showbusiness&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Underneath all this make-up, I've got black eyes,&quot; said Victoria.</p>
<p>They are set to record their second album and film a Spice Girl movie this summer and they plan to go on a world tour next February.</p>
<p>&quot;In the meantime, you know what to do,&quot; they say in unison. &quot;Spice it up bigtime!&quot; ($ = 0.612 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
