<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="526696" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FEATURE - French Cancan girls soldier on at Moulin Rouge.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - French Cancan girls soldier on at Moulin Rouge.</headline>
<byline>Francois Raitberger</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than a century on, the girls at the Moulin Rouge are still dancing the Cancan, kicking up their legs in defiance at the inroads of more modern forms of entertainment.</p>
<p>The cabaret with its celebrated neon-lit windmill in the Pigalle red-light district of Paris claims to be the last guardian of traditional shows &quot;a la Francaise&quot;.</p>
<p>The rival Folies Bergere just 800 metres (half a mile) away succumbed four years ago to the temptation of introducing pop music and high-tech staging into its saucy show.</p>
<p>Le Moulin Rouge, made famous by the paintings of Toulouse Lautrec, soldiers on with its basic fare of topless dancers, exotic costumes and staged extravaganzas.</p>
<p>The current show &quot;Formidable&quot;, created for the cabaret's 100th anniversary eight years ago, is on its last run. The new one to be launched next year will keep strutting the same array of French songs, bare breasts and ostrich feathers.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the last typically French show,&quot; says leading dancer 25-year-old Jacqueline Alcock.</p>
<p>Ironically for such a quintessentially French show, Alcock is British, from Stafford, in the English midlands. And apart from the songs, foie gras and champagne, little else is French at the Moulin Rouge.</p>
<p>MOST GIRLS ARE FOREIGN</p>
<p>The ostrich feathers on the opulent 50,000-franc ($10,000) costumes are Australian, like several of the 60 girls.</p>
<p>Only four of the girls are French. The others are from eastern Europe and northern countries where the required minimum height of 1.75 metres (5ft 8inches) is easier to find.</p>
<p>A live boa curling around a scantily-clad girl in a scene of a kidnapping from an Arab prince's harem obviously comes from more southerly latitudes and the white horse whisking her away is named Macbeth.</p>
<p>More than two thirds of the spectators, who down 200,000 bottles of champagne a year, are foreigners. Japanese form the largest contingent, with East Europeans and Chinese now arriving in significant numbers.</p>
<p>The rest are from the French provinces, with Parisians a rarity.</p>
<p>In a ritual ballet six days a week, tour buses dump hundreds of tourists for the two nightly performances: a 750-franc ($150) 7 p.m. dinner show and an 11 p.m. 450-franc ($90) show with champagne.</p>
<p>They emerge two hours later, loaded with Moulin Rouge memorabilia -- lighters, watches, caps, and tee-shirts.</p>
<p>Those who walk back to cheaper hotels in the steamy district have to run the gauntlet of doormen attempting to lure them into the leather-and-lace atmosphere of sex shops, strip-tease shows, and lurid live sex performances.</p>
<p>Besides glitz and bare flesh, history is the Moulin Rouge's asset. Company executives like to recall that the cabaret was a favourite of the Prince of Wales in the 1890s before he became King Edward VII.</p>
<p>The story goes that Cancan dancer &quot;La Goulue&quot; (The Glutton), immortalised by Toulouse Lautrec, called to the prince when she spotted him in the audience: &quot;Hey, Wales, you buy the champagne&quot;.</p>
<p>The Moulin Rouge has remained a favourite for the British royal family, and the whole company travelled to London in 1981 to perform -- breasts covered -- for Queen Elizabeth.</p>
<p>Anyone may hire the cabaret for a private performance, at a price: 700,000 francs ($140,000).</p>
<p>SHOW MIXES HISTORY, BEAUTY, EXTRAVAGANZA</p>
<p>The show goes into the cabaret's history and the stars it hosted, evoking Toulouse Lautrec's backstage visits at the turn of the century, and singers including Edith Piaf and Maurice Chevalier, Bing Crosby, Liza Minelli and Frank Sinatra.</p>
<p>The extravaganza mixes bare beauty and glittering costumes in scenes of desert adventures involving flying carpets, girl slaves and princesses, Arab warriors and French Foreign Legionnaires.</p>
<p>&quot;Formidable&quot;, which has had an unprecedented run of almost nine years to recoup its 50-million-franc ($10 million) cost, ends at the New Year.</p>
<p>The Moulin Rouge will re-open two months later with a new show which is a closely-guarded secret -- except for the first letter of its name: an 'F', as for all shows since the successful 1963 show, Frou Frou, named after the swishing of petticoats.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
