<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="526604" id="root" date="1997-04-21" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Airlift for million haj pilgrims begins in Saudi.</title>
<headline>Airlift for million haj pilgrims begins in Saudi.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-21</dateline>
<text>
<p>An airlift to take over a million haj pilgrims home from Saudi Arabia to 120 countries has begun and is due to be completed in a month, the Saudi daily Arab News said on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;The departure of pilgrims was authorised after the Ministry of Health declared the haj clean and free of any epidemics or contagious diseases,&quot; the English-language paper said.</p>
<p>Officials said about 1.2 million foreign pilgrims performed this year's haj.</p>
<p>Some 343 pilgrims were killed and over 1,000 injured during this year's haj when a fire swept through a tent complex at a key pilgrimage site.</p>
<p>Some 200,000 Indonesian pilgrims, the largest number from a single country, will be flown home on 940 flights at a rate of 20 flights a day on Garuda Indonesia airlines.</p>
<p>Pakistan International Airlines will carry most of the 125,000 Pakistani pilgrims home on 300 flights and Air India will start ferrying the 80,000 Indian pilgrims home on Monday , the newspaper said.</p>
<p>The paper said repatriation of pilgrims was due to be completed by May 18.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DUBAI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-21"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-21"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
