<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="528065" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Iraqi pilgrims head for choppers on Saudi border.</title>
<headline>Iraqi pilgrims head for choppers on Saudi border.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than 1,100 Iraqi haj pilgrims set off on land from Moslem pilgrimage sites in western Saudi Arabia to the Iraqi border where Baghdad sent helicopters in defiance of a &quot;no-fly zone&quot; to meet them, witnesses said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The pilgrims, travelling on buses and trucks, were expected to start arriving in the northern border area of Arar around 2:00 a.m. on Wednesday (2200 GMT on Tuesday), the witnesses in the Moslem holy city of Mecca and in Medina said.</p>
<p>Iraq said its helicopters arrived at its southern border with Saudi Arabia to pick up Moslem pilgrims on Tuesday, ignoring a U.S. warning not to violate the &quot;no-fly zone&quot; enforced since the Gulf War.</p>
<p>The official Iraqi News Agency (INA) said &quot;a number of helicopters were sent yesterday and this morning to the border area of Arar to transfer Iraqi pilgrims from the city of Arar to all provinces in the country.&quot;</p>
<p>INA said the undisclosed number of helicopters, including one carrying foreign TV crews on Tuesday, landed safely at the border post.</p>
<p>The helicopter flights were the second challenge this month to the longstanding restrictions -- &quot;no-fly zones&quot; in the north and south of Iraq and an U.N.-imposed ban on international flights.</p>
<p>Iraq flew a civilian plane to Saudi Arabia on April 9 carrying 104 elderly and sick pilgrims to Mecca for the haj. It returned to Iraq the same day.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
