<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="528059" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: Iraq to fly pilgrims home, ignores U.S. warning.</title>
<headline>Iraq to fly pilgrims home, ignores U.S. warning.</headline>
<byline>Leon Barkho</byline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraqi helicopters arrived on Tuesday at the southern border with Saudi Arabia to pick up Moslem pilgrims, ignoring a U.S. warning not to violate the &quot;no-fly zone&quot; enforced since the Gulf War.</p>
<p>A Reuters television soundman said reporters were taken in two helicopters to the border at Arar and that he saw seven more helicopters parked three km (1.8 miles) from the Saudi border, waiting for the pilgrims to arrive.</p>
<p>An Iraqi official told reporters the helicopters would transport between 60 to 70 elderly and sick pilgrims.</p>
<p>Witnesses in Saudi Arabia said more than 1,100 Iraqi haj pilgrims set off on land from pilgrimage sites there to the Iraqi border.</p>
<p>The pilgrims, travelling on buses and trucks, were expected to start arriving in Arar around 2 a.m. on Wednesday (2200 GMT on Tuesday), the witnesses in the Moslem holy city of Mecca and in Medina said.</p>
<p>In Washington, U.S. President Bill Clinton said religion should not be used to evade international obligations but gave no indication that the United States would retaliate.</p>
<p>&quot;My message is that we support people in exercising their religious liberties and in living out their religious convictions everywhere in the world...But we don't want to see religion in effect used and distorted in a way to try to avoid international obligations,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen had said on Monday, after Iraq first announced plans for the flights, that Baghdad could not flout no-fly rules by arbitrarily sending helicopters to pick up the pilgrims.</p>
<p>The White House had urged Iraq to reconsider, saying it would &quot;respond appropriately&quot; to any such flights.</p>
<p>Cohen said it might be eligible for a humanitarian exemption allowing the flights if it followed proper procedure. But Iraq, under flight restrictions since the 1991 Gulf War ended its occupation of Kuwait, has maintained it needs no permission.</p>
<p>The helicopter flights were the second challenge this month to the longstanding restrictions -- &quot;no-fly zones&quot; in the north and south of Iraq and an U.N.-imposed ban on international flights.</p>
<p>Iraq flew a civilian plane to Saudi Arabia on April 9 carrying 104 elderly and sick pilgrims to Mecca for the Moslem haj pilgrimage. It returned to Iraq the same day.</p>
<p>The U.N. Security Council issued a statement calling on Iraq not to fly more planes without its consent, but stopped short of calling the flight a breach of the embargo as sought by Washington.</p>
<p>&quot;America is the loser. Its failure to condemn Iraq after flying its sick pilgrims to Mecca by plane is a clear indication,&quot; Babel, Iraq's most influential newspaper, said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;America has to confess that it has failed and will fail in containing Iraq and bringing it under its hegemony via its traditional means,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>&quot;Iraq's decision to welcome and transport its sick pilgrims from the Saudi border and transport them to their provinces by air is a natural right. Neither America nor anybody else has the right to object,&quot; Babel said in a frontpage editorial.</p>
<p>Babel said any action by the United States to intercept the helicopters would be met &quot;at an appropirate time...and with a similar force shown by (Washington's) hostile reaction&quot;.</p>
<p>INA had said on Monday the decision was announced after a meeting of Iraqi leaders headed by President Saddam Hussein in which they warned the United States against any attempt to intercept the helicopters.</p>
<p>The decision to send the helicopters was published on the front pages of all Baghdad's state-run newspapers on Tuesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
