<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="528388" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Fire at cigarette exec's house blamed on butt.</title>
<headline>Fire at cigarette exec's house blamed on butt.</headline>
<dateline>WILMINGTON, N.C. 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>A discarded cigarette was the probable cause of a fire that destroyed the luxury vacation home of the president of R.J. Reynolds Tobacco Co. and caused $1 million in damages, fire officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The three-floor vacation home of Reynolds President Andrew Schindler on upscale Figure Eight island was reduced to a row of charred pilings after it caught fire while workers installing ceiling tile were at lunch on Friday.</p>
<p>Damage to the house was estimated at $750,000. Damage caused to houses nearby by flying embers as the fire raged was estimated at $250,000.</p>
<p>&quot;Every county fire department around was there,&quot; said a spokesman for the Wilmington Fire Department.</p>
<p>Fire officials said inspectors had not made a final determination of what caused the accidental blaze. But they said it likely was caused by a cigarette butt left by a worker who told inspectors he had smoked near where the fire started about half an hour before the crew left.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a very good possibility it was started by a discarded cigarette,&quot; New Hanover County fire marshal Aubrey Rivenbark told the Wilmington Star-News newspaper in Tuesday's editions. &quot;It could've been dropped, caught by the wind and rolled into the flower bed.&quot;</p>
<p>Rivenbark was not immediately available to comment on Tuesday.</p>
<p>R.J. Reynolds Tobacco is a unit of RJR Nabisco Holdings Corp. The second-largest U.S. tobacco company, its brands include Camel, Winston and Salem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WILMINGTON, N.C."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
