<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="528438" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Herbert Zipper, Viennese conductor, dead at 92.</title>
<headline>Herbert Zipper, Viennese conductor, dead at 92.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Herbert Zipper, a Viennese conductor who formed a secret orchestra at Dachau concentration camp during World War II, has died at the age of 92, a hospital spokeswoman said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>She said Zipper died of lung cancer at St. John's Medical Centre in Santa Monica on Monday.</p>
<p>Imprisoned in Dachau by the Nazis, Zipper recruited fellow inmates who had played with orchestras in Vienna and Munich and together they formed a secret orchestra which entertained other inmates on Sundays in an abandoned building in the prison grounds.</p>
<p>The conductor later was moved to the Buchenwald concentration camp, from where he was rescued by his family. He moved to Manila, Philippines, where he was again imprisoned, this time by the invading Japanese army.</p>
<p>Freed when war ended, Zipper moved to the United States where he first conducted the Brooklyn Symphony Orchestra. He then moved to Chicago and subsequently to Los Angeles, where he taught at the University of Southern California's School of Performing Arts.</p>
<p>A biography of Zipper, &quot;Dachau Song&quot; by Paul Cummins, was published in 1992. Zipper is survived by a niece and a nephew.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
