<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="528541" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Convicted paedophile Irish priest in new charges.</title>
<headline>Convicted paedophile Irish priest in new charges.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Irish Roman Catholic priest whose child-molesting crimes led to the downfall of the government admitted 74 more cases of sex abuse when he appeared in a Dublin court on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Brendan Smyth, 71, admitted the charges in a brief appearance in a Dublin court after being extradited when he was freed from a Northern Ireland jail last month.</p>
<p>He had served a four-year jail term for a catalogue of sexual offences against children committed while he was a priest in Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>Judge Cyril Kelly ordered that Smyth remain in jail until July when he will appear at a two-day hearing at which 20 people will make statements about the charges.</p>
<p>Smyth was at the centre of a row in 1994 row  which helped bring about the collapse of the government of former Irish Prime Minister Albert Reynolds.</p>
<p>It also sparked serious public debate about the sexual conduct of priests and celibacy in Ireland's Roman Catholic church and a pledge from church leaders to uncover and punish child-molesters in its ranks.</p>
<p>After the Smyth case, several more priests in Northern Ireland and the Irish republic were convicted of paedophile offences and the issue was rarely off the front pages of newspapers for months.</p>
<p>Smyth is a former member of the Norbertine Order who had been based in the Irish Republic. He was found guilty in Northern Ireland of abusing the children of friends.</p>
<p>The 74 other charges relate to incidents which happened when he was in the Irish republic. Some of the charges date back more than two decades.</p>
<p>In 1994 the Labour party, the junior partner in Reynolds' Fianna Fail-led coalition government, voiced its concern about delays in the processing of a Northern Ireland extradition request for Smyth.</p>
<p>According to the Labour party, the extradition request had gathered dust on a desk at the Attorney-General's office for months for no apparent reason.</p>
<p>The row between Labour, led by Foreign Minister Dick Spring, and Reynolds culminated in Labour withdrawing its support for the government and led to the present administration, headed by John Bruton of Fine Gael, taking over.</p>
<p>Reynolds, an architect of the Northern Ireland peace process, retired from front-line politics although his successor, Bertie Ahern, says he may still have a role on Northern Ireland if Fianna Fail wins elections this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
