<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="528552" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German region to continue observing Scientology.</title>
<headline>German region to continue observing Scientology.</headline>
<dateline>STUTTGART, Germany 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The southern German state of Baden-Wuerttemberg said on Tuesday a university expert opinion on the Church of Scientology had strengthened its resolve to keep the organisation under observation.</p>
<p>&quot;A study by the University of Tuebingen has strengthened my opinion that Scientology's programme is a threat to a state ruled by law,&quot; state interior minister Thomas Schaeuble said in a statement.</p>
<p>The study, based only on readily available documents, found no evidence that Scientology should be categorised as a criminal organisation, and no proof of involvement in organised or economic crime.</p>
<p>It said a number of source materials backed the hypothesis that Scientology, based on the teachings of late American science fiction author L. Ron Hubbard, was capable of exerting &quot;extreme pressure&quot; on people and fostering unusual dependency.</p>
<p>But it said it had not been possible to prove that contact with the organisation had long-term psychological consequences or encouraged people to commit suicide. It recommended further investigations.</p>
<p>Baden-Wuerttemberg and the neighbouring state of Bavaria are at the forefront of efforts in Germany to maintain checks on Scientology, and both have the organisation observed by their anti-extremist watchdogs.</p>
<p>Scientology's German branch attacked Schaeuble's comments.</p>
<p>It said in a statement that he had chosen to ignore the fact that the report &quot;clearly refutes&quot; allegations made against the organisation, and was instead mounting a &quot;hysterical witchhunt&quot; against Scientology at taxpayers' expense.</p>
<p>German authorities consider Scientology to be a profit-making organisation, not a religion. Officials say it exploits the insecurities of members to make money from expensive self-improvement courses.</p>
<p>This year's annual human rights report from the U.S. State Department listed Scientology's allegations of persecution in Germany, and the issue has prompted protests from U.S. entertainment celebrities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STUTTGART, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
