<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="529242" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Pakistan says 111 haj pilgrims dead, 100 missing.</title>
<headline>Pakistan says 111 haj pilgrims dead, 100 missing.</headline>
<byline>Youssef Kassem</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistan's ambassador to Saudi Arabia said on Tuesday 111 nationals were confirmed dead and 100 were still missing after a fire which killed more than 340 Moslem haj pilgrims last week.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a confirmed death toll of 111 Pakistanis and another 50 are still at hospitals in Mecca,&quot; Shahed Amin told Reuters by telephone from Riyadh. &quot;We believe our up-to-date list is complete&quot;.</p>
<p>He said six of the injured Pakistanis were in critical condition in intensive care at Saudi hospitals.</p>
<p>&quot;Some 100 Pakistanis are still missing, but this a normal pattern during haj...people go missing and then turn up after a week or so,&quot; Amin added.</p>
<p>The fire swept through a key pilgrimage site near the Moslem holy city of Mecca in Saudi Arabia last Tuesday, gutting 70,000 tents.</p>
<p>Witnesses said many victims were burned, others suffocated from fumes while some were crushed by a stampede. Saudi Arabia said 343 people died and more than 1,500 were injured.</p>
<p>Officials have said identification of bodies was difficult because many had been burned beyond recognition.</p>
<p>Diplomats said that about 120,000 Pakistanis performed the pilgrimage this year, making them the second largest group after Indonesia, which had a quota for 200,000 pilgrims.</p>
<p>Another 50,000 Pakistanis living in Saudi Arabia and other Gulf states took part in the haj, diplomats said.</p>
<p>Amin said he was not sure yet whether the kingdom would release the bodies of victims to their respective diplomatic missions.</p>
<p>&quot;This issue has to be settled with the Saudi authorities. In the past, the practice had been for Saudi Arabia to bury the victims in Mecca,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Saudi newspapers said on Tuesday four Sudanese pilgrims, three of them women, died in the blaze. Other countries have yet to specify death tolls.</p>
<p>The Indian Foreign Ministry said on Monday 281 Indian pilgrims were missing while 202 Indians remained in hospitals.</p>
<p>Some diplomats said the death toll could end up higher than already announced in view of the critical condition of some victims being treated at Saudi hospitals.</p>
<p>&quot;The official death toll is six days old. It is up to the Saudis to provide an update,&quot; a Gulf-based diplomat said. &quot;We cannot speak for them.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
