<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="529311" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton expects to meet with Dalai Lama.</title>
<headline>Clinton expects to meet with Dalai Lama.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton is expected to meet with the Dalai Lama on Wednesday at the White House, despite objections by China, administration officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The exiled Tibetan leader will meet with Vice President Al Gore at his offices, and Clinton will make a &quot;drop by visit&quot; during those talks, the officials said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The Dalai Lama is always a welcome visitor to the White House,&quot; one administration official said. &quot;He is a respected spiritual leader.&quot;</p>
<p>In Beijing, Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Cui Tiankai made it clear his government was opposed to such a meeting. &quot;We resolutely oppose any meetings between U.S. leaders and the Dalai Lama,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton has been under intense pressures over his dealings with China -- in part because of allegations that the Chinese government funnelled money into Democratic Party coffers during last year's elections. China denies the charges.</p>
<p>The meeting will be similar to a session Clinton had last week with Martin Lee, the democracy leader from Hong Kong who has also drawn Beijing's wrath. Clinton paid a &quot;drop by&quot; visit while Gore was meeting Lee, and later voiced concern that China should not erode freedoms now enjoyed by the residents of Hong Hong when Britain ends its control of the colony on July 1.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
