<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="529688" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's ITV criticised for over reliance on drama.</title>
<headline>UK's ITV criticised for over reliance on drama.</headline>
<byline>Keith Weir</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Independent Television Commission (ITC) criticised the ITV commercial network on Tuesday for an over-reliance on drama and called on it to boost its comedy programming.</p>
<p>&quot;The drama is good but the problem is one of diversity. It is crowding out other things and space must be made for these,&quot; ITC chief executive Peter Rogers said as the watchdog published its 1996 performance reviews.</p>
<p>&quot;We would say to ITV licensees...'Please, please, please try to get back into comedy,'&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The ITC, which regulates commercial television, acknowledged that ITV had faced a difficult year in 1996 as its terrestrial rivals held their own or boosted audience share, while cable and satellite viewing passed the 10 percent mark.</p>
<p>It praised high standards from ITV in several areas but was critical of the reduction in airtime given by the network to documentaries, arts and childen's drama.</p>
<p>The ITV network, which groups 15 regional licensees including the big three of Granada, Carlton and United News &amp; Media, expressed surprise at the ITC's criticism of its drama scheduling.</p>
<p>&quot;...The ITC's judgement that the ITV peaktime schedule relied too heavily on drama in 1996 is a cause of surprise and concern to us,&quot; said ITV chairman Leslie Hill. &quot;ITV has spent over a decade building itself as the home of quality British</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
