<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="529668" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: FEATURE-Canadian film of sex and death causes stir.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Canadian film of sex and death causes stir.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Hodgson</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The morbid tale of one woman's love for human remains has turned a small Canadian film into a runaway success story.</p>
<p>&quot;Kissed,&quot; the story of a young necrophile who takes a funeral home job to pursue her passion, is garnering critical praise rare for a film of its kind. Shot on a shoestring budget, the independently made feature became a film festival favorite before it landed a coveted U.S. distribution deal.</p>
<p>Critics have raved, including the powerful TV team of Gene Siskel and Roger Ebert, who gave it &quot;two thumbs up&quot; ahead of its U.S. release last week. Hollywood has also taken notice, with director Lynne Stopkewich and star Molly Parker fielding offers from major studios.</p>
<p>&quot;The shocking thing is how widely it has been embraced,&quot; the 33-year old Vancouver-based director said. &quot;I never imagined that we'd have such mainstream acceptance.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Kissed,&quot; based on Barbara Gowdy's short story &quot;We So Seldom Look on Love,&quot; tells the story of a woman obsessed with death. It traces her adult sexual longing for corpses to her childhood fixation on dead animals.</p>
<p>It was the strength and unapologetic nature of the main character, Sandra Larson, that compelled Stopkewich to make a film from the story, she said, citing surrealist director David Lynch as a major influence.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm really interested in provocative cinema and films that take you somewhere you haven't been before,&quot; she said. &quot;I feel like my job as filmmaker is to take the rock, turn it over and see what's underneath.&quot;</p>
<p>NUDITY AS WELL AS DEATH</p>
<p>&quot;Kissed&quot; is provocative, including full frontal nudity, a lesson on embalming and vivid depictions of Parker entwined with corpses. Parker concedes she had qualms about taking the role but in the end the part was too rich to pass up.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought it would be an incredible challenge to bring this character to life in a way that made people want to understand why she did the things she does,&quot; the 24-year old Parker said.</p>
<p>Given its subject matter and nationality, &quot;Kissed&quot; has drawn comparisons to Canadian director David Cronenberg's &quot;Crash,&quot; a film about a group of people erotically obsessed with car crashes. But unlike &quot;Crash,&quot; which sparked calls for censorship in Britain and Argentina, &quot;Kissed&quot; has attracted surprisingly little controversy.</p>
<p>&quot;There's nothing that disturbing or offensive about 'Kissed.' What's miraculous about the film and what makes it a success is how tender, delicate and tasteful it is, considering that its heroine is a necrophile,&quot; Brian Johnson, film critic for Canadian newsweekly Maclean's, wrote.</p>
<p>Johnson said &quot;Kissed&quot; was typical of recent Canadian films such as &quot;Crash&quot; and Atom Egoyan's &quot;Exotica&quot; in that it explored inviduals alienated from normal society. He said that was not surprising as moviemaking in Canada was something of a fringe industry.</p>
<p>Indeed, to get the initial production of &quot;Kissed&quot; started, Stopkewich borrowed heavily on her 16 credit cards and got a loan from her parents. Grants from various government agencies helped finish the movie, which cost less than $715,000 to make. But the critical success of &quot;Kissed&quot; could soon transfer into financial success for Stopkewich and Parker.</p>
<p>SEX, DEATH PAYS</p>
<p>Both have signed with the William Morris agency and have received numerous scripts. Stopkewich has been in discussions with Warner Brothers, Miramax and 20th Century Fox.</p>
<p>In the near term, Stopkewich, who has been on the road for most of this year promoting the movie, plans to begin work on a new project, which she will not discuss in detail. She also plans to sneak into a public screening of her film to see how a mainstream audience reacts.</p>
<p>&quot;I would tell (audiences) to probably forget everything they've read about it and just go into the movie with an open mind,&quot; she said. &quot;If they're willing to put aside their preconceived ideas of how the film is going deal with the material then they might be pleasantly surprised.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
