<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="530063" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Top Hong Kong actor, opera star Tang dies at 81.</title>
<headline>Top Hong Kong actor, opera star Tang dies at 81.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Popular Hong Kong opera singer and actor Tang Wing-cheung, better known to his fans as Sun Ma-Chai, has died at the age of 81, his family said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Tang, whose career spanned seven decades but whose final months were dominated by a family squabble over his fortune, &quot;died peacefully in the presence of his children&quot; on Monday evening his son Tang Siu-chuen told reporters.</p>
<p>His fourth wife and their four children had fought a well-publicised battle over his estate which they say is worth billions of Hong Kong dollars.</p>
<p>The wife, Hung Jin-mui, who he married five years ago after a 30-year affair, was not present when Tang died of chronic bronchitis. Dozens of reporters mobbed the hospital.</p>
<p>Tang also had three children from his third marriage.</p>
<p>Tang began his career as a Cantonese opera performer at the age of nine when poverty forced him to drop out of school and hit stardom only a year later.</p>
<p>He switched to films in the 1950s and made more than 200 films, mostly comedies and musicals.</p>
<p>He retired in the late 1970s but often appeared on the screen to raise money for charities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
