<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="530170" id="root" date="1997-04-22" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: Iraq to pick up pilgrims despite U.S. warning.</title>
<headline>Iraq to pick up pilgrims despite U.S. warning.</headline>
<byline>Leon Barkho</byline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1997-04-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraq's most influential newspaper said on Tuesday that Iraq would go ahead with a decision to send helicopters to pick up Iraqi Moslem pilgrims from the Saudi border despite a warning from Washington.</p>
<p>&quot;Iraq's decision to welcome and transport its sick pilgrims from the Saudi border and transport them to their provinces by air is a natural right. Neither America nor anybody else has the right to object,&quot; the newspaper Babel said in a front-page editorial.</p>
<p>The official Iraqi News Agency (INA) reported on Monday that Iraq had decided to send helicopters to pick up the pilgrims from the Saudi border in the south despite a U.S. and allied ban on flights by Iraq in the area.</p>
<p>INA said the decision was announced after a meeting of Iraqi leaders headed by President Saddam Hussein in which they warned the United States against any attempt to intercept the helicopters.</p>
<p>The White House on Monday urged Iraq to reconsider, saying it would &quot;respond appropriately&quot; to any such flights.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen said Iraq could not flout no-fly rules by arbitrarily sending helicopters to pick up the pilgrims, but it might be eligible for a humanitarian exemption allowing the flights if it followed proper procedure.</p>
<p>It was not known whether Iraq had already sent helicopters into the no-fly zone in the south policed by U.S., British and French planes.</p>
<p>Babel urged Washington to publicly admit that it had failed in its declared policy of containing Iraq by force.</p>
<p>&quot;America has to confess that it has failed and will fail in containing Iraq and bringing it under its hegemony via its traditional means,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>It said any action by the United States to intercept the helicopters would be met &quot;at an appropirate time...and with a similar force shown by (Washington's) hostile reaction&quot;.</p>
<p>The decision to send the helcopters was published on the front pages of all state-run newspapers.</p>
<p>Iraq flew a civilian plane to Saudi Arabia on April 9 carrying 104 elderly and sick pilgrims to Mecca for the Moslem haj pilgrimage despite U.N. sanctions on international flights from Iraqi imposed after Iraq's 1990 invasion of Kuwait. The plane returned home the same day.</p>
<p>The U.N. Security Council issued a statement calling on Iraq not to fly more planes without its consent, but stopped short of regarding the flight as a breach of the embargo.</p>
<p>&quot;America is the loser,&quot; Babel said. &quot;Its failure to condemn Iraq after flying its sick pilgrims to Mecca by plane is a clear indication.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-22"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-22"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
