<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="531351" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Warner Village aims to profit from UK cinema boom.</title>
<headline>Warner Village aims to profit from UK cinema boom.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britons are set to oust Germans as Europe's most avid cinema-goers by the turn of the century, Warner Village cinemas said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Warner Village seized on figures from UK-based film industry research group Dodona as vindication of its own expansion plans in Britain.</p>
<p>Dodona forecast that annual cinema admissions in Britain would leap from 114 million last year to 180 million in 2000. Germany, currently leading the way with 145 million admissions, would have 175 million by the same stage.</p>
<p>Warner Village, a joint venture between Warner Bros and Australia's Village Roadshow, owns and operates 17 multiplexes in Britain but aims to have up to 40 sites in operation by the millennium.</p>
<p>Four are already under construction, with another seven projects confirmed. These include a 30-screen 'megaplex' in Birmingham, the largest in the country.</p>
<p>The arrival of the multiplex in the mid-198Os, bringing with it improved facilities, has helped to revitalise the cinema in the UK, after annual admissions had dropped to around 50 million.</p>
<p>Warner Village is planning to increase its German multiplex chain to 20 sites over the next three years, from four at the moment. It is also expanding into Italy, opening its first cinema there later this year.</p>
<p>Warner Bros is also active in Portugal and Spain, where it has set up further joint ventures.</p>
<p>-- Keith Weir, London Newsroom +44 171 542 8793</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
