<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="531449" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Nigerian tribunal grants musician Fela bail.</title>
<headline>Nigerian tribunal grants musician Fela bail.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Maverick Nigerian musician Fela Anikulapo-Kuti was granted bail on Wednesday by a tribunal trying him on charges of possessing and smoking cannabis.</p>
<p>Judge Yusuf Tanko Usman said the bail was on condition that Fela, as he is widely known, would deposit 500,000 naira ($5,882) and give two sureties on landed properties in Lagos.</p>
<p>Drug offences in Nigeria are normally not bailable.</p>
<p>The judge adjourned any further hearing to Monday.</p>
<p>Fela faces 15 years in jail if convicted on the charges brought against him by the anti-narcotics agency.</p>
<p>Fela's fans who filled the venue jubilated as the judge gave him bail but the gaunt-looking musician was tight-lipped.</p>
<p>His lawyer, Femi Falana, a human rights activist, said: &quot;We appreciate the decision of this tribunal to obey the order of the high court which ordered Fela's release.</p>
<p>&quot;This attitude of the tribunal judge is the only sure way to avert anarchy in this country.&quot;</p>
<p>Fela, 59, was arrested on April 9 with 107 other people at his &quot;The Shrine&quot; nightclub in a working class district of Lagos for alleged possession of cannabis.</p>
<p>The National Drug Law Enforcement Agency (NDLEA) has since freed most of the others arrested with him.</p>
<p>Fela filed a suit at a Lagos court claiming 100 million naira ($11,765) in damages from the NDLEA for alleged violation of his human rights and a high court judge ordered that he should be released by the agency.</p>
<p>But the Afro-beat superstar, who is no stranger to controversy or to the jail cell, was quickly charged before the tribunal by the NDLEA.</p>
<p>A past critic of Nigeria's military rulers, he has a reputation for openly smoking marijuana and dressing only in his underpants.</p>
<p>($1=85)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
