<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="531531" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia sends second official to U.S. in jewel row.</title>
<headline>Russia sends second official to U.S. in jewel row.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Moscow sent a second official to the United States on Wednesday to try to resolve a dispute with the U.S. organisers of an exhibition tour involving a priceless collection of Russian jewels.</p>
<p>Itar-Tass news agency said its general director, Vitaly Ignatenko, had left for Washington hours after deputy culture minister Mikhail Shvydkoy flew there to try to sort out a contract row which has left the tour in limbo.</p>
<p>Ignatenko was until last month a deputy prime minister responsible for the media. Tass gave no details of his mission.</p>
<p>Moscow and the U.S. organisers are arguing about what to do next with the treasures.</p>
<p>&quot;If an agreement is not reached between the two sides to continue the exhibition, we will have to act fairly quickly and sharply and bring the items back to Russia,&quot; Deputy Culture Minister Pavel Khoroshilov told Reuters.</p>
<p>The collection, including art works, costumes and some of the world's biggest gems, was due to be shown in several U.S. cities this year. The first show, at Washington's Corcoran Gallery of Art, has just ended.</p>
<p>Khoroshilov said the dispute arose after U.S. organisers failed to exchange a series of documents related to the exhibition, including on financial matters.</p>
<p>&quot;The Russian embassy says numerous efforts to get the Americans to the negotiating table have failed,&quot; Khoroshilov said. &quot;The Ministry of Culture is now worried about a situation which could to a certain extent jeopordise the security of these items.&quot;</p>
<p>The Corcoran Gallery says Russia wants the goods back for Moscow's 850th birthday celebration in May. Other American officials say the squabble is really about money.</p>
<p>John Millian, a lawyer retained by the Russian embassy in Washingon, has denied that profits are the motive.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
