<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="531947" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila confirms identity of dead Bre-X geologist.</title>
<headline>Manila confirms identity of dead Bre-X geologist.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippine investigators have identified the remains of the chief Filipino geologist for the Canadian firm Bre-X Minerals Ltd through his fingerprints, a senior official said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>National Bureau of Investigation (NBI) director Santiago Toledo said tests on a thumbprint of Michael de Guzman sent by Indonesian police matched those of fingerprints that the NBI took from the body buried by his family in Manila on April 4.</p>
<p>The NBI tests &quot;showed they were taken from one and the same person&quot;, Toledo told reporters.</p>
<p>De Guzman helped discover in the Busang jungles of Borneo island in Indonesia what Bre-X at first said were gold reserves estimated at 70.95 million ounces, worth $25 billion at current prices. That would make the discovery the biggest gold strike in the world this century.</p>
<p>His plunge from a helicopter flying him to the gold site last March and a statement by Bre-X that it was possible the amount of gold at the property had been overstated jolted the mining world.</p>
<p>Some Indonesian officials have said de Guzman's death appeared to be a suicide based on a letter they said he left behind saying he was suffering from acute hepatitis B. His family in Manila said they doubted he would take his own life.</p>
<p>A brother of De Guzman, Simplicio, told reporters earlier this month after recovering the remains from Indonesia that he was &quot;absolutely sure&quot; the body was that of his brother.</p>
<p>Simplicio attacked a newspaper story suggesting the man his family buried was not the geologist.</p>
<p>Toledo said the NBI had also finished its autopsy on the body but that he needed the family's permission before releasing the results.</p>
<p>The Indonesian police also carried out their own autopsy of the body.</p>
<p>President Fidel Ramos said last week his government was still awaiting the results of the Indonesian investigation and that he had full confidence in Indonesia &quot;in unravelling the mystery&quot; of the geologist's death.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
