<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="532085" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton, Dalai Lama meet at White House.</title>
<headline>Clinton, Dalai Lama meet at White House.</headline>
<byline>Laurence McQuillan</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton met with the Dalai Lama on Wednesday and told the exiled Tibetan leader he will urge China to open a direct dialogue with him.</p>
<p>Despite warnings from Beijing that the White House visit might reopen strains in U.S.-Sino relations, Clinton joined a meeting between the Dalai Lama and Vice President Al Gore.</p>
<p>White House Press Secretary Mike McCurry said Clinton wanted to &quot;convey his respect for the moral leadership of his holiness, the Dalai Lama.&quot;</p>
<p>McCurry said Clinton used the meeting to &quot;convey to his holiness the president's willingness to suggest to the Peoples Republic of China that they enter into a dialogue with the Dalai Lama or the Dalai Lama's representative.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Clinton intended to raise the issue in the fall at a Washington summit with China's President Jiang Zemin.</p>
<p>Officials said Clinton would also meet Chinese Foreign Minister Qian Qichen when he visits Washington early next week. Those talks will include preparations for the summit.</p>
<p>Beijing has refused to hold talks with the Dalai Lama, insisting he is not a religious leader but a political activist trying to lead an independence movement.</p>
<p>&quot;I had a very good meeting,&quot; the Dalai Lama told reporters as he emerged from the White House. He said the session with Clinton and Gore involved a discussion of &quot;human values&quot; and &quot;some Tibetan problems,&quot; but declined to elaborate.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm very happy, very satisfied,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Before departing the White House, he also met briefly with first lady Hillary Rodham Clinton and discussed what the Dalai Lama described as &quot;some religious matters.&quot;</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama opened a high-level public relations mission in the U.S. capital on Wednesday by striking a conciliatory tone, insisting he only seeks self-rule for Tibetans, not independence from China.</p>
<p>&quot;We tried to make very clear to the Chinese government we are seeking self-rule, not independence,&quot; he told reporters shortly before the White House talks began.</p>
<p>In another U.S. move likely to displease China, a senior State Department official said on Wednesday that Taiwan President Lee Teng-hui was eligible for a U.S. transit visa.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect to continue to provide (transit) visas to (Taiwan) leaders,&quot; Jeffrey Bader, a deputy assistant secretary of state, told a House subcommittee. &quot;President Lee would be eligible as well.&quot;</p>
<p>Lee is expected to request permission to touch down en route to a high-level conference for Panama Canal Zone users scheduled to take place in Panama from September 7 to 10.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama began his latest Washington visit by addressing a World Parliamentarians Convention on Tibet at the U.S. Capitol, an event attended by several members of Congress, including Representative Benjamin Gilman, the chairman of the House of Representatives International Relations Committee.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama said he was hopeful residents of Hong Kong would continue to retain their rights and freedoms after China takes control of the British colony on July 1. And he said he would open an office in Taiwan within a short time.</p>
<p>He has been in exile since an abortive 1959 uprising against Chinese rule in Tibet.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama, winner of the 1989 Nobel Peace Prize for his Tibetan autonomy campaign, last visited Washington in September 1995. Clinton met with him briefly in Gore's office then too.</p>
<p>He plans to meet with Secretary of State Madeleine Albright on Thursday.</p>
<p>In Beijing, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said the United States should not have allowed the Dalai Lama to even visit. He warned Washington to avoid &quot;any form of meeting between U.S. leaders and the Dalai Lama, in order to prevent new damage to Sino-U.S. relations.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
