<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="532154" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Christian Coalition leader to step down. [CORRECTED 18:19 GMT]</title>
<headline>U.S. Christian Coalition leader to step down. [CORRECTED 18:19 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Alan Elsner, U.S. Political Correspondent</p>
<p>Ralph Reed, who mobilised millions of evangelical, conservative Christians into a powerful political force, announced on Wednesday (Corrects)</p>
<p>he is stepping down in September as director of the Christian Coalition.</p>
<p>Reed told a news conference he would set up a political consultancy company probably based in Atlanta to help conservative candidates opposed to abortion become elected. He said he had no current plans to seek elective office himself.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that institutions such as the Christian Coalition ... are energised and enriched by new blood and by new ideas,&quot; Reed said.</p>
<p>Reed, known for his boyish looks, spent eight years at the Christian Coalition, which was created by television evangelist Pat Robertson.</p>
<p>Its annual budget grew from $200,000 in 1989 to $27 million last year. Today, it claims 1.9 million dues-paying members in 2,000 chapters. In last November's elections, it distributed 45 million voter guides in 125,000 churches.</p>
<p>Reed said the Coalition had transformed the power and influence of Christian conservatives in U.S. politics. Formerly ignored or dismissed, they were now &quot;one of the most potent and effective forces in American politics,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>American University professor Daniel Dreisbach, who has studied the Coalition, said the organisation was capable of mobilising a quarter of the vote in many congressional districts, especially in the South.</p>
<p>&quot;In some places, they can pull out 40 percent of the vote --obviously much more than the margin between winning and losing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But the Christian Coalition has also been a polarising force. It attracts fervent opposition, even from some within the Republican Party who fear its members want to impose their morals and beliefs on the rest of society.</p>
<p>Barry Lynn, director of Americans United for Separation of Church and State, a group which opposes the Coalition, said Reed had played a very negative role in U.S. politics.</p>
<p>&quot;Ralph Reed has played a major part in bringing religious extremism into political life in a very destructive way. Rather than elevate the role of religion in politics, Reed's activities have dragged it into the gutter,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Under Reed, the Coalition has attempted to reach out beyond the group's basic constituency of white Protestants to embrace Catholics, orthodox Jews and most recently blacks. The effort has had mixed success.</p>
<p>&quot;We have matured into a movement known not for its self-righteousness but for its repentence and spirit of reconciliation,&quot; Reed asserted.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, Reed launched a new effort to throw the weight of the Coalition behind efforts to renew inner cities and help black youth. He said he would remain associated with such efforts through private charitable groups. He would also retain a seat on the board of governors of the Coalition.</p>
<p>His political consultancy firm would focus on helping build a &quot;farm team&quot; of conservatives who would serve on school boards and local or city counsels, he said.</p>
<p>It would be active in dozens and eventually hundreds of races across the country, starting with the elections of 1998.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
