<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="532444" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dalai Lama begins Washington visit, to see Clinton.</title>
<headline>Dalai Lama begins Washington visit, to see Clinton.</headline>
<byline>Robert Green</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Dalai Lama opened a high-level public relations mission in the U.S. capital on Wednesday with assurances he is only seeking self-rule for Tibetans, not Tibet's independence from China.</p>
<p>&quot;We tried to make very clear to the Chinese government we are seeking self-rule, not independence,&quot; the exiled Tibetan spiritual leader told reporters shortly before he was to make a White House visit China regards as a provocation.</p>
<p>He began his latest Washington visit by addressing a World Parliamentarians Convention on Tibet at the U.S. Capitol, an event attended by several members of Congress including Representative Benjamin Gilman, the chairman of the House of Representatives International Relations Committee.</p>
<p>Gilman, a New York Republican, urged China to grant Tibetans their freedom.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama also said he was hopeful residents of Hong Kong would continue to have their same rights and freedoms after China takes control of the British colony at midnight on June 30. And he said he would open an office in Taiwan within a short time.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama has been in exile since an abortive 1959 uprising against Chinese rule in Tibet.</p>
<p>He visits Washington periodically to drum up support for greater Tibetan political freedoms and -- despite Beijing's objections -- was scheduled to meet with President Bill Clinton and Vice President Al Gore on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Clinton was to &quot;drop by&quot; a meeting between the Dalai Lama and Gore in the vice president's office -- a diplomatic gambit the White House sometimes uses so that the president may show moral support for a controversial visitor while saving face for the foreign government that objects to the visit.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama, winner of the 1989 Nobel Peace Prize for his Tibetan autonomy campaign, last visited Washington in September 1995. Clinton met with him briefly in Gore's office then too.</p>
<p>He also plans to meet with Secretary of State Madeleine Albright later this week.</p>
<p>Beijing last year issued a warning that countries whose leaders met with the Dalai Lama would suffer the consequences in trade and business ties with China.</p>
<p>Chinese Foreign Minister Qian Qichen is due in the United States on Sunday and will meet with Clinton. His talks are expected to include preparations for a summit in Washington in the fall between Clinton and Chinese President Jiang Zemin.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
