<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="532432" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Six-year-old handcuffed, arrested in Florida.</title>
<headline>Six-year-old handcuffed, arrested in Florida.</headline>
<dateline>TAMPA, Fla. 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 6-year-old girl was arrested, handcuffed and detained for several hours in Largo, Florida, after she disrupted a crime prevention class, the Tampa Tribune reported Wednesday.</p>
<p>The child also allegedly kicked, hit and spat at the school principal and a police officer, the paper said.</p>
<p>State officials said children under age seven usually are not considered mentally capable of committing crimes.</p>
<p>Police said the child refused to move her chair back from a television set being used by police to show a crime prevention video. She allegedly yelled and threw a stuffed animal before being taken to the principal's office.</p>
<p>School officials said she was too upset to go home on the school bus and her grandmother could not pick her up. The girl was then arrested, handcuffed and taken to the Pinellas County Juvenile Assessment Centre until her father came for her several hours later.</p>
<p>The child's grandmother said she was told not to pick up the child because she needed to be locked up for the night. School officials said the girl had been suspended before for disruptive behaviour and would be put in a special class when she returned to school next week.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAMPA, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
