<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="533070" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Russian official arrives for Romanov jewel talks.</title>
<headline>Russian official arrives for Romanov jewel talks.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior Russian official on Wednesday tries to end a dispute that has kept an exhibition of priceless treasures from Russia's imperial past stranded because of an argument over who should control them.</p>
<p>Deputy Culture Minister Mikhail Shvidkoy arrived from Moscow to oversee negotiations on whether a planned tour of U.S. museums can continue or the collection will head back to Russia.</p>
<p>A Russian Embassy spokesman said Shvidkoy was &quot;first familiarizing himself with the situation before setting his schedule.&quot;</p>
<p>The Romanov czars' crown jewels remained in a Corcoran Gallery of Art vault and in a truck on a nearby street for the past week because of a legal wrangle over who was in charge.</p>
<p>The truck was moved to the Russian Embassy grounds on Tuesday night, but no decision had been reached on the ultimate fate of the collection.</p>
<p>The collection, including art works, costumes and some of the world's biggest gems, was due to be shown in several U.S. cities thoughout this year, starting with a successful show at Washington's Corcoran Gallery of Art that has just ended after a 10-week run that drew over 80,000 people at $9 each.</p>
<p>Russia now says it wants the treasures back for Moscow's 850th birthday celebration in May, according to the Corcoran, which wants a signed legal order before turning over the collection.</p>
<p>The U.S. group that had contracted to organise the tour has been arguing with the Russian Embassy about what to do next, but allowed the truck to be driven to the embassy grounds as a good will gesture.</p>
<p>&quot;Our agreement to release the truck is a good faith effort on the part of the Russian Embassy and the American-Russian Cultural Cooperation Foundation,&quot; the group's chairman James Symington said in a statement. The group raised $550,000 to mount the exhibition.</p>
<p>The moving van hired to take the exhibition to Houston for the next stop on a planned tour had been parked on a side street near the gallery since last Wednesday, blocked in by cars manned by drivers from the Russian Embassy.</p>
<p>Symington attributed the standoff to a dispute over revenue, not to Moscow's need for the jewels back home.</p>
<p>He said the deal with Russia's Culture Ministry was to split revenues after expenses were paid, but said Russian officials were now telling him that arrangement was not acceptable. &quot;It doesn't satisfy them,&quot; Symington said on Monday.</p>
<p>But John Millian, a lawyer retained by the Russian Embassy, denied that profits were the motive.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
