<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="533048" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Ice-T tries some satire on new album.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Ice-T tries some satire on new album.</headline>
<byline>Dean Goodman</byline>
<dateline>HOLLYWOOD 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ice-T has spent his life raising other people's hackles, whether in his younger days as a jewel thief or later as a pioneering &quot;gangsta&quot; rapper.</p>
<p>He upped the ante a few years ago when he formed a hard rock band called Body Count and wrote a song about police brutality called &quot;Cop Killer,&quot; which enraged the American political establishment.</p>
<p>But, ever-paranoid about going over old ground and risking &quot;corniness,&quot; he wants to be seen as more than a menace to society. He showcases his skills as a comedian and satirist on Body Count's third album, which has just hit the streets.</p>
<p>Bob Newhart or Jeff Foxworthy need not worry about the new competition. Titled &quot;Violent Demise: The Last Days,&quot; the album celebrates strippers, pokes fun at music journalists, honours Dr. Jack Kevorkian and even features a searing indictment of O.J. Simpson.</p>
<p>Such dark humour might surprise fans of the last Body Count album, &quot;Born Dead,&quot; which dealt with drive-by shootings, racism and grisly deaths. But Ice-T says his songs reflect what is happening around him at any given time. While &quot;Born Dead&quot; came out in 1994 with memories of the Los Angeles riots still fresh in his mind, life has moved on.</p>
<p>&quot;This year, we were back in L.A. We were dealing with rich, white kids going to Palm Springs, partying, getting drunk,&quot; he told Reuters at his home high up in the Hollywood Hills. &quot;You can't expect a kid out here that's in Brentwood riding about in his father's BMW to feel 'Born Dead,' y'know?&quot;</p>
<p>PLEAS TO 'TELL IT LIKE IT IS'</p>
<p>His spacious house with its swimming pool, black leather couches and 60-inch TV screen overlooks the vast Los Angeles urban sprawl and Ice-T never forgets the friends he left behind in the housing projects. They bombard him with pleas to &quot;tell it like it is,&quot; so the album has its more sombre moments such as &quot;Truth or Death&quot; and &quot;Root of All Evil.&quot;</p>
<p>The album's notes acknowledge the contributions of &quot;all vampires, serial killers, psychopaths, career criminals, pimps, hos, kidnappers and drug dealers&quot; who have provided Ice-T with inspiration. &quot;If this world was only full of angels, there would be no Ice-T,&quot; he explained. &quot;As they kill and murder and rape and rob, I'll always have material.&quot;</p>
<p>Ice-T, in his late 30s, certainly makes no claim to being an angel. Born Tracy Marrow, he was orphaned at an early age and ended up on the mean streets of South-Central Los Angeles as a member of the Crips gang. He began stealing jewelry and was frequently jailed before his first rap album in 1987.</p>
<p>Now he says he finds humour in the worst things. &quot;I'm just a fool. That's how I am. Everything is a joke to me. My buddies say I do anything for a laugh.&quot;</p>
<p>The Simpson saga, in which the former football star was acquitted of double murder in a criminal trial, then was found liable in a civil trial, seemed ridiculous to Ice-T. He believed Simpson to be guilty and wrote &quot;I Used To Love Her,&quot; about the whole affair.</p>
<p>O.J. SIMPSON CASE 'IS SO STUPID'</p>
<p>&quot;It could be considered wrong to make a joke about it, but it's so stupid, it's out there,&quot; he said. &quot;I tend to sometimes talk about things in its humorous form to make you say, 'Damn, that is kind of stupid.'&quot;</p>
<p>The album begins with a whining music journalist getting beaten up by Ice-T because he does not think Body Count rocks hard enough. A few tracks later is &quot;Strippers,&quot; whose X-rated video runs on a Playboy cable channel.</p>
<p>Towards the end is &quot;Dr. K,&quot; a song about the celebrated right-to-die advocate written by Body Count lead guitarist Ernie C. The song's message is that if you think life could not be worse &quot;call the doc up, he'll pick you up in a hearse.&quot;</p>
<p>The death motif is fitting for Body Count, which Ice-T formed as a side project in 1989 with Ernie C. and some old friends from South-Central.</p>
<p>The band released its self-titled debut album in 1992 and made headlines a few months later when a police group picked up on the &quot;Cop Killer&quot; track and turned it into an election-year issue involving everyone from then-President George Bush to free-speech advocates.</p>
<p>The album flew out of stores amid the ensuing publicity before the group's label, Warner Bros., deleted the track from further pressings with Ice-T's approval. They split by mutual agreement soon after and the band signed with Virgin Records.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't have a problem with the police at all,&quot; he says now. &quot;It was a record about a guy who lost it because the brutal police was (messing) with him. I didn't know this cat I invented would become a hero.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HOLLYWOOD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
