<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="533142" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE-Watt enjoys life after near-death experience.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Watt enjoys life after near-death experience.</headline>
<byline>Mark Egan</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>English musician Ben Watt is more sucessful now than ever before and relishing every moment of his life, which was almost snuffed out five years ago by an obscure illness.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a new vitality to my life and I'm enjoying myself and want to get myself out of bed in the morning,&quot; Watt told Reuters. &quot;There are things to get up for.&quot;</p>
<p>In 1992 Watt, famous as half of &quot;Everything But The Girl,&quot; one of the most successful English pop bands, was struck with an often-fatal illness called Churg-Strauss Syndrome, which causes a breakdown of the immune system. Sparked by allergies and asthma, the system, which is supposed to protect the body from bacteria and allergens, becomes overloaded and confused and starts to attack the body, usually ending in death.</p>
<p>Watt was admitted to a London hospital in 1992. After a bad bout of asthma brought on by allergies to house dust mites, he was suffering from chest pains thought to be a massive heart attack. He eventually spent nine weeks in the hospital. After misdiagnosis, he was eventually found to have Churg-Strauss Syndrome.</p>
<p>&quot;The doctors were tring to diagnose it through a jig-saw of symptoms but in the end they couldn't make a match so they had to ask the surgeons to cut me open and see what all the pain was being caused by,&quot; Watt said. &quot;That's when they discovered 75 percent of my gut had virtually rotted away inside me.&quot;</p>
<p>SUBJECT OF NEW BOOK</p>
<p>His misery is the subject of a new book &quot;Patient-The True Story of a Rare Illness&quot; released in the United States this month. The book reveals in brutal detail the anatomical minutiae of Watt's pain and misery as well as the impact his illness and recovery had on relationships with his loved ones.</p>
<p>On the night Watt was initially operated on doctors said he had a 25 percent chance of surviving the night. That week alone he had four operations to save his life. Surgeons removed part of his small intestine, leaving him with just enough to digest his food.</p>
<p>Recovering was not easy. Watt was put on a life support system to help him breathe and a saline drip to hydrate him. He was fed through a tube inserted deep in his chest and urinated through a catheter. In his hands he held a joy-stick that allowed him inject small doses of morphine into his system while an epidural tube was tapped into his spine to paralyse him from the waist down, where the pain was too much to bear. His vocal chords were temporarily paralysed.</p>
<p>&quot;You just have to deal with it,&quot; Watt said. &quot;Sometimes bored, sometimes in pain, sometimes frustrated, but you live your day at 20-minute intervals. 'Am I comfortable? Can I have more morphine? When is the next operation?' It's quite difficult to distance yourself from what's happening. That comes later when you have a chance to reflect on the whole traumatic experience.&quot;</p>
<p>After his hospital stint Watt became reflective and found the company of others a strain. He worked through his trauma by writing what eventually became the book &quot;Patient.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I certainly didn't want more doctors and I didn't want counselling,&quot; Watt said.</p>
<p>FELT NEED TO TELL HIS STORY</p>
<p>&quot;In a strange way the complete rarity of the case actually made it quite glamorous to me and I wanted to be the one person who had the scoop on the story and could tell it like it had never been told before,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>He is remarkably upbeat when looking back on it all.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm pretty much star guinea pig here and I'm an experiment for doctors in some way. All they know is that I've survived the first five years ... with any luck I will probably get away with it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Watt joked about his anorexic-looking frame, saying he is now referred to as &quot;the male Kate Moss&quot; in some quarters. His shrunken digestive system left him permanently on a severely restricted diet and he has blood tests every couple of months in the hope of detecting any return of the disease.</p>
<p>Does he worry death is looming? &quot;No. I don't look at it like that ... what is the point? I can't just sit here with my head in my hands. It is frustrating sometimes and depressing but it is also my life and it's never going to change.&quot;</p>
<p>After his illness Watt reinvented himself musically. He openly admits he was unhappy with the music he and longtime lover Tracey Thorn had been producing and, since his recovery, they have produced two new &quot;Everything But The Girl&quot; albums, &quot;Amplified Heart&quot; and &quot;Walking Wounded.&quot;</p>
<p>Both albums have far outsold anything the pair had produced since their first effort in 1984 and a re-mixed version of one song, &quot;Missing,&quot; topped the Billboard charts.</p>
<p>&quot;My illness was definitely a catalyst for change,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
