<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="533895" id="root" date="1997-04-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: India says 46 haj fire victims dead, 271 missing.</title>
<headline>India says 46 haj fire victims dead, 271 missing.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-04-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Indian official in Saudi Arabia on Wednesday said 46 Indians were killed in the fire at a Moslem haj pilgrimage site last week.</p>
<p>&quot;The up-to-date death toll on Indians killed in the blaze stands at 46,&quot; said an official at India's haj delegation in Mecca.</p>
<p>&quot;Another 271 Indians are still missing, and we have 291 in hospitals,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>This was the first official announcement of Indian victims since the blaze on April 15 which swept through 70,000 tents at the key pilgrimage site of Mena near the holy city of Mecca.</p>
<p>Saudi Arabia said last week that 343 people died and more than 1,500 were injured in the blaze. It was not immediately clear whether the Indian victims were accounted for in the official death toll.</p>
<p>The Indian official said 10 bodies were buried in Mena and six in Mecca. About 80,000 Indians performed the haj this year.</p>
<p>Diplomats and officials said identification of bodies was hard because so many had been burned beyond recognition.</p>
<p>Witnesses said many victims burned to death, others suffocated from the deadly fumes while some were crushed by a stampede as panic gripped the pilgrims.</p>
<p>A statement by the Indian Foreign Ministry on Monday gave no casualty figures but said 281 of its nationals were missing and 202 remained in hospitals.</p>
<p>Pakistan's ambassador to Saudi Arabia said on Tuesday 111 nationals were confirmed dead and 100 still missing.</p>
<p>Some diplomats said the week-old death toll could end up higher than already announced in view of the critical condition of some victims being treated at Saudi hospitals.</p>
<p>Saudi newspapers said on Tuesday four Sudanese pilgrims, three of them women, died in the blaze. Other countries have yet to specify death tolls.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
