<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="534868" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British minister cleared in N.Irish jobs row.</title>
<headline>British minister cleared in N.Irish jobs row.</headline>
<byline>Martin Cowley</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>An independent inquiry cleared a British minister on Thursday of unfairly treating a Roman Catholic official who was controversially transferred from a job in her private office.</p>
<p>Last month, the province's main minority Catholic parties called on Northern Ireland Office minister Baroness Jean Denton to resign, accusing her of flouting a government code aimed at combatting employment bias.</p>
<p>Maurice Hayes, called in by Britain to investigate the case and three other staffing disputes, said Denton's role was not malicious, but added the cases raised concern about management style in her office.</p>
<p>&quot;There was nothing in the least to suggest a pattern of discrimination. In fact there was no pattern either of religion or gender,&quot; he said in a report made public by Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;I am quite satisfied that in these cases discrimination was not a factor and that the minister in particular did not behave in a discriminatory manner.&quot;</p>
<p>Denton, the province's economic and agriculture minister, expressed delight that Hayes &quot;completely vindicates me from any insinuations of discrimination...I am sorry that some people should have thought I could behave in such a way. It was a hurtful time.&quot;</p>
<p>She came under fire when it was disclosed that a Catholic, who had been subjected to sectarian harassment by a Protestant official, was transferred to another post but the perpetrator had been allowed to remain in her job in the minister's office.</p>
<p>Denton said the transfer was suggested to resolve operational difficulties in her office and before the Catholic's complaint of religious harassment was lodged against the Protestant.</p>
<p>In another case, Denton was further accused of breaching fair employment procedures by choosing a woman for a private secretary postion who was not on an shortlist of candidates.</p>
<p>Hayes said the cases he probed had a pattern &quot;which should be sufficient to raise concern about management style and alert Ministers and Departments to the need for clarity and certainty in the procedures for appointing and transferring Private Office staff....&quot;</p>
<p>He called for more training of officials in procedures for handling harassment cases. Senior managers must give a lead in taking harassment seriously whether it was based on religion, politics, gender, disability or other grounds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
