<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535115" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Solidarity asks in vain for Church help in vote.</title>
<headline>Solidarity asks in vain for Church help in vote.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chiefs of the rightist Catholic Solidarity union have asked the Church to seek God's help in Poland's constitutional referendum next month -- but in vain.</p>
<p>&quot;This is creating a situation in which man would like God to conduct politics on his behalf,&quot; Bishop Tadeusz Pieronek, general secretary of Poland's episcopate, told public radio on Thursday when explaining the Church's refusal.</p>
<p>He said that there had been recent attempts to drag the Church into politics and that it was widely assumed that the Church supported the right and should behave just like it.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a very dangerous thing,&quot; Pieronek said.</p>
<p>The ruling ex-communists and three other parties in parliament have drafted a new constitution to replace the 1952 one rendered obsolete by the fall of communism in 1989, and the May 25 referendum will decide whether this is adopted.</p>
<p>Solidarity has produced its own more religious, patriotic constitution and urged its supporters to reject the parliament version which polls show is likely to win popular approval.</p>
<p>So some union leaders, including its chief Marian Krzaklewski, asked the Church to perform a ceremony of &quot;Enthroning Christ the King&quot; -- a step taken just before Polish troops defeated Bolshevik invaders in 1920 -- to halt it.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be hard for us to reject the constitution presented in the referendum using human forces alone,&quot; Gazeta Wyborcza daily quoted the Solidarity leaders as writing in their appeal.</p>
<p>The trade union has gathered right-leaning parties into a powerful alliance, Solidarity Election Action (AWS), to challenge the ruling left in elections due in September. @</p>
<p>It often uses the rhetoric of the pre-1989 past, when Solidarity backed by Churchmen bravely challenged communist rule, to denounce the former communists who recast themselves as social democrats and won 1993 parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>Pieronek's statement underlined that the right cannot count on overt support from the pulpit -- even though the Church has in the past made plain where its sympathies lie.</p>
<p>Pieronek said that in the constitutional referendum the church would urge people to vote but not how to vote. @</p>
<p>He also served notice on Radio Maryja, a popular station combining prayer with right-wing politics, that the bishops planned to lean on it.</p>
<p>In comments reported by PAP news agency Pieronek said Radio Maryja, which is campaigning against the new constitution, should not be identified with the views of the Church.</p>
<p>Attitudes towards religion are set to play a major part in the parliamentary elections, not least as Polish-born Pope John Paul ll, who was central to the fall of communism, will visit the country from May 31 to June 10. @</p>
<p>The Pope, like the Polish right, is deeply saddened the secular-minded ruling left has liberalised the abortion law.</p>
<p>But tension between Church and left has been lessened by prospects that the ex-communists may at last soon ratify a long-delayed concordat treaty between Poland and the Vatican.</p>
<p>Sociologists say the episcopate wants to avoid directly supporting any party, which might lose elections, and condemns the intolerance of some extreme Catholic nationalists.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
