<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535192" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Pope to mark saint's death in Czech Republic.</title>
<headline>Pope to mark saint's death in Czech Republic.</headline>
<byline>Nigel Stephenson</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul begins on Friday a visit to the Czech Republic, during which he will commemorate the 1,000th anniversary of the death of a Czech saint and put forward a message of European unity.</p>
<p>The Pope, on his third visit to Prague since the fall of Communism in 1989, is due to hold a mass on Saturday with young people in the town of Hradec Kralove, some 100 km (60 miles) east of the capital, to mark the death of St Adalbert.</p>
<p>The saint, known as Vojtech in Czech, was the first bishop of Czech origin but also took the Christian faith to Poland and is seen by the Catholic Church as &quot;an apostle of Europe&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pope comes to point out to us, and to the whole Church, this great figure of an apostle and martyr, whose European dimension at the present time, is felt more and more,&quot; Archbishop Giovanni Coppa, Papal Nuncio to Prague, said in a statement.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old Polish Pope, in declining health, is also due to hold an open air mass, which more than 100,000 people are expected to attend, in Prague on Sunday and an ecumenical service with Czech church leaders in the city's St Vitus Cathedral.</p>
<p>This visit to the Czech Republic should prove less controversial than the Pope's last, in May 1995, when he canonised Jan Sarkander, tortured to death by Protestants in 1620 during wars for religious supremacy. Protestants accuse Sarkander of being a traitor who encouraged a Catholic invasion.</p>
<p>Leading Protestants boycotted talks with the Pope but Adalbert is a less touchy topic. &quot;He lived in the Czech lands before the division of the church and surely he belongs to all of us,&quot; said Nadjeje Mandysova, general secretary of the Ecumenical Council of Churches.</p>
<p>The Czech Republic, with one of the highest standards of living in Eastern Europe, is highly secularised despite more than four million people in a population of 10.5 million calling themselves Catholics. Few people go to church.</p>
<p>But Mandysova said interest in the Pope's visit was high and she expected far bigger crowds at the masses than in 1995.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a bit surprising that people of non-Catholic churches have such interest in the visit,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Coppa said he expected 120,000 at the mass at Prague's Letna plain, the scene of Soviet-era military parades but later of massive anti-communist demonstrations during 1989's &quot;Velvet Revolution&quot;.</p>
<p>The Pope first came to Prague as Pontiff in April 1990, using the visit to hail the end of communism, and drew huge crowds. Church-state relations in the former Czechoslovakia, which split peacefully into the Czech and Slovak republics in 1993, were among the worst in the former East bloc.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1990, it was the first months after the end of totalitarianism and expectations were very high,&quot; said Czech Catholics Bishops Conference spokesman Miloslav Fiala.</p>
<p>&quot;It may be that the situation (here) is not as good as two years ago. People are awaiting changes in political and other aspects of human life so maybe that is linked with the interest in the Pope,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>On his last foreign trip, to Bosnia earlier this month, the Pope shivered in the cold and his left hand shook in what is widely regarded as a sign he has Parkinson's disease.</p>
<p>&quot;He is tired but if he is coming to the people, he gets new energy,&quot; Fiala said. &quot;He is inspired by youth and the thousands of people.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
