<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535140" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UZBEKISTAN: Human rights in Uzbekistan &quot;retrograde&quot; - rights group.</title>
<headline>Human rights in Uzbekistan &quot;retrograde&quot; - rights group.</headline>
<byline>Chris Bird</byline>
<dateline>TASHKENT 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Criminal charges brought by the Uzbek government against an Islamic cleric show human rights to be &quot;retrograde&quot; in the former Soviet republic, a human rights representative said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The evidence we collect is that things are not improving,&quot; John Macleod, Human Rights Watch Helsinki's representative in Uzbekistan, told Reuters in the capital Tashkent. &quot;All the evidence is retrograde,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Macleod said Abid Khan Nazarov, an Islamic cleric already battling the government in a civil case over his home, was summoned to court and charged on Wednesday under sections of the criminal code which deal with slander and inciting ethnic, racial or religious hatred respectively.</p>
<p>He said Nazarov and his lawyer were not told by the legal authorities who the cleric was meant to have slandered. Nor were they shown a document allegedly signed by elders in Tashkent's Sabir-Rakhimovsky district accusing the cleric of being a harmful influence on the district's youth.</p>
<p>Eyewitnesses said about 15 people from a small group of the cleric's supporters, who gathered outside the court in Tashkent on Wednesday, were detained briefly by police.</p>
<p>There was no word of the charges or detentions in the tightly-controlled state media or any official comment.</p>
<p>Mikhail Ardzinov, a leading human rights activist in Uzbekistan who witnessed the detentions on Wednesday, said: &quot;It was only the presence of foreign observers outside the court which stopped the detention of Nazarov himself.&quot;</p>
<p>Earlier this month, a civil case in which Nazarov is fighting the government over his home prompted a rare display of opposition in the largely desert nation of 23 million when about 300 of the cleric's supporters gathered outside the court.</p>
<p>Nazarov was evicted from his flat in Tashkent after he lost his post at the Tokhtobou mosque and medresa, or religious school, which was closed in 1995. A new home promised to him failed to materialise, so Nazarov took the government to court.</p>
<p>Macleod said the new criminal charges were a throw-back to the republic's Soviet past, &quot;where the law is used to get rid of your opponents&quot;.</p>
<p>Uzbek President Islam Karimov, the country's former Communist Party boss and nicknamed &quot;Papa&quot; by the population, tolerates little opposition.</p>
<p>Secular opposition groups such as Birlik (Unity) and Erk (Freedom) have virtually ceased to function, with many of their leaders in exile.</p>
<p>But Islam, with a wide support base among a population which has retained strong Islamic traditions despite decades of Soviet atheism, is a bigger worry for Karimov, who fears a rise of fundamentalism on the back of economic hardships.</p>
<p>The government closed two medresas in Tashkent in February, leaving no functioning religious school in the capital. Macleod says the government has imprisoned 20 other Moslem clerics.</p>
<p>Karimov, anxious for good ties with the United States, has often spoken publicly of the need to respect human rights and of the need for a political opposition.</p>
<p>On Thursday he told the country's obedient parliament that officials were still abusing human rights and urged deputies to investigate and &quot;speak more bravely&quot; about abuses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UZBK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TASHKENT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UZBEKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
