<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535114" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UZBEKISTAN: Arrest shows Islam makes Uzbek leader nervous.</title>
<headline>Arrest shows Islam makes Uzbek leader nervous.</headline>
<byline>Chris Bird</byline>
<dateline>TASHKENT 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Criminal charges made against an outspoken Islamic cleric in Uzbekistan show that the ex-Soviet state's government is increasingly nervous of Islam, observers said on Thurday.</p>
<p>Abid Khan Nazarov, an Islamic cleric sacked from Tashkent's Tokhtobou mosque in 1995, was summoned to court on Wednesday and charged under articles 139 and 156 of the criminal code, which cover slander and inciting ethnic, racial or religious hatred.</p>
<p>The cleric had already been battling the government in the civil courts over his home, from where he was evicted after being removed from the mosque.</p>
<p>With the purist Islamic Taleban militia in neighbouring Afghanistan on the march, Uzbek President Islam Karimov is anxious to dampen any fundamentalist sparks that could touch off unrest among a population fed up with economic hardship.</p>
<p>Uzbeks, Tajiks and other ethnic groups straddle the Uzbek-Afghan border.</p>
<p>Around 20 Islamic clerics are sitting in Uzbek prisons, according to human rights groups. Several mosques and medresas, or religious schools, have been closed.</p>
<p>The Uzbek leader has tried to place Islam under the control of a pliant, Soviet-style &quot;spiritual board&quot;, particularly in the restive Ferghana valley to the east where Islam is strong.</p>
<p>Karimov, the republic's former Communist Party boss who tolerates little opposition from the 23 million population, has dealt ruthlessly with opposition groups, which barely function.</p>
<p>But in taking on Islam, which survived virtually intact despite seven decades of sometimes bloody harrassment under the Soviets, Karimov has a much larger battle on his hands.</p>
<p>Gustav Krist, an Austrian who travelled in disguise through Soviet Central Asia in the 1920s, observed that even the Bolsheviks' ruthless attempts to crush Islam had largely failed.</p>
<p>&quot;You may see a praying carpet rolled in a corner with a Quran on top of it ready for immediate use, while above these mute witnesses to Islam a red flag flutters, or the picture of a Soviet leader hangs,&quot; he wrote.</p>
<p>Mosques have mushroomed across the republic, from 80 after independence in 1991 to around 5,000 today, while Uzbeks are once more making the &quot;haj&quot;, or Moslem pilgramage, to Mecca.</p>
<p>&quot;Islam (in Uzbekistan) is a mass phenomenon,&quot; said John Macleod, Human Rights Watch Helsinki's representative in Uzbekistan.</p>
<p>He echoes many observers when he says government actions against Islam are themselves creating an Islamic bugbear.</p>
<p>&quot;If you look at Algeria or Egypt, the more you whack them (Moslems), the angrier they get,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Across from Tashkent's smoky Chorsu bazaar on Thursday, men entered the Tokhtobou mosque and kicked off their shoes for evening prayers. Yellow kites flown by grubby boys jerked in the wind above the mosque's stubby turquoise minarets.</p>
<p>&quot;If our doors were closed, then we would be closed but we're not, we're functioning,&quot; said a pro-government cleric, his head bound in a neat white turban.</p>
<p>But one of the men who had come to pray said the government was wrong to have removed Nazarov from the mosque. He said he had witnessed the brief detention by police of around 15 of Nazarov's supporters outside the court on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The government is being unfair, all we want is to be left alone to pray,&quot; said the man in a white prayer cap.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UZBK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TASHKENT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UZBEKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
