<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535660" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Russia, U.S. discuss jewels in Washington.</title>
<headline>Russia, U.S. discuss jewels in Washington.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russian and U.S. negotiators made progress in talks on Thursday to determine if a priceless collection of Romanov jewels and art objects can continue a planned U.S. tour or must go back to Moscow.</p>
<p>Russia is demanding that the collection, which includes some of the world's largest gems, should be returned despite written agreements with an American organiser for a year-long tour of U.S. museums.</p>
<p>Russian Deputy Culture Minister Mikhail Shvydkoy met at the Russian Embassy with James Symington, a former congressman and U.S. protocol chief who is head of the American-Russian Cooperation Foundation, which mounted the exhibition by borrowing over $400,000.</p>
<p>Each side disputes the other's accounting for the costs and expenses of the exhibit.</p>
<p>In a joint statement issued late on Thursday, the two sides said &quot;considerable progress&quot; had been made.</p>
<p>&quot;We look forward to the continuation of productive negotiations and hope we are able to move forward and bring the matter to a positive conclusion as soon as possible,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Vitaly Ignatenko, Itar-Tass news agency's general director, flew in on Wednesday to help in the talks. Until last month, he was a deputy prime minister responsible for the media.</p>
<p>In Moscow, officials were adamant that the collection should be returned if there is no settlement of a dispute that involves both money and control over the exhibition.</p>
<p>&quot;If an agreement is not reached between the two sides to continue the exhibition, we will have to act fairly quickly and sharply and bring the items back to Russia,&quot; Deputy Culture Minister Pavel Khoroshilov told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said U.S. organisers failed to exchange a series of documents related to the exhibition, including financial matters.</p>
<p>&quot;The Russian Embassy says numerous efforts to get the Americans to the negotiating table have failed,&quot; Khoroshilov said. &quot;The Ministry of Culture is now worried about a situation which could to a certain extent jeopordize the security of these items.&quot;</p>
<p>In a 10-week exhibition at Washington's Corcoran Gallery of Art, over 80,000 people paid $9 each to view the collection.</p>
<p>The exhibition was timed to commemorate the U.S. visit 125 years ago of Grand Duke Alexis. The Romanovs ruled Russia for 300 years, ending in the 1917 Communist revolution.</p>
<p>Last Wednesday, Russian Embassy cars blocked a moving van from taking the art works to Houston, the next stop on its tour, and the Corcoran locked away the jewels in a vault until the dispute is settled.</p>
<p>The two sides agreed on Tuesday to move the van to the Russian Embassy grounds for security reasons and as a sign of goodwill.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
