<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535620" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkey's political war of attrition reignites.</title>
<headline>Turkey's political war of attrition reignites.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Lyons</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's ruling Islamists, locked in a political war of attrition with the secularist armed forces, on Thursday threatened to try an outspoken commander for defaming Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Sevket Kazan, of the Islamist Welfare Party, said he had directed prosecutors to weigh charges against a general who denounced the prime minister as a &quot;pimp&quot; for his admiration of the austere Islam of the Saudi monarchy.</p>
<p>Erbakan himself called for legal action to be taken over the general's comments after two hours of talks with President Suleyman Demirel in Ankara.</p>
<p>&quot;To make such comments about the head of state of a friendly country and the prime minister of your country is very wrong behaviour and is something which must not be accepted under our laws,&quot; Erbakan said.</p>
<p>He said he would send a letter to military headquarters and expected them to take the necessary action.</p>
<p>The escalation of rhetoric from both sides has sent politicians running for cover and investors looking to bail out of volatile markets amid fears of a government collapse or even fresh military intervention.</p>
<p>Investors dumped shares on the Istanbul Stock Exchange, sending the main index down almost seven percent at midday. It later recovered somewhat to end the day off almost five percent.</p>
<p>&quot;I am talking about the concept of crime. The prosecutors will investigate if there is a crime or not,&quot; the state-run Anatolian agency quoted Kazan as saying.</p>
<p>He said television coverage of anti-Islamist comments last week by General Osman Ozbek, head of the gendarmerie in the eastern region of Erzurum, indicated the law had been broken.</p>
<p>&quot;If it is true, there are three clear crimes in the speech we saw on television,&quot; Kazan said. He said the general may have defamed Erbakan, Saudi King Fahd and breached military rules.</p>
<p>Ozbek denounced Erbakan for accepting the hospitality of Saudi Arabia's conservative monarch during his haj pilgrimage to Mecca this month.</p>
<p>&quot;If he were a real man he wouldn't go as a guest of a king like that...I do not care whether he is prime minister or minister of whatever...the pimp,&quot; Ozbek said.</p>
<p>The reverberations from a military establishment that has toppled civilian rule three times in the last four decades exposed the deep fault lines in the coalition between Erbakan's Islamists and the secularists of Tansu Ciller's True Path Party.</p>
<p>They also set the stage for a potential showdown on Saturday, when the military-dominated National Security Council is expected to repeat demands to Erbakan's recalcitrant cabinet for an anti-Islamist crackdown.</p>
<p>&quot;The political picture reveals the government is now finished,&quot; commentator Bilal Cetin told Reuters. &quot;The military does not want it, even other institutions do not want it.&quot;</p>
<p>Investors voted with their pocketbooks, sending Istanbul shares down 6.85 percent in morning trade. The main index bounced off its lows to close off 4.9 percent, at 1,457.</p>
<p>In what was widely seen as public endorsement for Ozbek, Army Commander Hikmet Koksal refused demands by the ruling Islamist Welfare Party to rein in the soldiers: &quot;There is no way we can zip anybody's mouth.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
