<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535880" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Woodstock festival site to be turned into theme park.</title>
<headline>Woodstock festival site to be turned into theme park.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The field where the 1969 Woodstock rock festival was held has been purchased by a cable television billionaire for a music theme park that may include concert halls and outdoor entertainment.</p>
<p>&quot;There'll be no merry-go-rounds and Ferris wheels, we're talking about a cultural centre,&quot; Alan Gerry, the new owner, said on Thursday. &quot;We want something that's very well thought out, very well planned, something that everyone who comes to America or lives here will want to experience.&quot;</p>
<p>Gerry paid about $1 million for the original 37 acres (15 hectares) of farmland near Bethel, New York, where 400,000 people frolicked in the mud in August 1969. He also bought the surrounding 1,000 acres (400 hectares) for an undisclosed sum.</p>
<p>The three-day concert, one of the most famous of the era, featured performances by Jimi Hendrix, The Who, the Jefferson Airplane, Joan Baez, Country Joe and the Fish and dozens more.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it was a very special time in history and I think that the place is special, is known worldwide and has a certain significance to people who grew up in that era,&quot; Gerry, 68, said by telephone. &quot;I think that it is a thing they would like to see perpetuated but done in a very fine manner.&quot;</p>
<p>The festival was named for another upstate New York town where rock star Bob Dylan lived. Dylan did not play at the concert but appeared at the second Woodstock on the 25th anniversary of the original.</p>
<p>Gerry, listed by Fortune magazine as one of the 250 richest people in America, bought the land a year ago through a company that specialises in private deals.</p>
<p>But the purchase was not made public until Wednesday as Gerry worked to obtain support for the various ventures he plans at the site. He merged his local cable television business worth $2.7 billion with Time Warner last year.</p>
<p>Gerry said he envisioned the area might have concert halls, bandshells, outside entertainment and indoor movie theatres, bringing employment and business to the sagging economy of Sullivan County. He said that over the next six to nine months he would work with architects and entertainment experts to begin drawing up plans for the site.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
