<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="535849" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Texas senate approves bill to fight lurid lyrics.</title>
<headline>Texas senate approves bill to fight lurid lyrics.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Texas Senate Wednesday passed a bill banning state investment funds from being invested in companies promoting songs with violent or sexually aberrant lyrics.</p>
<p>The bill was passed by unanimous voice vote, a senate spokeswoman said Thursday, adding that it was unamended from the version passed last Thursday by the Senate Finance Committee.</p>
<p>Finance Committee Chairman Bill Ratliff, a Republican and the bill's author, last week said it grew out of an article he read earlier this year quoting Dr. C DeLores Tucker, national chairwoman of the National Political Congress of Black Women Inc. The article discussed such lyrics' effects on children.</p>
<p>Under the bill, Texas entities charged with investing state funds would be banned from investing in companies directly associated with offensive lyrics as well as those indirectly associated by virtue of a 10 percent or greater stake in such enterprises.</p>
<p>The bill defines such lyrics as those depicting acts of criminal violence including murder and assault; necrophilia, beastiality or pedophilia; illegal use of controlled substances; criminal street gang activity; degradation or denigration of females; or violence against a particular sex, race or ethnic group.</p>
<p>It also requires a governmental entity or retirement system that currently owns such investments to divest &quot;as soon as reasonable and practical considering protection of capital, but no later than Jan. 1, 1999.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
