<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="536139" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Turin Shroud to go on display in 1998 despite fire.</title>
<headline>Turin Shroud to go on display in 1998 despite fire.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Turin Shroud, one of Catholicism's most revered but controversial relics, will go on display next year despite a fire that devastated the 15th century chapel which housed it, officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Cardinal Giovanni Saldarini of Turin also told a news conference at the Vatican he would not seek new carbon-14 dating tests to help determine the age of the shroud -- which some Catholics believe wrapped the body of the crucified Christ -- before the next scheduled display.</p>
<p>After tests in 1988 three laboratories in England, the United States and Switzerland said it was 95 percent certain that the cloth dated from between 1260 to 1390, suggesting it was a mediaeval fake.</p>
<p>But those results were not universally accepted by the scientific community</p>
<p>Saldarini said it was the &quot;firm intention&quot; of authorities to put the shroud on display as planned from April 18 to June 14, 1998 in the main section of Turin's Renaissance cathedral, which suffered less damage in the April 12 fire.</p>
<p>The blaze gutted the baroque Guarini chapel, the home of the shroud at the back of the cathedral, and a tower of the city's Royal Palace.</p>
<p>Firemen managed to save the shroud after smashing through a bullet-proof glass screen with a sledgehammer.</p>
<p>The winding cloth is kept furled up in a silver case to save it from exposure to potentially damaging air pollution or sunlight. It suffered no damage.</p>
<p>About three million people saw the shroud -- which bears the blood-stained image of a crucified man -- the last time it went on display in 1978.</p>
<p>Saldarini said the exposition of the shroud next year did &quot;not intend to take sides in any scientific discussions about this mysterious and haunting ancient cloth&quot;.</p>
<p>Historically, the shroud can be traced no further than 1357 when crusaders were believed to have brought the 4.4 metre by 1.4 metre (14.5 by 4.6 foot) cloth to France from the Middle East.</p>
<p>Damaged by fire in 1532, it has been in Turin for more than 300 years.</p>
<p>Even if the shroud is a fake, scientists remain at pains to explain how the image of the crucified man was imprinted on it.</p>
<p>Some doctors who have examined the cloth are convinced it once held a corpse which had crucifixion wounds.</p>
<p>Saldarini said the Church might be open in the future to new scientific proposals to help determine the age of the shroud but he did not plan to seek new carbon dating tests.</p>
<p>The cardinal, who is the official custodian of the shroud, said it was likely it would go on display again in the year 2000 to mark the start of the third millennium of Christianity.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
