<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="536101" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Annan appeals for safety of Buddha sculptures.</title>
<headline>Annan appeals for safety of Buddha sculptures.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Secretary-General Kofi Annan appealed on Thursday to political and military commanders in Afghanistan to ensure no harm came to giant sculptures of Buddha in the north of the country, a U.N. spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;The secretary-general is deeply disturbed by reports that the great Buddhist sculptures in the province of Bamiyan in Afghanistan may be under threat of destruction in the continuing military operations in the area,&quot; the spokesman said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;He appeals to both the political and military commanders involved to ensure that no harm is done to these priceless sculptures, which have purely historical and cultural significance which should be preserved,&quot; the statement added.</p>
<p>A report from Peshawar, Pakistan, said a U.N. official expressed concern on Wednesday to a representative of Afghanistan's purist Islamic Taleban movement over a threat to destroy the giant statues of Buddha on religious grounds after Taleban captured Bamiyan from the opposition Shi'ite Moslem faction of Hezb-i-Wahdat.</p>
<p>The Taleban was reported to have replied that no decision had been taken on the fate of the statues.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
