<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="536358" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India says to probe cause of haj fire.</title>
<headline>India says to probe cause of haj fire.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>India said on Thursday that a high-level team would visit Saudi Arabia to examine the causes of last week's deadly fire at a haj pilgrimage site and a report that guides had prevented pilgrims from fleeing to safety.</p>
<p>The Foreign Ministry said three members of parliament and a former lawmaker would study the causes of the blaze in which several dozen Indian pilgrims died.</p>
<p>India's ambassador to Saudi Arabia said on Thursday that 55 Indians were confirmed dead after last week's fierce fire at the pilgrimage site where more than 300 people died.</p>
<p>A Foreign Ministry spokesman in New Delhi said 46 of the dead had been identified and 191 injured were in hospital.</p>
<p>Indian newspapers quoted India's consul general in Saudi Arabia as saying Indian victims of the fire could have escaped but that Saudi guides locked them in their compounds instead of letting them flee to safety.</p>
<p>&quot;This matter has been examined very carefully and it is concluded that these views appear to be derived from information provided by a few of the injured relating to the conduct of an individual gate keeper,&quot; the Foreign Ministry said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;No broad generalisations about the tragic accident can be drawn on this basis.&quot;</p>
<p>The Foreign Ministry spokesman, who recently returned from Saudi Arabia after visiting the site, said he had spoken to up to 60 pilgrims and none had mentioned guides shutting gates.</p>
<p>&quot;It is premature to take a view on what caused it and why the casualties were as high as they were,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Asked if it would be unfair to attribute the large number of deaths to guides, the spokesman said: &quot;Yes.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I don't believe we can say it is the fault of anybody,&quot; he said, adding that the compound where the Indians died was surrounded by steep hillocks which prevented escape.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not known if this door was shut or not,&quot; he said. &quot;You will never get a very firm answer one way or another.&quot;</p>
<p>Saudi Arabia said last week that 343 people died and more than 1,500 were injured in the April 15 blaze which raged through 70,000 tents at Mena near the holy city of Mecca.</p>
<p>Witnesses said many victims burnt to death in the fire, others suffocated from the deadly fumes while some were crushed by a stampede as panic gripped the pilgrims.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
