<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="536360" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India concerned at Afghan threat to Buddha statues.</title>
<headline>India concerned at Afghan threat to Buddha statues.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>India on Thursday expressed deep concern at the threat by Afghanistan's fundamentalist Taleban Islamic movement to destroy centuries old giant statues of Buddha.</p>
<p>A statement on behalf of the foreign ministry spokesman said he &quot;expressed deep concern at the reports that the Buddhist relics in Bamiyan in central Afghanistan may deliberately be blown up if they fell into the control of the local Taleban commanders.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The famous Buddhist site in Bamiyan, which has already suffered considerably, was an inheritance for all mankind,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is hoped that all Afghan parties will pay heed to international opnion and refrain from any action which would further damage this priceless inheritance,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>A new threat to Afghanistan's rich cultural heritage -- ideology -- surfaced last week when a commander of the purist Islamic Taleban said that he intended to dynamite two monumental, 1,500-year-old statues of the Buddha in central Afghanistan after capturing Bamiyan from the opposition Shi'ite Moslem faction of Hezb-i-Wahdat.</p>
<p>Commander Ahmadzai told journalists last week: &quot;We will destroy them because Islam has forbidden statues.&quot;</p>
<p>On Wednesday, a U.N. source in Pakistan, which shares borders with Afghanistan and India, said the United Nations had expressed concern to the Taleban over their threat.</p>
<p>The source said the Taleban responded that no decision had yet been yet been taken on the fate of the statues in the central Afghan province of Bamiyan. The Taleban took over Kabul last September and control more than two-thirds of the country.</p>
<p>The source said U.N. official Francis Okelo raised the issue with Mullah Hassan, Taleban governor of the southern Afghan town of Kandahar.</p>
<p>Okelo said no action should be taken against the statues and reminded Hassan of a U.N. General Assembly resolution that called last year for the preservation of monuments and culture in war-shattered Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Hassan told Okelo that &quot;no decision has been taken so far and that it is for the Ulema (Islamic scholars) to decide about the matter&quot;, the source said.</p>
<p>The Taleban, seeking to advance to Bamiyan, have been held at bay by Hezb-i-Wahdat, which is defending the strategic Shibar Pass that controls access to Bamiyan city and opens a route to the opposition-controlled north.</p>
<p>Sr Lanka also joined the campaign against the Taleban threat, appealing to the world community to persuade its Islamic leaders to prevent the destruction of the Buddha statues.</p>
<p>Sri Lankan Foreign Minister Lakshman Kadirgamar and Minister for Religious and Cultural Affairs Lakshman Jayakody had met Colombo representatives of Buddhist and Islamic nations to seek their cooperation to ensure that the statues were not harmed, Sri Lankan officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The two 4th century statues in Bamiyan, one of them the world's tallest standing Buddha, are considered sacred in Sri Lanka, where 70 percent of the population follows Buddhism.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
