<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="537185" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Tanya's still Tucker tough but the scars show.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Tanya's still Tucker tough but the scars show.</headline>
<byline>Barbara Novovitch</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>Country music star Tanya Tucker has a sassy riposte for a Nashville reviewer who dissed her autobiography as &quot;daddy-obsessed&quot; -- &quot;She probably said that 'cause she don't have one as good as mine. I bet my daddy could whip her daddy's ass!&quot;</p>
<p>Author of &quot;Nickel Dreams,&quot; No. 2 on the New York Times best-seller list, and a much-praised new CD, &quot;Complicated,&quot; Tucker at 38 is already a 25-year veteran of the country music industry.</p>
<p>She is no longer the 13-year-old whose daddy barged through doors in Nashville and gambled down to his last $3 in Las Vegas for money to make a pitch to recording executives for the little blonde dynamo with a big, husky voice. But her &quot;Delta Dawn&quot; from 1972 is still her most-requested number.</p>
<p>In a recent interview with Reuters, Tucker said she did the book, published by Hyperion, at the urging of her family and fans, talking into a tape recorder and giving notes to co-writer Patsi Bale Cox. Talking about herself was difficult, she said, and she did not particularly intend for it to be an homage to her father, her longtime manager, whom she praises as &quot;Tucker tough,&quot; but &quot;I'm glad it was perceived that way.&quot;</p>
<p>The CD, on Capitol, is her 30th album, replete with torch songs, rock songs and a new tenderness and maturity that come after her years as country music's hellcat.</p>
<p>AN HONEST ALBUM</p>
<p>Describing &quot;Complicated&quot; as &quot;the most honest album I've done,&quot; she said: &quot;Every song on here I've either experienced it or want to.&quot; On &quot;Wishing It All Away,&quot; whose lyrics seem to be from one lover to another, she said she sang it for her dad, who sometimes pushed her toward the career that she wanted but occasionally was reluctant to work for.</p>
<p>&quot;There's been times when I did wish it all away,&quot; she admitted. In &quot;Nickel Dreams,&quot; she wrote, &quot;Sometimes I feel like I've been on one long bungee jump.&quot;</p>
<p>In the 1970s Tucker was that rarity, a country artist on the cover of Rolling Stone. She was the teen phenomenon who could belt out rockers or put a heartbreaking quiver into ballads.</p>
<p>But fame soon turned into notoriety. In the 1980s her alcohol- and cocaine-fuelled affair with singer/TV host Glen Campbell was weekly gossip fodder for the tabloids, and by the end of the decade she was at the Betty Ford Centre being treated for substance abuse.</p>
<p>Another hit album, with modern classics like &quot;If Your Heart Ain't Busy Tonight&quot; and &quot;Down to My Last Teardrop,&quot; came to the rescue. In 1991, the Country Music Association named her Female Vocalist of the Year, but she could not accept in person because she had just given birth to her second child.</p>
<p>Her daughter, Presley, 7, is named for Elvis, and her son, Beau Grayson, 5, is named for Tucker's father. The childrens' father is Hollywood actor Ben Reed, who she says has a close relationship with them. Tucker has never married.</p>
<p>CRITICISES DAN QUAYLE</p>
<p>In 1992, she was a featured singer at the Republican National Convention and scolded Vice President Dan Quayle for his criticism of single mothers.</p>
<p>When Garth Brooks won a Grammy for Best Country Performance that year, and country music sales were skyrocketing, Tucker lambasted the Grammy Awards for focusing on rock and ignoring &quot;the greatest music in the world.&quot;</p>
<p>Tucker said she knew 25 years ago that country music &quot;was not as big as it ought to be ... but it was just like pulling teeth to get people to believe that, even in country music.&quot;</p>
<p>With the gritty in-your-face honesty for which Tucker is famous, &quot;Nickel Dreams&quot; takes readers along on her journey from trailers in Texas, Utah and Nevada to her current residence, a 25-room colonial mansion outside Nashville with 12 horses and the requisite barns and stables.</p>
<p>She drops plenty of celebrity names along the way -- she dated Don Johnson of &quot;Miami Vice&quot; and &quot;Nash Bridges&quot; when he could barely buy gas for his Volkswagen, and double-dated with O.J. Simpson and his late wife Nicole. At one of the ruptures in the Glen Campbell affair, she ran off with country legend Merle Haggard on his bus.</p>
<p>Although she says Campbell knocked out her two front teeth in one of their well-publicised fights (he denies it), her description of the affair is less harsh than his. &quot;I don't blame Glen any more than myself for any of this,&quot; she wrote, &quot;I'm hot-tempered, and if pushed, I fly off the handle.&quot;</p>
<p>Except for a few concert and charity dates, Tucker said she now is taking more time for herself, her children and her horses. An accomplished amateur at cutting horse competitions, she will try for $200,000 in prize money in December at the Celebrity Cutting Championship astride a mare sired by her favourite horse, a $150,000 palomino named Jesse Ray.</p>
<p>&quot;I just absolutely adore (the horse),&quot; she said with a throaty laugh. &quot;That's who I'd marry if I could get the ring over his hoof!&quot;</p>
<p>For her next albums she wants to venture more into songwriting. &quot;I've got a lot of songs in my head. It's just a matter of setting me down and getting me still enough to do it.&quot;</p>
<p>Tucker said the love affair with a Nashville landscaper mentioned in her book was over and she does not see marriage on the horizon. &quot;I like to be friends,&quot; she confided. &quot;All this rush rush I don't like.&quot;</p>
<p>But she conceded, &quot;It's hard with me not to rush rush -- You don't see me that much. I'm gonna be gone.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
