<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="537277" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Vatican newspaper urges Church respect for gays.</title>
<headline>Vatican newspaper urges Church respect for gays.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>In a startlingly frank article about homosexuality, the Vatican newspaper has urged Roman Catholics to respect gays, saying they too can achieve sanctity in the Church if they abstain from sex.</p>
<p>The article in L'Osservatore Romano broke no new ground on the Church's teaching that, while homosexual tendencies were not wrong, homosexual acts were sinful.</p>
<p>It also repeated the Church teaching that only heterosexual, monogamous marriage was permitted.</p>
<p>But its tone was far more compassionate and accepting of homosexuals than the Church has been in the past.</p>
<p>&quot;God loves all of us as we are, with our limits, our peculiarities, which can become paths to holiness,&quot; the article said.</p>
<p>It was written by Jean-Louis Brugues, a member of the Catholic Church's International Theological Commission.</p>
<p>&quot;One thing is certain: the homosexual person is called, like all others, to see his talents bear fruit and put them to the service of the human community and the building of the kingdom of God,&quot; Brugues wrote.</p>
<p>The article, the last of a 14-part series of reflections on homosexuality and Christianity and published in Wednesday's edition of the paper, was at times stunning in its openness towards gays, calling for the &quot;acceptance of people in their diversity&quot;.</p>
<p>It prompted headlines in the Italian press on Thursday such as one in Rome's La Repubblica: &quot;Chaste gays will be saints.&quot;</p>
<p>The article said gays should have a role in the Church and that role should be a full one, including participation in the sacraments, if they managed to remain chaste.</p>
<p>It said Catholics, including priests, should not show &quot;contempt&quot; for homosexuals but treat them with the same charity as they would other Christians.</p>
<p>A priest who administers to homosexuals must &quot;overcome his fears and perhaps repress his opposition or even the repulsion that homosexuality inspires in him more or less consciously&quot;.</p>
<p>It continued: &quot;Christian communities should be careful to refrain from every expression of contempt toward persons who have this particularity&quot;.</p>
<p>Priests who administer to homosexual Catholics should help them come out of the &quot;ghettos&quot; and take part with other Catholics in political, social and Church life, the article said.</p>
<p>&quot;Every human being without exception is called with his whole being to salvation, not despite of but because of the particular nature of how a personality develops...&quot;</p>
<p>Gay rights groups around the world have for decades urged the Church to accept homosexuals, including those who are sexually active, as full members of the Church.</p>
<p>Arci Gay, Italy's largest homosexual rights group, praised the Vatican for drawing attention to gay rights in the Church but blasted it for continuing to insist that they remain chaste.</p>
<p>&quot;The repeated interventions of the Church are a recognition of the homosexual question but the opinions expressed are heartless and cruel,&quot; said Arci Gay president Franco Grillini.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
