<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="537757" id="root" date="1997-04-24" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan guru denies subway gassing, blames followers.</title>
<headline>Japan guru denies subway gassing, blames followers.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-04-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The guru of the Japanese doomsday cult accused of masterminding the nerve gas attack on the Tokyo subway two years ago said on Thursday he was not guilty and accused his followers of carrying out the attack.</p>
<p>Shoko Asahara also told Tokyo District Court he tried to stop his top followers from carrying out the March 20, 1995, attack which killed 12 people and harmed more than 6,000.</p>
<p>&quot;I ordered (top disciple Hideo) Murai to stop on the night of the 18th and I ordered (senior follower Yoshihiro) Inoue to stop on the 19th but it turned out I lost against them,&quot; Asahara said in his first clear statement in a year-long trial.</p>
<p>Asahara, leader of the Aum Shinri Kyo (Supreme Truth) sect, also said the charge against him in the Tokyo subway case should be one of assault and not murder.</p>
<p>Asahara faces 16 other charges including several other murder charges and the masterminding of a separate nerve gas attack.</p>
<p>&quot;Asahara Shoko has not ordered any of these acts,&quot; Asahara said in what appeared to a plea of not guilty. In Japanese courts defendants are not asked to make clear pleas.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically this should be an assault charge,&quot; he said of the nerve gas attack but did not elaborate.</p>
<p>Murai was assassinated by a &quot;yakuza&quot; gangster in April 1995. Inoue and many other top followers have said Asahara ordered the subway attack and other murders.</p>
<p>After his statement in Japanese Asahara switched to incoherent English. Judge Fumihiro Abe tried unsuccessfully to stop his outburst as the court stenographer and defence lawyers strained to understand what he was saying.</p>
<p>Asahara has been repeatedly removed from court for interrupting the proceedings with incomprehensible statements but the judge gave him a chance on Thursday to enter his plea and add statements.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-04-24"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-04-24"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
