<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568292" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canadian Mounties launch probe of Bre-X fraud.</title>
<headline>Canadian Mounties launch probe of Bre-X fraud.</headline>
<byline>Darren Schuettler</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Royal Canadian Mounted Police launched an official investigation into the Busang gold scandal on Thursday, but experts said solving history's biggest mining swindle would not be easy.</p>
<p>&quot;We're commencing with a preliminary investigation and making some initial inquiries,&quot; RCMP spokeswoman Deleen Schoff said by telephone.</p>
<p>The RCMP, Canada's national police, received two fraud complaints involving Bre-X Minerals Ltd., which had touted Busang as the century's richest gold strike until a consultant said on Sunday there was virtually no gold worth mining at the Indonesian mine and called the case a fraud &quot;without precedent in the history of mining.&quot;</p>
<p>Since then Bre-X's stock -- once valued at over C$6 billion ($4.4 billion) -- has collapsed to pennies a share and more lawsuits have been filed against Calgary, Alberta-based Bre-X. The Toronto Stock Exchange delisted Bre-X on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Schoff would not say if the RCMP had any suspects at this point. &quot;Even if I had names, I couldn't discuss it because it is part of the investigation,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>David Walsh, Bre-X's embattled chief executive, asked the RCMP on Tuesday to investigate an alleged fraud perpetrated against his company, but he did not name a suspect.</p>
<p>A second fraud complaint has been filed by the Ontario Securities Commission, one of Canada's securities regulators. The commission also was investigating Bre-X for possible violations of insider trading and disclosure laws.</p>
<p>Alberta has appointed a special prosecutor to work with the RCMP on the case. Under Canadian law, a conviction for fraud carries a maximum 10-year prison sentence.</p>
<p>Schoff denied a report on Thursday from a Canadian diplomat in Jakarta that an RCMP liaison officer is in Indonesia to discuss the Bre-X case with local authorities.</p>
<p>In Jakarta, Indonesian investigators had begun gathering evidence of possible fraud over Busang.</p>
<p>As the Mounties begin delving into the scandal in Canada, it may be a while before angry Bre-X investors learn the truth about their lost millions of dollars.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a long, complicated investigation,&quot; predicted Joe Neuberger, a Toronto criminal lawyer with experience in securities fraud.</p>
<p>He said the RCMP would likely follow the paper trail of securities filings and test results dating back to when the Busang project was born in 1993. Interviews with those involved in the project were also likely.</p>
<p>&quot;It must have been a well-thought-out fraud. I'm sure they have suspicions as to who is involved, but they are going to have to start with the information they have,&quot; Neuberger said.</p>
<p>Don Holmes, a forensic accountant with Ernst &amp; Young consultants, said he would not expect to find a smoking gun in the Busang documents.</p>
<p>&quot;In terms of what an accountant might look at such as books and records, I'm not convinced initially there would be a lot there in terms of background information,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Rumors about Busang began circulating in March when Bre-X's chief geologist at the Busang site, Michael de Guzman, allegedly jumped to his death from a helicopter while flying to a meeting in Indonesia.</p>
<p>On March 26, Bre-X partner Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold Inc., a big mining company based in New Orleans, said that its preliminary tests found &quot;insignificant&quot; amounts of gold. After that announcement, Bre-X hired Strathcona to conduct a review.</p>
<p>In its report, Strathcona said Bre-X's storage warehouse near the Borneo town of Samarinda, where core samples were kept for a lengthy period of time, was the most likely spot for any tampering.</p>
<p>Walsh has denied any knowledge of tampering and vowed investigators hired by Bre-X will ferret out the culprits.</p>
<p>Bre-X's chief of exploration John Felderhof -- currently at his home in the Cayman Islands -- also has expressed dismay over the tampering at Busang and denied any involvement.</p>
<p>Citing an unnamed source, the Calgary Sun newspaper reported Thursday that Walsh had written Felderhof asking him to resign. Bre-X officials were not available to comment.</p>
<p>Bre-X itself has hired an ex-Mountie and other advisors to find out what happened.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
