<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568291" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Ford chairman defends Associates financial unit.</title>
<headline>Ford chairman defends Associates financial unit.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>WINDSOR, Ontario 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ford Motor Co. Chairman Alex Trotman defended Thursday the company's Associates First Capital Corp. against unethical loan accusations, although he acknowledged there have been some problems.</p>
<p>Trotman tried to focus on Ford's improving core automotive progress at the U.S. No. 2 automaker's annual shareholder meeting here. But he faced several angry questions from people who accused Associates, a consumer finance company, of discrimination and charging excessively high interest rates and fees.</p>
<p>&quot;We are very swift to take action where we find -- and we have found -- instances of people not behaving within the ethic of the company,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>One woman from West Hartford, Conn., said high interest rates and added loan costs caused her to lose her house. The group was organized by a Boston-based non-profit organzation called Neighborhood Assistance Corp. of America, which is a shareholder of Ford.</p>
<p>Ford sold about 20 percent of the Dallas-based Associates in an initial public offering last year. The company, the largest publicly traded finance company in the United States, is part of Ford's Financial Services Group.</p>
<p>Associates earned a record $238 million in the first quarter vs. $192 million a year ago. About 20 percent of its business comes from home mortgages.</p>
<p>Allegations of unethical loan practices were at the center of a recent ABC Prime Time Live television news program. Trotman told reporters after the meeting the program has prompted an internal company audit committee to focus its efforts on how the company makes loans and administers programs.</p>
<p>He stressed Associates, which has 10 million customers and made 1.2 million loans last year, adheres to high ethical standards. The 78-year-old company also has some of the highest consumer satisfaction ratings in the industry, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are millions and millions of very satisfied customers with that company,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In his speech to shareholders, Trotman said Ford's recent positive first quarter results were proof the company was making strides towards being a more competitive global automaker.</p>
<p>Trotman told reporters Ford will &quot;substantially&quot; surpass its cost-cutting goal of $1 billion worldwide in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;Quality, cost and speed is the name of the game,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ford's 1997 annual meeting was the first time it was held outside of the United States since the company became publicly traded in 1956.</p>
<p>Ford has more than 5,000 employees at five plants in Windsor. The city, across the Detroit River from Detroit, was where Ford of Canada was formed in 1904.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WINDSOR, Ontario"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
