<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568384" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX complex gains as gasoline leads the way.</title>
<headline>NYMEX complex gains as gasoline leads the way.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Crude oil futures rose sharply Thursday in a largely technical move, sparked by indications gasoline demand was firming up ahead of the Memorial Day weekend at the end of May.</p>
<p>Gasoline futures for June delivery rose 1.58 cents to 62.50 cents a gallon. June crude futures rose 72 cents to $20.34 a barrel.</p>
<p>Heating oil June futures gained 1.3 cents to settle at 54.38 cents a gallon.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically, I think a lot of traders were looking at the 59.25 level (for gasoline), where 'buy' support held,&quot; said Gerry Samuels a trader for ARB Oil in California. &quot;But we've been in a very wide and choppy range for a month and a half...(and) even with today's activity we didn't have a difinitive breakout.&quot;</p>
<p>The same view of the market was echoed by other traders and analysts.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see this as a major technical breakout at this point,&quot; said a Texas trader. &quot;So far, we're still stuck in the ranges (and for future direction) I'm guessing 'down' in the long term.&quot;</p>
<p>The gasoline move started on Wednesday after Department of Energy figures showed a big dip in stocks, which sent prices up and triggered stop-less 'buy' orders, traders said. That buying carried through in Thursday's market, though there was little evidence in the cash market of a strong seasonal uptick in buying, according to traders of physical gasoline.</p>
<p>There was little fundamental news to give the market clear direction, traders said.</p>
<p>Several of the seven OPEC oil ministers at an oil conference in Iran -- though not all-important Saudi Arabia, nor Iraq, United Arab Emirates, Algeria -- renewed their call for quota compliance on Thursday.</p>
<p>However, one of the ministers calling for quota compliance was Nigeria, one of the biggest cheaters with production in April over 2.11 million bpd in April, compared with a quota of 1.865 million bpd, according to a Reuter survey of oil companies and industry analysts.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't remember a time in the last few years when there has been less fundamental news to give the market clear direction,&quot; said Samuels of ARB.</p>
<p>There was no suggestion from the OPEC ministers of substantive action to be taken to enforce quota compliance and several ministers said they expect a rollover of the official 25.03 million bpd OPEC ceiling when the ministers next meet on June 25.</p>
<p>The Reuter survey estimated wellhead production by OPEC in April at 27.05 million bpd.</p>
<p>-- New York Energy Desk, + 1 212 859 1620</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
