<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568301" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canadian bonds open weaker in wake of poor auction.</title>
<headline>Canadian bonds open weaker in wake of poor auction.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian bonds opened weaker on Thursday as the impact of Wednesday's poorly received auction of 10-year Government of Canada bonds continued to weigh on prices, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We were much lower when we opened up. There's still a bad taste left from yesterday's auction,&quot; said Harvinder Kalirai, Canadian analyst with financial analysis firm I.D.E.A.</p>
<p>Canada's 30-year benchmark bond fell C$0.15 to C$109.65 to yield 7.176 percent. The U.S. 30-year bond rose 2/32 to yield 6.96 percent. The spread between the two bonds widened to 22 basis points from 19 basis points at Wednesday's close.  </p>
<p>Canadian bonds fell sharply on Wednesday after the Canadian government said its C$2.4 billion auction of 7.25 percent bonds due June 1, 2007 produced an average yield of 6.66 percent, with a low yield of 6.639 percent and high yield of 6.700 percent.</p>
<p>Dealers said the auction's tail, the difference between high and average yield, was the highest in recent memory and was an indication of poor demand.</p>
<p>Canadian bonds did pare some of their earlier losses this morning on renewed strength in U.S. Treasuries, analysts said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We've pared our losses and I think that really has to do with the fact that the Fed did a coupon pass so Treasuries sort of picked up and Canada has really followed suit,&quot; said Kalirai.</p>
<p>In other prices, Canada's 10-year benchmark bonds fell C$0.05 to C$102.45 to yield 6.648 percent. The U.S. bond fell 1/32 to yield 6.76 percent.</p>
<p>The negative spread between the bonds narrowed to 11 basis points from 12 basis points on Wednesday.  </p>
<p>((Jeffrey Hodgson (416) 941-8105, e-mail:</p>
<p>jeffrey.hodgson@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
