<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568302" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Russel responds to hostile shareholder bid.</title>
<headline>Russel responds to hostile shareholder bid.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russel Metals Inc responded on Thursday to a hostile takeover bid by a Russel shareholder in a letter seeking support for the slate of directors nominated by management.</p>
<p>In a letter to shareholders, Russel Chairman and Chief Executive John Pelton urged investors not to support the dissident slate of directors nominated by shareholder Paros Enterprises Ltd, the personal investment company of K. Rai Sahi and his wife.</p>
<p>Sahi also owns a 26-percent stake in Acklands Ltd, where he is chairman and chief executive.  </p>
<p>The election of directors is slated for the company's May 14 annual meeting. Paros owns about 7.8 percent of Russel's outstanding shares.</p>
<p>&quot;Rather than choosing individuals who would be truly independent of Mr. Sahi's personal interests, why has he nominated a dissident slate comprising 11 people of whom at least seven are related to Acklands Ltd,&quot; Pelton said in the letter.</p>
<p>&quot;He also has not stated... what his strategy or plan would be. He sould tell us why he has not disclosed his plans, if he has any, for the company,&quot; Pelton added.  </p>
<p>Pelton told shareholders that &quot;the kind of wholesale change of the Board that Mr. Sahi is proposing is unnecessary and would impair the progress the company has achieved.&quot;</p>
<p>He said current Russel management is expanding its profitable U.S. trading operations, reducing fixed cost and debt and &quot;aggressively pursuing the divestiture of all remaining non-core assets for maximum value.&quot;</p>
<p>The letter asked shareholders to consider why Sahi did not make an offer to take over the company.</p>
<p>&quot;Consider that Mr. Sahi is attempting to take control of your company without paying you for it,&quot; Pelton said.</p>
<p>((Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8100))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I61000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
