<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568310" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Foundation to buy Physicians for $280 million.</title>
<headline>Foundation to buy Physicians for $280 million.</headline>
<byline>Andrea Orr</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foundation Health Systems Inc., the country's fourth-biggest managed care company, said Thursday it agreed to buy Physicians Health Services Inc. for about $280 million in cash.</p>
<p>Foundation, based in Rancho Cordova, Calif., said the purchase will advance its strategy of extending its reach into the Northeast, particularly the valuable New York City region.</p>
<p>Foundation said it will pay $29.25 a share for Physicians, using a combination of cash on hand and bank debt. The deal is expected to close at the end of the year.</p>
<p>Foundation has made a series of acquisitions in Connecticut since 1995, and the purchase of Physicians Health, will expand its membership base by 440,000 members. About 65 percent of those members are in Connecticut and most of the rest are in New York City and surrounding suburbs.</p>
<p>The New York market's potential for expansion is significant not only because of its huge population but because the area has been one of the slowest in the country to adopt the managed care style of health care.</p>
<p>Foundation has demonstrated a facility for rapidly expanding the membership of companies it acquired. Since 1995, when it purchased M.D. Health Plan in Connecticut, for instance, Foundation has increased that plan's enrollment more than threefold.</p>
<p>Foundation spokesman Kurt Davis said the company hoped to do the same with Physicians Health.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe this gives us a good foothold in a relatively unpenetrated market,&quot; said Davis. &quot;The New York metropolitan area is obviously an area of oppportunity, especially relative to where we're from. The market penetration in California is quite high.&quot;</p>
<p>Unlike California, where close to 50 percent of the total population and 70 percent of the insured population belong to health maintenance organizations, the Northeast has been slow to shift to managed care. By most estimates less than 25 percent of that region's poplation is covered by an HMO.</p>
<p>Most analysts said Foundation would be paying a full price for Physicians Health, which has struggled to implement a profitable operating strategy. Last year, the company lost close to $13 million as its premium rates failed to keep up with rising costs.</p>
<p>Physicians Health on Thursday reported a first-quarter profit of $646,000, or 7 cents a share, far surpassing the consensus analyst forecast for a loss of 7 cents a share posted by First Call. It compared with a profit of $866,000, or 9 cents a share, in the first quarter of 1996.</p>
<p>Last year, Physicians Health had revenues of $482 million.</p>
<p>Foundation also said that, as part of the deal, it entered into a voting agreement with Greater Bridgeport Individual Practice Association Inc., which owns a majority of the voting power of Physicians.</p>
<p>Foundation was formed by the April 1 merger of Foundation Health Corp. and Health Systems International Inc. It projects 1997 revenues at nearly $9 billion.</p>
<p>Physicians Health's stock gained 69 cents to $27.625 in afternoon trading on the Nasdaq market, while Foundation Health dipped 12.5 cents to $26.875 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I95100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
