<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568300" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Ford expects to beat '97 cost goal.</title>
<headline>Ford expects to beat '97 cost goal.</headline>
<dateline>WINDSOR, Ontario 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ford Motor Co Chairman and Chief Executive Officer Alex Trotman said Thursday the company expects to beat its 1997 cost-cutting goal of $1 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we'll certainly be substantially north of a billion dollars,&quot; Trotman told reporters following the company's annual shareholder meeting.</p>
<p>Ford cut $800 million in the first quarter from year-ago cost levels.  But Trotman cautioned the company will not be able to save that much on a quarterly basis for the rest of the year.  </p>
<p>Trotman also said the U.S. No. 2 automaker expects the 1998 U.S. total vehicle industry to be in the range of 15.25 million to 15.5 million vehicles, roughly similar to estimates for 1997.  Trotman said his forecast is based on predictions the U.S. economy will continue to grow at a rate of about three percent, with inflation staying in the range of 2.5 percent to three percent.</p>
<p>At the meeting, Trotman acknowledged Ford has found ethical problems among employees of its Associates First Capital Inc affiliate.  But he defended the company's lending practices and customer satisfaction ratings.  </p>
<p>Trotman told reporters that a recent ABC Prime Time Live television news program alleging ethical problems at the Dallas-based company has prompted an internal company audit committee to refocus its efforts on how the company makes loans and administers programs.</p>
<p>&quot;We are very swift to take action where we find -- and we have found -- instances of people not behaving within the ethic of the company,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Several loan customers told Trotman that high interest rates and fees charged by the Associates had forced them into financial ruin, including loss of their homes.  </p>
<p>The group was organized by a non-profit organzation called Neighborhood Assistance Corp of America, which is a shareholder of Ford.</p>
<p>Ford sold about 20 percent of the Associates in an initial public offering last year.  The company is now the largest publicy traded finance company in the U.S.  Trotman said about four percent of Ford's net income comes from Associates home equity loans.</p>
<p>On other matters, Trotman said he is so positive about the potential sales demand for Ford's full-size sport/utility vehicles that he does not believe the current annual capacity of 282,000 units at the firm's Michigan Truck plant in Wayne, Mich., is enough.</p>
<p>However, he said the company probably would not consider expanding full-size sport/utility capacity until demand exceeded about 382,000 units.</p>
<p>Ford's 1997 annual meeting was the first it has held outside of the United States since the company became publicy traded in 1956.  Ford has more than 5,000 employees at five plants in Windsor.  The city, across the Detroit River from Detroit, was where Ford of Canada was formed in 1904.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WINDSOR, Ontario"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
