<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568440" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYC will ask rating agencies to upgrade its credit.</title>
<headline>NYC will ask rating agencies to upgrade its credit.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York City, which expects to follow up this year's record surplus with a $200 million windfall next year, said on Thursday that it plans to ask rating agencies for an upgrade once its budget is approved.</p>
<p>&quot;Once we have adopted a budget with the City Council, the City of New York will be visiting with all three rating agencies to discuss our credit rating and to begin discussing with the rating agencies an upgrade,&quot; said Joseph Lhota, the city budget director.  </p>
<p>New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani earlier proposed a $33.5 billion budget for fiscal 1998, which starts on July 1. Even though Wall Street's big profits are expected to help the city capture its biggest-ever surplus in the present fiscal year--$856 million--the new budget only raises spending around $575 million above last year's accord.</p>
<p>And the state comptroller, H. Carl McCall, while cautioning that the city still has huge, outyear gaps, noted the mayor's new budget plan has less risk.</p>
<p>Still, rating analysts are asking whether the city can keep its economic recovery going and whether the main engine fattening its tax coffers, strong earnings by the financial sector, will continue.</p>
<p>Bob Kurtter, a senior vice president with Moody's Investors Service, said: &quot;Obviously, there are more factors than just good revenue performance. The city still has significant other risks in terms of the state budget, welfare reform at the state level, and all the spending on Medicaid (that will be required). They've got a lot of risk.&quot;</p>
<p>However, he also said the Giuliani Administration had made progress in putting the city's books in order. &quot;The city clearly has got a record of fiscal improvement, they've shown, I think, caution and prudence going forward, by not spending the surplus restoring a lot of money, and the budget is reasonable going forward.&quot;</p>
<p>Standard and Poor's said no rating change was imminent, as it needed to be sure the trend would remain positive. &quot;Despite what is good news clearly in the short-term, where is it going in the longer-term is still a reasonable question, and any change in the rating will hinge on the longer-term, sustainibility of the results we've seen,&quot; said Martin Arrick, a director.</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
