<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568417" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US asks full appeals panel to rehear Cochran case.</title>
<headline>US asks full appeals panel to rehear Cochran case.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. government on Thursday petitioned the U.S. Tenth Circuit Court of Appeals to rehear part of a March 27 ruling that reversed last year's criminal conviction of Oklahoma bond dealer Robert Cochran on wire fraud charges, a Justice Department spokesman said.</p>
<p>A three-member panel of the Tenth Circuit last month unanimously reversed a federal jury conviction of Cochran on eight charges of wire fraud and moneylaundering in connection with bonds issued by two Midwest bond authorities.  </p>
<p>A reliable source told Reuters on May 6 that Justice would ask the court to rehear that part of the decision dealing with Oklahoma City Airport Trust bonds, which were taxable.</p>
<p>The source said Justice will not ask for a new ruling concerning Sisters of St. Mary Healthcare System of St. Louis bonds, which were tax exempt.</p>
<p>The Justice Department spokesman confirmed on Thursday that the department is seeking the rehearing on &quot;some of the issues involved&quot; in the original case.</p>
<p>The three-member panel ruled in March that Cochran did not have to disclose outside fees he got in connection with the two bond offerings because he was not acting in an official capacity for the issuers and, therefore, had no duty to disclose the information.</p>
<p>Cochran was an investment banker in the Oklahoma office of Stifel, Nicolaus &amp; Co at the time of the alleged activities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
