<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568477" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Treasuries end strongly, 10-yr volume soars.</title>
<headline>U.S. Treasuries end strongly, 10-yr volume soars.</headline>
<byline>Alden Bentley</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Treasuries recovered from an early stumble, bounding to a strong finish on Thursday after speculative players went bargain hunting and intra-day shorts ran for cover, dealers said.</p>
<p>A tumbling dollar and talk of a large speculative seller weighed on early trade. But Treasuries soon recovered amid swelling volume, particularly in the 10-year note.</p>
<p>The 30-year bond ended up 13/32 at 96-5/32, while its yield fell to 6.93 percent from 6.96 percent. At its midafternoon peak, the bond was up as much as 20/32.  </p>
<p>&quot;People are saying it's just locals were caught short and are covering and short-term spec accounts are coming in and buying and nothing more, no substantive story that suddenly has changed,&quot; said Josh Stiles, bond market analyst at I.D.E.A. Inc.</p>
<p>Fueling the move up was a techincal rally in the June T-bond contract and reports a large hedge fund bought $1.0 billion worth of 10-year notes in the aftermath of Wednesday's sloppy auction.</p>
<p>The yield on the new 10-year fell to 6.73 percent on Thursday from 6.77 percent on Wednesday.  </p>
<p>&quot;They effectively did distribution at lower prices then had buying come in for $1.0 billion and the market just traded up,&quot; said Mead Briggs, proprietary trading manager at Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
<p>Trading volume in the new 10-year note was more than $7.1 billion on Thursday, the highest level recorded in 1996 and 1997 for a 10-year note, according to GovPX.</p>
<p>&quot;Also worth noting is overall volume was average, making the level in the 10-year that much more interesting,&quot; said Maureen Mooney, an analyst at GovPX.  </p>
<p>The tone of the market was helped as the June bond scrambled above technical resistance at 109-14 and 109-22.</p>
<p>There was also talk of large selling of mortgage bonds for Treasuries. Even the Fed helped out by buying coupons in five and 10-year notes.</p>
<p>With Thursday's schedule devoid of any major economic releases, dealers were focusing in on a speech by Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve Chairman, to be delivered at 2030 EDT/0030 GMT in New York.</p>
<p>Bombshells or further warnings about irrational exuberence in stocks are not expected from the Fed chief, analysts said.  </p>
<p>Traders, however, will be cocking their heads to hear if Greenspan hints which way Fed policy-makers are leaning going into their May 20 meeting.</p>
<p>Though Wall Street forecasters generally expect the Fed to raise the fed funds rate another 25 basis points to 5.75 percent, investors said the very short end is not discounting a move.</p>
<p>Investors said fed fund futures and the yield on the 91-day T-bill, which  has fallen to around 5.20 percent from around 5.40 percent earlier in the year, clearly show the money markets do not expect the Fed will go.  </p>
<p>&quot;The only thing now that could possibly push them over the edge is the stock market is soaring. If you've got to raise rates to cool the stock market, I suppose now is the time to do it,&quot; said Hugh Johnson, chief investment officer at First Albany Corp.</p>
<p>&quot;Even then, I just don't see that being in the cards,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials soared again rising almost 130 points at one point on Thursday. The average closed up 50.97 and traders said sentiment in the bond and stock markets seem to be swinging the same way.  </p>
<p>Elsewhere, the five-year note ended up 6/32 at 100-05/32. The three-year rose 4/32 to 99-24/32.</p>
<p>As for the front end, three- and six-month bills each fell three basis points to 5.07 percent and 5.31 percent, respectively. The year-bill was down two basis points at 5.59 percent.</p>
<p>((--212 859 1667))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
