<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568434" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Employee Solutions named in holder suit.</title>
<headline>Employee Solutions named in holder suit.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lawyers for the purchasers of Employee Solutions Inc common stock during an almost two-year period said a class action complaint has been filed accusing the company of inflating its reported earnings.</p>
<p>The complaint accuses the company of violating federal securities laws by charging and collecting excess federal and state unemployment taxes from customers beyond what they were required to pay.</p>
<p>Then, the complaint alleges, the company illegally included this money in its reported earnings.  </p>
<p>The complaint also accuses the company of failing to establish and maintain adequate reserves for potential workers' compensation insurance claims.</p>
<p>The complaint was filed by Pomerantz Haudek Block &amp; Grossman and Dalton Gotto Samson &amp; Kilgard PLC in the United States District Court for the District of Arizona (Phoenix).</p>
<p>The attorneys said the complaint represents purchasers of stock between March 24, 1995 and March 17, 1997.</p>
<p>The complaint was filed against the company, its chief executive and its chief financial officer</p>
<p>The lawyers said they learned of the issue when the company released on March 17 its financial results for the fourth quarter and full year ended December 31, 1996.</p>
<p>The plaintiffs seek to recover damages.</p>
<p>Several similar lawsuits have been previously filed against the company, which has said that the complaints have no merit and that it would defend itself vigorously.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83954">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
