<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568570" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Novellus aims for 15-pct rise in revs.</title>
<headline>Novellus aims for 15-pct rise in revs.</headline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Novellus Systems Inc Chief Executive Officer Richard Hill said the company is aiming to increase after-tax profits by more than 16 percent and boost revenues by 15 percent a year.</p>
<p>&quot;We're going to drive the business to achieve the business model,&quot; he said in a conference call discussing the company's $150 million acquisition of Varian Associates Inc's Thin Film Systems business. &quot;Our goal is pretty simple, we'd like to get greater than 16 percent after-tax profit, we want to continue our top line growth year in and year out of at least 15 percent per year,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Novellus shares shot up as high as 83-3/4 after Hill's comments and were trading at midafternoon at 82, up 3-1/2. The shares had opened on a weaker tone, falling as low as 76, on investor concerns following the merger news over the financial impact of the merger and assimilation of the new unit.</p>
<p>But Hill said the deal was priced favorably at around 1.0 times revenues, and he provided assurances that &quot;we're not acquisition crazy.  We're not running around going to look and see what else we can acquire.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;Novellus is a financially driven company to see this as an accretive transaction for our shareholders,&quot; he said, adding he expects to exploit synergy in the field service organization, research and development and administration activities.  &quot;We feel this Thin Film Systems acquisition not only meets our strategic acquisition, but it's also financially beneficial to our shareholders.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The overall financial success is our ability to gain market share with the new products that are just coming out with the Thin Film Systems business,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Hill said the acquisition allows the company to provide a fully integrated device interconnect -- the wiring within a semiconductor which represents more than half of steps required to make advanced logic chips.</p>
<p>The new Thin Film Systems products address concerns about what he called &quot;micro-contamination&quot; in regard to the high levels of air purity required in the so-called clean rooms where semiconductors are manufactured.  The products are aimed at leading edge geometries of around 0.18 microns and below -- the measure of the semiconductor circuit resolution which has become increasingly minute in recent years.  </p>
<p>By contrast, Intel Corp has begun production at 0.35 micron for its newly-introduced Pentium II chips but will move towards 0.18 micron for its microprocessors as well in coming years.</p>
<p>Novellus had previously said it expected to complete the transaction within 45 days.  Hill said John Chenault, the Novellus Executive responsible for merging the Thin Film Systems group into the Novellus culture, is one of the company's most seasoned executives.</p>
<p>&quot;The major challenge in any acquisition is merging the cultures and we put our best man at their disposal to help lead this transition,&quot; he said, adding Novellus has frozen new hiring to make opportunities at Novellus available to some of the 450 former Varian employees as well.</p>
<p>&quot;The (Thin Film Systems) business right now is at break-even or slightly profitable, and it's a very down market right now,&quot; he said, adding it will soon be launching &quot;a whole slate of new products.&quot;</p>
<p>Hill said he believes the combined company together will have &quot;probably the largest intellectual property portfolio in the industry.&quot;</p>
<p>((sam.perry@reuters.com, Palo Alto Bureau 415 846 5400))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34350">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34420">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
