<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568503" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NY precious metals end higher across board.</title>
<headline>NY precious metals end higher across board.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>COMEX and NYMEX precious metals futures ended higher Thursday, with all contracts in the complex gaining, but volumes were only moderate.</p>
<p>&quot;It's starting to look positive, with the sharply lower U.S. dollar today helping to break gold and silver out of recent ranges, despite some producer selling overnight,&quot; Refco economist James Steel said.</p>
<p>Other analysts said the market remains convinced another European central bank gold sale, or swap-related transaction has occurred, and the way the gold market has been able to absorb it provided the encouragement for Thursday's rally.  </p>
<p>COMEX June gold ended up $2.40 an ounce at $344.80, after the contract climbed to a session high at $346.60 intraday, the highest level since April 15. Estimated total volume for COMEX gold was moderate at 35,000 lots.</p>
<p>In the bullion market, spot gold ended quoted $343.50/00, after climbing over $345.00 intraday for the first time in a month. In London Thursday afternoon spot gold fixed at $343.75 compared to the New York close Wednesday around $341.00/50.</p>
<p>COMEX June gold had been trapped in a $340-345 range for nearly a month, after sliding to contract lows at $339.50 on April 16.</p>
<p>But fund shortcovering, and robust physical demand have helped provide a floor in the past 10 days, while the dollar's sharp slide overnight made gold cheaper for investors and fabricators in other currencies, analysts said. The price of gold in yen terms fell to its lowest levels since January Thursday.</p>
<p>The strength of the U.S. dollar against yen in particular has been partly to blame for gold's slide to four year lows earlier this year.</p>
<p>The recovery in gold equity prices this week was also a leading indicator for the price of gold as a commodity, analysts said.</p>
<p>The Philadelphia Stock Exchange's gold and silver stocks index and options contract (.XAU) saw its highest level in six weeks Thursday at 105.80.</p>
<p>&quot;Its mostly technical, with the breakout of the recent range in gold and the strength of gold equities helping, but it's starting to look better for gold,&quot; Chase Manhattan New York managing director, Dinsa Mehta said.</p>
<p>Daily momentum indicators for COMEX June gold had turned positive for the first time in nearly two months, analysts noted.</p>
<p>A standard nine-day relative strength index (RSI) edged back up above 50 percent Thursday for the first time since early March, while a standard 13 and 26 day moving-average convergence-divergence (MACD) indicator turned positive for the first time since mid-March.</p>
<p>But silver was even stronger than gold Thursday, with the spot gold/silver index slipping to 71.1:1, after seeing a two month high at 73.5 in early April.</p>
<p>COMEX July silver ended up 10.2 cents at $4.860 an ounce, after seeing a six week high at $4.880 intraday, after a break of the $4.70-4.80 range of the past 10-days. Estimated total volume for COMEX silver Thursday was modest at 12,000 lots.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, platinum group metals (PGMs) also managed to gain, despite news Russia may be close to resuming exports of platinum and palladium which have been disrupted since December 1996 due to fiscal and administrative problems in Moscow.</p>
<p>NYMEX July platinum ended up $6.60 at $379.50 an ounce, while the July/October platinum spread contracted to 50 cents, and the October NYMEX platinum/COMEX gold spread edged up to $30.20 an ounce.</p>
<p>NYMEX June palladium ended up $2.90 at $157.90, with short term implied lease rates in the physical market jumping to around 20 percent, from around 12 percent Wednesday, reflecting ongoing tightness in the prompt market.</p>
<p>Officials of Russia's platinum group metal export agency, Almaz, said Thursday that the decree authorizing Russia's export quotas for PGMs had been signed Monday this week and exports could resume in late May or early June.</p>
<p>Russia supplies about 60 percent of the world's palladium and about 25 percent of its platinum. Japan and the U.S. are the world's two biggest consumers of PGMs which are used mostly in pollution control devices in automobiles and in semi-conductors in the computer industry.</p>
<p>email: clive.mckeef@reuters.com ((Clive McKeef, New York Commodities Desk, 212-859-1641))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
