<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568523" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PETsMART comfortable with Q2 EPS estimates $0.09.</title>
<headline>PETsMART comfortable with Q2 EPS estimates $0.09.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>PETsMART Inc said Thursday it is comfortable with earnings estimates of $0.09 a share for its second quarter and $0.55 a share for fiscal 1998.</p>
<p>Late Wednesday the retailer said net income from operations for its first quarter would be about $0.05 a share, below the First Call consensus estimate of $0.08 a share.</p>
<p>&quot;We're comfortable with the $0.09 estimate for the second quarter and ... we are comfortable with $0.55 a share (for the year),&quot; chief financial officer Susan Schnabel told Reuters in an interview.  </p>
<p>In its statement Wednesday the company said it experienced a number of problems during the first quarter including inventory management, a slump in sales of flea and tick products as well as unsuccessful advertising activities.</p>
<p>Analysts said the biggest factor behind the weaker than expected earnings was badly managed inventories which accounted for about two-thirds of the earnings shortfall.</p>
<p>&quot;We made some misguided decisions in hindsight,&quot; Schnabel said. &quot;Everyone clearly has one mission in life and that is to solve the problem.&quot;  </p>
<p>Schnabel admitted that management was distracted from the day-to-day running of the company.</p>
<p>&quot;There have been allegations that management was too busy on integrating acquisitions and I would be deceiving you if I told you management wasn't doing that,&quot; she said adding that management needs to focus itself on basics.</p>
<p>&quot;It certainly is being addressed and agressively addressed.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
