<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568569" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Oppenheimer in talks on being bought - source.</title>
<headline>Oppenheimer in talks on being bought - source.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Privately held Oppenheimer &amp; Co Inc is in talks on being acquired, an Oppenheimer source said.</p>
<p>The talks on a takeover were in the preliminary stages, said the source, with no announcement imminent.</p>
<p>&quot;Anyone who doesn't know that brokerage firms are the object of interest at the moment has been living inside the Arctic Circle,&quot; said the source, a senior executive at the firm. &quot;It's a fair conclusion to say we are being talked to.&quot;</p>
<p>An Oppenheimer spokesman said the firm had no comment on a Wall Street Journal report that it was in talks to be acquired by PNC Bank Corp.  A PNC spokesman declined comment.  </p>
<p>Another Oppenheimer source said the buyer was not expected to be PNC.</p>
<p>The newspaper reported that Fleet Financial Group Inc would review Oppenheimer's books in the next several weeks.  Fleet officials were not immediately available.</p>
<p>Oppenheimer managing directors were planning to discuss future plans at a previously scheduled meeting on May 20.</p>
<p>The price for Oppenheimer reported in the Journal, up to $500 million, is about 1.6 times book value.  </p>
<p>That figure is significantly less than the range of 2.5-times book value in the deal for Bankers Trust New York Corp to acquire Alex. Brown Inc, said an arbitrageur who declined to be identified.</p>
<p>&quot;I have always heard they were on the block,&quot; said the arb. &quot;All the brokerage firms are going to get taken over. Banks want to get into this business.  Bigger is better and the banks can provide the necessary capital.  For many brokerage firms, it is their only exit strategy.&quot;</p>
<p>On Wednesday, rumors ran through the market that J.P. Morgan &amp; Co Inc and Chase Manhattan Corp were looking at Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc.  Lehman denied the reports.</p>
<p>One analyst, who discounted the speculation, valued Lehman at 1.5 times book value in a takeover, or $50 to $55 per share, the arb said.  Lehman shares rose 3/8 to 38-1/8.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
