<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568542" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYC proposes less risky new budget -- state official.</title>
<headline>NYC proposes less risky new budget -- state official.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York State's comptroller said Thursday the new, fiscal 1998 budget proposed by New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani has less risk, but warned that big out-year gaps still were a problem.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear from the budget released today that structural imbalance persists and the size of the outyear gaps remains substantial,&quot; said H. Carl McCall in prepared remarks.  </p>
<p>Nor was the lack of structural balance the only potential threat to the city's finances.</p>
<p>McCall added, &quot;Moreover, the mayor's budget proposal indicates that the city is counting on significant, increased aid from Albany, which the city may not, in fact, receive. Going forward, the Council and Mayor must be careful not to spend money the city does not have.&quot;</p>
<p>However, he praised the Republican mayor for recognizing that surging profits on Wall Street, which drove tax collections sharply higher in fiscal 1997, producing an estimated $856 million surplus, might not continue in fiscal 1998.</p>
<p>This means the city needs to raise productivity as well as steadily grow revenues, McCall said, and not rely on one-shots or nonrecurring measures.</p>
<p>And the fiscal monitor, a Democrat and potential candidate for governor in next year's election, also commended Giuliani for using the city's biggest ever surplus to prepay debt service in fiscal 1998, which starts on July 1.</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
