<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568596" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: America Online, ABC Sports in new Website.</title>
<headline>America Online, ABC Sports in new Website.</headline>
<dateline>DULLES, Va. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>America Online said Thursday that it will produce an ABC Sports area on its Sports Channel space on the Internet.</p>
<p>The agreement, said the company, further expands the relationship between AOL and ABC, a unit of Walt Disney Co, which earlier this year agreed to include an ABC News Website on AOL.</p>
<p>AOL said the ABC Sports area will give AOL members exclusive online access to ABC's coverage of major sporting events while offering innovative sponsorship and advertising opportunities for both companies.  </p>
<p>The companies will work together to create integrated on-air/online advertising packages, and broadcast programming will be packaged with advertising in the AOL area.</p>
<p>And in a media innovation unique to AOL, said the company, sponsors will have the opportunity to purchase packages including combinations of broadcast network commercials, online advertising and electronic commerce. Online, an advertiser will have the ability to purchase general advertising or sponsor a specific aspect of the site, as well as to allow users to order merchandise from their screens.</p>
<p>While the content for the site is still under development, said AOL, potential activities under the agreement include not only continually updated statistics and commentator analysis but instant online polls during the event.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83940">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DULLES, Va."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
