<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568502" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: EVEREN open to acquisitions, alliances.</title>
<headline>EVEREN open to acquisitions, alliances.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>EVEREN Capital Corp is considering a variety of ways to expand its asset base and diversify its business mix, including acquisitions, alliances or joint ventures, the company's chief executive said.  </p>
<p>In an interview, EVEREN Chairman and Chief Executive James Boris said the company was looking for growth opportunities internally and externally and was keeping a close eye on the pace of consolidation in the financial services industry.</p>
<p>&quot;It's clear the landscape is continuing to change,&quot; Boris said. &quot;We'd be pretty open-minded about either making acquisitions or, if necessary, joint ventures or alliances.&quot;</p>
<p>One of EVEREN's goals is to shrink the firm's reliance on the volatile retail brokerage business for its revenues, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We have traditionally gotten about 80 percent of our revenue mix from retail brokerage,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Over time, EVEREN would like that percentage to shrink to 60 percent, he said, with 30 percent of revenues coming from capital markets business and 10 percent from asset management.</p>
<p>For that reason, EVEREN, which acquired a 20 percent stake in Mentor Investment Group, the asset management unit of Wheat First Butcher Singer, would consider adding a another small asset management outfit by way of acquisition.</p>
<p>But Boris said the firm is in no particular hurry to make a purchase.  </p>
<p>&quot;The market is pretty rich and multiples are pretty high right now,&quot; he said. &quot;I don't see a lot of pressure to move quickly.&quot;</p>
<p>Boris said EVEREN was not involved in any such talks at the current time and added that, despite the flurry of announced and rumored mergers in the industry, the firm would not hurry to strike a deal of its own, particularly regarding a link-up with a much larger U.S. or international outfit.</p>
<p>&quot;We would be very open-minded, but we're also going to be pretty cautious,&quot; he said. &quot;Maybe we're more acutely aware, because of our Kemper experience, what mistakes can be made.&quot;</p>
<p>EVEREN separated from Kemper Corp, its former parent company, via an employee buy-out in September 1995 and completed an initial public offering in October 1996.</p>
<p>Kemper is now owned by Swiss insurer Zurich Insurance Co.</p>
<p>((-- R. Melville, Wall Street desk, 212-859-1731))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
