<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568510" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. debt futures end higher after steadily rising.</title>
<headline>U.S. debt futures end higher after steadily rising.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. debt futures closed higher, but the market resorted to technical factors, rather than any fresh data or news, for its gains into the close, traders and analysts said.</p>
<p>The ability of June T-bonds to hold chart support at 108-30/32 at the opening attracted a consistent stream of retail buyers, they said. The 108-30/32 level roughly corresponded to a long bond yield of seven percent, some said.</p>
<p>&quot;This was just the kind of market that day traders got chewed to bits,&quot; one bond futures analyst said. &quot;They kept finding reasons for selling this market.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;Retail investors were lured into the market at the seven percent level,&quot; he said, referring to the 108-30/32 level.</p>
<p>Some traders also noted short-covering and fund buying, particularly in the note sector, for the market's steady march higher all day.</p>
<p>The U.S. weekly jobless claims, which rose higher than expected, coupled with the Federal Reserve's coupon pass, added to the constructive tone.</p>
<p>However, traders said shorts were established earlier in the day due to concerns about the dollar and the fate of the U.S. balanced-budget agreement.  </p>
<p>Several traders also noted the rally in the Commodity Research Bureau Index led some pit and local traders to increase short positions.</p>
<p>&quot;They really kept fighting the buying,&quot; another bond futures trader said.</p>
<p>Several bond futures sources said the gains could continue on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think enough weak longs liquidated during Wednesday's selloff,&quot; one bond trader said.</p>
<p>The next resistance level is at the 200-day moving average of 110-03/32.  </p>
<p>At the end of pit trade, June T-bonds were up 16/32 at 109-26/32, 10-year notes were up 08/32 at 107-02/32, September T-bills were up 0.005 at 94.435, September Eurodollars were up 0.005 at 93.845, and December Eurodollars were 0.015 at 93.625. ((Derivatives desk 312-408-8750)</p>
<p>E-mail derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
