<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568552" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYC bar urges curb on pay-to-play before SEC acts.</title>
<headline>NYC bar urges curb on pay-to-play before SEC acts.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>If municipal bond lawyers do not take steps to halt pay-to-play in their business, the SEC may do it for them, the head of New York City's prestigious bar association warned lawyers meeting here Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The abuses are out there for all of us to see,&quot; Michael Cardozo, president of Association of the Bar of the City of New York, said at a meeting of National Association of Bond Lawyers.</p>
<p>&quot;The question is whether we, as the legal profession, will do something about it. Plainly put, if we don't do it, the Securities and Exchange Commission may do it for us,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>An audience participant asked Cardozo what steps the SEC could take considering that bond lawyers are not directly regulated by the agency.</p>
<p>&quot;Since the SEC regulates public filings, they could, for example, say they are not going to approve a (disclosure) filing signed by lawyers that make political contributions to issuers,&quot; Cardozo said.</p>
<p>SEC currently is barred from collecting official statements and other bond documents from municipal bond issuers. But some lawyers say that eventually that restriction on SEC could be lifted by Congress.  </p>
<p>Cardozo's group wants the American Bar Association to endorse a rule it approved last year to bar muni lawyers that solicit or make contributions to muni clients from engaging in bond business for two years with those governments.</p>
<p>But the chairmen of several ABA panels, including Lawrence Fox, head of ABA's Standing Committee on Ethics, oppose the NYC bar rule.</p>
<p>Fox's panel last month sent a letter to the chairs of all ABA standing committees and sections urging the officials to reject the City bar's initiative when delegates vote on it at ABA's annual meeting in August.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
