<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568557" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: ReliaStar sets 1997 goal of 13 pct EPS jump.</title>
<headline>ReliaStar sets 1997 goal of 13 pct EPS jump.</headline>
<dateline>MINNEAPOLIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>ReliaStar Financial Corp said Thursday the company has a 1997 goal of an increase in earnings per share close to 13 percent over last year's $4.60 a share.</p>
<p>&quot;Our overall objective is for an average increase in earnings per share of 13 percent in each of three years,&quot; John Turner, ReliaStar chief executive, told Reuters after the annual shareholder meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;If you look back over the last two years, if we're going to make our three-year average, 1997 has to be close to a 13 percent increase over last year's $4.60 (EPS),&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>According to First Call, the consensus of analysts' earnings estimates is $5.16 a share for 1997.</p>
<p>Turner said the company would begin its previously announced share buyback after it has completed its acquisition of Security-Connecticut Corp at the end of June.</p>
<p>&quot;We anticipate the U.S. Security and Exchange Commission approving the shelf registration in a short period and our securing the financing in the second quarter,&quot; Turner said.</p>
<p>&quot;We haven't decided whether we're going to go retail or institutional, and we haven't decided whether the buyback will be done quickly or gradually,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;But it won't start until the close on Security-Connecticut, which if I had to guess, would be between June 25 and June 30,&quot; Turner said.</p>
<p>On February 24, ReliaStar said it agreed to acquire Security-Connecticut in a stock-for-stock transaction valued at $488 million. ReliaStar said it plans to repurchase up to $100 million of its common stock as part of the deal.</p>
<p>Turner said more acquisitions were likely over the next two years.</p>
<p>&quot;It's possible, even likely, that there will be another acquisition or two to help with economies of scale,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We'd be looking for those acquisitions over the next 12 to 24 months of life insurance companies, with a heavy emphasis on the individual life and annuity business, the retail side of the business,&quot; Turner said after the meeting.</p>
<p>ReliaStar's chief operating officer John Flittie told Reuters that in the employee benefits business, the company would continue to emphasize group life sales and de-emphasize group health sales.</p>
<p>&quot;We sell group health as an accommdation now. We don't care if we sell any,&quot; Flittie said. &quot;The key is sales of group life insurance, which in the first quarter were up 43 percent over last year's record pace. Our sales people are actively discouraged from selling group health.&quot;</p>
<p>In the first quarter 1997, group health sales fell 49 percent, the company said.</p>
<p>In 1996, employee group life sales increased 89 percent to $43.5 million while employee group health sales fell 35 percent to $32.1 million.</p>
<p>Flittie said the company expects a &quot;very very strong year in the sale of annuities&quot;. Annuity sales increased 25 percent in the first quarter after contracting four percent in 1996 to $643.3 million.</p>
<p>((--Chicago newsdesk, 312-408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINNEAPOLIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
