<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568566" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Finish Line April same-store sales up.</title>
<headline>Finish Line April same-store sales up.</headline>
<dateline>INDIANAPOLIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Finish Line Inc said Thursday its same store sales for the four-week period ended May 3 increased 1.8 percent.</p>
<p>The company reported same-store sales for the five week period ended April 5 fell 1.7 percent.</p>
<p>The numbers compare with same-store sales increases of 22.5 percent and 2.7 percent for April and May 1996, respectively.  </p>
<p>&quot;Slowness in certain men's and youth footwear departments were primarily responsible for the sluggish same-store sales in March and April,&quot; Alan Cohen, president and chief executive of Finish Line, said in a statement.</p>
<p>Total sales for the nine weeks ended May 3 were $62.54 million, a 23.1 percent increase from the $50.79 million reported last year, Finish Line said.</p>
<p>The company said product margins improved during the 1997 nine-week period, and per square foot inventory levels at May 3, 1997 were about 12 to 14 percent less than last year.</p>
<p>&quot;The overall sluggish same-store sales can be related to consumer price resistance and less than robust sell-throughs on some new product introductions,&quot; Cohen said, adding activewear sales were also slow.</p>
<p>&quot;We are looking for new footwear product introductions in the men's and youth departments scheduled for May through Back-to-School to help sales rebound in these areas,&quot; Cohen said.</p>
<p>((--Chicago newsdesk, 312-408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INDIANAPOLIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
