<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568500" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. retailers' April sales soft, hurt by apparel.</title>
<headline>U.S. retailers' April sales soft, hurt by apparel.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Commins</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cold, wet spring weather dampened apparel purchases in April, contributing to disappointing sales reported by U.S. retailers and raising concerns that consumers may be holding back on spending, analysts said Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;With unseasonably cold weather, people were not ready to buy spring merchandise,&quot; S&amp;P Equity Group analyst Karen Sack said.</p>
<p>Overall, same-store sales, which measure results from stores open at least a year, where mixed, with apparel down, while some low-priced discount chains posted strong gains.</p>
<p>&quot;If we don't see a nice uptrend in sales in May, we're going to see a promotional clearance environment in June,&quot; Montgomery Securities analyst Thomas Tashjian said.</p>
<p>Salomon Brothers' same-store sales index showed a 3.6 percent rise in April, compared with a 1.3 percent rise a year ago. The April rise, however, was below the 4.4 percent increase in March.</p>
<p>Because of the shift in the Easter holiday, which fell in March this year and in April last year, analysts said sales results for the two months should be taken together.</p>
<p>Even averaging the gains for both months, sales have slowed, added Natwest Securities analyst Robert Buchanan. His index showed a 3 percent rise in April and a 4.1 percent gain in March for a 3.5 percent average increase.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a confirmation that sales have slowed,&quot; Buchanan said, adding previous months had shown about a 5 percent increase in same-store sales.</p>
<p>Limited Inc.'s same-store sales fell 5 percent in April and Gap Inc.'s same store sales declined 6 percent. Luxury retailer Neiman Marcus Group Inc. had a 0.3 percent drop in April same-store sales, while Saks Holdings Inc.'s results were up only 0.6 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Weather even partially offset the benefit of an extra Sunday shopping day in April compared with a year ago,&quot; said Dillon, Read analyst Peter Schaeffer. April gained an extra sales day since Easter fell in March.</p>
<p>On the positive side, surprisingly strong sales results were reported by bargain discounters, Tashjian said. Mac Frugal's Bargains-Closeouts Inc. posted a 5.1 percent rise in April same-store sales and Family Dollar Stores Inc. showed a 7.7 percent gain.</p>
<p>Other retailers reporting above-trend sales were Sears, Roebuck and Co., which had a 3.4 percent increase in domestic same-store sales in April on top of a 10.9 percent increase a year ago.</p>
<p>&quot;Sears' performance was led by strong apparel sales -- including exceptional growth in private and national brands -- and a modest improvement in hardlines (appliances) which built upon a mid-teen increase in April 1996,&quot; Sears Chairman Arthur Martinez said in a statement.</p>
<p>Dayton Hudson Corp. posted a 2.9 percent same-store sales increase overall in April, with a strong 6.7 percent rise at its Target discount department store chain. Wal-Mart Stores Inc., the nation's largest retailer, posted a 6.7 percent gain in April same-store sales.</p>
<p>Sears' shares rose 62.5 cents to $50.375; Dayton Hudson gained 37.5 cents to $47.50. Limited was up 12.5 cents at $18.875 and Wal-Mart Stores Inc. was up $1 to $29.125.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I64500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I65600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I6560002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
