<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568507" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Catalina Marketing sets poison pill plan.</title>
<headline>Catalina Marketing sets poison pill plan.</headline>
<dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Catalina Marketing Corp on Thursday said it adopted a stockholder protection plan, sometimes known as a poison pill.</p>
<p>The company said the plan would protect shareholders in the event of a proposed takeover and guard against partial tender offers, squeeze-outs and open market accumulations.</p>
<p>To implement the plan, the company said it declared a dividend of one preferred share purchase right on each outstanding share of its common stock.  </p>
<p>Holders could excerise the purchase rights only if a person or group acquired 15 percent or more of its common stock, or announced or began a tender offer for 15 percent or more of the common stock, Catalina said.</p>
<p>The company said the acquisition of more than 15 percent but not more than 24 percent of its common stock with the written approval of the board of directors would not result in the exercising of these rights.</p>
<p>The company said the plan would not prevent a takeover, but should encourage anyone seeking to acquire it to negotiate with the board before attempting a takeover.  </p>
<p>Specifically, each right would entitle stockholders, other than the person or group acquiring 15 percent or more of the common stock, to buy shares of a new series of junior participating preferred stock at an exercise price of $120.</p>
<p>The dividend distribution would be made to stockholders of record on May 12 immediately after listing of the rights with the New York Stock Exchange. The rights will expire 10 years from the date of distribution.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ST. PETERSBURG, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
