<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568672" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: CRICKET-VETTORI SENDS NEW ZEALAND CRICKET INTO A SPIN.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-VETTORI SENDS NEW ZEALAND CRICKET INTO A SPIN.</headline>
<byline>Matthew Brockett</byline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Last year, Daniel Vettori was just another cricket-mad Kiwi schoolboy, who dreamed of playing for his country.</p>
<p>This year, the bespectacled 18-year-old left-armer, currently preparing for the Independence Cup one-day tournament in India, is New Zealand's leading spin bowler.</p>
<p>Vettori has been an immediate success since he was selected last February as New Zealand's youngest-ever test player.</p>
<p>&quot;He's a wonderful talent,&quot; said former captain Martin Crowe, the best batsman in New Zealand's history.</p>
<p>&quot;I would have had a lot of respect for him because he doesn't bowl bad balls. He's always there and you have to be patient with a bowler like that, play him with quality because he's giving you quality.&quot;</p>
<p>Vettori was thrown in at the deep end after New Zealand came back from the dead to salvage a draw against England in the first test.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd be lying if I said we didn't cross our fingers,&quot; convenor of selectors Ross Dykes said at the time.</p>
<p>In a telephone interview, Vettori added: &quot;It was a huge shock. But it was a good shock!&quot;</p>
<p>The gamble paid off handsomly.</p>
<p>In just four tests -- two against England and two against World Cup champions Sri Lanka -- the teenager has taken 18 wickets at the impressive average of 23.8.</p>
<p>New Zealand eventually lost the first test series 2-0 to England, but Vettori's consistently accurate line and length, and his ability to turn the ball wickedly for a finger spinner, troubled the best of the English batsmen.</p>
<p>He set up a winning opportunity in the third test, taking four for 97 from a mammoth 58 overs in England's second innings.</p>
<p>Often extracting venomous spin from the rough, Vettori had Alec Stewart playing like a novice, at one stage striking Stewart in the face and drawing blood with a viciously rising ball.</p>
<p>It was no surprise when Stewart, the most prolific test scorer in 1996, offered a bat-pad catch off Vettori for 17.</p>
<p>That was only a glimpse of what was to follow.</p>
<p>The touring Sri Lankans followed England to New Zealand expecting to clean up in the two test matches and one-day games. They had not seen the Kiwis' new spin bowler.</p>
<p>Vettori took the wickets of Sri Lankan captain Arjuna Ranatunga and century-maker Romesh Kaluwitharana on a seamers' wicket in the first test as New Zealand cruised to an easy win.</p>
<p>In the second test, he was instrumental in an even more emphatic victory, taking his first five wicket bag in the second innings and a total haul of nine wickets in the game and winning the man-of-the-match award.</p>
<p>Perhaps Vettori's biggest strength is his cool head. He has been dubbed Jack Frost by his team mates.</p>
<p>&quot;He's such a well-balanced kid. He doesn't appear to be too flustered by any of the hype that goes with test and one-day cricket,&quot; said New Zealand coach Steve Rixon.</p>
<p>Vettori admits to being &quot;nerve-racked&quot; when he was first called up to bowl against the likes of England captain Mike Atherton, but says he does not let the calibre of his opponents overawe him.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't look at the actual player, I just look at him as a batsman that I'm bowling to. I mean, I know they're bloody good players, but I try not to let that enter my mind,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Vettori's prospects seem limitless but he inevitably has much to learn in a trade where the top exponents are traditionally in their thirties before they reach their prime.</p>
<p>The selectors chose to omit him from the one-day internationals against England in order to ensure he remained an attacking bowler.</p>
<p>He played in the second one-day international against Sri Lanka but was taken out of the attack after conceding 21 runs in two overs.</p>
<p>Rixon is careful not to tempt the fates by over-praising his prodigy.</p>
<p>&quot;But what I will say is I like what I see so far,&quot; Rixon said. &quot;And I believe he is certainly part of New Zealand's cricket future.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
