<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568636" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: GOLF-TURNER FARES BEST IN WIND FOR FIRST ROUND LEAD.</title>
<headline>GOLF-TURNER FARES BEST IN WIND FOR FIRST ROUND LEAD.</headline>
<byline>Rob Batsford</byline>
<dateline>THAME, England 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Zealander Greg Turner defied blustery wind and intermittant showers to take a one-stroke lead in the first round of the Benson and Hedges International on Thursday.</p>
<p>A dropped shot at his final hole, his only blemish, prevented Turner lodging an even better score but he declared himself well content with his five under par 67.</p>
<p>The major suprise of the day came from veteran Irishman Christy O'Connor junior, who had four birdies and no dropped shots to claim second place on 68.</p>
<p>With his left arm tightly strapped following a debilitating muscle illness, O'Connor was the model of tidyness around this tough Oxfordshire Golf Club course.</p>
<p>Eight players were tied in third place on 69.</p>
<p>Recently returned to the European Tour following a lengthy and painful course of laser treatment, the 48-year-old Irishman admitted that at times last year he thought his playing career was over.</p>
<p>&quot;Last year I coudn't even squeeze a tube of toothpaste,&quot; said O'Connor, who has been playing on the Tour since 1970.</p>
<p>&quot;I wear a tight band on the forearm to disperse the pain. It's very uncomfortable but it's working and I've talked myself out of it being sore.&quot;</p>
<p>Both Turner and O'Connor played in the morning and although several later players threatened, they each in turn fell back as the buffeting wind made conditions difficult.</p>
<p>It was reminiscent, although not as bad, as the fierce winds in the final round of this tournament last year which saw many scores in the 80s.</p>
<p>&quot;I arrive on Tuesday and it started to snow and I thought I'd go home,&quot; said Turner. Instead his wife went out and bought him thermal underwear.</p>
<p>The New Zealander started from the 10th hole and an eagle at the next where he putted from 15 feet set him on his way. Birdies at four more holes on the front nine, including both par fives, left him superbly placed but his drive on the final hole was short and cost him his only dropped shot of the round.</p>
<p>Briton Colin Montgomerie, who suffered more than most last year when the wind blew him into a horrendous 84 after he had been in the lead, had a switchback ride of a round which saw him score exactly par on only five holes while returning a two under 70.</p>
<p>Of the remainder, eight were birdies, four were bogies and one, the par four, 390-yard eighth, he double-bogeyed.</p>
<p>He managed not one par on the front nine, which he played second, but in contrast to last year when he stormed in a temper from the course, this time he exited laughing and shaking his head in bemusement.</p>
<p>&quot;We're playing a big golf course here so eight birdies suggests something is going right, but all those bogeys suggests there's far too much going wrong,&quot; Montgomerie said.</p>
<p>&quot;Possibly the wind is buffeting so hard I'm dipping slightly and catching certain shots heavy and only going half the distance they should.</p>
<p>&quot;Still I've got to look positive and think I've had all those disasters. I could have shot 80, and shot 70, and that's not bad.&quot;</p>
<p>Also still well in contention were German Bernhard Langer, winner of last week's Italian Open, and Briton Ian Woosnam, who each hit 70, while Spain's Severiano Ballesteros finished on par 72 with four bogies cancelling out his four birdies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="THAME, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
