<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568640" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-PEARCE PLEDGES TO STAY AND HELP FOREST WIN PROMOTION.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-PEARCE PLEDGES TO STAY AND HELP FOREST WIN PROMOTION.</headline>
<byline>Chris Moore</byline>
<dateline>NOTTINGHAM 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stuart Pearce pledged his playing future to Nottingham Forest on Thursday after stepping down as caretaker-manager of the relegated premier league club.</p>
<p>&quot;Playing for Forest and England still means everything to me,&quot; said the 35-year-old international full-back who failed to prevent Forest from going down during his five months in charge.</p>
<p>As widely expected Pearce handed over control of the team to general manager Dave Bassett who joined the club from Crystal Palace in February.</p>
<p>&quot;I haven't really thought about whether being out of the premier league will affect my international career as a player,&quot; said Pearce.</p>
<p>&quot;But the World Cup in France next year is still my big target. That could be my last opportunity to represent my country so I am hoping to still be involved with the England team all the way through to the finals.&quot;</p>
<p>Pearce insisted he will have &quot;no problem&quot; giving up the managerial position and reverting to a playing role under his successor.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll give Dave Bassett all the help I can,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The important thing now is that everyone pulls the same way for him to try and get us promoted next season.</p>
<p>&quot;I've got three years left on my playing contract and I would like to think I'll see them out here.</p>
<p>&quot;If one or two of the players have a problem about me returning to the dressing room my attitude will be the same as when I was manager -- I'm here, I'm doing my job, and they can like it or lump it.&quot;</p>
<p>But Pearce admitted it would have been difficult carrying on in charge of the team in a playing and managing capacity.</p>
<p>&quot;When it came to signing new players I didn't have the time to go and watch them first,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I was having to rely on someone else's judgement when it was my neck on the block. That was one of the hardest parts of the job.</p>
<p>&quot;But I enjoyed the experience and would like to go back into management at the end of my playing career.&quot;</p>
<p>Forest were bottom of the table when Pearce took over from Frank Clark just before Christmas and started brightly under him, winning five of their next seven games.</p>
<p>But they only won one of 14 league matches after that and their fate was sealed when they could only draw 1-1 at home with Wimbledon on Saturday.</p>
<p>They play their last match of the season on Sunday at Newcastle United.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOTTINGHAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
