<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568680" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: HORSE RACING-DERBY WINNER DUMPS RIDER IN PREAKNESS PRACTICE.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-DERBY WINNER DUMPS RIDER IN PREAKNESS PRACTICE.</headline>
<dateline>BALTIMORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kentucky Derby winner Silver Charm on Thursday threw his exercise rider during a practice run for the Preakness Stakes, but neither the horse nor the rider was injured in the mishap, according to Pimlico race course officials.</p>
<p>Silver Charm was in the middle of a mile and a half gallop when he propped, or stopped short, and threw rider Larry Damore.</p>
<p>The three-year-old colt was loose for less than a sixteenth of a mile before being caught by outrider Bill Rudolph and he never tried to run off, but cantered calmly along the track's outside fence, a Pimlico spokesman said.</p>
<p>Silver Charm trainer Bob Baffert took the mishap in stride once he made sure the horse was unhurt. &quot;You can't let stuff like this get to you,&quot; Baffert said.</p>
<p>Damore said Silver Charm, who held off Captain Bodgit for a thrilling victory at Churchill Downs last Saturday, tried to prop at the shadow of the finish line the first time around on the inside of the track Thursday.</p>
<p>The next time around, Damore took Silver Charm to the middle of the track and that's when the horse stopped short and dumped Damore, who was dragged while trying not to let go of his valuable mount.</p>
<p>&quot;I've been thrown from a Breeders' Cup winner and an Eclipse Award winner, but until today I'd never been thrown by a Kentucky Derby winner,&quot; joked former jockey Damore.</p>
<p>The Preakness, second lef of thoroughbred racing's Triple Crown, will be run on May 17.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BALTIMORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
