<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568669" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: SOCCER-CHAMPIONS RIVER KNOCKED OUT OF LIBERTADORES.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-CHAMPIONS RIVER KNOCKED OUT OF LIBERTADORES.</headline>
<byline>Brian Homewood</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Defending champions River Plate of Argentina tumbled out of the South American Libertadores Cup at the first hurdle on Wednesday, losing on penalties to local rivals Racing Club.</p>
<p>River were beaten 5-3 in a penalty shoot-out after the second-round tie in Buenos Aires had ended 4-4 on aggregate.</p>
<p>Veteran Uruguayan international Enzo Francescoli was hero and villain for River, scoring his team's goal in a 1-1 draw on the night but missing his side's first penalty of the shoot-out.</p>
<p>River, excused the marathon first round as champions, were favourites after drawing 3-3 away but fell behind in the fourth minute to a goal by Esteban Fuentes.</p>
<p>Francescoli, a survivor of the 1986 World Cup, equalised four minutes later.</p>
<p>The game turned in the 38th minute when controversial refereee Javier Castrilli, who sent off three Boca Juniors players during an Argentine champinship match on Sunday, dismissed River midfielder Marcelo Gallardo for a foul.</p>
<p>Although Gallardo's tackle was heavy, it did not appear to be intentional. With the one-man disadvantage, River sat back in defence and waited for the penalty shoot-out.</p>
<p>When the penalites began, Racing's Argentina  goalkeeper Ignacio Gonzalez, suspended for three World Cup games last week for head-butting a Bolivian player in a qualifying match, converted his team's first shot. He then defended Francescoli's effort.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm sorry for my team mates after they played so well but these things are part of the profession,&quot; said a dejected Francescoli. &quot;The game was going to be decided by a mistake and unfortunately, it was mine.&quot;</p>
<p>Racing, coached by Argentina's 1994 World Cup coach Alfio Basile, had Claudio Ubeda sent off for a second bookable offence in the 88th minute.</p>
<p>Racing joined Gremio of Brazil and Penarol of Uruguay, who are already in the second round.</p>
<p>Two second-round, first-leg matches were played on Wednesday, both featuring teams called Nacional.</p>
<p>Nacional of Ecuador, who had the advantage of playing at 2,800 metres above sea level, beat Brazilians Cruzeiro 1-0 in Quito with a 73rd minute goal by international striker Kleber Chala.</p>
<p>In Montevideo, three-times winners Nacional of Uruguay were beaten 3-1 at home by Colo Colo, the only club from Chile ever to have lifted the trophy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
