<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568678" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NBA BASKETBALL-LARRY BIRD TO COACH INDIANA PACERS.</title>
<headline>NBA BASKETBALL-LARRY BIRD TO COACH INDIANA PACERS.</headline>
<dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Indiana 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Larry Bird, one of the greatest players in the history of the NBA and his homestate Indiana, has agreed to become the new coach of the Indiana Pacers after spurning a front-office job with the Boston Celtics.</p>
<p>The Pacers said Thursday that Bird had reached a multi-year agreement. A news conference was scheduled for Monday.</p>
<p>Bird, 40, replaces Larry Brown, who resigned last week and later was named coach of the Philadelphia 76ers.</p>
<p>Terms were not disclosed, but various reports put Bird's salary at $4 million per year, with options ranging from entering the front office to partial ownership.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm very excited about this opportunity to go back home and coach the Indiana Pacers,&quot; said Bird. &quot;Indiana is the only team I wanted to coach and I am excited about this new challenge and new career.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We're very happy he made that choice,&quot; Pacers president Donnie Walsh said. &quot;We know that he's going to be a real real good NBA coach.&quot;</p>
<p>Bird has never held any sort of coaching job. He was a special assistant for the Celtics since his retirement in 1992.</p>
<p>One of Bird's last duties was opening conversation with Rick Pitino regarding Boston's coaching vacancy. Pitino accepted the job Tuesday and said in a news conference earlier Thursday, before the Pacers' announcement, that he hoped Bird would stay with the Celtics as general manager.</p>
<p>Instead, the self-styled &quot;hick from French Lick&quot; is going back home.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm looking forward to working with the players and Donnie Walsh and his staff, and I'm going to give it everything I've got, just the way I did when I was playing,&quot; Bird said. &quot;I'm looking forward to producing the best basketball we can for the state of Indiana.&quot;</p>
<p>Before joining the pros, Bird starred at Indiana State, losing a national championship game in a memorable matchup with a Michigan State team led by Magic Johnson, the player with whom he will always be linked in one of the sport's historic rivalries.</p>
<p>Bird won three titles with the Celtics before retiring with various physical ailments.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="INDIANAPOLIS, Indiana"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
