<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568688" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-HUSKEY PINCH-HIT HOMER IN NINTH LIFTS METS PAST HOUSTON.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-HUSKEY PINCH-HIT HOMER IN NINTH LIFTS METS PAST HOUSTON.</headline>
<dateline>PHILADELPHIA 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pinch hitter Butch Huskey went up to the plate in the ninth to bunt, but instead smacked a first-pitch, two-run homer to snap a tie and give the New York Mets a 4-1 win over the Houston Astros Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;That was the first time I ever hit a pinch homer,&quot; Huskey said. &quot;It was a bunting situation but my game plan changed when I stepped into the box. I saw the ball and just made a good swing on it.&quot;</p>
<p>Armando Reynoso (2-0) allowed four hits over eight innings and stopped a string of three straight no-decisions. He walked two, struck out seven and retired the final eight batters he faced before Huskey batted for him in the ninth.</p>
<p>Manny Alexander opened the inning with an infield hit off Tom Martin. Huskey then hit the first pitch over the left-centre field wall for a 3-1 lead.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't think he would be swinging at the first pitch,&quot; Martin said. &quot;A guy that big and strong, you get a pitch up and that's what happens.&quot;</p>
<p>Pinch hitter Carl Everett followed with an infield hit and was sacrificed to second. Everett stole third and scored on John Olerud's sacrifice fly.</p>
<p>The runs were the first allowed by Martin (1-1), who had worked 11 2/3 scoreless innings over his first 12 major-league games. Starter Shane Reynolds had allowed one run and seven hits in eight innings.</p>
<p>John Franco pitched a perfect ninth for his eighth save in nine opportunities, sealing New York's eighth win in 11 games. The Astros have dropped eight of 12.</p>
<p>Reynoso's only mistake came in the first when Jeff Bagwell hit the first pitch over the fence in left-centre for his 10th homer.</p>
<p>In San Francisco, Mike Lansing homered twice in a franchise-record 13-run sixth inning as the Montreal Expos pounded their way to a 19-3 victory over the Giants, who absorbed their worst beating since moving west 39 years ago.</p>
<p>The Expos had half of their 26 hits in the sixth off Joe Roa, Jim Poole and Julian Tavarez, shattering the club record. They fell just shy of team marks for runs and hits in a game.</p>
<p>Henry Rodriguez hit a grand slam and Rondell White belted a solo shot for Montreal, which had 10 extra-base hits and 44 total bases.</p>
<p>Lansing -- who had four hits, five RBI and three runs scored -- became the fourth Expo to hit two homers in an inning and the first since Andre Dawson at Chicago in 1985.</p>
<p>In Colorado, Jose Guillen and Jermaine Allensworth each drove in three runs as the Pittsburgh Pirates launched five home runs to rout the Rockies 14-3.</p>
<p>Guillen, Al Martin, Jason Kendall, Kevin Elster and Joe Randa homered for Pittsburgh, which had not hit five in a game since 1987. The Pirates have won five of their last seven.</p>
<p>Marc Wilkins (2-0) allowed two runs and five hits with a walk and four strikeouts in 3 1/3 innings of relief.</p>
<p>Andres Galarraga had his 19th career two-homer game for the Rockies, who have dropped two of their last three at home.</p>
<p>Colorado starter Mark Thompson (3-3) was tagged for five runs and five hits with two walks over 3 2/3 innings.</p>
<p>In Florida, third baseman Bobby Bonilla's error with two outs in the top of the 10th inning allowed Tony Graffanino to score from second base with the go-ahead run as the Atlanta Braves edged the Marlins 3-2.</p>
<p>Paul Byrd (2-0) worked one inning, striking out two. Mike Bielecki worked out of a bases-loaded jam in the bottom of the 10th to notch his second save.</p>
<p>Reliever Jay Powell (0-1) took the loss.</p>
<p>In St Louis, Ray Lankford hit a grand slam and Gary Gaetti had a three-run shot in a nine-run seventh inning as the Cardinals pounded the Philadelphia Phillies 14-7.</p>
<p>Lankford went 3-for-4 with four RBI and four runs scored for the Cardinals, who set or matched season highs in five categories and won for the eighth time in their last 11 games.</p>
<p>Ron Gant also homered for the Cardinals, who banged out 13 hits. Gant was one of five Cardinals with at least two hits.</p>
<p>In Los Angeles, Ramon Martinez allowed two runs over eight innings as the Dodgers beat the Cincinnati Reds 4-2.</p>
<p>Martinez (3-2), after two poor starts, scattered six hits and three walks with eight strikeouts. Todd Worrell threw the ninth for his 10th save in 12 chances.</p>
<p>Todd Hollandsworth had an RBI single and Greg Gagne added a run-scoring double for the Dodgers.</p>
<p>Pete Schourek (2-3) had his personal two-game winning streak come to an end.</p>
<p>Reggie Sanders had a solo homer for Cincinnati.</p>
<p>In San Diego, John Flaherty went 3-for-4 with three RBI including a homer to lead the Padres to a 6-3 victory over the Chicago Cubs.</p>
<p>Steve Finley, who returned from a stint on the disabled list Tuesday, added two RBI for the Padres, who won for only the second time in their last six home game games.</p>
<p>Mike Hubbard homered for Chicago, which fell to 2-5 on their current 11-game road trip.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHILADELPHIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
