<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568633" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: TENNIS-SELES CRASHES OUT OF ITALIAN OPEN.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-SELES CRASHES OUT OF ITALIAN OPEN.</headline>
<byline>Alan Baldwin</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>France's Mary Pierce beat Monica Seles for the first time in her career on Thursday to send the top-seeded American out of the Italian Open tennis tournament.</p>
<p>In a remarkable match played in a light drizzle under floodlights at the clay court Foro Italico, Pierce deservedly won 7-6 7-6 to reach the quarter-finals after fighting back in each tiebreak to 8-6 from 6-3 down.</p>
<p>The Frenchwoman never let world number three Seles take the upper hand and played some breathtaking shots against an opponent struggling to find a way to stamp her authority on the match.</p>
<p>Just when it seemed Seles was sure to take the set, Pierce elegantly reeled the points back in with barely a murmur beyond an occasional &quot;allez&quot; to herself.</p>
<p>The crowd was more vocal for Seles, whistling and booing when Pierce queried a line call, but it did not matter.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't know what happened,&quot; a stunned Seles said afterwards. &quot;I can't explain. I don't think I ever held anybody down 6-3 in both sets and the other person won it. I felt I was going for my shots at 6-3.&quot;</p>
<p>Seles, who enjoyed a bye into the second round and a rest day on Wednesday, started the match badly when she lost her serve to Pierce in the opening game.</p>
<p>She soon found herself 3-0 and then 5-3 down before holding serve and breaking Pierce to level at 5-5.</p>
<p>Both then held serve to go into the tiebreak with Pierce breaking Seles before the American forged 6-3 clear.</p>
<p>Seles then hit two returns to the net and another wide to allow Pierce right back. The Frenchwoman broke and then clinched the set with a soft rally-killing drop shot.</p>
<p>The two held serve throughout the second set to 5-5, with Seles failing to take two break points at 3-3, and then each broke the other in quick succession to go to 6-6.</p>
<p>Seles again had two set points on her serve at 6-5 but squandered them before double-faulting.</p>
<p>The second tiebreak saw Pierce break Seles before the American took a 6-3 lead. Seles was again let down by her finishing and the Frenchwoman won with a deep forehand.</p>
<p>&quot;I just kept fighting for every point, I didn't worry about winning or losing,&quot; said Pierce, who had never before taken a set off Seles.</p>
<p>Pierce now plays Romanian 14th seed Ruxandra Dragomir for a place in the semifinals.</p>
<p>Dragomir beat fifth-seeded Croat Iva Majoli earlier in the evening in another third-round upset.</p>
<p>The departure of Seles left Spain's Arantxa Sanchez Vicario and Conchita Martinez as the top two seeds left.</p>
<p>Martinez kept on course for her fifth successive Italian title, cruising into the quarter-finals with the rain more of an obstacle than Russian 12th seed Elena Likhovtseva.</p>
<p>The third seed, who has dropped only eight games from two matches so far, won 6-2 6-1.</p>
<p>Rain had delayed the start of the third round by almost five hours and when play eventually started it was suspended again after about an hour as the skies opened once more.</p>
<p>Martinez now meets unseeded South African Joannette Kruger, who knocked out eighth seeded Slovak Karina Habsudova 6-2 6-4 to claim her second name player of the tournament.</p>
<p>The 23-year-old, ranked 121st in the world, beat Dutch ninth seed Brenda Schultz McCarthy 6-2 7-5 in the second round and appeared unconcerned at the prospect of Martinez.</p>
<p>&quot;She has the pressure on her because she has won here so many times. I'm just going to go out there and play as I have been playing for the past few weeks,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Second seed Sanchez, seeking her first title of the year, beat 13th-seeded Belgian Sabine Appelmans 6-3 6-4. She now plays unseeded Swiss Patty Schnyder, who edged out sixth seed Amanda Coetzer of South Africa 7-6 7-5.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
