<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568660" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: CRICKET-NEWPORT SENDS COUNTY CHAMPIONS REELING.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-NEWPORT SENDS COUNTY CHAMPIONS REELING.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>English county champions Leicestershire were sent reeling as Worcestershire's stalwart fast-medium bowler Phil Newport spearheaded a fightback on Thursday.</p>
<p>Newport captured four wickets in 21 deliveries to reduce Leicestershire to 42 for five at the close of a rain-curtailed second day of their four-day championship match at Worcester.</p>
<p>Worcestershire had earlier extended their overnight 199 for six to a moderate 257 all out.</p>
<p>Newport, who made his Worcestershire debut in 1982, put a year of injury worries behind him as he shook the champions with a spell of four for 20.</p>
<p>The 34-year-old paceman, who won three England test caps, said: &quot;This time last year I had a back injury and then an Achilles tendon problem which needed an operation.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel as right as rain now. The Achilles has recovered, the back is good, and hopefully I will hold together for the full season.&quot;</p>
<p>Newport wrecked Leicestershire's batting in 12.5 overs spanning two intervals and three hold-ups for rain, all his wickets coming with late swing.</p>
<p>Somerset's England pace bowler Andy Caddick grabbed  four for 22 in 11.2 overs as Northamptonshire crumbled from the overnight 126 for four to 185 all out.</p>
<p>However, Northants' new overseas signing, Pakistan paceman Mohammad Akram, struck back with three quick wickets to reduce Somerset to 23 for three at the close on the rain-hit second day at Northampton.</p>
<p>Caddick started his successful day by taking a low catch on the backward point boundary to send back Kevin Curran, top scorer with 73.</p>
<p>The England bowler then added four wickets to the two he took on the first day to finish with six for 65.</p>
<p>Somerset had only 10.2 overs batting but were quickly in trouble against Akram, who had openers Mark Lathwell and Marcus Trescothick caught in the slips, then bowled nightwatchman Jason Kerr.</p>
<p>Keith Brown completed his first century for two years to keep Middlesex in control against Sussex on the second day at Lord's.</p>
<p>Brown, who made 72 of the overnight 337 for five, went on to an unbeaten 144, reaching three figures in 203 deliveries and sharing a ninth wicket stand of 78 off 74 balls with Angus Fraser (35).</p>
<p>Middlesex declared at 490 for nine and then reduced Sussex to 44 for three at the close, Jamie Hewitt taking three for 26 with the new ball.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
