<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568692" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NHL ICE HOCKEY-FLYERS UP 3-0 OVER SABRES, EDMONTON HALVES COLORADO LEAD.</title>
<headline>NHL ICE HOCKEY-FLYERS UP 3-0 OVER SABRES, EDMONTON HALVES COLORADO LEAD.</headline>
<dateline>PHILADELPHIA 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Paul Coffey set up three goals in the first period and Eric Lindros and Dale Hawerchuk tallied on the power play 3:33 apart as the Philadelphia Flyers moved within one win of the Eastern Conference finals with a 4-1 victory over the Buffalo Sabres Wednesday.</p>
<p>In the Western Conference semifinals, the Edmonton Oilers halved the visiting Colorado Avalanche's lead to 2-1 in their best-of-seven series by rallying for a 4-3 victory.</p>
<p>The Flyers have a commanding 3-0 lead in the Eastern semis and can wrap it up at home in Game 4 on Friday.</p>
<p>Rod Brind'Amour added a first-period tally and Garth Snow stopped 15 shots for Philadelphia.</p>
<p>Darryl Shannon accounted for Buffalo's offence with a power-play goal in the first period.</p>
<p>The Sabres will try to become just the third team in NHL playoff history to erase a 3-0 deficit and win a best-of-seven series. The 1942 Toronto Maple Leafs and 1975 New York Islanders are the only teams to accomplish the feat.</p>
<p>&quot;As long as there's a chance, you're not dead yet,&quot; said Sabres winger Matthew Barnaby. &quot;It's a big hill and it's not going to be easy, but if you quit now, you'll be a quitter the rest of your life.&quot;</p>
<p>Buffalo goaltender Steve Shields made 34 saves playing in place of Dominik Hasek. Hasek, after a three-game suspension for an altercation with a Buffalo sportswriter, is eligible to play Game 4. He missed the final four games of Buffalo's quarter-final series with Ottawa due to a sprained right knee.</p>
<p>&quot;Shields played well,&quot; said Lindros. &quot;We had 38 shots, but he played strong, made some big saves, key saves. But we got a bit of a bulge early and we hung to it and ended up with a win. Dominik coming back will give them a jump.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Steve Shields got us here but I will think about Hasek tomorrow,&quot; said Buffalo coach Ted Nolan. &quot;Maybe a switch will shake them up. We let them get the jump on us and it's hard to play catchup from three goals back.&quot;</p>
<p>Coffey became the fifth player in Flyers' playoff history to record three assists in a period. He said Philadelphia had aimed to get off fast.</p>
<p>&quot;We talked about it, we wanted to have that type of first period tonight,&quot; Coffey said. &quot;We were fortunate to have a few goals, but we definitely had a mindset to come out strong.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We were undisciplined at the beginning of the game, this is not the way you want to play the game,&quot; said Nolan. &quot;We're not the type of team that can come back from any type of deficit. We were not totally in our element tonight.</p>
<p>&quot;We had guys chasing the puck when they weren't supposed to, we had guys dumping the puck in the zone when they were supposed to shoot. We were just totally off our game tonight.&quot;</p>
<p>Lindros and Hawerchuk both scored on the power play before the Sabres used a power play of their own to pull within 2-1 with 5:05 left on Shannon's goal.</p>
<p>Brind'Amour restored Philadelphia's two-goal lead with a great individual effort, blowing by Jason Dawe before beating Shields with a wrist shot that went inside the left post.</p>
<p>An Eric Desjardins empty-netter with 12 seconds to go in the game was the only goal of the last two periods.</p>
<p>Buffalo went 1-for-7 and is 2-for-15 in the man advantage in the three games.</p>
<p>In Edmonton, Kelly Buchberger and Ryan Smyth scored just over two minutes apart late in the third period to turn a 3-2 deficit into a 4-3 win over Colorado.</p>
<p>Game 4 is on Friday in Edmonton.</p>
<p>Second-period goals by Valeri Kamensky and Claude Lemieux -- his league-leading eighth goal of the post-season -- gave Colorado a 3-2 edge, but Buchberger tied it at 13:57 with his second goal of the game and fifth of the playoffs.</p>
<p>Smyth's fourth goal of the playoffs put the Oilers ahead to stay with 3:45 remaining. Jason Arnott, who had scored Edmonton's second goal of the game in the first period, dug the puck out of the right corner and slid a pass to Daniel McGillis at the right point. Roy stopped McGillis's shot, but Smyth jammed the rebound under Patrick Roy's pads.</p>
<p>Curtis Joseph stopped 21 shots for the Oilers, who outshot the Avalanche 38-24, including 14-5 in the final period.</p>
<p>Roy was pulled for a sixth attacker with 70 seconds left, but the Avalanche were unable to penetrate. Doug Weight narrowly missed an empty-net goal with 38 seconds to go.</p>
<p>Colorado centre Peter Forsberg, who scored the first goal of the game, left with 12:30 to play after he was knocked to the ice by Oilers defenceman Bryan Muir. Forsberg's head hit the ice and he was unconscious for several minutes, but was able to leave under his own power. His 16 points tied him with teammate Joe Sakic for the league post-season lead.</p>
<p>Colorado centre Stephane Yelle also left the game, with a leg injury midway through the third period.</p>
<p>Sandis Ozolinsh assisted on all three Colorado goals, giving him 12 post-season points, tops among defencemen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHILADELPHIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
