<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568662" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-RANGERS CELEBRATE, CELTIC MOURN, GLASGOW RECOVERS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-RANGERS CELEBRATE, CELTIC MOURN, GLASGOW RECOVERS.</headline>
<byline>Phil Gordon</byline>
<dateline>GLASGOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Glasgow was shaking off several thousand giant-sized headaches on Thursday after Rangers wrote themselves into the record books with a ninth successive Scottish League championship triumph.</p>
<p>Half of this divided, football-mad city was still recovering from the celebrations sparked by the title-clinching 1-0 victory over Dundee United last night, while the other half was plunged into mourning.</p>
<p>Celtic, who had jealously guarded their own place in history thanks to the nine-in-a-row achievement under Jock Stein between 1966 and 1974, have now seen their greatest rivals equal that record and wipe out two decades of superiority for the green half of the Old Firm.</p>
<p>Fittingly, it was Brian Laudrup who scored the vital goal which sealed Rangers' success with just one game left. The Danish star has been the outstanding individual for Walter Smith's team in this landmark season.</p>
<p>And while Laudrup's early goal in Dundee launched the party for Rangers' 5,000 travelling fans, it rendered an entire stadium 100 miles away into silence.</p>
<p>Celtic fans turned up for their match at home to Kilmarnock clinging to the hope that their rivals would lose to take the race into the final day on Saturday, but Parkhead was like a morgue once the 43,000 crowd learned of Laudrup's goal. The Celtic-Kilmarnock match fizzled out into a 0-0 draw.</p>
<p>The fierce competition between these two clubs over 109 years has never been greater than it has over the last 10 months as Rangers sought to haul in title number nine and Celtic fought to prevent it.</p>
<p>The battle cost Celtic manager Tommy Burns his job last Friday and even counterpart Smith admitted he felt he too might have been branded a failure if he had not delivered the goods.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a lot of pressure on us this season, in the sense that Celtic had obviously won nine in a row and have been our biggest rivals for a long number of years,&quot; Smith reflected.</p>
<p>&quot;When it came to the opportunity to equal nine, it would have been looked upon as a failure if it had not been achieved. There was pressure on me on a personal basis.</p>
<p>&quot;But this season there was a bit more pressure and tension all round -- maybe too much. Celtic had a lot to do to try and stop us. In the end it maybe cost Tommy Burns his job because he had not managed it.&quot;</p>
<p>Few could savour Rangers' moment of triumph  more than Smith. He had supported the club as a boy but a moderate playing career with Dundee United, where he was also a coach, kept him away from his beloved Ibrox until Graeme Souness recruited him as his right-hand man after becoming Rangers manager in 1986.</p>
<p>While the high-profile Souness exhausted Rangers' cheque book in chalking up the first three titles of the nine-in-a-row success, Smith was happier remaining on the training ground with his players.</p>
<p>Only when Souness abruptly departed for Liverpool in 1991 did Smith move into the spotlight. Rangers chairman David Murray insisted he had faith in Smith -- and Smith has rewarded that handsomely.</p>
<p>Now, six titles of his own later he has moved into the Ibrox hall of fame forever but he has no wish to be talked about as an equal to Jock Stein, who also took Celtic to the European Cup and Scotland to two World Cup finals before his death in 1985.</p>
<p>&quot;Jock Stein made me a manager of Scotland's under-21 team in the early 80's. My only regret is that he was not around long enough for me to learn more from him but he can never be matched.</p>
<p>&quot;During the period I have been Rangers manager, Celtic's achievement under him has become greater in my eyes because I know what Mr Stein had to go through to do it.</p>
<p>&quot;He suffered the same thing, that by winning the title so often it becomes devalued because it becomes accepted by everyone as part of the season. But you can't devalue your championship.&quot;</p>
<p>As if to signify the end of an era, Rangers also bid farewell to the one man who has been at the centre of their amazing championship monopoly -- captain Richard Gough.</p>
<p>The 35-year-old central defender, bought 10 years ago from Tottenham Hotspur for 1.5 million pounds, has repaid that sum many times over during his Ibrox decade with his inspiring leadership.</p>
<p>He flew out of Scotland on Thursday to start a new life in America, where he will join MLS team Kansas City Wizard. A calf injury robbed him of a farewell performance last night to add to the 263 league games he has played for Rangers.</p>
<p>But his last act for the club was to step onto the podium erected on the pitch at Tannadice and lift aloft the championship trophy.</p>
<p>Gough's normal iron-mask of emotions cracked and he departed the scene in tears, declaring: &quot;I always wanted to go out at the top -- and you don't get any higher than this.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GLASGOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
