<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568670" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: SOCCER-CORRUPTION INQUIRY LAUNCHED AFTER TOP OFFICIAL RESIGNS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-CORRUPTION INQUIRY LAUNCHED AFTER TOP OFFICIAL RESIGNS.</headline>
<byline>Brian Homewood</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>An inquiry is being launched after a leading director of the Brazilian national soccer confederation (CBF) resigned amid allegations of corruption.</p>
<p>A scandal erupted after the Globo television station played a recording of a telephone conversation which it said was between Ivens Mendes, head of the CBF's refereeing commission, and the president of Atletico Paranaense.</p>
<p>In the conversation, the man identified as Mendes offered to ask a referee to give Atletico a helping hand in a Copa Brasil match they were to play at home to Vasco da Gama.</p>
<p>The man identified as Mendes said: &quot;I need you to send me 25,000 Real (about $23,600)... If I get a chance I will even ask the referee to give you a little bit of a hand.</p>
<p>&quot;Tell your players to mark (Vasco da Gama striker) Edmundo closely, he gets angry easily.&quot;</p>
<p>The man identified by Globo as Atletico president Mario Celso Petraglia was heard to reply that Mendes should get in touch with his (Petralgia's) secretary who would &quot;look after it.&quot;</p>
<p>Atletico won the second round, first leg match 3-1. Edmundo, who has a long record of being sent off, and Atletico defender Andrei were dismissed in the first half for fighting. Edmundo said of his dismissal: &quot;It was a huge injustice.&quot;</p>
<p>Globo television alleged that Mendes, who resigned on Wednesday claiming he had been threatened, is seeking election to the Brazilian Congress and used money sent to him by club directors to help his election campaign. Globo said it been sent the tape anonymously.</p>
<p>Mendes admitted he had received money but claimed it was all above board: &quot;What is wrong with me as a Brazilian citizen...who is trying to start a political career accepting help from my friends?&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Petraglia denied he had spoken to Mendes about the game and match referee Oscar Roberto de Godoi said there had been no approaches &quot;even by phone.&quot;</p>
<p>CBF president Ricardo Teixeira said he would launch an inquiry, but pointed out that the Globo report only referred to one game.</p>
<p>Vasco director Eurico Miranda called for the competition to be halted and his club, who lost the second round tie 7-6 on aggregate, to be re-admitted.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the Copa Brasil has to stop,&quot; he said. &quot;Vasco have to be re-admitted and Atletico Paranaense must be given an exemplary punishment to re-establish the credibility of the competition.&quot;</p>
<p>Atletico were subsequently eliminated by Corinthians in the quarter-finals of the competition, which is currently at its semifinal stage.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
