<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568695" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-BURNITZ THE DIFFERENCE IN 1-0 BREWERS WIN OVER A'S.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-BURNITZ THE DIFFERENCE IN 1-0 BREWERS WIN OVER A'S.</headline>
<dateline>MILWAUKEE 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jeromy Burnitz scored the lone run and threw out the potential tying run at the plate to end the game as the Milwaukee Brewers edged the Oakland Athletics Wednesday in the longest 1-0 nine-inning game in major-league history.</p>
<p>Burnitz drew a two-out walk in the seventh inning from Steve Montgomery (0-1) and stole second. Jeff Cirillo then laced a 2-1 pitch to left, scoring Burnitz.</p>
<p>Oakland rallied in the ninth against closer Doug Jones. With one out, Scott Spiezio singled but was forced by Scott Brosius. Shortstop Jose Valentin threw away the relay, allowing Brosius to take second. Dave Magadan drew a pinch walk and pinch-hitter Matt Stairs hit a 1-2 pitch to right.</p>
<p>Burnitz came up throwing and catcher Jesse Levis was barely able to slap the tag on a sliding Brosius to end the game. Brosius threw his helmet to the ground and argued the call as Jones walked off with his sixth save.</p>
<p>&quot;You're thinking if a guy gets a base hit, there's probably going to be a tie game,&quot; said Burnitz. &quot;But fortunately, Stairs hit the ball hard and I charged it hard and got rid of it as quickly as I could and made a good throw.</p>
<p>&quot;You come up, throw as hard as you can to home plate and try to hit the cutoff man. I thought there was a chance as soon as I let loose of it, and there would be a close play.&quot;</p>
<p>Oakland manager Art Howe fumed at what he thought was a blown call by home plate umpire Dale Ford.</p>
<p>&quot;All I know is, the guy beat the play and we just lost a game we shouldn't have lost,&quot; he said. &quot;I don't know how you miss the call. He blew the call, just plain and simple.&quot;</p>
<p>Mike Fetters (1-0) picked up the win with two hitless innings in relief of starter Jeff D'Amico, who struck out a career-high seven in six innings.</p>
<p>The game lasted three hours, 20 minutes, surpassing the previous record for a 1-0 game of 3:07 set on May 17, 1988, when the Mets edged the Padres.</p>
<p>In Baltimore, Jimmy Key tossed six scoreless innings to become the first six-game winner in the majors and Chris Hoiles hit a solo homer as the Orioles improved the American League's best record, 3-0 over the Anaheim Angels.</p>
<p>Key (6-0) won his fifth straight outing and is off to the best start by an Oriole since Ben McDonald began the 1994 season with seven wins. Key gave up six hits with three walks and one strikeout and is 9-1 all-time at Oriole Park.</p>
<p>Jesse Orosco and Armando Benitez each worked one inning and Randy Myers pitched the ninth for his major league-leading 13th save.</p>
<p>The Orioles (21-9) have won seven of their last nine.</p>
<p>In New York, Joe Girardi's two-run double triggered a four-run second inning and David Cone allowed one earned run over six innings as the Yankees stayed hot with a 5-2 victory over the Texas Rangers.</p>
<p>Tino Martinez added his major league-leading 14th homer for the Yankees, who have won 13 of their last 18 games.</p>
<p>Cone (4-2), who allowed seven hits and struck out eight, improved to 12-1 all-time at Yankee Stadium.</p>
<p>Jeff Nelson struck out four in two innings before Mariano Rivera pitched the ninth to convert his seventh consecutive save and 10th overall.</p>
<p>In Cleveland, Jack McDowell scattered six hits over eight innings and the Indians continued their power surge with four home runs in a 7-1 victory over the Toronto Blue Jays.</p>
<p>McDowell (3-2) allowed one run, walked three and struck out eight. After two bulllpen appearances, McDowell has come back to win two starts, allowing just two runs and nine hits with eight walks and 17 strikeouts over 15 innings.</p>
<p>The four homers gave Cleveland a major league-leading 59. The Indians (16-14) have won five of their last seven games.</p>
<p>In Detroit, Bobby Higginson hit a three-run homer and Brian Hunter had two hits and three RBI to lead the Tigers to a 12-3 romp over the Kansas City Royals.</p>
<p>Felipe Lira (1-2) settled down after a rough first inning to win his first game since July 7, 1996. Lira threw 40 pitches in the first inning but just 60 over his final five.</p>
<p>Rookie Jim Pittsley (0-3) was tagged for six runs and five hits with three walks as he lasted just 1 2/3 innings.</p>
<p>In Boston, rookie Scott Hatteberg hit his first two major-league homers and drove in a career-high four runs and Reggie Jefferson went 4-for-5 with two homers and four RBI as the Red Sox pounded the Kansas City Royals 11-3, snapping a four-game losing streak.</p>
<p>The scheduled game in Chicago between the Seattle Mariners and White Sox was postponed due to rain and rescheduled as part of a doubleheader on Saturday, August 16.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILWAUKEE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
