<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568634" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: TENNIS-RAIN HOLDS UP MARTINEZ MORE THAN OPPONENT.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-RAIN HOLDS UP MARTINEZ MORE THAN OPPONENT.</headline>
<byline>Alan Baldwin</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spain's Conchita Martinez kept on course for her fifth successive Italian Open title on Thursday, cruising into the quarter-finals with the rain more of an obstacle than Russian 12th seed Elena Likhovtseva.</p>
<p>The third seed, who has dropped only eight games from two matches so far, won 6-2 6-1 against an opponent playing her first tournament at the clay court Foro Italico and meeting Martinez for the first time in her career.</p>
<p>Drizzle and occasional heavy showers had delayed the start of the third-round matches by almost five hours as staff removed and then replaced the court covers.</p>
<p>When play eventually started it was suspended again after just under an hour as the skies opened once more.</p>
<p>By then Martinez was already leading 6-2 2-0.</p>
<p>Play resumed again 40 minutes later in front of rows of empty seats and a few hardy supporters.</p>
<p>The Spaniard's opponent in the quarter-finals will be unseeded South African Joannette Kruger, who got through to the last eight in 1995 as well before injury hit her career.</p>
<p>Kruger knocked out eighth-seeded Slovak Karina Habsudova 6-2 6-4 to oust her second name player of the tournament.</p>
<p>The 23-year-old, ranked 121st in the world, beat Dutch ninth seed Brenda Schultz McCarthy 6-2 7-5 in the previous round and appeared unconcerned at the prospect of Martinez, despite having been beaten on both their previous encounters.</p>
<p>&quot;The first time I had a lot of opportunities to beat her,&quot; Kruger said. &quot;She's going to have to beat me, I'm not going to give the match to her.</p>
<p>&quot;She has the pressure on her because she has won here so many times. I'm just going to go out there and play as I have been playing for the past few weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>Second seed Arantxa Sanchez Vicario, seeking her first title of the year, joined her compatriot Martinez in the quarter-finals after a tougher game against 13th seeded Belgian Sabine Appelmans. Sanchez won 6-3 6-4.</p>
<p>She now plays unseeded Swiss Patty Schnyder, who edged out sixth seed Amanda Coetzer of South Africa 7-6 7-5.</p>
<p>Coetzer's defeat meant half the 16 seeds had fallen.</p>
<p>Sanchez made an inauspicious start, losing her first service game, but then immediately broke back. The Spaniard then broke again for a 5-3 lead and held serve for the set.</p>
<p>&quot;I played well yesterday but much better today,&quot; said the former world number one, whose poor form of late had her facing questions about the &quot;crisis&quot; in her career on Wednesday despite beating Argentina's Paola Suarez 6-2-6-2.</p>
<p>Romanian seventh seed Irina Spirlea beat Belgian Dominique Van Roost 6-1 6-3 and faces either Italian wild card Francesca Lubiani or Austrian 11th seed Barbara Paulus next.</p>
<p>Lubiani, who stunned and delighted the home crowd by beating German fourth seed Anke Huber on Wednesday, was scheduled for the late slot usually reserved for bigger names.</p>
<p>Spirlea, who speaks perfect Italian, promptly went on a charm offensive to win over the locals, declaring her love of Rome and Italy at a post-match news conference.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
