<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568654" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: RALLYING-MCRAE GETS BACK ON THE WINNING TRACK.</title>
<headline>RALLYING-MCRAE GETS BACK ON THE WINNING TRACK.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Vignal</byline>
<dateline>AJACCIO, Corsica 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Briton Colin McRae ended a frustrating run in style by winning the Tour of Corsica rally on Wednesday to keep alive his title hopes.</p>
<p>&quot;I should have been nervous but I was nice and calm,&quot; said McRae, whose Subaru Impreza was seven seconds behind Carlos Sainz's Ford Escort with just one timed stage remaining. &quot;I knew the only option was to push as hard as possible, I did just that and it worked.&quot;</p>
<p>McRae, who had not won a race since taking the Safari Rally in Kenya last March, gained 15 seconds on Sainz in that test alone to score a precious victory.</p>
<p>The roads had been dry until the last section but rain started to fall just before the crucial, 34.33-km stretch from Stiliccione to Marati, in the mountains south of Ajaccio.</p>
<p>&quot;We knew we were faster than Carlos on the dry stages but then it rained and we had no references for wet roads,&quot; said McRae. &quot;Anyway, we knew our only option was to attack.&quot;</p>
<p>The finale of the race was breathtaking with the four leading drivers covered by fewer than 15 seconds before the last timed stage.</p>
<p>Not only Sainz, but also Frenchmen Gilles Panizzi and Francois Delecour, in their lightweight, two-wheel drive Peugeots, were still in contention for victory.</p>
<p>Almost reckless driving eventually gave McRae the edge with Sainz having to settle for second place eight seconds back. Panizzi and Delecour came third and fourth respectively.</p>
<p>&quot;Sometimes, you're just in the right frame of mind,&quot; explained McRae. &quot;You don't feel any fear, not even pressure and you're confident. It doesn't happen often but this time, it happened just at the right time,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;The four-wheel drive cars obviously had an advantage because the road was greasy,&quot; said Panizzi. &quot;But what McRae did is incredible. To gain 15 seconds on a driver like Sainz, who's not just anybody, is quite an achievement.&quot;</p>
<p>McRae badly needed a win to restore his confidence after a puncture made him drop to fourth place when he was fighting for the lead in last month's Catalunya rally.</p>
<p>The 1995 world champion, who was 12 points behind world championship leader Tommi Makinen before coming to Corsica, closed the gap to two points as the Finn crashed out when his Mitsubishi Lancer bumped into a cow on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Tommi's accident was unfortunate,&quot; said McRae's co-driver Nicky Grist. &quot;But it's true that now, we're back on line for a good fight.&quot;</p>
<p>The upcoming rallies, starting with the Argentine event, later this month, are on gravel, McRae's favourite surface.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking forward to the gravel rallies,&quot; said Grist. &quot;The next five rallies certainly have suited Colin in the past and it's looking good.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AJACCIO, Corsica"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
