<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568641" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: CYCLING-CHIAPPUCCI FAILS BLOOD TEST, OUT OF TOUR.</title>
<headline>CYCLING-CHIAPPUCCI FAILS BLOOD TEST, OUT OF TOUR.</headline>
<dateline>ESTAVAYER-LE-LAC, Switzerland 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leading Italian rider Claudio Chiappucci was forced out of the Tour of Romandie on Thursday after failing a blood test.</p>
<p>His licence has been suspended for 15 days when he will be re-tested, the Swiss news agency ATS reported.</p>
<p>The suspension means Chiappucci, nicknamed Il Diavolo (the Devil), will miss the Giro d'Italia.</p>
<p>International Cycling Union (UCI) officials tested Chiappucci and several other riders before the 173-km second stage from Le Locle to Estavayer-le-lac, ATS said.</p>
<p>Blood tests were introduced in January to help combat the use of EPO (erythropoietin) and injectable blood-doping substances that simulate altitude training by increasing the number of oxygen-rich red blood cells.</p>
<p>If tests show a rider's level is above 50 percent he is automatically suspended.</p>
<p>Chiappucci was the fourth rider to fail blood tests this season.</p>
<p>Italians Mauro Santaromita, Luca Colombo and Frenchman Erwan Mentheour were the first casualties of the anti-doping procedures when tests before the second stage of the Paris-Nice in March found their red blood cell counts to be above set limits.</p>
<p>Riders must be re-tested at an UCI-sanctioned lab and their red blood cell count be back to normal before they are allowed to race again.</p>
<p>Davide Boifava, manager of the Asics team for whom Chiappucci rides, was quoted as saying he was shocked by the outcome of the test.</p>
<p>He said the team had carried out a blood test on Chiappucci on Wednesday night which was normal.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not know how to explain the difference of the results done just a few hours apart. There is something very strange about this result.&quot;</p>
<p>He said Chiappucci was not even planning to start Thursday's second stage because of a problem with his arm.</p>
<p>Chiappucci revels in his nickname,  but the last time he gave hell to his rivals was in the 1992 Tour de France.</p>
<p>Then an inspired solo through the Alps to the Italian resort of Sestriere had even the mighty Miguel Indurain in trouble.</p>
<p>He won the best mountain-climber award for the second consecutive year and finished second overall.</p>
<p>The big honour always eluded him but Chiappucci's consolations included the mountains prize in three Giros and winning the 1991 Milan-San Remo classic.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ESTAVAYER-LE-LAC, Switzerland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
