<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568663" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-WORLD CUP TO EMBRACE PAY TV REVOLUTION.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-WORLD CUP TO EMBRACE PAY TV REVOLUTION.</headline>
<byline>Keith Weir</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Next year's World Cup finals in France could be the last time billions of people around the globe are guaranteed seeing the tournament on free television.</p>
<p>FIFA, world soccer's governing body, has signed a two billion dollar television rights deal for the 2002 and 2006 tournaments under which subscription television appears likely to grab a piece of the action.</p>
<p>FIFA general secretary Sepp Blatter told a conference in London last week that only key matches were certain to remain on free television, that is state or advertising funded networks, after the 1998 finals.</p>
<p>&quot;The opening game, one semifinal and the final...They will be shown on free television,&quot; Blatter said. But he did not rule out pay television buying the rights to other games in what is set to become a 64-match marathon.</p>
<p>The words underline FIFA's determination to maximise television revenue from an event which it believes it had undersold in recent years.</p>
<p>Under the deal agreed last year, FIFA gave German media group Kirch and Swiss-based marketing agency ISL the opportunity to sell the rights to the World Cup on its behalf in return for a share of the revenue.</p>
<p>The two companies have guaranteed FIFA a minimum of 1.3 billion Swiss francs ($880 million) for the 2002 World Cup to be co-hosted by South Korea and Japan and at least 1.5 billion francs for the following finals.</p>
<p>The income is used by FIFA to develop the game around the world. It also passes one million dollars to each of its 200 or so federations every four years.</p>
<p>FIFA is guaranteed just 135 million Swiss francs for the 1998 finals in France, part of an agreement signed with television companies back in 1987.</p>
<p>That figure will be revised upwards to take account of the extra games created by the switch next year from a 24-nation to a 32-country format but will still fall a long way short of what FIFA regards as fair value.</p>
<p>&quot;Concerning the FIFA World Cup of 1998, you have no problems because it will still be broadcast by government-supported TV and FIFA will receive practically nothing in relation to the value of the product today,&quot; Blatter told the London conference.</p>
<p>Television coverage of the World Cup has made players such as Pele and Diego Maradona famous in every part of the globe.</p>
<p>Soccer's world governing body insists its guiding principle will remain that of making matches available to the largest number of people.</p>
<p>It points out that it retains the power of veto over who purchases the rights. The tournament will also stay on free television in the whole of Africa, with the sole exception of South Africa.</p>
<p>FIFA spokesman Keith Cooper adds that pay-per-view, the payment of a specific fee to see individual games, is not part of the World Cup television equation.</p>
<p>&quot;There are three types of television, what is known as free, pay or subscription and then pay-per-view,&quot; Cooper said.</p>
<p>&quot;Pay-per-view is and remains excluded. We have never made any distinction between the other two.</p>
<p>&quot;It is early days yet and certain options have to be left open,&quot; he added when asked about the balance between free and pay channels. But he said the key matches listed by Blatter would be the very minimum left on free TV.</p>
<p>Unlike FIFA, some European countries, notably Britain, France and parts of Belgium, do distinguish between free and pay television, preventing top sporting events from migrating to cable or satellite services. The European Union has taken up the cry and is in the process of seeking to extend the protection to cover its 15 member states.</p>
<p>Cooper acknowledged that the current European regulatory environment could complicate the sale of rights but said that the broadcasting landscape in 2002 could be very different from that of today.</p>
<p>One British television executive says that the FIFA position has &quot;metamorphosised&quot; since the Kirch-ISL deal was announced last year. The executive, who works for one of Britain's free television networks, detects an increasing openness on the part of FIFA towards pay television.</p>
<p>But he believes that FIFA would face massive criticism if it tried to leave free channels in Britain with a bare minimum of games.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there would be a huge outcry if just three games were shown on BBC and ITV,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But at the moment we haven't been approached by anyone about 2002. We won't now where we stand until negotiations begin.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
