<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568673" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: SOCCER-RECORD LOW J-LEAGUE CROWD REFLECTS SOCCER'S WOES.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-RECORD LOW J-LEAGUE CROWD REFLECTS SOCCER'S WOES.</headline>
<byline>Ken Ferris</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's professional soccer League, born on a wave of optimism five years ago, is going through hard times.</p>
<p>A record low crowd of only 2,245 turned up on Wednesday night for a match between JEF United and Sanfrecce Hiroshima at Ichihara stadium reflecting the game's struggle to hold onto the fans who have been deserting the J-League teams in droves.</p>
<p>The latest setback for a sport which was hoping to latch onto the coattails of the 2002 World Cup comes despite the continued inflow of foreign players.</p>
<p>Earlier this week JEF United signed the Ajax midfield player Arnold Scholten on an 18-month contract. But the latest foreign acquisition was clearly not enough to attract the fans to a team which also had the previous record low crowd of 3,057 for a game against Kyoto Purple Sanga.</p>
<p>The J-League's overall attendance target for this season is five million, or an average turnout of 15,000, compared to the goal of six milion which was easily reached in 1995.</p>
<p>But so far this year the League has attracted average crowds of only 10-12,000 - well below the average of around 17,000 in the first four years.</p>
<p>Those figures suggest the League should be concerned about the decline in soccer's popularity at the professional level.</p>
<p>But Mitsunori Fujiguchi, Deputy-Secretary of the J-League, believes the shake-out could be a good thing in the long-run.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not really concerned. In some ways the temporary fashion of the J-League is being stripped away and that's allowing the core support to come out clearly.&quot;</p>
<p>The J-League is nevertheless trying to encourage clubs to put more effort into creating the local following each club desperately needs to remain viable.</p>
<p>There are big differences between the various J-League clubs. JEF United struggle to attract fans partly because their stadium is in Ichihara while their offices and training ground are in Maihama.</p>
<p>&quot;The fans can't go down and see the players faces every day,&quot; says the J-League's Fujiguchi. &quot;The clubs need to be more focused on their home area. They need to create the support.&quot;</p>
<p>One of the few success stories this year is Cerezo Osaka whose stadium is in Nagai, Western Japan. In March the club moved their offices next to the stadium and they're now planning to have their training ground there as well.</p>
<p>The result of the changes: rising attendances. Cerezo, who are currently lying in mid-table, attracted a crowd of 27,734 on May 3 for the visit of local rivals Gamba Osaka.</p>
<p>On the same day a top-of-the-table clash between local rivals Kashima Antlers and Kashima Reysol attracted 31,083 to the national stadium which hosted the 1964 Summer Olympic Games.</p>
<p>The record crowd so far this year was the 38,707 who turned out for a match between Urawa Reds and Sanfrecce Hiroshima.</p>
<p>The challenge facing the J-League is to even out the levels of support between clubs. Its strategy is to help the clubs build up their fan-base slowly but surely.</p>
<p>&quot;This is only the fifth year of the J-League,&quot; says Fujiguchi. &quot;We've only just been born and we can't expect results overnight.&quot;</p>
<p>J-League officials are hoping Japan's co-hosting of the 2002 World Cup with South Korea will help boost the popularity of a game which, despite the low attendances, is proving more attractive to play than baseball for many Japanese youngsters.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the League is already looking beyond the World Cup to secure the future of the professional game.</p>
<p>Its official slogan is the &quot;100 year plan&quot; showing that those running the League believe professional soccer will remain in Japan, long after they have gone.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
