<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568632" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NCAA-UMASS FORCED TO FORFEIT 1996 FINAL FOUR BECAUSE OF CAMBY.</title>
<headline>NCAA-UMASS FORCED TO FORFEIT 1996 FINAL FOUR BECAUSE OF CAMBY.</headline>
<dateline>OVERLAND PARK, Kansas 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The NCAA Executive Council stripped the University of Massachusetts of its 1996 NCAA Basketball Final Four berth Thursday for violations arising from former star Marcus Camby's acceptance of money from an agent.</p>
<p>In addition to having its record deleted from the NCAA Tournament, the school has to give back the Final Four trophy and return 45 percent of the revenues from the 1996 NCAA Tournament -- costing the university $151,617.</p>
<p>According to NCAA representative Bill Saum, the figure of 45 percent has been established for institutions that use an ineligible player and are not aware of it. Massachusetts was in violation of NCAA rules involving athlete eligibility and players receiving money.</p>
<p>The NCAA Executive Council, which investigated the case, said UMass was not aware of the violations and that Camby competed while ineligible. Newspaper reports have said Camby, currently with the Toronto Raptors, paid $28,000 to protect a sports agent from being killed by loan sharks.</p>
<p>Camby was selected by the Raptors with the first pick in the NBA Draft last June and made the All-Rookie team in his first season. He led Massachusetts to a 35-2 record and its first-ever Final Four appearance in 1996 under current New Jersey Nets coach John Calipari.</p>
<p>In response to the NCAA action, Massachusetts Chancellor David K. Scott said &quot;nothing can take away the university's pride in the hard work and achievement&quot; in the 1995-96 team but acknowledged &quot;a great sense of loss for the university and supporters.&quot;</p>
<p>The Boston Globe reported Wednesday that details of the payment were made in a report that Massachusetts submitted to the NCAA in March. The newspaper said it obtained a copy of the report.</p>
<p>According to the report, Connecticut agent John Lounsbury went to Camby to demand repayment of money he claimed to have given the player and his friends when he was trying to lure Camby to choose him as his agent.</p>
<p>After Camby picked another representative in April 1996, Lounsbury asked for his money back, and said he had borrowed the money &quot;off the streets&quot; and would be murdered if the money was not repayed.</p>
<p>Citing unidentified sources, the Globe reported that the agency representing Camby, Virginia-based Pro Serv Inc., helped him obtain a bank loan to bail out Lounsbury.</p>
<p>Previously, Camby admitted receiving only $2,000 from Lounsbury. The newspaper said it was unclear how much of the $28,000 Camby received and how much went to his friends.</p>
<p>UMass officials said they were unaware of any wrongdoing by Camby until a June 1996 article in the Hartford Courant quoted Camby as saying he had taken a small amount of money and gifts from Lounsbury and Hartford attorney Wesley Spears.</p>
<p>Camby originally claimed he accepted a diamond necklace worth $3,400 and a chain valued at $1,800.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OVERLAND PARK, Kansas"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
