<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568665" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-S.A. RUGBY TRAILS N.Z., SAYS VILJOEN.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-S.A. RUGBY TRAILS N.Z., SAYS VILJOEN.</headline>
<byline>Mark Stokes</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>In the wake of recent unconvincing performances by South African sides in the southern hemisphere's Super 12 competition, Western Province coach Harry Viljoen believes South African rugby has fallen behind the New Zealan equivalent.</p>
<p>Viljoen told the Johannesburg-based Star newspaper that South African rugby players were less hungry than their New Zealand counterparts and that the level of coaching in the country had also slipped.</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps our players are more spoilt than elsewhere. They do earn good money and they have time to develop other interests as well. But it is not only the players who must shoulder the blame,&quot; Viljoen told The Star.</p>
<p>&quot;We have fallen behind in organisation and techniques in many aspects of the game. It's a sad but true fact and it's no good pointing fingers at certain individuals.&quot;</p>
<p>Viljoen said the Springboks' World Cup final victory over the All Blacks in 1995 had covered up weaknesses in the general structures of the game in South Africa.</p>
<p>&quot;And since that win, New Zealand have redoubled their efforts, while we have stayed where we were.</p>
<p>&quot;If we don't compete off the field, we won't be able to win on the field. Coaching is one area where we have fallen behind and it is starting to show in the Super 12.&quot;</p>
<p>Of the four South African provinces competing in the Super 12, only Natal appears likely to qualify for the semi-finals.</p>
<p>Last weekend's matches saw defending champions Auckland open up a nine-point lead at the top of the competition table while last season's defeated finalists Natal slumped to a 40-3 defeat against lowly Queensland.</p>
<p>Australian Capital Territory are second and Wellington third while Natal, although still in fourth place, have lost their chance of a home semi-final.</p>
<p>The Gauteng Lions (formerly Transvaal) were the early season front-runners in the competition but their shocking away form continued on Saturday with a 47-9 capitulation to Waikato in Hamilton.</p>
<p>Ironically, the only slim chance for bankruptcy-threatened Northern Transvaal, Gauteng and Free State to qualify for the Super 12 semi-finals is if Natal lose their last two games.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
