<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568724" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: SOCCER SHOWCASE-TACTICS FOR BARCELONA-REAL MADRID.</title>
<headline>SOCCER SHOWCASE-TACTICS FOR BARCELONA-REAL MADRID.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A look at the strengths and weaknesses of Barcelona and Real Madrid who meet in the Camp Nou stadium on Saturday (1830 gmt).</p>
<p>Barcelona</p>
<p>Strategy: Barcelona use a 4-5-1 formation, in which Josep Guardiola and either Gheorghe Popescu or Miguel Angel Nadal play in front of the back four to provide the link with midfield.</p>
<p>Giovanni or Ivan de la Pena play a central coordinating role up-front, with Figo controlling the right and Stoichkov or Amunike the left leaving Ronaldo as the solitary target man.</p>
<p>Strengths: Barcelona's main strength is easy to identify. Brazilian striker Ronaldo has scored 31 league goals, and is widely considered the best player in the world.</p>
<p>Barcelona have a legion of other match winners, and in individual quality are, at least on paper, superior to Real.</p>
<p>Giovanni, the temperamental Ivan de la Pena, Guardiola and -- to the suprise of many -- Luis Enrique, have already shown this season that they can turn round games with touches of brilliance.</p>
<p>Robson will be able to leave several internationals on the bench, and it is this strength in depth that sets aside Barcelona, even from another economic powerhouse like Real.</p>
<p>Barcelona have some extraordinarily committed players like overlapping full-backs Ferrer and Sergi, while former Real utility man Luis Enrique has scored 15 goals, many of them from headers, in an outstanding season.</p>
<p>Weaknesses: Barcelona started the season with an excessive dependence on the individual brilliance of Ronaldo. That trend has disappeared, but at the same time a fragility in the Barcelona defence has appeared, and this has often left an increasingly-nervous Baia exposed.</p>
<p>Motivation: Barca fans hate losing to their arch-rivals, and haven't given up a league match to Real in the Camp Nou since 1983-84. Anything less than a win on Saturday would hand Real yet another Spanish league title.</p>
<p>Probable team: goalkeeper-Vitor Baia defenders-Albert Ferrer, Laurent Blanc, Abelardo Fernandez, Sergi Barjuan midfielders-Josep Guardiola, Gheorghe Popescu, Ivan de la Pena strikers-Hristo Stoichkov, Luis Figo, Ronaldo.</p>
<p>Real Madrid</p>
<p>Strategy: Fabio Capello's modified 4-4-2 strategy is fairly similar to that of Robson's. Midfielders Redondo and Seedorf play as link-men in front of a four-man defence, with Raul pushing on the left and Amavisca on the right to supply target-men Suker and Mijatovic.</p>
<p>Capello's men have been effective, though not always stylish, throughout the season, and tend to rely excessively on the individual brilliance of Suker, Mijatovic, Raul and Roberto Carlos to find their way out of trouble.</p>
<p>Strengths:</p>
<p>Goalkeeper Illgner is a tower of strength at the back, while both his substitutes -- Canizares and Paco Buyo -- would stroll into practically any European club side.</p>
<p>International defender Fernando Hierro is a tower of strength at the back, and is also a danger coming forward through the middle. Hierro's own magnificent set-pieces have had to take a back-seat this season to the extraordinary swirling shots of Brazilian defender Roberto Carlos.</p>
<p>Roberto Carlos also uses his turn of pace to move down the left. Other match-winners are front-men Raul, Mijatovic and Suker.</p>
<p>Real have proved particularly good this season in coming back from early goals.</p>
<p>Weaknesses:</p>
<p>Capello's announcement last week that he would be leaving Real at the end of the season has caused an upheaval within the club that has been difficult to ignore, despite calls for calm from chairman Lorenzo Sanz.</p>
<p>Despite signing Illgner because of Capello's insistence on buying a taller keeper, Real have consistently suffered problems in the air at the back.</p>
<p>Capello has solid performers, but no real match-winners to call upon from the bench, and has no international striker like Barcelona's Pizzi in reserve to call upon in case of need.</p>
<p>Motivation: No special motivation is ever needed for a Real player in the Camp Nou, but no greater incentive could exist than the chance to all-but-clinch the club's 27th league championship.</p>
<p>Probable line-up: Goalkeeper-Bodo Illgner Defenders-Christian Panucci, Fernando Hierro, Rafael Alkorta, Roberto Carlos midfielders-Clarence Seedorf, Fernando Redondo, Raul Gonzalez, Emilio Amavisca strikers-Predrag Mijatovic, Davor Suker.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
