<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568712" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: TENNIS-KRAJICEK OUT OF GERMAN OPEN.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-KRAJICEK OUT OF GERMAN OPEN.</headline>
<dateline>HAMBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Wimbledon champion Richard Krajicek became the fourth seeded player to go out of the German Open when he fell at the first hurdle 6-1 6-1 against Russian Andrei Medvedev on Thursday.</p>
<p>The Dutchman, ranked fifth in the world and seeded three here, has lost both previous slow surface encounters with Medvedev and was overwhelmed in this second-round clash.</p>
<p>Krajicek lasted little more than 50 minutes against his opponent's consistently forcing ground strokes, though the Dutchman appeared less than fully motivated in the unpleasant conditions.</p>
<p>Medvedev began the match in light rain and won his serve to love. Krajicek dropped his service immediately and by the time Medvedev held again to love Krajicek already looked disillusioned.</p>
<p>Krajicek dropped serve again before the rain forced the players off, the Dutchman whacking the side of the umpire's stand in frustration as they did so.</p>
<p>A 20-minute delay was followed by Medvedev quickly wrapping up the first set and breaking immediately.</p>
<p>The match then turned into a procession, punctuated by mutterings and head shakings from Krajicek.</p>
<p>His departure followed the exit earlier in the tournament of Spain's Carlos Moya, seeded four, Switzerland's Marc Rosset, seeded 13, and another Dutch player, Jan Siemerink, seeded 15.</p>
<p>By contrast there were fighting recoveries from a set down on Thursday by both Alex Corretja, the ninth seed, and Sergei Bruguera, seeded 12, increasing the number of Spanish survivors in the last 16 to five.</p>
<p>Corretja beat compatriot Francisco Clavet 3-6 6-4 7-5 while Bruguera overcame American Jeff Tarango 4-6 6-3 6-2.</p>
<p>Two weeks ago Spain had six men in the world's top 20 for the first time. There would have been six Spaniards in the third round here had Alberto Martin managed to convert any of the five match points he held against sixth-seeded South African Wayne Ferreira.</p>
<p>Ferreira, who eventually won 3-6 7-5 7-5, also found the conditions annoying, suffering an unusually high error ratio and once getting a code-of-conduct warning for ball abuse.</p>
<p>Twice on match point at 5-3 Martin failed to put Ferreira second serves back into court and when Ferreira got his break back it was with the help of two Martin double faults.</p>
<p>The sixth seed then broke again in Martin's next service game when the Spaniard forsook his steady baseline game and began to increase his attacks from the net.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAMBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
