<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568717" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: SOCCER-LEVERKUSEN CAN SNATCH TITLE, SAYS DAUM.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-LEVERKUSEN CAN SNATCH TITLE, SAYS DAUM.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Warner</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bayer Leverkusen's outspoken coach Christoph Daum believes his team hold a key psychological advantage over leaders Bayern Munich as an intense run-in to the German championship begins this weekend.</p>
<p>Bayern, boasting a three-point lead over second-placed Leverkusen with four games remaining, should pick up three points on Saturday at home to bottom club Freiburg who are doomed to second division football next season.</p>
<p>But Bayern have slipped up against unglamorous opposition in the past.</p>
<p>Daum, who led VfB Stuttgart to the title in 1992 and is regarded as one of the Bundesliga's best motivators, believes his team could snatch the title because they are not under so much pressure as their richer Bavarian rivals.</p>
<p>&quot;Bayern have everything to lose. They are in a very difficult situation,&quot; he said. &quot;They have to win the title to get back on centre stage again. They have almost taken the championship as read. But often this great will to be successful can hinder you.</p>
<p>&quot;We are getting a lot of energy by just being in the race. We are just looking at each game as it comes. In theory that is the way we can become champions...We have the better cards in our hands.&quot;</p>
<p>After dominating the Bundesliga for much of the 1970s and 1980s, Germany's most glamorous club Bayern have won the title just twice in the 1990s, the last time in 1994.</p>
<p>Their campaign has been loaded with controversy again this season. Germany captain Juergen Klinsmann is leaving the club at the end of the season because he is unhappy with the atmosphere.</p>
<p>The Bavarians have a difficult final four games. After Saturday they must play away twice -- at Hansa Rostock next week and at Borussia Moenchengladbach on the last day of the season on May 31.</p>
<p>Their last game in Munich is a crunch match with third-placed Stuttgart on May 24. VfB still have a chance of the title but are five points behind Bayern in third.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not worried about Bayern's opponents,&quot; Daum said. &quot;Freiburg will put up a good show in Munich, Rostock are strong, Stuttgart are still in the championship race and 'Gladbach will make life difficult for Bayern on the last day.&quot;</p>
<p>By contrast Leverkusen, who just avoided relegation last season, have three home games to play -- against Hamburg on Sunday, lowly St Pauli next week and fifth-placed Bochum on the last day of the season. Their other match is a local derby at Cologne on May 24.</p>
<p>Although they won the UEFA Cup in 1988, Leverkusen have never won the league title. They picked up the only domestic trophy of their history in 1993 when they won the German Cup.</p>
<p>Bayern know they cannot afford to let Leverkusen narrow the gap this weekend. Their German international defender Thomas Helmer is well aware that Freiburg could be awkward opponents.</p>
<p>&quot;They can play without fear. They are much more dangerous to us than some of the top clubs,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
