<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568731" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: FOCUS - ILLOVO MOVES INTO SOUTHERN AFRICA.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - ILLOVO MOVES INTO SOUTHERN AFRICA.</headline>
<byline>Marius Bosch</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African sugar company Illovo Sugar Ltd was set to consolidate its leading position in southern Africa following its acquisition of Lonrho Plc's sugar division for over 1.6 billion rand.</p>
<p>Analysts and industry sources said the deal, which almost doubled Illovo's market capitalisation, was indicative of the company's core strategy to expand into the southern African region -- one of the lowest cost sugar producers in the world.</p>
<p>Illovo said on Thursday it had agreed to buy Lonrho's entire 94.25 percent shareholding in Lonrho Sugar Corp Ltd for 13.90 rand per share in cash, or 1,623.7 million rand.</p>
<p>The acquisition, which ends months of speculation about the future of Lonrho's sugar business, will create Africa's biggest sugar group with interests ranging across southern and East Africa.</p>
<p>Lonrho Sugar has operations in South Africa, Mauritius, Malawi and Swaziland. Illovo, which has a 44 percent domestic market share, owns seven sugar mills in KwaZulu Natal and has recently diversified into Mozambique and Kenya.</p>
<p>&quot;It doubles Illovo's size in the market place and I know that the guys are very excited about it,&quot; an industry source said.</p>
<p>&quot;It obviously underlines Illovo's intention to focus on its core strategy which is sugar downstream products and expansion into Sub-Saharan Africa&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;They consider Lonrho Sugar to be globally competitive and that fits right into (Illovo's) strategy,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>Analysts said the acquisition would give Illovo a more strategic position within the regional sugar industry.</p>
<p>&quot;Prior to this deal, Illovo was pretty much focused on Natal dryland cane.</p>
<p>&quot;Whereas buying in Lonsugar they have immediately captured a more secure strategic positioning within the whole southern African regional industry,&quot; Investec Securities analyst Carolyn Windsor said.</p>
<p>She said Illovo had paid a premium for the Lonrho sugar division but added that this was not unexpected.</p>
<p>Illovo would probably look towards selling the hotel interests of Lonrho's Mauritius-listed company Mon Tresor Mon Desert (MTMD) and could even sell the whole Mauritius operation -- including the sugar assets.</p>
<p>&quot;Certainly hotels is obviously not something that is in their portfolio, so I think they would very much be looking at divesting of the hotel interest.</p>
<p>&quot;I would question whether Illovo is actually going to hold onto the Mauritian side because maybe they can possibly sell that off and then utilise the cash and maybe expand the Malawian interest,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Illovo, which announced last month that it was eyeing Lonrho Sugar, said 1,103 million rand of the purchase price would be financed via an underwritten subscription of 129.76 million new shares at 8.50 rand each.</p>
<p>Analysts said Illovo would probably fund the remainder of the purchase through retained earnings -- which stood at around 476 million rand at the company's last half-year results -- and some borrowing.</p>
<p>The company said the link with Lonrho Sugar would create one of the world's lowest-cost sugar producers, with signfiicant geographic and climatic diversification and access to good water supplies. </p>
<p>&quot;The acquisition of Lonrho Sugar is an extremely exciting development for Illovo and is consistent with our stated strategy to focus on sugar, downstream products and expansion into sub-Saharan Africa,&quot; said managing director Don MacLeod.</p>
<p>The enlarged group will earn 38 percent of revenues from exports while only some 16 percent of revenues will be subject to world market sugar prices.</p>
<p>Windsor said she forecast March 1998 year end earnings for the two companies combined at 117.7 cents per share and would recommend a buy at up to 11 rand a share.</p>
<p>Illovo shares were last trading at 970 cents a share, up 30 cents mainly on news of the Lonrho buy.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom, +27-11 482-1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
