<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568700" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: ICE HOCKEY-SWEDEN BOOK PLACE IN FINAL.</title>
<headline>ICE HOCKEY-SWEDEN BOOK PLACE IN FINAL.</headline>
<byline>Steve Keating</byline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Olympic champions Sweden booked their place in the final and kept Canada's gold medal hopes alive with a 1-0 win over the Czech Republic at the ice hockey world championship on Thursday.</p>
<p>The Swedish victory ended any Czech hopes of retaining the title they won last year in Vienna and left old rivals Russia and Canada to face off on Friday to decide who will play Sweden in the final.</p>
<p>Sweden owe their success to the spectacular shutout goaltending of Tommy Salo, who turned aside all 40 shots directed at him.</p>
<p>&quot;It wasn't a great game for our team but Tommy Salo was great in the net,&quot; said Swedish head coach Kent Forsberg.</p>
<p>&quot;Maybe we were a little lucky but we deserved to win.&quot;</p>
<p>Salo, who plays for the NHL's New York Islanders, was particularly dazzling in the first period when the Czechs bombarded him with 18 shots.</p>
<p>He was almost as good in the scoreless second period and kept his team in the contest until Jorgen Jonsson drifted a low shot from the high slot past a badly screened Roman Cechmanek in the Czech net with a little over eight minutes to play.</p>
<p>It was hard luck on the weary, under-manned Czechs who were coming off a bruising 5-3 win over Canada less than 24 hours earlier.</p>
<p>The Czechs were missing several key players for the pivotal contest, including Robert Lang and Jiri Slegr who received one match suspensions for their part in a brawl.</p>
<p>Vladimir Vujtek, who led the Czechs past Canada with three goals and an assist, was also ruled out with concussion.</p>
<p>But Czech coach Slavomir Lener refused to look for excuses and said: &quot;I'm not going to complain about being short of players.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
