<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568706" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: TENNIS-BECKER, MUSTER, KRAJICEK OUT OF GERMAN OPEN.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-BECKER, MUSTER, KRAJICEK OUT OF GERMAN OPEN.</headline>
<byline>Richard Eaton</byline>
<dateline>HAMBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Boris Becker's comeback shuddered to a halt amid the wind and rain at the German Open on Thursday, beaten 7-6 6-2 by Spain's Felix Mantilla, while the top-seeded Thomas Muster was blown away 6-1 6-2 by a storm of brilliance from a 23-year-old Moroccan Hicham Arazi.</p>
<p>Six seeds failed to reach their places in the quarter-finals in a tournament which has provided ingloriously rapid dismissals for some other famous names.</p>
<p>Wimbledon champion Richard Krajicek, seeded three,  lost 6-1 6-1 to Andrei Medvedev and Wayne Ferreira, the sixth seed, went down 6-1 6-3 to Sergei Bruguera of Spain.</p>
<p>At least Becker had his moments. The three-times Wimbledon champion held a point to win the first set before going out 7-6 (8-6) 6-2 to the patiently rallying Mantilla, one of three Spaniards to make the quarter-finals.</p>
<p>The German might have done still better had not rain delayed the match for almost an hour with the score at 6-6 in the tie-break. At that stage Becker was creating some attacking momentum in slippery, gusty conditions which hindered a serve-volleyer most of all.</p>
<p>On the resumption, Becker twice approached the net a little ambitiously and saw two fluent backhands from Mantilla go past him.</p>
<p>First set captured, the Spaniard gained in confidence, and Mantilla's superior ground strokes increasingly assumed control of the contest. Becker, who the day before had achieved his first win for 11 weeks in only his second tournament since aggravating a wrist injury, was left to contemplate what might have been. &quot;The match was a bit different after the break,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Mantilla next plays Arazi, who can rarely have played better than while ousting clay court king Muster on his favourite surface.</p>
<p>Arazi covered the court with great speed and intelligently mixed teasing backhand slices with bouts of brilliant hitting.</p>
<p>He also launched fierce ambushes with sudden changes of pace on his serve and several times saw his shots skid off the line-tapes on important points. &quot;I played without thinking,&quot; he said. &quot;I couldn't understand what was happening. It was a very good day though I was a bit lucky, and at the end of the match I was always touching the lines.&quot;</p>
<p>Krajicek departed with hardly a whimper.  The world number five seemed quite unable to adapt to the conditions and delayed the progress of Medvedev, who had won both their previous contests on slow surfaces, little more than 50 minutes.</p>
<p>The eighth-ranked Chilean Marcelo Rios, trying to make his way back after a thigh injury, also looked well below par as he went out 6-4 6-1 to Spain's Alberto Berasategui.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAMBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
