<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568722" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: SOCCER-NICE SEEK TO EMERGE FROM SHADOW OF 1950S GREATS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-NICE SEEK TO EMERGE FROM SHADOW OF 1950S GREATS.</headline>
<byline>Etienne Ballerini</byline>
<dateline>NICE, France 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The exploits of  great Nice sides of the past have been well publicised all week as the club prepare to meet Guingamp in the French Cup Final on Saturday.</p>
<p>But it is a bitter-sweet occasion for the club. They have just been relegated from the French first division, but could yet be playing in Europe if they win the cup for the first time since 1954.</p>
<p>The Nice-Matin newspaper has run a series on the likes of Argentine-born Pancho Gonzales and Just Fontaine, key figures of the 1950s when the club won the Cup and League Double (1952), the league four times (1951, 1952, 1956, 1959) and cup twice (1952 and 1954).</p>
<p>For good measure the 1978 team which lost the final to Nancy have also been remembered.</p>
<p>&quot;We get the impression we don't exist,&quot; more than one player has said.</p>
<p>Coach Silvester Takac said: &quot;It's not right. But perhaps this will give them extra determination.&quot;</p>
<p>Takac's squad, meanwhile, have trained hard this week, putting in extra hours as they look to save an otherwise disastrous season by lifting the cup for the third time.</p>
<p>Deep in debt at the end of last season, Nice sold their best players and bought late and badly for this season.</p>
<p>&quot;The team started with a handicap of six to seven points,&quot; Takac, who took charge this season, said.</p>
<p>When they only managed one point in their opening seven games, including a 2-1 loss away to Guingamp, their rivals on Saturday, the die was cast.</p>
<p>But the cup has been their saving grace and they can take heart from the fact that their cup run has captured thir fans' imagination.</p>
<p>There will be more Nice fans, some 10,000 at the Parc des Princes in Paris on Saturday, than at any of their home games in the Stade du Ray in the league this season or the 1978 final with a far better team near the top of the first division.</p>
<p>But one deserving Nicois who could miss his biggest rendezvous since starting is career at the club 13 years ago and made his first division debut in 1985 is defender Jean-Philppe Mattio.</p>
<p>Mattio, injured at Lyon eight days ago, said: &quot;There's a 40 percent chance I'll play, it's heartbreaking for me that after spending all my career at Nice, at 32 I should miss a chance that no doubt will not be repeated.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm going to do everything possible not to say goodbye to the final.&quot;</p>
<p>Another player who rose through the ranks at Nice, midfielder Frederic Gioria, summed up the feelings of the locals when he said: &quot;I'd even say I have an account to settle because of the all the expectation generated by this final in the city. The club hasn't won anything for 40 years.&quot;</p>
<p>Confidant midfielder Frederic Tatarian, who has been in fine form lately, said: &quot;We're going to win the cup.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm convinced of that because we want to prove many things. The pressure favours us and if we do it that's what will remain of our season and we'll forget the relegation.&quot;</p>
<p>The much travelled Yugoslav-born Takac has played a far bigger part than Nice's league record might suggest in getting the team to the final.</p>
<p>&quot;I quickly understood that there was a squad ... victim of a situation of decline at the club and not responsible for that situation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was necessary to help them rediscover as quickly as possible their identity, their morale, encourage them.</p>
<p>&quot;It was too late in the championship, but the quality of their football was improving. We were never ridiculed against Monaco, Marseille, Bordeaux or Strasbourg,&quot; the former Vojvodina, Rennes and Standard Liege player said.</p>
<p>&quot;The French Cup was the opportunity and that's where we transferred our moral strength.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
