<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568761" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: LOVESICK ROMANIAN LINKS FUTURE TO NATO DATE.</title>
<headline>LOVESICK ROMANIAN LINKS FUTURE TO NATO DATE.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Romanians' political obsession that their country will be left out of the first wave of NATO expansion has even come to invade their love lives.</p>
<p>&quot;Come to me on the first wave,&quot; ran the entry in the lonely hearts column of this week's edition of the satirical newspaper Academia Catavencu.</p>
<p>&quot;I'll be here for you until we join NATO. But I may no longer be here for a second wave, that is, 20 years from now.&quot;</p>
<p>Romania is lobbying hard to win an invitation along with more advanced candidates Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic when the Alliance announces its first eastward expansion at a summit in Madrid in July.</p>
<p>Opinion polls show more than 80 percent of Romanians want their country to join NATO now rather than in a second wave of enlargement, which they fear might never come.</p>
<p>Virtually every day sees a new, impassioned spin-off from the campaign in eastern Europe's only Latin country.</p>
<p>Several hundred pro-NATO &quot;revolutionaries&quot;, veterans of the 1989 uprising which ousted dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, marched through central Bucharest towards the U.S. embassy on Thursday urging Washington to throw its weight behind Romania.</p>
<p>One private television channel has launched a lottery, with viewers buying tickets for the equivalent of less than $1 and answering questions related to Romania's NATO bid.</p>
<p>Winners are promised cash prizes, luxury cars and places on a cavalcade of buses bound for Madrid for the July summit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
