<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568797" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: INTERVIEW - HOIUPANK EYES UKRAINIAN MARKET.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - HOIUPANK EYES UKRAINIAN MARKET.</headline>
<byline>Eva Palu</byline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hoiupank, which has already said it wants to expand to Lithuania, is also considering how to start activities in Ukraine, chairman Olari Taal said.</p>
<p>In interview late Wednesday, Taal told Reuters that some of the bank's board members went to Ukraine at the start of this week to get introduced to the market.</p>
<p>&quot;Lots of our clients have started business with Ukraine and we need to follow our clients,&quot; Taal told Reuters.</p>
<p>Taal said Hoiupank also signed some protocols but that they do not oblige the bank to anything. He would not specify what the documents were.</p>
<p>Hoiupank, the third largest bank in Estonia, has said it wants to expand out of the dynamic but small Estonian market.</p>
<p>It has been in talks with Lithuanian banks and is also eyeing the market in Latvia.</p>
<p>Asked whether the bank wants to set up a branch office in Ukraine or acquire some stake in a local bank, Taal said there are many possiblities.</p>
<p>He added that negotiations were proceeding but did not mention any names.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not rule out that news from Ukraine will come quicker than from Lithuania,&quot; Taal added.</p>
<p>Hoiupank has said it will announce some news on its planned Lithuania move by St John's Day, June 24. It has said it will also announce plans for the Latvian market by that time.</p>
<p>Hoiupank has said it that it will enter the Latvian market through its subsidiaries.</p>
<p>Taal confirmed the news and added that the bank was also looking at the chance to buy a Latvian securities company.</p>
<p>Most Estonian banks have said they are investigating the Lithuanian market.</p>
<p>Hansapank , the largest bank in Estonia, has already opened business in Latvia while Tallinna Pank has bought a 20 percent stake in Latvia's Saules Bank.</p>
<p>-- Eva Palu, Tallinn Newsroom, +372 630 8400, reuters@reuters.ee</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LITH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81403">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
