<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568795" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: PRESS DIGEST - RUSSIA - MAY 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - RUSSIA - MAY 8.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the leading stories in Russian newspapers this morning. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>KOMMERSANT DAILY</p>
<p>- A regional court has ruled in favour of group of shareholders of Russian steelmaker Novolipetsk Metals Combine. They will now receive seats on the board of directors of the plant.</p>
<p>- The Russian Cental Bank-appointed administration has revealed a number of violations by Suprimeksbank which might lead to revoking the bank's licences.</p>
<p>- The question of libiralisation of gold export was discussed and supported by the two first deputy prime ministers during the government meeting on Wednesday.</p>
<p>- A new vision of the national security concept has been approved by Russia's Security Council, but no details have been published yet.</p>
<p>- Russian President Boris Yeltsin hopes to solve all remaining disputes during his meeting with the Belarus leader Alexander Lukashenko on May 23 and to sign a charter on forming a union between their two Slav former Soviet republics.</p>
<p>- Fresh talks on the status of the documnet defining Russia-NATO relations will be held in Moscow next week.</p>
<p>SEVODNYA</p>
<p>- Russia's main diamond producer, Almazy Rossii-Sakha, will export gems worth $180 million by the end of May, according to a government decree.</p>
<p>- The Moscow city government is likely to approve a law on renting and leasing land in the capital.</p>
<p>NEZAVISIMAYA GAZETA</p>
<p>- May 9, Victory Day, is one of the Russia's favourite holidays because former Soviet citizens can experience the pleasant feeling of being victors, says the paper.</p>
<p>- Rem Vyakhirev, head of Gazprom, holds top place in a list of the 50 most influencial businessmen of Russia, according to the paper's independent survey.</p>
<p>- Russia's Security Service has uncovered about 30 spies from foreign intelligence services since 1996, says a top Russian intelligence officer.</p>
<p>SOVIETSKAYA ROSSIYA</p>
<p>- First Mikhail Gorbachev, then his successor Boris Yeltsin betrayed the Great Victory and &quot;home-grown&quot; democrats succeeded in what Adolf Hitler had failed to do, communist leader Gennady Zuganov says in an address to the World War Two veterans in connection with Victory Day, celebrated on May 9.</p>
<p>MOSKOVSKY KOMSOMOLETS</p>
<p>- A former military plant will produce about 2,000 black cabs a year for the Moscow taxi service under a Russo-British project.</p>
<p>--Tatyana Ustinova, Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
