<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568723" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: SOCCER SHOWCASE-TITLE RAISES HIGH STAKES IN BARCA-REAL CLASH.</title>
<headline>SOCCER SHOWCASE-TITLE RAISES HIGH STAKES IN BARCA-REAL CLASH.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The traditionally high stakes in the big Barcelona-Real Madrid game will be even higher than normal in this Saturday's eagerly-awaited clash.</p>
<p>With six games left to play and Real eight points clear at the top, anything but a win for Barcelona would virtually hand the Madrid side their 27th Spanish league title.</p>
<p>The importance of the match is accentuated by the fact that final standings are determined not by goal difference but by the results of matches between the teams in the regular season.</p>
<p>Real outplayed their arch-rivals in December's 2-0 win in the Santiago Bernabeu stadium, meaning that a 1-0 victory for Barcelona on Saturday would still leave Bobby Robson's side having to make up six points in just five games.</p>
<p>But a bigger home win could turn the tables and destabilize a Real outfit that is already wracked by internal problems.</p>
<p>The league-leaders are still reeling from last week's announcement by coach Fabio Capello that he would leave Real at the end of the season.</p>
<p>Capello and club chairman Lorenzo Sanz seem to have agreed to moderate their comments after several angry clashes, but the tension at the club remains.</p>
<p>And all too fresh in the memory of Real fans are the two league titles handed to Barcelona in defeats at Tenerife in the last game of successive seasons.</p>
<p>&quot;What happened at Tenerife could be repeated,&quot; said Barcelona chairman Jose Luis Nunez.</p>
<p>Nunez, who celebrated 19 years in charge of the Catalan side earlier this week, is aware that he may shortly face re-election, and that there is no campaign slogan better than a win over Real.</p>
<p>Barcelona have got through to the final of both the Cup Winners' Cup and the Spanish Cup -- with wins over both Real and Atletico Madrid included.</p>
<p>But Nunez knows his fans won't be satisfied unless Barcelona secure Spain's second European Cup place.</p>
<p>And defeat by Real could set Bobby Robson's men into a downward spiral in a frantic run-in that includes clashes with both their rivals for a berth in the continent's most prestitigios competition -- Deportivo Coruna and Real Betis.</p>
<p>Nunez is also smarting from criticism for his handling of the renegotiations of contracts for star strikers Ronaldo and Luis Figo.</p>
<p>Hardly a day passes without the Spanish press naming a new Italian, English or Brazilian suitor for Ronaldo.</p>
<p>Barca fans are particularly unnerved by occasional reports linking the Brazilian prodigy to arch-rivals Real.</p>
<p>The obvious scapegoat for Nunez's problems could be Robson.</p>
<p>From the start the former England manager has had problems with fans at the Camp Nou stadium who would like to see him use a more attacking team.</p>
<p>Part of Robson's difficulties are not of his own doing.</p>
<p>By replacing Johan Cruyff, Robson jumped into a lions' den of fans who had idolised the Dutchman in his eight-year reign at the Camp Nou.</p>
<p>But Robson may take heart from a lesson that Cruyff learned back in 1989, when his side recovered from an early goal down to beat Real 3-1.</p>
<p>Cruyff had looked on the brink of being fired before the game, but saved his job with the win. Despite surrendering that season's championship he went on to clinch four successive titles -- two of them snatched from under the noses of arch-rivals Real.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
