<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568756" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: FEATURE-CZECH GOVT COULD FACE FIGHT OVER WAGE CUT PLAN.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-CZECH GOVT COULD FACE FIGHT OVER WAGE CUT PLAN.</headline>
<byline>Jan Lopatka</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Czech government, eager to control runaway wages at a time of slowing economic growth, could face a tough battle with labour unions which might force it to water down its plans.</p>
<p>The cabinet last month announced a package of measures intended to kick-start the economy, including a plan to cut wage growth in the state sector to 7.3 percent this year from the originally planned 12.</p>
<p>The government also wants to renegotiate a deal giving railway workers a 17 percent pay hike agreed after a five-day national strike in February.</p>
<p>&quot;The government will have big troubles managing it and keeping social peace. The unions are already sharpening their teeth,&quot; said political analyst Jiri Pehe.</p>
<p>Economists have identified wage growth as a key problem in the economy.</p>
<p>Nominal industrial wages grew 14.6 percent year-on-year in March and 13.4 percent in the first quarter of this year after soaring 18 percent in the whole of last year.</p>
<p>Central bank governor Josef Tosovsky said in March that the economy could not afford a wage rise of more than 10 percent in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;Industry is roughly 35 percent of the economy so this will be very difficult to achieve,&quot; said economic researcher Jiri Krovak of WoodCommerz.</p>
<p>COMPROMISE, OR STRIKES PREDICTED</p>
<p>Analysts said it was likely that the government would have to come to a compromise on wage growth or face strikes on the railways and in other sectors. Loss-making Czech Railways is the country's largest employer with some 101,000 staff.</p>
<p>&quot;The ink is still fresh on our collective agreement. It would be illegal for the government to touch it,&quot; Jiri Kratochvil, deputy head of the railway unions, told Reuters. &quot;If it does, we obviously will do everything we can.&quot;</p>
<p>Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus has said that the deal will have to renegotiated, but Kratochvil said neither the government nor the railway management had approached the unions directly.</p>
<p>&quot;A rail strike would be a hit to growth, and that is the last thing you want when the economy is already turning down,&quot; said Jack Schrantz, head of research at Raiffeisen Capital and Investment.</p>
<p>&quot;I think in the end there will be a compromise solution as opposed to implementing extremely small wage increases. I think they will meet somewhere in the middle ground to avoid massive protests,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The government plan would effectively freeze real wages.</p>
<p>LARGE DEFICITS LEAD TO CUT IN GROWTH FORECASTS</p>
<p>A slowdown in industrial output, exports and tax collection early this year led the state budget and the trade balance into large deficits which prompted the cabinet to cut its growth forecast to 2.7 percent this year from 5.4 percent.</p>
<p>April's measures include a 20 percent import deposit requirement, budget cuts nearing five percent of spending, and cleaning up the capital markets.</p>
<p>The Czech Republic had enjoyed a long period of social peace and the rail strike was the most serious labour unrest to hit the country since the 1989 fall of communism.</p>
<p>Czechs were ready to sacrifice material comfort in the early days of reform and living standards improved during the last four years of demand-led growth.</p>
<p>But Pehe said Czechs were not ready to sacrifice much more. &quot;I can see no source of social energy which would make people agree to stop loosening their belts.</p>
<p>&quot;The government was not convincing (in announcing economic measures), also because it did not make personnel changes (in the cabinet).&quot;</p>
<p>CRACKS IN CONSENSUS</p>
<p>Cracks in the social consensus began to appear last year, with teachers and doctors going on warning strikes since to demand pay hikes as their salaries dropped behind the national average.</p>
<p>Pehe said that the centre-right three-party governing coalition could even collapse under the pressure of any serious labour unrest because the junior partner, the centrist Christan Democrats (KDU-CSL), had appeared less than fully committed to the government package.</p>
<p>&quot;(KDU-CSL chairman) Josef Lux criticised (the government package) as too liberal, leaving the back door open for him...to leave. There is a realistic scenario that the government will either not keep to its promises or fall apart.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
