<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568764" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: INTERVIEW - HANSA SEES LATVIAN DEBT MARKET PICKING UP.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - HANSA SEES LATVIAN DEBT MARKET PICKING UP.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The scope of instruments available on Latvia's emerging debt market is set to increase as companies seek to improve their liquidity situation, an analyst said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;There are not too many debt instruments in Latvia now...there is government debt, the overnight market, and Merita Bank's bond issue,&quot; Maris Vinklers, head of the money markets unit at Hansabank-Latvija, told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Hansabank-Latvija is part of Estonia's largest bank, Hansapank .</p>
<p>&quot;But we expect to see more becoming available in the future,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect, in the next few months, to see commercial paper and bonds issued by corporates in Latvia,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The first issue should be out soon...at first, the maturities will only be short-term,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Vinklers said that commercial banks would lead the way but that other corporate issues would probably soon follow.</p>
<p>&quot;This will increase liquidity on the market, which is needed, and also help to attract foreign investment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Neighbouring Estonia has a relatively active commercial paper market with about 500 million kroons worth issued to date.</p>
<p>Like Latvia, Lithuania has no commercial paper market to speak of.</p>
<p>-- Ed Stoddard, Riga newsroom +371 721 52 40</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
