<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568790" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: ALMOST HALF OF SHARES IN FOREIGN HANDS.</title>
<headline>ALMOST HALF OF SHARES IN FOREIGN HANDS.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Almost half of Latvia's blue chip market is owned by foreign legal entities and investment funds, the central depository said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Our statistics on the investor structure show that more than half of the shareholders in leading stocks are foreign legal entities and funds, which is a postive showing,&quot; Martinsh Rikshis, president of the depository, told a news conference.</p>
<p>Leading Riga bourse companies show 41 percent of their shares in the hands of foreign legal entities and some seven percent owned by investment funds.</p>
<p>He said the data referred to the situation in April ahead of shareholder meetings.</p>
<p>The central depository also referred to the risks for the market involved in a high foreign ownerhsip.</p>
<p>Rikshis said that one of the reasons behind the dramatically low volumes on the bourse over the last two months was partly due to big foreign investors leaving for the U.S. market.</p>
<p>Some 10 percent of blue chips are controlled by Latvian legal entities and some 38 percent by resident individuals.</p>
<p>Riga Transport Fleet registered the highest foreign ownership at 75 percent and leading bank Unibanka was 33 percent foreign owned, the depository said.</p>
<p>One of the leading investors in RTF is the shipping company Lavinia while the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) and Swedfund are the main foreign shareholders in Unibanka.</p>
<p>-- Martinsh Gravitis, Riga Newsroom, +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
