<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568803" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: PRESS DIGEST - BULGARIA - MAY 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - BULGARIA - MAY 8.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the main stories in Sofia newspapers today. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>TRUD</p>
<p>-- The state-owned Bulgarian Telecommunication Company (BTC) is expected to raise its stake in the Bulgarian-Greek Bulfon telecommunication joint venture to 34 percent from 32 percent, private Balkan news agency said.</p>
<p>Greece's Intracom is the BTC partner in Bulfon.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's cabinet is expected to raise central heating prices two-fold by October, Energy ministry officials said.</p>
<p>STANDART</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's new parliament held its first session after the parliamentary elections on April 19 and elected Yordan Sokolov from the centre-right Union of Democratic Forces as parliament speaker.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria is expected to sell all its state-owned industrial plants by the end of 1998, deputy prime minister Alexander Bozhkov said.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria will call a tender by the end of the week for importing 50,000 tonnes of bread wheat to help cover its grain shortage until the new crop, deputy Agriculture minister Alexander Rangelov said.</p>
<p>PARI</p>
<p>-- The Bulgarian-Spanish consortium Marvex signed an agreement with Bulgaria's Privatisation Agency to buy 70 percent of Devnya Cement plant for $44.5 million, the agency said.</p>
<p>-- A criminal investigation was launched against seven senior executives of Bulgaria's private Central Cooperative Bank for siphoning some $6 million from a deposit account of the Russian private firm Blonde Investment International in 1994, the director of the National Investigation Service Boiko Rashkov said.</p>
<p>-- Bulgaria's Privatisation agency said it had sold a 57 percent stake in the state-owned non-ferrous metals processor OZM-Sofia to Bulmetal for $2.5 million.</p>
<p>24 CHASA</p>
<p>-- The central bank was expected to cut its main interest rate to 5.5 percent monthly from the current 6.2 percent, effective on Monday, in line with the falling yield of short-term discount government securities auctioned this week, central bank officials said.</p>
<p>-- The regional governor of Bulgaria's Black Sea city of Varna said he would call a tender for renting 14 local beach strips. -- Sofia Newsroom, (++359-2) 91188</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
