<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568869" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: New UK ministers forgo 1997 pay rise.</title>
<headline>New UK ministers forgo 1997 pay rise.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Members of British Prime Minister Tony Blair's cabinet agreed at their first meeting on Thursday to forgo the pay rise they were due this year, government officials said.</p>
<p>Finance minister Gordon Brown pledged when Labour was in opposition that the cabinet would not take the pay rise, and Blair told his ministers it was important for them to keep all the promises they had made.</p>
<p>The decision means Blair will not take 41,443 pounds ($67,200) of his 143,860 pound-salary ($233,000) this year, while other cabinet ministers will forgo 16,009 pounds of their 103,860-pound pay.</p>
<p>The officials said the pay freeze would only last this year. The pay rises were recommended by an independent review board and accepted by the previous Conservative government.</p>
<p>Officials described the mood of the inaugural cabinet meeting as serious and business-like, but Blair insisted that his ministers call each other by their first names and not by titles.</p>
<p>The cabinet agreed on a legislative programme of more than 20 bills to be announced in the Queen's speech next Wednesday's.</p>
<p>Officials said the centrepiece would be two bills on education, including a short bill to reduce primary-school class sizes, which the government expect to become law before the summer recess.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
