<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568863" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Studies narrow down how long drugs needed for HIV.</title>
<headline>Studies narrow down how long drugs needed for HIV.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>People infected with the HIV virus that causes AIDS received good news and bad news on Thursday -- drugs can probably kill off the virus but it will take years.</p>
<p>A flurry of studies showed that the cocktail approach using a combination of strong drugs can probably eventually get to every infected cell in the body, but it will take three years or more of the expensive and unpleasant treatment.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be wrong to believe that we are close to a cure for AIDS,&quot; Dr David Ho of the Aaron Diamond AIDS Research Center at Rockefeller University in New York and colleagues wrote in a report in the science journal Nature.</p>
<p>&quot;Given the high cost and toxicity of prolonged combination therapy, new strategies must be developed to facilitate the extinction of those viral 'embers' that could rekindle the infection.&quot;</p>
<p>Ho's team used a mathematical model to predict it would take 2.3 to 3.1 years, possibly more, to eliminate HIV from the immune system cells it attacks.</p>
<p>But scientists said the only way to truly know would be to watch people actually infected with HIV and see what happened.</p>
<p>&quot;A blunt personal view is never to think you've outsmarted HIV,&quot; Simon Wain-Hobson of the Institut Pasteur in Paris wrote in a commentary in Nature.</p>
<p>Robert Siliciano of the Johns Hopkins School of Medicine in Baltimore and colleagues looked at the cells that HIV lives in -- the CD4 immune system cells -- in 14 HIV-infected volunteers.</p>
<p>They found HIV persisted in about 0.05 percent of all the resting, or temporarily inactive, CD4 cells.</p>
<p>&quot;These are the cells that are the long-term reservoir of the virus. They are not affected by drugs -- drugs only affect the virus during the replicative cycle,&quot; Siliciano said in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;The good news is there aren't very many of these cells. The bad news is they can persist for a very long period of time.&quot;</p>
<p>Siliciano's work indicates that HIV needs only to hide in a very few CD4 cells -- maybe just one.</p>
<p>&quot;The presumption is that a single infected cell, once activated, can produce enough virus cells to start the whole thing going again,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Researchers at the University of Minnesota reported in the journal Science that they had found the combination therapy got to infected cells in the lymph nodes --one of the suspected &quot;reservoirs&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's good news,&quot; said Dr Winston Cavert, one of the authors.</p>
<p>Scientists knew the drugs reduced the virus in blood by 99 percent, but were not sure HIV was not lurking somewhere else in the body, like the lymph nodes.</p>
<p>Two studies in the New England Journal of Medicine looked at newborns. One concluded that a combination of three drugs could reduce the amount of HIV in their blood without causing serious side-effects.</p>
<p>A second found that babies with the highest levels of HIV had a bigger risk of quickly developing one of the immunity-related diseases that are the hallmarks of AIDS.</p>
<p>Their findings raised the possibility that early treatment with new anti-HIV drugs may slow or prevent the development of AIDS in infants born to HIV-positive mothers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
