<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568892" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Jaded Kasparov draws again with chess supercomputer.</title>
<headline>Jaded Kasparov draws again with chess supercomputer.</headline>
<byline>Grant McCool</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Human fatigue robbed world chess champion Garry Kasparov of a win in the fourth game of his re-match against the supercomputer Deep Blue on Wednesday and he had to settle for a draw in a complicated endgame.</p>
<p>The second consecutive draw between the world's best chess player and the IBM programme left the six-game match tied at two points each. One point is awarded for a win and a 1/2 point for a draw.</p>
<p>Kasparov, playing with the black pieces, sacrificed a pawn in the middlegame and then manoeuvred to the draw in a complex endgame with only rooks and a few pawns left on the board.</p>
<p>&quot;I think I outplayed the machine and I thought it was a very nice sacrifice. I missed something in the time trouble,&quot; said Kasparov, who had to play swiftly to reach the first time allotment of 40 moves in two hours.</p>
<p>The draw was agreed after the program's 56th move and just more than five hours play. &quot;I believe it was a win for black, I was tired and I couldn't figure it out,&quot; a subdued Kasparov told an audience of hundreds of spectators who watched the game on close-circuit TV in a Manhattan office complex.</p>
<p>He paced around the playing room repeatedly in between moves, grimaced at the board, drummed his fingers on the table and held his head in his hands during another long game that required intense concentration.</p>
<p>Kasparov surprised some expert observers because once again he declined the temptation to play in his usual creative and attacking style.</p>
<p>The 34-year-old has failed to stamp his authority on the $1.1 million contest, although he won the first game on Saturday with finesse. He then resigned needlessly in Sunday's second game and was held to a draw in the third on Tuesday despite having the advantage of the white pieces and the first move.</p>
<p>The winner over six games will collect $700,000 in prize money and the loser $400,000.</p>
<p>Kasparov, considered by most experts to be the strongest player in chess history, defeated the system with three wins, two draws and one loss in Philadelphia in February 1996. The score was 2-2 at the same juncture in the match last year.</p>
<p>Kasparov replied to Deep Blue's opening king's pawn move with the Prybl Defence or Czech opening that is not often used in top level play. It is named after Czech International Master Joseph Prybl, who specialises in the system.</p>
<p>The Russian sacrificed a pawn on his 20th move and was able to keep tactical complications to a minimum until deep into the endgame, when the programme eventually gave the pawn back to equalise the material.</p>
<p>&quot;I never saw a line that led to a clear win, Deep Blue certainly knew it was behind but never saw a clear loss,&quot; said Murray Campbell, one of the scientists who developed the machine.</p>
<p>Kasparov made a remarkable and rare miscalculation when he resigned the second game in a drawn position, the first time in his immensely succesful career that this has occurred.</p>
<p>The realisation that Kasparov had missed an opportunity to save himself from defeat on Sunday did not dawn on the chess world until well after the end of the game. The sequence that would have led to a draw was discovered by an untitled player in the Internet Chess Club and confirmed by hours of analysis.</p>
<p>Deep Blue's programers also said the computer had not evaluated the situation correctly.</p>
<p>The competition is part chess match and part research project to help develop computers that can make complex, simultaneous calculations for applications such as weather forecasting, air traffic control and molecular dynamics.</p>
<p>Deep Blue is an IBM RS/6000 SP parallel processor with specialised microchips for chess. It can calculate hundreds of millions of moves per second and its software has been modified to include more chess knowledge.</p>
<p>The fifth and sixth games of the match were scheduled for Saturday and Sunday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
