<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568820" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: London shares soar to new record, dlr sags.</title>
<headline>London shares soar to new record, dlr sags.</headline>
<byline>Ron Askew</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in London soared to a new closing high on Thursday for the fifth session in a row, galvanised by Wall Street which rallied strongly after making hefty overnight losses.</p>
<p>The dollar ended over a pfennig and a yen lower in Europe as jitters about Japanese foreign exchange intervention buoyed the yen, but with most of Europe, London apart, closed for the Ascension Day holiday trade was thin.</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 index leapt 42.9 points, almost one percent, to close at 4,580.4, having spent much of the day little changed after recouping the early 20 point losses it made on the back of Wall Street's near 140 point overnight slide. The expected weaker start in New York on Thursday turned out to be short-lived and UK shares were led higher by the surpruse U.S. rally. The Dow had climbed 46 points by the London close.</p>
<p>Traders said sentiment was still underpinned by the new Labour government's decision earlier this week to give the central bank greater freedom in setting interest rate policy.</p>
<p>The rise also flew in the face of a profit-warning from Britain's biggest industrial conglomerate, BTR Plc, which ended with a 38 pence loss at 229-1/2 pence after saying that the pound's strength could knock 300 million pounds off its first-half profits.</p>
<p>&quot;The last couple of days we have seen a few profit warnings and downgrades in some pretty significant stocks,&quot; said Ian Williams, UK equity strategist at Panmure Gordon. &quot;But the market just keeps on going up, which shows how strong it is.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There was massive relief that Wall Street didn't come off this afternoon, after yesterday's fall,&quot; commented one trader.</p>
<p>The market had managed to shake off the disappointing U.S. performance as sentiment remained firm. There was also talk that some UK strategists were preparing to upgrade their year-end forecasts after the FTSE's recent record run.</p>
<p>&quot;The market has been very resilient given the fall on Wall Street and the profit warning from BTR,&quot; said one dealer. &quot;We had a predictable mark-down, but the buyers came back in force.&quot;</p>
<p>In currencies, the yen's recovery was being fuelled by what many perceived as thinly-veiled official warnings that further yen weakness would be opposed.</p>
<p>&quot;The Japanese are warming us up for the fact that interest rates there may change,&quot; said Tony Norfield at ABN Amro.</p>
<p>Norfield, who is a treasury economist at ABN Amro, said the Japanese authorities have clearly allowed market interest rates to tick higher as well reminding traders the Bank of Japan has $220 billion of reserves with which to defend their currency.</p>
<p>&quot;This has seen Japanese investors cut a lot of overseas bond positions and was probably partly behind sterling's fall today too,&quot; said Norfield.</p>
<p>At 1530 GMT, the dollar was trading at 123.80 yen compared with 124.93 late Wednesday. Against the mark, it was trading at 1.7065 compared with 1.7210 late yesterday.</p>
<p>The yen's latest push higher was based on comments from senior Japanese Ministry of Finance official, Eisuke Sakakibara -- known in the markets as &quot;Mr. Yen.&quot; Sakakibara said that on past performances the dollar/yen's average annual range could allow its scope to as low as 103 yen this year.</p>
<p>&quot;For a man as clued-in to the market as Sakakibara, you don't mention specific levels like that without knowing their likely impact,&quot; said a trader at a U.S. house here.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, another Ministry of Finance official said Japan was prepared to use its huge foreign exchange reserves promptly if the yen continued to weaken exessively.</p>
<p>Sterling was a big loser in early trading, after a news report cited a ruling British Labour Party source as saying a return to Europe's exchange rate mechanism at a central rate of 2.50 marks by 2001 was possible. Sterling was trading about 2.82 marks before the report and fell as low as 2.7654, though it ended at 2.7630.</p>
<p>The British Treasury later denied the talk but analysts said the more Euro-friendly tone of the new government would keep talk of a lower sterling target in the market. Others say interest rate speculation is shifting against the pound and the government will be happy with a weaker pound. STOCK CLOSING PRICES</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 was up 42.9 points at 4,580.4.</p>
<p>The Paris CAC-40 index was closed for Ascension Day. It ended down 8.62 points at 2,643.31 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Frankfurt's DAX index was also closed for Ascension Day. It ended down 16.30 points at 3,551.98 on Wednesday</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 1530 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar closed at 1.7065 marks compared with 1.7210 late in Europe on Wednesday. It was at 123.80 yen compared with 124.93.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold was fixed $343.90 in the afternoon after closing at $340.85 an ounce in London on Wednesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
