<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568832" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Reuters historical calendar - May 15.</title>
<headline>Reuters historical calendar - May 15.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the major events to have occurred on May 15 in history:</p>
<p>1004 - Henry II, the last Saxon ruler of Germany, was crowned king of Lombardy following the defeat of Arduin of Ivrea. The city of Pavia rioted at the news.</p>
<p>1567 - Mary, Queen of Scots married James Hepburn, Earl of Bothwell, at Holyrood Palace in Edinburgh just three months after the death of her former husband King Henry who was assassinated.</p>
<p>1718 - James Puckle, a London lawyer, patented the world's first machine gun.</p>
<p>1800 - King George III survived a second assassination attempt when James Hadfield fired a shot during a performance at the Drury Lane Theatre, London.</p>
<p>1847 - Daniel O'Connell, Irish Catholic leader known as &quot;The Liberator&quot;, died in Italy. By his win in an 1828 election in County Clare, he forced the British government to accept Roman Catholics in parliament.</p>
<p>1860 - Giuseppe Garibaldi with one thousand volunteers heavily defeated the superior Neapolitan army under General Landi at the Battle of Calatafimi.</p>
<p>1886 - Emily Dickinson, U.S. poet, died. She wrote at least 800 poems, all but five of which remained unpublished until after her death.</p>
<p>1905 - Joseph Cotten, U.S. stage and screen actor, born. Notable in the films &quot;Citizen Kane&quot;, &quot;The Third Man&quot; and &quot;Portrait of Jennie&quot; for which he won a best actor award in Venice.</p>
<p>1909 - James Mason, British film actor, born. In films from 1935, he was best known for his roles in &quot;Odd Man Out&quot;, &quot;The Desert Fox&quot; and &quot;Lolita&quot;.</p>
<p>1916 - In Italy, Asiago fell when Austrian troops under von Hotzendorf attacked the Italian front along the Trentino.</p>
<p>1918 - The world's first airmail postal service began between New York, Philadelphia and Washington, using planes supplied by the U.S. War Department.</p>
<p>1934 - Karlis Ulmanis seized dictatorial power in a coup d'etat in Latvia.</p>
<p>1936 - Amy Johnson arrived in Croydon, England after a record-breaking return flight from South Africa taking just four days and 16 hours.</p>
<p>1940 - Nylon stockings went on sale for the first time in the United States.</p>
<p>1940 - The Dutch army surrendered to Nazi Germany.</p>
<p>1941 - Britain's first jet-propelled aircraft, the Gloster-Whittle E.28/39, flew for the first time.</p>
<p>1955 - The Vienna Treaty, signed by Britain, France, the United States and the USSR, restored Austria's independence.</p>
<p>1957 - Britain dropped its first hydrogen bomb on Christmas Island in the Pacific.</p>
<p>1972 - Alabama governor George Wallace was shot and crippled in an assassination attempt as he campaigned in Maryland for the U.S. presidency.</p>
<p>1978 - Sir Robert Menzies, long-serving Australian prime minister, died. He was Liberal prime minister from 1939 to 1941 and then from 1949 to 1966.</p>
<p>1987 - Rita Hayworth, American film actress and dancer, died. Best known for her roles in &quot;Blood and Sand&quot; and &quot;Gilda&quot;.</p>
<p>1988 - Moscow began the withdrawal of its estimated 115,000 troops in Afghanistan by pulling a unit out of Jalalabad.</p>
<p>1990 - &quot;Portrait of Doctor Gachet&quot; by Vincent Van Gogh sold for 82.5 million dollars at Christies in New York smashing the world record of 53.9 million dollars.</p>
<p>1992 - Opposition Popular Front forces in Azerbaijan swept President Ayaz Mutalibov from power only a day after parliament reinstated him.</p>
<p>1993 - French police rescued six schoolgirls and a teacher after a 46-hour hostage drama at a Paris suburban school shooting dead a man with 16 sticks of dynamite strapped to his body.</p>
<p>1995 - China conducted an underground nuclear test just days after it had agreed to an extension of the nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty.</p>
<p>1996 - Right-wing leader Atal Bihari Vajpayee became India's first Hindu nationalist prime minister after his Bharatiya Janata Party emerged as the largest single party in a hung parliament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
