<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568873" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Interactive TV faces uphill struggle.</title>
<headline>Interactive TV faces uphill struggle.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Neil Winton, Science and Technology Correspondent</p>
<p>Consumers will soon be able to surf the Internet on their televisions, shop, and do their banking, as well as watching their favourite soap operas.</p>
<p>But analysts doubt there will be a great clamour any time soon for interactive TV, unless new services are more exciting, useful, or cheap.</p>
<p>British Sky Broadcasting Group said on Wednesday that it would launch next year a 200 channel digital television service.</p>
<p>BSkyB, owned 40 percent by Rupert Murdoch's News Corp, also announced it had formed a consortium called British Interactive Broadcasting.</p>
<p>BIB, which includes British Telecommunications, would allow subscribers to connect their TV screens across telephone lines to buy computer games and music, order groceries or holidays, and organise banking.</p>
<p>Analysts say that it takes a great leap of imagination to see television watchers changing from inert imbibers of entertainment to active seekers after information and knowledge.</p>
<p>&quot;TV is a passive form of entertainment, and to drive this further you have to offer something very new, very exciting, or which makes very good sense,&quot; said Rebecca Winnington-Ingram, executive director at Morgan Stanley's media and entertainment group.</p>
<p>&quot;Do people honestly want to do a lot more with their TV sets than watch? A lot of investors say they do, but I'm not so sure. The Time Warner trial was inconclusive,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>U.S. media giant Time Warner has wired up subscribers in Orlando, Florida to measure the excitement generated by the possibility of dialing up videos, ordering pizzas or computer games. Reaction so far was said to be lukewarm.</p>
<p>Nevertheless satellite companies across the world like BSkyB, and cable TV groups like Cable and Wireless Communications are heading full speed towards launching digital TV which allow all these applications.</p>
<p>BSkyB said it had arranged for consortium members to subsidise the cost of so-called &quot;set-top boxes&quot;, which effectively transform plain old televisions into personal computers and provide the high-technology services.</p>
<p>This would mean that the cost to British consumers will be cut from about 500 to around 199 pounds ($323). Analysts still think this is too expensive.</p>
<p>&quot;Providers of services shouldn't overestimate the amount consumers will pay for core broadcasts, pay-for-view and online services,&quot; said Robert Montgomery, managing director of Kagan World Media.</p>
<p>&quot;Even at (about) 200, after early adopters have been signed up, it may be difficult to penetrate the mass market early,&quot; Montgomery said. &quot;BSkyB will have to look at renting boxes to achieve penetration.&quot;</p>
<p>But other analysts believe interactive television will succeed, sooner or later.</p>
<p>Trevor Bignall, managing consultant at Robson Rhodes, reckons that content providers like banks -- Midland, owned by HSBC, is part of BIB -- will push consumers into signing up for interactive TV. Banks see online as a powerful way to cut costs. Shops will also push for business.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll see TV change to a hybrid. Now it's just a dumb terminal. This will change TVs into a trojan PC,&quot; Bignall said.</p>
<p>Neil Winton 44-171-542-7975 Email neil@jinks.demon.co.uk ($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
