<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568884" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: IBCA rejects S&amp;P view of sovereign ceilings.</title>
<headline>IBCA rejects S&amp;P view of sovereign ceilings.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>IBCA, the European credit rating agency, said on Thursday the sovereign rating for most countries would continue to be the highest rating for any entity within that country.</p>
<p>It said the chances of a government defaulting on its debt while continuing to allow the private sector to service its foreign currency obligations, was substantially less than that assumed by rival agency Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
<p>&quot;IBCA thus rules out the chances of Argentinian banks or corporates having a higher foreign currency rating than that of the government,&quot; IBCA said in a statement.</p>
<p>It said a crisis which forced the sovereign to default would be so severe and involve so much capital flight from the private sector that it could severely damage the creditworthiness of banks and corporates, even if formal restrictions were not imposed.</p>
<p>&quot;It points out that banks are particularly vulnerable to such crises, because their clients have trouble servicing loans, and bad debts eat into their capital,&quot; said IBCA.</p>
<p>&quot;Certain natural resource exporting corporates might be better candidates for such treatment.&quot;</p>
<p>IBCA also repeated its stance on European Economic and Monetary Union (EMU), saying it would retain the sovereign ceiling ratings of individual member countries which join the union until the system had proved itself to be durable.</p>
<p>&quot;At that point, the EMU area as a whole will benefit from a AAA sovereign ceiling,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;As from 1 January 1999, however, the local currency ratings of the participating members will be aligned with the foreign currency ratings.&quot;</p>
<p>-- International Bonds Unit +44 171 542 8682</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
