<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568828" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Soros confident of prompt EMU start but sees risks.</title>
<headline>Soros confident of prompt EMU start but sees risks.</headline>
<byline>Mike Dolan</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>International fund manager George Soros said on Thursday that he believes European economic and monetary union (EMU) will start on time in January 1999, barring an unlikely derailment.</p>
<p>In a lecture in London entitled &quot;Building a Democratic Europe&quot;, Soros said he saw a 75 percent chance of a punctual start for the single currency and only this month's French elections posed a serious risk to the timing of the project.</p>
<p>&quot;EMU is going to happen, basically. The train has left the station and unless it's derailed I'm 75 percent sure it will get there,&quot; the Hungarian-born financier told the Royal Institute for International Affairs.</p>
<p>Soros, whose flagship investment fund Quantum is credited with making about $1 billion from sterling's exit from the European exchange rate mechanism (ERM) in 1992, told Reuters he had not calculated the chances of Britain joining the single currency but was &quot;not betting on it&quot;.</p>
<p>A more pro-European attitude from the new Labour government raised speculation in financial markets this week that Britain may take part in the single currency by the end of the current parliament in 2002.</p>
<p>Soros said, however, the thawing of UK relations with the rest of Europe may lead to a more successful conclusion to this year's Intergovernmental Conference on European Union reforms and may even facilitate enlargement of the EU.</p>
<p>The fate of EMU is now highly political, he said. &quot;The one crossing (EMU has to) make is the French elections.&quot;</p>
<p>French parliamentary elections are in two stages on May 25 and June 1. Even though opposition French Socialists, like the incumbent conservative coalition, are in favour of EMU, they may need support from the Communist party which is anti-EMU.</p>
<p>The 66-year-old billionaire said he was concerned public opinion had become &quot;disenchanted&quot; with the European idea and the French polls could send a strong signal to delay the project.</p>
<p>Neverthelss, Europe's political leaders, and Germany's Chancellor Helmut Kohl in particular, have already given EMU powerful momentum.</p>
<p>&quot;Kohl is a leader and he wants, in his time, to have a common currency and that is what is driving the common currncy,&quot; said Soros. &quot;Public opinion figures are not completely relevant in this matter.&quot;</p>
<p>In spite of his confidence in a punctual start for EMU, Soros said he is uncomfortable with the project which, if it failed, could blow the European Union apart. &quot;The design is flawed,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>An independent central bank that determines a common monetary policy and a post-EMU budgetary stability pact that imposes rigid rules on fiscal policy does not allow enough flexibility for governments to manage their economic differences, he said.</p>
<p>At a time of severe unemployment in many countries, economic equilibrium will be difficult to find and there needs to be some system of transferring resources to even out deviations in economic cycles, Soros said.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
