<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568816" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Bruton heartened after N. Ireland talks with Blair.</title>
<headline>Bruton heartened after N. Ireland talks with Blair.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irish Prime Minister John Bruton said on Thursday after talks with Tony Blair that he believed the new British prime minister would make the search for peace in Northern Ireland one of his top priorities.</p>
<p>Bruton told reporters outside Blair's 10 Downing Street office that the Labour prime minister's landslide election victory last Thursday gave him a mandate to kick-start stalled talks about the future of the British-ruled province.</p>
<p>He said he was heartened by the commitment Blair showed at the hour-long meeting, which also covered Europe, food safety, employment and other issues.</p>
<p>&quot;I think he recognises that there is a moment of opportunity here...but obviously he has to be very careful and balanced in the way that he responds to that opportunity,&quot; said Bruton, the first foreign leader to see Blair.</p>
<p>&quot;This meeting so soon after the prime minister came into office...indicates the very high priority he is attaching to this issues and to moving forward towards peace and reconciliation in Northern Ireland,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Bruton earlier called for IRA political wing Sinn Fein to be admitted to all-party talks on the future of Northern Ireland next month if the guerrillas announced an immediate, genuine ceasefire. The IRA ended a 17-month truce in February 1996.</p>
<p>Asked whether Blair shared his view, Bruton said: &quot;The prime minister understands the urgency of dealing with this matter in a way that will bring about a ceasefire.&quot;</p>
<p>But the Irish leader said it was also very important for Irish republican movements to recognise their responsibility and indicate a willingness to move towards a ceasefire.</p>
<p>The talks, chaired by former U.S. senator George Mitchell, began last June but had made little progress by the time they were temporarily halted ahead of the British election.</p>
<p>The outgoing British Conservative government always insisted the Irish Republican Army should begin to scrap its stocks of weapons and explosives before its political allies could be admitted to the talks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
