<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568880" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: EU's Santer sees turning point in ties with UK.</title>
<headline>EU's Santer sees turning point in ties with UK.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jacques Santer, president of the European Commission, said in an article published on Thursday that Britain could be at a turning point in its relations with the European Union.</p>
<p>He said the election of a new Labour government with a powerful majority should allow Britain to reclaim its place at the heart of the 15-nation bloc and be at the forefront of future EU developments.</p>
<p>&quot;The decisive result of last week's British general election could be a turning point in the country's relations with the European Union,&quot; Santer wrote in the latest edition of the Economist weekly magazine.</p>
<p>&quot;This is what many friends of Britain want. That is not to say they expect the new government to compromise on its defence of Britain's vital interests,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Santer, who heads the EU's executive arm, was writing one week after Labour routed the Conservatives in the polls to end 18 years in opposition. The new government has been quick to show a more positive face towards its European partners, while stressing it will be no pushover in negotiations.</p>
<p>The outgoing Conservatives had grown increasingly Euro-sceptic and sought to portray Labour as a soft touch on closer EU integration.</p>
<p>Santer said the EU faced an exciting future and urged Britain to play a key role in it.</p>
<p>&quot;The great European challenges ahead are opportunities, not threats. Opportunities to unite our continent, create prosperity, peace, security and social solidarity,&quot; Santer wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;Britain with its sense of fair play, pragmatism and efficiency should be one of the leaders of this process, regaining its rightful place at the heart of the European Union.&quot;</p>
<p>Santer laid out the arguments in favour of a single European currency, due to be launched in 1999, but stopped short of arm-twisting Britain over European economic and monetary union (EMU).</p>
<p>&quot;This EMU is not for turning,&quot; he said. &quot;I am sure Britain will weigh all the arguments when the time comes and I hope the City of London and others will be fully prepared for EMU if Britain does decide to join.&quot;</p>
<p>Labour has said it is unlikely Britain will join the single currency in the first wave, due to begin in 1999.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
