<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568819" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Serious talks needed ahead of crucial EU summit-UK.</title>
<headline>Serious talks needed ahead of crucial EU summit-UK.</headline>
<byline>David Ljunggren</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain is confident the European Union can reach agreement on further integration at a crucial summit next month but plenty of work remains to be done first, officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The new Labour government has distanced itself from threats by the previous Conservative administration to veto the Inter-Governmental Conference (IGC) summit in Amsterdam unless the EU makes a number of concessions.</p>
<p>&quot;The Foreign Secretary thinks a deal at Amsterdam is possible -- there is a clear willingness in France and Germany to start talks,&quot; said an official.</p>
<p>He was speaking a day after new foreign minister Robin Cook visited France and Germany to assure Britain's main EU partners that the government wanted to end the antagonism which marked the end of Conservative rule.</p>
<p>The new administration has been quick to show a more positive face towards its European partners, while stressing it will be no pushover in negotiations.</p>
<p>Officials said Britain especially wanted to see progress on the problem of &quot;quota-hopping&quot; -- the practice whereby foreign fishermen buy British boats to gain greater access to EU catch quotas.</p>
<p>&quot;Ministers need to look at quota-hopping and develop an approach. It's an extremely important issue for them,&quot; an official told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;The government is avoiding talk of vetoing the IGC but has made clear there must be real progress on this issue between now and Amsterdam.&quot;</p>
<p>British fishermen say quota-hoppers -- mainly from the Netherlands and Spain -- are driving them out of business.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think there's any lack of understanding in France and Germany. The problem is the inflexible attitude of Spain. We need to be making progress before the IGC,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Both the French and German ministers for Europe planned to visit London within the next two weeks for talks, he added.</p>
<p>Jacques Santer, president of the EU's executive  commission, said in an article published on Thursday that Britain could be at a turning point in its relations with the EU.</p>
<p>&quot;This is what many friends of Britain want. That is not to say they expect the new government to compromise on its defence of Britain's vital interests,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Santer said the EU faced an exciting future and urged Britain to play a key role in it.</p>
<p>He laid out the arguments in favour of a single European currency, due to be launched in 1999, but stopped short of arm-twisting Britain over European monetary union (EMU).</p>
<p>&quot;This EMU is not for turning,&quot; he said. &quot;I am sure Britain will weigh all the arguments when the time comes and I hope the City of London and others will be fully prepared for EMU if Britain does decide to join.&quot;</p>
<p>Labour has said it is unlikely Britain will join the single currency in the first wave, due to begin in 1999.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
