<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568866" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: LIFFE cocoa ends slow session off highs.</title>
<headline>LIFFE cocoa ends slow session off highs.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>LIFFE cocoa futures closed a sluggish day off session highs.</p>
<p>July ended up two stg at 1,005 stg per tonne after trading in a small range most of the day. July rose one stg above Wednesday's high. But it could not garner enough strength to climb higher and started to give back gains.</p>
<p>Total volume stood at 7,053, with December 1997 taking the biggest chunk with 3,206 lots traded. May 1998 traded 2,107 contracts and 1,189 July contracts changed hands.</p>
<p>Traders said light sales came from commission houses, possibly funds. New York's inability to rise also dampened cocoa's rise.</p>
<p>But most trading arose from crosses. Traders said a large trade house crossed about 620 December contracts in the morning at 1,016.</p>
<p>In the afternoon, another firm traded 2,000 Dec/May switches, traders said. They said 1,500 were done at 20 stg and the remainder at 21.</p>
<p>Though traders said cocoa could probably stay rangebound for a bit longer, they said sentiment has turned more optimistic. They said July could continue to inch up toward intial resistance at 1,015.</p>
<p>But sales in the upper 1,020-area and higher were expected to emerge and limit gains in the near-term.</p>
<p>In options, 10 July 1,050 calls traded.</p>
<p>--Medora Lee, London newsroom +44 171 542 8072</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
