<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568896" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: cricket-Penn looks to swing fortunes vs Pakistan.</title>
<headline>cricket-Penn looks to swing fortunes vs Pakistan.</headline>
<text>
<p>CHANDIGARH, May 9 - Andrew Penn wants to rewrite the script when New Zealand begin their campaign in the Independence Cup one-day cricket series against Pakistan at Mohali on Friday night.</p>
<p>An inauspicious limited overs debut for his country nearly six weeks ago has given the Central Districts swing bowler plenty of extra motivation entering this game under lights at the magnificent PCA stadium.  </p>
<p>&quot;Those were probably the worst two overs I bowled all of last season. I just think the occasion got to me,&quot; Penn told NZPA after the Kiwis trained under lights at the match venue yesterday.</p>
<p>&quot;It was definitely a case of nerves and letting the occasion get to me a bit.</p>
<p>&quot;I want to bowl as many overs as possible here against Pakistan.  </p>
<p>New Zealand have decided to delay confirming their lineup until about 1600 (NZT) but Penn is almost guaranteed a place because of the humid conditions here which aid his ability to move the ball in the air.</p>
<p>Penn, 22, wants to put the record straight after his disappointing performance against Sri Lanka in Wellington in late March when he was taken out of the attack after conceding 14 runs, including five wides, from the only two overs he was asked to deliver.  </p>
<p>&quot;Pakistan are a huge challenge because of the calibre of batsmen such as Saeed Anwar, Ijaz Ahmed, Salim Malik and Inzamam-ul-Haq. They are four of the better batsmen in the world, but three of them are right handers and the way they play to the on side increases your chances of getting them out providing you can get your outswinger in the right place,&quot; Penn added.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of the humidity here and the fact it is a night match (starting at 1700 local) there should be plenty of swing movement about.&quot;  </p>
<p>The Kiwis enter the game handicapped because of their long layoff since the Sri Lankan tour of New Zealand, but Pakistan find themselves vulnerable because of the absence of potent fast bowlers Waqar Younis and Wasim Akram as well as world class legspinner Mustaq Ahmed, all of whom are playing for their respective countries in England.</p>
<p>Their bowling attack will now centre around the recalled seamer Aaqib Javed and young spinners Saqlaim Mushtaq and Shahid Afridi, and the New Zealanders must take advantage of the weakened lineup to give themselves a chance of toppling Mushtaq Mohammad's team.  </p>
<p>The Pakistani coach has already guided his side to five wins in six one-day encounters against New Zealand last November and December and he will be eager to inflict more suffering on the Kiwis here in a tournament which spells the end of his brief reign in charge.</p>
<p>Mohammad began his third spell as Pakistani coach last September but he and the Pakistani board have already fallen out over money.  </p>
<p>His gripe is understandable. He has been paid just $US1000 ($NZ1480) a month while helping his side win the World Series limited overs crown in Australia, the Champions Trophy title in Sharjah and gain finals appearances in other one-day tournaments in Kenya and Sharjah.</p>
<p>He asked the board for more money but was bluntly turned down.</p>
<p>Mohammad is eager to continue coaching and told NZPA he would not mind plying his trade in Kenya, Zimbabwe or Canada.  </p>
<p>&quot;I was only doing it (coaching Pakistan) for the love of the game, but I have got to make a living,&quot; the amiable former international said.</p>
<p>Pakistan have decided to omit middle order batsmen Mohammad Wasim and Hasan Raza and medium pacer Azhar Mahmood from their squad for the match at PCA Stadium which is expected to attract a crowd of about 30,000.</p>
<p>Teams -  </p>
<p>New Zealand (likely): Stephen Fleming (captain), Bryan Young, Nathan Astle, Matt Horne, Chris Cairns, Chris Harris, Adam Parore, Dipak Patel, Gavin Larsen, Andrew Penn, Health Davis.</p>
<p>Pakistan: Remeez Raja (captain), Saeed Anwar, Inzamam-ul-Hag, Ijaz Ahmed, Salim Malik, Shahid Afridi, Abdul Razzaq, Moin Khan, Saqlain Mushtaq, Mohammed Hussain, Aaqib Javed.</p>
<p>Umpires: Srinivas Venkatraghavan (India) and Kandaiah Francis (Sri Lanka).</p>
<p>Match referee: A M Ebrahim (Zimbabwe).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
