<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568865" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Metals stumble in late LME, still end strong.</title>
<headline>Metals stumble in late LME, still end strong.</headline>
<text>
<p>LONDON, May 8 (reuter) - Base metal prices largely shied away from their mid-afternoon peaks during late Thursday LME trading, although the complex still ended firm across the board and poised for further gains.</p>
<p>Zinc took centre stage, racing to the highest since October 1992 in a surging rally, but there were notable gains in copper and in aluminium, which extended Wednesday's advances and reached six-week peaks.</p>
<p>&quot;It has been a better day all round...and I think that we will have to go with the flow tomorrow,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>During the afternoon, zinc partially resumed the  strong uptrend seen earlier, but advances were less dramatic with the market needing to take stock of a near-$60 jump over the last 24 hours.</p>
<p>However, the influx of speculative buying, spurred by the market roaring up through $1,300, as well as constructive fundamentals and charts, suggests that the uptrend will be maintained.</p>
<p>Also, much of the strength has been buying from powerful trade and investment quarters, against a background of forward backwardations from the last quarter 1997 onwards.</p>
<p>After the market closed news emerged that talks were taking place to convert an Italian zinc smelter at Crotone from zinc into a copper-nickel refinery, although traders said this was not an immediate factor.</p>
<p>Last trade was at $1,330, up $43 from Wednesday's kerb. The next objective is $1,350, traders said.</p>
<p>Copper finally broke above the $2,380 chart ceiling, with follow through buying impetus carrying prices up to a high point of $2,400. Profit-taking was evident at this level, although final business at $2,388 was still $18 up from the previous close and technically constructive.</p>
<p>There was little significant movement in the backwardations, with cash/threes a stable $60/62 at the close.</p>
<p>In the short-term the market may extend the rally, given the good chart close, but current fundamentals of stoppages and disputes in Chile and North America are all factored in now, they added.</p>
<p>Aluminium's advances were less dramatic than yesterday, but further borrowing of the spreads throughout the cash/threes structure kept the contango well around $19/22, against levels near $30 Wednesday midsession.</p>
<p>Three months prices lost momentum above $1,670, however, and last trade at $1,670 was just $9 higher.</p>
<p>Nickel built on morning strength, as well as the afternoon flip-up elsewhere in the complex, although the rise stalled at $7,800. But last trade at $7,770 was still $160 above the previous kerb.</p>
<p>Lead similarly ran out of steam at its highs above $640, but still finished $11 higher at $636. A strong zinc market was supportive, traders added.</p>
<p>Tin was prevented from extending morning gains by stubborn resistance above $5,900, although last business at this level was still $105 up from yesterday.</p>
<p>Alloy closed at a steady $1,505/10 a tonne.</p>
<p>	 --Martin Hayes, London newsroom 44 171 542 8080</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
