<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568857" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britain says holds two bars of Nazi gold.</title>
<headline>Britain says holds two bars of Nazi gold.</headline>
<byline>Robert Woodward</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Bank of England announced on Thursday it was holding two gold bars with Nazi markings that were transferred from Germany's central bank, the Bundesbank, in 1996.</p>
<p>The central bank detailed for the first time how much gold it held as custodian for the Tripartite Gold Commission (TGC) -- 114,637 troy ounces (3,565 kgs) -- and listed transations it had carried out.</p>
<p>The commission was set up in 1946 and run by Britain, the United States and France to restore to its rightful owners gold looted from World War Two victims of Nazi aggression.</p>
<p>In addition to this stock of gold, the bank said it also held a further two bars on behalf of the commission which were transferred from the Bundesbank in Frankfurt in September 1996.</p>
<p>The bars, bearing the refining stamp of both the Prussian State Mint (1938) and Degussa (1958), a German metals company, were the only ones with Nazi markings held by the bank.</p>
<p>They derive from bars which originally belonged to the National Bank of Belgium. Belgium transferred them to France in 1940 for safe-keeping but the Nazis took them from the Bank of France in 1942 after France was overrun.</p>
<p>They were subsequently re-smelted, along with other National Bank of Belgium bars and assigned new numbers. The false date of 1938 was entered in the mint's records and marked on the bars to disguise their origins, the Bank of England said in its statement.</p>
<p>They were recovered by U.S. forces in Germany in 1945 and put in a Munich bank vault. The Bank of England first became aware of their existence in 1988.</p>
<p>Eight years elapsed before the gold was transferred to the U.S. government, as a commission representative, because of &quot;problems in finding a mutually acceptable formulation on the technical question of liability,&quot; the bank said. They were then deposited in London.</p>
<p>The bank said almost all its holdings of gold for the commission, but not including the bars with Nazi markings, had recently been placed on interest-bearing fixed deposit.</p>
<p>Britain's new Labour government offered on Tuesday to host an international conference on the problems posed by holdings of Nazi gold. It said there was a strong case for looking at compensation for individual victims of Nazi persecution.</p>
<p>The commission has maintained that all its gold was looted from central banks occupied by the Nazis but Jewish groups say some of the gold belonged to private individuals.</p>
<p>The transaction records released by the Bank of England showed huge amounts of gold being transferred to and from London and European capitals from 1948 to 1950, starting with a transfer from the Swiss National Bank of 578,700 ounces in bars on behalf of the Romanian government in May 1948.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, a U.S. study criticised Switzerland for banking Nazi gold during and after World War Two and said there was evidence that some gold the Nazis sold to the Swiss was taken from Holocaust victims.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
