<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568856" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's GEC has most to win from Thomson sale.</title>
<headline>UK's GEC has most to win from Thomson sale.</headline>
<byline>Greg Mahlich</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French plans to privatise   defence</p>
<p>electronics firm Thomson-CSF has attracted wide interest from other defence companies across Europe, but Britain's General Electric Co Plc has most to gain from the sell-off, say analysts.</p>
<p>British Aerospace (BAe) and Daimler-Benz Aerospace (Dasa) have also entered the bidding for parts of the Thomson business.</p>
<p>But the central aim of the selloff must be to bring the core businesses of Thomson and GEC unit GEC-Marconi together to create the efficiencies to rival U.S. giants such as Raytheon and Lockheed Martin. Only two French firms, Alcatel Alsthom and Lagardere Groupe have been allowed to bid directly for the state's 58 percent stake but yesterday GEC, BAe and Dasa all declared their interest as final bids were submitted.</p>
<p>BAe and Dasa both announced they were teaming up with Lagardere, with a view to merging their missile and space businesses should Lagardere win.</p>
<p>But the main business of Thomson is defence electronics and GEC hedged its bets by announcing it had signed memoranda of understanding with both Lagardere and Alcatel to negotiate link-ups with whoever wins.</p>
<p>&quot;They (GEC) are playing a very open hand and I think there is an acceptance even in France that at the end of the day Lagardere or Alcatel on their own can do next to nothing with Thomson-CSF,&quot; said industry analyst Sash Tusa at UBS.</p>
<p>&quot;If they are going to create a European defence-electronics company that matters the only deal that makes any sense at all is Thomson and Marconi.</p>
<p>&quot;Thomson-CSF is Europe's number one defence electronics firm and GEC is Europe's number two and the two companies overlap massively in terms of capabilities, products, R&amp;D (research and development) spending, production facilities and marketing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Other analysts agreed. &quot;Thomson-CSF is the largest European defence electronics producer, with about seven billion dollars of sales,&quot; said Charles Armitage of Lehman Brothers. &quot;GEC-Marconi with five billion dollars of sales is the only logical partner.&quot;</p>
<p>Armitage reckons that cost-savings from a full merger of the two businesses could double Thomson-CSF's current margins from around five percent to the GEC-Marconi average of around 10 percent. But even at this level the two would be struggling to compete against U.S. rivals.</p>
<p>&quot;Benchmarking the business against Raytheon, which is in a very similar market and has margins of above 16 percent shows that overall margins of 10 percent in not only credible but also leaves even more potential upside,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>However, it is still far from certain that Thomson's sale will go ahead, and if it does, who will be allowed to do what.</p>
<p>The sale is due to be awarded before the end of June but after the election on June 1. And a change of government could mean all bets are off, since the opposition Socialist Party has made it clear that it would cancel the privatisation.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34430">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
