<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568835" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK natgas rises on heavy buying for next winter.</title>
<headline>UK natgas rises on heavy buying for next winter.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The UK spot natural gas market saw a return to hectic trading on Thursday as prices for next winter rose by half a penny or more per therm, traders and brokers said.</p>
<p>Dealers were divided over the causes of the increase.</p>
<p>&quot;Virtually nobody's offering gas,&quot; said one. &quot;People who are short are panicking and one of the key sellers is buying.&quot;</p>
<p>But another was less dramatic about the reason. &quot;It's cold in Q1 and it's been undervalued,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>And yet another took a more cynical line: &quot;People are getting bored of existing levels and decided to give it a run, and have proved once again just how easy it is to give it a run.&quot;.</p>
<p>Whichever view is correct, the market did not kick into real life until around 1600 BST, when people said the market started to &quot;go crazy.&quot; Q1 quickly traded up to 17.00 pence a therm, having been done as low as 16.50 pence earlier in the day. But the spike was short lived.</p>
<p>By around 1700 BST, players were saying that levels were dropping. Q1 was offered at 17.00 pence shortly after trading at that level, and it was reported that it was later done at 16.90 pence. By the close, one broker had the bid/offer spread at 16.75/16.90 pence a therm.</p>
<p>The fourth quarter was also active, although not quite as much as Q1, and levels did not spike to the same extent. But prices were still up by around 0.20 pence by the close. One feature of the market on Thursday was the large volume of gas sold out of St Fergus, in the fourth and first quarters and in the October gas year, which also nudged up.</p>
<p>Otherwise trade was relatively quiet, with less gas than recently traded on the within day and day ahead markets, and with three trades reported for differing periods in the spring and summer of 1998.</p>
<p>The IPE futures market had given some warning of the spike which lay ahead on the OTC market, trading up by as much as 0.5 pence a therm in 10 of the 12 monthly contracts before its close at 1600 BST. The average of the IPE settlement prices for the three months in the first quarter was 16.57 pence a therm, so although it closed up, the OTC market still had some way to go after the IPE close before prices there peaked and started to come down.</p>
<p>The result of the interest on the IPE market was that 230 lots were traded, giving it its busiest day for some time and ending a run of disappointing days when trade levels were minimal.</p>
<p>Rising temperatures continued to push down prompt gas demand, even if only slowly. Transco forecast Friday's demand at 226 mcm, 53 percent of peak day demand and down from Thursday's estimated 243 mcm or 57 percent of peak. The temperature forecast is 8.4 Celsius, still way below the seasonal normal 12.2 Celsius.</p>
<p>-- Sebastian Alison, London Newsroom, +44 171 542 6412</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
