<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568821" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BTR drops 14 pct after profit warning.</title>
<headline>BTR drops 14 pct after profit warning.</headline>
<byline>Hans de Jongh</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in BTR Plc, Britain's biggest conglomerate, slumped 14 percent on Thursday as the group lost further investor confidence after issuing its fourth profit warning in three years.</p>
<p>BTR, which is in the final stages of a major restructuring, said the strong pound would hit first-half 1997 operating profits by about 35 million pounds ($56.8 million) if the currency stayed at current levels.</p>
<p>BTR said it was also suffering from weak markets in Germany and Australia, which account for 30 percent of group sales. This meant that, excluding the currency effect, underlying operating profit would be &quot;somewhat lower&quot; than in 1996's first half.</p>
<p>Shares dropped 38 pence to 229-1/2 pence, extending five years of underperformance as investors were shocked that BTR's overhaul, started last year, still has not paid off.</p>
<p>In one fell swoop, one investor offloaded 80 million shares, which represents nearly two percent of BTR's issued ordinary shares.</p>
<p>The conglomerate's profit warning comes just two months after BTR reported better-than-expected 1996 results and said it was making good progress in getting its act together.</p>
<p>Industry analysts were particularly disappointed that first-half results would fall even without the currency effects. They cut 1997 profit estimates by about 10 percent to around 1.2 billion pounds.</p>
<p>But they seemed to keep faith in the strategy outlined by chief executive Ian Strachan, who took over in January 1996.</p>
<p>Strachan started weeding out underperforming operations, while boosting the global presence of core areas such as BTR's valves, packaging and certain automotive operations. BTR is widely diversified around its core businesses of industrial manufacturing and engineering.</p>
<p>&quot;He is going the right way. It is just a matter how quickly he is going to get where he wants to be,&quot; said Geoff Allum at Henderson Crosthwaite.</p>
<p>Analysts took heart from BTR's comment it expected underlying performance to improve in the second half of 1997.</p>
<p>Their conviction that the group was on the right track was further strengthened by BTR's separate announcement that it would buy a unit of GEC-Alstholm NV. GEC-Alsthom in turn acquires BTR's Mirrlees Blackstone unit.</p>
<p>The move marks BTR's exit from diesel engine manufacturing as it boosts its industrial motors and gear drives operation.</p>
<p>&quot;BTR needs to globalise more and that is what it is doing,&quot; said analyst Allum. &quot;The strategy in itself sounds fine. The problem is that the market has a limited amount of patience.&quot;</p>
<p>Strachan said new investments in the core business were in hand and that BTR's divestment programme was over 80 percent complete.</p>
<p>&quot;It cannot happen overnight and the speed at which the strategy begins to show through in the bottom line will continue to be influenced partly by factors outside our control,&quot; he said. ($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
