<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568876" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: LIFFE grains up after sterling fall, holiday helps.</title>
<headline>LIFFE grains up after sterling fall, holiday helps.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>LIFFE grains ended firmer, with new crop profiting most from an easier sterling.</p>
<p>&quot;It helps make the UK even more competitive,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>The absence of continental players, because of holidays in much of Europe, took some of the biggest sellers out of the market, which left open the chance for prices to rise, traders said.</p>
<p>On old crop, the suspension of an EU plan to tax exports, hit by French opposition, played a bullish role, the one trader said. &quot;It helps those with some exports on the books,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Talk of curbs on the commission's power to tax exports also helped the new crop, he said.</p>
<p>July was most active contract on wheat, with 348 lots of a total 765 done. It last changed hands 0.45 stg higher, at 93.55 stg.</p>
<p>But there were bigger rises for the new crop, with January 1.25 stg higher at 98.60 stg.</p>
<p>January was most active on barley, with 15 of a total 25 lots. It last traded 0.75 stg higher at 94.50 stg.</p>
<p>Sterling was close to its day's lows in late Europe after falling overnight by four pfennigs.</p>
<p>--Christopher Lyddon, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7928</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
