<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568846" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Talks held to decide fate of Italian zinc smelter.</title>
<headline>Talks held to decide fate of Italian zinc smelter.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Osmium Holdings, a group of British and U.S. investors, is in talks to buy Italy's Crotone zinc smelter and convert it into a nickel-copper refinery, a spokesman for Osmium said.</p>
<p>But even if the talks reached a successful conclusion the 100,000-tonne a year facility would not be closed for conversion until next year.</p>
<p>The smelter in the city of Crotone is owned by Pertusola Sud SpA, a unit of Eni, the giant Italian state-owned energy group.</p>
<p>&quot;Osmium is in negotiations with Eni on the prospective purchase of the Pertusola plant but contracts have not been signed,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>If the deal goes ahead, the smelter would not be closed until early 1998 at the soonest, and reopen about 18 months later to refine copper and nickel, he said.</p>
<p>The zinc market is tight and London Metal Exchange (LME) warehouse inventories have declined by about 15 percent since the start of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;The timing of any such move (to close the Crotone smelter) could prove to be critical,&quot; broker Billiton Metals said in a report.</p>
<p>Zinc shot up on the LME on Thursday as three month prices soared to a 4-1/2 year peak of $1,328 on fund and speculator buying. Prices have added nearly $300 or 26 percent since the start of 1997.</p>
<p>The spokesman for Osmium declined to give further details, but analysts said the group planned to ship low-grade concentrates from Russia's huge Norilsk facility to be refined in Italy.</p>
<p>The concentrates would also contain some platinum-group metals, which would be shipped to a refinery near London for processing, they added.</p>
<p>Osmium is a group of British and U.S. investors, including Mark Jones III, chairman of Crown Resources Corp, the spokesman said. The firm is likely to retain all of the 450 employees at the Italian smelter if the deal goes ahead, he added.</p>
<p>Eni was not available for comment since offices were closed for the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>--Eric Onstad, London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C182">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
