<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568874" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Protestant cleric urges IRA to choose peace.</title>
<headline>Protestant cleric urges IRA to choose peace.</headline>
<byline>Martin Cowley</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Protestant Archbishop Robin Eames, one of Northern Ireland's chief spiritual leaders, on Thursday made a fervent plea for an IRA ceasefire.</p>
<p>&quot;Here is one more opportunity,&quot; the Anglican cleric said before British Prime Minister Tony Blair was due to meet his Irish counterpart John Bruton in London.</p>
<p>&quot;In God's name I say to the Republican Movement...Don't bomb us, don't shoot us, talk to us, but let us believe that you mean it and can be trusted when you say 'we have stopped our violence'.&quot;</p>
<p>The Irish Republican Army has remained silent about a new ceasefire, but Labour's landslide victory in British elections last week and the election successes of members of the IRA's political wing, Sinn Fein, have fuelled speculation about a possible end to the violence.</p>
<p>Protestants are a small minority in the Republic of Ireland but form the majority population in Northern Ireland supporting continued rule from London and rejecting the IRA's aim for a united Ireland.</p>
<p>Eames, head the Church of Ireland (Anglican) on both sides of the partitioned island, said there was a genuine feeling that without a clear IRA truce, the province's deadlocked three-year peace process would remain incomplete.</p>
<p>&quot;Can I once more appeal, as I have done on numerous occasions, to the IRA -- now is the opportunity that history is giving you,&quot; he told Sky News.</p>
<p>&quot;If you take it and be honest and open in what you are saying and what you mean, I think history will acknowledge it.</p>
<p>&quot;If you lose the opportunity that is given by the mood of this moment to cease what you are doing and give ordinary dialogue in a political sense a chance, I don't think history is going to forgive you.&quot;</p>
<p>Bruton, the first foreign leader to meet Blair since the election, has urged the IRA to &quot;throw away for good the crutch of violence&quot; and commit itself unreservedly to the political process.</p>
<p>Britain and Ireland agree that the IRA must abandon violence before Sinn Fein is allowed into multi-party talks that are due to restart in Belfast on June 3.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein leader Gerry Adams and chief negotiator Martin McGuinness were elected for Northern Ireland seats in parliament last week in their party's best showing for 40 years.</p>
<p>They say they will not take up their places in the London legislature in protest against British rule.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
