<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568826" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British govt to free BT from bar on broadcast TV.</title>
<headline>British govt to free BT from bar on broadcast TV.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-05-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's new Labour government is to start early talks with British Telecommunications aimed at allowing the telephones giant to move swiftly into entertainment broadcasting, the Independent newspaper reported on Friday.</p>
<p>Any such dispensation would end the long-standing ban on BT broadcasting entertainment across its telephone network, the paper said.</p>
<p>BT has said the restriction prevented it from investing billions of pounds in high-capacity fibre-optic cables.</p>
<p>In an interview with the Independent, National Heritage Secretary Chris Smith said Labour would fulfil a promise it made while in opposition two years ago that BT would be allowed to compete with the cable TV industry sooner than 2001, when the ban is due to be reviewed.</p>
<p>In return he would expect BT to fulfil its pledge to connect schools, hospitals and libraries to the information super highway free of charge.</p>
<p>Smith said his department and the department of trade would talk to BT about the proposals in the near future.</p>
<p>&quot;We did set out a couple of years ago a set of proposals that enabled BT to have access to an entertainment market on a somewhat faster time scale than is envisaged in the current legislation,&quot; Smith said.</p>
<p>&quot;Those proposals are still on the page, so to speak. We'd want to begin discussions in the very near future.&quot;</p>
<p>Under the agreement, Smith said BT would be committed to developing a &quot;broadband network as near to nationwide as we could achieve&quot;.</p>
<p>He estimated such a project could cost BT as much as 10 billion pounds ($16 billion), although the company has previously said this would cost 15 billion pounds.</p>
<p>A BT spokesman was quoted as saying: &quot;This reaffirms Labour's commitment to the findings of the (parliamentary) Trade and Industry Select Committee which said the ban should be lifted earlier.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
