<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568804" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LITHUANIA: LITHUANIA - KRAFT MAY EXPAND PRODUCTION - REPORT.</title>
<headline>LITHUANIA - KRAFT MAY EXPAND PRODUCTION - REPORT.</headline>
<dateline>VILNIUS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kraft Jacobs Suchard Lietuva is considering the possibility of expanding its production lines in the country and introducing a new product, the daily Lietuvos rytas reported on Thursday.</p>
<p>The general director of the company, Gintaras Rimshelis, was quoted as saying that if the company's owners approve the expansion project, work on lines to make the new product might start next year.</p>
<p>Kraft's Lithuanian plant makes confectionary products.</p>
<p>Rimshelis declined to release any information on the new product and was quoted as saying that to launch the project investments of tens of millions of dollars would be necessary.</p>
<p>The company has put 87 million litas into upgrading its production lines at its plant in Lithuania's second city of Kaunas, the paper said, 27 million litas of it from its profit in Lithuania.</p>
<p>Rimselis was also quoted as saying that the company plans to boost its exports. Kraft Jacobs Suchard Lietuva now exports to Latvia, Estonia, Belarus and Russia.</p>
<p>Rimselis said that the company's turnover for the first quarter of 1997 was at the same level as the same period last year but declined to give any figures.</p>
<p>--Vilnius newsroom + 370 2 22 35 18</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LITH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VILNIUS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LITHUANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
