<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568932" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.Africa confident Zairean peace talks on track.</title>
<headline>S.Africa confident Zairean peace talks on track.</headline>
<byline>Anton Ferreira</byline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa on Thursday expressed confidence that its efforts to end the war in Zaire were on track and said it had no reason to believe Laurent Kabila's rebels were still fighting.</p>
<p>&quot;This peace process has reached a momentum that indicates that it can only go one direction, and that is forward,&quot; Parks Mankahlana, spokesman for President Nelson Mandela, told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;All the parties, all the sides to the conflict, are cooperating. There is no reason to believe Mr Kabila is not keeping to his undertaking that he will stop movement of his troops on all fronts,&quot; Mankahlana said.</p>
<p>Kabila gave the promise last weekend during talks with President Mobutu Sese Seko on board the South African navy ship Outeniqua, off the Congo coast.</p>
<p>At the end of that meeting Mandela said the two men had agreed to meet again in 10 days.</p>
<p>Mankahlana said South Africa had seen reports that Kabila's men were advancing on Kinshasa and had been involved in fighting, but he said these remained only rumours.</p>
<p>&quot;He has on a continuous basis been in touch with the government here to say that is not true, and all the experts are saying these reports may be unfounded,&quot; Mankahlana said.</p>
<p>He said Deputy President Thabo Mbeki, now on a six-nation tour of Africa to boost the peace process, was due to meet Kabila in Zaire's mining centre of Lubumbashi on Thursday.</p>
<p>Mbeki, who has visited Angola and Tanzania so far, also hoped to travel to Gabon later in the day for talks with Mobutu, who is attending a West African summit there.</p>
<p>Mankahlana said indications were that a second Mobutu- Kabila meeting would take place as scheduled on the Outeniqua, although no firm date had been set.</p>
<p>He said suggestions that Mobutu might not return to Kinshasa from Gabon were only speculation.</p>
<p>&quot;We are working on the basis that he is going back to Kinshasa and that is the reason Deputy President Mbeki will do everything in his power to speak to him today and get a firm commitment that indeed he will participate in the peace process until its conclusion,&quot; Mankahlana said.</p>
<p>He said South Africa expected that before Mobutu and Kabila met again, their aides would thrash out a formula &quot;which we hope will define very clearly the roles of both in the transition process&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
