<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568922" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Grains lose ground to oilseeds on price - Ag Canada.</title>
<headline>Grains lose ground to oilseeds on price - Ag Canada.</headline>
<dateline>WINNIPEG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian wheat, barley and oat acreage should lose ground to oilseeds on higher price prospects for canola and flax, Agriculture Canada said in its May outlook.</p>
<p>&quot;In western Canada, the area seeded is expected to shift out of wheat, barley and oats into oilseeds due to lower expected prices for wheat, barley and oats relative to canola and flax,&quot; Thursday's Ag Canada report stated.  </p>
<p>Statistics Canada released its March seeding report on April 30 which forecast spring wheat acreage nation wide to decline 11 percent to 22.9 million acres from 25.8 million in 1995/96 (Aug/July).</p>
<p>Barley and oats alike were seen down four percent at 12.7 million and 4.9 million, respectively.</p>
<p>The expected shift in acreage was also due to &quot;higher carry-in stocks of wheat, barley and oats for 1997/98 than for 1996/97 compared to lower carry-in stocks for canola and flax,&quot; Ag Canada said.  </p>
<p>Canola area should increase 30 percent to 11.6 million acres and flax should expand 53 percent to 2.3 million acres, StatsCan said.</p>
<p>&quot;In eastern Canada, the area seeded to corn and soybeans is expected increase because of the significant decrease in winter wheat area,&quot; Ag Canada said.</p>
<p>Corn harvested area should be 2.7 million acres and soybean harvested area should be 2.4 million acres in 1997/98, Ag Canada said.  </p>
<p>Ontario farmers seeded less acreage to winter wheat last fall after a severe fusarium outbreak downgraded more than half of the last crop to feed grade quality.</p>
<p>&quot;Seeding intentions may change due to a major increase in the Canadian Wheat Board Pool Return Outlook for wheat and barley in April and the flood in the Red River Valley which has affected 200,000 hectares (494,200 acres),&quot; Ag Canada said.</p>
<p>&quot;Assuming that rainfall is not excessive, most of the affected land will be seeded to crops and varieties with shorter growing seasons, although some reduction in yield can be expected,&quot; Ag Canada said.</p>
<p>&quot;The size of the U.S. winter wheat crop is very uncertain due to freeze damage in April, which may have reduced winter wheat production by five to 10 percent,&quot; Ag Canada added.</p>
<p>The U.S. Department of Agriculture is scheduled to publish its next crop production report on May 12.</p>
<p>((Gilbert Le Gras 204 947 3548))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WINNIPEG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
