<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568998" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Illovo swallows Lonrho Sugar.</title>
<headline>Illovo swallows Lonrho Sugar.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African market leader Illovo Sugar Ltd said on Thursday it had agreed to buy Lonrho Plc's entire 94.25 percent shareholding in Lonrho Sugar Corp Ltd for 13.90 rand per share in cash, or 1,623.7 million rand.</p>
<p>The acquisition, which ends months of speculation about the future of Lonrho's sugar business, will create Africa's biggest sugar group with interests ranging across Southern and East Africa.</p>
<p>Lonrho Sugar has operations in South Africa, Mauritius, Malawi and Swaziland. Illovo, which has a 44 percent domestic market share, owns seven sugar mills in KwaZulu Natal and has recently diversified into Mozambique and Kenya.</p>
<p>Lonrho Sugar had sales of 633 million rand in the six months to September 30, 1996, while Illovo's turnover was 974 million in the half-year to March 31, 1997.</p>
<p>In addition to the cash price of 13.90 rand a share, Lonrho Plc will be entitled to retain the Lonrho Sugar final dividend for the year to end-March of 25 cents, which is expected to be declared prior to completion.</p>
<p>The acquisition price values the entire issued share capital of Lonrho Sugar at 1,723 million rand.</p>
<p>Illovo, which announced last month that it was eyeing Lonrho Sugar, said 1,103 million rand of the purchase price would be financed via an underwritten subscription of 129.76 million new shares at 8.50 rand each.</p>
<p>CG Smith Foods, which owns 69.1 percent of Illovo, will take 37.65 million of the shares, other shareholders will be entitled to up to 16.86 million and the balance of the new shares are being placed with institutions.</p>
<p>The subscription has been fully underwritten by ING Barings and Cazenove &amp; Co.</p>
<p>The balance of the acquisition cost will be funded from existing cash resources and by the issue of 150 million rand in new preference shares.</p>
<p>Minorities will be offered 13.90 rand in cash per share and will also be entitled to the final dividend.</p>
<p>Lonrho Sugar shares, which are only infrequently dealt, last traded at 16.20 rand on Monday. The stock has risen from 12.60 rand since Lonrho Sugar first issued a cautionary notice saying it was in talks in February.</p>
<p>Illovo said the new group would be strongly cash generative. It expected the purchase to be neutral on headline earnings per share for the year to September 30, 1997, and -- assuming normal weather conditions -- for 1998 headline earnings per show real growth.</p>
<p>It added that it had identified potential pre-tax merger benefits of at least 28 million rand a year.</p>
<p>The company said the link with Lonrho Sugar would create one of the world's lowest-cost sugar producers, with signfiicant geographic and climatic diversification and access to good water supplies.</p>
<p>&quot;The acquisition of Lonrho Sugar is an extremely exciting development for Illovo and is consistent with our stated strategy to focus on sugar, downstream products and expansion into sub-Saharan Africa,&quot; said managing director Don MacLeod.</p>
<p>The enlarged group will earn 38 percent of revenues from exports while only some 16 percent of revenues will be subject to world market sugar prices.</p>
<p>The acquisition and subscription are conditional, among things, on the approval of Illovo shareholders who will be consulted at a general meeting on June 17.</p>
<p>-- Ben Hirschler, Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
