<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568930" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GAMBIA: Mideast and African port conditions - Lloyds.</title>
<headline>Mideast and African port conditions - Lloyds.</headline>
<text>
<p>GAMBIA, April 30 - Banjul - Due to construction work on new jetty from May 1-8, berths 3 and 4 closed to traffic. No.1 berth will be available as No.2 berth is too shallow.</p>
<p>ISRAEL, May 6 - No labour problems. Haifa - Three vessels discharging at berth (2 general, 1 bulker), 1 container, 1 tanker, 1 passenger. 3 Bulkers waiting at anchorage to discharge, 1 under repair/dry-docked, 1 awaiting orders. 4 due 1-2 days delay. Ashdod - 11 discharging at berth (9 general cargo, 2 bulkers), 1 bulker loading at berth, 1 container, 1 passenger. 6 waiting at anchorage to discharge (5 general, 1 bulker), 1 awaiting orders, 2-3 days delay expected. Eilat - One general cargo vessel discharging, 2 loading (1 general cargo, 1 bulker). 1 General cargo waiting at anchorage to load, 1 container vessel, 1 passenger vessel, 1 tanker also waiting.</p>
<p>JORDAN, May 3 - Aqaba - Three loading at berth, 6 discharging, 3 waiting at anchorage to load, 3 awaiting orders.</p>
<p>MOZAMBIQUE, May 5 - Nacala - Port working normally. No restrictions on berthing and sailing at night. Draft restrictions 9.5 metres at general cargo berth and 14 at container berth. One tug available. Beira - General cargo berths normal. Container/other terminals - normal, 24 hour berthing/sailing for vessels up to 140 metres LOA. Some restrictions for larger vessels and subject to arrangements with port captain. Maximum draft for 24 hour navigation 7.5 metres. Two tugs available. General access channel - Two waverider buoys deployed in approach channel approximate diameter 1 metre and flashing orange light. Maputo - 24 hour berthing/sailing for vessels up to 120 metres LOA. Some restrictions for larger vessels subject to arrangement with port captain. All berths working normally and expected to remain so. Draft restriction in channel 9.0 metres less 0.5 metres (UKC) plus rise of tide. Maximum draft for 24 hour navigation is 9 metres.</p>
<p>NAMIBIA, May 5 - Walvis Bay - Port working normally.</p>
<p>SIERRA LEONE, Freetown - May 5 - no labour problems. Two vessels berthed of which 1 pipes/accessories discharger, 1 container discharger, 6 due of which 3 to discharge/load containers, 1 to load containers, 1 container/vehicle discharger, 1 rice discharger, No vessels anchored.</p>
<p>SOUTH AFRICA, May 5 - Richards Bay - general cargo berths congested until weekend. Bulk import berths fully occupied for next 2 weeks. Bulk export congested until weekend, maintenance scheduled later at weekend. Bulk coal - 4 vessels berthed and 15 due up to and including 12/5, No delays. Durban - container terminal - delays of up to 96 hours expected whilst 2 new noel cranes being positioned. Point/new pier/Maydon wharf berths - working normally for general cargo vessels. Maize terminal (Maydon wharf 8) - two vessels expected for May and 1 for June. Bunker supplies - product available but this could change daily due to bunching. Dry-dock/floating dock - 70 pct committed for May and 70 pct for June. East London - general cargo/combi terminal/tanker berths busy but no delays expected. Dry-dock open for bookings. Tankers - 2 expected weekly. Scrap steel - 4,100 tonnes on hand. Wheat imports - 1 in port. Port Elizabeth - working normally, 2 in port. No delays expected on general, tanker ore or fruit berths.</p>
<p>TUNISIA, May 3 - Gabes - no labour problems. One acid tanker loading at berth, 3 vessels discharging at berth (1 Sulphur, 1 barley, 1 bulk aluminium hydroxide). Sfax - nine in port operating of which 4 loading (2 bulk olive oil, 1 fish, 1 bulk rock phosphate), 5 discharging (2 bulk wheat, 1 timber, 1 bulk sugar, 1 general cargo). Sousse - one In port discharging timber, No delays, No vessels awaiting orders. Tunis four awaiting instructions. Rades - 2 ro/ros, 1 discharging containers, 2 discharging bananas. La Goulette - north side - 1 passenger vessel, 1 vessel discharging bulk maize, 2 discharging bananas, South side - 1 vessel discharging grain, 1 tanker discharging gasoil, 1 vessel loading bulk zinc, 1 awaiting instructions, 4 in roads.</p>
<p>TURKEY, May 5 - Iskenderun - one discharging leather, 3 anchored, Sariseki terminal - 2 fertiliser dischargers,</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GAMB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GAMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
