<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568913" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Methanex seeks sites for Asian plant.</title>
<headline>Methanex seeks sites for Asian plant.</headline>
<dateline>VANCOUVER 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Methanex Corp, the world's biggest methanol producer, said on Thursday it was looking for sites for production facilities in Asia and could announce an initiative within one year.</p>
<p>&quot;Within 12 months we will probably have identified an ideal place to do this,&quot; Methanex President Pierre Choquette told reporters after the company's annual meeting.</p>
<p>Choquette said the company was investigating opportunities in Oman, Qatar, Malaysia and northwest Australia, regions that contain at least 1 trillion cubic feet of natural gas reserves.</p>
<p>Methanol is derived from natural gas and is used in a host of applications including paint, resin and clean-burning fuel.</p>
<p>Methanex could spend as much as C$1 billion over six or seven years to build methanol production facilities to serve the Asian market, Choquette said.</p>
<p>Asia accounts for 35 percent of Methanex's sales. Most of the Asian supply is produced at the company's aging New Zealand facilities, which will soon need to be replaced or upgraded.</p>
<p>Methanex, which recently lost a bid to buy a methanol plant in Trinidad, was not planning any immediate acquisitions to increase production, Choquette said. &quot;There are not many gems out there,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The company, which last year had a 38 percent share of the global methanol market, was not considering diversifying its output at the present time, as it sees a strong future in methanol as a clean-burning alternate fuel for automobiles, said Choquette.</p>
<p>Methanex has developed a proprietary emulsifier that would enable the company to supply a diesel/methanol fuel to power vehicles. The product is being tested in Santiago, Chile, a city with severe air pollution.</p>
<p>Choquette said the company, which aims to increase cash flow per share by an average of 15 percent per year, must move to create a methanol supply infrastructure for alternate-fuel vehicles. The lack of a methanol-fuel distribution system cannot be allowed to hamper the marketing of alternate-fuel vehicles, he said.</p>
<p>Methanex was close to signing a letter of understanding to that effect with Ballard Power Systems Inc, the leader in developing low-pollution fuel cell energy systems. &quot;It's time for a methanol producer to show leadership. The payoff is a long time off but it's a big prize,&quot; Choquette said.</p>
<p>He declined to speculate on methanol prices this year, saying that an increase in supply by competitors this year of 2 million tonnes would be offset by tight global inventories.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="OMAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="QATAR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25120">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34320">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VANCOUVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
