<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568963" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Rwandan repatriation chief visits refugee camp.</title>
<headline>Rwandan repatriation chief visits refugee camp.</headline>
<byline>David Fox</byline>
<dateline>BIARO, Zaire 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of Rwanda's repatriation commission arrived in the northeast Zairean city of Kisangani on Thursday to visit a refugee camp where dozens of Rwandan Hutus are dying every day.</p>
<p>Aid officials said Ephraim Kabaija, chairman of a group set up to oversee the reintegration of over two million Hutu refugees into Rwandan life, landed at Kisangani airport and left straight for Biaro camp, 41 km (25 miles) south of the city.</p>
<p>He was expected to hold talks later with officials of the United Nations refugee agency UNHCR on conditions in the camp and on an airlift that took a further 1,150 refugees back to Kigali on Thursday. The total flown home since the airlift began in earnest on April 27 is now 13,174.</p>
<p>Around 30,000 refugees are still gathered at Biaro, remnants of nearly 100,000 who arrived in the area in mid-March after a 500 km (300 mile) trek from their camps near Goma on the border between Zaire and Rwanda.</p>
<p>They were among more than 250,000 refugees who fled west rather than return home after rebels of the Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire began an offensive in eastern Zaire in October.</p>
<p>Aid officials hope Kabaija's visit to Biaro will help him impress on Alliance authorities the urgent need for greater cooperation on the refugee evacuation.</p>
<p>Rwanda's Tutsi-dominated government and army have openly backed the rebellion, which drew its initial support from ethnic Tutsi Banyamulenge tribesmen in eastern Zaire.</p>
<p>&quot;If he sees for himself the conditions there, perhaps he can shock the Alliance into action,&quot; said one aid official.</p>
<p>The 80,000 inhabitants of Biaro and nearby Kasese camps fled into the surrounding dense jungle on April 21 to escape attacks by Zairean villagers and Alliance rebels.</p>
<p>Aid officials and refugee survivors say hundreds, possibly thousands, of people were killed in the fighting or died later of hunger or illness. Thousands more are believed to have fled south to rejoin other large groups of refugees.</p>
<p>Aid officials said on Wednesday they had dramatically scaled down their estimate of how many refugees would be repatriated from Biaro in the immediate future.</p>
<p>&quot;We now think we will probably only move around 40,000 refugees back to Rwanda by air,&quot; said UNHCR spokesman Peter Kessler. &quot;The rest are either missing or dead.&quot;</p>
<p>On Thursday Kessler reiterated, however, that the UNHCR would maintain the airlift for at least two months.</p>
<p>UNHCR officials are still hoping for more meetings with Alliance authorities to press for more access to areas where they believe the refugees may have fled.</p>
<p>Rebel leader Laurent Kabila has promised aid agencies free access to all areas under his control but U.N. officials still cannot go more than 40 km south of Kisangani.</p>
<p>The refugees fled to Zaire in 1994 to escape reprisals for the genocide of over 800,000 Tutsis and moderate Hutus.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RWANDA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BIARO, Zaire"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
