<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568980" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: PRESS DIGEST - Zimbabwe - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Zimbabwe - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Zimbabwe press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>THE FINANCIAL GAZETTE</p>
<p>- Dozens of current and former students at the University of Zimbabwe, soccer players and members of the security forces have trooped before a panel of police investigators to level new allegations of homosexuality against former president Canaan Banana.</p>
<p>- The Zimbabwe Investment Centre and the Reserve Bank of Zimbabwe have turned down an application by Medical Investments Ltd, owners of Harare's Avenues and Montagu clinics, and South Africa's Afrox Healthcare group to form a joint venture to manage the two health facilities.</p>
<p>BUSINESS HERALD</p>
<p>- The Zimbabwe government has cut the prescribed asset ratio by 10 percent as it scales down its domestic borrowings to allow for increased investments in the productive sectors of the economy.</p>
<p>- The turnaround in the performance of Zimbabwe's economy has changed the fortunes of liquidating companies, some of which might themselves now be wound up owing to a slump in business.</p>
<p>THE HERALD</p>
<p>- The government will continue to fund all the projects that remain unfinished after next year's expiry of the multi-billion dollar Urban Sector and Regional Development Programme which it is co-funding with the World Bank.</p>
<p>- The Public Service Commission should investigate the administration of the Ministry of Public Construction and National Housing and weed out corrupt, ineffecient and incompetent officials who abused the VIP Housing Scheme, a high court judge has recommended.</p>
<p>--Harare Newsroom: +263-4 72 52 28/9--</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
