<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568957" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Gencor intends finalising CVRD alliance.</title>
<headline>Gencor intends finalising CVRD alliance.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gencor Ltd said on Thursday it intended to finalise a strategic alliance with the consortium which landed the winning bid for Brazilian state mining giant Companhia Vale do Rio Doce (CVRD).</p>
<p>Gencor, who signed a memorandum of understanding with the winning Valepar consortium, said it was committed to engage in post-auction discussions &quot;to define how Gencor's industry skills will be applied to assist the new owners in coming to grips with the CVRD challenge&quot;.</p>
<p>The consortium paid 3.338 billion reais for a 41.73 percent voting stake in CVRD.</p>
<p>&quot;We also intend to finalise details of a strategic alliance aimed at benefiting the shareholders of all parties, and of CVRD.</p>
<p>&quot;In the process we will explore whether it makes sense for us to participate directly in the company,&quot; Gencor executive director Dave Munro said in a statement.</p>
<p>Gencor said it was seeking to strengthen and expand both its commodity businesses and its global marketing and trading operations in metals an minerals through its involvement in CVRD.</p>
<p>The Valepar consortium still has the option to raise its controlling stake to 45 percent of voting shares.</p>
<p>The consortium includes NationsBank Corp, Banco Safra, investment fund Opportunity Asset Management, and four Brazilian pension funds.</p>
<p>Paper and pulp firm Cia Suzano de Papel and Celulose is also in the group.</p>
<p>-- Marius Bosch, Johannesburg newsroom, +27-11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
