<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568944" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Nigerian share prices mostly steady but index dips.</title>
<headline>Nigerian share prices mostly steady but index dips.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nigerian share prices on Thursday held onto their gains of the week as the all-share index, the barometer of trade, fell a little, dealers said.</p>
<p>The index closed at 8740.65 from 8745.63 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Most shares made some small gains but there is no clear direction in the way the market is moving,&quot; one broker said.</p>
<p>Food and beverages market leader Nestle Foods Plc consolidated its position as the highest priced stock, rising by 50 kobo to 78.50 naira. It was the biggest gain of the day.</p>
<p>Nestle stock has been bounding up since Monday when the company announced a doubling in its after tax profit for 1996 for 1995 and declared a generous dividend and bonus issue.</p>
<p>Oil marketer Agip lost 50 kobo, the same as on Wednesday, to close on Thursday at 25.00.</p>
<p>Two other oil stocks, Mobil and Texaco continued to make steady gains on the Nigerian bourse, each rising by 30 kobo to 62.80 and 48.00 naira, respectively.</p>
<p>&quot;They rose in anticipation that they will declare good profits within the next few weeks,&quot; said a dealer.</p>
<p>Other major gainers were newly-listed Guaranty Trust Bank which closed at 12.00 naira and Flour Mills which stood at 15.20, each appreciating by 20 kobo.</p>
<p>The main losers of the day apart from Agip were Union Bank, which fell by 20 kobo, the same level as on Wednesday to close at 15.60 naira.</p>
<p>United Bank for Africa, which also lost 20 kobo on Wednesday, slumped on Thursday by 10 kobo to close at 13.10 naira.</p>
<p>Computer stationary maker Tripple Gee on Thursday shed the 10 kobo it gained on Wednesday and now stands at 5.00 naira.</p>
<p>-- Lagos newsroom +234 1 263 03 17</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
