<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568975" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Standard fund to be fully invested offshore.</title>
<headline>Standard fund to be fully invested offshore.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa's Standard Bank said on Thursday its international unit trust fund is to become fully invested offshore following the relaxation in the country's foreign exchange control regulations.</p>
<p>The March 12 budget gave institutions the go ahead to invest up to 10 percent of their total assets abroad and not, as before, 10 percent of each individual mutual funds, known locally as unit trusts.</p>
<p>&quot;The attainment of a portfolio invested predominantly offshore is now possible,&quot; said Phillip Scheel, managing director of Standard Bank Fund Managers.</p>
<p>He said most of the fund management firm's asset swap capacity, including foreign investments held in certain other funds, would be pooled and consolidated into the international fund.</p>
<p>This would, however, be subject to formal exchange control approval and the availability of appropriate foreign investments, Scheel said.</p>
<p>&quot;Although we will try to ensure that the Standard Bank international fund is invested to its maximum legal capacity in foreign investments, this will depend largely on the size of the fund being maintained at a level which does not exceed 10 percent of Standard Bank Fund Managers' total funds under administration,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Fidelity Investments, which Standard said was the world's biggest investment management group handling assets of more than $400 billion for over 10 million private and institutional investors, will manage the international fund.</p>
<p>Standard last month launched a range of 12 offshore funds designed to give South Africans an opportunity to invest in international markets.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
