<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568901" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Bre-X fires head of exploration, gets court protection.</title>
<headline>Bre-X fires head of exploration, gets court protection.</headline>
<byline>Darren Schuettler</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canada's Bre-X Minerals Ltd. fired its chief of exploration, John Felderhof, on Thursday while the embattled gold prospector won court protection from its creditors and Canadian police delved into the biggest mining swindle in history.</p>
<p>As the Royal Canadian Mounted Police launched an official probe of the Bre-X affair on Thursday, the company was in a Canadian court seeking creditor protection -- barely a day after two of its directors quit.</p>
<p>The court order, which is similar to bankruptcy protection in the United States, covered Bre-X and its sister companies, Bresea Resources Ltd. and Bro-X Minerals Ltd.</p>
<p>In a statement announcing the court order, Bre-X also said Felderhof was no longer an employee or director.</p>
<p>&quot;In response to a request from the companies, John Felderhof has resigned from the boards of directors of each of Bre-X, Bro-X and Bresea and is no longer in their employ effective immediately,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Calgary, Alberta-based Bre-X had touted Busang as the century's richest gold strike until a consultant said on Sunday there was virtually no gold worth mining at the Indonesian mine and called the case a fraud &quot;without precedent in the history of mining.&quot;</p>
<p>Since then Bre-X's stock -- once valued at over C$6 billion ($4.4 billion) -- has collapsed to pennies a share and more lawsuits have been filed against the company.</p>
<p>The Toronto Stock Exchange delisted Bre-X on Wednesday, and the Nasdaq stock market said it would delist Bre-X stock as of the close of business Thursday.</p>
<p>Bre-X Chief Executive David Walsh has denied any knowledge of tampering and vowed investigators hired by Bre-X will ferret out the culprits.</p>
<p>Felderhof also has expressed dismay over the tampering at Busang and denied any involvement. But he has remained silent since Sunday, remaining in virtual seclusion on his $2.9 million estate in the Cayman Islands.</p>
<p>After two directors resigned on Wednesday, Walsh said the court filing would give shareholders and creditors &quot;some confidence from that fact that the assets of the various companies will remain intact.&quot;</p>
<p>Bre-X's three remaining directors are senior managers of the company, including Walsh who is also chairman.</p>
<p>Walsh said court protection would allow the company to deal with the various claims against it.</p>
<p>At least nine class action lawsuits have been filed against Bre-X in the United States and Canada. The suits charge that Bre-X executives gave inflated projections about the size of gold deposits so they could pump up the stock and sell it off for big profits.</p>
<p>Bre-X had estimated Busang contained about 71 million ounces of gold, potentially the century's richest discovery.</p>
<p>But in its report, Strathcona Mineral Services Ltd. said it found only traces of gold and pointed to a massive fraud.</p>
<p>Bre-X's storage warehouse near the Borneo town of Samarinda, where core samples were kept for a lengthy period of time, was the likely spot for tampering, the report said.</p>
<p>The Royal Canadian Mounted Police, Canada's national police, launched an official investigation into the Busang gold scandal on Thursday, but experts said solving history's biggest mining swindle would not be easy.</p>
<p>&quot;We're commencing with a preliminary investigation and making some initial inquiries,&quot; RCMP spokeswoman Deleen Schoff said by telephone.</p>
<p>Schoff would not say if the RCMP had any suspects at this point. &quot;Even if I had names, I couldn't discuss it because it is part of the investigation,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Walsh asked the RCMP on Tuesday to investigate an alleged fraud against his company, but he did not name a suspect.</p>
<p>A second fraud complaint has been filed by the Ontario Securities Commission, one of Canada's securities regulators. The commission also was investigating Bre-X for possible violations of insider trading and disclosure laws.</p>
<p>Alberta has appointed a special prosecutor to work with the RCMP on the case. Under Canadian law, a conviction for fraud carries a maximum 10-year prison sentence.</p>
<p>Schoff confirmed that an RCMP liaison officer will arrive in Jakarta on Friday to discuss the Bre-X case with local authorities.</p>
<p>As the Mounties begin delving into the scandal in Canada, it may be a while before angry Bre-X investors learn the truth about their lost millions of dollars.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a long, complicated investigation,&quot; predicted Joe Neuberger, a Toronto criminal lawyer with experience in securities fraud.</p>
<p>He said the RCMP would likely follow the paper trail of securities filings and test results dating back to when the Busang project was born in 1993. Interviews with those involved in the project were also likely.</p>
<p>&quot;It must have been a well-thought-out fraud. I'm sure they have suspicions as to who is involved, but they are going to have to start with the information they have,&quot; Neuberger said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
