<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568990" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Amaps makes strong debut on S.Africa JSE.</title>
<headline>Amaps makes strong debut on S.Africa JSE.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African electrical goods firm, Amalgamated Appliances Holdings Ltd (Amaps), made a robust debut on the Johannesburg Stock Exchange on Thursday amid perceptions the company held strong potential.</p>
<p>&quot;There is lots of buying interest in the share. There is good demand at 160 cents,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>By 0820 GMT The company was the most actively traded share on the exchange with 3.6 million shares worth over 6.1 million rand traded.</p>
<p>It was last changing hands at 164 cents after reaching a high of 178 cents in early trade. A range of 164-168 cents was seen on the day.</p>
<p>Dealers said the firm's share offer had attracted keen interest, being 38 times oversubscribed.</p>
<p>The company said earlier earnings in the current financial year were expected to rise 44 percent to a proforma 8.2 million rand or 8.6 cents.</p>
<p>A further 44 percent increase in earnings was expected in the 1998 financial year</p>
<p>The company earlier said it expected to benefit from strong demand growth in the 500 million rand a year small appliance market.</p>
<p>&quot;Emerging consumers are the backbone of demand in this industry and with half a million new customers a year expected for our products, we have built a strategy to secure competitive advantage through both low cost operation and production differentiation,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The company's portfolio of appliance brands includes Salton, Tedelex, Sanyo, Hoover and Rowenta.</p>
<p>-- Charles Phahlane, Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
