<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568993" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: PRESS DIGEST - South Africa - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - South Africa - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the South African press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
<p>- National Party leader FW de Klerk has disbanded the task group charged with forming a new political movement, putting &quot;realignment&quot; architect Roelf Meyer in a position where he is expected to resign and leaving the new vision in tatters.</p>
<p>- The Independent Broadcasting Authority (IBA) had shown a serious lack of management measures and financial controls, with shortcomings including misuse of company credit cards and travel allowances, a damning report by the auditor-general has shown.</p>
<p>- Eskom has bid for a 75 percent stake in a Zambian-owned power supply operation and is investigating the construction of a 400 kilovolt power line through Swaziland to Mozambique.</p>
<p>- Nurses and teachers might receive increases of only 7,04 percent, while the lowest paid of other public servants could receive 22 percent if a government proposal was accepted by all unions negotiating in the numerous public service chambers, a union source said last night.</p>
<p>- General Magnus Malan on Wednesday became the first apartheid-era politician to accept political and moral responsibility for illegal acts by forces under this command while he was defence force chief and defence minister.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BUSINESS REPORT</p>
<p>- Anglo American has failed in its bid to buy a controlling stake in Brazilian state mining group Companhia Vale do Rio Doce, and said on Wednesday it was disappointed at the outcome of the sale.</p>
<p>- First National Bank, the country's third largest banking group, said on Wednesday that it would cut jobs under a major restructuring plan that would be implemented from next month.</p>
<p>- A dramatic ruling from the high court on Wednesday morning in favour of Karos Hotels and Esikhehleni and against Tsogo Sun could delay the establishment of a casino complex in Nelspruit for months, industry sources said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>- Gold producers need not fear a substantial slide in bullion prices below current levels because strong physical demand continued to bolster the precious metal, Gold Fields Minerals Service (GFMS) said in a report on Wednesday.</p>
<p>- Some heavyweight investors in the scam uncovered at NBS 's Kempton Park branch in January might join hands with the bank in an attempt to recover the 135 million rand in outstanding funds, Tony Norton, the chief executive said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SAKE BEELD</p>
<p>- First National Bank  MTCL.O suffered losses of about 186,6 million rand due to the failures of its undertaking Firstpref to finance the retail sales of furniture. This appears from its interim results for the six months to end March, which were released on Wednesday.</p>
<p>- NBS Holdings performed better than well in the year to end March. This is the last year that the group will appear in its old form, because the next interim results will reflect the combined interests of Boland Bank and NBS. - Although Sacob's business confidence index rose in April by 0,3 percent, the economy will cool down over the next few months, Sacob said.</p>
<p>- Deelkraal will become a wholly owned subsidiary of Elandsrand, the two mines said on Wednesday in a joint statement.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>THE STAR</p>
<p>- National Party leader FW de Klerk dropped a political bombshell last night when he dissolved Roelf Neyer's task group charged with investigating the possibility of forming a new political party.</p>
<p>- Soldiers who committed unlawful atrocities in support of apartheid should be prosecuted, General Magnus Malan told the Truth and Reconciliation Commission on Wednesday, but he would accept moral and political responsibility for all their lawful actions including cross-border raids in which innocent people were killed.</p>
<p>- The Gauteng Tender Board has awarded a 14 million rand tender to supply a helicopter ambulance service to a consortium headed by a member of the board, even though a competing tender offered the same service for 7,9 million, the Star learnt on Wednesday.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
