<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568914" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada bonds close stronger but underperform U.S..</title>
<headline>Canada bonds close stronger but underperform U.S..</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian bonds pared early losses to close stronger on Thursday, but underperformed U.S. treasuries amid weakness in the Canadian dollar, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a relatively quiet day. Canada was just marking prices with the U.S.,&quot; said David Yu, a fixed-income portfolio manager with Perigee Investment Counsel Inc. &quot;We are underperforming the U.S. slightly today. It could be because our dollar is a touch weaker.&quot;</p>
<p>Canada's 30-year benchmark bond rose C$0.10 to C$109.90 to yield 7.156 percent.  </p>
<p>The U.S. 30-year bond rose 14/32 to yield 6.93 percent. The spread between the two bonds widened to 23 basis points from 19 basis points at Wednesday's close.</p>
<p>&quot;We were sort of toast from the get go today. In this rally, a lot of guys were selling into it. The Canadian traders were selling into it because it was fairly unexpected that it would be up a buck from low to high today,&quot; said a bond dealer with one bank-owned brokerage.</p>
<p>The dealer said poor demand for the Canadian government's auction of C$2.4 billion of 10-year bonds on Wednesday continued to weigh on prices early in today's session.  </p>
<p>In other news, Moody's Investors Service on Thursday downgraded the domestic currency rating of British Columbia's bonds to AA2 from AA1. Analysts said the news had more impact on the currency than Canadian government bonds, but was a factor in Canada's underperformance.</p>
<p>&quot;It appears to have undermined the Canadian dollar a bit,&quot; said Michael Gregory, a fixed-income economist and strategist with Lehman Brothers Canada Inc. &quot;It does highlight that there are still a couple of dark spots left on the Canadian fiscal horizon.&quot;  </p>
<p>In other prices, Canada's 10-year benchmark bonds rose C$0.05 to C$102.55 to yield 6.635 percent. The U.S. bond rose 6/32 to yield 6.73 percent.</p>
<p>The negative spread between the bonds narrowed to 10 basis points from 12 basis points on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The three-month cash T-bill traded with a yield of 3.09 percent against its U.S. equivalent, which yielded 5.22 percent.</p>
<p>((Jeffrey Hodgson (416) 941-8105, e-mail: jeffrey.hodgson@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
