<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568972" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ETHIOPIA: Ethiopian police kill leader of underground group.</title>
<headline>Ethiopian police kill leader of underground group.</headline>
<dateline>ADDIS ABABA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ethiopian police killed the leader of a violent underground group in the capital Addis Ababa on Thursday and detained several members, state radio said.</p>
<p>The leader, Assefa Maru of the Ethiopian United Patriotic Front, had resisted arrest and tried to flee, it said.</p>
<p>Police found three Kalashnikov assault rifles and several bombs, it added, quoting the police.</p>
<p>The previous leader of the group, university professor Taye Wolde-Semayate, was arrested last June and police said at the time the group was planning to assassinate government officials and foreigners. His case is pending in court.</p>
<p>Last month one person was killed and 86 were injured in grenade attacks on a supermarket, a restaurant and two hotels frequented by foreigners in Addis Ababa and the eastern town of Dire Dawa. No one has claimed responsibility.</p>
<p>A police statement last June said the movement also planned to force wealthy individuals to pay contributions and to carry out armed robberies of government institutions and companies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ETHPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ADDIS ABABA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ETHIOPIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
