<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568967" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: South Africa's main opposition party in disarray.</title>
<headline>South Africa's main opposition party in disarray.</headline>
<byline>Anton Ferreira</byline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa's National Party has disbanded a team of senior members who had the task of realigning opposition politics, underlining deep divisions in the party of apartheid over its future role and identity.</p>
<p>Party leader F.W. de Klerk said on Wednesday night that Roelf Meyer, who played a key role in negotiating the transition to majority rule at the start of the decade, had been relieved of his leadership of the team only three months after it was set up.</p>
<p>Party spokesman Martinus van Schalkwyk said de Klerk had acted because the team -- charged with forming a broad, moderate political movement capable of challenging the ruling African National Congress -- had created too much controversy within party ranks.</p>
<p>&quot;The biggest debate was 'should the National Party disband or not',&quot; van Schalkwyk said. &quot;The National Party is not going to disband.&quot;</p>
<p>The party, universally referred to as &quot;the Nats&quot;, began its life as an unashamedly white nationalist group and began implementing apartheid after winning power in 1948.</p>
<p>In 1990 de Klerk, then president, began dismantling apartheid, effectively negotiating himself out of power. The party came a distant second to President Nelson Mandela's ANC in elections in April 1994, having failed to broaden its support beyond the white and Coloured (mixed-race) communities.</p>
<p>Meyer's team, set up in February, was an attempt to create a broader movement in which the National Party could eventually be subsumed, it was hoped losing the stigma of being the party that created apartheid.</p>
<p>Political scientist Hermann Giliomee said the team appeared to have made no progress in its task.</p>
<p>&quot;I never had much hope for a broad alliance in the short term,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The task group tried to find out if there was a short cut, whether the Nats would get a couple of black leaders and they would deliver a constituency. I don't think that is working out.&quot;</p>
<p>Giliomee said Meyer, who formed a close working relationship with his counterparts in the ANC during the democracy negotiations, would probably quit the party.</p>
<p>Meyer is regarded as favouring the scrapping of the party's present name and identity to give it a better chance of competing with the ANC for black voters, who outnumber whites by about five to one.</p>
<p>His main opponent within the party is Hernus Kriel, premier of Western Cape province where the Nats have a majority due to their popularity among Coloured voters who form about 60 percent of the province's population.</p>
<p>Many Coloureds fear the ANC stands for black African hegemony, and Kriel is seen as wanting to capitalise on this.</p>
<p>Jannie Gagiano, a political analyst at the University of Stellenbosch, said the Nats were finding it difficult to play the role of a stridently critical opposition party.</p>
<p>&quot;They don't want the relatively moderate ANC leadership, which has compromised on a number of things, especially economic policy, to go into a more radical mode.</p>
<p>&quot;If you push the moderates too much, you are going to hear the radicals talking harder, so the Nats are saying 'Oh my God I don't want to hear that chicken crowing',&quot; Gagiano said.</p>
<p>&quot;So in a sense there's a kind of conspiracy of silence.&quot;</p>
<p>He said de Klerk was reluctant to portray the ANC as incompetent because this could scare off foreign investors which would in turn harm his own largely middle-class constituency.</p>
<p>&quot;He would be shooting himself in the foot,&quot; Gagiano said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
