<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568926" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGER: Libya's Gaddafi flies to Niger despite U.N. ban.</title>
<headline>Libya's Gaddafi flies to Niger despite U.N. ban.</headline>
<byline>Abdoulaye Massalatchi</byline>
<dateline>NIAMEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi flew to the impoverished West African country of Niger on Thursday in apparent defiance of a U.N. ban on flights from the pariah state.</p>
<p>There he urged the Moslem world to rise up and show its power in a sacred battle against colonialism and its vestiges and to impose its moral values.</p>
<p>&quot;From today, Thursday, which marks the start of the Moslem year, we should bring out the power of Islam, it is a sacred battle, it's a question of our moral values,&quot; he said in Niamey's main mosque where 40,000 faithful gathered for afternoon prayers.</p>
<p>Gaddafi, with a large entourage, arrived with four Boeing 727 jets of Libyan Airlines and was met by Niger's president.</p>
<p>Control tower officials at Niamey's Diori Hamani international airport declined to comment on whether the U.N. ban, slapped on Libya in 1992 over the 1988 Lockerbie bombing, had been broken.</p>
<p>Gaddafi urged Moslems to close ranks and fight colonialism and its vestiges, accusing the U.N. and its Security Council of seeking to destroy Islam.</p>
<p>Calling for the rejection of colonial boundaries, he added: &quot;We should respect the decision of Allah, carry out the will of Allah and reject the resolutions of the U.N., the Security Council and all form of corruption of Islamic values.&quot;</p>
<p>He also urged Moslems to reject the Christian solar-based calendar, noting that Allah had recommended that Moslems follow the moon -- as they did to determine the start of the fasting month of ramadan or the annual haj pilgrimage.</p>
<p>Gaddafi's last trip abroad was by land to Tunisia in October 1996. He violated the ban when a Libyan-registered plane flew him to Cairo and back to attend an Arab summit in June 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;I came to bring support and sympathy to President Ibrahim Bare Mainassara, to the government and Nigerian people,&quot; Gaddafi told reporters before going into a meeting with Mainassara.</p>
<p>The Libyan news agency JANA on Wednesday said Gaddafi would lead prayers in Niger and neighbouring Nigeria during a visit to West Africa as leader of the Islamic Popular Leadership, an organisation he created in 1989.</p>
<p>Gaddafi said when the grouping was established that he wanted it to become equivalent to the International Council of Churches or World Jewish Congress to help poor Moslems throughout the world.</p>
<p>The leaders of Niger and Nigeria came to power, like Gaddafi, in military coups and have been shunned by Western countries for undemocratic rule.</p>
<p>Mainassara resigned his army commission to stand in elections held with lightning speed in 1996. Half way through polling Mainassara named his own electoral commission, prompting cries of foul from the opposition and the United States.</p>
<p>Nigeria's General Sani Abacha has been shunned by the West and local pro-democracy groups since his 1993 coup after a previous military government annulled elections. Opponents say his plan to restore civilian rule in 1998 is insincere.</p>
<p>Residents of the northern Nigerian city of Kano on Thursday said arrangements were in top gear to receive Gaddafi.</p>
<p>They said Libyan television had brought equipment to Kano to telecast his visit live by satellite.</p>
<p>State radio said Abacha, who is from Kano, was expected to hold talks with Gaddafi during his one-day visit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LIBYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NIGER">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NIAMEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGER"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
