<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568908" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada dlr ends weak on B.C. downgrade by Moody's.</title>
<headline>Canada dlr ends weak on B.C. downgrade by Moody's.</headline>
<text>
<p>FORECAST RANGE   1.3815/1.3855	    ASIAN CLOSE     1.3816</p>
<p>RESISTANCE 1.3750   SUPPORT 1.3890	HI 1.3847   LO  1.3812</p>
<p>CANADA OPEN  1.3824/29    HI 1.3867     EUROPE OPEN     1.3820</p>
<p>PREV CLOSE   1.3817/22    LO 1.3816     HI 1.3834   LO  1.3824</p>
<p>---------------------MARKET COMMENT--------------------------</p>
<p>* Canada's dollar ended weaker at C$1.3862 (US$0.7213) on Thursday from Wednesday's close of C$1.3817 (US$0.7237) after Moody's Investors Service downgraded the domestic currency rating of British Columbia to AA2 from AA1, traders said. * They said the downgrade added to bearish sentiment ahead of labor force date due out on Friday at 0700 EDT/1100 GMT.  </p>
<p>Hall said that market players were awaiting the &quot;hotly debated&quot; labor force survey after Statistics Canada said on April 23 that it made a significant error in one of the ways it calculated Canadian payrolls.</p>
<p>Statistics Canada said the error inflated job growth numbers from December and January.</p>
<p>Canada's unemployment rate showed its first improvement in months, when it dropped to 9.3 percent in March from 9.7 percent in February. Some economists said the drop in unemployment had paved the way for the Bank of Canada to follow a possible U.S. interest rate rise after May 20.  </p>
<p>The Bank of Canada has resisted pressure to raise interest rates after the Federal Reserve hiked U.S. rates on March 25 by 25 basis points.</p>
<p>Since then, the Canadian dollar has dropped by about three percent against the U.S. dollar and remained near the weak end of its C$1.3400 to C$1.3800 range.</p>
<p>A Reuter survey of economists forecast Canada's unemployent rate for April to be around 9.3 percent.</p>
<p>On the crosses, the Canadian dollar fell to 1.2317 marks from Wednesday's close of 1.2443 marks and slid to 89.25 yen from 90.46 yen.</p>
<p>((Reuters Toronto Bureau 416 941-8100))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
