<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568927" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Rwandan urges quick repatriation of refugees.</title>
<headline>Rwandan urges quick repatriation of refugees.</headline>
<byline>David Fox</byline>
<dateline>KISANGANI, Zaire 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of Rwanda's repatriation commission visited Rwandan Hutu refugees in Zaire on Thursday and said they must be repatriated without delay.</p>
<p>Ephraim Kabaija, chairman of a group set up to oversee the reintegration of more than two million Hutu refugees into Rwandan life, told Reuters the refugees were in a sorry state but he also sympathised with their Zairean neighbours.</p>
<p>&quot;Compared to how they looked a few weeks ago, the condition of the refugees is pathetic,&quot; Kabaija said. &quot;It is crucial that we lead them out without delay.&quot;</p>
<p>Kabaija was speaking after a brief visit to Biaro, about 41 kms (25 miles) south of Kisangani, where nearly 100,000 refugees set up camp in mid-March.</p>
<p>The refugees were supposed to be repatriated in a U.N. airlift but they scattered into the dense forests after attacks by local villagers and soldiers of the Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire.</p>
<p>Around 40,000 drifted back to the camp and the United Nations has flown more then 13,000 home since the airlift began in earnest on April 27. Some 1,150 returned on Thursday.</p>
<p>Kabaija said the plight of the refugees was pitiful but local Zaireans had also suffered at their hands. &quot;Speak to the villagers,&quot; he said. &quot;Let them tell you about the refugees.&quot;</p>
<p>Villagers say refugees have stolem their crops and livestock. The rebels said it was the killing of seven Zaireans at a hamlet near the camp that led to the attack on Biaro.</p>
<p>Aid officials and refugee survivors say hundreds, possibly thousands, of people were killed in the fighting or died later of hunger or illness. Thousands more are believed to have fled south to rejoin other large groups of refugees.</p>
<p>Aid officials said on Wednesday they had dramatically scaled down their estimate of how many refugees would be repatriated from Biaro in the immediate future.</p>
<p>&quot;We now think we will probably only move around 40,000 refugees back to Rwanda by air,&quot; said UNHCR spokesman Peter Kessler. &quot;The rest are either missing or dead.&quot;</p>
<p>On Thursday Kessler reiterated, however, that the UNHCR would maintain the airlift for at least two months.</p>
<p>UNHCR officials are still hoping for more meetings with Alliance authorities to press for more access to areas where they believe the refugees may have fled.</p>
<p>Rebel leader Laurent Kabila has promised aid agencies free access to all areas under his control but U.N. officials still cannot go more than 40 km south of Kisangani.</p>
<p>The refugees fled to Zaire in 1994 to escape reprisals for the genocide of over 800,000 Tutsis and moderate Hutus.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RWANDA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KISANGANI, Zaire"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
