<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="568937" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GABON: Zaire parliament holds key to civil war settlement.</title>
<headline>Zaire parliament holds key to civil war settlement.</headline>
<dateline>LIBREVILLE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Mobutu Sese Seko and other Central African leaders in Gabon on Thursday said Zaire's parliament held the key to a settlement of the civil war and urged it to fill the vacant speaker's post.</p>
<p>Under Zaire's constitution the speaker of parliament takes over from Mobutu if he dies or is incapable of continuing in office.  </p>
<p>In a communique the heads of state said they had taken note of a statement made by Mobutu that because of his health he would not stand for election.</p>
<p>&quot;The heads of state invite Zaire's political forces under the direction of the High Council of the Republic - Transitional Parliament to proceed with the election of its president to allow normal functioning of institutions and favour an orderly and democratic transition,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Heads of state of Gabon, Chad, the Central African Republic, Congo and Equatorial Guinea met for most of the afternoon without Mobutu, who is ailing with prostate cancer. Cameroon, chairing the Organisation of African Unity (OAU) was represented by the foreign minister.</p>
<p>Rebel leader Laurent Kabila has said he will drive Mobutu from his capital Kinshasa if he does not hand over power before rebel fighters arrive. Residents say the rebels are around 200 km (125 miles) from the city.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GABON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIBREVILLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GABON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
