<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569045" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Bucharest bourse first tier stays in limelight.</title>
<headline>Bucharest bourse first tier stays in limelight.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bucharest stock exchange's first tier remained in the forefront on Thursday, taking the bulk of turnover with prices broadly mixed.</p>
<p>&quot;Interest in the first tier remained rather strong. But buyers were reluctant to pay higher prices for some of the listings, the way they were on Wednesday,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Traders said buyers would remain reticent at the last bourse session of the week on Friday. They expected prices to fall.</p>
<p>The first tier took 70 percent of Thursday's turnover of 8.14 billion lei.</p>
<p>High-cap fertiliser maker Azomures, the top performer of the last few sessions, stayed flat at 3,700 lei, while the other chemical plant, Oltchim, moved ahead 300 lei to close at 2,500.</p>
<p>First-tier pharmaceuticals company Antibiotice closed 100 lei stronger at 6,100. The other pharmaceutical sector stock, Terapia, lost 200 lei to 6,000.</p>
<p>&quot;Demand for Terapia was thin today, with buyers convinced its price had climbed too high,&quot; said another trader.</p>
<p>Two stocks dominated the second tier in trading delayed by work on the exchange's power supply system.</p>
<p>Dye maker Policolor had a special trade of 40,000 shares worth a total 172 million lei. Its turnover for the session was 1.69 billion and it closed 100 lei weaker at 4,100.</p>
<p>&quot;The large Policolor volumes of late entitle it to a place on the first tier,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>The other active second-tier stock was plumbing equipment maker Armatura which traded around 284,000 shares on turnover of 620 million lei.</p>
<p>Two unofficial bourse indices, the VAB and the BIG, inched down by 1.4 and 0.71 percent respectively from the previous session. The BIG first-tier index dropped by 1.07 percent to 3,259.55 points.</p>
<p>	     MAY 8   MAY 7  Week's change  1997 high  1997 low</p>
<p>VAB-Index  955.1   968.8	 n.a.*	 1,041.0    262.0</p>
<p>BIG-Index  936.35    943.02    n.a.*	 1,020.44   266.43</p>
<p>($=7,092 lei)</p>
<p>NOTE - * The bourse did not have a session last Thursday.</p>
<p>-- Luli Popescu, Bucharest Newsroom 40-1 3120264</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
