<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569085" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria parliament agrees crisis declaration.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria parliament agrees crisis declaration.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgaria's new parliament started work on Thursday with all parties backing a declaration of principles intended to lead the country out of crisis.</p>
<p>The deputies passed the seven-point Declaration of National Consensus drawn up by the Union of Democratic Forces (UDF), which won a big majority in last month's general election.</p>
<p>The new government's stated priorities are carrying out reforms agreed with the International Monetary Fund, making provision for the social cost of reform, fighting organised crime, opening secret police files on public figures, returning land to pre-communist owners, and bringing Bulgaria into the European Union and NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;The declaration will outline the main legislative priorities for the parliament in the first months of its work and will strengthen the government's position during talks with international lenders,&quot; said UDF leader Ivan Kostov.</p>
<p>The points of the declaration were voted individually and received strong support. The wish for membership of the European Union was endorsed unanimously.</p>
<p>Kostov, the UDF nominee for prime minister, said one of the first tasks of the new parliament which opened on Wednesday would be to introduce a strict fixed exchange rate regime known as a currency board as the only way out of the crisis.</p>
<p>The deputies, of whom 167 are in parliament for the first time, must also approve a 1997 budget.</p>
<p>&quot;A declaration of national consensus is a good start for the new parliament,&quot; said Socialist leader Georgi Parvanov, though he said his parliamentary group opposed joining NATO and had reservations about opening police files.</p>
<p>The Socialists hold 58 seats in the 240-seat parliament against 137 for the UDF and its coalition allies. Three smaller parties are also represented.</p>
<p>Both the Socialists and the smaller Euroleft coalition, which includes many Socialist dissidents, expressed concern about the social cost of reform and won addition of a clause stipulating &quot;fair distribution of the social burden&quot;.</p>
<p>The small Union for National Salvation (UNS) coalition of ethnic Turks and monarchists, and the populist Bulgarian Business Block also supported most of the UDF priorities.</p>
<p>&quot;We strongly suport Bulgaria's membership in the European Union and NATO and think it is high time the secret police files were opened in order to clear the political class from suspicion,&quot; UNS deputy Dimitar Ludzhev told parliament.</p>
<p>Since February, a caretaker cabinet appointed by President Petar Stoyanov has stabilised the national currency and brought bread and fuel shortages under control.</p>
<p>Kostov is expected to present his cabinet list to Stoyanov by the end of next week and it will then be voted by the parliament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
