<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569087" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia's wild alcohol market not tamed yet.</title>
<headline>Russia's wild alcohol market not tamed yet.</headline>
<byline>Christina Ling</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia has tightened controls on domestic vodka producers but it may be a long time before rattling state coffers feel the benefits of a well-regulated alcohol market.</p>
<p>&quot;You would think that these measures would put us slowly on the road to increasing tax revenues, but it will take years before everyone pays their taxes willingly,&quot; said Al Breach, an economist at the Russian European Centre for Economic Policy.</p>
<p>In the latest round of the government's long-standing battle for control over lucrative alcohol production, imports and sales, President Yeltsin last week signed a decree limiting liquor retail sales and tightening producer licensing rules.</p>
<p>The government is desperate to increase revenues from alcohol duties, which in recent years have fallen to two percent of total state income from one-third in Soviet times, in its race to plug gaping holes in the budget.</p>
<p>First Deputy Prime Minister Anatoly Chubais last month announced an emergency revenue programme to bring in 30 trillion roubles through new approaches to the precious metals market, the equities market, state sell-offs and the alcohol monopoly.</p>
<p>Import licences were re-issued under stricter rules and a system of pre-payment of import duties was introduced at the beginning of this year, while alcohol import tax breaks for special interest groups were scrapped last year.</p>
<p>But bootleggers and moonshiners are cheating Russia of about two trillion roubles a month and government officials said last month that illegal alcohol imports were costing the treasury dozens of trillions of roubles.</p>
<p>World Bank economist Alexander Morozov said Russia was losing about one trillion roubles a year in alcohol revenues through a tax-free customs union with neighbouring Belarus alone, as imports flooded in from Western Europe and Ukraine.</p>
<p>Breach quoted official statistics showing registered alcohol imports almost halved in 1996 -- to 1.07 billion dollars from 1.96 billion dollars in 1995 -- while Morozov said Belarus registered a 1,000 percent increase in alcohol imports.</p>
<p>&quot;It's physically impossible for Belarussians to consume that much, which means that this alcohol was re-exported to Russia,&quot; said Morozov, adding that empirical evidence contradicted official customs import statistics.</p>
<p>Official statistics put per capita consumption of pure alcohol at 6.5 litres in 1995, down from 10.5 litres in 1990.</p>
<p>Imported vodkas like Smirnoff and Absolut have become popular with Russians wary of moonshine posing as once-proud domestic brands, while Western gin and whisky labels are also gaining ground on Slavic palates.</p>
<p>Government officials welcomed the president's latest move, saying that the prohibition of millions of street kiosks dotted all over every Russian town from selling liquor would cut the sale of untaxed and often low-quality alcohol significantly.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it will (raise revenues) immediately but it ought to lead to that,&quot; said Viktor Berestovoi, head of the Federal Service for Control of the State Alcohol Monopoly.</p>
<p>&quot;If illegal production is decreased then it means legal production will increase and if that happens then revenues will increase.&quot;</p>
<p>But analysts say bribing tax and customs officials remains a common way of getting around unpopular liquor duties.</p>
<p>&quot;Increasing alcohol tax (collection) rates is an obvious one because it's so low and it had fallen so much, but you need a trustworthy tax collection sercvice. You can put in as many laws as you like but if they're not enforced...,&quot; Breach said.</p>
<p>And they said achieving compliance with the measures at the lowest levels of enforcement would take years.</p>
<p>&quot;In any case, this is at best a gradual process of bringing it out of the shadow ecomony into the legal economy,&quot; said Morozov.</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
