<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569033" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia-NATO pact nearly done, Alliance offers more.</title>
<headline>Russia-NATO pact nearly done, Alliance offers more.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin said on Thursday a treaty on Russia's relations with NATO was &quot;98 percent&quot; ready and an Alliance official said new incentives might be added to persuade Moscow to sign the pact.</p>
<p>But Poland, favoured to be included in NATO's first expansion along with Hungary and the Czech Republic, warned opposition was growing to the country's membership.</p>
<p>Romania, which harbours longshot hopes of being included alongside Slovenia, received backing for its bid from Belgium. And the three Baltic states, almost certain to be shut out of the &quot;first wave&quot; of expansion, were told by Germany's Defence Minister they would definitely be included one day.</p>
<p>&quot;About 98 percent of the document is ready,&quot; Yeltsin said after laying a wreath at Moscow's Tomb of the Unknown Soldier on the eve of the anniversary marking the end of World War Two.</p>
<p>But Yeltsin, fiercely opposed to NATO's plans to admit new members from the Soviet Union's Warsaw Pact allies, admitted talks with the Alliance were tough in the run-up to the Madrid summit in July when the candidates will be announced.</p>
<p>&quot;There has probably not been such an acute issue between Russia and the USA and NATO since the Cuban crisis,&quot; he said of the 1962 standoff between Washington and Moscow over Soviet missile bases on the Caribbean island.</p>
<p>Fresh talks between Russian Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov and NATO Secretary General Javier Solana are to be held in Moscow next week to try to clinch the treaty for a May 27 signing in Paris.</p>
<p>Russian commentators said Yeltsin appeared determined to sign the treaty but senior officials expressed misgivings and the communist opposition renewed its attacks on it.</p>
<p>In Brussels, a senior NATO official said the alliance was preparing a final package of &quot;sweeteners&quot; to induce Moscow to drop its remaining objections.</p>
<p>&quot;We are very close to our bottom line, and we cannot offer significantly more, but there are a few things we can do,&quot; the official said. He declined to elaborate.</p>
<p>Polish Foreign Minister Dariusz Rosati told parliament in Warsaw that his country had to stick to its plans to join the alliance despite what he said was growing resistance.</p>
<p>&quot;The leading opponent remains the Russian Federation, but objections and doubts are also visible in certain Western political circles,&quot; he said in his annual report to the house.</p>
<p>Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene became the latest of several Western leaders to back early Romanian and Slovene membership during talks in Bucharest.</p>
<p>Italy, France, other countries on NATO's southern flank and Canada have backed the two outsiders but the United States and Britain have been lukewarm to their bids. Germany has offered Romania understanding but little concrete support.</p>
<p>German Defence Minister Volker Ruehe told a meeting in Denmark that the Baltic states of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania, once Soviet republics, would definitely enter the Alliance one day.</p>
<p>&quot;I can only advise the Balts to co-operate closely so that they do not lose time. One day they will be members of NATO, there is no doubt,&quot; he said after meeting his Polish and Danish opposite numbers.</p>
<p>Russian opposition to membership of the three Baltic states is particularly intense. NATO and Ukraine, the second most important ex-Soviet republic, are working on a document to set up a closer relationship.</p>
<p>The Kremlin appears to accept that expansion is inevitable and is concentrating on seeking a deal to limit changes in troop deployments in Europe and win a say in NATO planning.</p>
<p>&quot;The main thing now is to ensure Russia's part in NATO's decision-making process,&quot; Yeltsin said in his remarks. &quot;We also want them not to move their forces into the new territories, including nuclear weapons.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
