<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569031" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: World Bank to help Romania tackle poverty.</title>
<headline>World Bank to help Romania tackle poverty.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The World Bank said on Thursday it planned to help Romania tackle the post-communist poverty it says affects one in five of its 22 million residents.</p>
<p>&quot;In the future we would like to start addressing effectively the issue of poverty in Romania,&quot; the head of the Bank's Bucharest mission, Francois Ettori, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We are beginning work on a project which will involve a social development fund to address poverty at the local level in pockets of poverty, using decentralised local administration and non-governmental organisations as the main instruments.&quot;</p>
<p>World Bank figures dating from 1994 show 21 percent of Romanians living in &quot;absolute poverty&quot; and Ettori said he had no indication whether matters had since changed.</p>
<p>Romanians earn about $80 on average per month.</p>
<p>Ettori was speaking ahead of a visit to Bucharest next week by World Bank President James Wolfensohn. He also said the World Bank had agreed to extend about $300 million in credits to Romania, subject to approval by its board next month, including a $50 million loan for social needs.</p>
<p>That credit, he said, was principally aimed at helping the government pay for an increase of two percentage points of allocations to social security despite big budget cuts elsewhere to meet the demands of international lenders.</p>
<p>Most of the increased expenditure, equivalent to between $600 million and $700 million, would go towards higher child benefit and severance pay for workers put out of jobs by closure of inneficient industries.</p>
<p>&quot;Our experience with transition economies in Europe shows that the first segment of the population which suffers are the children, immediately and with long-lasting effect,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Our analysis shows that families with more than two children are among the poorest. Though child allowances are imperfect, they will be an effective instrument in starting to address poverty and to protect children.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
