<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569025" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Vranitzky meets Albania's Berisha on election.</title>
<headline>Vranitzky meets Albania's Berisha on election.</headline>
<byline>Llazar Semini</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>European envoy Franz Vranitzky met Albanian President Sali Berisha on Thursday to try to resolve a deadlock over a law for early elections in the troubled Balkan state.</p>
<p>The dispute between Berisha's Democratic Party and the rest of the nine-party National Reconciliation government over how many seats should be chosen by proportional representation is holding up a formal announcement of the elections, agreed after riots in March and expected on June 29.</p>
<p>Neither Berisha nor Vranitzky, a former Austrian chancellor now acting as envoy of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE), made any comment after the one hour meeting at the president's office.</p>
<p>It is the European envoy's third visit since widespread rioting over failed pyramid savings schemes pushed Albania to the brink of anarchy in March.</p>
<p>&quot;Time is running short and so we are very serious about the fact that things need to happen now,&quot; Vranitzky's spokeswoman told reporters.</p>
<p>The European envoy earlier met leaders of the Democratic party and the Socialists, the other main party in Albania.</p>
<p>Democrat leader Tritan Shehu, a former foreign minister, said after meeting Vranitzky that he had suggested holding the vote two weeks earlier, on June 15.</p>
<p>But Fatos Nano, the leader of the Socialist party, dismissed the proposal.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a bluff. You could hold elections next week, but if the legal and technical conditions, which allowed the electoral manipulation in 1996, are not changed, then no party will take part in the vote,&quot; he told reporters after meeting Vranitzky.</p>
<p>The Socialists pulled out of the May 1996 general election late on polling day alleging widespread fraud. International observers agreed voting was seriously flawed.</p>
<p>Vranitzky said shortly after he arrived on the three-day visit on Wednesday that he would convey to all Albanian political leaders &quot;the expectation of the international community that they find political consensus as far as the election is concerned&quot;.</p>
<p>Interim Prime Minister Bashkim Fino said after he met Vranitzky on Wednesday that he was optimistic an agreement could be reached on the electoral law.</p>
<p>Democratic Party leaders, who want to keep the current law in which fewer seats are decided by proportional representation, played down the importance of the new legislation.</p>
<p>&quot;The electoral law is not such an essential item as the present electoral law is very democratic and it is already in force,&quot; Genc Pollo, secretary general of the Democratic Party, told reporters.</p>
<p>Fino, frustrated over a failure to reach a consensus on the issue after five all-party meetings, has said the government will now adopt the new law by majority and pass it to parliament for approval.</p>
<p>He has sought a vote of confidence from the Democratic-dominated parliament and has said the government will resign if the legislature does not pass the new law.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
