<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569014" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ANGOLA: FEATURE-Angolan agriculture may be key to economic gains.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Angolan agriculture may be key to economic gains.</headline>
<byline>John Fleming</byline>
<dateline>LUANDA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>War-torn Angola's farm sector could be the key to curing some of the southern African country's more serious economic ills, analysts say.</p>
<p>&quot;There isn't much chance of production rising in any other sector except agriculture in the near term,&quot; said Laurinda Hoygaard, an economist with Luanda's Augustino Neto University.</p>
<p>Apart from its oil and diamond wealth, Angola -- struggling to recover from two decades of civil war -- produces little but cement, beer and some food.</p>
<p>Although some sense of normality has returned to the country following a 1994 peace accord between the Luanda government of President Jose Eduardo dos Santos and Jonas Savimbi's former guerrilla opposition UNITA, the war has left painful scars on the economy.</p>
<p>Last year, inflation topped 3,700 percent while prices for foodstuffs in Luanda and other cities rival those in most of the world's capitals.</p>
<p>Typically a kg (2.2 lb) of potatoes or tomatoes will cost upwards of $3 while a kg of corn meal can cost as much as $5.</p>
<p>Increased farm production would lead to a fall in prices and inflation, and contribute to a decline in the artificially high exchange rate, analysts say.</p>
<p>POWER-SHARING DEAL, MORE FREEDOM OF MOVEMENT MAY HELP</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment there is some agricultural production in the interior,&quot; said Hoygaard.</p>
<p>&quot;But it isn't enough to make much of a difference. If there was more freedom of movement, and goods could reach the cities, then you would see a fall in prices quite fast.&quot;</p>
<p>Hoygaard and others said the April 11 power-sharing agreement between the government and UNITA should pave the way for an extension of central administration throughout the country. This could bring about unrestricted trade in Angola.</p>
<p>Much of the country is still controlled by UNITA and the free circulation of goods and services is severely restricted in those areas, economists say.</p>
<p>Farmers in UNITA areas, the most productive zones in the country, are often prevented from bringing their goods to Luanda and government-held provincial capitals for sale.</p>
<p>One foreign agronomist in Luanda pointed to Mozambique as an example of how quickly agriculture can be revived once farmers are allowed to move about freely.</p>
<p>Mozambique was devastated by a 16-year civil war which caused up to one million deaths and isolated the interior of the country for years.</p>
<p>After a 1992 peace treaty and elections two years later, goods began circulating in the Mozambican interior, the economy grew at over 18 percent -- albeit from a very low base -- and most of this was due to increased agricultural production, said the agronomist, who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>FOOD AID IMPORTS REPLACE PRE-INDEPENDENCE EXPORTS</p>
<p>Before Angola's independence from Portugal in 1975, it exported substantial volumes of farm products, and was once one of the world's largest coffee producers.</p>
<p>In 1973 it exported 218,000 tonnes of coffee, 112,000 tonnes of maize (corn) and 28.6 tonnes of beans.</p>
<p>But with its slide into civil war, it ended up importing hundreds of thousands of tonnes of emergency food aid.</p>
<p>Officials from the United Nations World Food Programme recently signed another contract with the Angolan government, to supply 114,000 tonnes of food aid in 1997 after 200,000 tonnes in 1995.</p>
<p>Angola's once farm-based economy is now driven by oil.</p>
<p>In 1960, oil accounted for less than three percent of gross domestic product, while agriculture contributed around 50 percent. By 1995, the latter's share had fallen to 17 percent, and that of oil had jumped to 40 percent.</p>
<p>Oil accounts for 90 percent of exports and 75 percent of government revenue, according to a report by the Ministry of Agriculture and the United Nations' Food and Agriculture Organisation.</p>
<p>Yet while such oil revenue has been used by the government to buy arms and boost security, spending on agriculture has been dismal mainly as a result of the civil war.</p>
<p>From 1991 to 1995, the government allocated less than two percent of spending each year to agriculture.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUANDA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ANGOLA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
