<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569054" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungary's first mortgage bank to be set up in July.</title>
<headline>Hungary's first mortgage bank to be set up in July.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungary will revive a pre-war financial institution by setting up a mortgage bank, probably in the middle of July, the Mortgage Bank Preparatory Rt (MBP) said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the most important targets (of the mortgage bank) is to extend long-term agricultural loans,&quot; MBP Chairman Istvan Tompe told a news conference, adding that agricultural enterprises don't yet have access to long-term mortgage loans.</p>
<p>Mortgage banks were an integral part of Hungary's financial system until communists came to power after World War II.</p>
<p>The new bank, Land Credit and Mortgage Bank (LCMB) would sell its mortgage bonds on the domestic and foreign markets, extend mortage loans to medium-size and large agricultural enterprises mainly for maturities over five years.</p>
<p>It would buy and sell such loans on the secondary market, and is also likely to enter the Budapest Stock Exchange with its securities, Tompe said.</p>
<p>MBP hopes that its founders, five Hungarian banks including Postabank and Kereskedelmi (K&amp;H), would buy LCMB's shares and MBP is also engaged in negotiations about ownership with other Hungarian banks with substantial branch networks, Tompe said.</p>
<p>He added that MBP would like the government to hold 50 percent or slightly less of LCMB's shares temporarily as its initial participation would increase customer confidence.</p>
<p>The registered capital of the mortgage bank will be at least three billion forints ($16.6 million), but MBP encourages the owners to raise four billion forints, Tompe said.</p>
<p>An MBP official said that LCMB was likely to extend loans of 15 billion to 17 billion forints next year.</p>
<p>MBP said that the development of Hungary's real estate and land market is hindered by a slow registration system and by the law which does not allow mortgaging of leased land.</p>
<p>Some 70 percent of Hungary's farmland is leased, Tompe said.</p>
<p>Foreigners and companies are not allowed to buy land in Hungary.</p>
<p>-- Sandor Peto, Budapest newsroom (36 1) 327 4040 ($ = 181.0 Hungarian Forints)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
