<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569015" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAMBIA: Zambia may revise mines sale plan,Sterlite in hunt.</title>
<headline>Zambia may revise mines sale plan,Sterlite in hunt.</headline>
<dateline>LUSAKA 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zambia's government may seek to revise terms for the planned sale of assets of Zambia Consolidated Copper Mines (ZCCM), ZCCM's monthly bulletin said.</p>
<p>The Mining Mirror bulletin quoted Mines Minister Christon Tembo as saying the government &quot;was revisiting its negotiations approach to ensure that Zambia realised the full benefits of the privatisation of ZCCM.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;He stated that he was not happy with the way some of the packages had been offered in the bids and had pressed for renegotiations,&quot; Mining Mirror said.</p>
<p>Tembo was not available for comment and an official for the Zambia Privatisation Agency (ZPA), overseeing the sale of state-run enterprises, told Reuters it was not aware of any renegotiation plans.</p>
<p>The government grouped ZCCM's assets into packages for privatisation purposes but some of the bids received grouped the assets in a different way.</p>
<p>The Mining Mirror gave as an example proposals to divide smelting and mining operations at Konkola and Mufulira.</p>
<p>&quot;The split (at Mufulira) would spell doom for the mine as well as the town with serious social, economic and political consequences,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Last month, the ZPA announced that the government had invited six bidders for final negotiations on the sale of ZCCM assets.</p>
<p>The bidders were AUR Resources, the Kafue Consortium (comprising Avmin Ltd, Noranda Mines, Phelps Dodge Corp and the Commonwealth Development Corp), the Binani Group, First Quantam Minerals Ltd, the Metorex Consortium (which includes Randex Ltd and the Crew Group), and Sterlite Industries Ltd.</p>
<p>ZCCM corporate affairs manager Pius Mambo said the privatisation talks would not be delayed.</p>
<p>&quot;The renegotiations are a normal process of selling anything. The seller and the vendor must haggle,&quot; Mambo said.</p>
<p>&quot;It does not mean the privatisation of ZCCM will be delayed,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>-- Lusaka office, +260 1 222689</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAMBIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150106">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUSAKA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
