<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569096" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungary debt agency sees securities yields falling.</title>
<headline>Hungary debt agency sees securities yields falling.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungary's Government Debt Management Agency (AKK) said it expects government securities yields to continue to decline, despite an interruption to the trend with a central bank interest rate hike in March.</p>
<p>&quot;The market has stabilised and we expect the (earlier) trend to continue,&quot; AKK deputy director Maria Dunavolgyi told a news conference on Thursday.</p>
<p>The National Bank of Hungary raised its six-month deposit rate by 0.25 to 21 percent in March to protect savings from an interest rate decline, which it regarded as too rapid.</p>
<p>Following the rate hike, an auction of 40 billion forints worth of three-year government bonds was more than 90 percent undersubscribed, with buyers seeking yields higher than offered.</p>
<p>The rate hike also led to a fall in demand for government bonds and strengthened interest in buying discount Treasury bills, which have up to one year maturity.</p>
<p>After failure of the three-year bond auction, AKK increased its six-month and 12-month Treasury bill offeringsand hopes to make up the delay in government security sales by the mid-June at latest, officials said.</p>
<p>AKK deputy director Laszlo Borbely said most government bond auctions since the failed three-year bond auction have been oversubscribed and bids for a new bond auction for the same maturity on Thursday almost doubled the offered amount.</p>
<p>AKK said its bond offering plans for the next few months were unlikely to change but the agency may offer fewer seven-year bonds as demand for them was low.</p>
<p>Three-year bond auction..... HTBJ</p>
<p>Seven-year bond-auction..... HTBK</p>
<p>    Benchmark secondary market yields.......... HUBONDFIX</p>
<p>-- Sandor Peto, Budapest newsroom (36 1) 327 4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
