<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569032" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: Bosnian central cabinet adopts state budget.</title>
<headline>Bosnian central cabinet adopts state budget.</headline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bosnia's post-war cabinet adopted a state budget on Thursday in a significant boost for reconstruction efforts, a World Bank official said.</p>
<p>The inter-ethnic cabinet, known as the Council of Ministers, ended months of political haggling and adopted the state budget which for the first time outlined the structure of the peacetime government.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a very significant moment in the implementation of the Dayton peace agreement,&quot; Rory O'Sullivan, director of the World Bank office in Sarajevo, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Boro Bosic, the Serb co-chairman of the Council of Ministers, said the budget amounted to 136 million German marks ($80 million), state television reported.</p>
<p>Under terms of the peace treaty signed in Dayton, Ohio in 1995, Bosnia is comprised of autonomous Serb and Moslem-Croat entities governed by a small central government.</p>
<p>The two entities control tax revenues and share the burden for covering the budget of the central government ministries, including the ministry of foreign affairs and foreign trade.</p>
<p>Bosic said the council hoped that a part of the budget would be covered by international reconstruction aid.</p>
<p>More than half of the budget was devoted to servicing the country's debt, O'Sullivan said.</p>
<p>The budget still has to be approved by the inter-ethnic parliament but diplomats expected deputies to approve the budget as the same political parties are represented in the council of ministers.</p>
<p>Adoption of the budget law is one of the conditions required for holding an international fund-raising conference for reconstruction which was originally scheduled for March.</p>
<p>Before committing funds to Bosnia, foreign donors want Bosnia to sign an agreement with the International Monetary Fund, which in turn requires the government to pass laws on a single central bank, customs, tariff and foreign debt.</p>
<p>International officials hope to raise $1.4 billion at the conference to help rebuild the economy devastated by the 1992-95 war.</p>
<p>Reaching agreement on a single central bank law is fraught with political difficulties after a war in which Serb separatists fought against Bosnian statehood.</p>
<p>But passing the budget law removed one of the obstacles to the reconstruction conference. O'Sullivan said.</p>
<p>&quot;The size and the role of the state has always been a controversial issue since Dayton.</p>
<p>&quot;There have been different interpretations between the entities on what the state is and that's why it has taken so long...This is an important step.&quot; ($ = 1.716 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
