<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569047" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Rabobank Polish unit to issue PLN 100 mln bond.</title>
<headline>Rabobank Polish unit to issue PLN 100 mln bond.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rabo-BRP Bank SA, a Polish subsidiary of Rabobank Nederlanden, will issue 100 million zlotys worth of bonds this month, Rabo-BRP Bank's head said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Rabo-Bank will issue two-year bonds worth 100 million zlotys...in a non-public issue addressed to less than 300 investors,&quot; Dariusz Ledworowski told a news conference.</p>
<p>He said the bank's supervisory board had authorised management to issue up to 300 million zlotys worth of bonds this year and that another bond issue was likely to follow in the last quarter of the year. @</p>
<p>Ledworowski said the bonds would carry an annual coupon of one percent below the central bank's discount rate, currently at 22 percent.</p>
<p>He said the proceeds from the bond issue would be used to step up the bank's lending.</p>
<p>Ledworowski said Rabobank Nederland this month would likely double the Polish subsidiary's capital to 75 million zlotys and increase its stake to 76 percent from the current 51 percent. @</p>
<p>Other main Rabo-BRP shareholders are the European Fund for Poland's Rural Development with 24.1 percent and the Polish-American Enterprise Fund with 9.2 percent.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
