<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569094" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria c.bank cuts main interest rate to 5.2 pct.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria c.bank cuts main interest rate to 5.2 pct.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bulgarian National Bank (BNB) cut its main interest rate to 5.2 pct monthly from 6.2 pct, dealers said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The new main rate becomes effective on Monday, May 12.  </p>
<p>&quot;The central bank informed us that it had decided to cut the main rate to 5.2 percent monthly or 64.20 percent annually,&quot; a commercial bank dealer told Reuters. The central bank itself declined to comment.</p>
<p>The cut was in line with the falling yield on one- and four-week discount T-bills auctioned daily by the Finance ministry from Friday through Thursday, the dealer said.</p>
<p>Under a $657 million funding agreement with the International Monetary Fund the BNB adjusts the rate weekly to the weighted average effective monthly yield on one- and four-week discount T-bills auctioned in five successive days.</p>
<p>The new, lower main interest rate reflected a projected fall in consumer price inflation to four to five percent monthly in April from 12.3 percent in March.</p>
<p>Inflation figure for April was expected to be released by the National Statistics Institute this week.</p>
<p>The effective monthly yield on one-week discount T-bills has been falling from 5.69 percent at last Friday's auction to 3.65 percent at today's auction.</p>
<p>The effective monthly yield on four-week discount T-bills also eased gradually to 5.14 percent today from 5.62 percent on May 2. -- Sofia Newsroom, (++359-2) 911 88</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
