<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569039" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: Ukraine seeks state-backed air cargo firm.</title>
<headline>Ukraine seeks state-backed air cargo firm.</headline>
<byline>Rostislav Khotin</byline>
<dateline>KIEV 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ukraine's defence ministry has cancelled air companies' leases on dozens of cargo planes and plans to use the planes as the core of a state-backed firm, aviation and military officials told Reuters on Thursday.</p>
<p>Defence Ministry spokesman Serhiy Nagoryansky said the ministry wanted to use the planes in a special air cargo company which would be backed by the policy-making Security and Defence Council, which is chaired by President Leonid Kuchma.</p>
<p>Nagoryansky said some of the cargo companies may have had a careless attitude towards the planes and neglected repairs and servicing.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to check what's going on with the planes and what condition they are in. The minister wants to take everything under his control,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The airlines denied the charges and said they had been forced to cancel contracts when the leases were cancelled.</p>
<p>&quot;The damage is huge. We were forced to give back all our Ilyushin-76s -- some of them were as far away as Angola. It hurts not only us but the state too,&quot; said Olexander Sanin, President of one of the 15 cargo companies affected.</p>
<p>&quot;Ukraine's reputation will be put in question,&quot; he said, adding that his company had been forced to cancel a contract to lift medical equipment for the Red Cross from Europe to Iran.</p>
<p>Ukraine was home to 182 giant Il-76 cargo planes when the Soviet Union fell apart in 1991.</p>
<p>The defence ministry, which now complains that it only receives about a third of the money it needs from state coffers, leased 62 of them to private Ukrainian companies, including BSL, Aerocharter, PanAlpina and Alan Company Ltd.</p>
<p>Sanin said his BSL airline had returned 12 of the 35 planes it had leased and Defence Minister Olexander Kuzmuk told the Kievskiye Vedomosti daily they had already been returned to military airfields.</p>
<p>Sanin said his company would now turn to Russia, Belarus or elsewhere for planes instead.</p>
<p>&quot;They are not reliable partners. One day they are nice, and we are flying. But the next they are not, and we are grounded. What kind of business is this when they act as if we were their own soldiers?&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Il-76, made in the Central Asian state of Uzbekistan, can carry 40 tonnes of cargo for 3,500 km (2,200 miles).</p>
<p>Local media said other air cargo companies had won contracts with the United Nations and intended to use Il-76s to carry the goods, some of them bound for Afghanistan, where civil war has created tens of thousands of homeless people and refugees.</p>
<p>Aviation experts said each plane could earn the state $7,000 per day if it was flying.</p>
<p>The state collects money from the services and companies pay $52 per 100 km (60 miles) of flights over Ukrainian airspace. Each landing costs $4,200 and the experts said domestic oil refineries would lose out from a drop in demand.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
