<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569027" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKMENISTAN: Cash-short Turkmenistan doubles bread prices.</title>
<headline>Cash-short Turkmenistan doubles bread prices.</headline>
<byline>Marat Gurt</byline>
<dateline>ASHGABAT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bread prices in Turkmenistan doubled on Thursday as the government struggled to replenish a treasury left bare because other former Soviet republics have not paid their bills for Turkmen natural gas.</p>
<p>Early morning shoppers in the capital Ashgabat were bewildered to find the price of a loaf had soared overnight to 1,000 manats (18 cents) from 500.</p>
<p>&quot;My 30,000-manat ($5.3) grant will now only be enough for bread,&quot; one student shopper complained.</p>
<p>The price hike was contained in a decree issued by President Saparmurat Niyazov, an official from the country's Economy and Finance Ministry told Reuters. The decree followed an extraordinary cabinet meeting held on Monday.</p>
<p>With a candour unusual in this secretive Central Asian state where Niyazov enjoys a Soviet-era personality cult, the official Turkmen Press news agency on Tuesday provided details of the meeting.</p>
<p>Niyazov was quoted as telling ministers the debts of other former Soviet republics for supplies of Turkmen natural gas were aggravating the economic situation.</p>
<p>&quot;The money to be received for supplies of Turkmen natural gas has been included in the expenses of this year's state budget, and its absence will create difficulties for the Turkmen economy,&quot; Niyazov said.</p>
<p>He said debts for natural gas amounted to $1.76 billion, with Ukraine the biggest debtor, owing more than $1 billion.</p>
<p>On March 1, Niyazov doubled public sector monthly wages to 200,000 manats ($36). He then spoke on television saying pay was being increased in anticipation of debt repayments from Ukraine and other states and promised it would not generate inflation.</p>
<p>But Ukraine and Georgia have been slow to pay off their debts to the gas-rich but otherwise impoverished nation of around four million people.</p>
<p>Niyazov's plans to achieve self-sufficiency in food have been also ruined. Last year the desert nation gathered a meagre 400,000 tonnes of grain, way below official forecasts of 1.2 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Turkmen Press has said that Turkmenistan, facing severe bread shortages, was forced to spend $800 million last year on grain purchases abroad. No official figures have been given.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURKM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ASHGABAT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKMENISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
