<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569000" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: PRESS DIGEST - Kenya - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Kenya - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Kenyan press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAILY NATION</p>
<p>- The electoral commission announces voter registration for general elections this year will start on May 19 and end on June 22.</p>
<p>- Cabinet minister Nicholas Biwott declares himself a clean man over the murder of the 1990 murder of former foreign affairs minister Robert Ouko.</p>
<p>- Police kill two suspected robbers outside a Nairobi temple.</p>
<p>EAST AFRICAN STANDARD</p>
<p>- Calm returns to Marakwet and Pokot districts after local leaders reach a peace agreement to end cattle rustling in the area.</p>
<p>- Armed gangsters raid a business firm at Nairobi's Jomo Kenyatta International Airport and steal property worth at least 1.2 million shillings.</p>
<p>- Pressure from top government officials may force the Nairobi City Council to raise water bills by 40 percent to pay off a foreign firm.</p>
<p>KENYA TIMES</p>
<p>- The hijackers of a Kenyan fishing trawler have removed all the 36 crew members from the ship and taken them to an unknown destination in Somaliland.</p>
<p>- Ousted chairman of the opposition Kenya National Congress Chibule wa Tsuma is expelled from the party by its national executive council.</p>
<p>- Eleven people drown while three others are reported missing following heavy rains in the country over the last few days.</p>
<p>($1=54 Kenyan Shillings)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
