<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569056" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: Slovenia sees no early reform of investment laws.</title>
<headline>Slovenia sees no early reform of investment laws.</headline>
<byline>Marja Novak</byline>
<dateline>LJUBLJANA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Slovenia's central bank said on Thursday it had no plans to reform unpopular rules that discourage foreign investment before 1998 when an accord with the European Union comes into force.</p>
<p>In February the central bank decreed that international investors had to open fiduciary accounts at one of Slovenia's 14 fully licensed banks in order to trade in securities. Banks have yet to make the accounts available.</p>
<p>&quot;The principle of the fiduciary accounts will not change but operational changes regarding the accounts may be expected when the association agreement with the European Union is enforced,&quot; Samo Nucic, deputy governor of the Bank of Slovenia, told Reuters during an investment conference.</p>
<p>The EU accord, signed in June last year, should come into force in January 1998 after ratification by the Slovenian and EU parliaments.</p>
<p>Nucic said the central bank may liberalise rules governing foreign exchange transactions by domestic banks. Currently banks have to balance foreign liabilities, including money paid into fiduciary accounts, against foreign assets.</p>
<p>Since the central bank clamped down on foreign portfolio investment the blue-chip SBI index has fallen by 18.2 percent and volume is down by about 75 percent.</p>
<p>Banks say they will open the first fiduciary accounts in mid-May but foreign investors so far have shown little interest in using them because of high costs of between nine and 15 percent of the amount handled.</p>
<p>Banks handling the fiduciary accounts will convert the amount deposited into tolars which will then be invested in Slovenian stocks.</p>
<p>&quot;We were surprised by the high costs of the accounts and we are sure they could be lower if banks tried harder to increase investment abroad,&quot; Nucic said.</p>
<p>Drasko Veselinovic, head of the Ljubljana Stock Exchange, said he believed the costs were high because of poor competition among Slovenian banks.</p>
<p>&quot;The bank sector is closed for international competition therefore the banks see no need to bring costs down. I believe the costs would be about five percent if there were stronger competition,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Just four out of 28 Slovenian banks are in majority foreign ownership. International banks are only permitted to establish branches in Slovenia, requiring substantial capital outlays.</p>
<p>&quot;That is why international banks operate in line with Slovenian standards and do not present strong competition to domestic banks. I expect this will change when the new bank law is passed by parliament,&quot; Veselinovic said.</p>
<p>The law, which will enable international banks to open branches in Slovenia in line with the EU regulations, is expected to be adopted by parliament later this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LJUBLJANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
