<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569049" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: FOCUS-World Bank backs loans ahead of top visit.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-World Bank backs loans ahead of top visit.</headline>
<byline>Ron Popeski</byline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The World Bank said on Thursday it had reached agreement to extend credits worth about $300 million to Romania ahead of a visit to Bucharest next week by the Bank's president.</p>
<p>The World Bank's chief of mission in Bucharest, Francois Ettori, said in an interview the loans had been agreed after months of negotiations on farm reform and social needs.</p>
<p>The credits are subject to approval at a meeting next month of the Bank's board, along with a further credit under discussion, bringing to about $500 million the total structural assistance the Balkan country can expect to receive.</p>
<p>Ettori said World Bank President James Wolfensohn's visit reflected widespread approval in the West of the new centrist government's pledges to proceed quickly with market reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Wolfensohn is coming here to express the strong support of the World Bank for the reform programme undertaken by the new government after seven years of lukewarm progress in Romania,&quot; Ettori said.</p>
<p>&quot;I have no doubt about the commitment of the president and prime minister to proceed with reforms. They cannot do this by themselves and have to rely on bureaucratic machinery. Like all machines it has some sputtering and may give the impression of stop and go. But on the two major actors there is no doubt.&quot;</p>
<p>Wolfensohn's visit will be the first to Romania since 1977 of a World Bank President. He is to meet President Emil Constantinescu, who ousted an ex-communist in last year's election, and Prime Minister Victor Ciorbea, a former trade union negotiator and Bucharest mayor.</p>
<p>Romania's new authorities have pledged to speed reforms to restore lost Western financial assistance. The freeing of prices, adoption of an austerity budget and pledges to shut down loss-making state firms persuaded the International Monetary Fund last month to approve $430 million in credits.</p>
<p>Both the IMF and World Bank stopped lending programmes last year, saying the leftist government of the time had fallen short on reform promises and overspent ahead of the election.</p>
<p>Ettori said negotiations completed last week produced an agreement under which the World Bank would provide $250 million under an Agriculture Structural Adjustment Loan (ASAL) and a further $50 million for social needs.</p>
<p>He said negotiations with Ciorbea's government were nearing completion on restoring a $180 million credit under a Financial and Enterprise Structural Adjustment Loan (FESAL).</p>
<p>About $100 million was paid out after the FESAL was initially approved last year but later suspended.</p>
<p>Ettori said the ASAL was intended to help reshape the farming sector. It demanded freeing of prices, trade and the land markets and a new system of financing agriculture. Closure of oversized state farms was also proceeding.</p>
<p>The social security credit would offset austerity measures associated with price increases which sent inflation in March to a record 30.7 percent. Most experts say the government's 1997 year-on-year target of 90 percent is now beyond reach.</p>
<p>Ettori said the credit would allow the government to increase social security allocations despite widespread cuts in other areas. The FESAL is linked to restructuring communist-era industries, faster privatisation and banking reforms.</p>
<p>Ettori said the government was making efforts to meet the conditions attached to the FESAL, including parliamentary approval of several laws and privatisation of two state banks.</p>
<p>&quot;This reflects the sputtering in the machinery,&quot; he said. &quot;Things here tend to be done at the last minute.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
