<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569091" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish parliament debates key pension reform bills.</title>
<headline>Polish parliament debates key pension reform bills.</headline>
<byline>Marcin Grajewski</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's lower house of parliament began a debate on Thursday on three key bills that would trigger a long-delayed programme to reform the country's ailing social security system.</p>
<p>&quot;The bills will lay ground for a new, three-tier pension system in Poland,&quot; Jarzy Hausner, a cabinet minister in charge of the reform, told parliament.</p>
<p>The bills, widely expected to go to parliamentary committees for further scrutiny on Friday, provide for creating new pension funds and using proceeds from privatisation of state-owned firms to finance the reform.</p>
<p>Hausner earlier said if parliament managed to pass the draft laws before parliamentary elections scheduled in September, the reform would be launched in 1999.</p>
<p>Without the reform, Poland's public finances may collapse after 2004 due to aging of the population and ineffiency of the current pay-as-you-go system, inherited from the communist era before 1989, he said.</p>
<p>But government officials and analysts say party bickering before the polls may bloc passage of the bills and a new government and parliament would start work on the reform afresh, further delaying overhaul of the system.</p>
<p>The social security reform is a political minefield because nine million pensioners and disability benefits collectors, many of whom fear reform would lower their income, are a powerful electorate in 38-million strong Poland.</p>
<p>A parliamentary debate on Thursday indicated the discussion in committees is likely to be heated, with many deputies, both from the ruling leftist coalition and right-centre opposition, criticising the bills.</p>
<p>Some deputies doubted whether revenues from privatisation could finance the reform and guarantee stable pensions.</p>
<p>The government bills envisage the creation of new pension funds, which would get 20 percent of the obligatory premiums now paid to the sole pension provider -- the state-run Social Security Office (ZUS).</p>
<p>The new funds, which people under 30 years of age would have to join obligatorily and others voluntarily, would invest in safe securities.</p>
<p>The government would issue bonds convertible into shares of companies undergoing privatisation and pump the proceeds into ZUS to make up for a loss of part of its premiums.</p>
<p>ZUS has to be subsidised by the central budget even though it gets 45 percent of all officially employed workers' wages. Subsidies to ZUS now account for 15 percent of budget spending.</p>
<p>Under the new system, people would continue to get a part of their pension from ZUS, which will be restructured, and get the second part of the pension from the new funds.</p>
<p>One of the bills also provides for creating the third source of the pension -- corporate pension funds to which employers, upon reaching a collective deal with workers, could contribute up to seven percent of the premium now compulsorily paid to the state-owned Social Security Office (ZUS).</p>
<p>The government estimates the social security reform would cost about one percent of Poland's gross domestic product annually for more than 20 years from the date of the reform's launch. GDP is forecast at 430 billion zlotys in 1997.</p>
<p>An average Polish pension is now 608 zlotys ($200), or some 60 percent of the national average wage. -- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
