<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569041" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: ROMANIA GVT DENIES PLANS TO CHANGE C.BANK CHIEF.</title>
<headline>ROMANIA GVT DENIES PLANS TO CHANGE C.BANK CHIEF.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The government on Thursday said it was not considering any change of the leadership of Romania's central bank (BNR) after the bank denied a newspaper report that its governor, Mugur Isarescu, would soon step down.</p>
<p>&quot;The government has not discussed a change of the National Bank governor, and there has been no criticism, at least so far, regarding BNR policies,&quot; a government spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;A change of Mugur Isarescu has not figured on the agenda of any cabinet meeting.&quot;</p>
<p>The daily Evenimentul Zilei said on Thursday that Isarescu, in an exclusive statement, had confirmed speculation that he was planning to quit his job before his mandate expired.</p>
<p>But the BNR denied the report.</p>
<p>&quot;The statement in the newspaper is not the governor's,&quot; spokesman Adrian Vasilescu told Reuters.</p>
<p>Isarescu, one of the few Romanian officials who has remained in his position since the 1989 fall of communism, was appointed BNR governor in July 1991.</p>
<p>Under Romania's banking legislation, the term of office for the BNR governor is eight years.</p>
<p>Isarescu's links to the previously ruling ex-communists appear to be a possible motive for seeking his removal.</p>
<p>Isarescu managed under the leftist administration voted out of office last November to resist political pressure to put the BNR under government instead of parliamentary control.</p>
<p>Only parliament can remove Isarescu, but the centrist coalition holds a large majority in both houses.</p>
<p>Unlike the leftist government he served under, Isarescu enjoys a good international reputation. He was criticised as long ago as 1994 for adopting tough monetary policy and taking steps to clear the banking sector of debt-ridden banks.</p>
<p>He acknowledged that his bank was forced by the former leftist administration to relax policies and print money ahead of last year's election.</p>
<p>-- Bucharest Newsroom 40-1 3120264</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81401">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
