<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569064" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Poland's Handlowy expects eurobond to help IPO.</title>
<headline>Poland's Handlowy expects eurobond to help IPO.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's Bank Handlowy expects its successful $200 million eurobond placement will help whet the appetite of equity investors for its public offering due in late May and June, the bank's chief executive said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Cezary Stypulkowski said after an official signing of the eurobond deal with its manager JP Morgan, that high demand, which made it increase the original offer by $50 million, and an attractive price bode well for the bank's share offer.</p>
<p>&quot;This issue is very much in preparation for our initial public offering,&quot; Stypulkowski said. @</p>
<p>&quot;We expect that with this (eurobond) issue we will be able to influence the way Bank Handlowy is perceived by investors on international markets,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>He said that Bank Handlowy, which placed the $200 million 3-year bond at 60 bp above U.S. treasuries, got the best price of all institutional issuers from Eastern and Central Europe.</p>
<p>Poland is offering up to 15 percent of Handlowy's shares in public subscription to domestic retail investors, 30 percent to domestic and foreign institutions and up to 42.86 percent to a selected group of international financial institutions. @</p>
<p>Last year Handlowy entered international capital markets with a $100 million eurobond, which then sold at 88 bp above U.S. treasuries.</p>
<p>Stypulkowski said that Handlowy's privatisation was perceived by investors as a very positive development and should not adversely influence the bank's rating, now at the same level as Poland's.</p>
<p>Bank Handlowy last year was awarded a Baa3 rating from Moody's, the same as Poland's sovereign debt. Stypulkowski said he hoped Poland's upgrade would allow to improve also Handlowy's rating. @</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
