<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569103" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Warsaw bourse extends loss, seen rebounding.</title>
<headline>Warsaw bourse extends loss, seen rebounding.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Warsaw bourse extended Wednesday's profit-taking fall but analysts expected a rebound at least on Friday as large-cap banks, recent underperformers, could rebound slightly after their recent slide.</p>
<p>But analysts saw no strong upside potential either for banks, amid current weaker earnings reports, or for the overall market, which could extend its seven-week sideways drift before Poland's parliamentary elections due in September.</p>
<p>&quot;In the second and third quarter a flat market is likely until the elections, though just before the polls speculative buying might begin,&quot; said Grzegorz Cimochowski of ING Baring.  </p>
<p>The main market's WIG index fell 1.1 percent to 16,368.3, and turnover fell 12.7 percent to 177.9 million zlotys on all three markets as 57 issues fell, 14 rose and 16 were flat.</p>
<p>Analysts said the expected sideways drift between 16,000 and 17,000 was likely as large investors, though cautious about buying before the vote, would likely refrain from significant selling due to Poland's generally good economic outlook.</p>
<p>Analysts said banks, the bourse's highest capitalised sector, could rebound after falls by some over the past two and a half months by about 30 percent could attract investors looking for bargains.  </p>
<p>But they said after weak first quarter earnings a significant rebound in the sector's earnings in 1997 was unlikely, making a longer-term bourse uptrend unlikely.</p>
<p>They also said the planned late May sale of shares in Poland's largest commercial bank, Bank Handlowy, might additionally weaken prices of currently listed banks.</p>
<p>Polish carpet maker Lentex SA started bourse trade on the main market at 33 zlotys, 53.5 percent above issue price.</p>
<p>-- Malgorzata Rzepka +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
