<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569108" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Croatia says currency exchange fears unfounded.</title>
<headline>Croatia says currency exchange fears unfounded.</headline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Croatia's central bank said on Thursday fears about the imminent re-introduction of its kuna currency into the Serb-held region of Eastern Slavonia were unfounded and the change would not affect the kuna's worth.</p>
<p>The exchange of currency will be one of the most concrete signs of a transfer of rule in an area taken by Serbs in 1991 when Croatia seceded from the federal republic of Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>Eastern Slavonia has been administered by the United Nations since January 1996. Its mandate ends on July 15 and the region will then come under the responsibility and rule of the Zagreb government.</p>
<p>As part of the handover the kuna will take the place of the Yugoslav dinar which is now widely-used by Serbs living there.</p>
<p>&quot;All technical preparations have been completed and it only remains for the date and exchange rate parity to be announced,&quot; the National Bank of Croatia said in a statement after its board meeting held on Wednesday.</p>
<p>It stressed that any fears and speculations about the &quot;Yugoslav dinar endangering the kuna&quot; were totally unfounded.</p>
<p>&quot;According to estimates, the total amount of cash and deposit money of the neighbouring country in (Eastern Slavonia) amounts to 0.2 percent of the total money supply. Therefore, even in the event of complete conversion of Yugo-dinars in that area into kuna, the stability of the Croatian currency can in no way be shaken.&quot;</p>
<p>The kuna has maintained a stable exchange rate since it was introduced at around 3.7 to the mark in May 1994. Exporters have said it is over-valued but a tight money supply and high foreign exchange flows into the country have kept it at around the same level. It now trades at 3.57 to the mark.</p>
<p>The kuna is likely to be exchanged at a rate of one to one for the dinar, which currently trades at 3.3 to the mark officially and is bought for 3.5 on the black market.</p>
<p>United Nations spokesman Doug Coffman said the kuna had already been partially integrated into the region. Civil servants and pensions have been paid in kuna for months and the Croatian-owned INA petrol stations accept the kuna.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a shock for some. But money is money and soon this will be completely reintegrated in the region. The dinar is not going to go away, it's not like when East Germany and West Germany were reunified. The dinar is still the official currency of the country next door.&quot; -- Caroline Smith, Zagreb newsroom, + 385 1 455 7075</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E121">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
