<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569142" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: PRESS DIGEST - Bosnia - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Bosnia - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Sarajevo press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>OSLOBODJENJE</p>
<p>- Deputy High Representative to Bosnia, Michael Steiner, says detention of Moslem opposition member Ibrahim Djedovic for alleged war crimes violates Moslem-Croat federation constitution because Djedovic enjoys parliamentary unity.</p>
<p>- Steiner says he expects a final decision from the U.N. war crimes tribunal on the Djedovic case. In the meantime, Djedovic is staying at a Sarajevo hotel under supervision of the International Police Task Force.</p>
<p>DNEVNI AVAZ</p>
<p>- U.S. envoy James Pardew, overseeing the U.S. military aid programme for Bosnia, is expected to announce a re-shuffle of the federation army to sack some officials who have failed to cooperate, newspaper says, quoting anonymous sources.</p>
<p>- Federation financial police say that oil company Energopetrol owes 65 million German Marks for unpaid road taxes.</p>
<p>VECERNJE NOVINE</p>
<p>- The Croat member of Bosnia's collective presidency Kresimir Zubak and chief of the OSCE mission in Bosnia, Robert Frowick, discussed municipal elections in the disputed town of Brcko. Zubak criticised proposal to create two municipalities in Brcko, saying it could legalise seizure of town by Serb forces. -- Sarajevo newsroom, +387 71 663 864</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
