<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569195" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Telebras pushes Brazil shrs to end higher.</title>
<headline>Telebras pushes Brazil shrs to end higher.</headline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil shares ended up strongly, led by Telebras which surged in a day marked by rumors of strong premiums on the Band B selloff and higher earnings forecasts, brokers said.</p>
<p>The Bovespa index  .BVSP, comprising the 48 most active stocks, closed 2.53 percent higher at 10,437 points.</p>
<p>Market turnover was 896.6 million reais ($845.8 million), one of the highest volumes of the year, according to statistics by the Sao Paulo Stock Exchange (Bovespa).</p>
<p>Telebras, whose preferred stock rose 3.86 percent to 131.70 reais, accounted for over 60 percent of today's trade.  </p>
<p>Traders said Telebras was up on market talks that the Communications Ministry would start soon opening bids for the Band B cellular concessions. They also speculated that the bids presented by consortia competing for the Band B would be much higher than the minimum price asked by the government.</p>
<p>Another rumor that sparked Telebras' rally was that Brazil's Banco de Investimentos Garantia had issued a report raising its earnings forecasts for the firm, traders said.</p>
<p>In the report, they added, Garantia expected the holding Telebras to receive higher receipts from its subsidiaries.  </p>
<p>Private steelmaker CSN, which led the consortium that bought a 41.73 percent voting stake in CVRD, rose 0.5 percent, ending at 37.99 reais.</p>
<p>Other steel firms, however, lost ground amid investor concern about the effects of CSN's acquisition of CVRD in the steel sector. Cosipa preferred fell 2.74 percent to 0.71 reais, Usiminas common stock plunged 5.26 percent to 0.90 reais, while CST dropped 1.03 percent to 14.35 reais.  </p>
<p>A Garantia spokesperson in New York said the Brazilian investment bank had reiterated its buy recommendation Wednesday, without providing further details.</p>
<p>After today's sharp rise, analysts said investors were likely to take profits on Telebras stock Friday, particularly on Telebras voting shares which surged 5.45 percent.</p>
<p>Among other blue-chips, CVRD preferred, which plunged over eight percent Wednesday on disappointment with the outcome of the firm's privatization auction, managed to end 0.98 percent higher at 25.80 reais.  </p>
<p>Acesita preferred lost 1.19 percent to 2.50 reais.</p>
<p>Earlier Salomon Brothers issued a report saying that CSN's participation in CVRD would significantly change the steel equation in Brazil.</p>
<p>It reiterated its buy rating on CSN and hold recommendation on Acesita, Cosipa and CST.</p>
<p>((--Fatima Cristina, Sao Paulo newsroom 5511 2485412))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
