<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569168" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Clinton tours Mexican town, ancient pyramids.</title>
<headline>Clinton tours Mexican town, ancient pyramids.</headline>
<byline>Steve Holland</byline>
<dateline>TLAXCALA, Mexico 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton escaped from meetings to play tourist in Mexico on Wednesday, visiting a typical colonial town and some huge ancient pyramids.</p>
<p>After visiting the picturesque town of Tlaxcala, where thousands welcomed him by tossing clouds of confetti into the air, Clinton, Mexican President Ernesto Zedillo and their wives toured the ancient ruins of Teotihuacan, some of the most impressive in Mexico.</p>
<p>Clinton is often envious of the freedom to see the countryside that his wife Hillary enjoys on her solo foreign travels, complaining he is always cooped up in meetings and does not have as much fun as she does.</p>
<p>So he spent most of the last day of his three-day visit to Mexico out of the capital.</p>
<p>In Tlaxcala, 75 miles (120 km) east of Mexico City, thousands of cheering government supporters were bussed in to greet the two presidents.</p>
<p>&quot;Buenos Dias, Tlaxcala,&quot; Clinton told the crowd gathered in the town square, many waving Mexican and U.S. flags. He and Zedillo then jumped into the crowd to shake hands and pose for photographs for with the locals.</p>
<p>&quot;President Clinton is a good friend of the Mexicans because he respects them,&quot; Zedillo told his countrymen.</p>
<p>Clinton mentioned in his speech that he and Hillary had honeymooned in the Mexican resort of Acapulco.</p>
<p>&quot;It is an especially important day for my wife and for me because we were married about 22 years ago and we came to Mexico on our honeymoon. So we always love to come back, and this is a very romantic setting to be in today and we thank you for that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The crowd cheered when this was translated into Spanish.</p>
<p>Just like he was at a campaign event back home, Clinton shook hands from the enthusiastic crowd along the ropeline after his speech as a mariachi band played, &quot;Viva Mexico&quot;.</p>
<p>After lunch in the courtyard of a monastery in Tlaxcala, Clinton emerged from the building wearing a necklace of red, green and turquoise-coloured wooden beads and was given two carved white canes.</p>
<p>Recovering from a March 14 knee injury, Clinton began the visit using crutches. But he traded them for the canes and took a few steps, saying: &quot;About next Monday, I get to go to the canes, so we're doing quite well.&quot;</p>
<p>Outside the monastery, Clinton browsed a display of local crafts, including vases, rugs and masks, laid out for him on a long table set under a tree.</p>
<p>The president and his wife saw a pair of coloured masks, which they put up to their faces. Clinton's had a beard and his wife's a moustache.</p>
<p>Mrs. Clinton said: &quot;I could wear this in public.&quot; Wearing the masks, the two touched noses playfully as waiting photographers snapped away in a frenzy.</p>
<p>The U.S. president selected the bearded mask and a large vase and Mrs. Clinton picked out a nativity scene but the merchants refused to let them pay.</p>
<p>Clinton insisted, telling the merchants that if they were going to give him a gift, they must allow him to buy one.</p>
<p>The merchants still demurred, until Clinton pulled some pesos from his pocket and said: &quot;Don't fight me, I'm trying to build up your tourism.&quot; The merchants took the money.</p>
<p>At Teotihuacan, the two leaders and their wives were driven through the site in a topless Volkswagen minibus adorned with the Mexican and U.S. flags.</p>
<p>They first stopped at the Temple of the Moon and then at the long street known as the Avenue of the Dead which leads past the Temple of the Sun, the tallest building in the area.</p>
<p>Teotihuacan, known as the City of the Gods, is located 35 miles (56 kilometres) northwest of Mexico City. At its peak it was one of the world's biggest and most spectacular cities but it fell into decline long before the Spanish conquistadors arrived in the early 1500s.</p>
<p>Clinton stopped at another part of the site and was told by his guide that it burned about 750 A.D., but before the fire it would have been painted in bright colours.</p>
<p>&quot;It is stunning the way it is, you can just imagine what it would be like,&quot; Clinton said, as drops of rain began to fall and fireworks could be heard in a nearby village where the villagers were celebrating a feast day.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TLAXCALA, Mexico"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
