<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569128" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Croatian Kras says has new potential investor.</title>
<headline>Croatian Kras says has new potential investor.</headline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leading Croatian confectioner Kras said on Thursday it had a new potential investor in addition to the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD).</p>
<p>&quot;Talks with the EBRD are still going on, but there are other interesting propositions being discussed with another party,&quot; finance director Tomislav Jovic told Reuters.</p>
<p>He declined to reveal the identity of the new suitor.</p>
<p>He did not say whether it was a strategic investor from the same branch or a financial institution, interested in backing up the company's development plans with a loan.</p>
<p>The two sides agreed to treat negotiations confidentially until a final deal was reached, Jovic said, but added: &quot;This could be very soon.&quot;</p>
<p>The EBRD was widely believed to be interested in granting a credit to the chocolate-maker and later converting it into an equity stake, as it did with drugs firm Pliva a year ago.</p>
<p>But talks have dragged on for months, with neither party appearing willing to disclose any concrete details.</p>
<p>Recent rumours about the deal being abandoned have gnawed at the price of Kras shares on Zagreb's bourse where it trades in the section for semi-regulated companies. Its shares closed five kuna lower at 415 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>This compares to the 430-460 kuna range Kras traded at last month and a high of 550 kuna, recorded earlier in the year.</p>
<p>However Jovic said the company paid little attention to the market speculation and was interested in &quot;securing a sound basis for its share growth&quot;. -- Kolumbina Bencevic, Zagreb Newsroom, 385-1-4557075</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150106">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
