<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569167" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Clinton hails free trade, presses flesh in Mexico.</title>
<headline>Clinton hails free trade, presses flesh in Mexico.</headline>
<byline>Michael Stott</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Eager to strike a positive note on the final day of his visit to Mexico, U.S. President Bill Clinton called on Wednesday for an expansion of free trade across the Americas and kissed a Mexican toddler during a stroll through a cheering crowd.</p>
<p>Clinton told a group of business leaders in the Mexican capital that the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) boosted trade and brought new, well-paid jobs to both nations.</p>
<p>&quot;NAFTA is working for America and it is working for Mexico,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>&quot;We must include more nations in our partnership, so that we can achieve the goal set out at the (1994) Summit of the Americas of a Free Trade Area of the Americas,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton then flew to the picturesque colonial city of Tlaxcala, 75 miles (120 km) east of Mexico City for a carefully managed meeting with &quot;ordinary Mexicans.&quot;</p>
<p>Several thousand Mexican peasants were bussed into the city by the government for the occasion, handed U.S. and Mexican flags and given a free packed lunch. They responded by showering the presidential motorcade with confetti and shouting welcome slogans.</p>
<p>Clinton made a brief speech in the town square recalling his honeymoon in Mexico nearly 22 years ago before plunging into the crowd along with his host, President Ernesto Zedillo.</p>
<p>Clearly relishing the occasion, Clinton shook hands, posed for pictures and kissed a little girl held out to him by a proud mother.</p>
<p>&quot;It is an especially important day for my wife and for me because we were married about 22 years ago and we came to Mexico on our honeymoon. So we always love to come back, and this is a very romantic setting to be in today and we thank you for that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Long in the grip of Zedillo's Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI), picturesque Tlaxcala suffers none of the grinding poverty, political violence or guerrilla revolts that afflict other Mexican tourist destinations such as Oaxaca or Chiapas.</p>
<p>But once the motorcade left, some Tlaxcalans complained about the way they said Americans treated Mexican migrants.</p>
<p>&quot;William Clinton is exciting but I also have complaints. He should not let them mistreat Mexicans,&quot; secretary Marcela Suarez Luna told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The U.S. won't function without Mexican dishwashers and gardeners,&quot; muttered Miguel Angel Garcia, who was deported from his job at a Wyoming hotel last year for lacking papers.</p>
<p>Earlier, in the Mexican capital, the two presidents again addressed the topics that have dominated Clinton's first official visit to Mexico -- drugs and illegal immigration.</p>
<p>On both subjects, Clinton stressed what has been the abiding theme of his visit -- the need to cooperate rather than argue with Mexico.</p>
<p>Protests have been sparse on Clinton's visit.</p>
<p>Demonstrators have complained that the massive police and army presence in the centre of Mexico's capital prevented them from even gathering, far less expressing dissent.</p>
<p>In speeches on Wednesday, Clinton praised the contribution that Hispanics and Mexican-Americans -- including his Energy Secretary Federico Pena -- had made to the United States.</p>
<p>But he emphasised Washington would not tolerate illegal immigration. &quot;We are a nation of immigrants and of laws,&quot; he said. &quot;Just as those who obey our laws are welcome, those who break them must face the consequences.&quot;</p>
<p>After lunch, Clinton and Zedillo visited Mexico's famous pre-Columbian pyramids at Teotihuacan -- one of the marvels of the ancient world -- before returning to the capital for a quick courtesy call to the U.S. embassy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
