<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569169" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil &quot;King of Steel&quot; open to more CVRD partners.</title>
<headline>Brazil &quot;King of Steel&quot; open to more CVRD partners.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The new owners of Brazilian mining conglomerate Companhia Vale do Rio Doce (CVRD) remain open to new partners, including deals with Japanese rivals who lost the bidding for CVRD, said the leader of the winning group.</p>
<p>&quot;We are open to talks with everyone. Anyone who adds value to the group is welcome,&quot; said Benjamin Steinbruch, chairman of Brazil's largest steelmaker Companhia Siderurgica Nacional (CSN).  </p>
<p>CSN, together with Charlotte, N.C.-based NationsBank, investment fund Opportunity Asset Management and four Brazilian pension funds, won a controlling stake in the world's largest iron ore exporter Tuesday with a $3.15 billion bid for 41.73 percent of CVRD's voting stock.</p>
<p>Their consortium, Valepar, also known as Consortium Brazil, paid 19.89 percent above the $25 per share base price to defeat the Valecom group, headed by Brazilian conglomerate Votorantim, South Africa's Anglo-American Corp and 11 Japanese steel firms.  </p>
<p>&quot;The Japanese can remain calm. The Consortium Brazil will travel to Japan,&quot; Steinbruch told reporters in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
<p>The man being dubbed Brazil's &quot;King of Steel&quot; by local newspapers and one of the most powerful men in Brazilian industry acknowledged that the CVRD auction rules prohibited a change in ownership for a two-year &quot;lock-up period&quot; after the sale.</p>
<p>But he told Reuters in a brief interview that CSN believed there were loopholes in the rules that would allow new partners into the Special Purpose Company set up to run CVRD, perhaps without direct capital participation.  </p>
<p>Consortium members have agreed that ownership of the controlling stake should be an obligatory 50-50 between the pension funds and the private firms.</p>
<p>Steinbruch reiterated assurances made Tuesday that there would be no abrupt changes in the way CVRD is run except perhaps a &quot;more flexible and aggressive&quot; style and said CVRD and CSN would both continue to operate perfectly independently.</p>
<p>He said he would not hive off the steel operations from CVRD and group them with CSN under a &quot;steel holding&quot; because his view was that &quot;good&quot; long-term supply contracts &quot;made more sense&quot;.</p>
<p>Steinbruch also said he believed the price paid for CVRD, too high for Votorantim's Japanese partners, was &quot;comfortable&quot; and insisted that CSN's financing was at fair international rates and within the servicing capabilities of the firm.</p>
<p>As for a nasty 6.5 percent drop in CVRD's preferred shares Wednesday, &quot;everyone who knows anything about the market knows it rises on the rumour and sinks on the fact,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>((-- Rio newsroom 55-21-5074151))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
