<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569191" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peru's Yanacocha issues $100 million debt.</title>
<headline>Peru's Yanacocha issues $100 million debt.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. investment bank Salomon Brothers said Thursday Peruvian gold miner Minera Yanacocha S.A., a joint venture run by Newmont Mining Co, had issued $100 million in new debt paper.</p>
<p>&quot;Minera Yanacocha, the largest gold producer in Latin America, successfully launched $100 million of seven-year future U.S. dollar-denominated gold receivable notes, priced at 185 basis points over the five-year U.S. Treasury,&quot; Salomon Brothers said in a statement faxed from New York.  </p>
<p>Salomon Brothers added the oversubscribed issue, which was &quot;broadly distributed to investors in the United States,&quot; received a BBB-rating from Standard &amp; Poor's and &quot;represents the first Peruvian commodity asset-backed transaction that has been rated investment grade.&quot;</p>
<p>Janice Warne, Salomon Brothers managing director and head of structured and project finance, said the issue was &quot;particularly remarkable considering that Peru was a new country for most of the investors and that this was the first export receivables securitization from any country to involve gold exports.&quot;  </p>
<p>Yanacocha, in the northern Andes, is owned by partners Newmont and local firm Cia. Minera Buenaventura S.A., which have 51.35 percent and 43.65 percent respectively. The remaining five percent is owned by the World Bank's International Finance Corp.</p>
<p>The firm produces gold through heap-leaching operations at its open-pit mines in highland Cajamarca department some 375 miles (600 km) north of Lima.  </p>
<p>&quot;Yanacocha produced more than 811,000 ounces of gold in 1996 and has current reserves and resources in excess of 11 million ounces,&quot; said the statement from Salomon Brothers, the sole manager of the debt issue.</p>
<p>((-- Lima newsroom, 511 221-2134))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
