<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569166" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COSTA RICA: Clinton arrives in Costa Rica for regional summit.</title>
<headline>Clinton arrives in Costa Rica for regional summit.</headline>
<byline>Dan Trotta</byline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton arrived late on Wednesday in Central America, where he will meet regional leaders eager to advance free trade while at the same time winning relief for their beleaguered illegal immigrants living in the United States.</p>
<p>Accompanied by first lady Hillary Rodham Clinton and a host of cabinet secretaries, Clinton said in opening remarks he was happy to be making his first visit to Costa Rica, the richest Central American country and one which avoided the Cold War-era guerrilla conflicts of the 1980s.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a moment of great opportunity and hope for all the Americas, but especially here in Central America, where decades of conflict and division have given way to peace and cooperation,&quot; Clinton told host President Jose Maria Figueres and hundreds of high school students gathered to greet him.</p>
<p>&quot;I am pleased and honoured ... to experience firsthand your unique tradition of greeting foreign leaders not with a military salute but with the cheers of your wonderful young people,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Costa Rica abolished its army in 1948.</p>
<p>Clinton came from a 48-hour state visit to Mexico, the first leg of his first trip to Latin America since becoming president in January 1993. It was the first visit to Central America by a U.S. president since George Bush came to Costa Rica in 1989.</p>
<p>Clinton on Thursday will meet with leaders of six Central American countries -- Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua, Costa Rica and Belize, and the Dominican Republic, a Caribbean island nation.</p>
<p>Figueres welcomed Clinton with a brief speech in Spanish and topped it off with a message in English, saying &quot;Thank you for your visit and the honour you have bestowed on this region.&quot;</p>
<p>But starting on Thursday, the protocol will give way to substantive differences over trade and immigration.</p>
<p>The Central Americans said they want concrete progress on a free-trade treaty with Washington and demand better treatment for their illegal immigrants in the United States. Neither topic likely to find support in the U.S. Congress.</p>
<p>Clinton will need to stake out a middle position between accommodating his Central American hosts while avoiding promises that could be rejected back home, diplomats said.</p>
<p>&quot;Yes, of course, we know these things are not popular there,&quot; Luis Guillermo Solis, director of policy in the Costa Rican Foreign Ministry, told Reuters. &quot;But we have decided that we can't be timid as we see the world dividing up into trading blocs like Mercosur (in South America) and NAFTA (the North American Free Trade Agreement grouping the United States, Canada and Mexico).&quot;</p>
<p>The tiny Central American economies, many battered by war and lack of foreign investment, have begun integrating in recent years, forming a more formidable market of 30 million people.</p>
<p>The seven regional leaders gathered for the first time on Wednesday night, naming Presidents Arnoldo Aleman of Nicaragua and Armando Calderon Sol of El Salvador as the point men with Clinton on immigration, Figueres told reporters.</p>
<p>President Carlos Roberto Reina of Honduras and Prime Minister Manuel Esquivel of Belize will cover the theme of democracy while President Alvaro Arzu and President Leonel Fernandez of the Dominican Republic will speak for the region on the economy, Figures said.</p>
<p>Clinton is venturing into a territory that has a long history of clashes with the United States, which has either invaded, engineered a coup or armed a favoured side in almost every country on the region except Costa Rica.</p>
<p>But with the Cold War now history, relations have changed.</p>
<p>The Central Americans will seek a pledge from Clinton to do something to protect the hundreds of thousands of illegal Central American immigrants living in the United States.</p>
<p>Major provisions of a tough new U.S. immigration law passed in 1996 took effect on April 1 of this year, including one that wipes out the preferential treatment on immigration matters formerly granted to Central American countries.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a problem that we Central Americans did not create,&quot; Figueres said regarding mass immigration. &quot;This problem has its roots in the Cold War years. ... More than anywhere else on the continent, we Central Americans suffered in flesh and blood.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="COSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ELSAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GUAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NICG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Costa Rica"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COSTA RICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
