<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569176" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil telcom law seen approved by June/July.</title>
<headline>Brazil telcom law seen approved by June/July.</headline>
<byline>Simona de Logu</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazilian Telecommunication Minister Sergio Motta said he expects Congress to approve at the latest by the end of July the new telecommunications law which sets the rules for the privatization of the sector.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe the law will be voted on in the lower house May 20-22. Then it will go directly to the Senate,&quot; Motta told reporters. &quot;It will probably spend 36 days in the Senate, so by June, at the latest by the end of July, we expect the law to be approved.&quot;  </p>
<p>The bill does not set down any restrictions on foreign capital taking part in the privatization of the federal Telebras system nor in the operating of telecommunications services.</p>
<p>Instead, the bill would give the Brazilian president powers to limit the involvement of foreign capital on a case-by-case basis, depending on Brazil's trade relations with each country in question.  </p>
<p>Motta said it was his &quot;personal opinion&quot; that foreign participation would probably be limited to 49 percent as in the privatization of Band B cellular concessions, which started earlier this year.</p>
<p>He said the government would be announcing May 15 to 20 which consortia had bids qualifying them to run the Band B concessions in the 10 different areas across Brazil.</p>
<p>He said the winners of the first two concessions, Sao Paulo city and the center west, were expected to be announced at the end of May, and the winners of the other areas throughout June and July.  </p>
<p>Fifteen consortia have submitted bids to operate the Band B concessions.</p>
<p>&quot;Our expectation is that the Band B privatization will achieve an exceptional result, probably far beyond that of CVRD,&quot; Motta said.</p>
<p>The privatization of mining giant CVRD, which kicked off this week with the successful auction of a 41.73-percent voting stake in CVRD, is expected to net the government at least $5 billion.</p>
<p>Private operators of Band B services will compete with existing Band A services provided by the state-level units of Telebras, which will be privatized as of next year.</p>
<p>Motta said the government would decide in the next 60 days whether the Band A services would be privatized separately or together with the Telebras state subsidiaries.</p>
<p>Sao Paulo state telecommunications company, the first unit of the Telebras system to be privatized, is expected to be sold off by the end of the first quarter of 1998, Motta said.</p>
<p>((--Rio de Janeiro newsroom, 5521 507 4151))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
