<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569105" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russians ask if Kremlin seeks NATO deal too fast.</title>
<headline>Russians ask if Kremlin seeks NATO deal too fast.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Heritage</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin said on Thursday a security deal with NATO was almost ready, but even some of his supporters are asking whether Russia is rushing too fast into a deal which might offer it little or no gain.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like Yeltsin has already made up his mind to sign a document with NATO on May 27. The question is -- will it be anything more than a fig leaf covering up shortcomings?&quot; said Alexei Pushkov, a commentator for the Moscow News newspaper.</p>
<p>The agreement is intended to lay the foundations of a harmonious partnership between the two former Cold-War foes in the next century and, in part, to address Russian fears over the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation's eastward expansion.</p>
<p>Yeltsin, who told reporters the deal was about 98 percent ready after months of haggling, says he will not sign a document on the target date of May 27 just for the sake of putting something on paper.</p>
<p>He indicated the Western defence alliance had not met all Russia's demands, most notably rebuffing Moscow's request for written guarantees that it will not build up nuclear and conventional arms in new member states.</p>
<p>But he also said he hoped NATO Secretary General Javier Solana and Russian Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov would resolve the remaining problems at talks in Moscow on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The latest talks with Solana this week in Luxembourg, and with U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright in Moscow last week, have been shrouded in secrecy.</p>
<p>Some Kremlin sources say a deal, establishing a council which would give Russia a say in some NATO matters affecting its security, is &quot;all but complete&quot; and that Moscow has won some important concessions.</p>
<p>They say NATO and Moscow may sign a broad declaration outlining the aims of their relationship and issue a separate document which contains the more contentious issues.</p>
<p>That, some independent analysts say, would be better than no deal at all because Moscow would have forced NATO to consider its views despite starting out with almost no cards to play. NATO has made clear all along that expansion will go ahead regardless of Russia's reaction.</p>
<p>Other analysts and politicans fear Moscow has still not obtained enough concessions to make the deal worth signing. A senior Kremlin security official made his doubts clear last month, although he later played down his remarks.</p>
<p>&quot;I simply suffered serious doubts about the quality of the agreement as it stood at that moment,&quot; Yuri Baturin, secretary of the advisory Defence Council, explained in an interview in the latest edition of the weekly Interfax-AiF newspaper.</p>
<p>The Communist Party, the largest opposition force in parliament, is more blunt.</p>
<p>&quot;They (the Kremlin) have lost on every front,&quot; Communist Party leader Gennady Zyuganov todl reporters this week. &quot;They are fooling the country and ignore the nation's interests.&quot;</p>
<p>Zyuganov's reaction, if predictable from Yeltsin's traditional opponents, was a sign of the criticism the president will face if he appears to have sold out Russian interests.</p>
<p>It will be hard to portray the final document as a victory if it includes no binding guarantees against an arms buildup near Russia's borders, and if Moscow's demands for the amendments it wants to a 1990 treaty restricting movement and numbers of conventional weapons in Europe are ignored.</p>
<p>&quot;As I see it, Russia will not get all the guarantees and obligations it wants,&quot; Pushkov told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;If it is signed just for the sake of signing it, the deal will not convince the Russian political elite, and ordinary Russians will not take it seriously. I ask myself what use it is rushing into a deal with no binding guarantees.&quot;</p>
<p>Although Yeltsin says his demands for concessions must be met, he is also anxious to sign the agreement before a NATO summit in Madrid in July at which some eastern European countries will be offered membership.</p>
<p>&quot;He wants a deal before Madrid so that Russia can attend the NATO summit and present itself as being part of the meeting, a country which was really considered over NATO expansion,&quot; said Viktor Kremenyuk of the USA and Canada Institute thinktank.</p>
<p>&quot;He wants to avoid a confrontation or crisis with the West.&quot;</p>
<p>Yeltsin has made overtures towards China to the east and Slav neighbour Belarus to the west in a clear response to NATO. But he is also wary of upsetting the West, a major source of financial help as Moscow undergoes tough economic reforms.</p>
<p>Some analysts say Yeltsin might consider continuing negotiations after the Madrid summit, but that he appears to believe Russia is less likely to win any concessions once the process of NATO enlargement is already under way.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
