<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569150" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: PRESS DIGEST - Latvia - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Latvia - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the main stories in Latvian newspapers on Thursday. Prepared for Reuters by the Co-operation Fund. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Prime minister Andris Shkele requested the resignation of Andrejs Krastins, the minister of defence, amid a corruption scandal surrounding the purchase by the ministry of defence of 2,900 tonnes of diesel and 200 of lubricants for the navy. Krastinsh denied the charges but said he would quit if the PM wanted him to. Krastins' party, the LNNK, said it would not leave the ruling coalition.</p>
<p>- Parliament held its first foreign policy debate. Foreign Minister Valdis Birkavs said it showed support for the policies of EU integration and efforts for NATO.</p>
<p>- Russian MPs on a trip to Latvia warn that the Russian Duma would not ratify any agreement until Latvia fulfils the recommendations of international bodies concerning the rights of non-citizens, most of whom are Russian-speakers.</p>
<p>- Latvia's constitutional court passed its first verdict over a dispute between 35 MPs and the government concerning cabinet rules for the purchase of energy produced by generation plants, backing parliament.</p>
<p>DIENA</p>
<p>- Latvian officials believe a project for the development of Latvian ports, drafted by EU PHARE experts for the period to 2000 and which predicted a drop in port turnover and slow growth in cargos after the year 2000, is unfounded.</p>
<p>BIZNES &amp; BALTIJA</p>
<p>- International auditing company Deloitte &amp; Touche is to organise the competition tender to replace two of the Latvian Privatisation Agency's four direrctors.</p>
<p>- Parliament will tomorrow again consider amendments to the law on gambling, that bans slot-machines from basement cellars</p>
<p>-- Riga newsroom, +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
