<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569171" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuela domestic mogas market seen open by 1998.</title>
<headline>Venezuela domestic mogas market seen open by 1998.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Venezuela's government is planning to begin liberalization of the gasoline retailing market by the end of this year, with full competition by the end of 1998, deputy Energy and Mines Minister Evanan Romero said Wednesday.</p>
<p>The government's bill governing liberalization was still being reviewed by the ministerial council, but would be presented to Congress soon.  </p>
<p>&quot;In this bill we incorporate a transition period of one year during which the executive branch will still regulate the prices and PDVSA (state-owned Petroleos de Venezuela) stay the main supplier of products even though the law allows wholesalers to import,&quot; he said after a meeting in Congress.</p>
<p>He added that imports during this period were unlikely because retail prices would be set at the factory gate level and wholesalers and retailers would be paid a fixed margin.</p>
<p>&quot;The executive branch during this year will establish a margin so that the service stations can recuperate their investment. Then after a year the whole thing will be open,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>When it arrives in Congress, the government's bill will have to fight off competition from a more conservative one drawn up by some congressmen which provides for partial liberalisation.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect that by the end of the year the Congress will give its approval (to the government's bill),&quot; Romero said.</p>
<p>((--Tom Ashby, Caracas newroom, 582 505 2611))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
