<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569138" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: PRESS DIGEST -  Yugoslavia -  May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST -  Yugoslavia -  May 8.</headline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Serbian and Montenegrin press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>			    - SERBIA -</p>
<p>POLITIKA</p>
<p>- Serbian parliament session scheduled for May 13 to discuss the bill on concessions.</p>
<p>- Economic policy fully carried out in the first four months of the year which is supported by economic indicators -- stable dinar exchange rate, zero price growth, balanced budget expenditure -- says Serbian government.</p>
<p>- Croatia agrees to demilitarisation of the area now under UNTAES control, to cross-border trade with Yugoslavia and dual citizenship for Serbs in Eastern Slavonia, says statement after meeting of Croatian President Franjo Tudjman and U.N. administrator Jacques Klein.</p>
<p>- A group of Spanish businessmen, including representatives of the three biggest banks, will visit Yugoslavia for a Spanish week from May 16 to 25, Spanish ambassador in Belgrade said.</p>
<p>- Yugoslavia and Croatia agree to respect ownership rights regardless of citizenship at a meeting of their joint commission in Zagreb.</p>
<p>- Internationally-mediated former Yugoslavia succession talks have not made any significant progress in defining state ownership, said Yugoslav government commission for relations with the Peace Implementation Council.</p>
<p>- Yugoslav metal works Trepca director Novak Bijelic said the Trepca $519 million deal with Greek Mitilineos will engage one third of Trepca's potentials.</p>
<p>- Small pox epidemic in Kosovo abates.</p>
<p>- So far 80 percent of the planned 2.36 million hectares have been sown in Serbia and spring sowing is expected to be completed in two to three days, says Serbian Agriculture Minister Jovan Babovic.</p>
<p>NASA BORBA</p>
<p>- Kosovo Albanians decide to hold elections for their parallel parliament within the next six months.</p>
<p>- Just ten firms, eight from the power industry, one in oil refining and one in the chemical industry, account for 41 percent of 1996 Yugoslav economy losses which stood at 12.6 billion dinars, says Institute of Economic Sciences.</p>
<p>- There are 100 Kosovo Albanian political prisoners in Serbian prisons, says Association of political prisoners from Kosovo.</p>
<p>- Zastava car factory from Kragujevac plans to produce 2,000 cars in May, 720 of which are for exports to Egypt.</p>
<p>POLITIKA EKSPRES</p>
<p>- Montenegrin Prime Minister Milo Djukanovic advocates independence of Montenegro and its possible separation from Yugoslavia and even tries to pull the Yugoslav army into his plans, commentary.</p>
<p>- Basket of food for four-member family in May stands at 1,485 dinars and was 1,504 dinars in April, statistics</p>
<p>VECERNJE NOVOSTI</p>
<p>- Third round of Yugoslav-Macedonian border talks ends today. Macedonians give up idea to demand monastery Prohor Pcinski in Yugoslav territory.</p>
<p>- Moslems are preparing for an offensive on Bosnian Serb republic in August, says Bosnian Serb Chief of General Staff General Pero Colic.</p>
<p>			  - MONTENEGRO -</p>
<p>POBJEDA</p>
<p>-  Prime Minister Milo Djukanovic received representatives of Siemens and VF-Tel. Siemens soon to open its office in Montenegro.</p>
<p>- Montenegrin Parliament Speaker Svetozar Marovic denies giving an interview to the Belgrade weekly Nedeljni Telegraf published on May 7.</p>
<p>- Head of the Democratic Party of Socialists parliamentary club Predrag Bulatovic denied reports that Montenegrin President Momir Bulatovic was dissatisfied because government reshuffle is not a separate issue on the agenda of next week's parliament session. Bulatovic said the issue will be be discussed under the topic elections and appointments.</p>
<p>- Montenegrin Airlines made its promotion flight to Bari, Italy.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Milo Djukanovic visited refrigerator factory Obod in Cetinje. -- Belgrade newsroom + 381 11 222 4305</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
