<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569107" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: PRESS DIGEST - Slovenia - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Slovenia - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>LJUBLJANA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are the main stories in Slovenia's Thursday morning newspapers:</p>
<p>DELO</p>
<p>- The Bank of Slovenia said on Wednesday its target M3 growth for 1997 was 18 percent, down from 19.9 percent growth in 1996.</p>
<p>- Slovenian army on Wednesday presented its medical unit that will participate in international peace keeping mission in Albania. The 24 staff unit, which starts operation next week is the first Slovenian unit to be sent abroad.</p>
<p>- Parliamentary boards of defence and international relations met on Wednesday to discuss Slovenia's efforts to join EU and NATO. The two boards agreed that the country should do as much as possible to join NATO in the first round of its expansion.</p>
<p>- The only slovenian nuclear power plant Krsko will be closed for 33 days from Friday for a regular annual refitting.</p>
<p>- Extremely high tide flooded Slovenian coastal towns on Wednesday, no major damages were reported.</p>
<p>DNEVNIK</p>
<p>- Tourist facilities with a capacity for 350.000 owned by Slovenian companies on the Croatian coast will most probably be closed this summer for Slovenian tourists, according to Croatian law freezing use and sales of foreign real-estate property.</p>
<p>- Over 154 companies from 18 countries participate in a four-day international computer exhibition that started in Ljubljana on Wednesday.</p>
<p>VECER</p>
<p>- Slovenia's industrial output in February fell 2.7 percent compared to the average industrial output last year, while January's industrial output fell 2.4 percent, the Statistical Office reported on Wednesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LJUBLJANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
