<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569154" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: FEATURE - Hardships force German exodus from Kazakhstan.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Hardships force German exodus from Kazakhstan.</headline>
<byline>Dmitry Solovyov</byline>
<dateline>KARL MARX, Kazakhstan 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A sign on the arch over the village of Karl Marx once declared it an &quot;exemplary collective farm&quot;.</p>
<p>Now, many of the houses look abandoned and the collective is slowly falling apart as the ethnic Germans who live there join the exodus from Kazakhstan for a new life abroad.</p>
<p>Soviet-era posters boasting a brave new world of collective farming have made way for &quot;House for sale&quot; signs tacked on gates and fences.</p>
<p>&quot;Germans are leaving Kazakhstan because life has become unbearable,&quot; said 72-year-old Anton Hartmann, standing inside his spacious single-storey brick home. &quot;My pension has not been paid for nine months. We have no water, electricity is intermittent and the streets are full of beggars.&quot;</p>
<p>Hartmann's wife Yekaterina admitted she sometimes felt like a traitor for leaving -- the couple plan to join their nephew in Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;We are traitors because we want to leave our motherland,&quot; she said. &quot;But this hard life is forcing us out.&quot;</p>
<p>ONCE A MAJORITY, NOW A MINORITY</p>
<p>Until recently ethnic Germans like Hartmann accounted for more than 90 percent of the population of this farm in Kazakhstan's Kostanai region, about 2,000 km (1,250 miles) north of the capital, Almaty. Now they are a 15 percent minority.</p>
<p>Members of the German society Wiedergeburt say 52,000 of Kostanai's 107,000 ethnic Germans have already left.</p>
<p>&quot;Local Germans are leaving for Germany because life has become so difficult...There are tears in their eyes when they leave,&quot; said Ivan Witstein, head of the collective farm.</p>
<p>&quot;Our farm was a prosperous one not so long ago -- there was a car in every other home. But what do people have today? When your pension is not paid, patriotism vanishes.&quot;</p>
<p>Witstein said the village and its 2,200 inhabitants had been severely hit by the collapse of Kazakh agriculture and crushed by high taxes.</p>
<p>&quot;But despite the circumstances, why are Kazakhs and Russians buying houses here? Because Germans always worked hard and lived better,&quot; he said with grim pride.</p>
<p>SOVIET GERMANS' TROUBLED HISTORY</p>
<p>The farm's history -- it was originally named Ozyorny (lake) -- is typical of other German settlements in Kazakhstan.</p>
<p>It was founded at the turn of the century by Germans who moved from Ukraine to work Kazakhstan's sea of empty steppe.</p>
<p>The Germans were first invited to settle in the Russian empire by Peter the Great in the 18th century. Later, Catherine the Great encouraged them, hoping they would bring progress to the region.</p>
<p>But after the 1917 revolution, local communists set up a commune in Ozyorny and called it Neues Leben (New Life). It was renamed Karl Marx during the Soviet Union's brutal collectivisation in the 1930s.</p>
<p>Hartmann's father disappeared in 1938 when million's vanished in dictator Josef Stalin's &quot;great terror&quot;.</p>
<p>Worse for the Germans was to come.</p>
<p>When Nazi Germany invaded the Soviet Union in 1941, Stalin dissolved the Germans' autonomous republic along Russia's Volga river, fearing ethnic Germans would collaborate with the fast advancing enemy.</p>
<p>Hundreds of thousands of Germans were deported in cattle wagons to the Kazakh steppes and the Siberian forests.</p>
<p>Hartmann -- like other able-bodied German men and women -- was not allowed to join the Red Army but was sent to the &quot;labour front&quot; to lay railways and work in coal mines. Germans were not allowed to speak their own language.</p>
<p>&quot;Even decades after the end of the World War Two, Germans were barred from getting a good education and children were often nicknamed 'fascists' in schools,&quot; Hartmann said.</p>
<p>Time has healed much of the grief but local German activists say that only the full rehabilitation of ex-Soviet Germans and some degree of autonomy could halt the emigration.</p>
<p>DEMANDS FOR GERMAN AUTONOMY</p>
<p>&quot;I think that besides the economic problems, another reason for German emigration is that we have not been fully rehabilitated in the former Soviet Union,&quot; said Jakob Bader, chairman of the Kostanai branch of Wiedergeburt.</p>
<p>&quot;If German autonomy in Russia had been restored, or a new autononomous republic set up, then at least 70 percent of Soviet Germans would not have emigrated,&quot; he said,</p>
<p>But Russia has turned a deaf ear to German demands for autonomy and Kazakhstan, itself a complicated mosaic of nationalities, declared itself a &quot;unitary state&quot; after it became independent following the Soviet collapse in 1991.</p>
<p>&quot;All this is sad...Now everything will depend on the speed at which Germany absorbs immigrants. In about five years the problem of Germans will no longer exist in Kazakhstan,&quot; Bader said.</p>
<p>An official from the Almaty-based German society Deutsches Haus said around 400,000 Germans still lived in Kazakhstan, compared to 1.1 million registered in the 1989 census.</p>
<p>He said that last year alone, 171,000 Germans from the former Soviet Union, including more than 92,000 from Kazakhstan, emigrated to Germany.</p>
<p>Germany has imposed an annual immigration quota of 200,000 people from the countries of the former Soviet Union and Chancellor Helmut Kohl and Kazakh President Nursultan Nazarbayev are likely to look at ways to try to stem emigration when they meet in Almaty on Sunday (May 11).</p>
<p>But Bader believes it is too late.</p>
<p>&quot;The older generation is slowly dying, while the younger one is unfamiliar with the language and traditions of its people...Too many now associate national revival with emigration to Germany,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARL MARX, Kazakhstan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
