<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569186" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Colombian stocks end higher with banks active.</title>
<headline>Colombian stocks end higher with banks active.</headline>
<text>
<p>BOGOTA, May 8 Reuter - Colombian stocks ended with modest gains on Thursday amid solid demand for Banco de Bogota and a huge cross-trade in shares of Banco de Colombia, brokers said.</p>
<p>Medellin's IBOMED general price index closed up 0.30 percent at 17,728.90 on trading volume of 2.2 billion pesos. Bogota's IBB index added 0.44 percent to 1,171.256 on above-average volume of 5.6 billion pesos.</p>
<p>Traders said some 4.2 billion pesos of volume in Bogota involved a cross-trade of shares of Banco de Colombia, the country's second-largest commercial bank in terms of assets.  </p>
<p>The bank's stock closed unchanged in Bogota at 397 pesos per share on what brokers described as a pocket-to-pocket deal between leading shareholders.</p>
<p>The day's biggest gainer was Banco de Bogota, which closed up 1.39 percent in Bogota at 6,900 pesos per share.</p>
<p>The stock rose amid expectations of cash and stock dividends to be announced at a meeting on May 29, a Bogota-based broker said.</p>
<p>Also, the Banking Superintendency said Wednesday that Banco de Bogota's first-quarter net jumped 117.5 percent over the same period a year ago to 47.5 billion pesos.  </p>
<p>Other movers included Cementos Argos, a cement maker that is part of the Sindicato Antioqueno conglomerate. The stock rose 0.12 percent in Bogota to end at 9,071 pesos per share. In Medellin, Argos added 0.45 percent, ending at 9,101 pesos per share.</p>
<p>Brewer Bavaria of the powerful Julio Mario Santo Domingo industrial group, gained 0.30 percent in Medellin, ending at 8,030 pesos per share.</p>
<p>((-- Juan Guillermo Londono, Bogota newsroom, 571 610 7944))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
