<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569120" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Moldova, Dnestr separatists sign peace deal.</title>
<headline>Moldova, Dnestr separatists sign peace deal.</headline>
<byline>Oleg Shchedrov</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leaders of Moldova and its breakaway Dnestr region signed a compromise peace document on Thursday aimed at ending the territorial division of the former Soviet republic that followed a brief conflict in 1992.</p>
<p>Moldovan President Petru Lucinschi and Dnestr leader Igor Smirnov met in Moscow to sign a memorandum formalising their landmark decision, reached at talks in April, to keep Moldova as a single state.</p>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin, who along with Ukrainian leader Leonid Kuchma and a representative of the Organisation for the Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) stands as guarantor of the memorandum, said the Kremlin could withdraw its 6,000 peacekeepers from the Dnestr region after the deal.</p>
<p>&quot;Now we are getting down to serious talks on the basic document which would finally complete stabilisation in the region,&quot; Itar-Tass news agency quoted Lucinchi as saying after the ceremony in the Kremlin.</p>
<p>Some two thirds of Moldova's 4.5 million people speak Romanian. About 30 percent, concentrated on the east bank of the Dnestr river, are Slavs speaking Russian or Ukrainian.</p>
<p>Travel between Dnestr and the rest of the country has been difficult and a curfew is in force in some areas. The economy of Dnestr has suffered badly and Moldovan authorities complain the area is a haven for armed criminal gangs.</p>
<p>An agreement setting out terms for normalising ties was worked out last summer. But Lucinschi, elected last December, insisted on an amendment to enshrine Moldova's territorial integrity within the borders in force at the end of Soviet rule.</p>
<p>The new article commits both sides to &quot;relations within the framework of a single state within the framework of the Moldavian Soviet Socialist Republic's borders at January 1990.&quot;</p>
<p>Russian Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov, who played a key role in reaching the compromise, has said this article had removed the final obstacles to the memorandum, explaining that January 1990 preceded Dnestr's declaration of independence.</p>
<p>The two sides are to start work on a document defining the status of Dnestr within Moldova after the memorandum is signed.</p>
<p>Moldovan forces clashed in 1992 with separatists demanding independence for Dnestr. Some Russian-speakers feared that the majority would seek union with Romania, from whose territory much of Moldova was carved by former Soviet dictator Josef Stalin during World War Two.</p>
<p>Hundreds of people were killed in the 1992 conflict before the intervention of Russian troops led by Alexander Lebed. It became a springboard for the general's political career and he is now seen as a potential successor to Yeltsin.</p>
<p>Interfax news agency quoted Yeltsin as saying after the signing: &quot;We are ready to withdraw troops at any moment and to leave for Moldova as many arms as needed if the sides agree.&quot;</p>
<p>One further problem will be the disposal of Soviet military hardware in Denstr. During the Cold War, Moscow stockpiled enough arms and ammunition in the region to wage several months of full-scale war in Europe.</p>
<p>Russian military experts say it will take years to destroy outdated stock and withdraw the rest or sell it abroad. The situation has been complicated by region's claims to much of the weaponry now in the hands of the Russian peacekeepers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOLDV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
