<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569174" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chile to privatize oil refineries - gov sources.</title>
<headline>Chile to privatize oil refineries - gov sources.</headline>
<byline>Paulina Modiano</byline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chile plans to privatize two oil refineries now wholly owned by state oil concern Empresa Nacional del Petroleo (Enap), government sources said.</p>
<p>President Eduardo Frei will make the announcement as early as May 21, in his annual speech to Congress, in what would be the most important privatization so far of his three-year-old government, the sources told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The privatization of the Enap refineries is part of the overall plan to modernize state companies,&quot; one source said.  </p>
<p>The government will use as a model the sale of the Tocopilla power plant formerly owned by state copper company Codelco, sources said. In that deal, Codelco sold 51 percent of Tocopilla to a Belgian-Spanish- Chilean consortium last year, kept 35 percent of it, and sold the rest to the plant's own workers.</p>
<p>Codelco plans to float its 35 percent on the Santiago Stock Exchange next year, company officials have said.</p>
<p>&quot;The model will be the incorporation of a strategic partner and also the sale of a percentage of the property to the companies' workers,&quot; said one source. &quot;Then it also calls for placing another percentage of shares on the bourse.&quot;  </p>
<p>The two refineries will be privatized as separate units. Enap acts as a holding company for the two state companies that operate the refineries, Enap-Concon, which operates a refinery near Valparaiso, and Petrox, which runs a refinery near the southern city of Concepcion.</p>
<p>Enap would keep exclusive control over its oil drilling operations in Chile, concentrated in the extreme south near Punta Arenas, and its foreign operations branch Sipetrol. But the refineries are considered the most profitable part of Enap.  </p>
<p>Apart from Tocopilla, Frei's government privatized hydroelectric power generator Colbun last October and has announced plans for a gradual sale of the country's public waterworks.</p>
<p>The sale of Tocopilla, which powers much of Chile's booming copper industry, drew major international attention. Codelco sold 51 percent of the company in early 1996 to a consortium of Iberdrola SA, Belgian companies Powerfin SA and Tractebel and Chilean company Enagas SA, which renamed the company Electroandina.</p>
<p>Then-Codelco president Juan Villarzu, who managed the Tocopilla sale, is carrying out the Enap privatization in his new job as Frei's secretary general of the presidency.</p>
<p>Enap's unions say they have gotten wind of the privatization plan and criticized, saying in a statement it was &quot;done beyond the backs of the workers.&quot;</p>
<p>((--Santiago newsroom +56-2-699-5595 x211))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
