<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569151" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Estonia - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the reports carried by Estonia's newspapers on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Tallinn city government and the education ministry are making efforts to prevent a teachers' strike planned for Monday.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Mart Siimann began a one-day visit to Finland and met President Martti Ahtisaari. They discussed Finnish-Estonian, Estonian-Russian relations and European integration.</p>
<p>- Raivo Murd, mayor of the eastern, mainly Russian town of Narva, was elected chairman of the Association of Estonian Cities after the previous chairman resigned.</p>
<p>SONUMILEHT</p>
<p>- State Prosecutor Indrek Meelak has dismissed four prosecutors of the eastern mainly Russian regions of Narva and Ida-Viru, who had forged the certificates which show they can speak Estonian. Four judges also forged their certificates.</p>
<p>- Siimann has expressed dissatisfaction with the rate of European integration and wants to take over the area himself.</p>
<p>- Polish President Alexander Kwasnievski has rejected the invitation to attend a meeting of Baltic and Ukrainian presidents in Tallinn on May 27, a Polish newspaper said.</p>
<p>EESTI PAEVALEHT</p>
<p>- The Bank of Estonia has begun preparations for a possible change of monetary policy if Estonia is admitted to the European Union and monetary union.</p>
<p>- President Lennart meri will award the Cross of Terra Mariana to the president of Hungary, Arpad Gonzc, and Slovenian President Milan Kucan. He will present the decorations during his visit to these countries on May 12-17.</p>
<p>- Writer Jaan Kross received the Herder Award in the University of Vienna. The 30,000 mark award is meant for cultural figures of Western and Eastern Europe.</p>
<p>- Interior ministry chancellor Vahur Glaase has suspended his Coalition Party membership while in office.</p>
<p>POSTIMEES</p>
<p>- Defence forces commander Johannes Kert announced at an arms dealers' trial that there were plans to found a modern weapons factory in Tartu with South African know-how and capital.</p>
<p>ARIPAEV</p>
<p>- The government conceded the need for a regional development programme for south-eastern Estonia. The programme will be submitted to the cabinet by August 1.</p>
<p>-- Riga newsroom, +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
