<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569139" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Deported Albanians accuse Italy of cruelty.</title>
<headline>Deported Albanians accuse Italy of cruelty.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>VELIPOJE, Albania 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanians deported from Italy after fleeing their troubled homeland accused the Italian authorities on Thursday of treating them like criminals with no concern for their welfare.</p>
<p>Since a wave of violence swept the Balkan nation in March after popular, high-risk savings funds collapsed, 15,387 Albanians have crossed the Adriatic to Italy. Italy has sent back 2,712, mostly young, single men, classed &quot;undesirables&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody wanted to leave as there is no life for us here,&quot; said unemployed bricklayer Engjell Sterkaj, who fled to Italy 10 days ago but was returned within two days.</p>
<p>&quot;But as soon as we arrived we were treated like criminals. Nobody asked us about our problems. We were humiliated.&quot;</p>
<p>It is the second recent flood of Albanian refugees into Italy. Thousands fled in 1991 after communism fell.</p>
<p>Passengers pay $500 a head to the organisers of the trips. Trafficking illegal immigrants has become a lucrative business.</p>
<p>But the overcrowding of vessels has had tragic results. Up to 103 Albanians died on March 28 when a packed ship collided with an Italian navy frigate 30 miles off Brindisi and sank.</p>
<p>Sterkaj, 34, was among 571 Albanians crammed onto a fishing boat built for a maximum of 50 that left from Velipoje, 30 kms (20 miles) south of Shkoder in northern Albania, on April 26, arriving at Barletta in southern Italy 27 hours later.</p>
<p>Sterkaj left his wife and two young children at his home in Shkoder, borrowing enough for his own fare on the Miki.</p>
<p>&quot;I wanted to find work in Italy for my family. I have not worked since the pyramid funds collapsed. Everyone lost money and there is no building. Also it is very dangerous,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>During riots in early March, state arsenals were looted and armed criminals now roam much of the country. Armed robberies, revenge killings and accidental shootings are daily events.</p>
<p>&quot;The police possess fewer arms than the criminals,&quot; Shkoder's major Bahri Barici told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;I appeal to countries trying to help Albania to pay more attention to supplying this equipment rather than food aid. We would endure only eating once a day to live in security.&quot;</p>
<p>Last weekend, a week after the Miki left, an overcrowded tanker limped from Velipoje to Bari in southern Italy, carrying 1,229 people, many of them women and children.</p>
<p>Most were sent to refugee centres around Italy but up to 200 were immediately repatriated.</p>
<p>Albania's interim prime minister, Bashkim Fino, summoned Italy's ambassador, Paolo Foresti, on Wednesday to convey concerns over repatriations and separating families.</p>
<p>&quot;I asked the Italian government to let Albanians join their families in Italy,&quot; Fino told Albanian television.</p>
<p>The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) had recommended Italy allow Albanians to put their cases for protection before acting.</p>
<p>A multinational force, assigned to Albania to oversee aid deliveries, does not have the authority to stop these ships. Spokesmen say its mission is not to act as police.</p>
<p>But securing the main southern ports of Vlore and Durres has effectively blocked such activity and pushed the trafficking of illegal immigrants up to the north coast.</p>
<p>Vasil Marku, a shopkeeper at Velipoje, a dilapidated, former communist holiday resort, said Spanish troops are patrolling the area daily since the last weekend's departure.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Italian-led force said the patrols were to ensure security in the area for aid distribution.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VELIPOJE, Albania"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
