<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569102" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungary BUX steady as Richter hits record, MOL dips.</title>
<headline>Hungary BUX steady as Richter hits record, MOL dips.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Losers outnumbered gainers on the Budapest Stock Exchange on Thursday weighed down by a weaker dollar, traders said, adding that strong demand in MOL kept its price relatively stable.</p>
<p>&quot;These days the dollar's weakening weighs more than the Dow's fall,&quot; said Kalman Schuszter of New York Broker Budapest.</p>
<p>The BUX index finished at a preliminary 5,970.90 points, up 5.47.</p>
<p>At midday on Thursday the forint stood at 181.50 to the dollar, half a forint firmer than at Wednesday's close.</p>
<p>Oil company MOL once again overshadowed most of the market with over one and a half million shares traded, including agency crosses. MOL closed at 3,460 forints, down 30.</p>
<p>&quot;Foreign investors, in addition to domestic ones, continue to buy MOL,&quot; Schuszter said. &quot;Huge demand for the stock prevents it from (major) falls.&quot;</p>
<p>But analysts said the share might lose ground once its domestic offer, starting on May 12, is completed as some local clients might decide to dump the shares to lock in profits, stemming from between the 2,970 forint issue price and the higher market price.</p>
<p>&quot;I think MOL might retreat, mainly on the domestic market there will be investors who sell it quickly after the purchase (in the domestic offer),&quot; said Tommy Erdei, analyst of ABN-AMRO Hoare Govett.</p>
<p>Pharmaceuticals Richter continued its rally hitting a new record and surprising some traders who said Richter's market was a little overheated shortly before its share issue, despite strong January-March earnings.</p>
<p>&quot;This price is surprising because the company will issue shares in May,&quot; one trader said earlier.</p>
<p>But Erdei said Richter's price is justified and this is reflected by its popularity among investors.</p>
<p>&quot;Its first quarter earningsexceeded expectations, it's a stable, quickly-growing company,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chemicals company TVK fell 20 forints to 2,875, with investors focusing mainly on MOL, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that MOL is increasingly in focus has a negative impact on TVK's price,&quot; Schuszter said, adding that TVK's longer-term perspective was positive. &quot;On longer-term TVK must rise as perhaps they had the best results so far (among companies that released their Q1 earnings report,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Elsewhere on the market, curtain maker Gardenia dipped below its issue price for the first time since its listing on April 14, before recovering to close at 1,490 forints, down 240. It fell to 1,450, below the 1,465 forint issue price.</p>
<p>Tile manufacturer Zalakeramia suffered steep early losses, although later regained some of them, triggered by the fact that its price was adjusting to the issue price in a private placement, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Zalakeramia was falling because of the (lower) issue price but investors have begun to buy so I don't think that would be a long-lasting fall,&quot; one trader said earlier.</p>
<p>But Erdei said Zalakeramia was undervalued at current price. &quot;I see room for some upward movement,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
