<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569180" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Rival police battle over army training in Mexico.</title>
<headline>Rival police battle over army training in Mexico.</headline>
<byline>Henry Tricks</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hundreds of disgruntled Mexican police battled with colleagues in anti-riot squads on Thursday using rocks and bottles, and news reports said dozens were injured and at least 17 were arrested.</p>
<p>Scores of riot police fired tear gas cannisters at the so-called &quot;dissident&quot; policemen, who later seized a police headquarters to protest plans to give them military training.</p>
<p>The dissident policemen threatened to use weapons stored inside the headquarters to defend themselves while riot police ringed the building outside in an uneasy standoff.</p>
<p>Dissident police said at least one of their members was killed by a bullet in the earlier melee but this could not be confirmed. State news agency Notimex said at least five people were injured, including a newspaper photographer. Television reports put the number of wounded in the dozens.</p>
<p>TV images showed phalanxes of riot police -- numbering about 1,000 -- advancing on the protesters with riot shields and helmets, firing tear gas. They were pelted with rocks, bottles and wooden clubs.</p>
<p>The pictures showed several wounded, some bleeding profusely, and protesters being dragged away, riot clubs roughly pressed to their necks. Enrique Salgado, head of Mexico City's police force, said 17 were arrested.</p>
<p>On the second day of protests in the Mexico City police force, dissidents initially blocked three main highways causing traffic chaos, until they were forced away by the riot squads. The riots have focused on a controversial plan launched earlier this year to give Mexico's notoriously corrupt police force military training, while soldiers dressed as policemen manned the streets on a rotational district-by-district basis.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, about 200 cops from the southern district of Ixtapalapa who were given low grades at the end of their two-month military training course -- the first of its kind -- blocked roads after they were ordered to change districts and start working in the north of the city.</p>
<p>On Thursday, they and their colleagues up north rebelled again, demanding guarantees that no police would be relocated. Salgado, himself an army general, said anyone relocated would be amply compensated.</p>
<p>At President Ernesto Zedillo's bidding, Mexico's army has taken an increasing role in law enforcement across Mexico while hundreds of civilian police have been fired.</p>
<p>Salgado said residents who have seen soldiers at work prefer them to their civilian counterparts, suggesting the militarization of the police force could broaden.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
