<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569122" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: Kinkel visits Bosnia amid row with German states.</title>
<headline>Kinkel visits Bosnia amid row with German states.</headline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel travelled to Sarajevo on Thursday to discuss the repatriation of Bosnian refugees although German state interior ministers dismissed the trip as a waste of time.</p>
<p>Kinkel planned to hold talks with U.N. relief officials and members of Bosnia's collective presidency to coordinate plans for the repatriation of refugees who fled to Germany during the Yugoslav conflict.</p>
<p>German state interior ministers declined to accompany Kinkel because they said without the participation of Germany's Interior Minister Manfred Kanther nothing significant could be accomplished.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Kinkel criticised the state ministers for pulling out of the trip, saying they were &quot;hiding behind&quot; Kanther.</p>
<p>Kinkel has slammed Germany's 16 states for deciding last year to compel refugees to return to their war-ravaged country if they failed to leave voluntarily.</p>
<p>The foreign minister has urged the states to come up with a unified plan to return refugees in a humane way.</p>
<p>International human rights workers and Bosnian government officials have condemned Germany for forcing some refugees back without ensuring they could return to their home towns safely.</p>
<p>Some Moslem refugees who were deported had no chance of returning to their homes which now lie in territory controlled by nationalist Serb authorities, U.N. relief officials said.</p>
<p>During the 1992-95 war, Germany accepted some 320,000 refugees from former Yugoslavia, more than the rest of the European Union.</p>
<p>But German states, complaining the Bosnians were becoming a financial burden, announced plans last year to deport between 70,000 to 90,000 refugees.</p>
<p>Relief workers and diplomats say there is little chance that refugees would be allowed to return to places where they might challenge local ethnic dominance established during the war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
