<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569145" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia takes first steps in gold liberalisation.</title>
<headline>Russia takes first steps in gold liberalisation.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A commission headed by Russian First Deputy Prime Minister Anatoly Chubais and charged with liberalising the gold market approved a resolution on direct gold sales to individuals, Interfax news agency said Thursday.</p>
<p>Interfax quoted Viktor Tarakanovsky, chairman of the Gold Prospectors' Union, as saying a document &quot;On the sale of precious metals to individuals&quot; was approved late on Wednesday, and would be passed to the government for signing in seven days.</p>
<p>The report said the commission also approved a resolution on the necessity of &quot;significantly simplifying the procedure for exporting precious metals from Russia&quot;.</p>
<p>But a document &quot;On precious metals trading&quot; was sent back for further work as it conflicted with a clause in Russia's Criminal Code giving five years imprisonment for precious metals sales which exclude the government, Tarakanovsky said.</p>
<p>Interfax quoted an unnamed source as saying the draft resolution would allow gold producers to sell gold freely if the government failed to pay for it within 30 days.</p>
<p>Last month Chubais announced that Russia's gold market needed radical changes, and that a working group was considering concrete proposals to liberalise the heavily-centralised market.</p>
<p>Officials had said that commercial banks were likely to play a much more important role in pre-financing gold production, with analysts saying that in exchange they could be given the right to export gold.</p>
<p>The authoritative business daily Kommersant quoted First Deputy Prime Minister Boris Nemtsov as saying that commercial banks should indeed have the right to export.</p>
<p>&quot;Let commercial banks export as much gold as they like,&quot; he was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>Where the liberalisation of the gold market left the even more secretive world of platinum group metals remained unclear.</p>
<p>Russian exports of the vital hard currency earners platinum and palladium have been held up for months because a decree outlining export quotas of platinum group metals had not been signed by the government.</p>
<p>But an official at export agency Almazjuvelirexport said on Wednesday that he understood the decree had finally been signed.</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
