<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569160" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Top Colombian lawman announces presidential bid.</title>
<headline>Top Colombian lawman announces presidential bid.</headline>
<byline>Tom Brown</byline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombian chief prosecutor Alfonso Valdivieso, a highly popular anti-drug and corruption fighter, announced he had resigned on Thursday and would be a candidate in next year's presidential elections.</p>
<p>&quot;As president, I can do much more to change Colombia,&quot; Valdivieso told a packed news conference at a downtown convention, vowing to bring a new sense of &quot;moral leadership&quot; to a country torn by violence and corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;Insecurity is everywhere,&quot; he said in a speech announcing his candidacy, referring to soaring crime and political bloodshed. &quot;And the Colombian people have suffered the insecurity of not having trustworthy leaders.&quot;</p>
<p>Valdivieso, who polls consistently show to be Colombia's most respected and popular public figure, was appointed in 1994, less than two weeks after President Ernesto Samper took office amid a scandal over charges that he received millions of dollars in drug money to finance his campaign.</p>
<p>He made his mark, and earned many public enemies, by heading the so-called 8,000 Process -- a probe into the campaign finance scandal that nearly led to Samper's impeachment last year.</p>
<p>Although he is a member of Samper's ruling Liberal Party, Valdivieso, 46, said he was launching an independent bid for the country's top job, a move that could put an end to Colombia's longstanding tradition of rule by the Liberal and Conservative parties.</p>
<p>His remarks at the news conference were peppered with references to a need to end politics as usual in Colombia and provide the country with &quot;a new leadership and new ideas.&quot;</p>
<p>Valdivieso is a cousin of Luis Carlos Galan, a charismatic and still revered political leader who was cut down by an assassin's bullets while campaigning for the presidency in 1989.</p>
<p>In addition to his current post as prosecutor general, a job from which he has seen all of Colombia's cocaine kings either jailed or killed and in which he nearly toppled Samper on drug-corruption charges, he has served as ambassador to Israel, education minister and senator.</p>
<p>His campaign is sure to focus on his image as a strongarm crusader against crime, but he could find himself open to attack on many fronts, including allegations already being voiced by some critics that he used the prosecutor's office as a political springboard for the presidency.</p>
<p>He has been given high marks by the United States for his efforts to shore up Colombia's judicial system and crack down on rampant corruption. But authorities say about 90 percent of all crimes still go unpunished in Colombia, which has the highest murder and kidnapping rates in Latin America.</p>
<p>Furthermore, despite what Valdivieso described as an overwhelming body of evidence that Samper used cocaine cash to fund his campaign, he failed, as prosecutor and Samper's chief nemesis, to build a strong enough case against the president to impeach him.</p>
<p>Valdivieso's leading opponent for the presidency, according to a flurry of recent polls, is Interior Minister Horacio Serpa, a staunch supporter of Samper and frequent critic of the United States.</p>
<p>A firebrand populist, Serpa is expected to step down to launch his own bid to succeed Samper within a matter of days. Colombian law requires that anyone in public office who plans to run for president step down a year ahead of the polls.</p>
<p>It was not immediately clear who Samper would name to replace Valdivieso in what is often described as Colombia's second most important job.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
