<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569144" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albanians pin hopes on fresh elections.</title>
<headline>Albanians pin hopes on fresh elections.</headline>
<byline>Paul Iredale</byline>
<dateline>GJIROKASTER, Albania 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanians reeling from recent riots and the loss of their savings in pyramid investment schemes are pinning their hopes on fresh elections, but they don't want any one party to win outright.</p>
<p>&quot;There has to be a coalition. That's the only way that the parties can control each other,&quot; teacher Angjelina Kola told Reuters.</p>
<p>A nine-party National Reconciliation government was set up in March to halt the drift to anarchy in Europe's poorest state and many Albanians want the experiment to continue.</p>
<p>The desire for a national unity government is widespread in this southern Albanian town that is the home of former Stalinist dictator Enver Hoxha and of interim prime minister Bashkim Fino.</p>
<p>Even mayor Ylli Asllani, a member of President Sali Berisha's Democratic Party who took over the municipality from Fino in local elections last October, thinks a coalition might be a good thing.</p>
<p>&quot;Our political class has not been clear about the road to true democracy. There should be a continous alliance of all the parties,&quot; he said in an interview.</p>
<p>Berisha's Democrats have ruled Albania since 1992, leading the Balkan nation out of Stalinist isolation and towards a market economy.</p>
<p>But last year's general election, seen internationally as flawed, and the collapse of the pyramid schemes, have convinced many it is time for a change.</p>
<p>Southerners blame Berisha, who comes from the north, for making political capital out of the pyramid schemes when they were paying out and for failing to prevent their collapse.</p>
<p>&quot;When he stole the people's vote they were angry, but they could live with it. But when he stole their money that was too much,&quot; said a policeman hitching a lift from the southern town of Tepelene.</p>
<p>The Democratic Party is already facing defections. A splinter group complaining of Berisha's autocratic style formed the Movement for Democracy late last month.</p>
<p>Many people are also disillusioned with Fino's Socialists, the heirs of the former communists, believing they should have played a more active role in opposing Berisha.</p>
<p>But there is wide support for the prime minister's efforts to push through a law to ensure fresh elections agreed by Berisha and expected on June 29 will involve a higher degree of proportional representation to allow minor parties to gain a foothold in parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;This law will allow people to have their voice in parliament,&quot; said engineer Mikail Cico.</p>
<p>Fino has threatened the resignation of the nine-party government of national reconciliation if parliament, which is dominated by Berisha's Democrats, does not approve the law.</p>
<p>Life has still not returned to normal in southern Albania.</p>
<p>Public servants have not been paid since March and there is little work to be had. Widespread looting of military arsenals has put huge numbers of weapons into the hands of the population, many of them bored teenagers who are using the arms to rob and terrorise the population.</p>
<p>A night-time curfew is still in force across Albania, and the evenings are alive with the south of gunfire. Several hundred people have been killed in the past two months, many of them accidentally.</p>
<p>&quot;If the elections are cancelled there will be civil war,&quot; said Fatmir Asllani, brother of the mayor and a teacher in Gjirokaster.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GJIROKASTER, Albania"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
