<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569153" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LITHUANIA: PRESS DIGEST - Lithuania - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Lithuania - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>VILNIUS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the main stories in Lithuanian newspapers on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>LIETUVOS RYTAS</p>
<p>- A senior law enforcement official in the second city of Kaunas may be sacked after allowing the president of a finance group suspected of fraud to escape home arrest.</p>
<p>- The parliament national defence comittee proposed the sacking of a senior army officer for allowing Russian military vehicles to cross Lithuania as the only permitted transit at the moment is by railroad.</p>
<p>- Birzai Dairy will join the official trading list of the Vilnius bourse.</p>
<p>- Sole Lithuanian refiner suggestrf the imposition of a 10-20 percent customs duty on imported oil products except heating oil. The company controls 35 percent of the fuel market and would like to increase its share to 80-90 percent.</p>
<p>- The trade deficit in January and Februaru 1997 was 915.8 million litas.</p>
<p>RESPUBLIKA</p>
<p>- Parliament chairman Vytautas Landsbergis urged Western countries to change its outdated view of Lithuania as a less advanced candidate to join the European Union.</p>
<p>- Unemployment in April fell by 0.3 percent to 5.9 percent.</p>
<p>LIETUVOS AIDAS</p>
<p>- The possibility to start talks over joining the European Union with the first group or become an outsider are more or less the same, diplomats in Brussels said.</p>
<p>- Polish newspaper Gazeta Wyborcza quoted unofficial sources that President Aleksandr Kwasniewski has refused the invitation of the presidents of the three Baltic states to take part in their summit in Tallinn at the end of May. Ukrainian President Leonid Kuchma has already accepted the invite.</p>
<p>-- Andrius Vilkancas, Vilnius newsroom +370 2 22 35 17</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LITH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VILNIUS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LITHUANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
