<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569178" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Pemex says West Coast contracts not yet signed.</title>
<headline>Pemex says West Coast contracts not yet signed.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico's state oil and gas monopoly Petroleos Mexicanos (Pemex) has not yet sold crude contracts to the U.S. West Coast, a Mexico City trader said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have nothing registered yet. We are working on it but still have nothing firm,&quot; she told Reuters.</p>
<p>She added that the contracts Pemex chair Adrian Lajous referred to last week were sold about six years ago, the last time Pemex sold crude to the West Coast.</p>
<p>&quot;We are looking for new markets for our crude products,&quot; Lajous said at a news conference. &quot;We have already concluded some specific transactions to place crude in the West Coast of the United States.&quot;</p>
<p>A barrier to the expected sale is the fact that Pemex's Pacific Coast port Salina Cruz in Oaxaca state does not have the depth capacity to handle large crude tankers. Pemex's oil tankers usually handle between 700,000 and 1.9 million barrels.</p>
<p>Pemex traders have said the company is looking to diversify and extend its client base to handle a glut of crude in the market, provoked by greater production in Mexico and Venezuela.</p>
<p>Greater refining capacity, being constructed in Cadereyta and Tula, should help turn Pemex's heavy Maya crude into marketable gasolines and other products later in the year.</p>
<p>((--Timna Tanners, Mexico City newsroom +525 728-7903))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
