<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569219" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Greenpeace says Asian loggers put Amazon at risk.</title>
<headline>Greenpeace says Asian loggers put Amazon at risk.</headline>
<byline>William Schomberg</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Powerful Asian logging companies that have exhausted forest reserves in their own countries were moving into the Amazon, posing a new threat to the world's largest rainforest, Greenpeace said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Asian industrial loggers are poised to significantly impact the Amazon rainforest, changing forever the ecological, social and economic composition of the region,&quot; Greenpeace said in &quot;Logging the Planet,&quot; a report issued in Brasilia.</p>
<p>Southeast Asian logging companies have expanded their operations in recent years to other countries in the South Pacific, Africa and Latin America to compensate for dwindling reserves back home, the report said.</p>
<p>The multinationals, most of them from Malaysia and Indonesia, have acquired logging rights in Amazon areas in Surinam and Guyana and, more recently, land and sawmills in Brazil, which holds about 60 percent of the rainforest, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;By opening up the heart of the Amazon to large-scale logging, the Brazilian government risks accelerating rates of deforestation and losing its already fragile political capability to ensure adequate control,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>Some 14 percent of the Brazilian Amazon has already been destroyed, according to government estimates. Environmentalists fear the arrival of the Asian loggers, whose equipment and financial muscle is far greater than that of local companies, will speed up the rate of deforestation.</p>
<p>&quot;There is ample documentation of the kind of destruction these companies have carried out around the world. Why would they do anything different in Brazil?&quot; Ana Toni, a Greenpeace researcher who drew up the report, said.</p>
<p>Last year, WTK Group of Malaysia announced it bought 741,300 acres (300,000 hectares) of forest deep in Amazonas state and began doubling capacity at a sawmill it purchased in the city of Manaus.</p>
<p>Brazil's Congress, which has been seeking information on the Asian logging companies' interests in Brazil, believes the multinationals may already have bought 3.5 million acres (1.4 million hectares) of land in the Amazon.</p>
<p>&quot;This is just the tip of the iceberg,&quot; Gilney Viana, a congressman with the left-wing Workers Party, said. &quot;We have to have a clear idea of the dimension of their acquisitions so we can have an idea of the impact on the region.&quot;</p>
<p>He also said the handful of government inspectors who try to monitor the forest will find it impossible to keep checks on a rapidly expanding logging industry.</p>
<p>In its report, Greenpeace urged the Brazilian government to audit logging companies &quot;to prevent the worst players in the forestry sector having access to Brazil's forest resources&quot; and suspend issuing new logging licenses to large foreign firms.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
