<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569250" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentina insists Falkland solution possible soon.</title>
<headline>Argentina insists Falkland solution possible soon.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Argentine Foreign Minister Guido Di Tella said in an interview published on Thursday it would be possible to reach a solution to the Falklands dispute with Britain before President Carlos Menem steps down in 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;You think I have lost my mind,&quot; Di Tella told the Argentine newspaper La Nacion. &quot;Nevertheless, I say it is now conceivable, we are now seeing signs that this could reach a final solution before Menem's mandate ends.&quot;</p>
<p>Menem has raised hopes for Argentina's claim to ownership of the British-run Falkland Islands since it became clear the Labour Party would win power in Britain -- despite Labour's statement there was &quot;not a shred of truth&quot; in such ideas.</p>
<p>When Labour triumphed on May 1, Menem repeated his vow &quot;that Argentine flags will fly in the islands by the year 2000,&quot; though he made it clear there would be no repeat of the 1982 war with Britain over the South Atlantic archipelago.</p>
<p>Argentina says Britain &quot;usurped&quot; the islands that it calls the Malvinas in 1833 -- a territorial claim that the military junta tried to enforce in 1982 by sending in troops. About 1,000 servicemen died in the ensuing 10-week war.</p>
<p>Argentina's defeat accelerated its return to democracy the following year. It restored diplomatic links with Britain in 1989 and trade has flourished, but Britain refuses to discuss sovereignty and rejects Menem's proposals of shared ownership.</p>
<p>&quot;The constitution says we have to seek total sovereignty, but the president spoke of shared sovereignty,&quot; said Di Tella.</p>
<p>&quot;Although the British said no, this opens up huge possibilities,&quot; said the minister, who spoke of finding an &quot;intermediate solution&quot; within a year.</p>
<p>Di Tella said he had already warned new British Foreign Secretary Robin Cook to expect a visit soon &quot;because I'm in the habit of knocking on the door every three months.&quot;</p>
<p>Argentina hopes to continue &quot;the dialogue we already began with the Conservatives,&quot; and plans a visit to London for Menem to meet new Labour Prime Minister Tony Blair.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FALK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
