<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569298" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuela highway dispute seen as threat to reform.</title>
<headline>Venezuela highway dispute seen as threat to reform.</headline>
<byline>Paul Hughes</byline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The future of Venezuela's public works concessions program, one of the earliest reforms proposed by President Rafael Caldera, is being threatened by an escalating dispute over highway tolls charged by a private consortium, analysts said.</p>
<p>The row has emerged as a major embarrassment for the government, with truck drivers and others balking at a sudden increase in tolls charged for using a highway linking the Venezuelan capital with the country's main port.  </p>
<p>Protests escalated Wednesday as the mayor of the Vargas district, through which much of the 10-mile (16 km) Caracas-La Guaira highway runs, backed calls by truck drivers for a boycott of the tolls.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the death knell for the credibility of the concessions program,&quot; independent analyst Erik Ekvall said.</p>
<p>Government officials agree the highway toll dispute could jeopardize the future of a once-ambitious privatization program.  </p>
<p>&quot;If this concession fails...it will be a failure for Venezuela because the country does not and will not have the resources  needed for the roads,&quot; Transport and Communications Minister Moises Orozco Gratero.</p>
<p>The Asoven consortium, majority owned by Mexico's Empresas ICA Sociedad Controladora SA, won the 30-year concession in 1995 and started operating the highway last month.</p>
<p>The group based its winning bid, involving a $214 million investment program, on raising the round-trip toll for private users from 10 bolivars ($0.02) to 200 bolivars ($0.42).  </p>
<p>But in the face of strong opposition, the government backtracked on the contract, exempting Asoven from a 16.5 percent sales tax and bringing the toll back down to 100 bolivars.</p>
<p>Some drivers, meanwhile, have simply refused to pay the heavy-vehicle tolls of up to 18,300 bolivars ($38.12).</p>
<p>The concessions law, approved in the second month of Caldera's term in March 1994, had promised to give the private sector opportunities to build and operate public projects. But three years and three transport ministers later, only the Caracas-La Guaira concession has been brought to auction.  </p>
<p>In a keynote address to Congress in March, even Caldera was forced to acknowledge that the much-heralded reform program had brought few concrete results.</p>
<p>When the Caracas-La Guaira highway was inaugurated in 1953, the two bolivars toll was equivalent to more than $1.00. But with the false security of once-massive oil revenues, the government barely increased the toll during the next four decades.</p>
<p>((-- Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I5020041">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
