<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569223" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil reform amendments voting to take 2 more wks.</title>
<headline>Brazil reform amendments voting to take 2 more wks.</headline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leaders of Brazilian politial parties solved an impasse blocking the government's civil service reform after deputies traded punches in a row over the bill on the floor of the Chamber of Deputies Wednesday.</p>
<p>But a government-allied official said the drawn-out process of voting on outstanding amendments to the bill would only be resumed next week and would probably take another two weeks to complete.  </p>
<p>&quot;We should have it done in a couple of weeks,&quot; said the official who attended a meeting Thursday aimed at soothing tensions between the opposition and government allies.</p>
<p>Two deputies punched and kicked one another during a brief scuffle in the lower house Wednesday during the latest session to vote on amendments to the bill.  </p>
<p>Passions were already running high as opposition members blew on whistles to drown out discussion of the amendments. They were protesting an attempt by the government to bury opposition proposals by sending them to a lower house panel.</p>
<p>Government whips had argued the amendments were invalid because each one of them sought to change more than one point of the reform bill, contrary to congressional rules. In the panel, the government would only have needed a straight majority to kill the proposed alterations to the bill.  </p>
<p>But in Thursday's meeting, the whips agreed the amendments could be rewritten so that each one contained a single point and could then be voted on the floor of the lower house, where the government needs a three-fifths majority to kill each one.</p>
<p>Included among those amendments were two proposals seeking to maintain the jobs-for-life guarantees of civil servants at which the reform aims.  Only one of those two amendments would be considered in the current round of voting.</p>
<p>About 20 amendments have yet to voted before the reform bill can be put to its second and final vote in the Chamber of Deputies, after which more amendments would be considered, including the second proposal to maintain job guarantees.</p>
<p>The bill also has to be approved in the Senate.  It is considered crucial to Brazil's attempts to reduce public spending and narrow its public sector deficit but has run into stiff opposition ever since it was sent to Congress in 1995.</p>
<p>(( -- William Schomberg, Brasilia newsroom 5561 2230358))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
