<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569291" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COSTA RICA: U.S., Central American nations meet, accent on trade.</title>
<headline>U.S., Central American nations meet, accent on trade.</headline>
<byline>Arshad Mohammed</byline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton will meet the leaders of Central American countries on Thursday at a summit focusing on the region's growing trade and economic cooperation after years of civil strife.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said the summit's most tangible result was expected to be the signing of an open skies agreement to liberalise air travel between the countries, adding they did not expect concrete progress on other trade issues.</p>
<p>Clinton arrived in Costa Rica on Wednesday for the meeting with the leaders of Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, Belize and the Dominican Republic, a Caribbean island nation.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a moment of great opportunity and hope for all the Americas, but especially here in Central America, where decades of conflict and division have given way to peace and cooperation,&quot; Clinton told Costa Rican President Jose Maria Figueres and hundreds of students gathered to greet him.</p>
<p>Clinton flew to Costa Rica after a three-day visit to Mexico during which he discussed many of the vexing issues that are likely to come up at the Central American summit, including free trade, migration, law enforcement and the environment.</p>
<p>Unlike Mexico, which shares a 2,000-mile (3,000 km) border with the United States and membership in the NAFTA trade pact, the tiny Central American economies are slowly emerging from Cold War-era civil wars and clamouring for closer trade ties.</p>
<p>One U.S. official said the issue of a free trade area encompassing Central America was likely to come up during the meeting, but said he did not expect any &quot;definite commitments&quot; on the matter.</p>
<p>Clinton's trip is the first visit to Central America by a U.S. president since George Bush came to Costa Rica in 1989.</p>
<p>The trip takes Clinton into territory that has a long history of bitter clashes with the United States, which has invaded, engineered a coup or armed a favoured side in virtually every country on the list.</p>
<p>The notable exception is summit host Costa Rica, the most peaceful and relatively prosperous nation in the region.</p>
<p>Before the summit, Central American officials said they wanted concrete progress on a free-trade treaty and better treatment for their illegal immigrants in the United States. Neither topic is likely to find support in the U.S. Congress.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course, we know these things are not popular there,&quot; said Luis Guillermo Solis, director of policy at the Costa Rican Foreign Ministry. &quot;But we have decided that we can't be timid as we see the world dividing up into trading blocs.&quot;</p>
<p>The Central Americans may seek a pledge from Clinton to protect the hundreds of thousands of illegal immigrants from their countries living in the United States.</p>
<p>Major provisions of a tough new U.S. immigration law passed in 1996 took effect on April 1 of this year, including one that wipes out the preferential treatment on immigration matters formerly granted to Central American countries.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a problem that we Central Americans did not create,&quot; Figueres said regarding mass immigration, prompted by the region's many civil conflicts. &quot;This problem has its roots in the Cold War years. ... More than anywhere else on the continent, we Central Americans suffered in flesh and blood.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="COSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ELSAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GUAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NICG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Costa Rica"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COSTA RICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
