<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569259" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ECUADOR: Ecuador's Congress fires deputies for corruption.</title>
<headline>Ecuador's Congress fires deputies for corruption.</headline>
<dateline>QUITO, Ecuador 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ecuador's Congress fired four deputies on Thursday as part of the caretaker government's anti-corruption campaign, legislators said.</p>
<p>In an extended session that ended early on Thursday, 63 of 77 deputies voted to oust the four, with the other 14 abstaining from the vote.</p>
<p>Leonidas Plaza and Humberto Delgado, both independents; Homero Lopez of the Roldosista Party and Patricio Almeida of the Radical Alfarista Front were ousted for violating an article of the Constitution prohibiting deputies from managing public funds.</p>
<p>&quot;I protest this because everybody that should have been present was not. All the same, I will give myself up to the authorities and I will not flee the country,&quot; Plaza said after surrendering to police shortly after the session ended.</p>
<p>The whereabouts of the other three were unknown, although media reports on Wednesday said Lopez headed to Colombia.</p>
<p>The move was the second time Ecuador's Congress had ousted parliamentarians. Two weeks ago, Congress fired 13 deputies accused of mismanagement of budget funds -- the first time in Ecuador's history the legislature had taken such a step.</p>
<p>After the impeachment of President Abdala Bucaram in February, the 13 deputies involved said the funds were put aside to be spent on projects in their respective provinces.</p>
<p>Caretaker President Fabian Alarcon must call elections in May 1998.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ECU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="QUITO, Ecuador"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ECUADOR"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
