<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569292" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine deputies OK sale of mortgage bank.</title>
<headline>Argentine deputies OK sale of mortgage bank.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Argentina's lower chamber of Congress on Wednesday passed a bill to sell the national mortgage bank, which has been valued at between $3 billion and $3.5 billion.</p>
<p>Deputies voted 122 to 97 to pass the bill that goes now to the Senate, were approval is taken for granted because of the large majority the Peronist Party has there.</p>
<p>To allay opposition fears that privatisation could end Banco Hipotecario Nacional's role in providing accessible home loans, President Carlos Menem vowed that part of the revenue would be channelled to finance public works, including credits to build houses.</p>
<p>Some $100 million is earmarked to build homes while the rest will be split in between the central government and the provinces.</p>
<p>Former economy minister Domingo Cavallo has said proceeds of the sale should be used to pay off Argentina's public debt.</p>
<p>After coming to power in 1989, Menem launched wide-scale privatisation, stabilised the currency and reduced inflation, but unmeployment grew steeply to 17.3 percent.</p>
<p>He vowed to cut unemployment as he did with inflation and promised his government would create 450,000 jobs next year, 200,000 of them related to the bank's sale. ((-Guillermo Haskel, Buenos Aires Newsroom, 541 318-0650))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
