<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569247" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Two stowaways found aboard Pacific reed ship.</title>
<headline>Two stowaways found aboard Pacific reed ship.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO, Chile 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two stowaways with criminal records have been found aboard a balsa reed raft captained by a Spanish adventurer sailing across the Pacific from Easter Island, Chilean police said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The two men were found on Wednesday hidden among food provisions on the fragile craft Mata Rangi, which set sail on Monday from Easter Island on a journey to New Zealand backed by UNESCO and the Spanish royal family, police said.</p>
<p>The 100-foot (30-meter) ship, meant to be a replica of ancient Polynesian vessels, has been sailing across the Pacific with a multi-ethnic crew of 11 and a message of international peace and brotherhood.</p>
<p>&quot;The ship has confirmed to us that two stowaways were found aboard,&quot; a police spokesman said by telephone from Easter Island, a Chilean possession known for its ancient stone statues.</p>
<p>Both men had criminal records but had served their sentences and no outstanding warrants against them, so their only new crime was leaving Chilean territory without documentation, he said.</p>
<p>He declined comment on a report by the Santiago newspaper El Mercurio that the two had been convicted for robbery and rape.</p>
<p>The ship was already outside Chilean waters and too far away to turn back when the stowaways were discovered, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;What ususally happens in cases like this is that the stowaways are arrested at the first port for lack of documentation and returned home by air,&quot; he said. The raft's first intended port of call is tiny Pitcairn Island, followed by Tahiti.</p>
<p>But the spokesman said ultimate responsibility lay with the ship's Spanish captain, Kitin Munoz, who supervised the building and launch of the reed vessel, a successor to the legendary Kon-Tiki, from Easter Island's Arakena beach.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a problem for Kitin Munoz because he is in charge of the ship and responsible for the people on it,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>El Mercurio said Munoz had employed the two men in building the boat on Easter Island but then rejected them as crew members after discovering they had criminal records. It identified the stowaways as Sergio Tuki and Ricardo Hito.</p>
<p>The journey has had a run of bad luck. Spain's Prince Felipe came for the launch two weeks ago but it was delayed until Monday, without the prince present, because of bad weather and last-minute technical hitches.</p>
<p>Chilean experts have questioned the project's historical veracity, saying the ship is much larger than any vessel known to have been used by ancient Polynesians.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO, Chile"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
