<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569217" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Warmth of Clinton visit mollifies wary Mexico.</title>
<headline>Warmth of Clinton visit mollifies wary Mexico.</headline>
<byline>Henry Tricks</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>It was a romantic picture that summed up U.S. President Bill Clinton's enjoyment of a country whose warmth makes nearly every Mexican proud.</p>
<p>Clinton, holding up a hand-carved mask, stooped to rub noses with his wife Hillary, her face also masked.</p>
<p>&quot;Happy end,&quot; the newspaper Cronica captioned the photograph, which was run on the front page of almost every Mexican newspaper on Thursday, the day after Clinton ended his first state visit to Mexico.</p>
<p>Over three days, Clinton managed to bring a sparkle back to the relationship between the two neighbours that had been severely tainted this year by disputes over drug trafficking and immigration.</p>
<p>With carefully reiterated respect for Mexican culture, history and sovereignty, Clinton surprised Mexicans who are used to far more painful images of their northern neighbour -- those of illegal Mexican workers in the hands of burly U.S. Border Patrol agents, sometimes beaten up, thrown back to Mexico where jobs are scarce.</p>
<p>Mexican newspapers on Thursday responded warmly to the sensitivity that Clinton portrayed: his recognition of the shared U.S. responsibility for both countries' chronic drug woes, and his respect for the contribution Mexican immigrants have made to the development of the United States.</p>
<p>But the enormous divide between Mexico, on the fringes of the Third World, and the world's only remaining superpower on its doorstep, means recrimination, rather than romance, is almost bound to remain at the core of the relationship.</p>
<p>&quot;The exchanges between border countries are always complicated but they are more so in cases like Mexico and the United States, a neighbourhood so peculiar that it has no parallel,&quot; wrote respected historian Lorenzo Meyer in a column in Reforma newspaper on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;In effect, in no other part of the planet do wealth and power on the one side and poverty and weakness on the other live so directly together, without intermediation.&quot;</p>
<p>Evidence of the lingering tensions were visible on Thursday in the leftist La Jornada daily, whose widely noticed cartoons depicted a sense of relief that Clinton had left without stepping on Mexico's toes.</p>
<p>The newspaper, in an editorial, noted that closer cooperation pledged between the two countries on fighting the drugs scourge -- most cocaine consumed in the United States is shipped via Mexico -- may be a double-edged sword, with risks to Mexico's jealously guarded sovereignty.</p>
<p>&quot;It implies a higher degree of involvement and inter-dependence that is not necessarily desirable, given the unequal dimensions and capacities of the judicial and police bodies of the two nations,&quot; La Jornada said.</p>
<p>For ordinary Mexicans, many of whom have family working north of the border, the test of Clinton's sincerity will be in the treatment of their compatriots who face a tough clampdown due to new U.S. immigration laws imposed in April.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, after enthusiastic -- but carefully selected -- Mexicans cheered Clinton during his visit to the quaint city of Tlaxcala, some 75 miles (120 km) east of Mexico City, there were mixed feelings about the future.</p>
<p>&quot;Seeing William Clinton is an exciting experience,&quot; said Magdalena Ruiz, a secretary, using the formal version of &quot;Bill&quot; that Mexicans stubbornly refuse to relax. &quot;But I have recriminations: He must not let his people mistreat Mexicans.&quot;</p>
<p>In the capital, three days of massive security, road blocks and a zealous effort to keep anti-American protests out of Clinton's sight, was to many residents a sign that the government of President Ernesto Zedillo continued to bow too low to the so-called Colossus of the North.</p>
<p>&quot;Has he left yet?&quot; asked a poor Mexican in a La Jornada cartoon, as he struggled to get out of an underground drain onto a sidewalk devoid of pedestrians.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
