<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569275" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Fujimori's popularity dives after Lima raid boost.</title>
<headline>Fujimori's popularity dives after Lima raid boost.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Alberto Fujimori, who received a boost in popularity after the April 22 hostage rescue in Lima, plunged 17 percentage points in polls this week, a leading Peruvian pollster said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The Apoyo SA survey, conducted on Wednesday, showed 50 percent of 404 adults in the capital approved of Fujimori's performance, down from 67 percent in a poll taken a day after the raid at the besieged Japanese ambassador's home.</p>
<p>Fujimori's popularity had fallen to 38 percent in the week before the military assault that rescued all but one of 72 hostages held for 126 days by Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement (MRTA) rebels at the diplomatic mansion.</p>
<p>Enthusiasm for the rescue quickly waned as reports emerged that state miners forced to dig tunnels for the raid had disappeared and that the military executed some guerrillas during the explosive attack.</p>
<p>All 14 MRTA rebels and two commandos died in the raid.</p>
<p>The Apoyo survey showed 55 percent of those polled would vote to keep Fujimori from running for an unprecedented third term in office if a referendum were called on the issue. The poll found 38 percent would approve an election bid in 2000.</p>
<p>The drop in Fujimori's popularity was in part due to the government party's decision last week to begin a process to dismiss four Constitutional Court judges for alleged misdeeds.</p>
<p>The Apoyo poll, which gave no margin of error, found 46 percent believed the accusations were a reprisal for the court's rulings earlier this year making Fujimori's presidential bid difficult on constitutional grounds. Only 29 percent said the allegations against the judges were justified.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
