<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569249" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRENCH GUIANA: Demonstrators mar French Armistice ceremony.</title>
<headline>Demonstrators mar French Armistice ceremony.</headline>
<byline>Alexander Miles</byline>
<dateline>CAYENNE, French Guiana 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Demonstrators protesting against the imprisonment of French Guiana independence leaders disrupted an armistice day ceremony in France's South American territory on Thursday, witnesses said.</p>
<p>More than 100 demonstrators chanting &quot;liberate our comrades,&quot; drowned out the music of a French Foreign Legion band playing France's national anthem at the war memorial in French Guiana's capital Cayenne.</p>
<p>There were no reports of violence. War veterans and officials present expressed shock at the protest at the ceremony commemorating the end of World War Two in Europe in 1945.</p>
<p>The demonstrators were protesting the detention of 11 people including 4 leading members of French Guiana's independence movement for allegedly setting fire to the home of French Guiana's state prosecutor during a wave of riots in November.</p>
<p>The arrests triggered a new wave of riots last month as para-military riot police flown in from mainland France clashed in Cayenne for three nights with hooded and armed demonstrators who fired hunting rifles and threw firebombs.</p>
<p>Officials said a total of 11 police have been injured during the unrest, ten by gunfire. One civilian bystander lost an eye when a projectile exploded in his face.</p>
<p>The riots shattered French Guiana's tranquil facade and laid bare economic, political and social woes.</p>
<p>French Guiana is the only non-independent territory on the mainland of the Western Hemisphere. Its economy is heavily dependent on subsidies from France and 23 percent of the population of 150,000 is unemployed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FGNA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAYENNE, French Guiana"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRENCH GUIANA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
