<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569257" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HAITI: Haiti state phone company to fire 800 workers.</title>
<headline>Haiti state phone company to fire 800 workers.</headline>
<byline>Anna Wardenburg</byline>
<dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than 800 workers at Haiti's state-run telephone company Teleco will be fired without severence pay in the next two weeks in a move toward privatisation, director Jean Jaunasse Elysee said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;There are too many employees with nothing to do. If we get rid of those people the international aid givers will give us more money,&quot; Elysee told Reuters.</p>
<p>The 2,800 employees now working at Teleco are too many hands for the 60,000 telephone lines in Haiti, he said.</p>
<p>Teleco is one of nine state-run enterprises slated to be privatised in a plan to modernise the Haitian economy, ravaged by years of poverty and political upheaval.</p>
<p>After months of debate in Parliament, laws in preparation for the plan were finally approved last month, including measures to cut down on employees in public enterprises. On Tuesday, parliament approved the 1996/97 budget, freeing funds to continue the process.</p>
<p>Teleco, which brings in $5 million a month, has the potential to earn $100 million a month and deliver lines to 400,000 people who have waited for up to two years in the capital Port-au-Prince alone, Elysee said.</p>
<p>But employees who will be affected by the reduction say the layoffs are unjustified.</p>
<p>&quot;The director says all those people are doing nothing but it's just not true. This is just the next step in privatisation, which will be bad for us in the long run,&quot; said a member of the Teleco workers' union, who did not want to be named.</p>
<p>Under the privatisation plan, 50 percent of each of the nine state enterprises will be rented out to private companies and the state will retain the other 50 percent.</p>
<p>Haitian President Rene Preval claims the programme is the only way to get Haiti on its feet in the international market.</p>
<p>&quot;No one is going to invest in Haiti unless there are phone lines to connect with the Internet, unless there is constant electricity,&quot; Preval said in an interview with Reuters last month. &quot;The Haitian state doesn't have the capital to provide this, so we need foreign companies to provide the funds and technology.&quot;</p>
<p>The privatisation programme, signed by former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide with the international community on the condition that he would be returned from a three-year exile, has caused a major split in the Lavalas party that brought Aristide to power in 1990.</p>
<p>Grassroots organisations say it will create more unemployment in the poorest country in the Americas and some have threatened violence if the plan is put into action. Up to 70 percent of Haitians are unemployed and most earn less than $100 per year.</p>
<p>&quot;Ultimately I think privatisation will be good for the country, because if we can start getting telephone lines to the people who need them, we can hire more qualified people,&quot; Elysee said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORT-AU-PRINCE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HAITI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
