<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569231" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuela privatization has only 50-50 chance - poll.</title>
<headline>Venezuela privatization has only 50-50 chance - poll.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Venezuela's private sector gives the government's privatization program only a 50-50 chance of success, with political interests the most likely cause of failure, a business survey showed Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a general feeling that the regulatory framework is weak, especially in the electrical sector ... and of a very slow political process,&quot; Pedro Carmona, the president of local business chamber Coindustria told reporters. Coindustria conducted the survey.</p>
<p>Eighty-seven percent of respondents also said they believed privatization would benefit the country, even as 55 percent said they would not participate in the sales.</p>
<p>National business confidence is nevertheless on the rise, according to Coindustria's first quarter country-wide survey of 450 small, medium and large businesses.</p>
<p>On a scale of one to six, with six the highest measure of bullish sentiment, the survey's general index rose to 3.94.</p>
<p>&quot;But when asked to look ahead over the next twelve months, the confidence index rises to 4.4 ... with the only qualms concern over the consistency of government policies,&quot; Carmona said.</p>
<p>Carmona warned that a strenthening bolivar, so far used successfully to beat down inflation, was high on the list of future worries.</p>
<p>&quot;We calculate the bolivar is now around 10 percent over- valued, a tolerable level ... but it could more than double that by the end of the year,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>((-- John Paul Rathbone, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
