<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569246" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COSTA RICA: Central American press sceptical of Clinton summit.</title>
<headline>Central American press sceptical of Clinton summit.</headline>
<byline>Michael Stott</byline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Some Central American newspapers wrote off U.S. President Bill Clinton's planned meeting with their leaders on Thursday before it had even started, complaining that the summit was nothing more than a giant photo-opportunity.</p>
<p>Struggling to emerge from poverty and misery wrought by civil wars, Central American nations feel that their rapid moves to democracy and free markets have not been reciprocated by generosity on trade or aid from Washington.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said before Thursday's summit that its main result was likely to be the signing of an open skies agreement to liberalise air travel -- hardly the trade breakthrough the Central Americans had been awaiting.</p>
<p>&quot;The San Jose summit will be the summit of the photos and the memories with Bill Clinton, period,&quot; wrote commentator Roberto Arguello in the Guatemalan newspaper La Prensa Libre.</p>
<p>The Dominican Republic daily HOY said little could be expected from a summit where there would be &quot;beautiful pieces of rhetoric. But we will continue to buy our cellphones in the United States and worse still, selling part of the rice we consume (to do so).&quot;</p>
<p>Former Nobel Peace laureate Oscar Arias, who won his prize for leading a regional peace plan when he was president of Costa Rica, urged Clinton in an open letter published in the La Nacion daily to make arms control a top priority.</p>
<p>&quot;It's time that the voices of our boys and girls are heard clamouring for schools and not for arms,&quot; he wrote. &quot;And it's time that the arms dealers read the diaries written in our jails by those who suffered torture and mutilation at the hands of our military.&quot;</p>
<p>Cold War battleground Nicaragua, which has recently elected a right-wing president, was no happier about the meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;Nicaragua can't expect much from this summmit which to tell the truth has more propagandistic than practical aims,&quot; said its main newspaper La Prensa. &quot;What interests Nicaragua most at the moment is to stop the harassment and deportations of Nicaraguans living in the United States.&quot;</p>
<p>Central American leaders agreed Wednesday to ask Clinton for a far-ranging free trade agreement and better treatment of their immigrants in the United States. Clinton is unlikely to agree to either.</p>
<p>&quot;The importance of the visit is more for the visitor than for the host countries, because with this Clinton is trying to fill one of the gaps of his first administration...Latin America&quot;, Guatemala's El Grafico newspaper said in an editorial.</p>
<p>Clinton did not visit Latin America during his first term.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DOMR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GUAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NICG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Costa Rica"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COSTA RICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
