<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569200" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Cemig eyes Level Two ADR issue in H1.</title>
<headline>Cemig eyes Level Two ADR issue in H1.</headline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cemig power firm, owned by the Brazilian state of Minas Gerais, said it plans to secure U.S. SEC approval and issue a Level Two American Depositary Receipt (ADR) program by the end of June.</p>
<p>Luiz Fernando Rolla, assistent to the firm's chief financial officer, told Reuters that Cemig hopes to win Securities and Exchange Commission approval this month to convert its Level One program to a Level Two so it can list on U.S. stock markets.</p>
<p>&quot;We are in the process of choosing an advisor bank and submitting our documentation to the SEC,&quot; Rolla said, adding a Level Two program would likely be launched in June.  </p>
<p>He said the firm has adapted its accounting practices to U.S. standards to upgrade its ADRs. A Level Two program will permit the company to list its shares but not issue new stock or raise capital on U.S. markets.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Rolla said he does not know if the federal National Development Bank (BNDES) has set a new date for its planned sale of a 32.9 percent stake in Cemig.</p>
<p>The sale had been set for earlier this week but was delayed because companies planning to bid on 18.7 million debentures convertible to Cemig common stock wanted more time to visit Cemig.  </p>
<p>BNDES and Minas Gerais state officials were not immediately available to comment on a new auction date. The five firms prequalified for the sale of the strategic stake had until Wednesday to visit the company's operations.</p>
<p>Rolla said the interested firms in the past have expressed concern about its long-term pension obligations but otherwise appear to have no major outstanding concerns ahead of the selloff.</p>
<p>The prequalified bidders are Southern Electric Brasil Participacoes Ltda, Community Energy Alternatives Americas Inc., Pacific Generation Development Co, Copel, and a consortium of Artica Investment Group and CEA group.</p>
<p>A base price of 60.37 reais ($57.03) per debenture was set and the sale is to take place on the Rio de Janeiro Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>((-- James Craig, Sao Paulo newsroom 5511 2485413))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
