<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569276" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: CPFL says groups picked to advise on sale.</title>
<headline>CPFL says groups picked to advise on sale.</headline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sao Paulo state power utility Companhia Paulista de Forca e Luz (CPFL) said two groups have apparently won contracts to advise on its planned privatization.</p>
<p>A CPFL spokesman said a consortium of Trevisan, Arthur D. Little, BFB and Banco Liberal beat two other competitors to carry out an economic and financial evaluation of the firm and suggest a minimum sale price.</p>
<p>He added a group made up of Maxima, Morgan Stanley, SBC Warburg and Banco Omega also scored highest out of eight groups vying for a broader contract to recommend as privatization model as well as conduct the financial study and suggest a base price.</p>
<p>So-called A and B service contracts, which give the consortia 120 days to complete work, have not been signed yet, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Losing bidders have five days to appeal and an injunction has been granted by a Campinas court preventing the formal granting of the contracts.</p>
<p>CPFL, the jewel of the state's electrical sector, is expected to be sold off by October, in the first selloff in Sao  Paulo's privatization program.</p>
<p>((-- James Craig, Sao Paulo newsroom 5511 2485413))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
