<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569224" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COSTA RICA: Clinton gets warm welcome at Central American summit.</title>
<headline>Clinton gets warm welcome at Central American summit.</headline>
<byline>Arshad Mohammed</byline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>For the leader of a country that was deeply involved in the brutal Central American civil wars of the 1980s, U.S. President Bill Clinton received a remarkably warm welcome at a regional summit on Thursday.</p>
<p>Thousands of people lined the streets as Clinton's black limousine crawled through San Jose, and children dressed in crisp blue, white and green uniforms were given the warm, sunny morning off to watch, and cheer, his parade.</p>
<p>Clinton joined leaders of six Central American countries and the Caribbean island nation the Dominican Republic for the summit, which began with motorcades gliding through the city to the elegant, 19th century National Theatre for the meeting.</p>
<p>Most people waving U.S. and other regional flags along the route appeared delighted to see Clinton through his limousine's dark-tinted windows, with loud cheers erupting as he passed.</p>
<p>About half a dozen bands had been set up along the route to stimulate the crowds by playing drum rolls. Costa Rican government workers were given the morning off to attend the parade.</p>
<p>But some people clearly were not pleased to see the U.S. leader, with a few people making rude gestures as he passed and one group holding up a banner that said in Spanish &quot;Central America is not for sale.&quot;</p>
<p>Trade is the centrepiece of the summit, which aims to highlight the region's growing economic progress after years of civil strife that afflicted most of the countries in the area.</p>
<p>Clinton arrived in Costa Rica on Wednesday night to meet the leaders of Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, Belize and the Dominican Republic, a Spanish-speaking island strongly identified with the region.</p>
<p>The trip takes him into territory that has a long history of bitter clashes with the United States, which has invaded, staged coups or armed a favoured faction in virtually every country on the list.</p>
<p>The notable exception is summit host Costa Rica, the most peaceful and relatively prosperous nation in the region which for the most part does not share the animus toward the United States felt by many other countries in the region.</p>
<p>At the summit's opening ceremony, held in a small square dominated by a single, tall palm tree in front of the National Theatre, Clinton's remarks won markedly louder applause than those of Costa Rican President Jose Maria Figueres.</p>
<p>Some in the crowd of several hundred listening politely to the welcome ceremony appeared to be U.S. citizens, with one couple holding up a &quot;Clinton-Gore 96&quot; placard from last year's U.S. presidential election and one man with an American accent calling out &quot;God bless you Bill.&quot;</p>
<p>In his opening remarks, Clinton glossed over the United States' deep involvement in the Cold War-era wars in Central America, and sought instead to put the accent on the region's recent economic progress.</p>
<p>&quot;Less than a decade ago, much of the Americas was still dominated by civil war, repression and hopeless poverty,&quot; he said. &quot;Today, we celebrate the advance of peace, growing prosperity and freedom across our hemisphere.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton, on his first presidential trip to Latin America, made his way to Costa Rica from Mexico, where he spent 48 hours discussing many of the issues on the agenda at Thursday's summit, including trade, illegal drugs and law enforcement.</p>
<p>On Friday, he was scheduled to visit a Costa Rican rain forest to sightsee and make a speech about the environment, and he then flies to Barbados for a Caribbean summit before returning to Washington on Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Costa Rica"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COSTA RICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
