<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569222" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chile drought boosts Andina drinks sales.</title>
<headline>Chile drought boosts Andina drinks sales.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chilean bottler Embotelladora Andina reported strong soft drink sales growth in the first quarter, with the severe drought offsetting the impact of the slowdown in the economy, said CEO Edwin Hahn.</p>
<p>&quot;With the summer season extending into April, we have had good climate conditions,&quot; Hahn said during a conference call with investors.</p>
<p>&quot;Our studies to improve consumption have also been working out well.&quot;  </p>
<p>Andina, Chile's largest Coca-Cola Co bottler, reported net sales in Chile climbing 12 percent from the first quarter last year to $105 million.  Volume rose 17 percent in the same period.</p>
<p>The company has also seen its market share rise to 71 percent at the end of March from close to 70 percent in December, he said.</p>
<p>The firm's sales in Argentine also climbed sharply as the result of the purchase of two new franchises last year and a steep rise in sales in its Cordoba and Mendoza divisions, he said.  </p>
<p>In Brazil, however, sales at Andina's Rio de Janeiro plant fell in the first quarter with the company facing tough competion with local bottlers, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The drop is the result of the decline in soft drink volume sales, lower prices and the devaluation of the real,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;This was partly offset by a 100 percent rise in beer volume.&quot;</p>
<p>((-- Margaret Orgill, Santiago newsroom, 562-699-5595x212))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
