<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569281" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico shrs inch up on scattered blue chip buying.</title>
<headline>Mexico shrs inch up on scattered blue chip buying.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexican stocks edged slightly up after zigzagging in thin volume at the open Thursday as dealers awaited developments to give trade direction.</p>
<p>&quot;A few blue chips are up, but many heavyweights have yet to open, so the market is uneven. Basically, nothing is happening, foreign investors are out and locals are not very keen, either,&quot; a desk trader said.</p>
<p>The leading IPC share index was up 4.10 points in the opening minutes of trade, or 0.11 percent, at 3,778.12. Trading volume was dull at 1.2 million shares.  </p>
<p>&quot;But no one will buy above a certain level either. I see it moving sideways at least until the FOMC meeting, if not until the elections here,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Federal Open Market Committee will meet May 20 to review U.S. interest rates, while Mexico will hold mid-term Congressional elections on July 6.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a little speculation on Grupo Carso. It is cheap after one major U.S. brokerage sold it heavily, but opinions are mixed on its recent earnings report,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Conglomerate Grupo Carso was up 35 centavos at 44.50 pesos.  </p>
<p>&quot;Telmex is up and that takes the market with it, but stocks that weigh, like Cifra and Cemex have not even opened,&quot; the desk trader added.</p>
<p>Telecom Telmex was up six centavos to 16.40 pesos, parallel to its ADRs, up 1/8 to 41-3/8. Dealing had not opened in retail stock Cifra and cement maker Cemex.</p>
<p>Dealers said they expected the bourse to move sideways over the coming weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;Right now, there is a little buying as no one is prepared to take losses below a certain level,&quot; a floor trader said.  </p>
<p>Mexico's two largest financial groups, Bancomer and Banacci, were notable early losers.</p>
<p>&quot;Financials had recovered a little recently, so sellers have stepped in again, but it's quick in-and-out stuff rather than anything fundamental,&quot; a floor trader said.</p>
<p>Bancomer was off two centavos to 2.78 pesos, while Banacci had slid six centavos to 16.74 pesos.</p>
<p>On the broad market, 41 stocks had changed hands, of which gainers outnumbered sliders by 18 to 10.</p>
<p>((-- Martin Roberts, Mexico City newsroom +525 728-7907))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
