<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569265" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico investigates Uruguay rice shipment - council.</title>
<headline>Mexico investigates Uruguay rice shipment - council.</headline>
<byline>Chris Aspin</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Government import authorites are currently investigating a 3,200-tonne shipment of white rice from Uruguay because of &quot;suspicious&quot; pricing levels, the director general of the Mexican Rice Council said Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;It was imported at suspiciously low prices,&quot; Antonio Lajud told Reuters in an interview, adding that it was still under quarantine in warehouses in the Gulf of Mexico port of Veracruz.</p>
<p>Lajud said the importers of the shipment have said it came into Mexico at an average price of 4 pesos per kilo, but the rice council have heard that importers are offering to sell it to industrialists at prices around 3.70 pesos per kilo.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody gives rice away,&quot; Lajud said. &quot;Why is it so cheap?&quot; Lajud questionned, adding his umbrella orgnisation suspected that it had been subsidised, was of poor quality of was a case of rice dumping to gain market share.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to get out hands on the billing of this shipment,&quot; Lajud said, adding that cheap imports at time of the national crop could hurt domestic growers.</p>
<p>Mexico imports half its annual demand of around 400,000 tonnes of white rice, producing the remainder itself. Most imports come from the United States. The national irrigated harvest is just getting underway in southern states.</p>
<p>Lajud said the council was not against imports but did seek to protect its members -- 13,000 growers and 23 major rice businesses. &quot;We are not asking to protect our inefficiencies, but we ask if people are going to import they do so correctly and not at damaging prices,&quot; Lajud added.</p>
<p>Lajud said the Uruguay shipment reached Veracruz two weeks ago on the &quot;Ciudad de Oviedo&quot; ship. Rice council members blockaded the port to force authorities to undertake a thorough check of the shipment to make sure it is not contravening import standards or practices.</p>
<p>Authorities are still investigating and Lajud said that although it was a small quantity of rice involved his organisation thought it right to force the government's hand so that routine checks were carried out in full.</p>
<p>&quot;If it turns out that everything is fine, and in order then we have no problem,&quot; Lajud said. Lajud did not name the importers.</p>
<p>Lajud said that as far as the council was aware that no rice imports had been made from Asian nations since the government moved late last year to drop a outright ban on imports from all nations other than the United States to a posture in favour of strigent import checks and permits.</p>
<p>((--Mexico City newsroom (525) 7289530))</p>
<p>E-mail at chris.aspin@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="URU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
