<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569273" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico Cetes rate pares rise on trade balance data.</title>
<headline>Mexico Cetes rate pares rise on trade balance data.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexican overnight Cetes rates checked an initial advance to stand up 75 basis points at 18.75 percent in early trade on Thursday, following strong trade balance figures, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;We expected upside pressure on rates, but trade balance figures are helping the market a lot,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Dealers said overnight Cetes rates had opened up 19.25 percent under pressure from a weak peso.</p>
<p>Mexico's Finance Ministry announced in early trade in had revised trade surplus data for March up to $636 million from a preliminary figure of $565 million.  </p>
<p>Benchmark 48-hour peso contracts opened 2.1 centavos weaker at 7.9450/7.9500 per dollar, but had since firmed to 7.9220/7.9250.</p>
<p>Overnight rates on bank paper mirrored the trend in government rates by receding to 20.00 percent, or 10 percent up on Wednesday's close, from 20.15 percent at the open.</p>
<p>Dealers said secondary interest rates had also moderated initial advances due to a recovery by U.S. long bonds.</p>
<p>The U.S. 30-year Treasury bond was up 10/32 to yield 6.94 percent in mid-morning trade.</p>
<p>Liquidity of 1.034 billion pesos was slated to return to the system from prior central bank participation.</p>
<p>(( --Elena Vega, Mexico City newsroom +525 728-9554))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
