<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569209" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuelan executives reject strong bolivar policy.</title>
<headline>Venezuelan executives reject strong bolivar policy.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most businessmen in Venezuela disagree with the current policy of a strong local currency as a weapon in the fight against inflation, according to a survey by the National Investment Promotion Chamber, Conapri.</p>
<p>In the poll of 60 top executives from local and multinational companies with more than 2,000 employees, only 24 percent agreed the strong bolivar was a good strategy for economic stability.</p>
<p>Government and Central Bank officials have defended their policy of maintaining an &quot;anchored&quot; currency as the best means to cool runaway inflation, which topped 100 percent in 1996.</p>
<p>But the businessmen said the foreign exchange policy would lead to a sharp devaluation in the future and was reducing the competitiveness of Venezuelan exports.</p>
<p>The same survey found that 71 percent of respondents did not believe the government would carry out its $3 billion privatization of aluminum and steel companies this year as planned. The executives pointed to political opposition, lack of government will and union pressure among the reasons for their pessimism on the proposed sell-offs.</p>
<p>((-- Omar Lugo, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
