<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569227" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Lima shrs end up led by strong mining sector gains.</title>
<headline>Lima shrs end up led by strong mining sector gains.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares on the Lima stock exchange closed higher Thursday led by strong gains in the mining sector, which was buoyant due to solid first quarter financial results and high international metal prices, brokers said.</p>
<p>But the market was expected to fall back Friday as investors were likely to cash in on profits, they said.</p>
<p>Thursday, the General Index  rose 1.19 percent to 1,775.89 points, while the blue-chip Selective Index climbed 1.12 percent to 2,583.46 points, according to bolsa figures given at the market's 1.30 p.m. (2.30 p.m. EDT) close.  </p>
<p>In a total of 1,236 trades, volume was 30.0 million soles ($11.3 million).</p>
<p>&quot;The miners -- especially Atacocha and Morococha -- had exagerated rises,&quot; Miguel Bondy of local brokerage JPBT said.</p>
<p>While the sector had received encouraging news recently, such a sudden jump Thursday was less appropriate than more gradual gains spread over the medium-term, he added.</p>
<p>Polymetal miner Atacocha dominated the market closing up 10.53 percent at 1.47 soles on strong volume of 1.37 million shares.  </p>
<p>Atacocha's rise was due to higher international zinc prices Thursday, strong first quarter financial results and the implementation of a workforce reduction program that have recently made the miner attractive, brokers said.</p>
<p>Morococha also continued to rise Thursday following a 27 percent purchase of the miner by Phelps Dodge earlier this week. The miner gained 9.78 percent to close at 3.48 soles on volume of 335,000 shares.</p>
<p>Benchmark Telefonica del Peru edged up 0.63 percent to 6.41 soles in volume of 1.11 million shares.</p>
<p>((-- Eduardo Orozco, Lima newsroom, 511 221-2134))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
