<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569264" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Colombia to reopen extradition debate.</title>
<headline>Colombia to reopen extradition debate.</headline>
<byline>Tom Brown</byline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The on-again, off-again debate in Colombia's Congress over calls for an end to the country's ban on extradition will resume next week, government officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The constitutional affairs committee of the Senate voted 8-8 late on Wednesday against approving a draft law that would end the prohibition of extradition of drug lords and other criminals.</p>
<p>But government officials said the vote, where a simple majority was needed for the legislation to be passed on to a plenary session for further debate, was critically flawed in many ways and would be held again next Tuesday.</p>
<p>Among other problems, officials said the draft law voted down on Wednesday had nothing to do with the bill submitted to Congress by Justice Minister Almabeatriz Rengifo on April 29.</p>
<p>The government bill, which mysteriously failed to make its way onto the Senate floor, called simply for the abrogation of Article 35 of Colombia's 1991 constitution -- the one prohibiting the extradition of Colombian nationals. Implementing legislation would be introduced later to revive the practice that has been outlawed for the last six years.</p>
<p>The substitute bill that was voted down, similar to one that failed to win passage in the House last year, set a number of preconditions under which extradition would be considered permissible.</p>
<p>Wednesday's session -- where one leading senator likened extradition to a death sentence and something &quot;worse than a concentration camp for a Jew&quot; -- was adjourned immediately after the vote even though Rengifo said cases involving split decisions require a second vote be held almost immediately.</p>
<p>It was not clear whether the government bill or a substitute proposal would be put to vote next week. But Interior Minister Horacio Serpa said the government remained fully committed to seeing the ban on extradition lifted before President Ernesto Samper leaves office in August, 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a commitment the government has made with the country,&quot; Serpa said.</p>
<p>Constitutional reforms must be approved by two consecutive sessions of Congress. The current session ends on June 20, leaving what Serpa described as just enough time for lawmakers in both houses of Congress to pass the controversial issue on to the session that will be installed on July 20 for a final vote.</p>
<p>Serpa, acting head of state until Samper returns from an official visit to the Mideast and Africa, conceded that the government faced an uphill battle winning approval of a practice that polls consistently show most Colombians oppose.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a supremely contentious issue and the positions on both sides are extremely radical,&quot; he said on one of several early morning radio news interviews on Thursday.</p>
<p>Hundreds of people, including three presidential candidates, a justice minister, high court judges, journalists and scores of police were killed in a campaign of assassinations and bombings that drug lords waged against extradition in the late 1980s and early 1990s.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
