<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569211" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico April CPI 1.08 pct - Banco de Mexico.</title>
<headline>Mexico April CPI 1.08 pct - Banco de Mexico.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico's consumer price index rose 1.08 percent in April from the month before after rising 1.24 percent in March, Banco de Mexico said.</p>
<p>The central bank added that the producer price index rose 0.70 percent in April from the month before, compared to rise of 0.97 percent in March.  </p>
<p>A survey of 10 Mexican brokerages and research companies found expectations of a rise of 1.11 percent for April's CPI.</p>
<p>The central bank said that compared with the same month a year earlier the CPI was 22.33 percent higher, compared with 36.93 percent the year period before.</p>
<p>The accumulated inflation rate for the first four months of the year was 6.73 percent, compared with 11.43 percent in the same period a year earlier.</p>
<p>It said that the main causes of inflation during the month was an increase in prices of urban transport, automobiles, insurance, local telephone service, soft-drinks, LP gas, alcholol and restaurants.</p>
<p>It said that the basic basket of consumer goods rose 1.09 percent in April from the month before.</p>
<p>Banco de Mexico gave the following breakdown for April:</p>
<p>INDEX					   Percent</p>
<p>Food, drinks and tobacco		   0.82</p>
<p>Clothing and shoes			   1.77</p>
<p>Housing					  0.77</p>
<p>Furniture					1.11</p>
<p>Health and personal care		   1.26</p>
<p>Transportation				 1.76</p>
<p>Education					0.53</p>
<p>Other services				 1.36</p>
<p>In April, the producer price index, excluding petroleum, was 0.70 percent higher than the same month a year earlier.</p>
<p>The central bank said that compared with the same month a year earlier the PPI was 18.35 percent higher, compared with 37.33 percent the year period before.</p>
<p>The accumulated increase for the first four months was 5.45 percent. In the first four months of 1996, the index rose an accumulated 11.27 percent, Banco de Mexico said.</p>
<p>Banco de Mexico said that of the 46 cities where it collects information for the consumer price index, the greatest increases were seen in the following:</p>
<p>CITY				CHANGE</p>
<p>Guadalajara		     +1.57</p>
<p>Durango			   +1.19</p>
<p>Matamoros			 +1.14</p>
<p>Cordoba			   +1.13</p>
<p>Chihuahua			 +1.12</p>
<p>((-- Timna Tanners, Mexico City newsroom 525 728-9559))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
