<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569215" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil central bank reveals gold dealing scam.</title>
<headline>Brazil central bank reveals gold dealing scam.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA, Brazil</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's Central Bank has revealed a suspected kickback scam by former gold traders, officials and bankers said Thursday.</p>
<p>International Affairs Director Gustavo Franco told reporters Wednesday that two former employees of the central bank's trading room were suspected of having demanded commissions for dealing in gold through international banks.</p>
<p>&quot;What we have is indications of irregularities in certain transactions carried out with a certain partner,&quot; said Maria do Socorro Costa de Carvalho, head of the international reserves operations department.</p>
<p>&quot;A committee of inquiry is investigating to see if the irregularities really took place,&quot; she said Thursday.</p>
<p>It was not the first time that rumours have swirled arouind the gold market operations of Brazil's central bank.</p>
<p>Just over a year ago, the markets were abuzz with rumours a &quot;rogue&quot; trader at Brazil's central bank had carved out an enormous position in a rapidly rising market, without being hedged.</p>
<p>Carvalho said the bank had &quot;something like&quot; 226 tons of gold.</p>
<p>The shorts rumours, which resurfaced repeatedly despite vigorous denials from Carvalho's predecessor Joubert Furtado, caused the bank to suspend gold trading for a while last year.</p>
<p>Carvalho said the bank was now continuing to trade normally.</p>
<p>Bankers said that by coming out into the open so rapidly on the kick-back suspicions, the normally-secretive institution was trying to shore up its credibility and show the world it was a mainstream player in international markets.</p>
<p>&quot;They want to show credibility. We believe their operations are clean,&quot; said Tommy Taterka, general supervisor of Sao Paulo's Banco Cidade.</p>
<p>Taterka said the alleged scam revealed a serious problem in public institutions like the Central Bank, where low-paid civil servants, earning a fraction of what they would in the private sector, played for high stakes with billions of dollars.</p>
<p>Franco said Wednesday the suspected kickbacks probably did not involve more than $2 million.</p>
<p>He said the scam came to light after a foreign bank complained about having to pay a commission to a financial institution in Uruguay for trading Brazilian central bank gold.</p>
<p>Carvalho, who took over the operations department last September, said she had been &quot;downsizing&quot; dealing room activity in the sense of making operations &quot;absolutely conservative&quot;.</p>
<p>She added that at 5 percent of the bank's total foreign reserves, which stood at $58 billion in March, the gold stock was &quot;very small&quot; and gold operations therefore minimal.</p>
<p>Carvalho also stressed that one of the two employees under suspicion had left the bank years ago and the other, who was a trader, had retired.</p>
<p>The operations head acknowledged that like most central banks in the world it was discussing internally the possibility of selling off its remaining gold reserves because of gold's decline in value and its low returns.</p>
<p>But she said, &quot;We are a conservative central bank.&quot;</p>
<p>She said for now the policy was to hold onto the bank's &quot;residual&quot; gold reserves and maintain them at about 5 percent of total reserves.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA, Brazil"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
