<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569225" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COSTA RICA: Clinton preaches harmony at Central America summit.</title>
<headline>Clinton preaches harmony at Central America summit.</headline>
<byline>Steve Holland</byline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton opened a Central American summit on Thursday preaching a message of hemispheric harmony to expand trade and fight crime in a region making democratic progress after decades of strife.</p>
<p>&quot;We know that we must not just be neighbours but real partners, working together in a spirit of friendship, equality and mutual respect,&quot; Clinton said in a welcoming ceremony on a red-carpeted platform outside the National Theatre under bright sunny skies.</p>
<p>Clinton immediately heard appeals for improved trade from the leaders of the five traditional Central American countries -- Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua and Costa Rica - - plus neighbouring Panama and Belize, and the Dominican Republic, a nation on the Caribbean island of Hispaniola.</p>
<p>Costa Rican President Jose Maria Figueres said in opening remarks that Central America needed &quot;greater reciprocity&quot; in trade relations to attract new foreign investment.</p>
<p>&quot;This would be a recognition of the enormous effort that our countries have carried out in an attempt to avoid being left behind by the vehicle of progress,&quot; Figueres said.</p>
<p>Clinton was to pledge to seek approval by the United States Congress of legislation that would allow tariff-free access to a broader variety of products from the region than currently allowed, including some import-sensitive products like textiles.</p>
<p>&quot;We are here to help our economies grow, and to grow closer by opening our markets,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>During their one-day summit, the most concrete achievement was relatively modest. The leaders were to sign an &quot;open skies&quot; agreement to improve commercial air travel.</p>
<p>Otherwise, the leaders planned to affirm their commitment to creating a Free Trade Area of the Americas by 2005. They also were to sign a Declaration of San Jose, pledging to intensify the dialogue on a broad range of issues, including strengthening democracy and regional security, building trade and investment, combating crime, illegal drugs and corruption and promoting a dialogue on immigration.</p>
<p>Clinton was in a territory with a long history of clashes with the United States, which has either invaded, engineered a coup or armed a favoured side in virtually every country on the list. The exception was host Costa Rica, the most peaceful and relatively prosperous nation in the region.</p>
<p>&quot;Less than a decade ago, much of the Americas was still dominated by civil war, repression and hopeless poverty. Today, we celebrate the advance of peace, growing prospertiy and freedom across our hemisphere,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Clinton, who arrived late on Thursday after a three-day state visit to Mexico, was warmly received as the first American president to visit Costa Rica since George Bush in 1989.</p>
<p>His route to the National Theatre was lined with schoolchildren who cheered loudly and waved flags as his limousine crawled by, and the crowd at the theatre voiced its approval when Clinton referred to the region's democratic advances when he said in Spanish, &quot;Es realmente un nuevo dia&quot; (It's really a new day).</p>
<p>But not everybody was happy. One group along Clinton's route held up a banner that said in Spanish, &quot;Central America is not for sale.&quot;</p>
<p>And some Central American newspapers wrote off the summit before it had even started, complaining it was nothing more than a giant photo opportunity.</p>
<p>&quot;The San Jose summit will be the summit of the photos and the memories with Bill Clinton, period,&quot; said the Guatemalan newspaper La Prensa Libre.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CAM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="COSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Costa Rica"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COSTA RICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
