<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569236" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: New Brazil CVRD owners preparing for payment day.</title>
<headline>New Brazil CVRD owners preparing for payment day.</headline>
<byline>Simona de Logu</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The international Valepar consortium led by Brazilian steelmaker CSN is getting ready to pay for its controlling stake in mining giant CVRD and select the company's new management team.</p>
<p>Valepar bid $3.15 billion for 41.73 percent of voting CVRD share capital at the company's privatization auction Tuesday, offering 20 percent above the minimum price of $25 per share.  </p>
<p>The government is due to transfer the shares to the new owners and receive payment for the public sector crown jewel Friday, but a court injunction suspending the auction outcome could put the transaction on hold.</p>
<p>&quot;We are preparing to carry out the payment tomorrow,&quot; said CSN spokesman Francisco Padilha. &quot;We are confident the BNDES (Brazil's National Development Bank) will be able to resolve any legal problems today.&quot;  </p>
<p>The CVRD sell-off has been dogged by a flood of lawsuits and court injunctions from the start and even as the hammer came down on Latin America's biggest privatization deal, a judge granted the injunction suspending the outcome of the auction.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for the BNDES, which oversees the CVRD privatization process, said the BNDES was appealing against the court ruling today and was confident the injunction would be overturned.  </p>
<p>However, a second lawsuit filed in a Rio federal court Wednesday also requests the suspension of the auction outcome and could result in yet another injunction.</p>
<p>Padilha said Valepar's members would be meeting Monday to discuss their auction victory and to decide on their next moves regardless of whether Friday's ownership transfer had taken place.</p>
<p>The composition of CVRD's board of directors and a new management team for the company are the most urgent matters to be decided by Valepar, said a CVRD spokesman.  </p>
<p>He said an assembly of all CVRD shareholders was scheduled to vote and approve Monday at 1500 local time/1400 EDT/1800 GMT the company's new board of directors as presented by Valepar. Another assembly would be convoked to vote on CVRD's new management.</p>
<p>However, the shareholder assembly will only take place if the ownership transfer takes place Friday, the spokesman added.  </p>
<p>Local newspapers Thursday cited former CVRD president Eliezer Batista as one of the favorites for the presidency of the mining conglomerate, which owns the world's largest iron ore mine and runs its own railways, ports and shipping operations.</p>
<p>Batista, who advises Brazilian metal and metallurgical group Caemi which is 40 percent owned by Japan's Mitsui &amp; Co, could provide a useful link to Japanese investors Valepar is eager to attract.</p>
<p>CSN Chairman Benjamin Steinbruch has said Valepar is open to new partners and that he will travel to Japan for talks with steel and trading companies. Japan is CVRD's biggest customer.</p>
<p>((-- Rio de Janeiro newsroom, 5521 507 4151))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
