<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569319" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: CIL to sell Aust property for NZ$52 mln.</title>
<headline>CIL to sell Aust property for NZ$52 mln.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1996-05-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Corporate Investments Ltd said on Friday it had entered into a contract for the sale of Fifty Cavill Avenue Pty, the company that owns the office tower at 50 Cavill Avenue, Surfers Paradise, Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;After taking account of all costs, inclusive of a rental guarantee until June 30, 1998, the sale provides a net return of NZ$52 million (A$46 million),&quot; CIL said in a statement.</p>
<p>The return was equal to CIL's book value for the building.  </p>
<p>The sale contract was conditional only upon the Australia Foreign Investment Review Board's (AFIRB) approval. Should that be forthcoming, settlement was expected before June 30.</p>
<p>The building is currently 95 percent leased, and is being sold to an international investor.</p>
<p>CIL chief executive Bryan Mogridge told Reuters it was up to that party to disclose its identity.</p>
<p>&quot;I suspect they'll do that over there (Australia) in their own due time,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Mogridge said he was confident the sale would go through.  </p>
<p>&quot;This is only conditional upon one thing. Subject to the AFIRB, I am 100 percent confident,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>CIL said all funds from the sale would be used to repay debt.</p>
<p>The completion of the sale will bring to a close the major reconstruction of the CIL Group which began five years ago.</p>
<p>The company will now largely comprise Montana Wines (80 percent of gross assets) and Truck Investments (12 percent of gross assets).  </p>
<p>CIL said the profit growth of the company would come from the expansion of the Montana Wines business, both at home and overseas.</p>
<p>--Wellington Newsroom (64 4) 4734746</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
