<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569370" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK activists vow to mark Tiananmen after handover.</title>
<headline>HK activists vow to mark Tiananmen after handover.</headline>
<byline>Dominic Lau</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong pro-democracy activists planning protests to mourn the anniversary of the Tiananmen Square crackdown in 1989 vowed the colony's handover to China would not stop them commemorating the event in future.</p>
<p>&quot;We will still hold the gathering even if they ban it,&quot; veteran campaigner Szeto Wah told a news conference on Thursday.</p>
<p>He said the Hong Kong Alliance in Support of the Patriotic Democratic Movement in China plans to hold its traditional candlelit vigil on June 4 in memory of those who died when Chinese troops and tanks crushed the student-led pro-democracy movement around Beijing's Tiananmen Square eight years ago.</p>
<p>They also plan to display in a Hong Kong park an eight metre (26 ft) high sculpture titled the Pillar of Shame by Danish artist Jen Galschiot that is composed of 50 painfully twisted human bodies.</p>
<p>It is not clear whether Hong Kong's post-colonial government that will be led by former shipping magnate Tung Chee-hwa will seek to ban the annual pro-democracy protest.</p>
<p>But many believe this year's gathering will be the last major demonstration before the British colony reverts to Chinese rule at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>Tung has sparked controversy over plans to force demonstrators to get police permits before staging protests and to prohibit foreign funding for local political parties.</p>
<p>Earlier this week he said demonstrations promoting independence for Taiwan or Tibet should not be allowed in Hong Kong after the handover to China.</p>
<p>Szeto said the Alliance had written to Tung urging him to attend this year's June 4 protest.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope Mr Tung, as a Hong Kong citizen, can participate the June 4 vigil in order to experience how Hong Kong people commemorate the victims of the June 4 massacre,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The leader of Hong Kong's populist Democratic Party, Martin Lee, who emerged as a civic leader in the wake of the Tiananmen protests, described Tung's views on elections as outdated.</p>
<p>&quot;What Mr Tung has shown, I think it's clear, is that his set of Chinese values is at least two generations outdated compared with modern Hong Kong people's thinking,&quot; Lee said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;What Mr Tung said clearly indicates that if people demonstrate about things which he agrees, then you can demonstrate.&quot;</p>
<p>But a senior Chinese official responsible for Hong Kong Affairs sought to sooth fears over a loss of democracy and rights in post-handover Hong Kong, which will become a Special Administrative Region (SAR) of China after the handover.</p>
<p>&quot;The Hong Kong SAR will develop democracy in a gradual and orderly way,&quot; Chen Ziying, deputy director of Beijing's Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office, said.</p>
<p>Chen added the ultimate goal was having both the leader and the legislature picked by universal suffrage.</p>
<p>He also said Hong Kong would retain its way of life beyond the 50-year period that Beijing had already pledged.</p>
<p>&quot;The One Country, Two Systems policy will not change for 50 years after 1997 and it will remain unchanged even beyond that period,&quot; Chen told a business lunch in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;Hong Kong will have an even better tomorrow and a new era of continued prosperity and stability is sure to dawn on Hong Kong in post 1997.&quot;</p>
<p>Political analysts say the rise of corruption in Hong Kong is now the number one worry on people's minds.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the thing people are most concerned about,&quot; said Michael DeGolyer, a political scientist at the Baptist University of Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;We asked people which post-1997 aspects worried them most in July 1996, December 1996 and February 1997. It (corruption) was number one out of a total of seven various aspects...three times in a row. It's been number one there for over a year.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
