<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569387" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Piltel takes beating after net downgrade.</title>
<headline>Piltel takes beating after net downgrade.</headline>
<byline>Dolly Aglay</byline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pilipino Telephone Corp's (Piltel) share price plunged to a record low on Thursday as brokers slashed their 1997 earnings forecasts for the firm despite assurances from the company of a recovery later in the year.</p>
<p>Shares of the cellular telephone operator fell 1.20 pesos, or 10.91 percent, to close at 9.80 pesos. The price has skidded 56 percent since the start of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;Cloning problems continue to hound Piltel,&quot; a trader, who declined to be identified, said in reference to the illegal use of mobile phone numbers.</p>
<p>Piltel reported a net income of 42.6 million pesos ($1.61 million) in the first quarter of the year against 246.6 million in the same period last year. Analysts blamed the sharp earnings drop on cloning problems.</p>
<p>&quot;We are trying to upgrade and improve our system to prevent a repeat of the 1996 experience. We are telling people 1997 will be a consolidation year, but definitely the second half will be better than the first quarter,&quot; a Piltel spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>Cloning is the fraudulent use of a cellular line, resulting in genuine subscribers getting billed for calls they did not make.</p>
<p>DBP Daiwa Securities Phils Inc analyst Patrick Carague said he slashed his net profit estimate for Piltel this year to 492 million pesos, more than halving an earlier forecast of 1.01 billion after the first quarter results came out.</p>
<p>Russell Ong, analyst at Anscor Hagedorn Securities Phils Inc, said he cut his target to 269 million pesos from an earlier estimate of 1.164 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;It's really the past receivables that are still on its (Piltel's) books that are worrisome,&quot; Ong said.</p>
<p>As of March 31, the firm's accounts receivables reached 3.36 billion pesos, compared with the end-1996 figure of 3.15 billion, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It will take Piltel some time before it shrinks its receivables to a manageable level,&quot; Ong said.</p>
<p>&quot;At 9.80 pesos, Piltel was trading at 25 times our projected 1997 earnings,&quot; DBP Daiwa's Carague said.</p>
<p>Alexis Cabel, analyst at Angping Securities, said reforms being instituted by Piltel to solve its cloning problems and its proposed 20-percent share swap with international Philippine Global Communications Inc (Philcom) would help earnings in the long term.</p>
<p>&quot;In the meantime, it has to grapple with its cloning problems and grab back its number slot from upstart Smart Communications Inc,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>Smart, a unit of Metro Pacific Corp, says it has taken the number one spot from Piltel in terms of subscriber numbers. By February, it had 362,000 subscribers as against Piltel's 357,000.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, Piltel said its present concern was to upgrade its network to deal with its cloning problems.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not pushing to get more subscribers because we wanted to be better prepared,&quot; the Piltel spokesman said. ($1 = 26.30 pesos)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
