<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569304" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: INSIGHT-Steady rates view gives Aussie dlr a base.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT-Steady rates view gives Aussie dlr a base.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1996-05-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>AUS$ S/Term range  *Support *Restnce *RSI-14 *MA-10  *MA-20</p>
<p>US$ *0.7750/0.7860 *0.7790  *0.7830  * 51.45 *0.7800 *0.7781</p>
<p>--------------VIEWS FROM THE MARKET - May 9 --------------------</p>
<p>*Overnight range roughly US$0.7760/7816.</p>
<p>*Aussie pushes back above US$0.7800 in offshore trade, after local market failed to run with Thursday's stronger employment data and RBA Governor ruling out rate cut.</p>
<p>*Aussie seen broadly range bound ahead of budget, U.S. FOMC.</p>
<p>*Aussie softer on crosses as U.S. dollar closes New York at lowest levels in a month against mark and yen.  </p>
<p>The Australian dollar reclaimed US$0.7800 as the offshore reacted more favourably than locals to the hawkish testimony on Thursday of Reserve Bank Governor Ian Macfarlane, which all but ruled out a cut in official rates.</p>
<p>With the dollar having made the move higher, traders felt it could continue to strengthen in local trade, but ahead of next week's Federal budget and more importantly the U.S. FOMC meeting on May 20, US$0.7860, the cap of last week's rally, should provide solid resistance.</p>
<p>By 8.00 a.m. (2200 GMT), the Australian dollar was trading at US$0.7807/12 from a local close on Thursday of US$0.7776/81.  </p>
<p>Macfarlane told a parliamentary committee that the RBA expected the economy to grow at four percent in 1997, with the current level of interest rates accomodating that pick-up, and he could see no economic benefit from another rate cut.</p>
<p>He also said that acceleration in wages growth from current levels could provoke a tightening of monetary policy to ensure continued low inflation.</p>
<p>His comments ended market speculation of a rate cut, which had grown in recent months as employment data has remained weak and other data have moderated after a strong start to 1997.  </p>
<p>April employment data, released on Thursday, showed a rise of 37,100, which appeared strong. However, it only reversed a March fall and left the unemployment rate steady at 8.7 percent.</p>
<p>While the outlook for rates being on hold was providing a base for the Australian dollar, it was also helped on the upside by firmer commodity prices, including base metals, overnight.</p>
<p>While the bias was for the dollar to squeezer higher, traders said there was still some concern U.S. rates would rise after the May 20 FOMC meeting, something which could hurt the local dollar by narrowing yield differentials, and so therefore should act as a restraint on any rallies.  </p>
<p>Another factor that could also restrain any upside was U.S. dollar softness. The U.S. dollar posted its third successive weaker New York close overnight, ending at its lowest level in a month against the mark and the yen.</p>
<p>The weakness against the yen was sparked by a comment from a senior Japanese Ministry of Finance official, Eisuke Sakaibara, that the yen could strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar.</p>
<p>That saw the yen strengthen further against the Australian dollar, which had already been strengthening on gains in stocks and bonds. The Australian dollar was trading 96.59/69 yen from a local close of 97.08/18. -- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
