<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569308" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: PRESS DIGEST-Australian Business News - May 9.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST-Australian Business News - May 9.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW The aquarium industry is currently experiencing a A$117 million boom of developments along Australia's east coast from Cairns to Melbourne, however, some industry figures fear the market will become saturated. Queensland will, once a A$20 million projectin Cairns is completed, have more aquariums alone than mainland Asia or Japan. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- An Ernst &amp; Young survey which estimates overall merger and acquisition activity in both the listed and more active private sectors, has found M&amp;A competition increased sharply last year, with Australian-linked companies paying a total of A$12.5 billion, mstly in an effort to gain more market share. Page 3.</p>
<p>-- Impressive results from the re-release of Star Wars, coupled with an increase in earnings from its United Kingdom newspaper interests, has seen Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation Ltd enjoy a 34 per cent increase in profits for the third quarter, at A$373 mllion, based on revenue of A$3.7 billion. Page 35.</p>
<p>-- The strong supermarkets and liquor divisions - which includes Coles Supermarkets, Bi-Lo, Liquorland, and Red Rooster - have provided Coles Myer Ltd, Australia's biggest retailer, with a 6.5 per cent rise in third quarter sales to A$4.56 billion, a result hat was in line with expectations. Page 35.</p>
<p>-- Under a shareholder scheme unveiled last November, BHP Ltd will raise a maxiamum of A$636 million, with shareholders able to purchase a maximum of 2,400 shares at a 2.5 per cent discount on the present market price. The scheme has been introduced as partof a restructuring by BHP of several discounted share purchase schemes. Page 36.</p>
<p>-- The Bell Securities Emerging Gold Producers Conference was told yesterday by Acacia Resources Ltd managing director Dr Michael Folie that the miner is predicting a lift in gold production from 410,000 ounces in 1998 from 350,000 ounces this year, before the development of its A$260 million Wandoo project in Western Australia. Page 38.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN In its first semi-annual report to the Federal Government, the Reserve Bank of Australia has confirmed there is no room for any further interest rate cuts despite a consistent unemployment figure of just below 9 per cent. The RBA said high wages growth ad indications of an improving economy could not justify another rate cut. Page 21.</p>
<p>-- Australia's largest retailer Coles Myer Ltd yesterday reported sales for the three months to April were up 6.5 per cent to A$4.6 billion, indicating a recovery. Managing director Dennis Eck said the result puts the retailer on target to pass last year's rofit of A$280 million. Page 21.</p>
<p>-- Global media company The News Corporation Ltd yesterday announced it was on track for a 20 per cent rise in 1996/97 profit, with figures for the nine months to March of A$330 million, a 31 per cent increase. The figures represent strong performances in all the company's core operations, bar book publishing. Page 21.</p>
<p>-- Airline Ansett Australia yesterday reported a &quot;small profit&quot; despite a quieter business travel market and increased fuel prices. The News Corporation Ltd, a major shareholder, said while Ansett's Hong Kong route has improved, losses on the Jakarta and Seul routes had affected overall figures. Page 21.</p>
<p>-- Great Central Mines Ltd, controlled by mining magnate Joseph Gutnick, is hoping to announce next month a significant upgrade of its Barton Deeps resource at the Jundee gold mine in Western Australia. The resource estimate is an increase of 660,000 ouncesto 1.7 million ounces. Page 22.</p>
<p>-- RTZ-CRA chairman Bob Wilson said yesterday the mining giant is experiencing problems with its Kennecott copper project in Utah, which may take until the end of September to reach full capacity following the completion of several major structural repairs. age 22.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD Reserve Bank Governor Ian Macfarlane said yesterday borrowers will not enjoy a further interest rate cut this year, but small business borrowers should, through increased competition, get a better deal. Macfarlane said small business will soon benefit frm the sort of competition that was seen in housing lending several years ago. Page 25.</p>
<p>-- In response to the Wallis inquiry recommendation for the creation of the Australian Prudential Regulation Commission, a mega-regulator to supervise all financial institutions, Reserve Bank Governor Ian Macfarlane said one regulator would stifle the abili for authorities to react quickly in the event of a collapse. Page 25.</p>
<p>-- Media group News Corporation should satisfy its chairman Rupert Murdoch's prediction that earnings for 1997 will increase substantially, following the release yesterday of figures indicating a 34 per cent leap in operating profits to A$376 million in the arch quarter. Page 25.</p>
<p>-- A statement by Casino Control Authority chairman Christopher Cullen has hit back at Kerry Packer's Publishing and Broadcasting, rejecting claims by PBL that the CCA was to blame for the media group's withdrawal from its Sydney Harbour Casino deal. Page 27</p>
<p>-- George Weston Foods is under fire from the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission for breaching the Trade Practices Act, with ACCC lawyer Jacob Fajgenbaum asking the Federal Court to impose a A$2 million fine on the company for breaching the Act fve times in 1995 while it was under pressure from retailer Safeway, which took 19.2 per cent of the Victorian Tip Top bread division. Page 27.</p>
<p>-- Former Allen &amp; Hemsley partner Adrian Powles was yesterday committed for trial on September 5 in the Victorian Supreme Court after being charged in the Melbourne Magistrates Court on Tuesday with 27 charges, including conspiracy to defraud, several of obtining property by deception, 12 to give secret commissions, and one to use false documents. Page 27.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE Sales in Coles Myer have lifted 5.7 per cent in the March quarter, thanks to double-digit growth in food and liquor turnover in the past nine months, yet overall results were dampened by poor trading in women's fashion and disruptions within the Myer Grace Bros division. Page B1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BHP yesterday delivered on its November promise of a limited share-purchase discount scheme for its 250,000 shareholders. The move, which comes as BHP shares performances are flat, will see a limited number of shares offered to shareholders at a discountof 2.5 per cent. Page B1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Reserve Bank Governor Ian Macfarlane said yesterday a further increase in wages growth will force an increase in interest rates. He said wages growth was &quot;out of whack&quot; with economic reality, and blamed managers inexperienced with enterprise bargaining rther than unions for the growth in wages. Page B1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Australian Competition and Consumer Commission has taken George Weston foods to court for breaking the Trades Practices Act nine times between March and November 1995. The ACCC wants the company who produces Tip Top bread, to be fined A$2 million for anti-competitive price fixing and retail price maintenance. Page B3.</p>
<p>-- Negotiations are taking place within the ICI company with directors dividing themselves into groups to discuss the issue of a trade and company name change with the departure of 62 per cent share holder ICI plc With the impending sale, a deadline of July has been set for a decision to be made and it looks as if the Australian company will lose its name. Page B3.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>The Casino Control Authority has refuted claims made by Kerry Packer's Publishing and Broadcasting, saying that the deal for PBL to takeover the Sydney Harbour Casino management from Showboat Inc, fell through because of PBL and not because of any mistakeon the part of the authority. The authority's chairman Christopher Cullen said PBL did not complete necessary paperwork for the release of papers to complete the deal. Page B3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
