<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569307" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News - May 9.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST-Australian General News - May 9.</headline>
<text>
<p>(Compiled for Reuters by Media Monitors)</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW It is understood that next week's Federal Budget will see a relaxation of the tax regime for Australia's 300,000 family trusts, a move that will be a major concession to small business. The loosening of the controversial rules will see tightly held famil trusts now quarantined from the backdown proposed in February. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Reserve Bank of Australia governor Ian Macfarlane says the RBA expects growth in the economy of 4 per cent for this year, but has warned that continued wages growth will see an increase in interest rates. Macfarlane said that at the moment, there would b nothing to gain by another movement in interest rates. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- In a speech motivated by the anti-Asian sentiments rocking Australia, Prime Minister John Howard last night lashed out at Independent MP Pauline Hanson, describing her as wrong, and classing some of her supporters as &quot;racist&quot;. Howard's stand came as he adressed the opening of the AustralAsia Centre of the United States think-tank the Asia Society. Page 3.</p>
<p>-- Following an escalation in tensions between the Liberal and National parties, Prime Minister John Howard last night risked further trouble by saying his Coalition partners were &quot;absolutely wrong&quot; to say he had made major concessions in his 10-point respone to the High Court Wik case. Page 4.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AUSTRALIAN Prime Minister John Howard last night told the Asia Society in Sydney that Independent MP Pauline Hanson was seeking to exploit fear and uncertainty, but was unable to offer any solutions. Howard warned Hanson supporters that her &quot;cure would be worse tha the disease&quot; and added that he would seriously be responding to Australian's concerns at the pace of change. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Victorian Premier Jeff Kennett, joined by Crown chairman Lloyd Williams, last night descended the stairs of the grand atrium of the Crown casino and declared the Crown World of Entertainment open. Kennett said that while the Government had received a lotof &quot;knocking and rubbing&quot; about the opening of the complex, it was &quot;a Victorian cultural asset for the 21st century.&quot; Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Reserve Bank Governor Ian Macfarlane told a parliamentary committee in Sydney yesterday that now is the best time for borrowers to lock in their housing loan rate, and for new borrowers to take out a loan. Macfarlane described home mortgage rates as the lowest in a generation, and said housing finance was now more affordable and accessible than ever. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Amid tension within the National Party over the Wik case, Prime Minister John Howard is intending to give his backbench a boost with a confident briefing paper on the impact of his 10-point Wik plan in an attempt to win back the support of the National Paty, and restore order in the Coalition. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE SYDNEY MORNING HERALD Reserve Bank of Australia Governor Ian Macfarlane told the House of Representatives Standing Committee on Financial Institutions and Public Administration in Sydney yesterday another interest rate cut to rule out Australia's high unemployment rate would nt occur, adding that Australia must look at the adoption of a United States-style deregulated labour market to ensure long-term jobs growth. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- New South Wales Police Minister Paul Whelan said yesterday 10 murderers involved in the separate murders of Virginia Morse and Peter Lamb, Anita Cobby, and Janine Balding are almost certain to stay in prison for the rest of their lives, under new laws pased last night in the State Parliament which is aimed at prisoners whose files read &quot;never to be released&quot;. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Government sources say several Government ministers are happy with a proposal that would allow Kerry Packer to buy John Fairfax Holdings on the condition he sold The Australian Financial Review. The news came as Fairfax head Sir Laurence Street warned the break-up of Fairfax could see rival Rupert Murdoch's News Ltd dominate Australia's print media. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- The director of Immunology and Allergy at Sydney's Concord Hospital, Dr Ron Walls, says a study in the United States which found cockroaches are one of the major causes of asthma in inner cities confirms a long-held suspicion of Australian researchers. Hwever, Walls clarified that Australian researchers do not believe cockroaches are the most important cause of asthma. Page 1.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE AGE Melbourne's Yarra River was lined with thousands of spectators last night to watch a fireworks display to mark the opening of the new casino and entertainment complex. Meanwhile, inside the casino, 8,000 invited guests enjoyed several parties inside the $1.85 billion complex, which was opened by Victorian Premier Jeff Kennett. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Prime Minister John Howard said last night Independent MP Pauline Hanson had no answers to Australia's problems, and that she was only exploiting the Australian public's fears and instabilities. Howard said many of Hanson's policies are wrong, and that her approach would not lead to a more cohesive Australian society for the next century. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Talks were being held last night between Melbourne's Metropolitan Fire Brigade and Intergraph, following a mistaken call which called for two Melbourne MFB vehicles to attend an incident near Sydney. The mistake was the &quot;final straw&quot;, and highlighted safty concerns with the computer dispatch system. Page 1.</p>
<p>-- Federal Schools Minister David Kemp yesterday announced a new A$17.5 million civic education program which will see Australian students tested annually on local history and politics. The program focuses on the evolution of Australia's democracy, and is amed at students from grade four to Year 10. Page 3.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
