<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569391" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asia Fuel Oil - Firm swaps boost sentiment.</title>
<headline>Asia Fuel Oil - Firm swaps boost sentiment.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sentiment in the Singapore high sulphur fuel oil market was bullish on Thursday amid anticipation of fresh demand, traders said.</p>
<p>The 180-cst grade was heard sold to a local trader by an European major at $102 per tonne for May 26-30 delivery, compared with the $100 traded level on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The 380-cst grade, which was traded at $91 per tonne last week, was bid at $94, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall, the price uptrend is very clear now,&quot; said one trader with a major.  </p>
<p>Fuel oil swaps rose in the afternoon on expectations of fresh buying interest in the physical market soon, traders said.</p>
<p>May swaps were at $101.50/$102.50, up from Wednesday's $100.25/$101.00. June swaps also edged up to $99.50/$100.50 from $98.75/$99.50.</p>
<p>Traders said the rise was partly based on the perception by some that the market would be bidded up in the coming days to coincide with the arrival of a large cargo from the Gulf.</p>
<p>&quot;Fewer exports from the Middle East during the summer time have been supporting the market despite the fact that demand is not big,&quot; said one trader.  </p>
<p>&quot;If the local trader continues buying, I won't be surprised to see $103 or even $104 per tonne for the 180-cst fuel oil,&quot; the trader added.</p>
<p>Lower weekly residues fuel oil stocks, which fell by 509,000 barrels to 9.922 million barrels for the week ending May 7, also helped sentiment although traders said the stocks only returned to their normal level.</p>
<p>The SIMEX fuel oil futures contract went up in line with firm fuel oil swaps, with July inching 10 cents up to $99.30. Trade improved from previous days and 135 lots for July were traded toward the end of the trading.  </p>
<p>Recent fuel oil import tender from Taiwan and South Korea also boosted sentiment slightly, traders said.</p>
<p>On Thursday, the Korean Electric Power Company (KEPCO) issued a tender to buy two 70,000-tonne, 540-centistoke fuel oil for July delivery, a company source said.</p>
<p>The tender, which seeks to buy 0.3 percent fuel oil, will close on May 16 and is valid for three days.</p>
<p>The two cargoes are for delivery July 8-12 and 27-31 to Ulsan, the source said.</p>
<p>Taiwan's import tender for two 38,000-tonne cargoes closed on Wednesday and is valid until Friday.  </p>
<p>(Prices in dollars per tonne, unless stated)</p>
<p> MTH  FOB SIN		     BUY/SELL	  PREV BUY/SELL</p>
<p> MAY  LSWR *		    15.00/15.20	   15.00/15.20</p>
<p> MAY  FUEL OIL (180 CST)   102.00/103.00	 100.00/101.00</p>
<p> MAY  FUEL OIL (380 CST)    94.00/96.00	   93.00/94.00</p>
<p> MAY  FUEL OIL SWAPS	 101.50/102.50	 100.25/101.00</p>
<p> JUN  FUEL OIL SWAPS	  99.50/100.50	  98.75/99.50</p>
<p>*Dollars per barrel</p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom (+65-870 3571)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
