<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569378" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai rice mart lull, '97 sales seen below target.</title>
<headline>Thai rice mart lull, '97 sales seen below target.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Thai rice market was quiet with no fresh buying heard over the week and prices remained steady, traders said.</p>
<p>Activity was focused mostly on covering. However, most exporters slowed down buying in an attempt to pressure prices and most of them were well-covered, they added.</p>
<p>Thai benchmark 100 percent grade B was quoted at $335-370 per tonne and 100 percent fragrant at $690-700, unchanged from last week.</p>
<p>Exporters projected rice exports for 1997 below the government target of 5.0-5.5 million tonnes as the sale of lower grade rice was not competitive.</p>
<p>Somboon Pathaichat, the manager of Thai Rice Exporters Association, said total exports this year might be only 4.8 million tonnes.</p>
<p>He said exports in the first quarter of this year amounted to 1.04 million tonnes, below 1.40 million in the same period last year. January-March rice exports fetched 10.81 billion baht against 13.62 billion baht last year.</p>
<p>&quot;High quality rice is still competitive. But the performance of lower grade rice was not very good,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Our prices are quite high now compared to that of our competitors such as Vietnam, India or Pakistan. Thai fragrant rice, for example, is more expensive than Basmati now,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Somboon blamed hoarding by merchants for high prices but expected Thailand to ship at least an average of 400,000 tonnes of rice a month for the remaining nine months. Currently, 14 vessels are loading 76,100 tonnes of rice, mostly for Asian destinations.</p>
<p>--Anchalee Koetsawang (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
