<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569376" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shanghai Ind to broaden investment base.</title>
<headline>Shanghai Ind to broaden investment base.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Red chip conglomerate Shanghai Industrial Holdings Ltd will broaden its investment base with the aim of giving investors a better window into Shanghai's future economic growth, senior executives said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Further investments in areas such as service industries and high tech manufacturing will enable us to realise a more perfect Shanghai (investment) concept,&quot; said president Chen Wei Shu at a press conference following the company's annual general meeting.</p>
<p>The company will continue to concentrate on its existing operations which include consumer goods manufacturing, retailing and wholesaling, auto parts manufacturing and infrastructural development.</p>
<p>Management also confirmed that Shanghai Industrial is acquiring a stake in the newest H share offer to come to the market, Zhejiang Expressway Co Ltd.</p>
<p>Shanghai Industrial will invest about HK$300 million, taking 10 percent of the new issue and giving it a three percent stake in the enlarged issued capital of the new H share company, chairman Cai Lai Xing said.</p>
<p>The offer price of shares of Zhejiang Expressway is expected to fall in a range of HK$2.06 tp HK$2.38, the company said.</p>
<p>The offer will close on Friday and dealing in the shares is expected to commence on May 15.</p>
<p>In April, Shanghai Industrial announced plans to buy a 35 percent stake in two toll roads in Shanghai for US$600 million. The investment, in Shanghai's Inner Rind Road and North-to-South Elevated Expressway, would give the company a holding in the entire elevated roadway system in Shanghai.</p>
<p>Separately, the company's parent company Shanghai Industrial Investment (Holdings) Co Ltd (SIIC) will take a stake in Beijing Enterprises Ltd, a company based in Hong Kong but backed by the Beijing municipal government.</p>
<p>Beijing Enterprises is forecast to be brought to the Hong Kong market later this month.</p>
<p>-- Kathleen Kearney (852) 2843 6933</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
