<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569344" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Beijing says it opposed to Taiwan, Sao Tome ties.</title>
<headline>Beijing says it opposed to Taiwan, Sao Tome ties.</headline>
<byline>Benjamin Kang Lim</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>China said on Thursday it was resolutely opposed to Sao Tome and Principe establishing diplomatic relations with rival Taiwan, but it stopped short of saying it would cut official ties with the African republic.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a shortsighted action that breaches trust and abandons justice,&quot; Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Shen Guofang said about Sao Tome and Principe's decision to switch diplomatic recognition to Taiwan.</p>
<p>&quot;We are resolutely opposed to countries with diplomatic relations with China at the same time establishing so-called diplomatic relations with Taiwan,&quot; Shen told a news briefing.</p>
<p>Asked if China would sever diplomatic relations with Sao Tome and Principe, Shen said Beijing would take further action depending on how the situation developed. He did not elaborate.</p>
<p>Taiwan announced on Tuesday it had established formal ties with the small, twin-island nation, scoring a modest victory in a diplomatic tug-of-war with communist China.</p>
<p>Beijing has regarded Taiwan as a rebel province since the Nationalists fled there after losing the Chinese civil war to the communists in 1949.</p>
<p>Diplomats in Beijing said they expected China to sever diplomatic relations with Sao Tome and Principe as it had in the past when other countries switched recognition to Taiwan.</p>
<p>Shen said the People's Republic of China was the sole legitimate government of China and that Taiwan was an inseparable part of China.</p>
<p>&quot;Sao Tome and Principe has not considered the traditional friendship and friendly cooperation between the two countries,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The switch by Sao Tome and Principe brought to 31 the number of countries in the world that maintain official relations with Taiwan's exiled Republic of China government.</p>
<p>That number will drop to 30 later this year when South Africa is due to recognise Beijing. Most of Taiwan's diplomatic allies are developing nations in the Caribbean and Africa.</p>
<p>Sao Tome and Principe, a former Portuguese colony 200 km (125 miles) off the coast of Gabon, is one of the poorest countries in the world and heavily dependent on foreign aid.</p>
<p>It became independent in 1975, and in 1991 held its first presidential and multi-partisan congress elections.</p>
<p>The country has a foreign debt of $340 million, which it is unable to finance, and desperately needs aid to fund development projects.</p>
<p>China and Taiwan have competed bitterly for diplomatic recognition since 1949, often accusing each other of using large sums of cash and aid to woo potential backers.</p>
<p>In the past five years, another poor African nation, Niger, switched ties twice -- first to Taipei from Beijing in 1992 and then back to Beijing in 1996.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
