<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569332" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: &quot;No Busangs here,&quot; Australia gold conference hears.</title>
<headline>&quot;No Busangs here,&quot; Australia gold conference hears.</headline>
<byline>Michael Byrnes</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ghost of Busang's non-existent millions of ounces of gold haunted an emerging gold producers conference on Thursday despite a stream of optimistic forecasts on new Australian and Southeast Asian gold prospects.</p>
<p>Company after company at the Bell Securities conference spoke of prospective gold deposits, from one side of Australia to the other, as well as in Malaysia and the Philippines.</p>
<p>But when Indonesia was mentioned, it was mostly in the context of how projects under discussion were safe from Busang-style fraud.  </p>
<p>Alastair Provan, managing director of Bell Securities, opened the conference with the point that while gold had performed poorly over the past year, much of recent gold stock price falls was because of the Busang scam.</p>
<p>The still unquantified industry effects of the Bre-X Minerals Ltd scandal will &quot;be with us for a while&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Speakers at the conference lauded Philippine and Malaysian prospects, either explicitly or indirectly in contrast with Indonesia.  </p>
<p>Horacio Ramos, director of the Philippine's Mines and Geosciences Department, after delivering an address on liberalised mining laws in his country, told Reuters the Manila government was introducing a tougher mineral reporting code as one of the lessons of Busang.</p>
<p>It was strengthening requirements for reporting reserves and resources, covering proven, probable, possible and &quot;prediction&quot; categories, with strict accurate definitions, he said.  </p>
<p>It was introducing professional codes of conduct which required company officials to sign off on mining methods. The officials would be personally liable and could face cancellation of licences as a penalty for wrongdoing, he said.</p>
<p>Philippine securities authorities would also work with the Mines Department for validation of reports, he said.</p>
<p>The new regulations, which had been &quot;introduced&quot; but were yet to be &quot;put into effect&quot;, were based on U.S. and U.N. requirements, which were in turn based on Australian regulations, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;I don't think Busang could happen in the Philippines, or (at least) could be perpetrated for so long,&quot; he said. Immediate government validation of reserves would be required, he said.</p>
<p>Alan Phillips, chairman of Australian gold junior Eastern Gold Corp NL, said the company was one of the first smaller mining groups to take advantage of freer Philippine mining laws through its entry into a joint-venture to further explore and develop the T'boli deposit, in the southern island of Mindanao.  </p>
<p>At T'boli, the site of a hand-mining gold rush by individual miners, the deposit showed many similarities to deposits in Papua New Guinea and Indonesia and was regularly returning high grades of 30-50 grams of gold a tonne, he said. The prospect had the potential to become a major gold resource, he said.</p>
<p>Phillips went on to painstakingly outline the stringency of sampling and testing methods at the deposit.</p>
<p>The message was clear that T'boli would be no Busang.</p>
<p>&quot;Malaysia is not Indonesia and is a long way away from Busang,&quot; Peter Kestel, chairman of another gold junior Target Mining Corp NL, told the conference.  </p>
<p>Target has a holding of blocks which contained the old Selinsing gold mine, in the state of Pahang, which had the potential to contain one million ounces of gold or more, Kestel told the conference.</p>
<p>Malaysia was very different from Indonesia, as a former British colony with Western-style laws, political stability and secure mining leases, he went on to say.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
