<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569373" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Sony issues cautious 1997/98 profit forecast.</title>
<headline>Sony issues cautious 1997/98 profit forecast.</headline>
<byline>Yuko Inoue</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japanese electronics giant Sony Corp said on Thursday that sales of its consumer electronics remain strong but it projected relatively conservative profit growth for the current business year.</p>
<p>Sony, whose group net profit more than doubled in the year ended in March 1997, said it expects those profits to rise a more modest 15 percent, to 160 billion yen ($1.29 billion), in the 1997/98 business year that started on April 1.</p>
<p>&quot;We have made conservative estimates for the current business year because we don't want to make any downward revisions later,&quot; Sumio Sano, one of Sony's financial directors, told a news conference.</p>
<p>With almost three-quarters of Sony's business dependent on overseas markets, &quot;Our business tends to be affected by global economic conditions, particularly those in the United States,&quot; added Kenji Tamiya, a senior managing director at the company.</p>
<p>Sony's forecast for the current business year was generally in line with market expectations and analysts reacted favourably to Sony's cautious stance.</p>
<p>&quot;There could be a case for a little bit of profit upgrading,&quot; said Kazuya Yamamoto, an analyst at Daiwa Institute of Research, adding he would maintain the highest rating of &quot;A&quot; for Sony.</p>
<p>Sony said its 1997/98 earnings forecast assumed a currency rate of 115 yen to the dollar, versus 112 yen to the dollar in 1996/97.</p>
<p>Yamamoto said Sony's forecast was too cautious.</p>
<p>Masahiro Ono, an analyst at Credit Lyonnais Securities, added: &quot;Sony might anticipate a possible change in the economic trend in the United States and a strengthening of the yen in the second half of the current business year.&quot;</p>
<p>Sony's share price in London rose as high as 9,925 yen ($80) after the company announced its business results and forecasts.</p>
<p>Earlier, in Tokyo, Sony's share price briefly touched a record high of 9,800 yen ($79) ahead of the earnings announcement, as the market anticipated a strong result. The shares ended at 9,720 yen ($78) in Tokyo, up 90 yen ($0.72) from Wednesday's close.</p>
<p>Sony's Sano said that, by rapidly diversifying its operations, the company has achieved a more stable profit position.</p>
<p>Asked about the recent strong climb in the company's share price, Sano said: &quot;Compared with the rally in our stock price in the late 1980s, our business now is more stable due to diversification into new business areas, such as satellite broadcasting and content production.&quot; Sano said that unit sales of consumer products such as camcorders, CD players and colour TVs will rise by around 10 percent in fiscal 1997/98. Sales of minidiscs are expected to jump 72 percent to 2.5 million units.</p>
<p>Sano added that Sony's semiconductor production equipment unit in the United States reported a large loss in fiscal 1996/97, resulting in a 4.5 percent decline in the company's overall operating profits in the United States. Without that loss, profits at Sony's U.S. operations would have risen substantially, he said.</p>
<p>It is not yet clear if the chip equipment unit will become profitable this business year after restructuring measures, Sano said. ($1=124 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34540">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
