<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569300" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Small, mid-sized Brazil firms' output, sales fall.</title>
<headline>Small, mid-sized Brazil firms' output, sales fall.</headline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Output, sales and revenue at small and mid-sized Brazilian industrial firms dropped in the first quarter compared with 1996's last three months, the National Industry Confederation (CNI) said.</p>
<p>In a statement, the CNI said a survey revealed &quot;an interruption in the rhythm of recovery of industrial activity compared with 1996's last quarter but a higher level of productivity than last year's first quarter.&quot;</p>
<p>The survey, titled &quot;Business Survey of Small and Mid-sized Industry,&quot; showed physical production declined in 39 percent of the firms polled and was stable in 37 percent while sales dropped for 42.2 percent of the companies, the CNI said.</p>
<p>&quot;Of 18 states surveyed, only Minas Gerais registered a rise in sales during the period,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Revenues fell at 63.8 percent of the companies, due mostly to the drop in sales, it said.</p>
<p>Employment at 50.5 percent of the companies remained steady while 32 percent reduced their work forces and 28.4 percent added employees, it added.</p>
<p>Layoffs were mostly seen at clothing, textile and transport materials firms, the confederation said.</p>
<p>The statement did not say how many firms were polled or give a margin of error for the survey.</p>
<p>Of the firms surveyed, 62.3 percent had no investment in the first quarter.</p>
<p>The best-performing sectors in the period were electrical materials, machine metals, metallurgy and textiles while the worst were publishing, beverages, clothing and footwear.</p>
<p>By states, companies in Minas Gerais, Santa Catarina, Para and Sao Paulo performed the best in the period, it added.</p>
<p>(--James Craig, Sao Paulo newsroom 5511 2485413))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
