<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569384" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: SIMEX Euroyen, JGBs slide on technicals, Nikkei.</title>
<headline>SIMEX Euroyen, JGBs slide on technicals, Nikkei.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>SIMEX Euroyen and Japanese government bond (JGB) futures headed south on Thursday due to a bearish technical outlook and the Nikkei's resilience in the face of a steep overnight drop on Wall Street.</p>
<p>&quot;JGBs opened firm but they hit resistance at 124.76 and moved down from there. The technical scenario still shows a bear trend,&quot; a senior trader at an Asian institution said.</p>
<p>He said market rumours that the Bank of Japan (BOJ) was considering hiking rates by September also weighed on Euroyen and JGB futures.  </p>
<p>June JGBs ended at 123.86 against their previous 124.56 after hitting a low of 123.88. Support is seen at the recent contract low of 123.68.</p>
<p>&quot;People are concerned about an over-supply of bonds. Mitsubishi Motor is supposed to issue 80 billion yen next week,&quot; the trader said.</p>
<p>December Euroyen, dampened by the weakness in JGBs, stood at 98.90 at 1115 GMT after hitting a low of 98.88 against an IMM close at 98.96. Support is seen at 98.85.  </p>
<p>Dealers said a series of comments by key Japanese Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara had little impact on the market, despite causing a sharp drop in dollar/yen.</p>
<p>Sakakibara told a parliamentary committee it was possible the yen could strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar, causing the dollar to fall by more than a yen, but he later said his comment contained no specific intent regarding the dollar/yen rate.</p>
<p>Eurodollar futures eased on follow-through selling after the U.S. government's quarterly refunding exercise ended with a poor result in its 10-year note auction.  </p>
<p>December Eurodollars ended at 93.565 against an IMM close at 93.610 on volume of 16,133 lots.</p>
<p>-- Sonali Desai (65-8703090)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
