<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569333" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Stowaway twins to be sent home to New Zealand.</title>
<headline>Stowaway twins to be sent home to New Zealand.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two New Zealand stowaway twins who were found alive and well in Australia's remote outback after an unlikely swim through shark-infested waters were set on Thursday to be sent home to their parents.</p>
<p>An immigration official said 21-year-old twin sisters Sarah and Joanne Ingham would be sent back home &quot;today, if we can book airline seats&quot;.</p>
<p>A 27-year-old Malaysian crewman, Ja'afar Bin Mohamed Zan, who jumped ship with the girls and survived with them in an apparent love triangle had already been deported.</p>
<p>The twins stowed away on the Malaysian freighter Bunga Terasek on February 5 after being invited on to the ship by the crewman but were not discovered until April 14.</p>
<p>A few days later all three leapt overboard as the ship passed through Princess Charlotte Bay, north of Cairns in tropical Queensland state.</p>
<p>They then paddled 20 kms (12 miles) through shark and crocodile-infested waters, prompting a large but unsuccessful air-and-sea search.</p>
<p>Police had presumed them dead two weeks ago, if not from the height of the fall overboard, then from exposure or because of the sharks or other predators.</p>
<p>But they defied the odds and were found on Wednesday by members of a remote Aboriginal community around 50 kms (30 miles) inland at Coen in the Cape York Peninsula.</p>
<p>An Aboriginal police tracker, Barry John Port, said he believed the trio had survived once they reached the shore by scavenging for seafood.</p>
<p>&quot;They lived on the fish that they caught, oysters and crabs,&quot; Port said. &quot;I think it is amazing that they survived.&quot;</p>
<p>Eventually the trio had been found and given some food by local Aborgines who then tried to take them by car to Coen.</p>
<p>When they got close to town the runaways became threatening and the Aboriginals were forced at knifepoint to let them out of the car. They were eventually run to ground in nearby hills by police and local people after robbing a local store of food and new shoes -- which allowed them to be tracked down.</p>
<p>Officers involved in the case told reporters it appeared the runaways were &quot;deeply in love&quot; and wanted to be together, and that this appeared to be the motive for their escape.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
