<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569399" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Foreign sales drive Thai stocks to fresh low.</title>
<headline>Foreign sales drive Thai stocks to fresh low.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thailand's battered stock market took another beating on Thursday as foreign selling of bank shares pushed the key index down to its lowest closing level since January 1991.</p>
<p>Although the index recovered slightly from the day's lows, it still ended down two percent, or 12.51 points, at 614.06.</p>
<p>The market has now lost 7.1 percent of its value in consecutive falls over the last four trading days.</p>
<p>&quot;I've been told foreigners have been selling the banks and it has got some retail players panicky, while those foreign investors who might want to get in are sidelined,&quot; said a trader at Union Securities.</p>
<p>Analysts had feared bank shares would become a target for selling as some major bank stocks have recently outperformed the market.</p>
<p>There were a number of factors weighing on the market, traders said, and no fresh positive news to provide support.</p>
<p>They blamed poor sentiment on a combination of lower economic growth prospects, a disappointing corporate earnings outlook, sluggish export growth, liquidity concerns, a property slump and loan portfolio quality.</p>
<p>Several private analysts say the Thai economy will grow by only about five percent this year, its lowest level for a decade, and most current indicators suggest it is unlikely to rebound soon.</p>
<p>Concerns over weaker growth are translating into lower corporate growth prospects, prompted investors to unload bank, telecommunication and energy stocks during the day, traders said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
