<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569393" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: COSCO seen Shun Shing issue solved soon.</title>
<headline>COSCO seen Shun Shing issue solved soon.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>COSCO (Hong Kong) Group Ltd's planned subscription of new shares in Shun Shing Holdings Ltd is facing technical problems but these would be solved soon, COSCO (Hong Kong) president Zhang Dachun said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think this is nothing major. Peregrine, our financial adviser is discussing with the Securities and Futures Commission (SFC) and I believe this can be solved very soon,&quot; he told a news briefing on Thursday.</p>
<p>Kelvin Wong, a director of COSCO (Hong Kong) said the worst possibility would be that the share holding in Shun Shing would not 61 percent in the short term.</p>
<p>Wong said COSCO's property arm, COSCO (H.K.) Property Ltd's holding in Shun Shing fell to 53.2 percent currently from 61 percent after it placed 52.4 million existing Shun Shing shares with professional investors at HK$4.68 per share.</p>
<p>&quot;The original plan was, on May 31 or before Shun Shing would issue 134.4 million new shares at the same price to COSCO Property,&quot; Wong said.</p>
<p>After the subscription, COSCO's interest in Shun Shing should maintain at 61 percent, he added.</p>
<p>Shun Shing earlier said it would need the SFC's consent before it could complete a placement and share issue announced in early May.</p>
<p>The consent was required &quot;if a person purchases any shares of a company within six months of the closure of an offer made by him for that company, at a higher price than that made available under the offer,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>COSCO group completed a general offer in late March of Shun Shing shares at HK$0.72 per share through COSCO Property.</p>
<p>Trading in Shun Shing shares has been suspended since early Wednesday pending for an annoucement. The shares were last traded at HK$5.85, down HK$0.05.</p>
<p>&quot;The SFC and Peregrine are still in meetings on interpretation of their understandings of Code 31.3,&quot; Wong said. Zhang described Shun Shing as one of the two legs of COSCO group and it was natural that COSCO wanted to inject funds to speed up the expansion of Shun Shing.</p>
<p>&quot;We have prepared some beautiful projects to inject in the company,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Shun Shing would be the major construction, property development and infrastructure arm of the COSCO group in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>COSCO Pacific Ltd, another listing arm of COSCO, would focus on shipping related businesses, such as the owning, manufacturing and leasing of containers and terminal investment, the president said.</p>
<p>COSCO (Hong Kong) is a wholly owned unit of China's China Ocean Shipping (Group) Co (COSCO), which is controlled by the Ministry of Communications of China.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843 6369</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
