<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569368" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Lawyers challenge adequacy of Sumitomo Corp's controls.</title>
<headline>Lawyers challenge adequacy of Sumitomo Corp's controls.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lawyers for former Sumitomo Corp copper trader Yasuo Hamanaka on Thursday continued their campaign to cast doubt on the adequacy of checks and controls at the giant trade house.</p>
<p>In the fourth session of Hamanaka's trial on fraud and forgery charges, the defence grilled Hiroshi Nishino, a former general manager of Sumitomo's credit control division, about the firm's response to a Hamanaka deal through a Sumitomo Hong Kong subsidiary four years ago that broke internal rules.</p>
<p>&quot;We had a meeting in Tokyo with the Hong Kong subsidiary's chief regarding the transaction, but I don't remember the details (of the meeting),&quot; Nishino told the court.</p>
<p>Hamanaka, for many years the most influential trader in the world copper market, has pleaded guilty to charges of fraud and forgery in connection with unauthorised trades that Sumitomo blames for a $2.6 billion copper market loss.</p>
<p>Despite the guilty plea, defence lawyers have said they hope to achieve a lighter sentence for their client by demonstrating that lax controls at Sumitomo were partly to blame for the huge loss.</p>
<p>Toru Yoshiki, one of the lawyers on Hamanaka's defence team, said after Thursday's session that the defence would continue to highlight Sumitomo's actions following the 1993 deal through the Hong Kong subsidiary.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a possibility that Sumitomo could have stopped Hamanaka's unauthorised transactions if its system of checks and controls was working properly,&quot; Yoshiki told Reuters after the session.</p>
<p>The next sessions of Hamanaka's trial are scheduled for June 6 and July 9</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
