<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569310" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: PRESS DIGEST - New Zealand newspapers - May 9.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - New Zealand newspapers - May 9.</headline>
<text>
<p>THE DOMINION</p>
<p>Setback for Peters on super poll: A select committee recommendation to have the word &quot;compulsory&quot; included in the question to be put to voters in September's referendum on a proposed superannuation scheme is being described as a &quot;significant defeat&quot; for Treasurer Winston Peters. Page 1.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Control of spending 'very loose': Even the lowliest employee at Aotearoa Television Network could have spent hundreds of thousands of dollars of the station's money, Maori broadcasting agency Te Mangai Paho said on Thursday. Page 1.  </p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Morgan vows to stay in Parliament till voted out: NZ First MP Tukoroirangi Morgan declared on Thursday night he had nothing to hide and would remain in Parliament till voted out by his Te Tai Hauaru electorate. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Lee got sums wrong, says commission: Allegations by Alliance MP Sandra Lee that Treaty of Waitangi fisheries commissioners &quot;creamed&quot; $6.1 million in fees in four years were rejected by the commission on Thursday as faulty arithmetic. Page 2.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Minister defends ban on work-time meeting: Conservation Minister Nick Smith defended on Thursday his decision to ban Napier-based staff from talking to Helen Clark during working hours. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Free child health care abandoned: The Coalition Government's promise of free health care for all children under six was finally abandoned on Thursday, though neither NZ First nor National would comment on it. Page 2.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Snapper ruling to be challenged: The Treaty of Waitangi Fisheries Commission is going to the Court of Appeal to challenge a cut to snapper quotas that it says will reduce the value of the Maori fisheries settlement by at least $14 million. Page 2.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Democrat party quits Christian Coalition: The Christian Democrat Party is pulling out of the Christian Coalition. Page 2.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Float paves way for new food chain: A public float of 85 million shares is being offered to fund the purchase of a new company that will oversee 122 KFC and Pizza Hutt fast-food franchises in New Zealand. Page 13.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Room for growth seen in fast-food business: Fast-food restaurants may seem to be ubiquitous in New Zealand but the ratio is one for every 10,000. Page 13.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Size of deceitful advertisers may rule size of fine: Bigger companies could face bigger court fines if they break the Fair Trading Act after a record $63,000 fine imposed on retailer Bond and Bond. Page 13.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Roundtable wants boards wound up: Producer boards should be wound up over one to two years, the Business Roundtable told the primary production select committee considering the Producer Board Acts Reform Bill. Page 13.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Floating mortgage rates continue down: Countrywide Bank and the National Bank cut their floating mortgage interest rates to 8.95 percent on Thursday, while niche provider HongkongBank slashed its floating rate to 8.4 percent. Page 13.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Drop in Farmers Deka sales: Sales by department store group Farmers Deka slipped 0.9 percent to $200.4 million in the group's third quarter compared to last year, the group's Perth-based owner Foodland Associates said on Thursday. Page 13.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Warehouse sales up in last quarter: Retailer The Warehouse announced its same-store sales increased 7.2 percent in the three months to April 30, 1997 compared with the same period last year. Page 13.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Singapore-Air NZ meeting fuels alliance rumours: Speculation is mounting that an alliance between Singapore Airlines and Air New Zealand is imminent after senior executives from both airlines met in Auckland last week. Page 14.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Hopes for home-grown experts: New Zealanders often look overseas for economic analysis while at the same time many foreigners visit New Zealand to check out economic changes. Page 14.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Alliance might become unlisted public company: New Zealand's biggest meat processor, Alliance Group, may become an unlisted public company and be open to new shareholders if its farmer shareholders opt to change from the present cooperative structure. Page 14.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
