<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569350" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: JGBs seen falling toward 123 amid downtrend.</title>
<headline>JGBs seen falling toward 123 amid downtrend.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1996-05-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Key June 10-year Japanese government bond (JGB) futures are likely to fall to the lower end of the 123 to 124 yen range on Friday amid an ongoing downtrend, after poor results at Thursday's six-year JGB auction.</p>
<p>The June contract ended on LIFFE at its session low of 123.77 on Thursday after Tokyo's finish of 124.05.</p>
<p>Selling overnight was mainly attributed to the dollar's sharp fall against the yen, triggered by a senior MOF official's remark after the Tokyo close on Thursday that the yen could strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar.  </p>
<p>The dollar lost nearly two yen on the remark.</p>
<p>&quot;Japanese authorities' efforts to keep the yen from falling can be either a bullish or a bearish factor,&quot; said a dealer at a city bank's securities unit.</p>
<p>&quot;But this time, they fuelled fears of higher interest rates. If verbal and actual intervention does not work, Japan may raise interest rates to deter the yen from falling further,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>June may find a floor at this year's low of 123.60 and then at 123.39, the previous low hit on November 12, but traders said the downtrend may continue unless investors stop selling.  </p>
<p>&quot;The June may fall by one yen from the current level within a couple of days,&quot; the dealer said.</p>
<p>-- Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-33432-8570</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
