<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569327" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia says won't lecture Asia on human rights.</title>
<headline>Australia says won't lecture Asia on human rights.</headline>
<byline>Michael Perry</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian Prime Minister John Howard said on Thursday Australia was an integral part of Asia and would not bully Asian nations on sensitive issues such as human rights, but in turn Asia should not lecture Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not see that public hectoring or lecturing other countries about their shortcomings or differences from us is appropriate behaviour for a neighbour or indeed likely to promote our interests or values,&quot; Howard said.</p>
<p>&quot;Equally, Australia herself does not expect to be on the receiving end of lectures. We have the same right to have our values and sensitivities respected. Mutual respect has to be two-way,&quot; Howard said in a major speech on Australia and Asia.</p>
<p>But Howard added, &quot;On the issue of human rights, Australia will always stand up for her beliefs and values&quot;.</p>
<p>In April, Australia's year-old conservative government agreed with China to hold formal human rights dialogue. It reversed Australia's long-standing support for a U.N. motion censuring Beijing for rights abuses.</p>
<p>The move was criticised by human rights groups. Asian nations often criticised Australia's previous Labor governments for taking a &quot;Western&quot; stance on human rights.</p>
<p>As a bitter, domestic race row raises concerns in the region towards Australia, Howard also stressed Australia's commitment to Asia, citing a long history of engagement.</p>
<p>&quot;Australia's engagement in her region plays a vital part in my government's strategy,&quot; said Howard.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the most decisive influences on our standard of living and the capaicty of our economy to provide worthwhile jobs for our children will be our success in exporting our goods and services to Asian countries.&quot;</p>
<p>But in a message to supporters of race row politician Pauline Hanson, who fear Australia has been kowtowing to Asia and should halt Asian immigration, Howard said Australia did not have to change its identity in order to be part of Asia.</p>
<p>&quot;Australia does not have to choose between her geography and her history. Our history and our links with the West make a unique contribution to our region,&quot; Howard said.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not come as a supplicant to the regional association, because we have brought much to it. Australia has been a dependable friend and an important economic and security partner to many countries in the region,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Howard said Australia was an important player in Asia, whose raw materials had fuelled Japan's &quot;dramatic industrial take-off&quot;, adding Australia could play a similar role in China.</p>
<p>&quot;Australia could also provide the financial, legal and other services for which China has a growing need as its economy modernises and becomes more sophisticated,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Citing various bilateral visits by himself and Asian leaders as proof of close links with the region, Howard announced that Chinese Vice Premier Zhu Rongji would visit later in May.</p>
<p>Howard also defended his government's closer ties with the United States, which have been criticised by Chinese media as part of a U.S. containment policy towards Beijing.</p>
<p>&quot;These activities do not reflect a fear on the government's part of any particular threat. I especially want to emphasise that it is in no one's interests to treat China as a threat. We want to see China involved in regional and global institutions.&quot;</p>
<p>Howard said Australia should be confident of its place in Asia and that Asia should be comfortable with Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;Australia can be confident about its place in the region. We bring many strengths to bear. Australia has -- economically, politically and strategically -- an important role to play.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
