<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569330" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia's Crown casino opens to mixed reviews.</title>
<headline>Australia's Crown casino opens to mixed reviews.</headline>
<byline>Michael Stapleton</byline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's Crown casino, the largest in Asia, rolled out the red carpet for a star-studded guest-list at its opening on Thursday, throwing the spotlight on a fierce debate over the nation's embrace of gambling.</p>
<p>Performers from around the world, including singers Billy Joel, Elton John and Ray Charles, were flown in for the event, the highlight of which was an extravagant fireworks display.</p>
<p>The Melbourne casino, the cost of which has been put by some analysts at over A$2 billion (US$1.56 billion), aims to deprive unlucky punters of more than A$1 billion in its first year, most of it from Asian high rollers.</p>
<p>In a clear sign Crown wants to lure the region's heaviest gamblers, Crown Ltd's founder and chairman, Lloyd Williams, fed a lettuce to a Chinese &quot;dragon&quot; during a good-luck ceremony. Crown has said that the focus is Asia in terms of international revenue.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we've created a really major entertainment precinct in Melbourne,&quot; Williams said at the opening.</p>
<p>But church and welfare leaders have attacked the project, concerned that gambling is tearing at the fabric of Victoria state's conservative community.</p>
<p>Crown won Victoria's exclusive casino licence in September 1993 and has operated a temporary casino since June 1994.</p>
<p>Victorians are the country's biggest gamblers, though five years ago they were Australia's most timid punters. One in every 30 dollars earned by Victorians is now spent on gambling.</p>
<p>Gambling fever has also taken hold across the country. Australia now has 14 casinos dotted around the continent.</p>
<p>But moral crusaders are not alone in criticising this trend.</p>
<p>Major business groups like retailers, and even media baron Rupert Murdoch, have said that money once spent on consumer goods and newspapers is now fed into the gambling industry.</p>
<p>Sceptics in the financial markets have nicknamed the new complex the &quot;Spruce Goose&quot;, after the U.S. 1940s seaplane which was too big to fly.</p>
<p>Even the casino's backers have expressed doubts about the project's mammoth size.</p>
<p>&quot;This great city has a great image and we don't want it to be seen as 'Casino City',&quot; Melbourne mayor Ivan Deveson said on Thursday. He said he did not want any more gambling projects.</p>
<p>The casino has 2,500 slot machines and 350 gaming tables.</p>
<p>Victoria state Premier Jeff Kennett, whose government has become increasingly reliant on gambling taxes, officially opened the casino.</p>
<p>One notable absentee from the opening was Australian Prime Minister, John Howard.</p>
<p>Howard has voiced concerns about the impact of gambling on the poor and on small businesses and says he believes gambling has reached saturation point.</p>
<p>Apart from gaming tables, the complex houses Australia's largest hotel, a convention centre, a cinema complex, 52 bars and restaurants and 34 upmarket retailers.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$0.78)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
