<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569364" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Hanbo staff quit CalEnergy site near Manila.</title>
<headline>Hanbo staff quit CalEnergy site near Manila.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippine police have deployed troops at a major power plant and irrigation project north of Manila after workers of South Korea's Hanbo Engineering &amp; Construction Ltd pulled out, officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Regional police commander Edgar Aglipay said he had ordered security around the project site to protect equipment and facilities after three busloads of Hanbo workers left the area on Wednesday night.</p>
<p>CE Casecnan Water and Energy Company Inc has ended a contract with Hanbo to build the project and entered into an agreement with another group of companies to complete it, Casecnan's parent company, CalEnergy Corp, said in a statement in Omaha, Nebraska on Wednesday.</p>
<p>CE Casecnan's project includes a combined irrigation and 150 MW capacity hydroelectric facility located in the northern part of the main Philipine island of Luzon.</p>
<p>The project, estimated to cost 10.6 billion pesos ($403 million), will sell electricity and water to the Philippines' state-owned National Irrigation Administration.</p>
<p>Suspected communist guerrillas last year raided the project site and burnt down construction equipment, police said.</p>
<p>CalEnergy said in its statement that a contract with Hanbo Engineering &amp; Construction Co and Hanbo Corp had been terminated because of contract default.</p>
<p>CE Casecnan has entered into a new construction contract to finish the Philippine project with a group of contractors and subcontractors including affiliates of Siemens A.G., Sulzer Hydro Ltd., Black &amp; Veatch and Colenco Power Engineering Ltd. The consortium will be headed by affiliates of Cooperativa Muratori Cementisti CMC di Ravenna and Impressa Pizzarotti &amp; C. Spra., CalEnergy said.</p>
<p>-- Manila newsroom (632) 841 8913 Fax 817 6267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I1610107">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I17000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I32200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
