<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569329" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian petroleum refinery output said rising.</title>
<headline>Australian petroleum refinery output said rising.</headline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's average petroleum refinery output has continued to rise over the past three years, to more than 3,500 megalitres a month so far in 1996/97 ending June 30 from 3,300 ML a month in 1993/94 and 1994/95, the Department of Primary Industries and Energy said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The department said in its February Petroleum Bulletin that the major product increases were in diesel, aviation turbine fuel and liquid petroleum gas.</p>
<p>Production of petrol has been falling since the end of 1996, partly due to competition from imported petrol, it said.  </p>
<p>Refinery feedstock sources were also changing, with only 40 percent of input sourced locally over the past four months, compared with an average of 49 percent in 1993/94 and 1994/95, it said.</p>
<p>The main reasons for the change were refiners with improved secondary processing facilities taking advantage of lower priced imported crude oils, and the North West Shelf crude oil attracting a quality premium for exports.  </p>
<p>The percentage sales of unleaded petrol rose one percent each month in the first two months of 1997, with unleaded petrol sales accounting for nearly two-thirds (66.1 percent) of the total petrol consumption, it said.</p>
<p>Turning to the supply-demand balance in calendar 1996, the department said Australia's total oil supply (domestic production plus imports) rose 7.6 percent over 1995 to more than 1,118,000 barrels per day (bpd).</p>
<p>After trending down in 1995, domestic oil/condensate production increased by 30,000 bpd, or 5.3 percent, to 601,800 bpd in 1996, it said.  </p>
<p>Crude oil and petrol product imports rose by 11 percent to 490,400 bpd in 1996, while exports of oil and products, including liquid petroleum gas, rose by 16 percent to 318,400 bpd.</p>
<p>Net liquid petroleum earnings in 1996 stood at A$274 million after total liquid petroleum exports of A$5,186 million and total liquid petroleum imports of A$4,912 million.</p>
<p>Australia's domestic sales of petroleum amounted to 744,000 bpd in 1996, 1.2 percent higher than in 1995, it said.</p>
<p>NOTE: One megalitre equals 6,290 barrels.</p>
<p>-- Canberra Bureau 61-6 273-2730</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
