<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569395" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China stocks down sharply on clampdown fears.</title>
<headline>China stocks down sharply on clampdown fears.</headline>
<byline>Graham Earnshaw</byline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's A and B share indices ended sharply down on Thursday as rumours swirled through the markets about possible official measures to cool down trading, brokers said.</p>
<p>The Shanghai B index tumbled 4.871 points or 4.96 percent to 93.335 while the Shenzhen B index fell 6.13 points or 3.35 percent to 176.61.</p>
<p>Two local brokers in Shanghai said that if Beijing came out with serious measures to rein in the markets, the A share indices could fall up to 15 or 20 percent in the short-term, given the speed of the rises in recent months.</p>
<p>But many brokers expressed scepticism about Beijing planning anything major with the Hong Kong handover now so close.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no way they'd do anything serious at this point,&quot; said John Crossman, general manager of Jardine Fleming in Shanghai. &quot;Everything has got to be smooth sailing through the Hong Kong handover (on June 30).&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Beijing doesn't want to see any dramatic movements either up or down before the handover,&quot; said a broker in Shenzhen. &quot;I don't expect anything drastic to be announced.&quot;</p>
<p>China's official newspapers are continuing to publish articles warning of risks in the stock markets and a leading economist was quoted on Thursday as saying the time had come to list currently non-tradeable state and institutional shares.</p>
<p>A Hong Kong newspaper also said China's Ministry of Finance was considering increasing stamp duties for trading stocks from the current 0.3 percent to 0.4 or 0.5 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Beijing will not tolerate the abnormally high domestic A share prices, and rumours circulating in the market say clampdown measures will be worked out soon,&quot; said one local broker.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is a crackdown, I would say the A market could fall 15 or 20 percent, and would then consolidate for a while,&quot; said another broker.</p>
<p>Shanghai Worldbest was the biggest loser in Shanghai, slumping $0.07 or 9.33 percent to $0.68.</p>
<p>The market barometer Shanghai Lujiazui Finance &amp; Trade Zone Development was the most actively traded, down $0.108 or 6.67 percent to $1.51 on volume of 3.6 million shares.</p>
<p>&quot;Investor jitters over recent strong A share gains affected the B share market,&quot; an analyst at J&amp;A Securities said.</p>
<p>In Shenzhen, upcoming B share offers drained some funds from the B share market, analysts said.</p>
<p>Pesticide maker Hubei Sanonda Co Ltd, Shandong Chenming Paper Holdings Ltd and Nanjing Posts &amp; Telecommunications Equipment Co Ltd will each offer 100 million B shares for listing in Shenzhen this month.</p>
<p>But analysts said they expected the three new stocks to perform well on their listing debuts, which will likely boost investor sentiment.</p>
<p>Most analysts said they were confident that the underlying trend remained bullish.</p>
<p>The Shanghai A index slipped 94.789 points or 6.07 percent to 1,467.861 on turnover of 15.4 billion yuan. The SSE30 blue chip index fell 320.921 points or 7.27 percent to 4,092.126.</p>
<p>The Shenzhen A share index plunged 31.87 points or 5.97 percent to end at 501.92 on turnover of 20.2 billion yuan, following a record high close of 533.78 points on Wednesday on turnover of 21.3 billion yuan.</p>
<p>($1=8.3 yuan, $1=HK$7.8)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
