<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569369" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan ministers quit ahead of reshuffle.</title>
<headline>Taiwan ministers quit ahead of reshuffle.</headline>
<byline>Alice Hung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three Taiwan ministers resigned on Thursday, increasing pressure on the government ahead of a planned cabinet reshuffle triggered by public discontent over rising crime on the island.</p>
<p>Ma Ying-jeou, minister without portfolio and a popular politican, Interior Minister Lin Feng-cheng, and Tjiu Mau-ying, chairman of Taiwan's Council of Agriculture, all tendered their resignations to Premier Lien Chan.</p>
<p>The unexpected resignations caught the ruling Nationalist Party and Lien's administration by surprise. The administration, which has faced intense criticism over a spate of violent crime, was expected to announce a reshuffle next week.</p>
<p>Ma appeared to take a swipe at Taiwan's political culture in his resignation statement, saying he stepped down &quot;due to a change of political ethics, obstacles in reforms and growing public discontent.&quot;</p>
<p>He also accused unnamed officials of &quot;struggling for power, taking credit and shunning responsibility.&quot;</p>
<p>Lin had been under fire over the island's crime wave, which culminated in the kidnap and murder of the teenage daughter of renowned actress Pai Ping-ping.</p>
<p>Last month, the body of 17-year-old Pai Hsiao-yen was found floating naked in a river. Police said she had been kidnapped and murdered. The killers remained at large.</p>
<p>The murder was the latest in a number of high-profile violent crimes to hit Taiwan beginning last year.</p>
<p>More than 50,000 people marched in Taipei on Sunday to protest against the government's failure to stop crime and demand Lien's resignation and a cabinet reshuffle.</p>
<p>Tjiu has been under fire since March for the Council of Agriculture's failure to prevent the outbreak of a deadly epidemic of hog foot-and-mouth disease that forced Taiwan to ban pork exports, jeopardising the island's economic recovery.</p>
<p>The protest over crime prompted President Lee Teng-hui, who doubles as chairman of the Nationalist Party, to call for a partial reshuffle of the cabinet on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Lien, who had tendered his resignation to Lee, was asked to stay on. But Lee asked the premier, who is also vice president, to deliver a list of reshuffled cabinet positions for approval during next Wednesday's central standing committee meeting.</p>
<p>State media had speculated that Lin would be asked to step down and be replaced by the popular Ma.</p>
<p>Opposition parties said a partial government reshuffle was not enough.</p>
<p>Lawmakers from the main opposition Democratic Progressive Party and the opposition New Party sought support for a motion asking President Lee to call for a complete cabinet reshuffle and to replace Lien.</p>
<p>&quot;Public discontent is boiling. We want President Lee to name a new premier,&quot; Chen Chung-hsin, deputy secretary-general of the Democratic Progressive Party, told Reuters in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;The public has demanded a change. The ruling Nationalist Party cannot ignore the voice of the people,&quot; Chen said.</p>
<p>Analysts forecast the island's hypersensitive stock market would nose-dive on Friday on fears of political upheaval.</p>
<p>&quot;Local politics is expected to be unstable and uncertainty is the market's biggest enemy,&quot; said Alex Chan, an analyst of HSBC James Capel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
