<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569306" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: PRESS DIGEST - NZ Business weeklies - May 9.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - NZ Business weeklies - May 9.</headline>
<text>
<p>THE NATIONAL BUSINESS REVIEW</p>
<p>Tuku told: It's time to go: Two powerful forces in Maoridom say New Zealand First MP Tukoroirangi Morgan is threatening Maori business credibility and undermining its leadership. Page 1.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Public joins MPs in opposing plebiscite: Public opinion is hardening against a proposed savings-based compulsory scheme to decided in a September referendum. Page 1.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Ministry warned of boat disaster: The Ministry of Transport ignored repeated warnings that could have prevented last year's Whale Watch boat tragedy off Kaikoura that killed a Taiwanese tourist. Page 1.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Government admits IT wastage: Government departments have wasted hundred of millions of dollars on failed or troubled information technology projects, and Communications and Information Technology Minister Maurice Williamson admits the government doesn't even know how much it is spending in this sector. Page 2.  </p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Pay-out plan aims to save racing clubs: New Zealand racing clubs will get performance-based payments next season as part of a Racing Industry Board financial recovery package designed to rescue the $1 billion industry from stagnancy. Page 4.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Slipway to success: When the second of New Zealand's billion-dollar Anzac frigates slips into the water in Melbourne this weekend, a growing number of New Zealand businesses will be celebrating with the navy. Page 5.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Britten plans road version of racer: The Britten Motorcycle Company in Christchurch is preparing to expand as a prototype design studio and may also develop a road version of the now-famous racing bike design. Page 5.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Two roadblocks to clear on path to US free trade: There are two major obstacles to the free-trade agreement between New Zealand and the US which both countries will start discussing in Washington this month. Page 9.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Searoad directors face investigation: Liquidators for coastal shipper Searoad, which collapsed last month with debts of $3.6 million, say they will investigate the conduct of the company's directors. Page 9.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Few National MPs favour superannuation scheme: Most National MPs are opposed to a compulsory superannuation scheme as proposed in the September referendum. Page 10.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Developer plans 'theme town' for Matakana Is: Chris Wingate, cock-a-hoop after winning a major victory this week in his bid to control Matakana Island, is pressing ahead with plans for a theme town on the island. Page 11.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Companies lambasted after R&amp;D funds queue vanishes: Up to $5 million of government money available for business growth is going begging each year because New Zealand companies are afraid of new technology. Page 13.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Defiance's fate hangs in the balance as Goodman Fielder grinds on: The future of Christchurch-based Defiance Food Industries hangs in the balance as acceptances for Bunge Foods' takeover of the Australian parent company Defiance Mills reached 56.7 percent this week. Page 14.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Makin regretful as he quits Clear: Words of weariness and regret accompanies Makin's abrupt resignation as chief executive of Clear Communications on Wednesday. Page 15.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>Casino brings big dividend to Skyline: The Christchurch Casino has proved a boon for Queenstown-based Skyline Enterprises. Page 16.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
