<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569476" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Hariri says civilian rule threatened in Lebanon.</title>
<headline>Hariri says civilian rule threatened in Lebanon.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lebanese Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri was quoted on Thursday as saying an intelligence agency failing to obey political directives was threatening civilian rule in Lebanon.</p>
<p>The conservative daily an-Nahar said Hariri made the statement to members of the Lebanese press syndicate after they criticised his government's commitment to strengthening state institutions.</p>
<p>An-Nahar said Hariri replied that he had been aware of attempts to undermine state institutions since taking office in October 1992.</p>
<p>&quot;Since I took office there have been continual attempts to show that civil institutions, beginning with the presidency, parliament, the cabinet, the administration and the judiciary are not in good condition, with the aim of marginalising them and reducing their credibility,&quot; it quoted Hariri as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;Civilian rule is threatened by the behaviour of an intelligence agency that does not comply with political directives and behaves in a way that threatens constitutional institutions and safety of civilian rule,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>He did not identify the agency.</p>
<p>An-Nahar said journalists at the meeting originally decided not to publish Hariri's remarks but later found that the official National News Agency published them, followed by television stations which speculated on the identity of the agency.</p>
<p>Hariri's remarks followed widespread questioning of his government's commitment to democracy after a decision to delay municipal elections due this summer, a proposal to extend parliament's term by eight months, allegations of political pressure on the constitutional court and use of the police and strong-arm tactics to split the labour confederat1ion.</p>
<p>The government has also been under heavy attack in the press recently for alleged corruption, abuses of power, mounting public debt and failure to halt abuses.</p>
<p>In the latest onslaught, Hassan Sabra, a friend of Hariri and editor of the weekly news magazine Ash-Shiraa, said in an open letter to him that failure to rein in corruption at all levels of the government was &quot;mercilessly suffocating Lebanon&quot;.</p>
<p>Sabra said that kickbacks pocketed by go-betweens of whom the government was aware accounted for more than 50 percent of Lebanon's ballooning public debt.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
