<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569423" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan nationalism bubbles over - again.</title>
<headline>Japan nationalism bubbles over - again.</headline>
<byline>Brian Williams</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan has again been embarrassed by a sudden individual outburst of nationalism -- this time over disputed islands -- that has the country's diplomats wringing their hands in anguish.</p>
<p>With Japan still vulnerable more than 50 years after the end of World War Two to any hint of territorial expansion, the landing this week by a conservative parliament member on rocky outcrops in the East China Sea was an immediate headache for Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto's government.</p>
<p>The landing on Tuesday on the uninhabited islets, called the Senkaku Islands by Japan and the Diaoyu Islands by China, drew sharp protests from rival claimants China and Taiwan, which each slammed Tokyo for its low-key stance towards the action.</p>
<p>It was no matter that legislator Shingo Nishimura was a member of the opposition New Frontier Party and took the action without even the support of his own party, let alone the government.</p>
<p>What mattered was that he planted Japan's Rising Sun flag on the islands, which are about midway between Taiwan and Japan's Okinawa chain of islands.</p>
<p>Japan has claimed the islands since 1895, while China says it has owned them since ancient times.</p>
<p>It was only the latest episode in a decades-old dispute which was rekindled last year when a Japanese right-wing group built a makeshift lighthouse on the islands.</p>
<p>&quot;The landing was...not a good idea from the point of view of foreign relations,&quot; commented top government spokesman Seiroku Kajiyama in describing it as &quot;illegal&quot; the day after it happened.</p>
<p>Nishimura, whose constituency is more than 1,000 km (625 miles) away from the islands, left no doubt that his action was meant to strike a symbolic blow for Japanese nationalism.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe this landing on the Senkaku Islands will be the starting point for an awakening of national consciousness and the rebirth of a Japan with pride,&quot; he said in statement.</p>
<p>But some analysts saw Nishimura's landing as simply the act of an obscure politician wanting publicity.</p>
<p>&quot;I would say that Nishimura's action was merely a self-advertisement,&quot; Tadashi Iyasu, professor of politics at Tokyo's Ryukoku University, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;If he was a real nationalist who cared about the country, he wouldn't have done such a thing to cause an uproar in other countries,&quot; Iyasu said.</p>
<p>But other analysts said Nishimura spoke for a yearning among many Japanese for their nation to throw off the shame of its World War Two actions and stand tall in the world.</p>
<p>Rei Shiratori, president of the Institute for Political Studies in Japan, said Nishimura should not be lumped in with ultra-rightists who long for pre-war days when the country's emperor was regarded as a living god and to be Japanese was to be regarded as one of the world's chosen races.</p>
<p>&quot;Nishimura's visit was completely different from the actions taken by ultra-rightists,&quot; Shiratori said.</p>
<p>&quot;First he didn't represent his party or any other political groups. He merely wanted to bring up the territorial issue and urge the Japanese government to take action on the problem.&quot;</p>
<p>Kaoru Okano, dean of Tokyo's Meiji University, said that while ultra-rightists were often an embarrassment to the government by their wild and often outdated protests, Japanese like Nishimura simply wanted the right to be patriots.</p>
<p>&quot;These emotional right-wingers have pride in Japan and take things like the national flag and the national anthem seriously,&quot; Okano said.</p>
<p>Akio Watanabe, professor of international politics at Tokyo's Aoyama Gakuin University, said there was growing frustration in Japan that the country was always morally on the defensive in dealings with its Asian neighbours because of World War Two.</p>
<p>&quot;Nationalists like Nishimura are frustrated by the government's handling of criticism from Asian neighbours for Japan's wartime actions,&quot; he said. &quot;The landing is closely linked to this feeling.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
