<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569468" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: Turkish energy minister arrives in Iraq for gas deal. [CORRECTED 21:45 GMT]</title>
<headline>Turkish energy minister arrives in Iraq for gas deal. [CORRECTED 21:45 GMT]</headline>
<byline>Hassan Hafidh</byline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkish Energy Minister Recai Kutan arrived in Baghdad on Thursday to discuss with Iraqi officials final details of a gas (corrects from oil) deal, the Iraqi News Agency (INA) said.</p>
<p>Under the deal, which officials from the two countries have been discussing over the last few months, Turkey is to develop Iraqi gas fields and buy gas through a pipeline.</p>
<p>&quot;The Turkish delegation will hold talks with (Iraqi) oil ministry officials...to complete discussions on setting up a pipeline to transfer natural gas from Iraq to Turkey,&quot; INA said.</p>
<p>The agency said a Turkish technical delegation had been in Baghdad over the last few weeks to discuss details of the project with Iraq.</p>
<p>The pact would entail building a 1,300 kilometre gas pipeline at a cost of $2.5 billion. It would be capable of carrying 10 billion cubic metres (bcm) of gas a year.</p>
<p>Iraq's Oil Minister Amir Muhammad Rasheed said in remarks published in April that the 20-year contract would be signed in July.</p>
<p>Baghdad is under stringent U.N. trade sanctions imposed after its 1990 invasion of Kuwait. But the U.N. has allowed it to sell limited oil since last December to pay for urgent needs.</p>
<p>U.N. Under-Secretary General Yasushi Akashi said in Baghdad on Thursday the programme has not yet alleviated Iraqis' sufferings.</p>
<p>Most of Iraq's gas production consists solely of associated gas dissolved in oil and contained in oilfield gas gaps. But Iraq boasts several gas fields, among them Al-Anfal which came on stream in May 1990 at a rate of 200 million cubic feet a day.</p>
<p>Official estimates put proven gas reserves at more than 3,115 billion cubic metres in 1989.</p>
<p>Turkey is trying to secure as many contracts as possible under Iraq's oil-for-food deal with the United Nations.</p>
<p>Under the deal, Turkey has a contract to lift 75,000 barrels per day of Iraqi crude. The bulk of the limited Iraqi oil exports is being shipped through a pipeline to the Turkish terminal of Ceyhan on the Mediterranean.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
