<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569432" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: No import surge seen from China leaded petrol ban.</title>
<headline>No import surge seen from China leaded petrol ban.</headline>
<byline>Ang Bee Lin</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's decision to ban the use of leaded gasoline by 2000 is not expected to trigger a surge of imports as major domestic refineries are equipped to meet the new demand, industry sources said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The ban will first be enforced in in Beijing from June and will be gradually extended to other large cities culminating in a nationwide ban in 2000.  </p>
<p>&quot;Most of the major refineries along coastal China are equipped to produce unleaded gasoline. There are no problems for us to meet that requirement when it comes into effect,&quot; said a source at state refiner Sinopec.</p>
<p>&quot;China has always been quite self-sufficient. We have never been importing a lot of gasoline but have boosted our exports in recent years. Exports may dip in the near term to fulfill demand but I do not expect exports to be suppressed for long,&quot; said a source at statetrader Sinochem in Beijing.  </p>
<p>Chinese trade sources said coastal refineries responsible for meeting more than half of the country's demand had been upgraded in the last few years.</p>
<p>&quot;Refineries at Fujian, Shanghai, Zhenghai have also been producing unleaded gasoline and have been exporting it as well,&quot; the source at Sinopec said.</p>
<p>The sources said that while inland refineries had yet to be upgraded, there were also fewer cars in the remote areas of China.  </p>
<p>&quot;These refineries are very small and we do not depend on them to meet our gasoline requirements in the larger cities like Guangzhou, where the number of cars is increasing rapidly,&quot; said the Sinochem source.</p>
<p>China's Xinhua news agency said on Wednesday China would introduce unleaded gasoline by 2000 to try to reduce pollution caused by auto emissions.</p>
<p>They said Beijing Yanshan Petrochemical, one of Sinopec's refineries, had spent 1.1 billion yuan ($132.5 million) on equipment renewal and began producing unleaded petrol in March.  </p>
<p>Sources at Sinopec also said China planned to ban the use of poor quality low octane gasoline by 2000 as well.</p>
<p>Sources at the refineries told Reuters that instead of using lead to boost the octane level of gasoline and improve its quality, Chinese refineries had been using other octane boosters such as aromatics and methyl tertiary butyl ether (MTBE).</p>
<p>China exports high-octane unleaded gasoline and imports a mixture of unleaded and leaded low octane petrol.  </p>
<p>In the first quarter of this year, China imported 14,565 tonnes of a gasoline. It sold 504,112 tonnes of unleaded supplies, more than triple its exports in the same period last year.</p>
<p>As the move would have marginal impact on Chinese gasoline imports, traders in Asia said they did not see the international spot market to be affected significantly.</p>
<p>&quot;This may direct some of the exports to the domestic market for a while but the market in Asia has never seen lack of supplies after Thailand and South Korea boosted production,&quot; said a major oil firm in Singapore</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
