<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569441" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean won ends higher on stop-loss dlr selling.</title>
<headline>S.Korean won ends higher on stop-loss dlr selling.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stop-loss dollar selling and the weakening dollar against the yen in world markets pushed the won to close higher on Thursday, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;As the dollar fell against the yen, they have no choice but to sell the greenback,&quot; said a local bank dealer. &quot;Everybody had gone long on dollars in anticipation of an inflow of foreign funds for stock investment.&quot;</p>
<p>Dealers said the dollar fell on a remark by a Japanese Finance Ministry offical the yen could strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar.</p>
<p>The won ended at 892.90 from Wednesday's close of 894.80.  </p>
<p>After opening at 894.80, the won moved in a 895.00-892.90 range.</p>
<p>Dealers said fewer-than-expected importer deals and dollar supply from exporter negotiations also boosted the local unit. The local bank dealer said many companies had already secured dollars for importer deals in forward transactions.</p>
<p>&quot;But the dollar's bullishness has not changed as dollar demand will continue on the nation's trade deficit,&quot; said a foreign bank dealer.</p>
<p>Friday's mid-rate is expected to be pegged at 894.10 against 895.20 today.</p>
<p>-- Yeom Yoon-jeong (822) 727 5647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
