<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569489" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Explosion rips through Arkansas chemical plant.</title>
<headline>Explosion rips through Arkansas chemical plant.</headline>
<dateline>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three firefighters were killed and more than a dozen injured battling an explosion and fire that ripped through a chemical plant in West Helena, Arkansas, on Thursday, officials said.</p>
<p>The blast at the BPS Co. chemical plant released a plume of highly toxic chemicals used in insecticides and forced the evacuation of hundreds of residents in the path of the poisonous cloud, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's bad. I don't know how much worse it's going to get. I'm not sure anybody knows right now,&quot; Arkansas State Police spokesman Wayne Jordan said.</p>
<p>The early afternoon explosion flattened a section of the plant and rocked this manufacturing and farming community located along the Mississippi River near the tri-state border with Tennessee and Mississippi, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;We understand the fire is now under control, but officials there are asking people to remain out of the area,&quot; Arkansas Office of Emergency Services spokeswoman Francis Huddleston said.</p>
<p>The explosion released azinphos-methyl, an insecticide that attacks the central nervous system and is used as a pesticide to control mites and other bugs, a hazardous materials expert said.</p>
<p>Brief exposures can generate symptoms ranging from breathing problems to paralysis. Longer exposures could cause permanent, degenerative damage to the central nervous system, University of Houston chemist James Cox said.</p>
<p>&quot;If I were exposed to it I would regard it as exceedingly hazardous,&quot; Cox said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LITTLE ROCK, Ark."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
