<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569410" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: General Sekiyu to export Okinawa refinery naphtha.</title>
<headline>General Sekiyu to export Okinawa refinery naphtha.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>General Sekiyu KK said on Wednesday it would start exporting to Asian countries its share of naphtha produced at a refinery in southern Japan, instead of selling the supplies in the domestic market.</p>
<p>General Sekiyu has an 87.5 percent stake in the 100,000 barrel-per-day Nansei Sekiyu refinery on Japan's southernmost island of Okinawa.</p>
<p>Okinawa is closer to South Korea, Taiwan and some of China's coastal cities than it is to most major cities in Japan.</p>
<p>&quot;The cheaper freight is behind the decision,&quot; a General Sekiyu spokesman said.</p>
<p>Trading house Sumitomo Corp has the remaining 12.5 percent interest in the Nansei Sekiyu plant.</p>
<p>General Sekiyu has already started selling naphtha from the Okinawa refinery to a few Asian firms including China's Shanghai Gas Co, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>The refiner, which exported only a small quantity of naphtha last year, plans to export its total share of Nansei Sekiyu's naphtha output, or 100,000 kilolitres, this year, he said.</p>
<p>Oil industry analysts said it would be the first time for a Japanese refiner to export naphtha on a regular basis.</p>
<p>Japanese refiners have third-party processing contracts with Asian countries, but have not exported naphtha under term contracts before, an industry source said.</p>
<p>Sumitomo Corp said it would continue selling its share of refined products in the domestic market.</p>
<p>General Sekiyu is owned 49 percent by Exxon Corp.</p>
<p>--Tokyo Energy Desk +81-3-3432-8837</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
