<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569455" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Kobe Steel sees 1999/2000 prnt curr prft Y40 bln.</title>
<headline>Kobe Steel sees 1999/2000 prnt curr prft Y40 bln.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kobe Steel Ltd said on Thursday that it expects to achieve a parent current profit of 40 billion yen in the fiscal year ending on March 31, 2000, on parent sales of 1.26 trillion yen.  </p>
<p>Kobe, one of Japan's top five steelmakers, also expects to achieve a group current profit of 110 billion yen that year on group sales of 2.53 trillion yen, a company spokesman told a news conference.</p>
<p>The firm also plans to cut its workforce by 1,400 to 12,200 by the end of that fiscal year, executive vice president Koshi Mizukoshi told the news conference.</p>
<p>The cuts would be achieved by natural attrition and by seconding more than 1,000 workers to affiliates, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We will continue our restructuring with the job cuts, but the pace of the reduction of job numbers is slowing as we cut 4,000 jobs in the past three years to the end of fiscal 1996/97,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Kobe also said it plans to reduce total costs by 30 billion yen in the three years to 1999/2000 through an increase in product yield and cuts in distribution and procurement costs.</p>
<p>Kobe plans to a total of 220 billion yen in capital investment in the three-year period, including spending for facilities related to development of new products.</p>
<p>Kobe earlier said in a statement it aimed to achieve annual parent current profits of 80 billion yen and group current profits of 150 billion yen, equivalent to five percent of sales, by early in the 21st century.</p>
<p>The company wants to achieve such projected profits by the year 2005/06, another Kobe spokesman said.</p>
<p>The company plans to achieve such profits in 2005/06 through an improvement in profitability, development of products meeting user needs, and cuts in overall costs.</p>
<p>By 2005/06, it plans to develop new products which can become part of its mainstay business with annual sales of over 300 billion yen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
