<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569418" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan central bank to keep money policy unchanged.</title>
<headline>Taiwan central bank to keep money policy unchanged.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan's central bank governor Sheu Yuan-dong said on Thursday it would maintain its longstanding stable-to-loose monetary policy.</p>
<p>&quot;The central bank will keep its stable-to-loose, but not too loose, monetary policy,&quot; Sheu told a news conference after the bank's board meeting.  </p>
<p>Sheu said the current monetary policy will enable the central bank to guide financial stability as well as economic growth.</p>
<p>&quot;The central bank will fully provide funds for normal economic activities and it will continue to mildly mop up liquidity if banking system's liquidity becomes too loose,&quot; Sheu said.  </p>
<p>Sheu said the central bank had no intention to interfere with the foreign exchange market.</p>
<p>&quot;The operation of the foreign exchange market is currently very sound. There are no unusual factors of interference,&quot; Sheu said.</p>
<p>&quot;The central bank will respect market forces and let the market's supply and demand determine the rate of the Taiwan dollar,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Taiwan dollar has fallen recently after the murder of a famous actress's daughter triggered mass protests which dealers feared may lead to foreign funds outflow.  </p>
<p>The murder also has led to calls for a cabinet reshuffle and even the resignation of Premier Lien Chan. President lee Teng-hui has declined Lien's resignation offer but has asked Lien to launch a partial reshuffle of the cabinet.</p>
<p>Ma Ying-jeou, a minister without portfolio and one of the most popular members of the ruling Nationalist Party, said on Thursday he would resign due to &quot;change of political ethics, obstacles in reforms and growing public discontent.&quot;</p>
<p>Sheu, however, said the recent political developments had not impacted the financial sphere.  </p>
<p>&quot;The recent political events have not had an influence on the financial markets,&quot; Sheu said.</p>
<p>Sheu added that the central bank would not formulate its monetary policy based solely on stock market performance.</p>
<p>&quot;The stock market is only one part of the financial market. What we are concerned about is overall financial stability and economic growth,&quot; Sheu said.</p>
<p>Private analysts had said that the recent torrential trade volumes registered in the stock market may prompt the central bank to launch tightening measures to curb liquidity.</p>
<p>-- Taipei Newsroom (5080815)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E121">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
