<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569488" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Northrop and Lockheed team up for Joint Fighter bid.</title>
<headline>Northrop and Lockheed team up for Joint Fighter bid.</headline>
<byline>Mark Egan</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Aerospace giant Lockheed Martin Corp. said Thursday it has added Northrop Grumman Corp. to its team to develop the next generation of fighter jets.</p>
<p>Lockheed said in a statement that Northrop will improve its chances of winning the Joint Strike Fighter contest against Boeing Co.</p>
<p>&quot;Each of our companies has gained a lot of proven experience&quot; with stealth warplanes, which will give Lockeed and Northrop a strong chance of winning the competition, said Lockheed Martin Tactical Aircraft Systems President Dain Hancock.</p>
<p>The companies said details about exactly what work Northrop would do for the effort were being worked out.</p>
<p>In November, Lockheed and Boeing won contracts worth $718.8 million and $661.8 million, respectively, to develop prototypes for the Joint Strike Fighter, which will be used by both the United States and Britain. The winner will be chosen in 2001 and will build 3,000 fighter jets.</p>
<p>Los Angeles-based Northrop was part of a third team led by McDonnell Douglas Corp. that lost out to Bethesda, Md.-based Lockheed and Boeing of Seattle to develop the prototypes. The loss was a severe blow for McDonnell and was seen as a precursor to its proposed merger with Boeing.</p>
<p>Northrop was expected to approach either Lockheed or Boeing in an attempt to take part in the lucrative contract, which is seen as the last mega-contract of the century.</p>
<p>Industry experts estimated the Joint Strike Fighter contract could be worth as much as $170 billion. Aerospace companies have said it could be worth multiples of that amount when spare parts and services are factored in.</p>
<p>&quot;It certainly is important to be on one of the few major programmes left. It all depends on whether (Northrop) picked the right horse,&quot; said Paul Nisbet, defence analyst at stock research firm JSA Research. &quot;I suspect that Lockheed Martin needed Northrop more than Boeing did, given that Boeing obtained McDonnell Douglas by virtue of the proposed merger.&quot;</p>
<p>Northrop has a lot of experience working with McDonnell Douglas on the F-18 fighter jet as well as on the initial Joint Strike Fighter bid. Northrop is also maker of the famed B-2 stealth bomber, complementing Lockheed's F-117 stealth aircraft.</p>
<p>The two companies have teamed up together in the past on Airborne early Warning and Control Systems (AWACS) radar, the C-130 Hercules military transport plane, the P-3 Orion aircraft and other programmes.</p>
<p>British Aerospace Plc which was also part of the losing McDonnell Douglas team, is expected to align itself with either the Boeing or Lockheed teams.</p>
<p>While Boeing is the world's largest producer of commercial aircraft, it has not built a fighter since World War II, and was considered the underdog in the competition by many.</p>
<p>Since November, Boeing has improved its position by closing the acquisition of the aerospace and defence assets of Rockwell International Corp. and agreeing to merge with McDonnell Douglas..</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640047">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C331">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
