<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569428" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Key suspect confesses all in Vietnam drugs trial.</title>
<headline>Key suspect confesses all in Vietnam drugs trial.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A key defendant at a high-profile drugs trial in Vietnam pleaded guilty on Thursday and blamed a state official for his earlier not-guilty plea, Voice of Vietnam radio said.</p>
<p>Dao Xuan Xe, a driver accused with 21 police officers, border guards and others, retracted a denial that he had received 60 cakes of heroin from a Laotian national, state radio said on the sixth day of the trial.</p>
<p>Xe named an official in the Interior Ministry's Economic Police Department who, he alleged, told him to deny all charges levelled against him in the Hanoi People's Court.</p>
<p>He also said that fellow defendant Vu Xuan Truong, a former captain in the ministry's anti-crime unit, brought a batch of heroin back to Hanoi after a ceremony to mark the 40th anniversary of the 1954 rout of French forces near the border with Laos.</p>
<p>Truong is accused of playing a key role in the syndicate, which is believed to have flooded the country with more than 300 kg (660 pounds) of heroin from Thailand, Laos and Burma over several years.</p>
<p>Truong has admitted his involvement in the ring and said he expects to face the firing squad.</p>
<p>He has offered to name some &quot;very important people&quot; during the hearing in return for the lives of his wife and brother -- who are also on trial -- being spared.</p>
<p>Newspaper reports about the closed-door trial said Truong had twice tried to commit suicide by dashing his head, first against the wall of a prison cell and then against the corner of a water tank as he was being led from the court back to jail.</p>
<p>He was reported to have become very weak, unable to stand during Wednesday's proceedings and whispered his testimony to the court.</p>
<p>Newspapers said Xe had also tried to kill himself by ramming the handle of a toothbrush into his ear.</p>
<p>Two police captains and a lieutenant-colonel, all of them from the border province of Lai Chau, have been arrested in connection with the drugs ring in the past week.</p>
<p>At least 18 other people, against whom evidence is still being compiled, are expected to stand trial at a later date.</p>
<p>The court's presiding judge has said that more than 10 of the 22 currently on trial may be sentenced to death when the trial ends early next week.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BURMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LAOS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
