<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569495" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Exel to acquire GCR for $637 million.</title>
<headline>Exel to acquire GCR for $637 million.</headline>
<byline>Jeff Mamera</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Exel Ltd. said Thursday it agreed to acquire the publicly held shares of reinsurer GCR Holdings Ltd. that it does not already own for about $637 million, or $27 a share in cash.</p>
<p>The deal, the latest in the industry, came a day after life insurer Unitrin Inc. said it would buy Reliable Life Insurance Co..</p>
<p>&quot;The entire industry is in the midst of a consolidation,&quot; said Cathy Seifert, an analyst at the S&amp;P Equity Group. &quot;I think if you look at the list of insurance companies out there a year from now, there will be fewer smaller insurance companies.&quot;</p>
<p>Exel said it will start a cash tender offer for the 23.6 million outstanding GCR shares no later than May 14. It now owns 1.2 million, or 4.9 percent, of GCR's 24.8 million shares outstanding.</p>
<p>The offer has been unanimously approved by both companies' boards directors and is subject to the tender of at least 75 percent of GCR's shares.</p>
<p>Exel said the merger of the two companies should boost 1997 earnings and increase shareholder value.</p>
<p>GCR's stock shot up $4.875 to $27.25 on Nasdaq. Exel rose $3.75 to $43.375 on the New York Stock Exchange, indicating that investors thought the company got a bargain.</p>
<p>&quot;I liked what I saw,&quot; said Merrill Lynch analyst Jay Cohen. He upgraded Exel from &quot;accumulate&quot; to &quot;buy&quot; and raised his 12-month price target for the stock to $51 to $53.</p>
<p>Analysts expect Exel to make further acquisitions as the deal leaves it with about $250 million in excess capital in a rapidly consolidating insurance industry.</p>
<p>&quot;After the deal we'll still have enough capital to do an acquisition or a buyback,&quot; said EXEL spokesman Gavin Arton. &quot;But it will slow our buyback plan for this year, and we certainly wouldn't do a buyback in the next few months.&quot;</p>
<p>Arton said Exel would consider a company that provides risk-management products, such as currency risk coverage. But so far, &quot;there's nothing we've targeted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Exel, based in Bermuda, is a leading provider of general liability, directors' and officers' liability, employment practices and professional liability, excess property insurance and reinsurance worldwide.</p>
<p>GCR, also based in Bermuda, provides property, marine, energy, satellite and financial products reinsurance worldwide through its Global Capital Reinsurance Ltd. subsidiary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BERM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8200318">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
