<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569406" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan steps up warning against dollar buying.</title>
<headline>Japan steps up warning against dollar buying.</headline>
<byline>Yoshiko Mori</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's powerful Ministry of Finance (MOF) stepped up a warning against dollar buying by institutional and individual investors on Thursday in an apparent bid to rein in the strength of the dollar against the yen.</p>
<p>&quot;Japanese monetary authorities are stepping up warnings against dollar purchases that could otherwise escalate,&quot; said Takeshi Hanai, executive manager of the Industrial Bank of Japan Ltd's International Treasury Department.</p>
<p>The dollar lost nearly two yen in late Tokyo trading on Thursday amid panicky selling triggered by a senior MOF official's remark that the yen could strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar.</p>
<p>The market has been extremely sensitive to warnings that could be followed by dollar-selling intervention by the Bank of Japan (BOJ), because fundamental variables are in favour of a stronger yen, traders said.</p>
<p>IBJ's Hanai said: &quot;A rising trend in Japan's current account surplus and strong Tokyo stocks and weak bonds on the back of the economic recovery all promise success if the BOJ were to intervene to sell dollars.&quot;</p>
<p>The BOJ has so far steered clear of actual dollar sales, but the Finance Minister Hiroshi Mitsuzuka has reiterated that Tokyo is ready to &quot;decisively&quot; deal with excessive foreign exchange movements.</p>
<p>Eisuke Sakakibara, director-general of MOF's International Finance Bureau, said on Thursday: &quot;Looking at currency fluctuations in the past 10 years, (the dollar/yen rate) moved at an annual average of 23 yen per dollar. This year, the yen weakened up to 127.50 yen to the dollar. If you subtract 23 yen, it is theoretically possible for the yen to strengthen to about 103 yen.&quot;</p>
<p>His remark knocked the dollar down to a low of 123.42 yen in late Tokyo trading from its early peak of 125.36 yen.</p>
<p>Soon afterwards, Vice Finance Minister Tadashi Ogawa said Sakakibara's remark was not a forecast of foreign exchange movements. Sakakibara himself also said later there was no specific intent in his remarks.</p>
<p>The dollar made up some losses after the denials but was still drifting lower at below 124 yen in late Tokyo dealings.</p>
<p>Sakakibara said he was worried that individual Japanese investors were putting a lot of funds into foreign bonds and foreign currency deposits without taking into account the currency risk.</p>
<p>Industry sources estimated about 500 billion yen ($4 billion) worth of foreign bonds were bought by individual Japanese investors in April, and they expected this pace to continue or even pick up speed in the months ahead.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, a local news agency quoted an international monetary source as saying Japan, the United States and Germany are exploring the possibility of joint intervention in the foreign exchange markets to sell dollars for yen.</p>
<p>The move follows an accord reached in Washington last week by the Group of Seven (G7) industrialised nations, it said.</p>
<p>In a statement, the G7 emphasised the importance of avoiding exchange rates that could lead to the reemergence of large external imbalances.</p>
<p>U.S. Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin also appears to be joining the move to curb the dollar's strength against the yen.</p>
<p>Rubin has been reiterating that he agreed with Japan's recently expressed concern about the weakness of the yen.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, others were cool towards monetary authorities' verbal warnings against a further dollar rally against the yen.</p>
<p>&quot;Authorities were creating quite disruptive conditions in the currency market by referring to a specific dollar level,&quot; said a senior trader at a major U.S. bank.</p>
<p>&quot;Only major players are benefiting from such erratic forex moves, while individual foreign bond investors are penalised for no good reason,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Japanese investors' foreign bond investments were prompted by extremely low yen interest rates that could not be justified by current Japanese economic fundamentals, he said.</p>
<p>($1=124)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
