<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569440" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan to act on excess forex moves - Sakakibara.</title>
<headline>Japan to act on excess forex moves - Sakakibara.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan will deal decisively with excessive movements in the currency markets if needed, senior Ministry of Finance (MOF) official Eisuke Sakakibara said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;An excessive rise or fall in the yen are both undesirable,&quot; said Sakakibara, director-general of the ministry's International Finance Bureau.</p>
<p>Asked about his remarks earlier in the day on the dollar/yen exchange rate at a parliamentary committee meeting, he said his remarks contained no specific intent regarding the dollar/yen rate.  </p>
<p>&quot;What I wanted to say was that Japanese individual investors should adequately take into account foreign exchange risks when they invest their money overseas,&quot; he told reporters at his ministry.  </p>
<p>Sakakibara had told the parliamentary committee it is possible the yen could strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar.</p>
<p>&quot;Looking at currency fluctuations in the past 10 years, (the dollar/yen rate) moved at an annual average of 23 yen per dollar. This year, the yen weakened up to 127.50 yen to the dollar. If you subtract 23 yen, it is theoretically possible for the yen to strengthen to about 103 yen,&quot; he told the committee.</p>
<p>The dollar, which had been trading around 124.70 yen, dropped more than a yen after Sakakibara's comments.</p>
<p>The dollar was trading near 123.90 yen at 0915 GMT.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
