<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569464" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Cyprus Airways pilots suspend action.</title>
<headline>Cyprus Airways pilots suspend action.</headline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pilots of national carrier Cyprus Airways on Thursday backed down in a labour dispute with management which had prompted the government to warn it could withhold a guarantee for a loan sought by the airline.</p>
<p>Pilots union PASIPI said late on Thursday it was suspending work-to-rule measures adopted to protest over the transfer of work from Cyprus Airways to Eurocypria, its charter subsidiary.</p>
<p>On Monday a pilot sticking to the union guidelines landed a plane from Zurich with 153 passengers at the wrong airport on the holiday island, refusing to fly an extra 10 minutes to the proper destination.</p>
<p>The incident prompted a warning from Finance Minister Christodoulos Christodoulou that the government may decide to withhold its guarantee to a $30 million loan the company is due to seek later this year.</p>
<p>The loan is designed to replace an existing short-term loan and to carry out maintenance checks on the Cyprus Airways fleet, company officials said.</p>
<p>At the end of 1996, Cyprus Airways had outstanding loans of about 100 million pounds ($193 million).</p>
<p>Last week the Cyprus Airways group announced a preliminary consolidated pre-tax loss of 2.15 million pounds ($4.2 million) in 1996, compared to a pre-tax profit of 5.03 million pounds in 1995. The company has blamed falling load factors and increased fuel prices for the decline.</p>
<p>The situation in the airline is due to be discussed at the weekly cabinet meeting next week.</p>
<p>($=0.516 pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
