<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569443" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: MOF says may simplify Eurobond identification plan.</title>
<headline>MOF says may simplify Eurobond identification plan.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Ministry of Finance (MOF) is to simplify a proposal that would require investors in foreign bonds, such as Euroyen bonds, issued by Japanese firms to be identified, a senior MOF official said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are planning to ease the identification plan a great deal if the issuer can clearly state that the bonds are only for foreigners,&quot; the official at MOF's Tax Bureau told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;If the issuer states that in a bond sales contract, then the identification requirement will be kept to a minimum and buyers will not be required to give their names,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Otherwise, buyers will be required to provide their names and addresses to prove that they are non-Japanese residents in order to be exempt from paying withholding taxes on income gains made from such bond investments, the official said.</p>
<p>In October, MOF announced that it would scrap the current tax exemption and introduce a rule that would require investors in foreign bonds issued by Japanese firms to identify themselves. MOF has since softened its stance amid strong opposition from various industry groups.</p>
<p>MOF wants to close a loophole which has allowed Japanese investors to avoid paying withholding taxes on income gains made from foreign bonds issued by Japanese firms. It hopes to introduce the identification rule at the start of April 1998.</p>
<p>A MOF study showed that about 70 to 80 percent of such bonds are held by Japanese investors.</p>
<p>The official said the ministry would keep in mind the special characteristics of the Swiss market, which adheres to a strict rule of confidentiality.</p>
<p>&quot;We are still in discussions with the Swiss government,&quot; the official said. &quot;The government said that it could not provide identification, but would take full responsibility to avoid any injustices. We believe the words of the government.&quot;</p>
<p>MOF is still waiting for the Swiss government's response.</p>
<p>MOF's Tax Bureau has submitted the plan to various domestic industry associations and other MOF and Trade Ministry departments, the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are asking them (the associations and ministries) to review the plan. So far, nobody is strongly opposed to the plan,&quot; the official said. &quot;We are planning to finalise the plan by the end of June.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-3-3432-8785</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
