<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569420" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LAOS: Laos predicts Thai power demand will fuel growth.</title>
<headline>Laos predicts Thai power demand will fuel growth.</headline>
<byline>Katya Robinson</byline>
<dateline>VIENTIANE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laos said on Thursday that Thailand should be able to absorb nearly all the power from several planned hydroelectric dams and the electricity sales would drive economic growth in the impoverished nation.</p>
<p>The prediction was made by the Laotian government as part of a consultation over the controversial $1.5 billion Nam Theun 2 (NT2) dam project on the Nakai Plateau, about 250 km east of Vientiane in central Laos.</p>
<p>&quot;Hydropower is one of the highest priorities for the Lao government,&quot; Vice Minister for Industry and Handicrafts Khammone Phonekeo told Reuters in an interview, adding that some 18 planned projects would account for most of the eight percent economic growth forecast for the small communist nation this year.</p>
<p>Laos' economy grew by 7.1 percent in fiscal 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;We are confident, we are sure that providing 3,000 megawatts by the year 2006...is only a small portion of Thai demand,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The government was forced to hold the consultations and conduct further studies on the dam's feasibility after the World Bank refused to provide $100 million in partial loan guarantees until it learned more about the dam's prospects.</p>
<p>The international consortium developing the dam, which would be the country's largest, has in turn refused to proceed without the guarantees.</p>
<p>Under a June 1996 agreement, the Electricity Generating Authority of Thailand (EGAT) agreed to purchase 3,000 megawatts from Laos by 2006.</p>
<p>Suntorn Jungpatanaprecha, an EGAT representative at the NT2 meeting, confirmed the 3,000 megawatts were part of Thailand's power development plan but did not say whether the 900-megawatt Nam Theun 2 would be one of the suppliers.</p>
<p>Phonekeo said the EGAT would negotiate to buy power from the planned NT2 in the next several months.</p>
<p>Engelbertus Oud, project manager of a study of the regional power market, said he was bullish on the dam's prospects and on Thai energy demand despite Thailand's recent economic slump and plans to conserve electricity.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no doubt whatsoever that the absorptive capacity of Thailand is more than sufficient,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But even Phonekeo conceded there were problems with reliance on one country's market.</p>
<p>&quot;If Thailand can generate electricity in a more economical way than NT2, then NT2 is not in a position to survive,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Nam Theun II Electricity Consortium (NTEC) which is developing the project includes Australia's Transfield Corp, Electricite de France, Italian-Thai Development, Thailand's Jasmine International and Phatra Thanakit</p>
<p>Those fighting World Bank support claim the dam will harm an adjacent conservation area and displace communities and wildlife in a 450-square-km area to be flooded if the dam is built.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LAOS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1610107">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I5020011">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENTIANE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LAOS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
