<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569457" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. envoy in effort to revive Israel-PLO talks.</title>
<headline>U.S. envoy in effort to revive Israel-PLO talks.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Heller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Middle East envoy Dennis Ross held high-level talks on Thursday in Gaza and Jerusalem on reviving Israel-PLO peace negotiations but appeared to make little headway in his rescue mission.</p>
<p>The issue that plunged the peace process into crisis, Jewish settlement on land claimed by the Palestinians, took centre stage as settlers occupied a newly acquired house in Arab East Jerusalem in a move coinciding with Ross's visit.</p>
<p>Making his second trip to the region in a month, Ross met Palestinian President Yasser Arafat in Gaza and later held talks in Jerusalem with Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.</p>
<p>&quot;I cannot tell you that I am optimistic,&quot; Netanyahu said to reporters before meeting the envoy.</p>
<p>Asked on Israel Television if a resumption of the peace talks was in the offing, Netanyahu's cabinet secretary, Danny Naveh, told Israel Television: &quot;I am sorry to say I still cannot say that is so.&quot;</p>
<p>In a brief statement after Netanyahu and Ross met, the Prime Minister's Office said the U.S. envoy &quot;reported on his meeting with Arafat and will continue to move between the sides in order to continue the process of clarifying positions. Tomorrow (Friday), Ross will be with Arafat&quot;.</p>
<p>Israel demands Arafat crack down on &quot;terror&quot; before resuming talks, a move which Netanyahu told reporters &quot;would help the peace process&quot;. A Moslem militant blew up a Tel Aviv cafe in March, killing himself and three Israeli women.</p>
<p>Arafat spokesman Marwan Kanafani said the Palestinian leader stressed to Ross the need to stop all settlement activity before peace talks could resume. Netanyahu's aide David Bar-Illan said the work would continue.</p>
<p>&quot;There are difficult problems that have to be overcome but we all realise the importance of trying to find ways to move forward,&quot; Ross told reporters in Gaza after meeting Arafat. Ross said he would hold talks again with Arafat on Friday.</p>
<p>Israeli-PLO peace negotiations broke down two months ago after Netanyahu gave the final go-ahead to build 6,500 houses for Jews on a West Bank hilltop which Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East war.</p>
<p>Israeli and Palestinian officials have played down any expectation of a breakthrough during Ross's mission.</p>
<p>Palestinians have rejected Israel's offer to build housing for East Jerusalem Palestinians and to discuss speeding up talks on building a seaport and opening an airport in Gaza as part of a compromise to revive peace talks.</p>
<p>On Jerusalem's Mount of Olives on Thursday, Jewish settlers moved into a house acquired for a Jewish religious seminary from a church.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't negate the right of Arabs to live in Jerusalem but Jews have a right to live in all of the city,&quot; said Chaim Silberstein, the school's director. &quot;As a yeshiva (seminary) we are not political,&quot; he told Reuters at the house.</p>
<p>Palestinians, however, viewed the move as a purely political act to strengthen Jewish presence in the mostly Arab part of the city where the Palestinians hope to establish the capital of a future state.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a very dangerous provocation which will raise tensions and the chance and danger of a clash,&quot; said Ahmed Tibi, an aide to Arafat. &quot;It is an attempt to Judaise Arab East Jerusalem.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
