<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569425" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Canadian Mountie in Indonesia for Busang probe.</title>
<headline>Canadian Mountie in Indonesia for Busang probe.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP) arrived in Indonesia on Thursday to discuss investigations into the Busang gold fiasco with the government, a Canadian diplomat said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have an RCMP liaison officer accredited to Indonesia. He's based in Singapore, he's come in here now,&quot; diplomat Rene Cremonese said.</p>
<p>&quot;The idea will be he will have preliminary discussions with Indonesian authorities on the Bre-X issue,&quot; Cremonese said. &quot;There is no one coming in at the moment from Canada.&quot;</p>
<p>Brigadier-General Ahwil Luthan, secretary of Indonesia's National Central Bureau which handles investigations requiring Interpol assistance, said on Wednesday he would hold talks with the RCMP officer on Friday.</p>
<p>An independent report released on Sunday concluded the once-fabled Busang gold site in Indonesia's East Kalimantan province in Borneo, contained no gold worth mining and said data had been falsified on a massive and unprecedented scale.</p>
<p>The RCMP said in Alberta on Wednesday it had received two complaints of fraud concerning Busang, which was discovered by Canadian exploration company Bre-X Minerals Ltd. Bre-X is based in Calgary, Alberta.</p>
<p>In a letter to the RCMP, Bre-X chief executive David Walsh alleged a fraud had been perpetrated against his company, but he did not identify a suspect.</p>
<p>A second fraud complaint was filed by the Ontario Securities Commission (OSC), Canada's top securities regulator. The Ontario Securities Commission is conducting its own investigation of Bre-X for possible violations of insider trading and disclosure laws.</p>
<p>Luthan said his department had begun gathering evidence of possible commercial crime over Busang, which at one point was touted as one of the biggest gold finds this century.</p>
<p>&quot;We have asked for information from the Ministry of Mines and Energy and it is expected to come through the national police department,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are gathering evidence...from the death of the Filipino geologist (Michael de Guzman)...it starts from there.&quot;</p>
<p>De Guzman, chief geologist of Bre-X, fell to his death from a helicopter on his way to the Busang gold property in March.</p>
<p>One week after de Guzman's death, Bre-X's Busang partner Freeport McMoRan Copper and Gold Inc announced that its test drillings at the property showed &quot;insignificant&quot; amounts of gold.</p>
<p>An independent audit of Busang has since confirmed Freeport's findings. Consultant Strathcona Mineral Services Ltd said in its report that data on the Busang property had been falsified on a scale &quot;without precedent in mining history&quot;.</p>
<p>Bre-X held 45 percent of Busang, Freeport 15 percent and Indonesian interests the rest. The Indonesian government held a 10 percent stake and the Nusamba Group, linked to President Suharto, held 30 percent along with a local partner.</p>
<p>All the partners have now withdrawn from the Busang project.</p>
<p>Luthan said it was possible the RCMP officer would interview the local partners for more information about Busang, but added no final schedule had been drawn up.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
