<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569403" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thailand faces first budget deficit in decade.</title>
<headline>Thailand faces first budget deficit in decade.</headline>
<byline>Vithoon Amorn</byline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Economic woes have eroded the Thai government's traditionally strong fiscal position, but the first expected budget deficit in a decade is unlikely to trigger a collapse of fiscal discipline, analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>They said losses by battered Thai businesses were likely to cause a drop in tax revenues, leaving the government with a large budget deficit in fiscal 1996/1997 (October/September).</p>
<p>The Bank of Thailand said the government posted a 44.3 billion baht ($1.7 billion) operating budget deficit in the first half of this fiscal year against a 34.1 billion baht surplus during the same period last year.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Amnuay Viravan faces the dilemma of either cutting government expenditure further to help balance the budget or earning the dubious honour of presiding over the first budget deficit since the mid-1980s.</p>
<p>Analysts said Amnuay faced an uphill struggle in avoiding a deficit.</p>
<p>&quot;Excessive budget cuts would aggravate the economic slowdown at a time that our exports show no signs of picking up,&quot; said Suchit Bungbongkarn of Chulalongkorn University.</p>
<p>However, Supavat Saichua of Krungthai Thanakit Plc said Thailand's prudent fiscal and monetary management remained intact, adding that the government was saddled with a far smaller debt service burden than the private sector.</p>
<p>He said the Thai public sector accounted for less than 20 percent of the country's nearly $100 billion foreign debt with the rest being borrowed by the private sector.</p>
<p>&quot;Under the present bearish environment, issues like a possible budget deficit can easily be overblown,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Amnuay on Wednesday cautioned against any further budget cuts that would put more pressure on an already sharply slowing economy. Private economists have forecast the economy will grow this year at its slowest pace since 1986.</p>
<p>Some analysts expect gross domestic product to expand only five percent this year, against the central bank's targeted 6.8 percent and actual growth of 6.7 percent in 1996.</p>
<p>Amnuay in March won cabinet approval to slash the current year's 984 billion baht budget by 59 billion and to shelve another 47 billion baht of state enterprise projects to help curb the current account deficit.</p>
<p>He said on Wednesday that Thailand's policy of adopting balanced, deficit-free budgets should not be sustained at the risk of jeopardising economic stability.</p>
<p>After tax revenue from October to March fell about 50 billion baht below target, Finance Ministry sources estimated that total 1996/1997 revenue could end up 72 billion baht short.</p>
<p>Charl Kengchon, chief analyst at Thai Farmers Research Center Co Ltd, urged the government to convince investors that it would remain financially disciplined even though it could do little to avoid a budget deficit this year.</p>
<p>He said the government should clarify that it had delayed low-priority spending, especially proposed purchases of military hardware by the armed forces.</p>
<p>Kengchon said any increase in tax revenue would largely hinge on a recovery in sluggish exports, which fell 0.2 percent year-on-year in the first quarter against 7.2 percent growth a year ago.</p>
<p>The central bank forecast earlier that exports for the whole of 1997 would rise 7.7 percent, while the Commerce Ministry set a 10 percent growth target.</p>
<p>(US$1 = 26 baht)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
