<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569407" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Vietnam adopts trade law to prepare for WTO.</title>
<headline>Vietnam adopts trade law to prepare for WTO.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Vietnam's National Assembly has adopted a trade law designed to prepare the communist country for membership of the World Trade Organisation (WTO), official media reports said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Vietnam News Agency said the legislation, along with two new laws on corporate tax and value added tax, would help the business community's regional and international integration.</p>
<p>The law, Vietnam's first on trade, will come into effect on January 1, 1998.</p>
<p>Vietnam initiated the formal process for entry into the WTO in early 1995, soon after the organisation was set up to replace the Generalised Agreement of Tariffs and Trade (GATT).</p>
<p>The government has vowed to liberalise its trade regime as part of a drive to reform the economy along market lines.</p>
<p>It has set up an office to work on meeting the Association of Southeast Asian Nations' Free Trade Area (AFTA) goal of reducing tariffs on thousands of goods to between zero and five percent.</p>
<p>The target date for AFTA to come into effect is 2003, but Vietnam has been granted a special three-year grace period to become full integrated.</p>
<p>Although the new legislation enshrines the right of equality before the law, it also maintains advantages for Vietnamese entities bidding for contracts.</p>
<p>The daily Vietnam News said the draft committee agreed that if foreign bidders for a tender made equal bids and had equal qualifications, those that sub-contracted Vietnamese companies would be awarded the contract.</p>
<p>&quot;However, Vietnamese bidders should be given first priority in winning the bid if both foreign and Vietnamese bidders have the same qualifications,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Separately, a finance ministry official said new regulations were being drafted to stamp out rampant smuggling of consumer goods such as bicycles, alcohol, televisions and video recorders.</p>
<p>He said that if the regulations were approved, certain consumer items would be deemed illegally imported if they did not carry a special customs stamp.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
