<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569442" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore leaders await ruling on huge libel claims.</title>
<headline>Singapore leaders await ruling on huge libel claims.</headline>
<byline>Nick Edwards</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Arguments ended on Thursday in libel cases brought by Singapore Prime Minister Goh Chok Tong and other top members of the ruling party in which they are seeking huge damages from an opposition politician.</p>
<p>Justice Chao Hick Tin, sitting without a jury, gave no indication when he would rule on the demands of the People's Action Party (PAP) leadership for a record S$12.9 million (US$8.9 million) in damages against Tang Liang Hong.</p>
<p>Chao said he would give a written verdict &quot;in due course&quot; on cases 11 PAP leaders brought against Tang for calling them liars over election campaign charges that he was an &quot;anti-Christian Chinese chauvinist&quot; who endangered racial harmony.</p>
<p>Tang fled Singapore after losing in January elections, saying he had received death threats. The libel cases were awarded against Tang in March after he failed to return to defend himself.</p>
<p>Goh is claiming S$2.15 million in damages from the man he said tried to destroy his honour and integrity.</p>
<p>Senior Minister Lee Kuan Yew, Singapore's founding father and prime minister for three decades until stepping aside for Goh in 1990, has demanded S$3.35 million.</p>
<p>The other PAP leaders have also demanded hefty sums. They have all asked for &quot;aggravated&quot; damages because Tang has continued to attack them through the media from his refuge just across the border in Malaysia.</p>
<p>Tang's final bill could be much higher than the S$12.9 million demanded in damages if Justice Chao were to award legal costs against him.</p>
<p>It could also be higher if Chao accepted a recommendation from the lawyers of the PAP leaders that he should award &quot;exemplary&quot; damages, normally given when a defendant is deemed to have won more financially than he might pay in damages.</p>
<p>There has been no suggestion Tang gained financially from his legal battle with Singapore's leaders, but Goh's lawyer K. Shanmugam charged that Tang did intend to profit from his remarks, &quot;perhaps not in a pecuniary sense, but politically&quot;.</p>
<p>Shanmugam also argued exemplary damages should be awarded as Tang had continued to aggravate the libel in media interviews.</p>
<p>Tang had done so again by attempting overnight to get a 60-page affidavit containing allegations about Lee Kuan Yew admitted into evidence, the lawyer told the court on Thursday.</p>
<p>The affidavit had been the source of a dispute between Tang and his former lawyers who were scared to file it, Shanmugam said.</p>
<p>Tang sent the document to Chao and Lee 's lawyer Davinder Singh late on Wednesday and asked for it to be admitted into evidence.</p>
<p>Singh said the affidavit contained &quot;scurrillous allegations&quot; about Lee and charged that Tang was trying to make it a court document which could then be released to the public.</p>
<p>&quot;We have no doubt that it is Mr Tang's intention to distribute and publish the scandalous allegations in this affidavit,&quot; Singh said. He asked for it to be &quot;expunged and destroyed&quot;.</p>
<p>Singh gave scant detail of the affidavit, other than to say it contained allegations about the Singapore police, Inland Revenue and Immigration departments.</p>
<p>Chao ruled that the affidavit would not be admitted in evidence, that all copies of it should be seized and destroyed, and that Tang could not show it to anyone or repeat its allegations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
