<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569482" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Solidere shares hit 16-month high.</title>
<headline>Solidere shares hit 16-month high.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Solidere shares hit their highest level in more than a year on Thursday and brokers said expectations of a dividend declaration on May 27 were helping to stimulate demand.</p>
<p>Solidere A rose to $11.75 from Monday's $11.5 and B rose to $12 from $11.5 amid heavy demand totalling 735,275 shares.</p>
<p>Brokers said the prices were the highest since January 1996 when Solidere, Lebanon's biggest company, still traded its shares on the private Beirut Secondary Market.</p>
<p>It switched to the Beirut Stock Exchange last September and the private market no longer operates.</p>
<p>&quot;Demand for Solidere shares seems to be a trend preceding the distribution of dividends before the end of May and that is raising the price,&quot; Tania Hajj, a broker for Arab Finance Corporation told Reuters.</p>
<p>The rise of the shares on the Beirut market also follows a 50 percent surge last week in the price of Solidere's GDRs SOLAq.L on the London Stock Exchange attributed to purchases by U.S. and European emerging markets funds.</p>
<p>The Solidere rise helped the LISPI and BLOM general indices rise 1.18 percent and 2.45 percent to 88.64 and 1013.19 respectively.</p>
<p>The LIBX bank index also rose 1.08 percent to 139.75.</p>
<p>Bank of Beirut rose to $3.5625 from $3.5 and Banque Libanaise pour le Commerce rose to $17.25 from $17, bringing its rise since listing last December to 53 percent.</p>
<p>Banque Audi was steady at $20.125.</p>
<p>Among the four industrial shares only Eternit rose, reaching $1.9375 from $1.875. Ciments Libanais was steady at $1.2812 and there was no trade in Ciments Blancs and Uniceramic  UNIN.BY.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
