<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569481" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turk shares fall on renewed political worries.</title>
<headline>Turk shares fall on renewed political worries.</headline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Istanbul shares posted losses in afternoon selling on Thursday amid renewed political concerns over the fate of the Islamist-led coalition government, brokers said.</p>
<p>The IMKB National-100 closed 19 points, or 1.29 percent lower at 1,459 after soaring 6.2 percent in a strong correction in the past two days. It was up 0.27 percent at the end of the first session.</p>
<p>Daily trade volume fell to 14.84 trillion lira from 19.20 trillion on Wednesday.  </p>
<p>&quot;Yalim Erez's statements negatively affected the market in the afternoon session,&quot; said Erden Gokay from Taksim securities.</p>
<p>Former minister Yalim Erez said on Thursday he was confident of forming an alliance with other secularist politicians to oust Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan's Islamist-led government.</p>
<p>&quot;What is important is that I have no more worries about the formation of an alternative government,&quot; Yalim Erez, from the True Path Party, the conservative coalition partner, told reporters after meeting opposition leaders.</p>
<p>Erez has been trying to drum up support for a secularist pact since he resigned as trade and industry minister last month over the government's reluctance to comply with army demands for a crackdown on Islamist activism.</p>
<p>&quot;The market cannot get out of the sideways movement because of politics. There is support at 1,420, I do not expect sharp movements. there will be share-based activity,&quot; said Neslihan Kacamak from Bab securities.</p>
<p>The index recovered 6.2 percent in the last two days after plunging 9.1 percent in eight trade days amid concerns over the fate of the Islamist-led coalition government after the market opened on April 24 following a 6-1/2 day holiday.</p>
<p>Of the 248 shares traded, falls outdid rises by 150 to 51 and 47 closed unchanged. The IMKB Industrial  dropped 1.64 percent to 1,441, the IMKB Services firmed 0.45 percent to 1,325 and the IMKB Financial  eased 1.17 percent to 1,600.</p>
<p>Actives were led by utility Kepez Elektrik, down 2,500 lira at 170,000, steel rope producer Celik Halat, steady at 8,300 lira, and largely state owned flat steel maker Eregli, down 1,000 lira at 14,500. They made up 15.2 percent of the total turnover.</p>
<p>-- Aydan Eksin, Istanbul newsroom +90-212-2750875</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
