<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569444" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan urges Kabila to avoid Zaire bloodshed.</title>
<headline>Japan urges Kabila to avoid Zaire bloodshed.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan has appealed to Zairean rebel leader Laurent Kabila to avoid bloodshed in his struggle with ailing President Mobutu Sese Seko over control of the African country, a senior Japanese Foreign Ministry official said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Ryuichi Shoji, director of the ministry's Africa division, said he met Kabila last week in Goma and urged him to avoid violence in Zaire's capital of Kinshasa.</p>
<p>It was the first formal contact by the Japanese government with the rebel leader.</p>
<p>Japan heavily depends on Zaire for cobalt supplies, importing about 1,500 tonnes last year.</p>
<p>World cobalt prices have risen since early this year, due to the civil war in Zaire.</p>
<p>Mobutu's hold on power has been almost broken by the advance of Kabila's rebels, who control about three-quarters of mineral-rich Zaire after seven months of fighting.</p>
<p>Mobutu, who has dominated mineral-rich Zaire for more than 30 years, is now in the Gabonese capital of Libreville for a mini-summit with other African leaders.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to admit that Kabila is now a key player in Zaire, but his ability as a policy-maker is still unknown,&quot; Shoji told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Therefore, we told him (Kabila) that the international community is monitoring with great interest what's going to happen in Kinshasa, and his credibility is at stake.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
