<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569458" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Iran cleric defends rejection of election hopefuls.</title>
<headline>Iran cleric defends rejection of election hopefuls.</headline>
<byline>Firouz Sedarat</byline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior Iranian cleric on Thursday defended an Islamic screening body's decision to allow only four of more than 200 would-be candidates to run in Iran's presidential election on May 23.</p>
<p>Ayatollah Ahmad Jannati, secretary of the Guardian Council, said the body ruled on political and legal grounds to disqualify all but four of 238 who signed up to stand in the election to replace President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani, Tehran radio said.</p>
<p>&quot;Some of them had Marxist views or political problems such as having belonged to anti-revolutionary groups or backing groups fighting the government,&quot; Jannati was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>He said some had only elementary education or were barely literate while others had higher education but were disqualified because they were not prominent political or religious personalities as required by Iran's laws, the radio said.</p>
<p>The council, a body of clerics and lawyers, on Wednesday named the four as Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri, who is parliamentary speaker, Mohammad Mohammadi Reyshahri, a former intelligence minister, Mohammad Khatami, a former minister of culture and Islamic guidance, and Reza Zavarei, deputy head of judiciary.</p>
<p>All four are Shi'ite Moslems and only Zavarei is not a clergyman.</p>
<p>The council screened the contenders for their allegiance to Iran's Islamic system of government and &quot;absolute obedience&quot; to the Iranian supreme spiritual leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.</p>
<p>Those rejected included nine women who had sought a legal ruling on women's right to run for president for the first time.</p>
<p>In the last presidential polls in 1993, four out of 128 who signed up were approved by the powerful council.</p>
<p>Campaigning officially starts on Saturday. But supporters of Nateq-Nouri and Khatami, who appear to be front-runners, have been waging a war of words over which of them has the best Islamic qualifications. Each side has accused the other of receiving free publicity from state-run media.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri, who is close to Iran's traditional bazaar merchants, is backed by key clerical groups and by the majority conservative faction in the parliament.</p>
<p>Khatami draws support from a coalition of pro-Rafsanjani centrists and Islamist left-wingers who have moderated many of their views in recent years.</p>
<p>Two Iranian members of parliament predicted in remarks published on Thursday that the election would go to a run-off, after a close race in which no candidate would obtain an absolute majority of votes.</p>
<p>A survey published on Wednesday showed Nateq-Nouri in the lead with 40.8 percent of popular support among a sample of 1,182 Tehran residents, with 33.8 percent for Khatami and 8.2 percent for Reyshahri.</p>
<p>Rafsanjani must stand down in August after two four-year terms as president but is expected to continue to wield considerable influence in state affairs as head of a powerful body that will draw up government policies and advise Khamenei.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UAE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
