<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569433" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan stock options to focus attention on profits.</title>
<headline>Japan stock options to focus attention on profits.</headline>
<byline>Linda Sieg</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan on Thursday took a key step towards allowing companies to offer stock options as incentives to employees and executives, a move analysts say could help refocus management attention on share price and profits.</p>
<p>But few forecast any big impact soon from the change, which perhaps ironically comes as huge executive pay packages with hefty doses of stock options are under fire overseas.</p>
<p>&quot;Generally, this is probably good news for shares. Almost invariably, it is very good for profits because companies try very hard to make profits as big as possible,&quot; said Pelham Smithers, a strategist at ING Baring Securities.</p>
<p>Stock options, popular in the United States and Europe, are currently permitted only at venture companies under Japan's Commercial Code. Some larger firms such as Sony Corp have got around the restrictions by issuing warrant bonds, buying back the warrants and allotting them to executives.</p>
<p>On Thursday, parliament's Lower House passed a revision to the Commercial Code allowing firms to buy back up to 10 percent of their own shares to be used for stock option schemes for employees and executives. Stock options are the right to buy the shares at a set price within a certain period.</p>
<p>The bill will take effect from June 1 if, as expected, it is passed by the Upper House next week.</p>
<p>Corporate Japan has been keen to see the rule relaxed to allow greater flexibility to link pay with performance.</p>
<p>&quot;Firms want to introduce stock option schemes so they can provide incentives to directors and employees to rebuild their companies,&quot; said Kenjiro Egashima, a University of Tokyo professor who specialises in commercial law.</p>
<p>Traditional Japanese compensation schemes tied to seniority have done little to reward corporate high-flyers and hence, critics say, provided scant incentive to outperform the pack.</p>
<p>Such pay practices have come to be viewed as flawed given pressure on Japanese firms to boost global competitiveness.</p>
<p>&quot;How do you compensate a Bill Gates in Japan? At the moment there is no carrot to wave in from of him,&quot; said Jesper Koll, chief economist at JP Morgan in Tokyo. &quot;Japan needs super-stars, performers who can pull up the average.&quot;</p>
<p>How quickly companies will move to adopt stock option plans remains to be seen, but some have already said they might.</p>
<p>Daiwa Securities Co Ltd said earlier this week that it was considering the step positively, while a Toyota Motor Corp spokesman said on Thursday that the top carmaker was also studying the matter.</p>
<p>&quot;If companies take it up, it should mean that management becomes more interested in share price,&quot; said Jason James, a strategist at HSCB James Capel.</p>
<p>Enormous U.S. executive compensation packages based on stock options have come under attack for widening the pay gap between employees and their bosses and for potentional damage to shareholders' interests by diluting their investment.</p>
<p>&quot;Compensation inflation is running riot in many corner offices of Corporate America,&quot; said a recent editorial in Business Week magazine. &quot;This has simply got to stop.&quot;</p>
<p>Japanese firms, however, are unlikely to introduce any time soon schemes on the scale which have generated outrage overseas.</p>
<p>&quot;Japan is starting from basically a situation where there is equality of compensation and they want to create opportunities for incentive-based pay,&quot; Koll said. &quot;Worries about a gap between rich and poor are completely overblown.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
