<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569456" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asian trade sees aluminium up on falling stocks.</title>
<headline>Asian trade sees aluminium up on falling stocks.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Far East base metal traders said three-month aluminium prices on the London Metal Exchange (LME) were expected to rise later on Thursday due to expectations that stocks will fall further.</p>
<p>Three-month aluminium was quoted at US$1,656/60 a tonne at 0560 GMT, compared with the close on the LME on Wednesday of $1,654/59 a tonne. Asian trade remained thin, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;A very bullish close and further gains are expected in the near term. Next resistance is seen at $1,670 and then $1,680,&quot; LME brokers Brandeis said in its daily review.  </p>
<p>LME aluminium stocks reached 785,925 tonnes on Wednesday, down nearly 54,000 tonnes from the level of 839,850 tonnes early last month.</p>
<p>Borrowing of nearby dates resulted in the cash/threes spread narrowing to $23/$25 by the end of Wednesday's LME kerb, against a $29 contango on the previous day.</p>
<p>Aluminium prices on the Tokyo Commodity Exchange (TOCOM) rose on Thursday in line with overnight gains on the LME.</p>
<p>TOCOM's April aluminium contract rose slightly in thin trading to 208.2 yen per kg at 0500 GMT, up 0.4 yen from Wednesday's close of 207.8 yen.  </p>
<p>&quot;The aluminium market was very quiet today. Prices were up due to the strong overnight close of the LME,&quot; said a trader at Japanese broker Okato Shoji Co Ltd.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, three-month zinc prices were also expected to breach its recent resistance level of $1,300 a tonne in the next few days, but there was a gap between $1,270 and $1,273 which needs to be filled, Brandeis said.</p>
<p>Broker Macquarie said zinc stocks had fallen by 75,000 tonnes so far this year and it remained confident a fall of 250,000-300,000 tonnes for the year as a whole remained likely.  </p>
<p>&quot;After the current consolidation period, which could last to mid-year, prices should move sharply higher,&quot; Macquarie said.</p>
<p>Three-month copper prices were barely changed in Asian trade as the red metal was supported by recent increases in stocks, dealers said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
