<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569471" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: U.N. aide says Iraqi situation bad despite deal.</title>
<headline>U.N. aide says Iraqi situation bad despite deal.</headline>
<byline>Hassan Hafidh</byline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.N. Under-Secretary General Yasushi Akashi said on Thursday Iraq's humanitarian situation was still serious after five months of an oil-for-food deal with the world body.</p>
<p>&quot;Indeed there is a significant degree of humanitarian sufferings...The conditions in hospitals are deplorable,&quot; Akashi told reporters at the end of his six-day visit to Iraq.</p>
<p>The deal went into effect in December but Iraqis, suffering from tough U.N. sanctions imposed for Iraq's 1990 invasion of Kuwait, have only received one month's worth of rations which do not include all foodstuffs. No medicines have arrived yet.</p>
<p>The deal allows Baghdad to sell $2 billion worth of oil over six months to buy food, medicines and other humanitarian supplies.</p>
<p>&quot;We still have a lot to do to expedite and accelerate the arrival of goods,&quot; Akashi said, adding the United Nations was doing its best to &quot;speed the arrival and distribution of goods.&quot;</p>
<p>The U.N. envoy said medical supplies under the oil deal were expected to reach Iraq in one or two weeks.</p>
<p>Iraq's Vice-President Taha Yassin Ramadan complained to Akashi on Thursday about the sluggish approval of contracts for the purchase of humanitarian goods.</p>
<p>The official Iraqi News Agency, reporting on a meeting with Akashi, said Ramadan blamed the U.S. representative in the U.N. sanctions committee on Iraq for delaying these contracts.</p>
<p>&quot;I had good discussions here in the last several days. I have good understanding of their concerns, wishes and complaints which we will try our best to address,&quot; Akashi said.</p>
<p>He said he would report to U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan on what had been accomplished of the humanitarian programme. It expires on June 7.</p>
<p>Annan is to submit a report before then to the Security Council, which must decide whether the programme should be extended.</p>
<p>&quot;Certainly, I will report as quickly as possible about my findings to the U.N. Secretary-General as well as the (U.N.) Security Council,&quot; Akashi said.</p>
<p>The whole operation is being carried out under strict U.N. supervision. About 151 international observers supervise the arrival, storage and distribution of food.</p>
<p>&quot;As far as our observers are concerned...we are satisfied...They are given visas without difficulty and they are given full and unrestricted movement,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Akashi spent three days in northern Iraq, out of the control of the Iraqi government since the 1991 Gulf War. Apart from meeting with Iraqi officials, he visited hospitals in Baghdad, Mosul and northern provices.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
