<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569412" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: INTERVIEW - Japan's Ado says set to raise dividend.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - Japan's Ado says set to raise dividend.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Trading company Ado Electronic Industrial Co Ltd said on Thursday it would be able to exceed its prior earnings estimate for the year to March 31, 1997 and was likely to boost its dividend for the year.</p>
<p>Ado president Kazuo Kanayama told Reuters that both sales and parent current profit for 1996/97 would exceed the company estimate announced in November.</p>
<p>The company will announce its earnings results on May 23.</p>
<p>Last November, Ado, a dealer of semiconductors and personal computers (PCs), raised its estimated sales for 1996/97 to 112 billion yen from its earlier forecast of 100 billion yen.</p>
<p>It also upwardly revised its parent current profit forecast to two billion yen from its previous estimate of 1.6 billion yen.</p>
<p>Ado's actual sales were 80.4 billion yen and its parent current profit was one billion yen in 1995/96.</p>
<p>On the company's plan to return profits to shareholders, Kanayama said: &quot;We are likely to increase the dividend in order to keep our promise of maintaining a payout ratio of 30 percent.&quot;</p>
<p>In November, the company said that it would pay a 15-yen total dividend for 1996/97, unchanged from the previous year.</p>
<p>Kanayama added that the company has been cutting down on inventories and that its financial health is improving.</p>
<p>-- Koichi Kawaguchi, Tokyo Equities Desk +81-3-3432-9991</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
