<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569479" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel shares end higher led by Teva.</title>
<headline>Israel shares end higher led by Teva.</headline>
<dateline>TEL AVIV 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli shares closed slightly higher on Thursday, recovering early losses by a rise led by shares in Teva Pharmaceutical Industries, traders said.</p>
<p>The benchmark Mishtanim index of the top 100 shares rose 0.43 percent, or 1.11 points, to 259.72 on an all-share turnover of 118 million shekels against 93 million shekels on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The Maof 25 blue chip index closed 0.55 percent higher at 268.47.</p>
<p>&quot;The session opened with a mild decline continuing Wednesday's correction but the trend changed after Teva released its earning reports,&quot; said Daniella Finn head of sales at Batucha Securities and Investments.</p>
<p>Teva, the most active share, rose 2.5 percent to 18,947 agorot on volume of 13.9 million shekels after the company said that earnings per ADR rose in the first quarter of 1997 to $0.51 from $0.30 in the same quarter of 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;The results were above expectations and Teva was the trigger for today's rise pushing the whole market upwards. Teva is traded now at 3.7 percent above its ADR price on Nasdaq,&quot; Finn added.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is very strong and today's rebound is a clear indication that the market looks good. It opened with a decline of 0.25 percent, but then it started rising remaining stable during the day,&quot; said a trader at the First International Bank of Israel.</p>
<p>Finn added that the market is expected to stabilise at the current level.</p>
<p>Elron closed unchanged at 4,598 agorot. Elron said on Thursday that earnings per share in the first quarter rose slightly to $0.13 against $0.12 in the same period last year.</p>
<p>Industrial Building gained 1.5 percent to 519 agorot. The company said on Thursday that net profit rose in the first quarter of 1997 to 16.8 million shekels from 8.3 million a year earlier.</p>
<p>Other active shares include Bank Hapoalim, which rose 1.0 percent to 704 agorot on volume of 5.5 million shekels; Israel Discount Bank, which closed unchanged at 356 agorot on turnover of 3.3 million shekels.</p>
<p>On Sunday and Monday there will be no trading on the Tel Aviv Stock Exchange because of the Israeli Memorial and Independence Days.</p>
<p>($1 = 3.40 shekels)</p>
<p>- Dan Gerstenfeld, Tel Aviv newsroom, 972-3-537-2211</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEL AVIV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
