<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569580" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NOTICE OF SALE - University of Alabama.</title>
<headline>NOTICE OF SALE - University of Alabama.</headline>
<text>
<p>SUMMARY NOTICE OF SALE</p>
<p>				 $11,675,000*</p>
<p>The Board of Trustees of the University of Alabama</p>
<p>			 General Fee Revenue Bonds</p>
<p>		 The University of Alabama Series 1997</p>
<p>			    Dated June 1, 1997</p>
<p>The Board of  Trustees of  the University of  Alabama (the Board'') will receive sealed bids for the purchase from it of the  bonds  referred  to  above  (the  offices  of  Sterne,   Agee  &amp;  Leach,   Inc.,  Suite   2100</p>
<p>AmSouth/Harbert Plaza,  1901 6th  Avenue North,  Birmingham, Alabama 35203, up to the hour  of 11:00 a.m., Central  Time, on such date as may be  established by the undersigned  Vice President for Financial Affairs of the University of Alabama and communicated  through  Munifacts News  Service  (and  as otherwise provided in the Official Invitation for Bids)  not less than twenty-four (24) hours prior to the time the  bids are to be received.</p>
<p>The Bonds will be issued as  fully registered bonds in the denomination of $5,000 or any integral multiple thereof  and will mature in the following aggregate principal amounts  on June 1 in the following years:</p>
<p>    Year ofPrincipal*Year ofPrincipal*   Year of    Principal</p>
<p>MaturityAmount MaturityAmount MaturityAmount</p>
<p>1998 $615,000  2003 $760,000  2008$960,000**</p>
<p>    1999 635,000   2004 795,000   20091,015,000**</p>
<p>    2000 665,000   2005 835,000   20101,065,000**</p>
<p>    2001 695,000   2006 875,000   20111,120,000**</p>
<p>    2002 725,000   2007 915,000</p>
<p>Interest on the Bonds (computed on  the basis of a 360-day year of twelve  consecutive 30-day months)  will be  payable semiannually on  each  June  1  and  December  1,  beginning December 1, 1997. The principal of the Bonds will be payable  at  the  principal  office  of  Compass  Bank,   Birmingham,</p>
<p>Alabama, in its capacity as trustee  (the Trustee'') under a General Fee Revenue Trust Indenture  dated as of April  1, 1987. Interest  on the  Bonds will  be payable  by check  or draft mailed by the Trustee to the registered holders of the Bonds at the addresses  shown on the  registry books of  the Trustee pertaining to the Bonds.</p>
<p>Each bid must be  on the Official Bid  Form and conform to  the  terms  and  conditions   set  forth  in  the   Official</p>
<p>Invitation for Bids.</p>
<p>This announcement does not  constitute the solicitation of bids to purchase the Bonds. The  sale of the Bonds shall  be made exclusively  pursuant  to  the terms  of  the  Official Invitation for Bids. Copies  of the Official Invitation  for Bids, the  Official Bid  Form and  the Preliminary  Official Statement will be furnished upon request made to the Board's Financial Advisor, Sterne, Agee &amp; Leach, Inc., P.O. Box  750</p>
<p>	(707  Union  Bank   Building),  Montgomery,  Alabama</p>
<p>Attention: J. Fairley McDonald (334) 263-3892.</p>
<p>				ROBERT A. WRIGHT</p>
<p>		 Vice President For Financial Affairs</p>
<p>			 The University of Alabama</p>
<p>		   271 Rose Administration Building</p>
<p>		    Tuscaloosa, Alabama 35487-0142</p>
<p>			 Telephone: (205) 348-4530</p>
<p>Dated: April 18, 1997</p>
<p>*Subject to change, as provided in the Official Invitation for Bids.</p>
<p>** Subject to special term bond option, as provided in the Official Invitation for Bids.</p>
<p>			  (From The Bond Buyer)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
