<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569503" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dlr stays depressed vs mark, Swissy at U.S. close.</title>
<headline>Dlr stays depressed vs mark, Swissy at U.S. close.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar failed to push higher for a third consecutive U.S. session and closed at its lowest level in a month against the mark and yen as concerns grew over possible central bank intervention to stymie the dollar's recent rise, traders said.</p>
<p>However, traders said it was too soon to call an end to the dollar's spectacular two-year rally in which the U.S. currency has appreciated 10 percent against the yen and 12 percent versus the mark so far this year.</p>
<p>&quot;It's too early to say that yet. But we could see lower levels in dollar/mark, down to 1.6950. I'm not sure we'll go much lower than that,&quot; said Alfonso Alejo, senior proprietary dealer at Sakura Bank Ltd in New York.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it is anything fundamental that developed over the last 24 hours in Europe (that drove dollar/mark lower).  It's just positioning in the market,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Sparking an overnight slide in the greenback was a remark from senior Japanese Ministry of Finance official Eisuke Sakakibara that the dollar could fall as low as 103 yen.</p>
<p>Japan's Vice Finance Minister Tadashi Ogawa later clarified the remark, saying Sakakibara was not predicting the dollar would fall to 103 yen, but the U.S. unit failed to recover.</p>
<p>Nerves were raw following Wednesday's scare after a wire service reported that Japan, Germany and the United States were exploring the possibility of selling dollars for yen.</p>
<p>&quot;If history is any guide, it is mostly just talk,&quot; said Sung Won Sohn, chief economist at Norwest Corp, when asked if the recent slew of remarks from Japanese officials was a precursor to Bank of Japan intervention.</p>
<p>The dollar closed down at 1.7075/85 marks from 1.7120/30 at Thursday's open. It ended at 123.62/72 yen, barely changed from 123.72/77 at the open but well below Wednesday's close of 125.05/10.</p>
<p>Dealers said thin trading conditions exaggerated the intraday swings as most of continental Europe, including Germany, was out for the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>A continued slide in the British Pound on Thursday, following Wednesday's sharp fall in late U.S. trade, also depressed the dollar as traders sold sterling and bought marks, yen and Swiss francs in bulk.</p>
<p>Sterling partially recovered by the end of Thursday's session to close up at $1.6172/82 from $1.6153/60 after Wednesday's thrashing sparked by a wire service report -- later denied by the British Treasury.</p>
<p>The report quoted an unidentified UK Labour Party source as saying the pound should join Europe's single currency grid at a lower level than it currently trades.</p>
<p>&quot;Sterling's fall was definitely overdone. We knocked out all the long positions,&quot; Alejo said.</p>
<p>The dollar also fell prey to a strengthening Swiss franc as investors fled to the traditional safe-haven currency amid talk Europe's drive to monetary union will include a wider array of participants than originally thought.</p>
<p>The dollar fell to 1.4455/65 Swiss francs from 1.4490/00 and rose to Canadian $1.3865/75 from C$1.3831/36. The Australian dollar rose to $0.7795/00 from $0.7771/76.</p>
<p>((-- Roanne Daniels, 212-859-1677))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
