<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569517" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. MTBE edges up, but more strength seen ahead.</title>
<headline>U.S. MTBE edges up, but more strength seen ahead.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cents/Gallon  Prompt(May)    Any (June)	05/01/97(PptMay)</p>
<p>Houston     75.50/76.00	75.25/76.00     75.25/75.75</p>
<p>New York    79.50/80.25	79.00/79.50 N   79.25/80.75</p>
<p>--------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>U.S. spot MTBE prices firmed only slightly this week following sharp gains by NYMEX gasoline futures but some traders on Thursday pointed to more bullish sentiment ahead with the approach of the driving season.</p>
<p>In the Gulf Coast, spot MTBE was pegged a quarter cent stronger between 75.50 cents and 76.00 cents a gallon, with 75.25 cent deals heard done.</p>
<p>New York Harbor values were a tad weaker with 79.50 and 80.00 cent deals heard sold in a week of quiet activity.</p>
<p>Harbor offers were talked 80.25 cents.</p>
<p>&quot;With NYMEX up one day and down the next no one knows what it will do next. But gasoline inventories are pretty low going into the driving season and that should mean better value for MTBE,&quot; said a Gulf trader.</p>
<p>Meanwhile in refinery news, Texas Petrochemicals Corp. said it halved production at its 16,000-barrel per day Houston MTBE unit after losing a dehydro compressor late Wednesday. The unit will return to full steam in four to five days.</p>
<p>The Global Octane MTBE plant, which went down over the weekend, is expected to return online by Friday morning, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall, not that much product was lost. Players didn't get that excited about the refinery news,&quot; said one MTBE player.</p>
<p>-- Laney Salisbury, New York Energy Desk +1 212 859 1631</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
