<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569591" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Talk show host Springer quits Chicago news show.</title>
<headline>Talk show host Springer quits Chicago news show.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jerry Springer, the tabloid talk show host whose hiring as a local news commentator set off a firestorm of criticism and moralizing about television news, quit Thursday after just two appearances as a pundit.</p>
<p>Springer delivered a vitriolic commentary on his first broadcast Monday night in which he condemned long-time local anchorwoman Carol Marin's resignation the previous Friday as an attempt to use his hiring as a &quot;stepping-stone to martyrdom.&quot;</p>
<p>Springer also compared the station's decision to put him on the air to the tough choice he faced 20 years ago as mayor of Cincinnati when he gave a neo-Nazi group a permit to march, even though his parents were Holocaust survivors.</p>
<p>The Cincinnati Post subsequently reported that the city's mayor does not sign off on permits -- a revelation that Springer dismissed as semantics.</p>
<p>Springer's hiring despite his role as host of one of daytime TV's most outrageous talk shows raised hackles in Chicago and around the country -- although some defended his credentials and right to speak.</p>
<p>Marin, whose on-air resignation after 19 years lifted the local news show's ratings temporarily, appeared on several national news and interview shows to denounce ratings-hungry station bosses.</p>
<p>WMAQ-TV general manager and president Lyle Banks issued a statement defending Springer, adding &quot;we regret the personal attacks he has endured.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It was truly unfortunate that the beginning of his tenure as a guest commentator was unfairly associated with the departure of Carol Marin. Instead of celebrating the enormous contributions made by Carol, the headlines were filled with insinuations that we had chosen Mr. Springer over her. As both Carol and (the station) have stated, that simply was not the case. Carol had discussed her desired departure with us for several months preceding this turn of events,&quot; Banks said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
