<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569505" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Airways to cut unprofitable routes.</title>
<headline>US Airways to cut unprofitable routes.</headline>
<byline>Robin Sidel</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>US Airways Group Inc. said Thursday it would cut unprofitable routes, close some facilities and reduce its fleet in a sweeping restructuring aimed at slashing costs at the troubled airline.</p>
<p>The move, which came a day after the Arlington, Va.-based carrier said it would furlough 103 of its 5,000 pilots, was its latest attempt to cut costs and compete with other acarriers that have made similar moves the past four years.</p>
<p>Under the plan, US Airways will end jet service in September to nine cities and ground 22 aircraft to reach its goal of cutting capacity about 6.5 percent by the summer of 1998. The airline, known formerly as USAir, said the steps were necessary whether it ultimately decides to turn itself into a global carrier or a regional airline.</p>
<p>The company made no estimate of the cost savings from the plan and did not mention any one-time charges or other impact on earnings.</p>
<p>The plan quickly won the endorsement of billionaire investor Warren Buffett, whose Berkshire Hathaway Inc. owns $358 million of U.S. Airways preferred stock, or about 10 percent of the airline's voting rights.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe these actions represent a level of foresight and a sense of urgency essential to its future,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Buffett gave up his board seat on the airline in 1995 and wrote down his investment in the carrier, citing its lack of success in cutting labour costs.</p>
<p>The restructuring was the largest undertaken so far by Chief Executive Officer Stephen Wolf, an industry veteran who took the top spot at the airline last year. Wolf was a former chief executive at UAL Corp., which owns United Airlines.</p>
<p>&quot;The company's new management is ready to act in the best interests of all shareholders, employees and communities served ...&quot; Buffett said. &quot;If the labour groups have the will, I know management has the ability to make this airline into the global competitor everyone wants it to be.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts said the restructuring was made possible because a &quot;no furlough&quot; clause in the pilots' contract is set to expire on June 30. The airline has announced plans to lay off 103 of its 5,000 pilots starting July 1.</p>
<p>Analysts said US Airways has been losing millions of dollars in the nine cities where jet service will be halted as of Sept. 4. They include Albuquerque, N.M.; Austin and San Antonio, Texas; Bangor, Maine; Cincinnati, Ohio; Daytona Beach, Fla.; Islip, N.Y.; Melbourne, Fla., and Newburgh, N.Y.</p>
<p>&quot;They've given those cities a long time and they just are not going to turn profitable so they're closing them, which is a smart thing to do,&quot; said Candace Browning of Merrill Lynch.</p>
<p>But US Airways still needs to win cost cuts from its pilots, analysts said. The airline, which has the highest cost structure of major U.S. carriers, has been unsuccessful in winning concessions from union pilots.</p>
<p>&quot;They need a contract that is going to change their competitive position,&quot; said Vivian Lee at Bankers Trust.</p>
<p>While negotiations continue, strong traffic has propelled US Airways' earnings and made it more difficult for management to convince workers that the carrier is facing tough times.</p>
<p>The restructuring plan won approval from investors, who bid US Airways's stock up $2.75 to $34.50 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>The plan also calls for US Airways to close its Los Angeles crew base by February, with affected employees transferred to other bases, and reservations centres in Nashville, Tenn., and Utica, N.Y., by Oct. 1.</p>
<p>The pilots union did not have an immediate response to the company's announcement, but a May 6 tape-recorded message to members said that the union opposes the furloughs and will consider its alternatives, including legal action. The union also said the next negotiating session was set for Friday.</p>
<p>Shares of other major airlines jumped on expected gains from US Airways' cutbacks. Continental Airlines Inc. rose $1.75 to $34.125, UAL Corp. gained $1 to $74.50, and Delta Air Lines Inc. climbed $1.50 to $95.75, all on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
