<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569514" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dollar falls for third session as intervention fears grow.</title>
<headline>Dollar falls for third session as intervention fears grow.</headline>
<byline>Roanne Daniels</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar fell for the third straight session Thursday, to its lowest level in a month against the German mark and Japanese yen, as concerns grew that central banks would sell dollars to halt its two-year-old rally.</p>
<p>But traders said it was too soon to say the rally was over for the dollar, which has jumped 10 percent against the yen and 12 percent vs. the mark so far this year alone.</p>
<p>&quot;You have to respect the price action. It makes me nervous, but I think it's too early or premature to throw in the towel,&quot; said Marc Chandler, senior currency analyst at Deutsche Morgan Grenfell.</p>
<p>The dollar started falling after senior Japanese Ministry of Finance official Eisuke Sakakibara said the dollar could fall as low as 103 yen this year. Japan's vice finance minister Tadashi Ogawa later clarified the remark, saying Sakakibara was not predicting the dollar would fall that low.</p>
<p>But the dollar failed to recover since traders' nerves were raw after a Japanese wire service reported on Wednesday that Japan, Germany and the United States were exploring the possibility of selling dollars for yen.</p>
<p>&quot;If history is any guide, it is mostly just talk,&quot; said Sung Won Sohn, chief economist at Norwest Corp., regarding the recent slew of remarks from Japanese officials.</p>
<p>The dollar fell to 123.75 yen in late New York trading from 125.08 late on Wednesday, and it lost more than a pfennig against the mark to 1.7085 from 1.7195.</p>
<p>Light trading because of the Ascension Day holiday in Europe exaggerated the drop, dealers said.</p>
<p>Weakness in the British pound after Wednesday's sharp drop helped drag down the dollar as traders sold pounds and bought marks, yen and Swiss francs in bulk.</p>
<p>But the pound recovered some ground by Thursday's close and ended at $1.6200, up from $1.6155 late on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The pound tumbled Wednesday after a wire service report -- later denied by the British Treasury -- quoted an unidentified Labour Party source saying the pound should join Europe's single currency at much lower than its current levels.</p>
<p>&quot;Sterling's fall was definately overdone. We knocked out all the long postions,&quot; said Alfonso Alejo, senior proprietary dealer at Sakura Bank Ltd in New York.</p>
<p>The dollar also fell prey to a strengthening Swiss franc as investors fled to the traditional safe-haven currency amid talk Europe's single currency plan will include a wider array of participants than originally thought.</p>
<p>The dollar fell to 1.4450 Swiss francs from 1.4584.</p>
<p>It rose to Canadian $1.3862 from C$1.3820.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
