<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569595" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Texas separatists indicted on fraud charges.</title>
<headline>Texas separatists indicted on fraud charges.</headline>
<byline>Harihar Krishnan</byline>
<dateline>DALLAS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Federal prosecutors on Thursday unsealed indictments against five Republic of Texas members who allegedly conspired with leader Richard McLaren to issue $1.8 billion in worthless financial warrants.</p>
<p>The five, including the acting president of one of the group's several factions, appeared in federal court on charges contained in a 25-count indictment alleging federal bank fraud, wire fraud and conspiracy.</p>
<p>Federal prosecutors said the investigation into the militia's attempts to float bogus currency to underwrite their efforts to battle for Texas' independence had not ended with the latest round of arrests.</p>
<p>&quot;The investigation continues. There will be more people charged,&quot; Assistant U.S. Attorney Mike Uhl said.</p>
<p>Named in the indictments were Steven Craig Creer, 36, of Dallas, the acting president of one of the group's factions; Jasper Edwar Baccus, 69, of Dallas; Joe Louis Reece, 50, of Fort Worth; Erwin Leo Brown, 33, of Dallas and Mark Anthony Hernandez, 28, Cedar Hill, Texas.</p>
<p>None of the newly indicted Republic of Texas members had joined McLaren and his ragtag militia during a week-long standoff with police that ended on Saturday when members of the group laid down their arms and surrendered.</p>
<p>Texas officials also stepped up their pressure on the renegade secessionists, arresting one militia leader and threatening to haul others into court for conducting military style manoeuvres and distributing &quot;anti-government rhetoric.&quot;</p>
<p>Police on Thursday arrested Robert Kesterson, leader of one of three factions of the group wanted for allegedly ordering banks to turn over the state's assets to the group, Texas Attorney General Dan Morales said.</p>
<p>McLaren, 43, and his wife Evelyn McLaren, 50, face fraud and conspiracy charges for their role in a scheme to float $1.8 billion of Republic of Texas &quot;warrants&quot; that looked like cashiers checks but were worthless.</p>
<p>McLaren was being held without bond in a Marfa, Texas, jail on criminal and civil contempt warrants issued in Tarrant County and on state charges tied to the standoff in Jeff Davis County. He has not been arraigned on the federal charges.</p>
<p>According to the indictment, more than $1 billion of the warrants were seized in Puerto Rico, where unnamed conspirators were trying to open a commercial bank account.</p>
<p>Among other things the warrants were used to buy jewelry and airline tickets, pay credit card bills and open bank accounts, according to the indictment returned by a grand jury during the third day of the group's standoff with police.</p>
<p>From a dilapidated trailer &quot;embassy&quot; in the Davis Mountain Resorts subdivision near Fort Davis, McLaren had proclaimed himself &quot;ambassador&quot; and sought international recognition of his claim of independence for the Republic of Texas.</p>
<p>The group, which has split into several factions, believed the state's 1845 annexation by the United States was illegal. Texas was an independent nation for nine years after it broke from Mexico in an 1836 rebellion.</p>
<p>A Texas police spokeswoman said there have been no sightings of a lone fugitive militiaman, identified as Richard Keyes, 21, who escaped into the Davis Mountains as the stand-off ended on Saturday.</p>
<p>Police on horseback and in helicopters and bloodhounds tracking the Keyes through one of the most remote sections of the state were pulled out of the mountains out of concern for their safety.</p>
<p>Keyes had escaped along with McLaren bodyguard Mike Matson, 48, who was wanted in California and had vowed to &quot;die fighting&quot; in the siege. Matson was killed in a brief wild-West style shootout with police on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a lot of speculation that (Keyes) could not survive past a few days in the rugged terrain out there without food and water,&quot; Texas police spokeswoman Sherri Deatherage Green said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DALLAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
