<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569515" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US stock index futures end up strongly, off highs.</title>
<headline>US stock index futures end up strongly, off highs.</headline>
<text>
<p>May 8 - U.S. stock index futures ended strongly higher but off the day's peak, hit by a late bout of profit-taking and jitters near record territory.</p>
<p>June Standard and Poor's 500 futures rallied sharply before stalling out just shy of Wednesday's high. The contract drifted down 828.50 where it triggered sell stops.</p>
<p>&quot;Locals offered it down and it was a pretty sloppy move,&quot; one S&amp;P 500 futures trader said. He said June quickly pared its gains in choppy, erratic trade.</p>
<p>&quot;It will make the market a little jittery for tomorrow,&quot; the trader said. But overall, he said, sentiment remained bullish. Several traders said a new record high was imminent.</p>
<p>June set an all-time high on Monday at 838.00 and reached above there in subsequent overnight trade to hit 838.40. Since then, June S&amp;Ps have seesawed in big daily ranges.</p>
<p>Traders were said to be shunning the notion that a proposed capital gains tax cut would invite waves of selling. Instead, they noted, many players saw a capital gains cut as a long-term positive for the market.</p>
<p>Strong Treasury bond futures and rallying technology stocks also propelled the midday S&amp;P rally.  </p>
<p>On the rally, aggressive dealer buying and buy stops pushed the contract as high as 834.20.</p>
<p>&quot;Sentiment is definitely to the upside,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>He blamed Wednesday's selloff not on any change in trend, but on belief the market was &quot;grossly overbought&quot; in record territory. He said disappointing Treasury auctions early this week also kept buyers skittish.</p>
<p>He said bullish players who were unable to buy on Monday's rally to record highs likely waited out Wednesday's selloff and bought on early strength Thursday, seeing Wednesday's pullback as a buying opportunity.  </p>
<p>&quot;Still, I would not be surprised to see us do a lot of work around 820.00 to 823.00,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At the close, June S&amp;P 500s were up 4.90 points at 822.55, Midcap 400s rose 1.50 to 268.20, Russell rose 0.60 to 362.20, Value Lines rose 0.30 to 724.50, NYSE Composite rose 2.00 pts to 428.00, Nasdaq rose 12.00 points to 925.75, and Nikkei 225 rose 280.0 to 20,185.0.</p>
<p>((DerivativesDesk(312)408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail:derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
