<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569589" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: California Democrats unveil welfare reform plan.</title>
<headline>California Democrats unveil welfare reform plan.</headline>
<dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>California Democratic leaders on Thursday unveiled a welfare reform plan offering community service jobs to the poor and benefits more generous than those proposed by the Republican governor.</p>
<p>By the Democrats' own estimates, however, the proposal would cost $849 million more to implement in fiscal 1997-98 than Gov. Pete Wilson's welfare reform plan.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a pragmatic approach to an enormous challenge,&quot; state Senate President Pro Tem Bill Lockyer, a Democrat, said of his party's &quot;welfare-to-work&quot; program.  </p>
<p>Democratic Assembly Speaker Cruz Bustamante added: &quot;Our plan means diversion away from welfare, transition into jobs and protection for children, the elderly and disabled.&quot;</p>
<p>Democrats said their welfare program would provide counties with significant cost savings and commit $50 million to job creation programs.</p>
<p>Wilson said elements of the Democratic plan were &quot;disturbing.&quot; The plan will allow people to receive benefits for much longer than the governor had proposed.</p>
<p>Wilson said Democrats have yet to explain how they would pay for their plan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SACRAMENTO, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
