<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569543" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Tiger kills trainer at U.S. circus performance.</title>
<headline>Tiger kills trainer at U.S. circus performance.</headline>
<dateline>PITTSBURGH 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A tiger mauled and killed its trainer during a circus performance in Pennsylvania as a crowd of children watched in horror, authorities said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The tiger attacked Wayne F. Franzen and dragged him around a circus pen in Carrolltown, Pennsylvania, on Wednesday night during a fund-raising performance for a local school.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not really sure what happened exactly,&quot; Cambria County Coroner Dennis Kwiatkowski said. &quot;We have reports saying he was attacked from behind and reports saying he was attacked from the front. He was pronounced dead at the scene.&quot;</p>
<p>Franzen, 50, owned the Franzen Brothers Circus Inc. of Bushnell, Florida. His son managed to get the Bengal tiger into a cage after the attack.</p>
<p>A crowd of about 300 people, more than half of them children, was watching the performance at a local fairground. An emergency counselling service was set up at the circus for those who witnessed the attack.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of the kids felt confusion,&quot; said Philip Garmen, director of mental health at the Cambria County Mental Health Centre. &quot;A lot of them were elementary school age and they're not really attuned to death and dying. Some of them said they didn't want to go to the circus again.&quot;</p>
<p>Garmen said crisis counsellors were receiving calls on Thursday from parents who saw the attack and still were shocked or concerned about the possible effects on their children.</p>
<p>Kwiatkowski said an autopsy would be performed on Franzen but police were not investigating the incident. &quot;It's a pretty clear-cut case,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Circus officials were not available for comment. Garmen said circus workers told him the tiger would not be used in a performance again, and would likely be retired to a zoo.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PITTSBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
