<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569516" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Giddings rejects Harnischfeger bid.</title>
<headline>Giddings rejects Harnischfeger bid.</headline>
<byline>Brad Dorfman</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Machine tool giant Giddings &amp; Lewis Inc. Thursday rejected a $747 million hostile takeover offer from Harnischfeger Industries Inc. and said it was in talks with others about a possible transaction.</p>
<p>Giddings said its board carefully considered the manufacturing equipment maker's offer of $19 a share and assumption of about $116 million in debt, which Harnischfeger announced April 25, and decided it was inadequate.</p>
<p>Giddings said financial adviser Credit Suisse First Boston Corp. found Harnischfeger's offer was financially inadequate for Giddings shareholders other than Harnischfeger.</p>
<p>Fond du Lac, Wis.-based Giddings also said it had had preliminary discussions with other parties about their interest in a possible transaction. It did not identify the parties.</p>
<p>Harnischfeger, based in the Milwaukee suburb of St. Francis, Wis., said Giddings' response confirmed its decision to take the offer directly to shareholders.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's (Giddings) statement offers nothing to shareholders. Our bid offers real value and we will pursue it with dispatch,&quot; Harnischfeger Chief Executive Jeffery Grade said in a statement.</p>
<p>Analysts said even though Giddings was in talks with some parties, the company might not be able to find a taker willing to offer much more than Harnischfeger.</p>
<p>&quot;I just think that list of potential bidders is limited,&quot; said William Cooke, an analyst who follows Giddings for McDonald &amp; Co. Investments. &quot;I'm not aware that any domestic machine tool makers would be interested in Giddings.&quot;</p>
<p>At the same time, a foreign firm seeking to buy Giddings could face scrutiny from the U.S. government because some of Giddings customers have defence contracts, analysts said.</p>
<p>Harnischfeger reiterated it plans to seek a special shareholder meeting where it would ask shareholders to remove Giddings' board. If the board is removed, Harnischfeger would then ask the new board to remove Giddings &quot;poison pill&quot; takeover defence.</p>
<p>Harnischfeger also has filed a lawsuit challenging the completeness and accuracy of filings Giddings made with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The lawsuit could be used as a vehicle to ask the court to prevent Giddings from employing its takeover defence or taking other action to prevent a takeover, Harnischfeger said.</p>
<p>The $19-a-share offer was about a 39 percent premium over Giddings' closing price the day the offer was announced, and analysts still doubt Giddings will receive a much higher bid.</p>
<p>But Harnischfeger might raise its offer, possibly to as high as $21 a share, if it were convinced there were other serious offers for Giddings, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;I still think the most likely scenario is Harnischfeger will buy this company,&quot; said J. Blair Brumely, an analyst who follows both companies for Dain Bosworth Inc.</p>
<p>Giddings stock rose 12.5 cents to $20.625 on Nasdaq. Harnischfeger fell $1.25 to $40.625 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>Harnischfeger said when it made the offer it hoped to use Giddings to expand into the fragmented industrial products service business.</p>
<p>Giddings' products include drill point grinders, lathes, cutting tools and industrial computers.</p>
<p>Harnischfeger makes heavy machinery and manufacturing systems for papermaking, mining and materials handling.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I32754">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
