<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569535" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. hearings on campaign funds scandals weeks away.</title>
<headline>U.S. hearings on campaign funds scandals weeks away.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Alan Elsner, U.S. Political Correspondent</p>
<p>Two U.S. congressional committees on Thursday seemed weeks away from beginning hearings on alleged campaign finance wrongdoing as Republicans were forced to return more than $100,000 in foreign money.</p>
<p>The Senate governmental affairs committee and the House of Representatives government reform and oversight committee focused on whether China and other foreign interests sought to help President Bill Clinton and the Democratic Party with illegal contributions. They were also concerned with whether the White House and Democratic National Committee knowingly received and laundered illegal foreign funds.</p>
<p>But on Thursday, the Republican Party said for the first time it had returned a political contribution of more than $100,000 because it learned the money came from the Hong Kong parent company of a Florida-based subsidiary.</p>
<p>A statement by Republican National Committee chairman Jim Nicholson said the money came from Young Brothers Development USA, and the party had no reason to believe the money came from overseas when it accepted the donation.</p>
<p>&quot;We were not able to secure the facts from the company until (Wednesday) afternoon when a company officer reported by telephone that the source of the funds was not an American company ... but a 'parent' company in Hong Kong,&quot; Nicholson said. &quot;Upon learning those facts, we immediately returned the contributions before day's end.&quot;</p>
<p>The development was a further complication for the committees, whose work had already been slowed by the disappearance of several key witnesses abroad and statements by others that they will refuse to testify.</p>
<p>The problem was particularly severe for the Senate committee chaired by Tennessee Republican Fred Thompson because he was given a Dec. 31 cutoff date for his probe and a Jan. 21, 1998, deadline to present a final report.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a very narrow window of opportunity in which to conduct our investigation,&quot; said Thompson, in a letter on Thursday to Ohio Sen. John Glenn, the senior Democrat on the committee.</p>
<p>In the letter, Thompson agreed to a Democratic request to issue six new subpoenas to groups suspected of illegally funnelling money to Republicans. They included Young Brothers Development and Ambrose Tung Young, father of the brothers who run the company.</p>
<p>Thompson hired 22 investigators and had nine FBI agents assigned to help the investigation. He issued 90 subpoenas and started depositions with some key witnesses. Still, nobody expected hearings to begin until late June at the earliest and possibly not until July.</p>
<p>On the House side, chairman Dan Burton, Republican of Indiana, was engaged in a war of words with the White House over documents he requested but which had not been handed over. He threatened to seek a contempt of Congress citation from a court if the dispute was not resolved.</p>
<p>&quot;We're months away from hearings. It isn't going to be that soon,&quot; said one committee source.</p>
<p>Still, the House investigation was open-ended and could be kept rolling until the 1998 congressional elections or even beyond for maximum political effect.</p>
<p>Democratic sources who saw the evidence collected so far were not impressed.</p>
<p>&quot;Two months ago I thought the hearings would be riveting. Now, the trail is going a bit cold. The big question is, is there a smoking gun. It's not there yet,&quot; said one source.</p>
<p>Several key figures in the investigation were unlikely to divulge their secrets. Former Commerce Department official and Democratic National Committee fund-raiser John Huang has said he will assert his constitutional right not to answer self-incriminating questions.</p>
<p>He raised more than $3.4 million for the Democrats, of which $1.6 million was subsequently identified as illegal foreign contributions.</p>
<p>Charles Yah Lin Trie, a friend of Clinton and a Little Rock, Arkansas, restaurant owner, was suspected of illegally funnelling foreign funds to the Democrats and to a defence fund set up to pay Clinton's legal expenses in a sexual harassment case filed by former Arkansas state employee Paula Jones. He fled to China.</p>
<p>Thai businesswoman Pauline Kanchanalak gave $253,000 to the Democrats, but it was returned when she admitted it was not her money.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
