<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569508" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. says it will enforce sanctions on Libya.</title>
<headline>U.S. says it will enforce sanctions on Libya.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States said on Thursday it would enforce sanctions against Libya after leader Muammar Gaddafi defied a U.N. ban on flights imposed over the 1988 Lockerbie bombing of Pan Am Flight 103.</p>
<p>But State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns did not specify how Washington might carry out this threat. One official told Reuters there was no consideration of military action.</p>
<p>&quot;We are investigating these reports to confirm the facts,&quot; Burns said.</p>
<p>&quot;If they are accurate it would be a serious violation of U.N. Security Council resolution 748, which prohibits Libyan aircraft from engaging in international flights. We will pursue this matter in the U.N. Security Council and in the sanctions committee.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The issue here is Pan Am 103. We haven't forgotten the...people who were killed on that plane on Dec. 21, 1988. That's why the sanctions are in place against Libya. We have an obligation to the victims' families to enforce these sanctions,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Burns was referring to news reports that Gaddafi on Thursday travelled as part of a flotilla of four Boeing 727s to Niger to lead Moslem prayers.</p>
<p>The Libyan news agency JANA said Gaddafi would lead prayers in Niger and neighbouring Nigeria during a visit to West Africa as leader of the Islamic Popular Leadership, an organisation he created in 1989.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a Saddam Hussein tradition,&quot; Burns said, referring to the Iraqi leader's successful defiance on April 25 of a U.N.-imposed no-fly zone in his country. Hussein used aircraft to fly Moslems to Saudi Arabia for their religious pilgrimage.</p>
<p>&quot;You violate U.N. resolutions under the guise of religious freedom. This is bull. The Moslems in Niamey can say their prayers freely -- and they ought to be able to say their prayers freely -- without Muammar Gaddafi flying in to lead them,&quot; Burns said.</p>
<p>He called upon the government of Niger -- where the plane was reported to have landed -- to comply with the U.N. resolution and prevent Gaddafi's plane from departing.</p>
<p>The United Nations in 1992 imposed an air, arms and diplomatic embargo against Libya for failing to extradite two agents linked to the 1988 bombing over Scotland, which killed 270 people, and four other agents linked to the 1989 bombing of a French airliner over Niger, which killed 170.</p>
<p>Gaddafi's last trip abroad was by land to Tunisia in October 1996. He also violated the U.N. ban when a Libyan-registered plane flew him to Cairo and back to attend an Arab summit in June 1996.</p>
<p>The security council's Libya sanctions committee, which has the same 15 nation-membership as the council itself, could ask Libya for an explanation of the flight and could issue a statement criticising Libya. Eventually the council itself could issue a statement faulting Libya.</p>
<p>Theoretically, the council could slap Libya with tougher sanctions, but experts consider that unlikely.</p>
<p>The sanctions committee and the council could also ask Niger and Nigeria for an explanation since they are not supposed to allow Libyan planes to land.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LIBYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NIGER">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
