<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569599" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Luxury imports said to fare poorly in bumper tests.</title>
<headline>Luxury imports said to fare poorly in bumper tests.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four of six luxury cars tested, all of them imports, had bumpers that fared poorly in five-mile-per-hour crash tests, the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety said Thursday.</p>
<p>The industry supported institute said the four &quot;all cost big bucks to repair after walking-speed impacts.&quot;</p>
<p>It said the Lexus LS 400, made by Toyota Motor Corp., was the worst performer, racking up $6,195 in total repair costs for the four bumper tests, and the Mercedes E420, made by Daimler-Benz AG., was nearly as bad, with $6,042 in repair costs.</p>
<p>The two others, the Infinii Q45, made by Nissan Motor Co. Ltd. Motors, and the BMW 540i, each had more than $3,500 in repair costs, the institute said.</p>
<p>Two domestic cars were the best performers.  The Lincoln Continental, made by Ford Motor Co., had $1,090 in total damages and the Cadillac Seville, made by General Motors Corp., was next best with $1,747 total damage.</p>
<p>&quot;Costs to repair the imported luxury cars are high not only because of parts prices, but because the bumpers are poor designs,&quot; said institute president Brian O'Neill.</p>
<p>He said the tests showed what can happen when styling is more important than function, adding that car makers can make bumpers that are both effecive and stylish.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not too much to expect good bumpers, no matter what a car costs,&quot; O'Neill said. &quot;But it's particularly sad when a consumer pays a lot of money for a luxury car and gets lousy bumpers.&quot;</p>
<p>He noted that Toyota put effective bumpers on its 1997 Camry, but did not do the same on its luxury Lexus. He said the Lexus sustained more than four times the damage to the Camry.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
