<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569523" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Making funds less taxing.</title>
<headline>Making funds less taxing.</headline>
<byline>Clint Willis</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
<text>
<p>Many mutual fund investors got a surprise this April, and it wasn't a pleasant one. After enjoying a year of sterling performance in the financial markets, they discovered that a significant portion of their profits were owed to the government as taxes.</p>
<p>Those taxes were generated by the sizable capital gains that many funds incurred during 1996. The worst-hit funds included those that are frequent traders. Every time the managers of these funds sold a stock for a profit, they realised a taxable capital gain on behalf of shareholders.</p>
<p>For example, investors who owned Fidelity Magellan shares received almost $14 per share in distributions for the year. That amounted to 15 percent of the fund's net asset value. Thus, investors paid around $50 in taxes for every $1,000 worth of Magellan shares in their portfolios.</p>
<p>The moral? The only return that matters is the one that you get to keep after taxes.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, fund returns are almost always reported before taxes are taken out. That's a shame, because the practice often distorts the relative performance rankings that many investors consult when choosing funds for their portfolios.</p>
<p>A recent study by Morningstar Investor, an investment newsletter that covers the fund industry, found that taxes can reduce a fund's performance sharply. For example, Van Kampen American Capital Pace's five-year pretax returns whipped those of the typical large company growth fund. But after taxes, the fund's returns trailed more than 85 percent of its competitors'.</p>
<p>Morningstar's study also found that some funds are much better than others at keeping the taxman at bay. For example, Domini Social Equity (800-762-6814; $1,000 minimum investment; no load) rarely trades the stocks in its portfolio, since it invests in an index. Thus, the fund doesn't realise profits -- and capital gains -- as often as more actively managed funds that turn over their holdings on a regular basis. (Remember, you don't realise a gain until you sell shares at a profit.)</p>
<p>The result is that Domini Social Equity's after-tax returns put it in the top 10 percent of funds that hold a mix of fixed-income investments and large company stocks. Before taxes, the fund's ranking barely puts it in the top third of its peers.</p>
<p>Of course, tax efficiency isn't everything. But it can help you gauge a fund's appeal versus its competitors. For example, say two funds have similar pretax records, but one is more tax efficient. All other things equal, the second fund is probably a better choice.</p>
<p>You might be able to find out if a fund is tax efficient by calling the fund's sponsor -- but don't count on it. Sponsors aren't always eager to give out that information. The alternative is to take a trip to the library and look up the fund in Morningstar Mutual Funds, which tracks the performance of more than 7,900 funds. The publication recently instituted new tax efficiency ratings for domestic equity funds.</p>
<p>For example, Mairs &amp; Power Growth (800-304-7404; $2,500 minimum; no load) gets a high rating, which puts it in the top 10 percent for tax efficiency; while Columbia Special (800-547-1707; $2,000 minimum; no load) gets a low rating (worst 10 percent ).</p>
<p>Another solution is to consider &quot;tax-managed funds&quot;, which try to keep taxes down by limiting trades -- many tax-managed funds are index funds -- or timing its sales of stock to reduce tax liabilities.</p>
<p>For example, say such a fund bought shares of Company XYZ at $10 a share and later bought more at $12 a share. When the manager wants to sell some of the stock, he or she might sell the $12 shares first to produce a smaller capital gain.</p>
<p>Among tax-managed funds, you might consider entries such as Schwab 1000 (800-526-8600; $1,000 minimum; no load), which invests in an index of the 1,000 largest publicly-traded U.S. companies. Another option: USAA Growth &amp; Tax Strategy (800-382-8722; $3,000 minimum; no load), a balanced fund that holds a combination of income-producing stocks and tax-free municipal bonds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
