<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569590" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Astronaut's widow quits over Hall induction policy.</title>
<headline>Astronaut's widow quits over Hall induction policy.</headline>
<byline>Brad Liston</byline>
<dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Betty Grissom said on Thursday that her resignation from the U.S. Astronaut Hall of Fame governing board resulted from 30 years of frustration over the launchpad fire that killed her husband and two other Apollo 1 crewmen.</p>
<p>At the heart of the issue was the board's decision not to induct Roger Chaffee, the junior member of that crew, because the January 1967 onboard fire killed him before he actually flew in space.</p>
<p>&quot;This might be the last straw,&quot; Grissom, widow of U.S. space pioneer Virgil &quot;Gus&quot; Grissom, told Reuters. &quot;The least they can do is honour him.&quot;</p>
<p>Grissom said NASA's investigation of the Apollo 1 fire was &quot;a cover-up from the beginning,&quot; led by many of the same astronauts now honoured in the Hall. Those astronauts, she said, were driven by personal desires to fly in space and did not want to find anything that might scuttle the programme.</p>
<p>&quot;You can't investigate yourself,&quot; she said, &quot;and that investigation should have been handled outside the agency.&quot;</p>
<p>The astronauts, veterans of the United States' earliest manned programmes, Projects Mercury and Gemini, also serve on the board of the Astronaut Scholarship Foundation, which established the criteria for induction into the Hall.</p>
<p>Until her resignation on Saturday, Grissom, 69, had served there in her husband's place.</p>
<p>NASA's probe concluded 30 years ago that an electrical spark ignited the oxygen-rich atmosphere of the pressurized command module during a test days before the scheduled launch.</p>
<p>Gus Grissom, Chaffee and Ed White all died of smoke inhalation before launch technicians could open their hatch. The system that caused the spark was never determined.</p>
<p>Extensive changes to the Apollo spacecraft were made following that investigation, and again after an explosion crippled the Apollo 13 mission midway to the moon.</p>
<p>But Grissom said NASA and its Astronaut Office, in their rush to put Apollo 1 behind them, never gave the three crewmen their due. She said the trio should have had their own memorial many years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;Gus really took a beating&quot; in the Tom Wolf book &quot;The Right Stuff&quot; and the movie based on it, she said, in part because the surviving Mercury astronauts never wanted Grissom to eclipse them.</p>
<p>Gus Grissom was inducted in the Hall of Fame in 1990 and White was inducted in 1993. When the Apollo astronauts are inducted in October, Chaffee will be the first member of a U.S. space crew to be excluded from the honour role.</p>
<p>The rules for induction were set up by surviving Mercury astronauts when the foundation was known as the Mercury Seven Foundation, foundation director Howard Benedict said.</p>
<p>He said the rules were that any U.S. astronaut who flew in space during Projects Mercury, Gemini and Apollo would automatically be inducted as a space pioneer. After Project Apollo, a committee would consider astronauts on their merit, Benedict said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
