<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569690" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. firm aids Grand Forks flood victims.</title>
<headline>U.S. firm aids Grand Forks flood victims.</headline>
<byline>Doug Barrett</byline>
<dateline>GRAND FORKS, N.D. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Another benefactor, this time an unnamed U.S. corporation, descended on this flood-ravaged city Thursday to offer $5 million to help residents get back on their feet.</p>
<p>An earlier gift of $15 million from another anonymous donor will soon be used up. City officials said 12,500 applications for aid had poured in and the donor's wish to give $2,000 to each flood-damaged household would not be realised.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't second-guess the gift,&quot; city attorney Howard Swanson said.</p>
<p>&quot;While there may be people frustrated, we can't imagine they would go back and try to determine why the wrapping paper was blue, why the bow was pink. We were fortunate to have gotten the gift (and) not try to decipher it and not try to tear down the fabric of the gift,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Roughly $9 million in checks have already been distributed in $2,000 increments to thousands of families affected by last month's devastating flood in Grand Forks and its smaller sister city, East Grand Forks, Minnesota.</p>
<p>But with thousands more applications being processed, the fund established by the anonymous donor, believed to be a wealthy California woman, has been exhausted.</p>
<p>The charitable arm of a U.S. company stepped in Thursday and agreed to put up another $5 million, to be distributed in $1,000 allotments per household.</p>
<p>&quot;In conversation with the new donor, we will try service as many of those applications we have in house as possible,&quot; said Kevin Dvorak, head of the North Dakota Community Foundation, which was overseeing the donor distributions.</p>
<p>&quot;The original donor's gifts proved to be expended and we'll try service as many applications as we can -- up to $1,000 per head of household,&quot; Dvorak said.</p>
<p>Grand Forks, a city of 50,000, and East Grand Forks, with 9,500 people, were virtually abandoned to the swollen Red River of the North. Subsequent fires that burned unchecked for hours in downtown Grand Forks leveled two city blocks.</p>
<p>In the more than two weeks since the floodwaters have receded, recovery has been slow and large sections of the cities remain uninhabitable.</p>
<p>Drinking water and electricity were only just being restored, and many homeowners were tearing out much of their ruined possessions and leaving the cities at night.</p>
<p>City officials were considering what areas to abandon for good, and examining a plan by engineers to build a permanent diking system and possibly straighten out the river so that it could handle a larger volume of water.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GRAND FORKS, N.D."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
