<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569632" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. seeks to clarify N. Korea food aid position.</title>
<headline>U.S. seeks to clarify N. Korea food aid position.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States on Thursday sought to clarify its position on food aid for North Korea, a central issue in the question of whether Pyongyang will agree to join Korean peninsula peace talks.</p>
<p>State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns said Washington intended to continue providing assistance to North Korea when the U.N. World Food Programme makes appeals.</p>
<p>But he said the United States has no intention of providing large-scale aid that would prop up Pyongyang's Stalinist regime.</p>
<p>However U.S. officials have said repeatedly the issue of larger-scale food assistance could be discussed when and if Pyongyang agrees to accept a U.S.-South Korean proposal for four-party peace talks aimed at replacing a fraying armistice from the 1950-53 Korean war with a permanent peace treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not favour the current economic system in North Korea, which is a communist system, which has clearly failed the people,&quot; Burns told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;We'd like to see that system changed because it's that system that has failed the North Korean people, and has led to the starvation and to the deprivation that millions of North Koreans are now experiencing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;So are we going to put into North Korea billions of dollars of American or Western or Asian money, either bilaterally or multilaterally, to subsidise a communist economic system?  No way. We're not going to do that.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;But that's not the question that we've been asked by the United Nations World Food Programme. The World Food Programme came forward with a limited appeal ... So we're going to respond on an emergency, humanitarian basis to try to get food to people who need it in a failing system,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The World Food Programme, a United Nations agency, has so far this year appealed for 200,000 metric tons of food for North Korea, or about $95.5 million. About $38.6 million of this has been raised. The United States has pledged $25 million and South Korea $6 million.</p>
<p>During a meeting in Tokyo on Wednesday, the United States and South Korea decided not to offer further large scale aid until North Korea agreed to peace talks.</p>
<p>At the same time, Japan decided to withhold all aid until Tokyo-Pyongyang ties were normalised and other issues put to rest, in particular charges that North Korea kidnapped a Japanese schoolgirl in 1977 and spirited her away to Pyongyang.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
