<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569609" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Call risk makes Poland Discount bond wallflower.</title>
<headline>Call risk makes Poland Discount bond wallflower.</headline>
<byline>Nailene Chou Wiest</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A rally in Poland's Brady debt has generated a headwind for Discount bonds, which face increasing call risk as the price inches toward par, U.S. analysts said.</p>
<p>At 98-1/8 bid, the bond has less than two points to go before triggering the call provision, thus capping any big potential gains, they said.  </p>
<p>The $1.7 billion buyback of Brady debt confirmed by Polish Finance Ministry officials on Wednesday sparked a rally, in which the spread of Par bonds contracted by 25 basis points (bps) but the spread of discount bonds narrowed less than 10 bps, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;If Poland keeps on buying back, the discount will trade like the Aztec,&quot; said John Cadley, vice president of emerging markets research at J.P. Morgan Securities, referring to the early redemption of Mexico's Aztec bond in late February.  </p>
<p>On the surface, the spread for Discount bonds was much wider, hence appearing cheaper, than par bonds, but it is important to consider the call risk in comparing the prices of Poland's various Brady debt, he said.</p>
<p>As of Wednesday's close, the spread for par bonds was 151 bps and for Discounts 188 bps, but adjusted for optionality, the spreads were 141 and 143, respectively.</p>
<p>With a mere 20 bp spread tightening, the Discount bonds would bump against the call ceiling, while par bonds, bid at 55-1/2, still have a long way to go, Cadley said.  </p>
<p>Poland's five-year Eurobond issued last summer, which carries no call provision, has been trading above par, according to a Eurobond source, who noted that the bond was trading like a single-A credit.</p>
<p>Poland's sovereign debt is rated triple B-minus by Standard and Poor's and Bas3 by Moody's Investors Service Inc.</p>
<p>Gretchen Rodkey, East European and Russian debt analyst at Bear Stearns and Co Inc, said Poland was ripe for an upgrade, which could come as early as mid-summer.  </p>
<p>Strong growth in the first quarter, declining inflation and an influx of foreign capital all argue for a higher credit rating for Poland, she said.</p>
<p>The $1.7 billion Brady buyback would further improve its debt-to-Gross Domestic Product ratio, she added.</p>
<p>All in all, Rodkey said, those Polish numbers compare favorably with the macroeconomic picture of the Czech Republic, which is rated single-A by S&amp;P and Baa1 by Moody's.</p>
<p>In New York trading on Thursday, Poland Brady bonds extended Wednesday's gains, while other Brady bonds slipped.</p>
<p>PDI bonds led the climb, rising 3/4 to 83-1/4. The uncollateralized PDI bonds have an average life of 12.8 years, compared to 27.5 years for the collateralized Par and Discount bonds.</p>
<p>(( -- 212-859-1674 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
