<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569675" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Bid to reopen famous U.S. murder case moves ahead.</title>
<headline>Bid to reopen famous U.S. murder case moves ahead.</headline>
<dateline>CLEVELAND 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A local judge on Thursday said he would hear motions next month in a bid to reopen the 43-year-old murder case that inspired &quot;The Fugitive&quot; TV series and movie.</p>
<p>Judge Ronald Suster of Cuyahoga County Common Pleas Court asked the parties involved to return to court on June 2 after which he could throw the case out or set a trial date.</p>
<p>The case involves Sam Sheppard, a Cleveland osteopath convicted of second-degree murder in the 1954 killing of his pregnant wife Marilyn. He was acquitted in a new trial in 1966 and died at the age of 46 in 1970.</p>
<p>His son, Sam Reese Sheppard, is seeking a civil trial and a finding that his father was wrongfully convicted at the first trial -- a move that would clear his father's name completely and open the way for him to collect damages from the state.</p>
<p>His lawyer contends that evidence was withheld that would have cleared his father earlier and that blood at the crime scene linked the murder to a former handyman for the family.</p>
<p>Assistant County Prosecutor Carmen Marino said on Thursday no evidence was withheld and his office has nothing left to turn over in the case.</p>
<p>Hollywood's version of the &quot;Fugitive&quot; holds little resemblance to the Sheppard case since Sheppard was arrested a month after the murder and convicted six months later. He maintained his innocence throughout, contending a home invader killed his wife.</p>
<p>In the movie and TV series, the &quot;fugitive&quot; escapes from custody and goes underground to clear his name.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CLEVELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
