<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569644" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PG&amp;E Energy Trading CEO targets N.American market.</title>
<headline>PG&amp;E Energy Trading CEO targets N.American market.</headline>
<byline>James Jelter</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lyn Maddox, the newly-appointed head of PG&amp;E Energy Trading, said he is fixing his sights on all of North America in a bid to make PG&amp;E one of the biggest energy wholesalers in the U.S.</p>
<p>&quot;We are already very close to being in the top three, and hope to be there by the end of the year,&quot; Maddox said Thursday in a telephone interview with Reuters.</p>
<p>Maddox will take up his post as president and chief executive officer of the new unit from May 12, heading San Francisco-based PG&amp;E Corp's competitive wholesale commodity trading and marketing unit.</p>
<p>He comes to PG&amp;E from PennUnion Energy Services in Houston, a leading energy commodity marketing company.</p>
<p>Maddox said PG&amp;E Energy Trading plans to set up a single trading operation in Houston with about 160 employees, including risk managemanent and support staff.</p>
<p>&quot;Our primary focus is going to be outside California, frankly. This is primarily a continental, North American play to develop new markets,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We think we have all the ingredients to compete with the likes of an Enron or Southern,&quot; he said, citing other key competitors in the opening gas and electricity marketplace.</p>
<p>PG&amp;E Energy Trading is a central element in PG&amp;E Corp's bid to break out of its traditional service territory in northern California and move into the nation's $200 retail electricity industry as it moves toward open competition.</p>
<p>The Houston-based subsidiary will coordinate all of PG&amp;E's energy trading activities, including those formerly conducted by Energy Source Inc (ESI), Teco Pipeline in Texas, and PG&amp;E Energy Services Inc.</p>
<p>PG&amp;E acquired ESI, a Houston-based gas marketer, in December, 1996.</p>
<p>It will also include Valero Energy Corp's trading activities, pending approval of PG&amp;E and Valero's merger plan.</p>
<p>&quot;Hopefully, closure of the Valero merger will occur sometime in July. This will give us a lot of flexibility in Texas,&quot; Maddox said.</p>
<p>The merger, valued at $1.5 billion, still needs final approval from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission in Washington and from Valero shareholders, a move Maddox expects at Valero's next shareholder meeting in June.</p>
<p>Valero Natural Gas operates a 7,500-mile pipeline system that can carry about three billion cubic feet of gas a day.</p>
<p>Maddox said he expects Valero to give the new trading unit a &quot;very strong&quot; presence in the Midwest, while ESI will boost the company's profile in the East, a region he admitted needs a lot of business development.</p>
<p>Part of PG&amp;E Energy Trading's strategy involves building a North American network of natural gas transmission and storage hubs to give its traders a valuable operational cushion.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to create hubs...We are looking forward to working with Valero on this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Maddox said he envisions developing a continental network of seven hubs, located on the U.S. Gulf Coast, in Texas, west Texas, the Northeast, Northwest, Chicago area, and Calgary.</p>
<p>The company will continue its activities in Canada through PG&amp;E Energy Trading, Canada, in Calgary, which recently changed its name from PG&amp;E Energy Source of Canada.</p>
<p>PG&amp;E Energy Trading will start off with natural gas sales estimated at 4.5 billion cubic feet a day.</p>
<p>Maddox said he did not yet have an estimate for the group's initial power sales.</p>
<p>He also said there would be no need to borrow to fund the new unit, since each of the group's components already are financially self-sustaining.</p>
<p>Provided the Valero merger goes ahead as planned, Maddox estimated the new unit would be able to make its first revenue contributions to PG&amp;E Corp sometime in the third quarter.</p>
<p>&quot;But this will be better reflected in the fourth quarter,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>((--New York Power Desk 212 859 1621))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
