<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569668" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Senate bill gives states lead in electricity.</title>
<headline>U.S. Senate bill gives states lead in electricity.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Electric utility deregulation would largely be left up to the states under legislation introduced in the U.S. Senate Thursday.</p>
<p>At a Senate Energy Committee meeting on electricity restructuring, Wyoming Republican Craig Thomas said he would introduce a bill to let states take the lead in restructuring, without imposing federal mandates for competition by a certain date.</p>
<p>&quot;If the Congress is going to make fundamental changes to the last major regulated monopoly, its role should be to help implement competitive changes in a positive manner, rather than interject the heavy hand of government with a 'Washington-knows-best' mentality,&quot; Thomas said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a consensus bill that will give lawmakers, who want to see states have the opportunity and the power to deregulate the industry, a thoughtful option to support,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The bill would give each state and non-regulated utility authority over retail transactions to allow stranded costs recovery, and would give states authority to make electricity providers help offer universal service to all classes of consumers.</p>
<p>The bill would repeal the Public Utility Holding Company Act and would lift requirements of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act for new contacts.</p>
<p>Senate Energy Committee Chairman Frank Murkowski, an Alaska Republican, has also said he does not want the federal government to interfere with states' restructuring efforts.</p>
<p>Murkowski held the session to look at the effects of increased utility competition on fuel use and types of generation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
