<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569660" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Midwest direct hogs seen steady-weak - dealers.</title>
<headline>US Midwest direct hogs seen steady-weak - dealers.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Midwest direct cash hog prices Friday were seen steady with a weak tone, livestock dealers said.</p>
<p>Weakness was attributed to ideas there were enough hogs to satisfy the needs of packers following a slight increase in marketings on Wednesday and Thursday, they said.</p>
<p>Packer demand was light following reductions in slaughter for the third consecutive week amid poor margins, sources said. Outlooks for light Saturday slaughter also could weigh on cash hog prices on Friday, they noted.  </p>
<p>The light slaughter reduced pork supplies, which in turn, bolstered pork prices, they said.</p>
<p>The higher pork reportedly was easing some packer operating margins, which could lead to increased hog buying early next week, several dealers said.</p>
<p>Fresh bone-in prices for 1/4-inch trimmed 13-18 lb loins had a weighted average of $149.36 per cwt at midday Thursday, well up from $140.00 at Friday's close, USDA reported in its carlot pork primal cut report.</p>
<p>Hog slaughter Thursday was pegged at 330,000 head, which brought week-to-date to 1.239 million head, USDA reported. The weekly figure was down 4.3 percent from a week ago and down 7.8 percent from a year ago, USDA statistics showed.</p>
<p>Interior Iowa and southern Minnesota top prices for hogs delivered to plants Friday could range $58.00 to $58.50 per cwt. Illinois top prices at plants could span $57.00 to $57.50 and Indiana/Ohio top prices were seen at $57.50 to $58.00, sources in those areas said.</p>
<p>((Bob Janis 312-983-7347))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
