<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569641" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Petsmart stock slumps after earnings warning.</title>
<headline>Petsmart stock slumps after earnings warning.</headline>
<byline>Mark Egan</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Petsmart Inc. shares tumbled to a 12-month low Thursday, a day after the company warned of disappointing quarterly earnings, sparking concerns about the pet products retailer's operations.</p>
<p>The stock slid as low as $9.19, before ending down 81 cents at $10.81 on Nasdaq. It was the second the most heavily traded issue, with almost 18.3 million shares changing hands.</p>
<p>The retailer said late Wednesday it expected to report earnings of about 5 cents a share for the first quarter ended May 4, or about half of the Wall Street consensus estimate according to First Call, which tracks analysts' estimates.</p>
<p>Petsmart lost $7.6 million, or 6 cents a share, on sales of $457.4 million in the fourth quarter.</p>
<p>Analysts said inventory problems accounted for about two-thirds of the earnings shortfall. Inaccurate data was fed into a computerized inventory system, leaving the Phoenix-based company without many essential items, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;They were overstocked at the end of the fourth quarter and they were understocked by the end of the first quarter,&quot; said Joan Bogucki, an analyst at Needham &amp; Co.</p>
<p>&quot;They had shortfalls in inventories due to some executional screw-ups,&quot; said Bill Armstrong of Fahnestock &amp; Co. &quot;People are wondering if management really has their thumb on the execution side of the business.&quot;</p>
<p>Petsmart stock has fared poorly in recent months. On March 22 Petsmart traded as high as $22 before falling to $16.8125 by April 30. Last Friday, Petsmart's investment bank Donaldson Lufkin &amp; Jenrette downgraded the stock and removed it from its recommended list, sending it skidding $3.8125 to $12.125.</p>
<p>&quot;We made some misguided decisions in hindsight,&quot; said Susan Schnabel, Petsmart's chief financial officer who recently joined the firm from DLJ.</p>
<p>She said in an interview that management had been distracted from the day-to-day running of the company by recent acquisitions and needs to focus on basics.</p>
<p>&quot;It certainly is being addressed and aggressively addressed,&quot; Schnabel said.</p>
<p>Chris Vroom, an analyst at Alex Brown said the company's complex accounting procedures accentuated its problems, leading to higher expenses when inventories were low.</p>
<p>&quot;They made a very serious mistake on their buying system and they were not keeping appropriate control over that system,&quot; he said. &quot;It has precipitated a credibility problem with investors and that is likely to persist probably until the third quarter.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts blamed the rest of the earnings shortfall to a consumer shift away from flea and tick collars, powders and sprays in favour of pills and other new treatments which are only available through veterinarians.</p>
<p>Sales of flea and tick items can account for as much as 10 percent of sales during the spring months, analysts said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
