<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569643" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX Hub natgas mostly ends down as longs bail.</title>
<headline>NYMEX Hub natgas mostly ends down as longs bail.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX Henry Hub natgas futures ended broadly lower Thursday in another active session, with front months hit hardest by a flood of long liquidation after early reports of softer physical prices, sources said.</p>
<p>June skidded eight cents to close at $2.273 per million British thermal units. July settled 8.7 cents lower at $2.288. Most others ended steady to down by 7.4 cents.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we moved up too far, too fast, and now we'll see a consolidation into the low-to-mid $2.20s. I still think we're going higher down the road, but we don't have the (hot) weather yet to drive it,&quot; said one East Coast trader.  </p>
<p>With Northeast temperatures expected to turn more seasonal next week and no heavy cooling load forecast for the South, some think the upside may be stalled near-term.</p>
<p>But many expect the bulls to return once hotter weather kicks in, particularly with many still short physical gas this month.</p>
<p>Technical traders said the explosive growth in open interest over the last week to record levels also had many expecting a further profit-taking pullback, but few expected paper or physical prices to crater any time soon.</p>
<p>They pegged resistance in June at the new high of $2.43 and then at $2.47-50. Support was seen first at $2.20, with major buying likely at $2.05 and then along the up trendline around $2.04.</p>
<p>In the cash, Gulf Coast swing prices were steady to down slightly Thursday at about the $2.30 level, with Hub gas mostly quoted at $2.31-2.34. Midcon pipes also were unchanged to modestly lower in the $2.09-14 range. New York city gate gas also lost some ground to the $2.55-60 area.</p>
<p>The NYMEX 12-month Hub strip tumbled 6.4 cents to $2.322. NYMEX said 50,002 contracts traded, down from Wednesday's revised tally of 68,734.</p>
<p>On the KCBT, June finished 3.7 cents lower at $2.143, while deferreds ended down by 2.2 to four cents. The East/West spread narrowed by 4.3 cents to 13.0 cents (NYMEX premium). KCBT said 674 lots changed hands, up slightly from Wednesday's total of 656.</p>
<p>((J Silha, New York Power Desk 212-859-1624))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
