<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569616" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Cuban exile sues Miami newspaper over Castro bash.</title>
<headline>Cuban exile sues Miami newspaper over Castro bash.</headline>
<byline>Angus MacSwan</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A noted Cuban exile writer is suing a Miami newspaper, saying he received death threats that forced him into hiding after it reported he was invited to Cuban President Castro's 1996 birthday party and it published his telephone number, his lawyer said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Writer Norberto Fuentes has lived in exile in Miami since fleeing Communist-ruled Cuba in 1994.</p>
<p>The idea he would be invited to Castro's birthday bash was rather as if Salman Rushdie were to attend a party for the Iranian Ayatollah Khomeni, attorney Luis Dominguez said.</p>
<p>Fuentes is best known for his biographical work &quot;Hemingway in Cuba&quot; about the American writer's years living on the island. The prologue was written by Colombian Nobel laureate Gabriel Garcia Marquez, a friend of Castro.</p>
<p>Last August, the Spanish-language Nuevo Herald, sister paper of the Miami Herald, published an article about a party in Havana for Castro's 70th birthday. In a sidepiece it gave a list it said was of those who had been invited but could not attend. It included Fuentes and gave his unlisted telephone number.</p>
<p>The next day Fuentes received a stream of insulting phone calls and death threats from enraged Cuban exiles, Dominguez told Reuters. He fled with his family to Key West, fearing for their safety.</p>
<p>Dominguez said it was absurd to suggest Fuentes had been invited to the party.</p>
<p>&quot;You would have to be personally approved by Castro and cleared by state security. Here in the exile community that is dangerous. It means they see you as an infiltrator, as a Castro crony or a sympathiser, that he's an exile under false pretences,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Extreme sectors of the Cuban exile community in Miami have a record of hounding, sometimes violently, singers, artists or other figures they see as having even the most tentative of links with Cuba.</p>
<p>Fuentes filed a lawsuit in a Dade County Court last month alleging negligence and invasion of privacy against El Nuevo Herald. Now back in Miami but keeping a low profile, he says his reputation is badly affected and his wife's plans to establish a doctor's practice among the Cuban community were set back, Dominguez said.</p>
<p>Fuentes was a member of Cuba's intellectual elite for many years until he fell out with the government. He tried to escape the island and was jailed in 1993.</p>
<p>Writers in the international authors' organisation PEN, incuding John Updike and Norman Mailer, campaigned for his release. He was eventually allowed to leave in August 1994 with help from Garcia Marquez.</p>
<p>His latest project is on the 1989 trial and execution of Cuban general Arnaldo Ochoa and Colonel Antonio de la Guardia over a drugs trafficking scandal.</p>
<p>Armando Correa, who wrote the article, and El Nuevo Herald publisher Alberto Ibarguen were not available for comment when Reuters contacted the paper. The New Times weekly quoted Ibarguen as saying publication of the phone number was an error and no harm was intended towards Fuentes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
