<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569651" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Analysts see US ending soy stocks below 125 mln bu.</title>
<headline>Analysts see US ending soy stocks below 125 mln bu.</headline>
<byline>Emily Kaiser</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Agriculture Department next week will likely shave five million to 10 million bushels off its current estimate for U.S. soybean ending stocks to account for strong crush and export demand, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The bean number is going to shrink on the carryout down to 120&quot;  million bushels, said Don Roose, president of U.S. Commodities in Iowa. &quot;The crush figure has to be raised.&quot;</p>
<p>USDA in April put 1997 soybean ending stocks at 125 million bushels, the lowest level in 20 years. Updated estimates will be released Monday at 0730 CDT/1230 GMT.  </p>
<p>Corn ending stocks projections drew mixed reviews with some analysts forecasting another increase in feed usage figures while others predicted industrial demand would slide as ethanol production lagged USDA projections.</p>
<p>USDA in April put corn ending stocks at 909 million bushels. Analysts' estimates for Monday's report ranged from 869 million to 929 million bushels.</p>
<p>Opinions on wheat stocks were also mixed but most analysts interviewed suggested export figures would be increased by 10 million bushels, cutting ending stocks to roughly 450 million bushels. USDA in April forecast stocks of 460 million bushels.  </p>
<p>The soybean stocks situation was already expected to be the tightest in 20 years so analysts said trade attention would be focused on that figure.</p>
<p>&quot;I think they should bring exports up by 10 million (bushels) on this report,&quot; said Doug Hjort, president of Hjort Associates in Iowa.</p>
<p>USDA on May 1 put marketing-year-to-date soybean export inspections at roughly 752 million bushels, well above last year's pace of 659 million bushels. USDA in April said total marketing-year exports would total 895 million bushels.  </p>
<p>Several analysts said they expected that figure would be raised to 900 million bushels.</p>
<p>Estimates for soybean production from Brazil and Argentina were falling which could bring more export business to the U.S., analysts said. The U.S. agricultural attaches to those countries trimmed production estimates by a combined 1.25 million tonnes, according to reports released this week.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of our export pace is going to be dependent on what the Brazilians do,&quot; said Dale Durchholz, analyst with Agrivisor Services, a subsidiary of the Illinois Farm Bureau.  </p>
<p>&quot;It looks like they're going to export seven million tonnes, maybe more. Last year, to put that in perspective, they shipped 3.5 million tonnes.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. crush usage figures were also expected to jump as the crush pace continued to exceed USDA's projection for 1.420 billion bushels. Analysts pointed to expansion in U.S. pork production. Soymeal is a primary hog feed ingredient.</p>
<p>Roose said crush needs to fall by record levels over the next four months to stay within USDA's current projections.</p>
<p>&quot;The second half of the year our crush does tail off historically to about 93 percent of the first half of the year but to meet the government numbers, you're going to have to shrink the second half usage by another five percent,&quot; Roose said. &quot;With the profitability in the poultry and pork industries, that's just not going to happen.&quot;</p>
<p>Hjort noted Brazil last year lifted an export tax on soy products which made it more profitable for exporters to ship soybeans rather than crush them and sell the products. That scenario encouraged more world buyers to turn to U.S. soy.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that South America has taken their export tax off and are exporting more beans, that means that somebody's got to do more crushing,&quot; Hjort said.</p>
<p>&quot;We may export a few less beans but we'll continue to crush more,&quot; Hjort added.</p>
<p>((Chicago Newsdesk 312-408-8749))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
