<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569676" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME hogs end mixed after new high, pork bellies up.</title>
<headline>CME hogs end mixed after new high, pork bellies up.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>CME hog futures retreated to mixed levels by the close on local profit taking after surging late to post a new contract high in July. Pork bellies ended higher after trading on both sides of previous levels early.</p>
<p>Hogs closed 0.725 cent per lb higher to 0.225 lower with June up 0.475 at 84.850 cents. July was up most after setting a new contract high of 86.500 earlier. Pork bellies posted gains of 0.525 to 1.050 with July up 0.525 at 91.575 cents.</p>
<p>Futures shot up around 1200 CDT when increased local demand added to fund rolling in July to touch off large buy stops. Prices slipped when locals took profits, traders said.</p>
<p>Providing support in nearbys was the firmer tone to cash pork prices and the continued concern that hog marketings were running well under expectations. Even though fieldwork reduced marketings, the numbers coming to market despite high cash prices left traders wondering where the hogs had gone.</p>
<p>&quot;Our slaughter has been running for three weeks in a row now eight to nine percent below a year ago, and I think with the demand and the export pace still fairly strong, it's hard to think too negative in that (pork) complex fundamentally,&quot; said Dan Roose, President of U.S. Commodities Inc.  </p>
<p>Roose cited increased pork product movement after the recent setback in prices. Improved weather will also keep hog marketings tighter the new few days, he said.</p>
<p>Fund rolling accounted for much of the early action and the shifting of long June contracts into July continued late. Some of the spreading was the &quot;Goldman roll&quot; but other funds were also pushing longs into back months, traders said.</p>
<p>ADM Investor Services and Lind-Waldock actively bought July on the rally while E.D.&amp;F. Man and Dean Witter bought late. Cargill Investor Services, FIMAT Futures USA and Refco were rolling longs, pit sources said.</p>
<p>In hog options, a local did the June 83/86 straddle roll. Refco bought December 74 puts, pit sources added.</p>
<p>Pork bellies ranged on both sides of previous levels but moved up late following the strength in live hogs. Locals short covering added to late strength, traders said.</p>
<p>The light amount of frozen bellies currently in storage and continued light hog slaughter again buoyed pork bellies despite concern the recent runup in cash bellies would again cut off domestic demand. Export interest appears to be holding in light of another larger-than-expected out-movement from storage last week, sources noted.</p>
<p>&quot;Export demand still seems to be fairly solid,&quot; Roose said.</p>
<p>((Jerry Bieszk 312-408-8725))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
