<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569667" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pentagon to investigate charges in Army scandal.</title>
<headline>Pentagon to investigate charges in Army scandal.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Pentagon said on Thursday it would investigate allegations that a number of sex harassment cases against black Army drill sergeants and the service's top enlisted man might be racially motivated.</p>
<p>&quot;Those charges will be examined...we take any allegation of irregularity seriously,&quot; Defence Department spokesman Ken Bacon told reporters in response to questions.</p>
<p>But Bacon stressed at the Defence Department's regular news briefing that the U.S. military &quot;remains an exemplary institution in dealing with the question of race,&quot; offering equal opportunity for enlistment, support and promotion.</p>
<p>He declined to give details or to comment on specific cases, including the Army's charges on Wednesday of adultery and assault against its top enlisted man, Army Sgt. Maj. Gene McKinney.</p>
<p>McKinney, a black, is accused by four white female servicewomen of sexual harassment.</p>
<p>The 46-year-old McKinney denied the charges and said in a statement on Wednesday he believed race was &quot;driving this investigation and the way it is being conducted&quot;.</p>
<p>McKinney's attorney said he, too, was disturbed by allegations that Army investigators had asked witnesses if McKinney was specifically interested in sex with white women.</p>
<p>The Army's Criminal Investigation Command denied race was an issue in the investigation of McKinney or others.</p>
<p>The McKinney case was the latest development in an Army harassment scandal that includes charges of rape of women recruits, many of them white, by a number of drill sergeants and trainers, most of them black, at several training bases.</p>
<p>Army Staff Sgt. Delmar Simpson, a key figure in one of the worst U.S. military sex scandals, was sentenced on Tuesday to 25 years in prison for raping six women and other sexual offences at Aberdeen Proving Ground in Maryland.</p>
<p>Some critics accused the Army in the Simpson and other cases of being too willing to accept the charges of white women against black men.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't believe it is a problem,&quot; Bacon said, when asked by reporters if the issue was creating racial tension in the armed forces.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that the military remains an exemplary institution in dealing with the question of race,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We train everybody equally to work as a team and to trust one another. The military has a very well-defined promotion system where everybody is treated equally to the best of the system's ability.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked about the allegations that Army investigators might be targeting black men for conviction, he replied:</p>
<p>&quot;I am not aware that there is any truth or credibility to those charges. But those are serious charges and we look into charges made about the adequacy or the fairness of investigations.&quot;</p>
<p>Meanwhile, an Army colonel is investigating the charges against McKinney, the only soldier who carries the venerated military title Sergeant Major of the Army as leading member of the service's highest enlisted rank.</p>
<p>The investigator will decide if McKinney will face court martial on any of the 18 charges of sexual misconduct and obstruction of justice involving three Army women and a woman sailor between October 1994 and March this year.</p>
<p>McKinney is assigned to administrative duties at nearby Fort Myer, Virginia. A base official said McKinney would remain on the job pending a determination of whether any of the charges might be dismissed and whether he would be tried.</p>
<p>Conviction of adultery alone may be punished by jail and dismissal from the Army under military rules.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
