<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569669" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. MUNICIPAL FOCUS -- ends 1/4 to 3/8 higher.</title>
<headline>U.S. MUNICIPAL FOCUS -- ends 1/4 to 3/8 higher.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. municipal bonds were up 1/4 to 3/8 in late trading Thursday, reversing early weakness and tracing the Treasury market's late day gains.</p>
<p>&quot;We snapped back smartly,&quot; one trader said. &quot;We're up about 1/4 point.&quot; The trader attributed the gains to a rebound effect after Wednesday's post-auction selloff.</p>
<p>A market analyst said activity levels were light to moderate, and some modest bid-wanted lists circulated during the day.</p>
<p>Munis followed the direction of the benchmark 30-year Treasury bond Thursday, which was up 14/32 at 96-6/32 to yield 6.93 percent after trading lower in early action.</p>
<p>Late day muni secondary quotes were also showing some improvement after being flat at midday.</p>
<p>Bids on Chicago Board of Education AMBAC 5-3/4s of 2020 were down two basis points to 5.89 percent. Port of Seattle FGIC 5-1/2s of 2022 were also two basis points lower at 5.80 percent.</p>
<p>In debt futures, June municipal contracts reversed early losses to finish up 15/32 at 115-9/32. June T-bonds ended up 16/32 at 109-26/32. The MOB spread narrowed to 175 ticks from 176 ticks at the close Wednesday.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch &amp; Co. priced and repriced the day's largest new issue, a $111 million Massachusetts Port Authority deal. At the repricing, the top yield was 6.03 percent in 2039. To see the scale, double click on  nN08245516.</p>
<p>PaineWebber Inc. won the day's largest competitive deal, a $54 million Minnesota Housing Finance Agency deal which the firm reoffered to yield 5.35 percent in 2009. The 2017 term bonds were not formally reoffered.</p>
<p>--Steven Dickson, 212-859-1652</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
