<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569633" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Oil prices rally, wheat and gold also rise.</title>
<headline>Oil prices rally, wheat and gold also rise.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A rally in gasoline prices tied to rumors of production problems at southern refineries and signs that OPEC might take steps to tighten its exports combined to push oil prices higher on Thursday.</p>
<p>At the New York Mercantile Exchange, crude oil for June delivery closed 72 cents higher at $20.34 a barrel. June gasoline rose 1.58 cents a gallon to close at 62.50 cents and June heating oil rose 1.30 cents a gallon to 54.38.</p>
<p>Abdullah Salem al-Badri, president of the Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries, said he expected the group to stick to its 25.03 million barrel per day production ceiling at its meeting next month.</p>
<p>Badri, also Libya's oil minister, said demand was not strong enough to support any rise in the 11-member cartel's output, which reached 27.05 million bpd in April.</p>
<p>&quot;We are overproducing, yes, but I have contacted everyone and I hope we will have cooperation,&quot; he told Reuters while attending a conference in Iran.</p>
<p>&quot;They must address overproduction soon or the price will almost certainly fall,&quot; said Bob Finch, head trader of Vitol SA, the world's largest independent oil trading and refining company.</p>
<p>Oil prices have shed almost $7 a barrel since the start of the year.</p>
<p>Refined product prices were boosted by talk that Amoco Inc.'s Texas City, Texas, refinery and Conoco's Lake Charles, Louisiana, refinery had been slowed by operational problems. Both companies declined comment.</p>
<p>At the Chicago Board of Trade, wheat prices closed higher on continued good export demand as Japan bought 60,000 metric tons of U.S. wheat. Wheat for May delivery closed up 5 cents a bushel at $4.00.</p>
<p>&quot;They do need rain in the northwestern part of Kansas, but otherwise world weather is favorable for wheat,&quot; said Victor Lespinasse, a trader with Dean Witter brokerage in Chicago.</p>
<p>Dry weather in the western Midwest and some parts of the Plains was also a concern, though rains were forecast by some meteorologists for western Kansas and Texas next week.</p>
<p>But other forecasters expect hot, dry temperatures in the central and southern Plains through May. Wheat there, already hit by a freeze, badly needs cool, moist weather.</p>
<p>After the close of trading, a tour of 42 crop specialists estimated this year's wheat crop in Kansas would total 336.2 million bushels, up from 255 million last year when the crop was hit by drought. Kansas is the top-producing wheat state.</p>
<p>Precious metals prices gained, with gold for June delivery on the COMEX in New York closing up $2.40 an ounce at $344.80. The day's high at $346.60 was the highest since April 15.</p>
<p>&quot;It's starting to look positive, with the sharply lower U.S. dollar today helping to break gold and silver out of recent ranges, despite some producer selling overnight,&quot; said Refco economist James Steel.</p>
<p>The dollar's sharp slide overnight made gold cheaper for investors and fabricators in other currencies. The price of gold in yen terms fell to its lowest since January.</p>
<p>The strength of the dollar against yen in particular has been partly to blame for gold's slide to four-year lows earlier this year.</p>
<p>&quot;It's mostly technical, with the breakout of the recent range in gold and the strength of gold equities helping, but it's starting to look better for gold,&quot; Chase Manhattan New York managing director Dinsa Mehta said.</p>
<p>July silver at COMEX closed up 10.2 cents an ounce at $4.860 after seeing a six-week high at $4.880 on Thursday.</p>
<p>At the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, lumber prices soared in thin trade on reports of fresh strength in the cash market and a rumor of labor unrest at Canadian mills.</p>
<p>Lumber for May delivery ended up $16.80 per thousand board feet at $399.50.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
