<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569686" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ohio voters back four levies for troubled schools.</title>
<headline>Ohio voters back four levies for troubled schools.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ohio voters supported levy or tax referendums in four out of five troubled school districts that sought them in Tuesday's elections.</p>
<p>The approval rate for Ohio public school bond issues and tax levies rose slightly for the election this week over past years, a spokeswoman for the Ohio Department of Education said Thursday.</p>
<p>The requests did &quot;slightly better than average&quot; when compared to results from other primary elections over the last 10 years, Miriam Segaloff said.</p>
<p>Voters approved additional revenues in requests from four out of five school districts listed under a fiscal emergency or fiscal watch by Ohio Auditor Jim Petro.</p>
<p>A new levy request for the Switzerland of Ohio Local school district to fund operational expenses was &quot;handily&quot; defeated by voters, a district official noted.</p>
<p>Without it, the district will have to find some other way to account for approximately $1.5 million in operating funds and will likely have to make cuts by July 1 and plan for a new levy request and school bond issue in November, said Walter Calinger, administrative assistant for curriculum and instruction.</p>
<p>The district had sought a five-year levy that would have allowed it to restructure longterm debts accrued in a period of school consolidations, Calinger said.</p>
<p>The Monroe County district in far eastern Ohio now draws its approximately 3,100 students from a 525 square mile area, Calinger said.</p>
<p>Voters approved a levy renewal and new levy for the Osnaburg Local and Ledgemont Local school districts respectively. Both are on the auditor's fiscal emergency list.</p>
<p>Voters also approved a four-year income tax for the Massillon City school district, which is on the auditor's watch list, and a levy renewal for the Madison Local School District in Richland County, which is also on the fiscal watch list.</p>
<p>Ohio voters approved 17 school bond issues and rejected 25 others in the election as well.</p>
<p>((--David Bailey, 312-408-8647))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
