<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569637" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Rallying US crude prices sustain sharp gains late.</title>
<headline>Rallying US crude prices sustain sharp gains late.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. cash crude prices staged a rally Thursday, pushing outright benchmark crudes above $20.00 a barrel due to a sustained technical push higher on the NYMEX futures market.</p>
<p>June West Texas Intermediate/Cushing was around 70 cents higher at $20.30-40 a barrel late in the day, pulling even with July WTI and eliminating a weeks-old discount the prompt month held to the second month.</p>
<p>Paper market gains were underpinned by a jolt higher in gasoline values, amid bullish sentiment for prompt fundamentals.</p>
<p>News also played a role Thursday in the crude rally, though some traders shrugged off developments.</p>
<p>Earlier in the day, OPEC President Libyan Oil Minister Abdullah Salem al-Badri said he expected the group to roll over its 25.03 million barrels per day (bpd) quota at the next OPEC meeting in June.</p>
<p>Al-Badri spoke in Iran at an OPEC ministerial meeting where seven of the group's members agreed to push for compliance to current quotas in an effort to boost world prices.</p>
<p>Late news also aided outrights, with Washington stating it would push the United Nations to enforce sanctions against international airflights by Libya.</p>
<p>Tripoli is banned from such flights for not handing over supsected terrorists thought to be responsible for the Lockerbie bombing in 1988 of a Pan Am jet.</p>
<p>Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi reportedly traveled to Niger Thursday to lead Muslim prayers.</p>
<p>In the markets, crude traders said domestic grade barrels continued to pace a steady course for most sectors, though West Texas Sour/Midland returned to weaker differentials after rallying higher on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like people are playing around in the sour market, we were down to around a $1.30-35 discount on Wednesday but we're right back out to $1.60 today,&quot; said a Texas cash trader.</p>
<p>Late talk put WTS/Midland at minus $1.60-55 to the June WTI/Cushing, with Eugene Island talked around the same levels.</p>
<p>Light Louisiana Sweet/St. James was still at a three cents premium to the benchmark as the day ended. The only confirmed deals for LLS were at that mark, traders said.</p>
<p>A lack of Brent offerings in the U.S. Gulf allowed LLS to remain at a positive price to WTI.</p>
<p>&quot;Last month people were comfortable delivering Brent to the Merc (NYMEX), but that's not a viable alternative with Dated (Brent) hanging around 25 cents,&quot; said a cash dealer.</p>
<p>Traders also noted that sizable chunks of North Sea and West African barrels were headed to Far East destinations due to sharp shrinkage of Brent-Dubai spreads.</p>
<p>July Brent-Dubai was pegged around plus 90-95 cents Thursday, some 30-40 cents lower than recent days.</p>
<p>--Patrick Connole, NY Energy Desk, ((+1 212 859 1620))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
