<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569621" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Northeast sets nuclear chief's bonus plan.</title>
<headline>Northeast sets nuclear chief's bonus plan.</headline>
<dateline>HARTFORD 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of Northeast Utilities' nuclear operations will receive a stock bonus now worth about $350,000 if the Millstone complex is removed from a federal list of worst-run plants by late 1999, the company said in regulatory filings.</p>
<p>Bruce Kenyon will receive at least 39,585 shares of stock if the three Millstone nuclear plants in Waterford, Conn., are taken off the Nuclear Regulatory Commission's (NRC) &quot;watch list,&quot; Northeast said in documents filed April 29.  </p>
<p>The goal must be reached within three years of Kenyon's joining the company in September 1996, and the bonus is also contingent upon steady performance of the company's Seabrook reactor in New Hampshire, Northeast said.</p>
<p>Kenyon received a 1996 salary of $144,231 and a bonus of $400,000, Northeast said in the Securities and Exchange Commission documents.</p>
<p>The three Millstone units, with combined power capacity of 2,700 megawatts, have been shut since March 1996 amid safety concerns raised by the NRC.</p>
<p>Northeast has said it plans to have Millstone Unit No. 3 ready for restart in September, Unit No. 2 in November and Unit No. 1 in early 1998, pending NRC approval.</p>
<p>Northeast stock rose 1/4 to 8-7/8 on Thursday.</p>
<p>((--Hartford newsroom (860) 727-0224))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARTFORD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
