<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569648" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME live and feeder cattle futures close lower.</title>
<headline>CME live and feeder cattle futures close lower.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>CME live and feeder cattle futures closed lower, pulled down by expectations fed cattle markets will begin easing soon, traders said.</p>
<p>Live cattle closed 0.225 to 0.425 cent per lb lower with June off 0.400 at 64.825 cents. Feeder cattle ended 0.600 to 0.150 lower with August off 0.500 at 76.425 cents.</p>
<p>Expectations that increased fed cattle supplies are just ahead combined with fund rolling to push June to a one-week low by the close. Lower boxed beef values again at the midday quote stimulated increased ideas the beef complex may have topped out, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;The general feeling is that we are going to see bigger numbers come at us, in the cattle,&quot; said Don Roose, President of U.S. Commodities Inc.</p>
<p>Roose also said the market turned technically soft.</p>
<p>Early indications on next week's USDA Cattle-on-Feed report pointed to possibly heavy placements during April and large on-feed supplies as of May 1.</p>
<p>Early feedlot placement estimates by analysts for April were running as high as 127.5 percent of a year earlier and on-feed numbers as high as 111 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
