<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569693" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT soy products end mixed, soybeans hit old crop.</title>
<headline>CBOT soy products end mixed, soybeans hit old crop.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soy product futures ended mixed on Thursday with old crop months hit by spillover weakness from soybeans, pit sources said.</p>
<p>Nearby soybeans were battered by USDA weekly export figures which were at the low end of trade expectations. The bearishly construed soybean figure overshadowed soymeal sales that came in above expectations.</p>
<p>The U.S. Department of Agriculture put soymeal sales at 97,000 tonnes. That figure came in above trade expectations for 60,000 to 80,000 tonnes. Soyoil sales were a paltry 5,100 tonnes, which prompted some soymeal/soyoil spreading.</p>
<p>Cash sources said they expected Thursday's National Oilseed Processors Association weekly crush figure to come in between 23.9 million to 25 million bushels. Those figures were below last week's tally of 25.043 million bushels.</p>
<p>&quot;We're expecting to have a period of about three weeks now where weekly crush is expected to be low as crushers take downtime for routine maintenance,&quot; said Ann Frick, analyst with Prudential Securities.</p>
<p>Soymeal closed $1.90 per ton lower to $0.90 higher with July down $1.90 at $291.90. Soyoil ended 0.10 cent per lb lower to 0.04 cent higher with July down 0.10 at 24.74.  </p>
<p>However, Thursday's price action may actually encourage an increase in the crush pace. While nearby soybeans fell sharply, soymeal and soyoil ended only slightly lower, improving CBOT crush margins. CBOT put futures crush margins for the May contract up 6.52 cents per bushel at 44.42.</p>
<p>&quot;The crush markets widened out on the board so that's certainly not sending any signals to the crushers to slow down,&quot; Frick said.</p>
<p>Trade was said to be thin ahead of Monday's USDA supply and demand report. Many trade sources and analysts predicted USDA would further trim tight U.S. ending soybean stocks.</p>
<p>The market shrugged off reports after the close of trading Wednesday that the U.S. agricultural attache in Argentina had cut production estimates to 12.5 million tonnes from 13.25 reported last month.</p>
<p>On the day, funds were largely on the buy-side of soymeal and commercials underpinned the nearbys. Dean Witter bought 600 lots December, Refco Inc bought 400 July and 100 each August and September and Rand Financial bought 400 July, pit sources said. Cargill Inc, Continental Grain and ADM were also said to be buyers.</p>
<p>In soyoil, Prudential Securities sold 500 July, E.D. and F. Man International sold 300 lots July, Tenco Inc, Merrill Lynch and R.J. O'Brien each sold 200 July and Griffin Trading sold 500 July.</p>
<p>Soymeal volume was estimated by CBOT at 25,000 lots, compared with Wednesday's actual volume of 31,966. Soyoil volume was pegged at 20,000 lots, against Wednesday's actual of 19,386.</p>
<p>((Emily Kaiser 312-408-8749))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
