<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569741" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US budget deal seen unlikely to impact Fed policy.</title>
<headline>US budget deal seen unlikely to impact Fed policy.</headline>
<byline>Jose Paulo Vicente</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The balanced budget agreement reached by the White House and the Republican Congress is not expected to have a large influence on Federal Reserve monetary policy, Fed sources and public finance pundits said.</p>
<p>The budget accord announced last week, they said, was seen more as a continuation of current efforts to reduce the public deficit rather than a major overhaul of fiscal and tax policy.</p>
<p>&quot;The budget agreement just doesn't seem to be enough to have a big impact on the economy,&quot; a Federal Reserve source, who asked not to be named, told Reuters.  </p>
<p>&quot;There is not enough evidence that it (the budget accord) should have an impact on how the Fed sets its monetary policy,&quot; the source added.</p>
<p>In a recent interview with Reuters, the director of research at the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco Jack Beebe also said he did not think the accord was likely to change the way the Fed will conduct monetary policy.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think this (accord) is enough of a change in the direction of fiscal policy to matter a great deal to the way monetary policy has to be managed over the next several years,&quot; Beebe said earlier this week.  </p>
<p>Wall Street and academic economists said Fed Chairman Alan Greenspan has expressed willingness during recent speeches to adopt a more relaxed monetary policy in a bid to cushion the impact of deficit-reduction efforts on the overall economy.</p>
<p>But they were quick to note that the announced accord was not likely to change the overall economic scenario to a point that it would &quot;force&quot; the Fed to be less aggressive.</p>
<p>So the question is: How much easier can the Fed's monetary policy possibly be given the balanced budget agreement announced last week by the White House and Republican leaders?  </p>
<p>&quot;The answer is not much easier because really only about half as much has been done,&quot; said Brad DeLong, a former deputy assistant secretary of the Treasury for economic policy.</p>
<p>DeLong, who is currently an economics professor at the University of California at Berkeley, said he expects the federal deficit to be balanced by the year 2002 as planned.</p>
<p>He added, however, that the balanced budget deal does not assure a long-term solution for the U.S. deficit because it fails to fully address known potential problems, such as Social Security and Medicare.  </p>
<p>De Long said the agreement does not either solve or restore balance to the Social Security system or establish a long-run plan to bring the government's resources in balance with its commitments.</p>
<p>&quot;The goal line was defined as balance the budget in 2002 because that's a lot easier to do,&quot; DeLong said. &quot;(But) we are postponing a problem, I think. We're taking tiny steps towards solving a long-run problem.&quot;  </p>
<p>The balanced budget plan announced late last week includes an $85 billion net tax cut over five years, accommodating reductions in capital gains and estate taxes as well as a $500 per child tax credit.</p>
<p>The five-year budget pact also requires cuts in many government programs, including $115 billion in reductions in Medicare, the health care program for the elderly.</p>
<p>&quot;People migth think, 'Oh, the government is now back into balance.' But they're wrong.</p>
<p>&quot;It's back into balance for the next five or 10 years, but beyond that we still have a social insurance system designed for a 2.5 percent per year real wage growth economy and we have a 1.0 percent per year real wage growth economy,&quot; De Long said.</p>
<p>The Federal Reserve last changed monetary policy on March 25, when it raised its target for the federal funds rate by 25 basis points to 5.50 percent.</p>
<p>The central bank's policy-setting body, the Federal Open Market Committee, will meet next on May 20 to deliberate on monetary policy.</p>
<p>(( -- 212-869-1676 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
