<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569733" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: OPTIONS - U.S. T-bond vols mixed, eyes on July.</title>
<headline>OPTIONS - U.S. T-bond vols mixed, eyes on July.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Implied volatilities for U.S. Treasury bond options were mixed in relatively light mid-afternoon trade as the underlying market bounced from early lows to make mild gains on the day, dealers said.</p>
<p>Volatility for July T-bond futures options on the Chicago Board of Trade was buoyant as traders began focusing on the Federal Open Market Committee meeting on May 20, which would not be covered by the front-month June options.</p>
<p>&quot;Open interest is still pretty low in July, but it will pick up once people roll their June (positions) into July,&quot; said a brokerage trader at the CBOT.  </p>
<p>CBOT June T-bond futures options expire on May 16.</p>
<p>June volatility was little changed at around 7.9 percent, while July was up about 0.2 point at 8.2 percent and September was off a quarter point at around 8.2.</p>
<p>The brokerage trader noted that July options, which currently trade in the FLEX option pit, will move into the central bond pit from Sunday's night session.</p>
<p>&quot;Liquidity will be better when it comes into the big pit,&quot; he said, adding that price-sensitivity would probably also improve.  </p>
<p>Many of the biggest trades in the soon-to-expire June contracts were in spreads, in part to hedge the steep time decay, traders said.</p>
<p>An investment bank was said to have bought 3,000 lots of the June 108/109 put spread, while another firm bought 500 lots of June 110/111 call spread in a one-by-two ratio.</p>
<p>In general, volatilities were likely to remain under pressure as long as June futures stay within their recent 109-110 range, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;We got down to 108-30/32 this morning but volatility never really picked up,&quot; the brokerage trader said.  </p>
<p>Traders said the market was awaiting a speech by Federal Reserve chairman Alan Greenspan scheduled for tonight.</p>
<p>In Eurodollar options on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, volatilities were softer as futures bounced back and stayed within recent ranges.</p>
<p>Implied volatilities for September and December futures options were off marginally at around 9.8 and 11.2 percent respectively.</p>
<p>&quot;We couldn't get any follow-through,&quot; a bank trader said of Eurodollar futures. &quot;Some of the day-trading money tends to get out quickly.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;No one has any deep convictions any more,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>While most traders still believe the Fed will raise rates at the May FOMC meeting, opinions were more divided for further tightenings, he said, noting that a European firm was buying back-month futures aggressively and selling puts.</p>
<p>He said expectations for a limited Fed tightening and an improvement in the technical picture on the bond market could prompt interest in curve-flattening trades to pick up, keeping front-month Eurodollars lagging the rest of the market and dampening interest in front-end options.</p>
<p>-- Chicago Derivatives Desk ((312-408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail: derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
