<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569739" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. spot natgas supported by outage, cool weather.</title>
<headline>U.S. spot natgas supported by outage, cool weather.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. spot natgas prices began drifting lower Thursday morning, but shortly before nomination deadlines buyers scrambled for gas, thereby pushing prices higher ahead of cooler weather in the East and Midwest.</p>
<p>Prices at the Henry Hub, La, on average were down only one cent to a wide range of $2.30-2.36 per mmBtu despite the sharp downward turn in June Henry Hub futures to the high-$2.20s.</p>
<p>The outage at Entergy Corp's 936 megawatt River Bend nuclear unit in Louisiana, which is expected to last another one to two weeks, continued to keep supply tight and prices supported, traders said.  </p>
<p>Also, Entergy Corp's 858 MW Arkansas 2 nuclear unit is operating at 75 percent power for testing.</p>
<p>At the New York city-gate, prices were also steady to lower at $2.55-2.60 as forecasts called for temperatures to drop to about eight to 10 degrees below normal Saturday.</p>
<p>Appalachian prices slipped an average of five cents to $2.47-2.50 on Columbia and $2.49-2.55 on CNG.</p>
<p>In the Midcontinent, prices fell about one cent to $2.10-2.12, with Demarcation quoted mostly at $2.12-2.14.</p>
<p>Chicago city-gate values also eased by about one to two cents to the high-$2.30s to low-$2.40s.</p>
<p>In west Texas, a strong air conditioning demand and power outages kept Permian prices strong at $2.06-2.11. Similarly at the southern California border, prices were up one cent to $2.23-2.25.</p>
<p>A 750 MW coal-fired unit at the Four Corners power facility in Arizona will likely be down for a few days for repairs, the operator, Arizona Public Service said.</p>
<p>((--H McCulloch, New York Power Desk +212-859-1628))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
