<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569706" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kuwaiti, Illinois men indicted in plane parts scam.</title>
<headline>Kuwaiti, Illinois men indicted in plane parts scam.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A London-based Kuwaiti and three Americans have been indicted for selling damaged parts scavenged from two aircraft destroyed by Iraqi troops in Kuwait during the Gulf War, prosecutors said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The 25-count indictment unsealed in Chicago followed the arrest in Hawaii on Tuesday of Kuwaiti citizen Faleh Al-Rashidi, a parts dealer operating in London.</p>
<p>The multi-billion-dollar used airplane parts market has come under increasing scrutiny because unscrupulous dealers reap huge profits from selling parts that should be scrapped.</p>
<p>U.S. authorities have indicted 130 people in the past seven years for dealing in non-airworthy parts.</p>
<p>In the current case, charred parts were scavenged from a British Airways Boeing 747 and a Kuwaiti McDonnell-Douglas DC-9 destroyed by occupying Iraqi troops on Kuwait City's airport tarmac in 1991.</p>
<p>With the aid of two conspirators who have not been charged, the four men allegedly falsified insurance and airline documents to obscure the origin of the parts and sold them to brokers.</p>
<p>&quot;These parts were sold to at least 10 customers; brokers who in turn sell parts to airlines both in the United States and other countries,&quot; U.S. Attorney for the Northern District of Illinois Jim Burns said.</p>
<p>Burns said federal authorities were satisfied that airlines that obtained the roughly $500,000 worth of faulty bolts, fan blades and other parts scavenged from Kuwait had replaced them.</p>
<p>Federal authorities also seized three truckloads of parts -- representing 90 percent of the parts smuggled into the United States from the two planes in Kuwait -- at the now-defunct Navaero Aviation Corp. in the Chicago suburb of Alsip.</p>
<p>Also indicted on multiple fraud counts were Navaero's former chief executive officer Robert Mansfield, along with salesmen Dennis McCormick and David Dohm. All three were expected to turn themselves in for arraignment, and Rashidi was to be transported to Chicago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KUWAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
