<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569702" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT soybeans end mixed, nearbys down on exports.</title>
<headline>CBOT soybeans end mixed, nearbys down on exports.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soybean futures closed mixed on Thursday with old crop contracts down on lackluster USDA weekly export sales data which suggested prices had risen enough to ration demand, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;We had a poor export inspections figure last Monday and then the number today was disappointing,&quot; said Ann Frick, analyst with Prudential Securities. &quot;We're expecting to have a period of about three weeks now where weekly crush is expected to be low as crushers take downtime for routine maintenance.&quot;</p>
<p>USDA put net export sales at 238,900 tonnes, which was at the low end of expectations for 200,000 to 400,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Floor sources said the sales figure, combined with Monday's USDA weekly export inspections figure, suggested world demand was tapering off in the wake of high U.S. prices and abundant South American supplies.</p>
<p>The sales figures spurred active unwinding of bull spreads. Traders said buyers were wary of the July contract which topped the $9.00 per bushel mark for the first time this week but failed to hold the gains. Meanwhile, November drew strength on ideas end-users would start buying new crop.</p>
<p>Soybeans ended 8-1/2 cents per bushel lower to 1-3/4 cents higher with July down eight at $8.84.  </p>
<p>&quot;We've been making contract highs here the last several days but there just isn't any follow through to the upside,&quot; Frick said. &quot;The July/November spread is weak. There's some uncertainty in the market right now.&quot;</p>
<p>The July/November spread was further weakened by outlooks for new crop demand to supplant old crop business. Some trade sources speculated end-users would switch old crop purchases to new crop which was priced nearly $2 per bushel lower.</p>
<p>Brazil's aggressive export pace was also deemed supportive to U.S. new crop supplies. Traders said Brazil's export program was running at such a strong pace that the country would likely have to import U.S. new crop soybeans this fall.</p>
<p>&quot;It makes perfect sense,&quot; one trader said. &quot;Why shouldn't they sell at $9.00 and buy our new crop at $7.00? Sounds like a good trade to me.&quot;</p>
<p>The CBOT July/November spread lost nine cents per bushel to close at $1.75-1/2, premium July.</p>
<p>Talk China bought up to 300,000 tonnes of South American soy was deemed mildly supportive but trade sources said China rumors had been rampant for a week and the floor was reluctant to believe them.</p>
<p>The trade shrugged off reports after the CBOT close Wednesday that the U.S. agricultural attache in Argentina had cut production estimates to 12.5 million tonnes from 13.25 reported last month.</p>
<p>On the day, funds sold at least 13 million bushels. Refco Inc sold six million bushels July, Smith Barney sold two million July and one million August and Prudential Securities sold two million July.</p>
<p>In spread action, Prudential spread 1.6 million November/July at $1.76-1/2 to $1.77, premium July, and Iowa Grain spread 0.5 million November/July at $1.77-1/2.</p>
<p>In options, Lind-Waldock bought 1,200 July $9.25 calls and sold 1,200 July $8.75 calls at 17-1/2 cents. Lind-Waldock also bought 700 July $9.25 calls and sold 700 July $9.75 calls at 9-1/2 cents.</p>
<p>Soybean futures volume was estimated by CBOT at 60,000 contracts, compared with Wednesday's actual volume of 61,800.</p>
<p>((Emily Kaiser 312-408-8749))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
