<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569710" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT wheat ends up on commercial buying, weather.</title>
<headline>CBOT wheat ends up on commercial buying, weather.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soft red winter wheat futures ended higher Thursday, boosted by commercial buying and forecasts for dry weather in the US Plains, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Commercials have been buyers again today in the wheat pit and I think that's why we're up,&quot; said one floor trader.</p>
<p>The wheat market has fallen to levels that end-users are finding attractive, so over the past two days, traders have noted fresh export sales and commercial buying.</p>
<p>Overnight Wednesday, Japan bought 60,000 tonnes of U.S. wheat. That purchase followed moderate to heavy buying by other Asian countries this week.</p>
<p>Long-term forecasts for hot, dry weather in the U.S. southern Plains generated concern about the developing hard red winter wheat crops and lifted prices, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;They do need rain in the northwestern part of Kansas, but otherwise world weather is favorable for wheat,&quot; said Victor Lespinasse, trader with Dean Witter brokerage in Chicago.</p>
<p>Several private forecasters see hot and dry temperatures in the Central and Southern Plains through May, and the freeze-damaged crop is said to need cool and moist weather.</p>
<p>CBOT wheat settled two to five cents per bushel higher, with July up 4-3/4 at $4.09.  </p>
<p>Traders also eagerly awaited final results from the Wheat Quality Council Tour's Kansas wheat tour because there is vast uncertainty over how much freeze damage the crop suffered.</p>
<p>After the market closed, the tour forecast Kansas wheat production to be 336.2 million bushels and estimated the states average yield at 36.8 bushels per acre.</p>
<p>Lower-than-expected weekly export sales of 176,200 tonnes had little impcat on market prices Thursday. The sales came in below expectations for 200,000 to 300,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>On the day, Cargill bought 3.5 million bushels July, FIMAT bought three million, Refco bought two million December, and LIT sold four million bushels, pit sources said.</p>
<p>In options trade, Tenco bought 100 July $4.00 puts and 100 $4.00 July calls. Tenco also bought 100 July $3.60 calls and sold 100 $3.60 puts.</p>
<p>Volume was estimated at 18,000 contracts, versus Wednesday's final volume of 15,357 contracts, according to CBOT data.</p>
<p>((Anna Driver 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
