<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569743" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Enova says NAFTA aids Mexico natgas deals.</title>
<headline>Enova says NAFTA aids Mexico natgas deals.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) along with actions like President Clinton's visit to Mexico this week, are key to the expansion of U.S. natural gas interests south of the border, said Enova Corp Chief Executive Officer Stephen Baum.</p>
<p>In a telephone interview with Reuters on Wednesday, Baum applauded Clinton's handling of Mexican anxieties about its northern neighbor.</p>
<p>&quot;Clinton's tone couldn't have been better. There was none of the arrogance that sometimes attends U.S. representatives coming to Mexico.&quot;</p>
<p>Enova, parent of San Diego Gas &amp; Electric Co, is interested in developing significant infrastructure in Mexico, Baum said.</p>
<p>So far, activities have focused on natural gas distribution projects, but opportunities in co-generation and cross-border energy trade are likely to develop as the U.S. power market is deregulated, he added.</p>
<p>Enova and Pacific Enterprises, which plan to merge by early next year, have won bids for natgas distribution concessions in Mexicali and Chihuahua.</p>
<p>The companies, in a venture with Mexico's Proxima Gas, have said they plan to bid for distribution permits in Toluca, Monterray and Mexico City, to be tendered later this year.</p>
<p>The consortium, along with a unit of Bechtel and PG&amp;E Enterprises, also plans to bid on construction of the Rosarito power generating plant in Baja Calfiornia.</p>
<p>Mexico has a preference toward building its own indigenous power plants, but where (power transmission) interconnections exist, they are importing electricity from the U.S., the Enova CEO said.</p>
<p>Baum applauded Clinton's attitude during this week's visit to Mexico and said expansion of NAFTA would be beneficial to U.S. businesses.</p>
<p>&quot;The root cause of immigration problems and border problems is the lack of jobs in Mexico. What we are doing is building a gas infrastructure that brings manufacturing opportunities to Mexico,&quot; Baum said.</p>
<p>((--Los Angeles bureau + 1 213 955 6761))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
