<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569773" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Top U.S. military officer to visit China.</title>
<headline>Top U.S. military officer to visit China.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Army Gen. John Shalikashvili, chairman of the U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff, will visit China next week as part of a programme to improve U.S.-China military ties, the Pentagon said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The four-day visit, which begins on Monday, will be the first by the top U.S. military officer to China since Army Gen. John Vessey went there in 1983, the Defence Department said.  </p>
<p>Pentagon spokesman Ken Bacon told reporters that Shalikashvili would meet his counterpart, Gen. Fu Quanyou, chief of the general staff department of the People's Liberation Army, and also visit military facilities and units.</p>
<p>Shalikashvili will make a speech at the PLA'S National Defence University, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;This is...part of our programme of strengthening military-to-military relationships between China and the United States,&quot; Bacon said.</p>
<p>&quot;The goal is to increase understanding and transparency so that we have a clearer idea of how each military establishment operates so we can do more to cooperate with each other when necessary.&quot;</p>
<p>Chinese Defence Minister Chi Haotian visited the United States last year and U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen has said that he will visit China before the end of this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
