<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569776" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Plains feedlot cattle slow at $69 - feedlots.</title>
<headline>U.S. Plains feedlot cattle slow at $69 - feedlots.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Plains feedlot cattle sales were light near midday Thursday at $69.00 per cwt, steady with active trade on Tuesday, feedlot sources said.</p>
<p>About 4,000 steers and heifers that will likely grade select and choice were sold in the Texas Panhandle and western Oklahoma area, they said. The sales bring Panhandle week-to-date sales near 85,000.</p>
<p>There were no reported sales in Kansas, but light trade was also expected at $69.00, the sources said.</p>
<p>Week to date sales in Kansas by early Thursday were pegged near 88,000 head, they said.  </p>
<p>Most of this week's showlists were close to being sold out, market sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;There's no wall of cattle out there. People have done a good job of staying current,&quot; one Kansas feedlot manager said.</p>
<p>Fed cattle prices were lifted this week by strong demand from packers looking to fill beef orders from retailers stocking up for Memorial Day promotions, market sources said.</p>
<p>However, lower beef prices on Wednesday suggested that holiday beef demand may have peaked, they said.</p>
<p>Beef prices at midday were quoted down $0.18 to $0.62 per cwt, with 210 fabricated beef loads sold, USDA reported.</p>
<p>((Bob Janis 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
