<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569735" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Airways future still in doubt despite plan.</title>
<headline>US Airways future still in doubt despite plan.</headline>
<byline>Robin Sidel</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A restructuring announced Thursday by US Airways Group Inc does little to ensure the long-term viability of the troubled carrier which has lagged its competitors for years, industry experts said.</p>
<p>Despite the latest plan, a new name, and a new logo, the former USAir remains plagued by the highest cost structure in the industry and desperately needs to reach a cost-cutting pact with its unionized pilots.</p>
<p>&quot;They need a contract that is going to change their competitive position,&quot; said Vivian Lee of Bankers Trust.  </p>
<p>The Arlington, Va.-based airline earlier announced a restructuring that calls for it to eliminate unprofitable routes, consolidate facilities and reduce its fleet.</p>
<p>Investors reacted positively to the news, bidding shares of US Airways up 2-3/8 to 34-1/8.</p>
<p>But Wall Street analysts said the actions reflect a tiny portion of what is needed to fix the airline.  They also noted other airlines took the same measures three or four years ago when carriers were losing billions of dollars.  Those steps, combined with improved ecomonic conditions, have resulted in widespread profitability for major carriers.  </p>
<p>&quot;I think these are moves the company ultimately had to make.  I think they are smart moves, but I remain hopeful that they will ultimately get an agreement with their employees,&quot; said Candace Browning of Merrill Lynch.</p>
<p>The airline has been trying for years to negotiate a new cost-saving contract with its pilots, warning that it would be forced to shrink the airline if it did not set a new pact. Although negotiations are continuing, robust industry trends have propelled USAirways' earnings and made it more difficult for management to convince workers that the carrier is facing tough times.  </p>
<p>The restructuring announced Thursday was possible because a &quot;no furlough&quot; clause in the pilots' contract is set to expire June 30.  The airline has announced plans to lay off 103 of its 5,000 pilots starting July 1.</p>
<p>Analysts said USAirways has been losing millions of dollars in the nine cities where service will be discontinued, including San Antonio, Cincinnati and Daytona Beach.</p>
<p>&quot;They've given those cities a long time and they just are not going to turn profitable so they're closing them, which is a smart thing to do,&quot; Browning said.</p>
<p>Helane Becker of Smith Barney sees more opportunities for US Airways to reduce unprofitable flying in Florida, Boston and on transcontinental routes.</p>
<p>&quot;This is just the beginning.  It's the tip of the iceberg,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The pilots union did not have an immediate response to the company's announcement, but a May 6 tape-recorded message to members said that the union opposes the furloughs and will consider its alternatives, including legal action.</p>
<p>The union also said the next negotiating session is set for May 9.</p>
<p>Shares of other major airlines rose sharply on Thursday on views they will benefit from US Airways' flight cutbacks. The gains also were in line with a rise in the broader market.</p>
<p>Continental Airlines Inc stock rose two to 34-3/8, UAL Corp gained 2-1/4 to 75-3/4, AMR Corp rose 1-1/2 to 94-1/2 and Delta Air Lines Inc climbed 1-7/8 to 96-1/8.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
