<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569703" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: McVeigh letter calls for action against &quot;bastards&quot;.</title>
<headline>McVeigh letter calls for action against &quot;bastards&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Arthur Spiegelman</byline>
<dateline>DENVER 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The prosecution in the Oklahoma City bombing trial on Thursday read into evidence a dramatic letter from defendant Timothy McVeigh in which he described himself as becoming &quot;an animal&quot; ready to &quot;cut the bastards' heads off.&quot;</p>
<p>The often vague letter, written two months before the April 19, 1995, bombing of the Alfred P. Murrah federal building, was to a woman friend in Michigan, trying to get her to join a &quot;citizens militia,&quot; a self-styled patriotic group opposed to the federal government.</p>
<p>The woman became so upset by the letter that she gave it to another McVeigh friend, Michigan farmworker Kevin Nicholas, who testified on Thursday that he recognised it as being in McVeigh's handwriting. The woman was not called as a witness.</p>
<p>Prosecutors contend that McVeigh was so upset by the 1993 government confrontation with the Branch Davidian religious cult in Waco, Texas, and a previous shootout with rightwing militant Randy Weaver, that he decided to take direct action and blow up the Murrah building, killing 168 people.</p>
<p>In the letter, the decorated Gulf War veteran said his body was wearing out, possibly from his war service, and &quot;I might as well do something good while I can still be 100 percent effective. My whole mindset has shifted from the intellectual to the animal.</p>
<p>&quot;You only live once and it is better to burn out than to rot away in some nursing home.&quot;</p>
<p>He added, &quot;Cut the bastards' heads off, shove s--- down their necks and I will show you how with a simple pocket knife.&quot;</p>
<p>The letter asked the woman if she wanted to be put in touch with people who could get her into the militia movement, even though her name could wind up on a &quot;super-computer&quot; in Belgium where the names of 300,000 subversives and suspected terrorists are kept.</p>
<p>He said if people were afraid to get on such a list, &quot;then we have lost already. The Founding Fathers, if they had been afraid, then we would still be under the tyrannical rule of the crown.&quot;</p>
<p>He added he was now &quot;associated with direct action types.&quot; The letter made no mention of Waco but did talk of the FBI shooting of Weaver's wife and added, &quot;What goes around, comes around.&quot;</p>
<p>In earlier testimony on Thursday, an FBI computer expert said a telephone calling card, which the prosecution contends belonged to McVeigh, was used to call the agency that rented the Ryder truck employed in the bombing.</p>
<p>Computer expert Frederick Dexter surprised the defence during a tense cross-examination when he insisted he could prove the card was used to call Elliott's Body Shop, a Ryder rental station, in Junction City, Kansas, from a nearby bus terminal despite a missing phone record.</p>
<p>&quot;You can't tell me the call was made from the bus depot,&quot; said defence attorney Cheryl Ramsey. &quot;Yes, I can,&quot; Dexter shot back, saying he had used alternative records to trace where the April 14, 1995, call originated and which telephone debit card was used.</p>
<p>For the better part of three days, the prosecution has put into evidence calls made from a pre-paid calling card issued to a &quot;Daryl Bridges,&quot; saying the false name was a front for McVeigh and his alleged co-conspirator Terry Nichols, who will be tried later. The card was found during a search of Nichols's home by the FBI.</p>
<p>The prosecution admits it cannot prove who made the calls to such places as the rental agency, Nichols' home and to an array of companies that sold bomb-making components.</p>
<p>It also admits it cannot prove what was said in the calls, but it maintains the calls mirror McVeigh's trips through the country and show a pattern of conspiracy that ended with the bombing.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DENVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
