<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569736" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX Hub natgas still down late, longs exit.</title>
<headline>NYMEX Hub natgas still down late, longs exit.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX Henry Hub natgas futures remained broadly lower late Thursday in moderate trade, still undermined by long liquidation after recent gains amid talk of slightly softer physical prices, industry sources said.</p>
<p>At 1405 EDT, June stumbled 6.8 cents to $2.285 per million British thermal units, while July was 7.5 cents lower at $2.30. Most other deferreds were down by 1.5 to 6.2 cents.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we may have exhausted the (up) move for a while. There are no new shorts in here. To assume we took out most of the weak shorts is probably a valid assumption, so who new is going to buy at these levels,&quot; said one Texas trader.  </p>
<p>But he agreed physical buyers likely went into May short, leaving them vulnerable to firmer prices when broader cooling loads kick in.</p>
<p>&quot;People went into the month short physical gas again. Now we need to see some A/C (air conditioning) demand to see how the market reacts,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Technical traders said the explosive growth in open interest as prices moved up over the last week also had many expecting a sharp profit-taking pullback.</p>
<p>They pegged resistance in June at the new high of $2.43 and then at $2.47-50. Support was seen first at $2.20, with major buying likely at $2.05 and then along the up trendline around $2.04.</p>
<p>In the cash, Gulf Coast swing prices were steady to down slightly Thursday at about the $2.30 level, with Hub gas mostly quoted at $2.31-2.34. Midcon pipes also were unchanged to modestly lower but still mostly in the $2.10-15 range. New York city gate gas also lost ground to the $2.55-60 area.</p>
<p>Temperatures for most of the East and Midwest are expected to remain below normal into the weekend, then turn milder by early next week, Weather Services Corp.</p>
<p>NYMEX said 34,459 contracts traded at 1340 EDT.</p>
<p>On the KCBT, June was still down by three cents at $2.15, while deferreds were steady to five cents lower. The East/West spread narrowed by 3.8 cents to 13.5 cents (NYMEX premium).</p>
<p>((J Silha, New York Power Desk 212-859-1624))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
