<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569717" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: OPTIONS - Dlr/yen vols climb after spot tumbles.</title>
<headline>OPTIONS - Dlr/yen vols climb after spot tumbles.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Implied volatilities for dollar/yen options were strongly higher in U.S. trading Thursday after spot sank overnight on remarks by a senior Japanese Finance Ministry official about a stronger yen.</p>
<p>The dollar shed more than a full yen in Tokyo after Eisuke Sakakibara told a parliamentary panel it was possible the Japanese currency could strengthen to 103 yen.</p>
<p>Sakakibara also offered up a reminder that Japanese individuals should consider currency risk when investing overseas, which was taken as an indication of the government's resolve to support the yen, options traders said.  </p>
<p>Strong bidding for currency calls, evident throughout the week, continued during the session, they said. Risk reversals, the put/call pricing differential, widened further to reflect the trend, pushing to 0.7/1.0 in favor of yen calls on the 25-delta options.</p>
<p>By afternoon, the dollar was bid at 123.81 yen, off its lows.</p>
<p>Implied volatility for one-month dollar/yen options climbed to 9.20/9.45 percent Thursday from 8.65/8.85 percent the previous session.  </p>
<p>Dollar/mark volatility firmed but only slightly, rising to 8.50/8.75 percent from 8.45/8.65 percent previously.</p>
<p>An options trader for a U.S. bank said it would take a break below the psychologically important 1.70 level to roil dollar/mark volatility.</p>
<p>So far, the spot was holding above that level after skidding overnight along with dollar/yen.</p>
<p>Risk reversals for dollar/mark shifted to a mark call skew of 0.1/0.4 from a narrow mark put bias the day before.  </p>
<p>Options traders said a large option in the 1.71 mark strike was set to expire Friday, which could have a gravitational pull on the spot price because the investor who is long the option has incentive to sell dollars above 1.71 to defend the position.</p>
<p>Traders also noted brisk activity in sterling/mark and dollar/sterling options during the session amid lingering fear of Labour devaluation that weighed on the U.K. currency.</p>
<p>Susan Kelly, Chicago Derivatives Desk ((312-408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail: derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
