<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569719" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Futures funds do well in currencies in April.</title>
<headline>Futures funds do well in currencies in April.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Futures fund managers who trade the currency markets were the top performers for the month of April, according to fund monitor TASS Management Ltd.</p>
<p>Managed futures funds realised most of their gains during April by shorting the Japanese yen and deutschemark against the U.S. dollar, but performance in the managed futures industry for the month overall was lackluster, TASS chief executive Nicola Meaden said.</p>
<p>The yen hit a four and half year low against the U.S dollar in April, while the mark saw a three and half year low against the dollar.</p>
<p>&quot;April was a bit of a disappointment, especially as compared with performance during the first quarter, Meaden said. &quot;Volatility in the U.S. markets presented fund managers with a difficult trading environment.&quot;</p>
<p>Shifts in the short term trading trends of both U.S. equities and fixed income markets were cited as some of the key reasons April was a difficult month, but good profits were realized in base metals by going long zinc, nickel and lead, and the grains were also profitable from the long side, Meaden said.</p>
<p>The TASS Management monthly report follows the performance of 70 futures and currency managers, each with a minimum of $45 million under management.</p>
<p>TASS Management Ltd is a London-based research company which monitors about 1,600 alternative investment managers with about $11 billion in assets under management globally.</p>
<p>The &quot;alternative investment&quot; universe includes hedge funds, CTAs, managed currency managers, emerging market funds and funds of funds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
