<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569712" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. man wants doctor to help him kill himself.</title>
<headline>U.S. man wants doctor to help him kill himself.</headline>
<byline>Michael Peltier</byline>
<dateline>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Moments after the Florida Supreme Court finished hearing arguments in his case, AIDS patient Charles Hall was emphatic: the state of Florida should let him kill himself and let his doctor help.</p>
<p>&quot;Two judges have already made their rulings in this case,&quot; said the wheelchair-bound Hall, whose blue suit fit loosely over his 110-pound (50-kg) frame.</p>
<p>&quot;Why do they have to keep pushing it, causing me more grief and pain. Why not just let me die in peace?&quot;</p>
<p>For Hall, a 35-year-old Citrus County man who is dying, the court hearing on Thursday in Tallahassee was yet another hurdle in his quest to legally end his life when he chooses, with the help of a physician he trusts.</p>
<p>In January, a state circuit judge in Palm Beach County granted Hall's request, citing a provision in Florida's Constitution that guarantees a resident's right to privacy.</p>
<p>In striking down a 129-year-old state law prohibiting assisted suicide, Judge S. Joseph Davis ruled the state did not have an &quot;unbridled&quot; interest in preserving life when it comes to personal medical decisions.</p>
<p>The state immediately appealed.</p>
<p>For opponents of physician-assisted suicide, the issue is not whether patients should have the right to end their lives, but if doctors should be active participants in the process.</p>
<p>Physicians are allowed to withhold food and water from terminally ill patients. But critics say physicians should not be allowed to recommend and possibly administer the medical instrument of death.</p>
<p>&quot;Our hearts go out to Mr. Hall,&quot; said Jim Towey, head of the Florida Commission on Ageing with Dignity, an opponent to physician-assisted suicide. &quot;But when it gets down to it, he's asking for something from the state of Florida that is going to affect millions of people, particularly the poor, the handicapped and the elderly.&quot;</p>
<p>Oregon is the only state to legalise physician-assisted suicide. In contrast, 35 states have laws expressly forbidding assisted suicide. Nine states have common law prohibitions and in five states the laws are unclear.</p>
<p>The 1994 Oregon law required at least a 48-hour cooling off period and confirmation of the patient's diagnosis from another physician.</p>
<p>In 1995, a federal district judge declared the law unconstitutional, although the American Hemlock Society has appealed the decision. Until it is resolved, a permanent injunction prohibits the law's implementation.</p>
<p>The Hemlock Society argues for an individual's right to control how his or her life ends.</p>
<p>Dr. Cecil McIver, a soft-spoken 73-year-old physician from Jupiter, Florida, has agreed to assist Hall if he decides to end his life. McIver, a Hemlock Society member, could face 15 year in prison for helping Hall.</p>
<p>Two other patients whom McIver also agreed to help have since died during the appeal process. &quot;I'm looking out for the best interest of the patients, first, last and all the time,&quot; McIver said following oral arguments on Thursday.</p>
<p>For Hall, who wears a gold angel pin on his hat, a gift from an attendant, McIver will be acting in his best interest if the day comes when he wants to end the pain.</p>
<p>&quot;To me it's not murder, It's caring about people,&quot; Hall said. &quot;That's what a physician is supposed to do.&quot;</p>
<p>The court did not say when it would rule.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLAHASSEE, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
