<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569724" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chrysler, BMW plan joint plant in Brazil.</title>
<headline>Chrysler, BMW plan joint plant in Brazil.</headline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bayerische Motoren-Werke AG and Chrysler Corp. said Thursday they plan to build a new joint venture engine plant in Brazil next to a new Chrysler truck plant.</p>
<p>The $500 million plant will be able to produce up to 400,000 engines a year. Construction is expected to begin before the end of 1997, and when the plant reaches full capacity, it could employ about 1,200 people, the companies said.</p>
<p>The plant will produce newly designed 1.4 litre and 1.6 litre engines to power future small cars from Chrysler and the Rover Group, a BMW company. BMW and Chrysler will have equal interests in the engine company, they said.</p>
<p>The joint venture company has yet to be named. BMW and Chrysler said the forming of the joint venture was announced last October at the Paris Motor Show, but the location for the plant was not decided until now.</p>
<p>The site is in the town of Campo Largo, near Curitiba, Parana.</p>
<p>&quot;This is another important step in furthering the internationalization of BMW,&quot; said Henrich Heitmann, sales director for BMW America. &quot;This plant will provide us with direct access to the market and a stable sales outlet with good long-term prospects.&quot;</p>
<p>Chrysler plans to break ground this year on a plant that will produce 12,000 Dakota pickup trucks a year for the South American market.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
