<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569768" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Greenwich loses Southwest repair contract.</title>
<headline>Greenwich loses Southwest repair contract.</headline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greenwich Air Services Inc said that it will lose the contract to overhaul Southwest Airlines Co's engines to General Electric Co's General Electric Engine Services Inc.</p>
<p>Greenwich said the Southwest contract accounted for approximately five percent of its total revenues.</p>
<p>Greenwich has been servicing a portion of these engines under an agreement with Southwest which expired at the end of 1996 and which had been renewed on an interim basis pending the results of competitive bidding for a new long-term agreement.  </p>
<p>Greenwich said that Southwest Airlines has signed a letter of intent to enter into a long-term agreement with General Electric Engine Services for the repair and overhaul of Southwest's CFM56 and JT8D engines, commencing in the second half of this calendar year.</p>
<p>Greenwich's Chairman and CEO, Eugene Conese, said &quot;We are disappointed in the results of the Southwest decision, as we and other engine companies competed vigorously with GE for the work.  However, in the past, Greenwich has demonstrated the ability to capture new business when current business was lost due to pricing, and we are already making plans to replace this lost business.&quot;</p>
<p>As previously reported in March, Greenwich and General Electric have entered into an agreement and plan of merger which Greenwich anticipates will occur within the next few months.</p>
<p>Greenwich Air repairs and overhauls gas turbine engines.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640048">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
