<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569896" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Plane drops fuel tanks over Karachi, 5 die.</title>
<headline>Plane drops fuel tanks over Karachi, 5 die.</headline>
<byline>Amir Zia</byline>
<dateline>KARACHI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Pakistan Air Force plane dumped its fuel tanks over a residential area in Karachi on Thursday, setting off a fire that killed at least five people and injured eight, police said.</p>
<p>The pilot of the Mirage fighter jet had to jettison the tanks after the aircraft developed engine trouble on a routine training flight early on Thursday, an official from the joint public relations department of the Pakistan Army, Air Force and Navy said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was an engine fault in the plane and the pilot was forced to eject the fuel tanks to make a safe landing,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Witnesses said fire broke out when one of the fuel tanks fell on Gharibabad, a heavily populated residential area in Karachi's District Central.</p>
<p>Police said five people, including one child, died in the blaze. A police official earlier said four children died.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Sattar Edhi Ambulance Services said at least 10 people were killed.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a loud explosion...I thought a bomb had exploded,&quot; said teenager Rashid, who lives nearby.</p>
<p>&quot;When I came out I saw neighbouring houses in a blaze.&quot;</p>
<p>Deputy Superintendent of Police Khawja Nisar said only one of the tanks from the fighter exploded.</p>
<p>&quot;One fuel tank which fell in Gharibabad area exploded, the other one which fell in nearby Sharifabad locality did not explode and resulted only in minor injuries,&quot; he said</p>
<p>&quot;We were lucky that the incident occurred early in the morning. Casualties could have been much higher if shops were open and there had been traffic on the road.&quot;</p>
<p>Witnesses said a female school teacher and teenage boy who were standing on the road were critically injured in the blaze.</p>
<p>&quot;I saw them burning in front my eyes but could do nothing,&quot; said Rashid.</p>
<p>Ajmal, another witness, said: &quot;I was standing outside when the accident had occurred. First the plane flew past and then we heard explosion. I thought the plane had fired rockets.&quot;</p>
<p>The plane landed safely at an air force base in Karachi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARACHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
