<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569880" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Poll shows French election race at tightest yet.</title>
<headline>Poll shows French election race at tightest yet.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>An opinion poll on Thursday showed France's parliamentary election race at its tightest yet, with the left-wing opposition snapping at the heels of the ruling centre-right coalition.</p>
<p>The Ipsos survey for the weekly Le Point magazine projected the coalition would get 290 seats in the 577-seat National Assembly in the May 25-June 1 vote, just one seat more than is needed for a majority. The Socialists and their allies would win 264, Communists 22 and the far-right National Front one.  </p>
<p>It was the narrowest lead for Prime Minister Alain Juppe's coalition, which now has a huge majority with 464 seats, since President Jacques Chirac called the early election last month.</p>
<p>Two previous Ipsos polls had given the coalition 331 and 292 seats. Polls by other institutes have also found a tightening race, although none has yet given the left a majority of seats.</p>
<p>Of 1,591 voters interviewed on May 6 and 7, 45 percent thought the centre-right had the greatest chance of victory, and just 23 percent reckoned the left was best placed.</p>
<p>But 33 percent said they would prefer opposition Socialist leader Lionel Jospin as prime minister against 32 percent who favoured Juppe. Chirac called the vote saying that France needs a &quot;new elan&quot; to fight record unemployment and enter a single European currency from a position of strength.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
