<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569866" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: U.N. Sahara envoy, James Baker, to revisit region.</title>
<headline>U.N. Sahara envoy, James Baker, to revisit region.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Goodman</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.N. envoy dealing with the problem of Western Sahara, former U.S. Secretary of State James Baker, will return to the area in June and then make recommendations on the future of the disputed territory, Secretary-General Kofi Annan said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Annan then hoped to be able to submit a comprehensive report to the Security Council on the former Spanish colony, claimed by both Morocco and the Algerian-backed Polisario Front independence movement.</p>
<p>A U.N.-organised referendum to decide the future of Western Sahara was originally scheduled for January 1992 but has repeatedly been postponed because of differences between the two sides over who should be eligible to vote. A ceasefire has been in force since September 1991.</p>
<p>Baker last month carried out an exploratory trip to Morocco, Algeria and Mauritania and to Polisario's headquarters at Tindouf, near Algeria's border with Western Sahara.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Baker will return to the region in June, after which he will report to me on his findings and recommendations,&quot; Annan said in a written report.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope to be in a position thereafter to submit to the Security Council a comprehensive report on all aspects of the Western Sahara issue,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Annan, meanwhile, recommended a four-month extension, until Sept. 30, of the U.N. force in the territory, called the U.N. Mission for the Referendum in Western Sahara (MINURSO). It consists of 228 military observers and support troops and its six-month mandate expires on May 31.</p>
<p>When Baker was appointed Annan's personal envoy in March, his mandate was to recommend whether the U.N. peace plan calling for a referendum could be implemented in its present form, whether adjustments acceptable to both sides might be made, or whether some other way of resolving the conflict could be found.</p>
<p>Noting that six years had elapsed since the U.N. operation was established, Annan said: &quot;The international community has made it clear that it cannot continue to support the extension of MINURSO's mandate indefinitely and that the parties must demonstrate in a clear and tangible manner the political will necessary to take decisions that would bring about a fair and lasting solution to the problem of Western Sahara.</p>
<p>&quot;I urge the parties to cooperate fully with my personal envoy, so as to achieve this goal and strengthen the prospects for peace and stability in the region,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPSAH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
