<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569816" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: United HealthCare sees cost trend stable.</title>
<headline>United HealthCare sees cost trend stable.</headline>
<dateline>MINNEAPOLIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>United HealthCare Corp said it is seeing strong new enrollment and high retention in the face of price increases of more  than five percent, even as medical cost trends remain stable.</p>
<p>&quot;The overall medical cost trend was stable during the first quarter and in line with the company's expectations i.e., in the three to four percent range observed during the latter part of 1996,&quot; said the largest U.S. for-profit health maintenance organization holding company.</p>
<p>Shares in the company were up 2-3/8 to 52-7/8.  </p>
<p>The company said its consolidated 84.4 percent medical cost ratio was up over the 84 percent reported in the fourth quarter due to expected seasonally higher first quarter utilization, as well as changes in product mix.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important to note, however, that the medical cost ratio for the commercial business declined during the quarter,&quot; the company said.</p>
<p>Medical cost ratio is a measure of premium revenues paid out to cover HMO members' medical costs. The portion remaining covers administrative costs and constitutes profits.  </p>
<p>&quot;Rapid growth associated with recently introduced Medicare products ... and the absence of Medicaid premium increases contributed to the increased medical cost ratio,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The company on Thursday reported revenues for the first quarter ended March 31 of $2.85 billion, up 23 percent over the year-ago period. First quarter net earnings were $108.9 million, down from $118.9 million in the year-ago quarter.</p>
<p>The results &quot;reflect our focused efforts to rebalance pricing in relation to medical inflation, realization of continued efficiencies from SG&amp;A, and ongoing efforts to appropriately moderate health care cost trends,&quot; United said.  </p>
<p>Health plan enrollment topped five million for the first time in the quarter, a 3.3 percent gain over the fourth quarter of 1996 and nearly 23 percent year-over-year same store growth, the company said.</p>
<p>&quot;These advances were achieved despite the company's decision to exit selected Medicaid markets and withdraw from several large and unprofitable commercial health plan groups,&quot; said Minneapolis-based United.</p>
<p>((--Chicago Newsdesk 312-408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I95100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINNEAPOLIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
