<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569828" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Republican Party returns $100,000 to Hong Kong.</title>
<headline>Republican Party returns $100,000 to Hong Kong.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Republican National Committee said on Thursday it had returned over $100,000 in political contributions because it learned the money came from the Hong Kong parent company of a Florida-based subsidiary.</p>
<p>It was the first time the Republicans have been forced to return a foreign contribution. The Democratic Party has acknowledged receiving over $3 million in questionable foreign funds. The Justice Department and two congressional committees are investigating the affair.  </p>
<p>A statement by RNC chairman Jim Nicholson said the money was returned Wednesday as soon as it became clear the money had originated in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>The contributions came from Young Brothers Development USA. Nicholson said the party had no reason to believe the money came from overseas when it accepted the donation.</p>
<p>&quot;We were not able to secure the facts from the company until (Wednesday) afternoon when a company officer reported by telephone that the source of the funds was not an American company...but a 'parent' company in Hong Kong,&quot; Nicholson said.</p>
<p>&quot;Upon learning those facts, we immediately returned the contributions before day's end,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
