<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569881" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Olivetti sees loss narrowing in Q2.</title>
<headline>Olivetti sees loss narrowing in Q2.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italian information technology group Olivetti said on Thursday it expects to see a second quarter 1997 pretax loss, excluding its interest in mobile phone consortium Omnitel, of 93 billion lire after a comparable loss of 171.2 billion lire loss in the first quarter of 1997.</p>
<p>The group's chief executive Roberto Colaninno told an analysts meeting in Milan that there would be no group capital increase today or later in 1997.  </p>
<p>Colaninno said that for the period April-June 1997, the group loss before interest and tax was estimated at 43 billion lire after a loss of 122.80 billion lire in the first quarter.</p>
<p>He said in the first half of 1997, the group expected a pretax loss and before Omnitel of 264.2 billion lire, against a loss of 350.2 billion lire in the first half of 1996.</p>
<p>The loss before interest and tax would be 165.8 billion lire in the first half of 1997 from a loss of 232.1 billion lire.  </p>
<p>Asked about a possible capital increase for the group in the analysts meeting Colaninno replied. &quot;This is the moment for consolidating the operating results and carrying forward the strategy, therefore the (capital) increase will not be tomorrow nor in 1997.&quot;</p>
<p>On the detailed estimates for the second quarter of 1997, Olivetti Solution (ex-systems and services) is seen with a profit of 10 billion lire from a loss of 38.3 billion in the first quarter, and office equipment group Lexikon a profit of five billion lire after a profit of 7.6 billion lire.</p>
<p>For Olivetti's Telemedia, the second quarter 1997 estimate is for a loss of 120 billion lire after a first quarter loss of 127 billion lire.</p>
<p>On selling off non-core businesses, Colaninno said the process would continue up the end of 1997 and would hope to raise some 300 billion lire, which would have a positive effect on the group's finances of 200 billion lire.</p>
<p>-- Milan newsroom +392 66129502</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
