<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569855" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: AIDS drug cocktails suppress virus in lymph tissue.</title>
<headline>AIDS drug cocktails suppress virus in lymph tissue.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The drug cocktails now being used for AIDS patients are proving able to suppress the virus in lymph tissue as well as in their blood, scientists said Thursday.</p>
<p>The lymph findings, appearing in the journal Science on Friday, dovetail with numerous studies that have shown the new triple combination drug therapies are reducing the virus to undetectable levels in the blood and raise hopes that AIDS is becoming a chronic but manageable disease.</p>
<p>&quot;It's good news,&quot; said Dr. Winston Cavert at the University of Minnesota, one of the authors of the Science paper.</p>
<p>&quot;Before lymphoid tissues were studied, we had no certainty that the reduction in the viral burden we are seeing in the bloodstream was in fact happening in the rest of the body and in the tissues of the body&quot; which serve as reservoirs for the virus.</p>
<p>He and his colleagues found that 10 HIV-infected adults with moderately advanced cases of AIDS and no previous drug treatment responded quickly to the triple therapy.</p>
<p>The viral suppression was much faster than expected in just a few days, and then continued at a slower but still strong pace.</p>
<p>Doctors are not yet sure how long people will have to stay on triple therapy -- and many believe they will have to remain on anti-AIDS drugs for life.</p>
<p>But Cavert said it may be possible for patients to take a heavy drug regimen for a few years and then go on a lower, maintenance level which would be easier to tolerate.</p>
<p>Some scientists have discussed the possibility that they may be able to eradicate the HIV virus that causes AIDS from some patients in a controlled laboratory setting. But few think a cure is on the horizon.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
