<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569844" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Pittsburgh puts on hold plan to sell taxable bonds.</title>
<headline>Pittsburgh puts on hold plan to sell taxable bonds.</headline>
<dateline>PITTSBURGH 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>City finance officials put on hold a plan to issue $300 million in taxable bonds to help pay Pittsburgh's unfunded pension liabilities while elected officials investigate whether municipal pension bonds can be made tax-exempt.</p>
<p>&quot;We were going to issue $300 million in taxable bonds which would have been 30-year bonds,&quot; said city Finance Director Paul Hennigan. &quot;That's been put on hold.&quot;</p>
<p>An annual audit by the city controller's office, released every May, showed that Pittsburgh's unfunded pension liability as of December 31, 1996, was $531.9 million.</p>
<p>&quot;It's one of the worst in the country,&quot; City Controller Tom Flaherty said at a media briefing at which the audit was released.</p>
<p>The city currently is paying its pension obligations with the proceeds from a bond floated in 1985. This year the city is paying back $20 million on that bond, but the payments will grow every year and approach the $100 million mark by the year 2024.</p>
<p>City officials had been considering a plan to even out the payment schedule and fund the pensions by floating a $300 million pension bond.</p>
<p>However, Chief Accounting Officer Linda Kusner said the city can only borrow another $284 million before it hits its debt ceiling.</p>
<p>Hennigan said the city's pension board met with Rep. Bill Coyne, D-Pa., a member of the House Ways and Means Committee. Hennigan said Coyne plans to investigate whether municipal pension bonds can be made tax-exempt, currently prohibited by federal law.</p>
<p>&quot;I think if that doesn't work we will have to make a decision about whether to issue more taxable bonds,&quot; Hennigan said.</p>
<p>Flaherty said some good news in the annual audit was  that Pittsburgh ended '96 with a fund balance of $23.7 million, marking the first time the city has been in the black since 1990.</p>
<p>Cash revenues were up $19.2 million and expenditures were down $9 million from '95. &quot;It shows...an admirable job has been done of keeping expenses down while increasing revenues,&quot; Flaherty said.</p>
<p>The city's fund balance was buoyed last year by a $48 million cash infusion from the sale of the Water and Sewer Authority and delinquent tax liens, as well as Mayor Tom Murphy's decisions to cut the city payroll by 1,000 and streamline the worker's compensation program.</p>
<p>The audit also showed that as of December 31, the city's net bonded debt was $651,006,703, an increase of about $13 million from '95, translating to about $1,764.25 per city resident.</p>
<p>--U.S. Municipal Desk, 212-859-1650</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PITTSBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
