<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569826" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dlr slide worsens at US noon on Swiss franc buying.</title>
<headline>Dlr slide worsens at US noon on Swiss franc buying.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar continued to weaken in US morning trade as the focus shifted to Swiss franc buying from yen buying and sterling selling overnight, dealers said.</p>
<p>Dealers reported heavy sales of mark/Swiss, which may have had an exaggerated effect on dollar/Swiss with trade thinned by holidays across much of continental Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;People were buying mark/Swiss and that's going to weigh on the dollar. The trade was coming out of Switzerland,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>The dollar fell to 1.7070/80 marks from 1.7120/30 at the open and 1.4443/53 Swiss francs from 1.4490/00.  </p>
<p>The dollar fell as low as 1.7047 marks and 1.4410 Swiss before finding support, steepening its decline from 1.7190/00 marks and 1.4581/86 Swiss at Wednesday's close.</p>
<p>The greenback stood flat at 123.73/83 yen versus 123.72/77 at the open, but well off Wednesday's close at 125.05/10.</p>
<p>Currency players speculated that the Swiss might attract buyers amid talk that European Economic and Monetary Union will include a wide array of participants in its first round.</p>
<p>Sterling on Wednesday got hit by a news report that Labor leaders would reintroduce it to the Exchange Rate Mechanism at a central rate of 2.50 marks, down from about 2.77 now.  </p>
<p>The UK Treasury would later deny the report, but the market would continue to sell the pound, which fell another three pfennigs on Thursday.</p>
<p>Rumors flew about the pound, including an apparently bad rumor that new Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown had told a UK radio outlet that sterling was too strong.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's all rubbish; they have absolutely no intention of going into ERM. But this is a new (UK) government and any slight hint of them doing something unexpected is having a magnified effect,&quot; said Chris Iggo, chief economist at BZW Securities.  </p>
<p>Sterling/mark stood near its session low of 2.7635 at U.S. midday, well off its overnight high at 2.7914. That helped strengthen the mark against the dollar, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Dollar/mark is coming down on its own, but sterling/mark certainly helped it come down some,&quot; said John Hazelton, chief dealer at Manufacturers and Traders Bank.</p>
<p>Dealers expected to see some rebound by sterling soon, with current bargain prices seen too tempting to pass up.</p>
<p>&quot;Sterling got crushed over the last 24 hours and there's some feeling that that move was overdone,&quot; said Richard Vullo, vice president at Bayerische Hypothenken und Weschelsbank.  </p>
<p>Dollar/yen sat in a narrow U.S. trading range despite hitting a session low when the dollar sold off versus Europe.</p>
<p>A subsequent attempt to rally failed just above 124, where dealers said Asian names had parked a heavy slate of offers.</p>
<p>Sentiment has turned steadily more negative on dollar/yen amid repeated jawboning by Japanese officials and signs of embryonic growth in the beleaguered Japanese economy.</p>
<p>Ministry of Finance currency guru Eisuke Sakakibara sparked dollar sales by noting dollar/yen fluctuated by 23 yen per year on average over the last 10 years, adding that that meant a fall to 103 yen was theoretically possible.  </p>
<p>Despite later clarification by the MoF, the dollar failed to recoup its overnight losses.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is very nervous about buying dollars against yen and will continue to be. Japan has achieved what I call 'virtual intervention.' They've managed to achieve a lower dollar without actually spending any forex reserves,&quot; Iggo said.</p>
<p>The dollar edged lower to Canadian $1.3823/33 from C41.3831/36. Sterling rose to $1.6198/08 from $1.6153/60.</p>
<p>((--Chris Stetkiewicz, 212-859-1664))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
