<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569849" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Cuban exile leader Mas Canosa has bone disease.</title>
<headline>Cuban exile leader Mas Canosa has bone disease.</headline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Powerful Cuban exile leader Jorge Mas Canosa is suffering from the bone disorder Paget's Disease but is still &quot;enthusiastic and energetic,&quot; a spokeswoman for the Cuban American National Foundation said on Thursday.</p>
<p>He was diagnosed as suffering from the disease, which weakens and deforms the bones but is not life-threatening, in December, Ninoska Perez told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not at all serious. He's as enthusiastic and energetic as ever,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Mas Canosa, 57, has shunned the limelight in recent months, provoking rumours in Miami's exile community about the state of his health, among them that he had cancer. Perez said he had undergone a gall bladder operation since Paget's disease was diagnosed.</p>
<p>Mas Canosa attended a meeting of the Presidential Advisory Board on Cuba Broadcasting on Wednesday and was quoted in Thursday's Miami Herald as saying: &quot;I'll live to read the obituaries of all those who say I'm dying. Mas Canosa will be around for a while.&quot;</p>
<p>Mas Canosa is chairman of the CANF, the most powerful of the Florida-based Cuban exile groups opposed to President Fidel Castro's government.</p>
<p>Analysts say he wields great influence over U.S. policy towards the communist-ruled island and harbours hopes of one day replacing Castro should he fall.</p>
<p>He is also chairman and chief executive of MasTec Inc. telecommunications company. In March Hispanic Business magazine placed hin fifth on its list of the richest Hispanics in the United States with an estimated fortune of $257 million.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
