<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569862" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Jospin wants shift EU to jobs, growth.</title>
<headline>France's Jospin wants shift EU to jobs, growth.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-05-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Socialist leader Lionel Jospin, pledging policies based on &quot;respect&quot; if the left won France's close parliamentary election, said on Friday he would seek to re-orient the European Union towards jobs and growth.</p>
<p>Buoyed by opinion polls showing the left in striking range of an upset victory in the May 25-June 1 vote, Jospin said France needed to restore confidence in its rulers after a string of broken promises and errors by right and left.</p>
<p>&quot;To change, France must find confidence in itself,&quot; the white-haired former education minister, 59, wrote in an article appearing in French newspapers on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;It will only do so by finding confidence in its leaders. It's a question of respect...the foundation of this future we want to build.&quot;</p>
<p>Jospin's article, following a column by President Jacques Chirac on Wednesday criticising the left and seeking to persuade voters to re-elect his centre-right coalition, said one pillar of Socialist policy would be &quot;respect for Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We want a Europe without undoing France. We do not want Europe to dissolve into globalisation,&quot; Jospin said, reaffirming that the Socialists wanted a single European currency but only on certain conditions.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to re-orient European policy towards growth and jobs,&quot; he said, urging faith in a &quot;world which does not have to be this jungle we are promised by the self-interested fatalists of unrestricted liberalism and finance.&quot;</p>
<p>French voters, weary of political sleaze and rising unemployment, dumped the Socialists in 1993 in the last National Assembly elections. But both factors now threaten Prime Minister Alain Juppe's centre-right coalition.</p>
<p>&quot;We have know how to draw the lessons of the 10 years during which we were in government. I take responsibility, and the Socialist party with me, for the past errors,&quot; Jospin said.</p>
<p>Polls show many voters are disillusioned with politicians and believe neither the Socialists nor Juppe's coalition have answers to their main concern -- record unemployment of 12.8 percent of the workforce.</p>
<p>Jospin, who has reputation of being short on charisma but long on honesty, was defeated by Chirac in the 1995 presidential election.</p>
<p>He said his policies would be based on &quot;respect for truth&quot;, &quot;respect for the individual&quot;, &quot;respect for what binds us&quot;, &quot;respect for Europe&quot; and &quot;respect for democracy&quot;.</p>
<p>He described Chirac's criticisms of the left's platform and record as &quot;negative, partisan and unfair&quot; but he otherwise steered clear of personal barbs.</p>
<p>An Ipsos opinion poll for the weekly Le Point magazine projected that the ruling coalition would win 290 seats in the 577-member National Assembly, just one more than would be needed for a majority.</p>
<p>It forecast that the Socialists and their allies would get 264 seats, the Communists 22 and the far-right National Front one.</p>
<p>It was the narrowest lead for Juppe's coalition since Chirac, elected to a seven-year term ending in 2002, gambled his presidency by calling the early election.</p>
<p>Chirac called the vote saying that the government needed a new impetus to combat unemployment and enter a single European currency from a position of strength. But he risks becoming a lame duck for the next five years if the left wins.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
