<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569861" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: Greek shares come off early gains, end up 0.45pct.</title>
<headline>Greek shares come off early gains, end up 0.45pct.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Greek equity market lost some of its early enthusiasm as the extended rally in banks slowed down with profit-taking eroding prices on Thursday.</p>
<p>The Athens general index settled 0.45 percent or 6.94 points higher on the day at 1,544.47.</p>
<p>It opened on a firm note and rose steadily throughout the morning to as high as 1,562.30 or 1.61 percent above Wednesday's close of 1,537.53 with banks leading the market.</p>
<p>They firmed 1.04 percent while most other sectors were flat to lower. Small-caps climbed 2.65 percent.</p>
<p>The mid-session downturn was the result of mild profit-taking ahead of the announcement of the April CPI inflation figure.</p>
<p>CPI inflation was 6.0 percent in March and was seen easing to 5.9 percent in April, money sources said.</p>
<p>Brokers had contrasting views over the short-term impact of falling CPI inflation.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices already incorporate the easing in inflation for the coming months. Any positive impact will be realised indirectly through imminent interest rate cuts,&quot; said Maria Lentziou, analyst at Olympic Securities.</p>
<p>&quot;Market sentiment remains positive and the selling pressure is limited. The positive developments on the CPI front will assist the sustainability of increased buying interest, especially for banks,&quot; said Telesis Securities in a report.</p>
<p>Corrections were seen by analysts as short-lived patterns in an otherwise bullish market.</p>
<p>&quot;Any correction to prices will be very brief because there is considerable momentum in banks, the driving force of this year's rally,&quot; said Lentziou.</p>
<p>Banks are appreciating on fundamentals which keep buying interest at high levels.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a positive market-moving story behind nearly all banks, be it a rights issue, balance sheet cleansing or strong 1997 profit growth,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Turnover exceeded 26 billion drachmas in volume of 8.3 million shares.</p>
<p>Advancing stocks beat decliners 123 to 111 with 25 stocks unchanged on 259 traded.</p>
<p>The Merrill Lynch call spread warrant on OTE with a strike price of 3,800 drachmas was quoted higher at 1,110-1,140. Shares of OTE telecom, the underlying, were unchanged at 6,600 drachmas.</p>
<p>The ING Baring Financial Products American style call warrant based on a basket of six bank stocks was quoted higher at $74.37-$76.07. The strike price is set at $99.60 and the warrants expire October 8, 1997.</p>
<p>The ING Baring Financial Products American-style call warrant on a basket of six blue-chips denominated in drachmas was quoted higher at 2,849-3,058 drachmas.</p>
<p>The strike price is set at 10,000 drachmas and the warrants expire on February 2, 1998.</p>
<p>The recently launched ING Baring American-style second call warrant on a basket of six bank stocks was quoted higher at $17.50-N/O. The strike price is set at $110.0 and the warrants expire April 9 1998.</p>
<p>--Angelos Kiosklis, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
