<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569859" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Juppe quizzes Jospin, poll jolts right.</title>
<headline>France's Juppe quizzes Jospin, poll jolts right.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Prime Minister Alain Juppe blasted the opposition Socialist party on Thursday on issues ranging from tax to Europe as an opinion poll showed his coalition's election race lead had slipped to its smallest yet.</p>
<p>Juppe, whose allies had hoped for a clear victory in the May 25-June 1 poll but are now increasingly uneasy, sent Socialist leader Lionel Jospin four questions covering taxes, immigration, Europe and privatisations.</p>
<p>&quot;How will you finance the Socialist programme without considerably raising the taxes of each French person?&quot; he asked.</p>
<p>Jospin, who plans to publish an article in French newspapers on Friday, says he can avoid tax rises while implementing a programme that includes creating 700,000 jobs and cutting working hours.</p>
<p>Juppe's statement, oddly faxed from the premier's office rather than campaign headquarters, also asked how the Socialists would avoid a &quot;massive return of clandestine immigration&quot; if they carried out a pledge to scrap tough new immigration laws.</p>
<p>He said Jospin should also spell out how he would &quot;avoid a crisis for Europe&quot; if he appointed Communist ministers to a cabinet. The Communists say they should get seats in a left-wing coalition.</p>
<p>Finally, Juppe said the Socialists were split on whether to nationalise or privatise and asked which way Jospin would go.</p>
<p>An opinion poll by the Ipsos institute for the weekly Le Point magazine projected that Juppe's coalition would get 290 seats in the 577-member National Assembly, just one more than is needed for a majority.</p>
<p>It forecast that the Socialists and their allies would win 264, Communists 22 and the far-right National Front one.</p>
<p>It was the narrowest lead for Juppe's coalition since President Jacques Chirac took a gigantic gamble last month and called the early election, saying France needed a &quot;new elan&quot; to tackle problems including record unemployment and preparations for a single European currency.</p>
<p>The franc was stable against the mark, at around 3.3732 francs per mark, after the Ipsos poll was issued. French markets were closed for an Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>Jospin hit back at a barb by Juppe who said the Socialist programme had &quot;exploded in flight&quot;. Jospin, saying he was increasingly confident of an upset win, retorted that Juppe's campaign &quot;had not yet taken off.&quot;</p>
<p>Juppe won endorsement from a French European commissioner who dropped his impartiality to say that Socialist conditions for joining a single European currency from 1999 could create uncertainty and push up interest rates.</p>
<p>Yves Thibault de Silguy, a conservative in charge of EU monetary affairs, also said he believed the Socialists would be committed to a single currency and their policy would be little different from that of the present government.</p>
<p>Jospin has said that he will not impose extra austerity measures to meet budget deficit targets for qualifying for the euro. He has also set conditions, saying that Italy and Spain should join from the start and the euro should not be overvalued.</p>
<p>The election campaign has yet to fire the public's imagination, with many believing neither side has the key to their main concern -- unemployment. &quot;When's it going to begin?&quot; asked the daily France-Soir in a front-page headline.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
