<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569892" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: Asian port conditions - Lloyds.</title>
<headline>Asian port conditions - Lloyds.</headline>
<text>
<p>Port conditions from Lloyds Shipping Intelligence Service --</p>
<p>BANGLADESH, May 5 - Chittagong - 24 vessels in port of which 5 containers, 3 general cargo, 4 cement, 2 food grain, 1 cement clinker, 1 tanker, 1 fertiliser, 7 other vessels. 28 due by 13/5 of which 13 containers, 7 general cargo, 1 cement, 1 food grain, 1 cement clinker, 3 tankers, 1 export loader, 1 for scraping. No berthing delays.</p>
<p>INDIA, May 6 - Bombay - Labour shortages due to holidays. Five vessels loading at berth, 23 discharging, 8 at anchorage to load, 7 to discharge. 4 under repair, 1 awaiting orders. Delays expected, containers/general cargo vessels 1-2 days, bulkers 4-5 days. Calcutta - Eight loading at berth, 17 discharging, 2 discharging at anchorage, 2 bunkering. 17 due of which 2 coking coal, 3 products tankers, 5 containers, 2 general, 1 crude, 2 logs, 1 pulses, 1 coal. Cochin - No labour problems. Two loading at berth, 9 discharging, 2 waiting at anchorage to discharge, 2 under repair/dry-docked of which 1 at CSL jetty. 1 Naval vessel at dry-dock, 5 vessels due, up to 1 day delay expected.</p>
<p>Madras - No labour problems. Three vessels loading at berth, 6 discharging, 2 waiting at anchorage to load, 2 to discharge. 36 due (5 coal, 5 iron ore, 2 fertiliser, 2 general cargo, 12 containers) with following delays, scrap 4-5 days, coal/coke/fertiliser/others 2 days, no delays containers/iron ore. Mormugao - Two loading at berth, 3 discharging. 6 loading at anchorage, 1 discharging. 11 due (9 ore, 1 sugar, 1 petroleum) delays ore 4-5 days, sugar/petroleum up to 1 day.</p>
<p>Kandla - Three loading at berth, 4 discharging, 2 discharging in stream, 5 waiting to load, 4 to discharge, 2 under arrest, 3 tankers, 11 waiting. 16 due with 10-11 days delay. Mangalore - No labour problems. Six loading/discharging at berth, 3 awaiting berths, 1 under arrest, 10 due with 1-2 days delay expected. Jawaharlal Nehru - No labour problems. Three fertiliser/raw materials/food grain vessels discharging at berth, 3 tankers/iron ore vessels, 1 fertiliser/raw materials/foodgrain vessel waiting at anchorage to discharge. 3 due (1 food grain/fertiliser, 2 tankers/iron ore) with delays, food grain/fertiliser 20 days, tankers/iron ore 10 days.</p>
<p>Paradip - No labour problems. Two vessels loading at berth, 3 discharging, 3 waiting at anchorage to load. 10 due, 6 days delay expected. Tuticorin - No labour problems. Three vessels loading at berth, 6 discharging, 2 discharging at anchorage, 3 waiting at anchorage to load, 1 to discharge, 1 awaiting orders. 3 due, 1-2 days delay. Visakhapatnam - Two loading at berth, 6 discharging, 4 waiting at anchor to discharge at inner harbour berth. 6 to load at inner harbour berth. 21 due with 7-8 days delay expected.</p>
<p>SOUTH KOREA, May 6 - Inchon - 59 vessels in port (32 berthed, 27 anchored) of which berthed 7 logs, 6 general cargo, 6 containers, 2 pig-iron, 2 coils, 2 scrap, 1 silica sand, 1 raw sugar, 1 copra, 1 cars, 1 pulp, 1 salt, 1 plywood. Anchored, 5 coils, 4 cars, 4 containers, 4 general cargo, 3 logs, 1 lupins, 1 wheat, 1 palm oil, 1 pig-iron, 1 corn, 1 h-beams, 1 bananas. Approx. 1 days berthing delay expected. Busan - 161 in port (47 berthed, 114 anchored including 59 laid-up) of which berthed, 34 general cargo, 6 containers, 4 scrap, 3 coal. 56 awaiting berths, 2 days delay expected. Pohang - 24 in port (berthed) of which discharging, 3 billets, 3 scrap, 2 steel, 1 iron ore, 1 coils, 1 logs. Loading, 6 coils, 4 plate, 3 pipes. No delays expected. Ulsan - 30 in port berthed of which discharging, 3 monoethyl glycol, 2 mixed xylene, 2 wood-chips, 2 zinc concentrate, 2 copper concentrate, 1 coal, 1 feedmeal, 1 coke, 1 salt, 1 cement, 1 styrene monomer, 1 rock phosphate, 1 corn, 1 naphtha, 1 fuel oil, 1 crude</p>
<p>MALAYSIA, May 7 - Port Klang - North/south port - Container/ro-ro berth - 6 vessels berthed, 2 waiting, 1 day waiting time. Deep draft conventional wharf - 4 berthed, 2 berthing today. 6 waiting with 4 days waiting time. Dry/cement bulk terminal - 3 berthed, 2 waiting with 1 day waiting time. Liquid bulk terminal - 2 berthed, 1 waiting, no waiting time. West port - Container/ro-ro berth - 4 berthed, none waiting, no delays. Deep draft conventional wharf - 6 berthed, 4 waiting. 2 days waiting time. Cement bulk terminal - 3 berthed, 1 waiting. No waiting time. Liquid bulk terminal - 1 berthed, none waiting, no delays.</p>
<p>MAURITIUS, May 6 - Port Louis - No labour problems. 11 vessels in port including 7 discharging general cargo, 2 discharging/loading containers, discharging bulk cargo. No idle vessels, 17 due by 13/5.</p>
<p>SINGAPORE, Singapore - 6 May - Tanjong Pagar container terminal - 10 container vessels berthed. Keppel terminal - 10 container/general cargo vessels berthed. Pasir Panjang terminal - 9 container/general cargo vessels berthed, Seawang terminal - 10 general cargo vessels berthed. Jurong port - 1 bulk cargo/steel/general cargo vessel berthed, Oil terminals/SBM buoys - 19 tankers berthed. Minimal berthing delays at all terminals/ports/buoys.</p>
<p>SRI LANKA, May 6 - Colombo - no labour problems. 19 vessels loading at berth (14 containers, 5 essential services), 24 discharging (6 bagged sugar, 12 containers, 1 bagged rice, 1 steel, 2 general cargo, 1 bagged flour, 1 bagged onions), 6 waiting at anchorage to load (5 containers, 1 essential services), 12 to discharge (5 containers, 1 bulk LPG, 1 bagged fertiliser, 2 bagged sugar, 1 bagged flour, 2 general cargo), 1 vessel bunkering, 2 under repairs, 5 dry-docked, 6 vessels awaiting orders, 9 vessels due of which 7 containers, 1 bagged fertiliser, 1 bulk cement. Delays - conventional vessels 7-10 days, containers 1-2 days. Rainy weather. Galle - one vessel discharging at berth. Trincomalee - one discharging at berth, 1 loading.</p>
<p>TAIWAN, May 5 - Keelung - Five vessels anchored. Berthing delays, coal 5 days, steel 4 days, iron ore 3 days, no delays for grain. Kaohsiung - Four vessels anchored. Berthing delays, grain/steel 1 day, coal/scrap 2 days (public berth). Taichung - Seven anchored. Delays, grain 5-6 days, grain/iron ore/coal/scrap/steel/others 1-2 days.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MAURTS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
