<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569884" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German unions urge SPD to compromise on pensions.</title>
<headline>German unions urge SPD to compromise on pensions.</headline>
<byline>Svea Herbst-Bayliss</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>German unions on Thursday urged the opposition Social Democrats (SPD) to compromise with the ruling coalition over pension reform and not turn the issue into a contentious campaign issue in next autumn's federal election.</p>
<p>&quot;Every attempt must be made to keep the pension reform out of the election campaign and to find a solution that reflects both the interests of employers and pensioners,&quot; Ursula Engelen-Kefer, deputy of the German trade union federation DGB said in an interview with the Handelsblatt newspaper.</p>
<p>A summary of the article to appear in Friday's edition was made available before publication.</p>
<p>The Social Democrats have spent this week arguing with Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian Democrat and Free Democrat ruling coaltion, having rejected Security Minister Norbert Bluem's plan to cut old-age pay in the early decades of the next century.</p>
<p>Bluem has proposed modest reductions in pensions to cope with the &quot;greying&quot; of Germany and has won government approval for a plan which would eventually reduce a typical pension to 64 percent of average net wages -- a level last seen in the 1970s -- from around 70 percent now.</p>
<p>At the same time, the transfer of around 15 billion marks ($8.7 billion) in non-welfare costs from the state pension fund to the federal budget would enable contributions to be cut from today's record level of 20.3 percent of wages.</p>
<p>But Rudolf Sharping, an important SPD member, told German newspaper Stuttgarter Nachrichten that the party could well turn the issue into a major factor as party positioning heatd up before the federal election.</p>
<p>&quot;If the coalition wants to cut the pension to 64 percent, which would mean that most pensioners would receive less than 64 percent, putting them into the category of receiving deluxe welfare payments, then we need to show the voters this,&quot; Sharping told the newspaper.</p>
<p>The SPD is hoping to unseat Chancellor Kohl after over 14 years in office but critics say it appears to be wasting precious political energy through party infighting and has trouble in formulating a clear attack on the Kohl government.</p>
<p>In an effort to calm the situation, Engelen-Kefer said talks between the unions and Bluem's representatives should be held in the not too distant future.</p>
<p>But  Engelen-Kefer herself  is firm on some issues, opposing the proposed reduction to 64 percent and criticising planned reductions in pensions for the disabled.</p>
<p>She told the paper if Bluem did not show some willingness to compromise she would not be interested in any concessions the SPD might be willing to make.</p>
<p>Engelen-Kefer warned that the plans were especially bad for women, reducing their pensions to the level where many would need to collect welfare.</p>
<p>The SPD wants 30 billion marks a year in costs -- including the cost of pensions paid to immigrants from the former Soviet Union -- to be borne by the taxpayer.</p>
<p>Both sides are considering an increase in indirect taxes to pay for the pensions reform which would dilute coalition plans to cut income and corporate taxes. The SPD has threatened to block the plan in the Bundesrat upper house of parliament after cross-party talks collapsed in acrimony recently.</p>
<p>The SPD does not, however, have the power to block pensions legislation, a policy area which has traditionally been kept out of party politics.</p>
<p>Despite this week's SPD rebuff, Bluem said he would keep working to achieve a compromise to try and prevent pensions from becoming &quot;a bone of contention&quot; in next year's general election.</p>
<p>($ = 1.716 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
