<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569888" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Besson recreates sci-fi world at Cannes gala.</title>
<headline>Besson recreates sci-fi world at Cannes gala.</headline>
<byline>John Follain</byline>
<dateline>CANNES, France 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Luc Besson recreated the monster-filled universe of his science-fiction blockbuster &quot;The Fifth Element&quot; at the Cannes festival's opening gala, hiring a glass and steel hangar in the old harbour for a party which cost a reported $2 million.</p>
<p>In a throwback to the extravagant jamborees of Cannes' golden years in the 1950s and 60s, the hangar was graced on Wednesday night with a pyramid -- which opened up to reveal a rock band -- and hanging models of the film's flying cars while a blue planet floated overhead.</p>
<p>The 'enfant terrible' of French fashion, Jean-Paul Gaultier, paraded his costume designs for the $90-million movie on a catwalk to the film's deafening score. The score later accompanied a firework display in the bay of the Riviera resort.</p>
<p>&quot;So noisy nobody could hear you boo,&quot; one critic had quipped of the film starring Bruce Willis and Gary Oldman.</p>
<p>----------------</p>
<p>At the festival's earlier opening ceremony, a quieter affair save for a 50-strong band of Senegalese drummers, French actress Jeanne Moreau led a tribute to ailing Italian master Michelangelo Antonioni.</p>
<p>The director was given a standing ovation when Vanessa Redgrave, who had starred in Antonioni's &quot;La Notte&quot;, handed him a replica of the Golden Palm award which had been stolen from him.</p>
<p>Jury president Isabelle Adjani, also awarded a standing ovation, pledged to defend cinema as a guarantee of liberty -- a veiled reference to China's preventing Zhang Yimou from showing &quot;Keep Cool&quot; in Cannes, and to Iranian pressures on Abbas Kiarostami.</p>
<p>----------------</p>
<p>French Culture Minister Philippe Douste-Blazy missed the opening ceremony because he was still recovering in hospital after he was stabbed while campaigning for the May-June parliamentary election in the streets of Lourdes last Friday.</p>
<p>He sent a message to the gala guests saying he had done all he could to promote French cinema since he took office two years ago. Both Douste-Blazy and President Jacques Chirac are expected to attend Sunday's 50th anniversary gala sporting a bevvy of stars and past Golden Palm winners.</p>
<p>----------------</p>
<p>Hot on the heels of Michael Jackson, music will again hijack the Cannes festival on Friday when Britain's Spice Girls promote their next movie with the adventurous title: &quot;Spice Girls: The Movie&quot;.</p>
<p>Richard E. Grant, who says he was bullied by his eight-year-old daughter into playing their manager, describes it as &quot;'A Hard Day's Night' with bras&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANNES, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
