<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569857" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Juppe and Jospin spar as poll jolts right.</title>
<headline>France's Juppe and Jospin spar as poll jolts right.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Prime Minister Alain Juppe traded barbs with the opposition Socialists on election issues including taxes and Europe on Thursday as an opinion poll showed his coalition's lead had dwindled to its slimmest yet.</p>
<p>Juppe, whose centre-right allies are growing uneasy after hoping for a clear win in the May 25-June 1 parliamentary vote, sent Socialist leader Lionel Jospin four questions criticising his policies on taxes, immigration, Europe and privatisation.</p>
<p>Emboldened by opinion surveys showing the race for the 577-seat National Assembly was almost neck-and-nect, Jospin retorted that the questions showed Juppe's campaign was floundering.</p>
<p>&quot;The right is reduced to defining itself by comparison with us, we are the ones in the centre of the campaign,&quot; he said in Pamiers in the Pyrenees. &quot;I am convinced...we are going to win.&quot;</p>
<p>An opinion poll by the Ipsos institute for the weekly Le Point magazine projected that Juppe's coalition would get 290 seats in the Assembly, just one more than is needed for a majority.</p>
<p>It forecast the Socialists and their allies would win 264 and the Communists 22 for a total of 286, just four short of the coalition total. The far-right National Front would win one seat.</p>
<p>It was the narrowest lead for Juppe's coalition since President Jacques Chirac took a gigantic gamble last month and called the early election, saying France needed a &quot;new elan&quot; to tackle problems including record unemployment and preparations for a single European currency.</p>
<p>The franc was stable against the mark, at around 3.3732 francs, after the Ipsos poll was issued. French markets were closed for an Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>Juppe, shown by opinion polls to be deeply unpopular amid record unemployment in France, asked Jospin in a statement how the former education minister would finance campaign pledges including creating 700,000 youth jobs and cutting working hours.</p>
<p>Juppe's questions also asked how the Socialists would avoid a &quot;massive return of clandestine immigration&quot; if they carried out a pledge to scrap tough new immigration laws.</p>
<p>Jospin brushed aside the question, saying the government's laws were misguided.</p>
<p>The premier also said Jospin should spell out how he would avoid &quot;a crisis for Europe&quot; if he appointed Communist ministers to a cabinet. The Communists say they should get seats in any left-wing coalition.</p>
<p>Jospin reiterated that any Communist ministers would have to bow to the programme of the major partner in a coalition and said Juppe's attempts to to whip up fears of communism &quot;does not even scare children&quot;.</p>
<p>Since the end of the Cold War, he said the Communist Party &quot;was a democratic force worthy of respect&quot;.</p>
<p>Finally, Juppe said the Socialists were split on whether to nationalise or privatise and asked which way Jospin would go.</p>
<p>&quot;We say no to new privatisations, and we will interrupt the procedures under way,&quot; Jospin said. &quot;Don't expect the left to carry out a right-wing programme. The right doesn't like public services while we're proud of them.&quot;</p>
<p>Juppe won an endorsement from French European commissioner for monetary affairs, Yves Thibault de Silguy, who dropped his traditional impartiality to say that Socialist conditions for joining a single European currency from 1999 could create uncertainty and push up interest rates.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
