<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569889" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italian shares end down, but fight back to highs.</title>
<headline>Italian shares end down, but fight back to highs.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italian stocks ended lower but at the day's best levels on Thursday in lacklustre trading with many European markets closed for an Ascension Day holiday, while the share market reflected the lower trend on domestic bonds.</p>
<p>Despite London and Wall Street stocks moving firmer today, there was little positive to encourage buyers into the market. &quot;There was little real interest after the U.S. overnight fall, but with the early rise in Wall Street today, Milan started to recover some of its losses,&quot; said one share dealer.</p>
<p>The blue-chip Mib30 ended 0.43 percent off at 18,315 while all-share Mibtel index closed 0.44 percent down at 12,272.</p>
<p>Olivetti shares off 0.86 percent at 495.6 lire as analysts meet the company in late afternoon. Among other blue chips, Montedison closes off 0.65 percent at 1,067 lire and oil and chemical group ENI down 0.19 percnet at 8,632 lire.</p>
<p>Energy group Edison bounced back after two days of heavy losses following the announcement of an intended link-up between ENI and ENEL. Shares ended up 0.99 percent at 8,361 lire.</p>
<p>Fiat slipped late after the company met analysts on Wednesday and said operating margins were on an upward trend after averaging 2.6 percent in the first quarter of 1997. Fiat shares ended off 0.21 percent at 5,711 lire.</p>
<p>Retailer Rinascente continued its fall after a 8.25 percent drop on Wednesday following Tuesday's news of a deal between IFIL and France's Auchan which included a capital increase for Rinascente. Shares ended off 1.57 percent at 8,451 lire.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
