<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569868" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy's Dini criticises Labour Party over Europe.</title>
<headline>Italy's Dini criticises Labour Party over Europe.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italian Foreign Minister Lamberto Dini said on Thursday he hoped the arrival of the new Labour government in Britain would mark an improvement in Anglo-EU relations but that first impressions were not encouraging.</p>
<p>Dini condemned the attitude of the old Conservative government, which was defeated in a general election last week, and said the Labour party might provide a breathe of fresh air.</p>
<p>&quot;We can't but hope that the new British government will confirm a negotiating approach less tainted by ideological prejudices and preconceived ideas,&quot; Dini told a meeting of Italian members of the European Parliament.</p>
<p>However, he said he was worried by the stance taken by the new British Minister for Europe, Doug Henderson, at a meeting of the inter-governmental conference (IGC) on the EU's workings held in Brussels earlier this week.</p>
<p>&quot;The first intervention of the new British representative at the inter-governmental conference certainly did not reassure us,&quot; Dini said.</p>
<p>&quot;The closed approach on some points, which are important for us, like common defence and security policy, the European justice system and internal affairs of the union are not very encouraging,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Henderson told colleagues that London would end its opt-out on various social clauses included in European Union treaties, but the Labour party has confirmed its opposition to other policies close to Italians' hearts.</p>
<p>Among these is Italy's desire to see the Western European Union (WEU) defence group gradually incorporated into the EU to give the 15-nation bloc a common defence policy.</p>
<p>The IGC is scheduled to agree a new treaty by June which could be the EU's last chance for real reform before its planned eastward expansion.</p>
<p>&quot;In the context of continued divergences (with European policy), the British confirmation it will respect the June (EU treaty) deadline is not enough to soften our fears,&quot; Dini said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
