<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569876" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: U.N. official to visit Cyprus, Greece, Turkey.</title>
<headline>U.N. official to visit Cyprus, Greece, Turkey.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Goodman</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.N. under-secretary general for political affairs, Sir Kieran Prendergast, will visit Cyprus, Greece and Turkey later this month for the first time since taking up his U.N. post earlier this year, U.N. sources said on Thursday.</p>
<p>He will help lay the groundwork for face-to-face talks expected to take place in June between Cypriot President Glafcos Clerides, as head of the Greek Cypriot community, and Turkish Cypriot leader Rauf Denktash.</p>
<p>No date has been announced for the talks nor their duration. But they are expected to be held in or near U.N. headquarters. One source said June 20 was a likely starting date.</p>
<p>Clerides will be in New York then anyway to attend a special session of the General Assembly on the environment and development, scheduled for June 23 to 27, as a five-year followup to the 1992 U.N. Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
<p>Secretary-General Kofi Annan said late last month he intended convening a meeting between Clerides and Denktash in June. It would be their first known face-to-face encounter for nearly three years.</p>
<p>&quot;If the June talks go well, we would hope to have two more sessions and hopefully have a clear indication by August or September whether we are going to make real progress or not,&quot; Annan added.</p>
<p>He also recently announced the appointment of former Ecuadorean Foreign Minister Diego Cordovez as his special adviser for Cyprus. Cordovez, a former U.N. under-secretary general, would chair meetings between the Cypriot leaders that other duties prevented Annan from attending.</p>
<p>Cyprus has been virtually partitioned since 1974 when troops from Turkey took over the north of the island after a coup in Nicosia engineered by the junta then ruling Greece. The United Nations has been trying for more than 20 years to reunite the Greek and Turkish Cypriots under a bi-zonal, bi-communal federal system.</p>
<p>U.N. sources said even if the planned talks between Clerides and Denktash revived the long-dormant negotiating process, a hiatus was inevitable while the Greek Cypriots prepared for elections due next February.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
