<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569946" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: Sri Lanka moots alliance to boost natural rubber.</title>
<headline>Sri Lanka moots alliance to boost natural rubber.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sri Lanka plans to form an alliance with natural rubber producers Malaysia and Indonesia to counter competition posed by synthetic rubber, the state-owned Daily News on Thursday quoted a senior minister as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;My proposal has been well accepted by most of the rubber producing countries and now we have to sit at a table and work out the organisational framework to make it a reality,&quot; Trade Minister Kingsley Wickramaratne told the paper.</p>
<p>He did not name the other countries that had expressed interest in joining the alliance, but said Malaysia and Indonesia would play prominent roles.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka, which produces just two percent of the world's natural rubber, has been in the forefront in finding ways to raise consumption of natural rubber over synthetics.</p>
<p>The Association of Natural Rubber Producing Countries (ANRPC) says demand for the commodity is expected to exceed supply in the long term as the world economy gathers pace, led by the booming Asia-Pacific region.</p>
<p>Recent forecasts project a shortfall in natural rubber production compared with consumption from 2000 onwards.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka has slipped from being the world's fourth biggest rubber producer to eighth in 25 years.</p>
<p>The Indian Ocean island is the sole producer of latex crepe, used for making surgical and pharmaceutical rubber products, infant toys and rubber goods used in contact with food.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25140">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
