<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569913" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India's Congress party a force despite scars.</title>
<headline>India's Congress party a force despite scars.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's Congress party, boosted by the entry of Sonia Gandhi into its ranks on Thursday, wields tremendous influence in the country's politics despite a recent history of corruption scandals and electoral defeat.</p>
<p>The Congress saw the entry of the Italian-born widow of former prime minister Rajiv Gandhi into the party as a much-needed tonic for millions of cadres at a time when its image had been sullied and social base eroded.</p>
<p>Sonia's entry is symbolic but comes in a powerful tradition of Rajiv, his mother, Indira Gandhi, and her father, Jawaharlal Nehru, whose charisma has ruled the world's biggest democracy.</p>
<p>The three ruled India as prime ministers for 38 of the 50 years since independence. Congress has ruled for all but five years since independence.</p>
<p>With 140 deputies in the 545-member lower house, the Congress last month forced the minority United Front to change its prime minister from H.D. Deve Gowda to Inder Kumar Gujral.</p>
<p>The Congress derives its strength from independence leader Mahatma Gandhi, whose name still inspires awe across India. Nehru was his political heir and India's first prime minister.</p>
<p>Formed in 1885 by an Englishman, Allan Octavian Hume, the Congress grew from being a lobby of traders and civil servants fighting discrimination under British rule to a mass movement.</p>
<p>Mahatma Gandhi, who saw the Congress as a movement, wanted it to be dissolved after independence, but its leaders turned the organisation into a monolithic party that cleverly exploited divisions linked to caste and regional and economic ideologies.</p>
<p>But the party's fortunes began slipping after Rajiv Gandhi's assassination during an election rally in 1991 by a female suicide bomber, believed to be a Sri Lankan separatist opposed to the Indian army's help for Colombo in 1987.</p>
<p>Then prime minister P.V. Narasimha Rao took over the reins of the party, which regained power in the elections after 18 months on the strength of a sympathy wave linked to Gandhi's murder.</p>
<p>But despite broad support for Rao's foreign policies and free-market economic policies, Congress was thrown out of office in general elections last year in its worst-ever showing.</p>
<p>Rao's personal style was seen as dour and colourless, and corruption scandals involving leaders made matters worse.</p>
<p>The Congress had in the past suffered shocks, especially after Indira Gandhi's electoral defeat in 1977 after two years of a controversial emergency rule. But the Gandhi family's image and charisma helped the party stage comebacks.</p>
<p>Nehru and Indira Gandhi carefully nourished huge vote banks among minority Moslems and low castes.</p>
<p>But Rajiv Gandhi was seen by many as living off his family's political wealth. New parties under aggressive low-caste leaders filled a vacuum created by his inexperience.</p>
<p>Moslems were seen leaving the Congress for what they saw as its ineffectiveness in checking Hindu fundamentalism.</p>
<p>Many Sikhs, too, left Congress. They accuse it of sparking anti-Sikh riots in 1984 after Indira Gandhi was gunned down by Sikh bodyguards.</p>
<p>Congress polled 28.8 percent of the vote in last year's general elections -- the first time it fell below 30 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
