<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569922" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Kashmir separatists say rights violations on rise.</title>
<headline>Kashmir separatists say rights violations on rise.</headline>
<dateline>SRINAGAR, India 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kashmir's leading separatist alliance on Thursday said human rights violations by Indian security forces had increased at an alarming rate in recent months, but authorities denied the allegation.</p>
<p>&quot;The human rights violations, rape of our women and the killings at the hands of Indian security forces in Kashmir in recent months are at an all-time high,&quot; Umar Farooq, chairman of the All Parties Hurriyat (Freedom) Conference, said.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation is alarming,&quot; he told a news conference.</p>
<p>The Hurriyat is an umbrella organisation banding together some 30 religious and political groups.</p>
<p>A senior Indian army official denied the charge.</p>
<p>&quot;There are a lot of subversive people who instigate such reports,&quot; Lieutenant-General J.S. Dhillon told another news conference in Srinagar, summer capital of troubled Jammu and Kashmir state.</p>
<p>&quot;We have taken much faster action in reported security excesses. In fact, four soldiers were sentenced for 10 years imprisonment for a rape case,&quot; Dhillon said.</p>
<p>Dhillon, who heads a unified command of different Indian security agencies fighting a separatist insurgency in Kashmir, is also a security adviser to the state government.</p>
<p>The Hurriyat accused security agencies of killing at least 818 people in the first four months of this year. &quot;Over 141 people were killed in the custody of security forces during this period,&quot; Umar Farooq said.</p>
<p>According to an official spokesman, more than 700 people were killed in 174 bomb explosions and other militancy-related incidents during the first four months of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;About some excesses committed by the security forces, I assure you that all cases have been investigated and wherever we have found that we required to take action, action has been taken,&quot; Dhillon said.</p>
<p>Dozens of guerrilla groups seeking merger with Pakistan or independence have been fighting Indian security forces in Kashmir since 1990.</p>
<p>More than 20,000 people have died in violence since then.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SRINAGAR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
