<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569940" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: Sri Lanka gas monopoly strike ends.</title>
<headline>Sri Lanka gas monopoly strike ends.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A six-day-old strike at Sri Lanka's monopoly gas distributor ended on Thursday after workers and management reached an agreement on the transfer and dismissal of some employees, a company spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;The strike is over. An agreement has been reached,&quot; said a spokesman for Shell Gas Lanka Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;People have already started to return to work,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>The strike at Shell Gas Lanka Ltd., owned by the Royal Dutch/Shell Group, affected industries and domestic consumers alike while restaurants and food outlets were forced to put up shutters.</p>
<p>The strike was launched last Friday by workers of the All Ceylon Commercial and Industrial Workers Union demanding an immediate halt to transfers of employees and the reinstatement of six workers who were dismissed.</p>
<p>The strike threatened to shut down at least a dozen industries which used liquid petroleum gas (LPG) in their operations.</p>
<p>&quot;The company has assured they will start issuing gas no sooner the strike ends,&quot; said Bandula Perera of the Industrial Gas Users' Association, which represents 11 factories who are among Shell Gas' biggests customers.</p>
<p>&quot;Had the strike not ended today, several of our member companies would have been forced to close down,&quot; Perera told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't agree with monopolies. But since a monopoly has been created with gas, there must be safeguards to protect the consumer. We must be guaranteed of supplies in cases like this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the association's members planned to lobby the government to allow them to purchase LPG from the Ceylon Petroleum Corporation (CPC) during times when supplies are disrupted.</p>
<p>An agreement between Shell and the govenrment of Sri Lanka prohibits anyone else from selling LPG. CPC, the country's only other producer, sells the LPG generated at its refinery to Shell.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
