<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569911" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Sonia Gandhi revives whiff of dynasty in India.</title>
<headline>Sonia Gandhi revives whiff of dynasty in India.</headline>
<byline>Nelson Graves</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sonia Gandhi's entry into formal Indian politics breathes life into a dispirited Congress party that longs for the heady days of the Gandhi-Nehru dynasty.</p>
<p>But her role within the nation's oldest party may well remain modest, for the Italian-born widow could be an easy target for critics if she sought a public position of power, analysts said.</p>
<p>Congress leaders were elated the elegant 50-year-old, known in her adopted homeland as Sonia, had finally stepped out of the shadows to stand at the edge of the political fray.</p>
<p>&quot;She has joined hands with millions of Congress workers,&quot; said party president Sitaram Kesri, who had pressed the late Rajiv Gandhi's wife to leave her reclusive ways and join his party's uphill fight to recapture power.</p>
<p>Many of those Congress workers remember the charismatic hold that Rajiv Gandhi, his mother Indira and her father Jawaharlal Nehru had on the world's most populous democracy.</p>
<p>Those three leaders were at the helm for 38 of India's 50 years since independence.</p>
<p>&quot;It will definitely give the rank and file a morale boost which they need very badly,&quot; said Mahesh Rangarajan, a research fellow at Delhi's Centre for Contemporary Studies. &quot;They are not used to being out of power.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It will be good for Congress,&quot; said the head of research at a large brokerage house in Bombay. &quot;She could be the rallying point around which various factions pull together.&quot;</p>
<p>Barricaded behind tight security since her husband was killed by a female suicide bomber in 1991, Sonia has exercised subtle but unmistakable influence over the 112-year-old party from the stylish confines of her drawing rooms.</p>
<p>Her Delhi address -- 10 Janpath -- is synonymous in the press with the faction politics that has long characterised the sprawling, umbrella organisation that was once the political home of Mahatma Gandhi.</p>
<p>Characteristically, Sonia was nowhere to be found on the day when her party trumpeted her political coming out.</p>
<p>Born December 9, 1946 into the family of a middle-class Turin businessman, Sonia Gandhi married Rajiv Gandhi in 1968 after an unlikely romance in the British university town of Cambridge.</p>
<p>A naturalised Indian citizen, she long ago adopted the sari as her garment of choice. But her enemies await her move towards the centre stage of politics, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Her formal entry onto the political scene will be treated as an intrusion by a foreigner,&quot; said B.G. Verghese of the Centre for Policy Research, an independent think-tank.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of people would be totally unfair to her. She's seen as an outsider and some think her only claim to any position is being her late husband's wife.&quot;</p>
<p>The Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) could be expected to make much ado about her foreign roots if she became more than a mere party member.</p>
<p>&quot;That is one of the problems,&quot; said Jay Dubashi, a member of the BJP's executive council. &quot;Also the fact that she is among the people connected to Bofors.&quot;</p>
<p>He was referring to a controversial 1986 gun deal with Swedish arms maker AB Bofors. The furore over alleged illegal payments contributed to Rajiv Gandhi's defeat in 1989. The family has denied any involvement in one of India's longest-running scandals.</p>
<p>&quot;She is a foreigner and she can expect the Bofors case to be dragged up,&quot; said an analyst with a securities house in Bombay.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral's United Front coalition denied that Sonia Gandhi represented a threat to the alliance.</p>
<p>But some analysts said a galvanised Congress could eventually pose a threat to the centre-left coalition, which lost its previous leader, former prime minister H.D. Deve Gowda, when Congress suddenly withdrew its support.</p>
<p>Charan Wadhwa of the Centre for Policy Research said Sonia might be preparing the ground for an eventual entry into politics by either her daughter Priyanka, 24, or her son Rahul, 26. &quot;She may want to keep the seat warm for her children,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
