<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569902" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - May 8.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Indian business and political stories in leading newspapers prepared for REUTERS by Business News and Information Services Pvt Ltd, New Delhi Tel:3324842, 3351006, 3761233 Fax:+91-11-3351006 Internet: biznis@giasbm01.vsnl.net.in</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>		   -------oo0oo-------</p>
<p>			TOP STORIES</p>
<p>The Times Of India</p>
<p>GOVERNOR HAS FULL POWERS TO ALLOW PROSECUTION</p>
<p>The Bihar governor said the governor had powers to permit the prosecution of a chief minister facing criminal charges. However, he clarified that so far there was no question of any action on his part. Whatever steps he would take in this regard would be after the Central Bureau of Investigation sought his permission to prosecute chief minister Laloo Yadav in the animal husbandry case on the basis of a charge sheet.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Economic Times</p>
<p>FINANCE BILL MOVED IN PARLIAMENT</p>
<p>The finance minister moved the Finance Bill in parliament, giving a push to infrastructure, the power sector in particular, and clarifying the revenue aspects of the proposed voluntary disclosure scheme. There were no changes in the personal income tax. The two major changes in the bill were the deferment in the proposed tax on the service sector and a modification in the voluntary disclosure scheme. Nine billion rupees were proposed to be provided to the power sector over the next five years.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>HINDUSTAN LEVER, ICI JOINT VENTURE ON CARDS</p>
<p>Hindustan Lever (HLL) was likely to spin off its three billion rupee speciality chemicals division into a separate joint venture with ICI in India following parent Unilever's decision to sell the chemicals business to ICI for $8 billion. The HLL board would consider the impact of the Unilever decision on its Indian operation in due course. HLL and ICI have been negotiating over an arrangement with regards to the chemical business.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>TRADE DEFICIT WINDENS TO $ 5.44 BILLION, EXPORTS TOTTER</p>
<p>India's exports in April-March 1996/97 were estimated at $33.10 billion, representing a growth of 4.01 percent. The trade deficit widened to $5.44 billion against $4.53 billion, said an official release. Exports for March 1997 were put at $3.29 billion, 5.69 percent lower than the previous year's. Monthly export values in March 1997 were the highest for the year. Imports were estimated at $38.54 billion, 5.99 percent higher against $36.36 billion. Oil imports had been valued at $9.61 billion, 34.38 percent higher than the previous year's, and incremental oil imports at $2.5 million. Non-oil imports had been estimated at $28,931 billion, 0.96 percent lower than last year's.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>SBI CAPITAL MARKETS TOPS AMONG MERCHANT BANKERS</p>
<p>In a year in which most merchant bankers were likely to declare losses, the top five merchant bankers managed to retain their top positions. As per the latest data available on funds mobilised by all India merchant bankers through public issues of debt and equity in 1996/97 (April-March), SBI Capital Markets led the pack, closely followed by JM Financial, Kotak Mahindra, DSP Merrill Lynch and Enam Securities. RR Finance and Looha Caps ended the year in the list of top 10 merchant bankers in terms of money raised. The performance of these two relatively smaller merchant bankers was better than ANZ, Industrial Development Bank and I-Sec, which ranked eighth, ninth and tenth respectively.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Financial Express</p>
<p>FOREIGN COMPANIES WIN NOTE PRINTING TENDER</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank of India awarded contracts worth 3.4 billion rupees to print 3.6 billion currency notes to nine foreign companies. For the first time, the RBI will import currency notes through the flotation of a global tender inviting international bids to print currency notes. The first tranche of imported notes will be released into the banking system in July. RBI has awarded the contract to two parties, a consortium of three UK companies and a French-Canadian bank consortium.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY SETS MAY 31 DEADLINE</p>
<p>The Telecom Regulatory Authority (TRAI) has given the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) until May 31 to resolve all pending issues regarding the finalisation of licence agreement for basic services. TRAI said in case DoT was unable to meet this deadline, it would move in to decide these issues. The TRAI move, according to experts, was aimed at resolving the imbroglio between DoT and private operators on the issue of interconnect charges.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>SINGAPORE COMPANIES MAY DESERT BANGALORE AIRPORT PROJECT</p>
<p>The consortium of Singapore investors may pull out of the 14-billion-rupee Bangalore airport project as the Civil Aviation Ministry gave clearance for build-operate-transfer and not the promised build-own-operate basis. Sources said the consortium would reconsider participation in the joint venture after studying the new terms. The consortium, which has 24.5 percent stake in the project, may opt out of the venture since the government reneged on the original agreement to allow build-operate-own terms. The consortium has already spent around 200 million rupees on feasibility studies and other development expenses.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>STATE BANK TO OFFER ONE-WAY QUOTE IN TERM MONEY MARKET</p>
<p>State Bank of India (SBI) planned to enter the term money market by offering only one-way quotes. This would be a deviation from the standard practice as commercial banks offer two-way buy and sell quotes in money markets. The bank does not intend to borrow from the market. To start with, SBI might offer quotes for two-week and one-month money. SBI's entry might stabilise the fledgling term money market which was unable to take off following an apex bank directive.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>DUTY CONCESSIONS WORTH 1.11 BLN RUPEES ANNOUNCED</p>
<p>The finance minister announced concessions in customs and excise duties on items of common consumption and some industrial inputs, amounting to 1.11 billion rupees. The minister also relaxed the Voluntary Disclosure Scheme, enhanced allocation for power sector, provided special incentive for telecom and excluded software exports from the ambit of minimum tax. The items include umbrellas, fruit juice based non-alcoholic beverages, synthetic sewing thread, roofing tiles, matches, switches and plugs, sanitary towels, napkins for babies and match boxes. Ferro-nickel, CNC systems, carbon black and certain specified raw material would also now be cheaper.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Standard</p>
<p>WHIRLPOOL LOSSES CLIMB TO 642 MLN RUPEES</p>
<p>Whirlpool, despite a 74 percent growth in turnover, plunged deeper into the red, with losses climbing to 641.8 million rupees for the 15-month period ended December 1996. In September 1995, the company had reported a 362.4 million rupee loss. For 1995/96 (April-March), the home appliances maker reported a loss before depreciation of 506.7 million rupees, against 284.3 million in the previous year. Depreciation nearly doubled to 141.5 million rupees from 78 million, pushing up the losses. The total turnover of the company rose from 4.4984 billion rupees to 7.8457 billion rupees.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>INDUSTRIAL GROWTH SLIPS TO 1.1 PCT IN JANUARY</p>
<p>Industrial growth in January dropped to 1.1 percent, against 12.9 percent in January 1996 (base 1980/81), led primarily by a drastic drop in the growth rate of the consumer durables and capital goods sectors. The capital goods sector registered negative growth of 3.2 percent against a growth rate of 19.5 percent in January 1996.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Observer</p>
<p>COURT WANTS ACTION ON GRANT OF DTH LICENCES</p>
<p>The Delhi High Court asked the government why it was neither granting nor rejecting applications seeking licences to receive signals from satellites through Direct to Home devices. The court took exception to the government sitting on the applications submitted as per law and not taking a decision. It asked the counsel for all the respondents, including the Department of Telecommunications, to respond within two weeks regarding the status of the application by the petitioner and also the reasons behind the action.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>AUTO EXPORT NORMS TO BE EASED</p>
<p>The government decided to relax stipulations on export obligations by passenger car joint ventures under the existing memorandum of understanding (MoU) system. Foreign collaboration ventures in the automobile sector would now be allowed to postpone their annual export commitments of their initial years' operations to the later years of their MoU period. Moreover, passenger car ventures would be allowed to export auto components instead of passenger cars as stipulated under the existing MoU. Licences would be issued to these companies for importing certain number of completely knocked down/ semi knocked down kits.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
