<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569941" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan scraps tenders for 50,000 tonnes sugar.</title>
<headline>Pakistan scraps tenders for 50,000 tonnes sugar.</headline>
<dateline>KARACHI, Pakistan 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The state-run Trading Corporation of Pakistan (TCP) said on Thursday it had scrapped tenders invited last month from international suppliers for the import of 50,000 tonnes of crystal white refined sugar, with shipments to reach Karachi in June and July.  </p>
<p>A TCP official said fresh tenders would be invited within the next few days. Suppliers would be asked to ship 25,000 tonnes of sugar to Karachi by June 20 and the remaining 25,000 by July 10.</p>
<p>&quot;We scrapped the tender as neither the lowest prices were up to our expectations nor were suppliers prepared to meet other specifications,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>He said the lowest bidder had offered to supply 14,000 tonnes by June 20 at $340.50 per tonne while the second lowest bid was $352 per tonne. In its last tender in January the TCP bought 60,000 tonnes from India and private traders have also booked imports of more than 150,000 tonnes this year.</p>
<p>Pakistan has already imported  484,835 tonnes of sugar worth $185 million during the July-March 1996/97 period, the Federal Bureau of Statistics said.</p>
<p>The Pakistan Sugar Mills Association said on Monday sugar production had reached 2.32 million tonnes by April 15 compared to 2.43 million at the same time a year ago. Mills aimed to produce 2.4 million tonnes in 1996/97, compared to 2.47 million in 1995/96 and 3.0 million in 1994/95.</p>
<p>--Ovais Subhani 9221-5685192</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARACHI, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
