<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569908" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: IMF says it continues talks with Dhaka on loan.</title>
<headline>IMF says it continues talks with Dhaka on loan.</headline>
<dateline>DHAKA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior official of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) said on Thursday the Fund would continue talks with Bangladesh on a possible loan, but said the country should first remove &quot;structural rigidities&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Bangladesh still has got some structural rigidities in a number of areas and the government should deal with those strongly,&quot; Margaret Kelly, a senior adviser in the IMF's Asia and Pacific department, told a news conference.</p>
<p>Kelly is leading an eight-member IMF team to Bangladesh for talks with government officials on a soft-term balance of payment support and other fiscal and monetary issues.</p>
<p>Kelly did not elaborate on the structural rigidities&quot;</p>
<p>She, however, said Bangladesh must strengthen its banking system dogged by huge non-performing loans, and make efforts to privatatise public enterprises or close down loss making ones.</p>
<p>The official said Bangladesh needed to liberalise further its trade regime and intensify fiscal reforms.</p>
<p>Bangladesh has recently asked for soft term loans from the IMF as the country is facing a tighter balance of payment position because of its depleting foreign exchange reserves.</p>
<p>Kelly would not say the amount of the possible IMF loan that would be available from the fund's Enhanced Structural Adjustment Facility (ESAF).</p>
<p>Finance Minister S A M S Kibria recently told reporters that Bangladesh might seek $600 million from the IMF.</p>
<p>Kelly appreciated the government's success in containing inflation and growth in agricultural production.</p>
<p>&quot;The present government made a good pick up by containing the rate of inflation and reaping a very good harvest during the current year,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Finance Ministry officials said the current inflation rate is 3.2 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DHAKA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
