<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569909" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India cites 10 airline near-misses since November.</title>
<headline>India cites 10 airline near-misses since November.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>There have been 10 near-misses mainly involving commercial airliners in Indian air space since the world's worst mid-air collision near Delhi in November, Civil Aviation Minister C.M. Ibrahim said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Ibrahim said in a written statement to parliament that the government was modernising air traffic services at Delhi and Bombay, insisting on proper maintainence of equipment and improving training to avoid further mishaps.</p>
<p>But he said there had been 10 close calls since a Saudi Arabia Airlines Boeing 747 and a Kazakh Ilyushin Il-76 freighter collided about 80 km (50 miles) west of New Delhi on November 12, killing all 349 people aboard the two aircraft.</p>
<p>He named four Indian airlines, the Indian Air Force and eight foreign airlines among those whose aircraft were reported in near-misses since November.</p>
<p>There were six cases, including three involving Indian passenger planes, reported in January alone, the statement said.</p>
<p>The mid-air collision in November focused world attention on flight safety in India, where economic growth has spurred tourism, putting pressure on outdated air traffic systems.</p>
<p>A multi-million-dollar plan to modernise radar and communications systems at major airports has fallen well behind schedule.</p>
<p>Due to go into operation six months ago, a state-of-the-art air traffic control system built by Raytheon Co of the United States has been held up by technical glitches.</p>
<p>In November Raytheon said the system would soon be ready for use.</p>
<p>India needs massive doses of private investment to build vital airport infrastructure and improve flight safety, aviation experts say.</p>
<p>India dismantled a state aviation monopoly as part of a series of sweeping economic reforms in 1991, opening its skies to a dozen private airlines.</p>
<p>India has five international and 87 domestic airports. Delhi and Bombay airports handle nearly half the total traffic.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
