<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569924" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Foreign investors cautiously watching India - HSBC.</title>
<headline>Foreign investors cautiously watching India - HSBC.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign investors have adopted a wait-and-see attitude due to political uncertainties in India but the overall trend is positive and encouraging, a senior official of HSBC Investment Bank Plc said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there is a desire to invest and they are just taking a wait-and-see attitude before committing themselves,&quot; Paul Selway-Swift, chairman of HSBC Investment Bank Asia Holdings Ltd, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It hasn't given them strong encouragement to invest at this moment,&quot; Selway-Swift replied when asked if the recent change in government had affected foreign investment.</p>
<p>Selway-Swift is also deputy chairman of HSBC Investment Bank Plc, part of HSBC Holdings Plc.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral assumed office last month after his predecessor H.D. Deve Gowda lost a confidence vote in parliament.</p>
<p>The Congress party withdrew its make-or-break support from Deve Gowda in March but later pledged to back his United Front coalition if Deve Gowda was replaced as leader.</p>
<p>&quot;The economic signals overall are generally positive,&quot; Selway-Swift told Reuters after a news conference in the Indian capital.</p>
<p>Foreign investors have confidence in domestic companies and their ability to innovate, work and compete with foreign firms, he added.</p>
<p>HSBC Investment Banking said earlier on Thursday that it is setting up a merchant bank in India.</p>
<p>India's Foreign Investment Promotion Board has approved a $20-million equity investment in HSBC Capital Markets India Private Ltd, making it one of the largest dedicated merchant banks in the country, a company statement said.</p>
<p>It said an application had been submitted to the Securities and Exchange Board of India for a Category One merchant banking licence.</p>
<p>HSBC Investment Banking handles the merchant banking, equity securities and asset management activities of the HSBC group.</p>
<p>HSBC Capital Markets India will specialise in the four products of equity capital markets, debt capital markets, financial advisory including mergers and acquisitions, and project finance.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to provide the full range of our investment products into the Indian market,&quot; Selway-Swift said.</p>
<p>He said foreign investors had shows a great deal of interest in Indian stocks. &quot;There is lot of appetite among international investors for good quality Indian papers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>- New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
