<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="569918" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Sonia Gandhi, Indian dynasty's standard-bearer.</title>
<headline>Sonia Gandhi, Indian dynasty's standard-bearer.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sonia Gandhi, whose decision to join her late husband's Congress party was announced on Thursday, is India's favourite enigma.</p>
<p>The Italian-born widow of former prime minister Rajiv Gandhi, whose family members have ruled India for 38 of its 50 years since independence from Britain, has enrolled as a party member, Congress president Sitaram Kesri said.</p>
<p>For Indians it was a move fraught with significance.</p>
<p>Often since 1991, when a Sri Lankan Tamil suicide bomber killed Rajiv Gandhi in an election rally, Sonia had spurned calls to inherit her husband's political mantle.</p>
<p>But her presence has been noticed during visits by world leaders who are as apt to call on her as on opposition leaders.</p>
<p>Congress, weakened by feuds and corruption scandals, has sought a role for her since the elegant, now naturalised Indian citizen, shrouded in a white sari of Hindu mourning, brought her mangled husband's corpse to lie in state.</p>
<p>Sonia, aged 50, has also addressed gatherings organised by the Rajiv Gandhi Foundation, a non-profit think tank and social organisation formed in her husband's memory.</p>
<p>Aside from the much-talked-about wedding of her daughter, Priyanka, to a New Delhi businessman in February, Sonia has been the subject of magazine cover stories, lurid headlines and a favourite topic of armchair political experts.</p>
<p>In the only instance that smacked of politics, Sonia Gandhi complained about the slow progress of an inquiry into her husband's murder during a public meeting two years ago.</p>
<p>Her apparent target was then prime minister P.V. Narasimha Rao, whose authority was gradually undermined by Congress rebels close to Sonia Gandhi.</p>
<p>Sonia Gandhi was named in a survey in April, 1996 as the most popular choice for prime minister after then Congress chief Narasimha Rao and Atal Bihari Vajapyee, leader of the Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party.</p>
<p>Rao quit the prime ministership one month later after general elections, and Vajpayee held the post for only 12 days before giving way to H.D. Deve Gowda's centre-left coalition.</p>
<p>Sonia's mystique derives from the dynasty which is tightly associated with India's freedom fight against the British and its struggle as an independent nation since 1947.</p>
<p>On May 21, 1991, the woman suicide bomber robbed Sonia of the man she had called her &quot;greatest security&quot; when he entered the volatile politics of the world's most populous democracy after the assassination of his mother, Indira Gandhi, in 1984.</p>
<p>In the early 1990s, Indians speculated she would enter politics herself with a flourish, draw on Rajiv's popularity and become India's first non-native-born prime minister.</p>
<p>Others said Rajiv Gandhi's death had ended the dynasty.</p>
<p>A furore over alleged illegal payments in an arms case had contributed to Rajiv Gandhi's defeat in 1989. The family has denied any involvement in one of India's longest-running scandals.</p>
<p>By mid-1996, with Congress fractured and ridden with corruption scandals, there was a growing conviction she would remain a powerful party figure behind the scenes.</p>
<p>News on Thursday that she had decided to join the political fray could mark her coming out.</p>
<p>Born on December 9, 1946, into the family of a middle-class Turin businessman, she was thrust into the political limelight by three deaths in just over a decade.</p>
<p>When the former convent schoolgirl married Rajiv Gandhi in 1968 after a romance in Britain's university town of Cambridge, her husband was an unassuming pilot for Indian Airlines.</p>
<p>But he was also the scion of India's first family, the son and grandson of prime ministers Indira Gandhi and Jawaharlal Nehru.</p>
<p>Neither of Sonia and Rajiv's two children, Rahul, 26, or Priyanka, 24, has expressed a desire to enter politics.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
