<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570011" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Attorneys general say progress made at tobacco talks.</title>
<headline>Attorneys general say progress made at tobacco talks.</headline>
<dateline>DALLAS 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Gail Appleson, Law Correspondent</p>
<p>State attorneys general said Wednesday they were encouraged by progress made at tobacco settlement negotiations on the key issue of liability and talks with the industry would continue next week.</p>
<p>&quot;This is one of the best days we've had in the six weeks of negotiations. We're very happy with what has gone on today,&quot; said Mississippi Attorney General Mike Moore after talks with the industry recessed Wednesday evening.</p>
<p>&quot;We've got a long way to go, but we made alot of progress today. We set out this morning with some goals and we accomplished those goals today,&quot; he said but refused to give details.</p>
<p>Connecticut Attorney General Richard Blumenthal, who heads the group's committee on civil liability, was less enthusiastic.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been progress and there are signs of flexibility but there has not been enough progress to cheer or applaud or celebrate. But at least there's enough to keep us going and keep us at the table,&quot; Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>Blumenthal said that the issue of the tobacco industry's liability was the critical focus of the negotiations.</p>
<p>&quot;Liability is front and center,&quot; he said adding that that the parties cannot consider other issues until this question is resolved. He said the parties are not discussing money.</p>
<p>Blumenthal said the attorneys general had made proposals to cigarette companies that would allow them to anticipate their potential financial liability without depriving plaintiffs of their right to sue.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a real possibility of securing a high degree of predictability through the ideas we have put on the table,&quot; Blumenthal said. He declined to give details.</p>
<p>Another negotiator, however, told Reuters previously that one idea would allow plaintiffs to sue cigarette companies and any damages awarded would be paid out of a special fund with an annual cap. If the fund is exhausted in one year, a successful plaintiff would get paid the following year.</p>
<p>The attorneys general are united in their stance that they will not agree to a settlement that would give the industry total protection from lawsuits, Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>He said the attorneys general were determined to preserve individuals' right to sue cigarette makers.</p>
<p>&quot;If they are insisting on taking away a person's rights, then the chances of settlement are significantly diminished,&quot; Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>He said the attorneys general would never agree to any pact that would present enough obstacles to plaintiffs that it would amount to immunity.</p>
<p>The attorneys general have sued the tobacco industry to recoup Medicaid costs of smokers. Also taking part in the negotiations are members of the health community and lawyers representing smokers and their families.</p>
<p>The attorneys general also indicated Wednesday that they had rejected an industry plan that would set stiff barriers for smokers seeking compensation from the industry, capping claims at $250,000 and barring punitive damages.</p>
<p>Mississippi's Moore said that proposal, which was reported in Wednesday's Wall Street Journal, was &quot;old news&quot; and that the negotiators were &quot;way beyond that.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DALLAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
