<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570045" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Washington Homes sets writedown, sees loss.</title>
<headline>Washington Homes sets writedown, sees loss.</headline>
<dateline>LANDOVER, Md. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Washington Homes Inc said Thursday it will incur pretax third quarter, ended April 30, charges of about $19 million to write down goodwill and certain land inventory to fair value.</p>
<p>The writedown will result in an after tax charge of about $16.0 million, or $2.01 per share, the company said.</p>
<p>It also said operating results in the quarter fell significantly below those of last year's third quarter when it had net earnings of $614,000, or $0.08 per share.</p>
<p>For the first half of fiscal 1997, the company reported earnings of $0.20 per share, up from $0.14 last year.  </p>
<p>Washington Homes said net new orders in the latest quarter represent a record level of orders for any quarter, rising 6.8 percent from a year ago to 438 orders valued at $67.0 million.</p>
<p>During the quarter, the company said, it delivered 258 homes compared with 245 for the same period last year, up 5.3 percent.</p>
<p>At April 30, the backlog of homes under contract was up 15.2 percent from a year earlier to a record 841 homes valued at $135.0 million.  The Washington market backlog was up slightly, two percent, while other markets were up 43 percent.  </p>
<p>Washington Homes said it expects to report third quarter results later this month. The company previously announced a third quarter charge of $400,000, or $0.05 per share, on a settlement of taxes related to its 1992 recapitalization.</p>
<p>The company said it &quot;obtained a necessary waiver from a lender&quot; and the writedown and tax settlement will not violate any covenants of its lending agreements.</p>
<p>It said a significant portion of the writedown was land for two long term development projects owned for more than 20 years and goodwill which resulted from the acquisition of Washington Homes in 1988.  The rest was related to six communities being closed out and three condominium properties in the Maryland suburban areas of Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>The company said it has reviewed its long-lived assets, including goodwill, for possible impairment. This was indicated by a decline in margins in the Washington market, increased goverment regulations and fees and continued competitiveness of the Washington market, it explained.</p>
<p>Noting the writedowns were non-cash charges, it said the action &quot;will permit us to position the company to better compete with other homebuilders who have already taken writedowns.&quot;  ((-- New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610.))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I5010022">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LANDOVER, Md."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
