<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570037" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Harvard Inds seeking buyers for Doehler.</title>
<headline>Harvard Inds seeking buyers for Doehler.</headline>
<dateline>TAMPA, Fla. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Harvard Industries Inc said it is seeking buyers for its Doehler-Jarvis subsidiary because it can no longer support the subsidiary's capital requirements.</p>
<p>Harvard's Chairman, John Adams, said Thursday that Harvard Industries' Chapter 11 bankruptcy filing was precipitated by the continued operating losses at Doehler-Jarvis and the need to reorganize its  capital structure.  </p>
<p>Adams said Doehler-Jarvis &quot;may be profitable in the long run, (however,) Harvard Industries cannot support this subsidiary's current capital requirements and still adequately finance its profitable subsidiaries.&quot;</p>
<p>Harvard Industries is also seeking buyers for its Harman Automotive subsidiary, which manufactures outside rearview mirror systems and exterior door handles and its Harvard Interiors subsidiary which manufactures and assembles office furniture and defense components.</p>
<p>The company said it has engaged Houlihan Lokey Howard &amp; Zukin to assist with the sale of Doehler-Jarvis and to provide financial advisory services.</p>
<p>Doehler-Jarvis manufactures die-cast metal automotive components.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAMPA, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
