<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570010" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chrysler, UAW reach tentative pact.</title>
<headline>Chrysler, UAW reach tentative pact.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chrysler Corp. and union bargainers said Wednesday they reached a tentative agreement to end a month-old engine plant strike here that paralyzed production of some of the automaker's most profitable vehicles.</p>
<p>The strike at the Mound Road Engine plant was the most disruptive at Chrysler in more than 20 years and will end up costing the automaker between $300 million and $475 million, according to a range of estimates provided by analysts.</p>
<p>The agreement would allow Chrysler to proceed with controversial plans to transfer drive shaft work to an outside supplier, sources close to the talks said.</p>
<p>Details were not officially released. But analysts, union officials and other sources said the nation's third largest automaker promised in return to add a new engine block line at its Mound Road Engine plant in Detroit. The company also pledged to bring future drive shaft work into the plant.</p>
<p>The use of outside suppliers, or outsourcing, was at the heart of the dispute, which paralyzed Chrysler's North American production of its high-profit full-size pickup trucks and sport utility vehicles.</p>
<p>More than 18,900 workers have been idled because of the strike, and the number had been as high as 23,000.</p>
<p>The dispute has cost Chrysler production of about 95,000 vehicles, said Lehman Brothers analyst Joseph Phillippi.</p>
<p>&quot;Was it worth it? I guess it was worth it to prove your point,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The 1,856 members of United Auto Workers union Local 51 who walked off the job shortly before midnight April 9 are scheduled to vote on the deal Friday.</p>
<p>Roger Barham, a steward at Local 51, said employees were not likely to return to work before next Monday.</p>
<p>Barham said the agreement offers Mound Road workers the opportunity to transfer to Chrysler's New Mack Engine plant, and addresses numerous health, safety and discrimination grievences.</p>
<p>&quot;It sounds satisfying. Now it's up to our membership,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Engine block work coming to the plant will be for 3.9 liter V6 and 5.2 liter V8 engines. Previously, the blocks were made in Germany and shipped into the plant.</p>
<p>UAW members had insisted Chrysler drop plans to shift production of drive shafts to Toledo, Ohio-based Dana Corp. The union said the transfer could mean the loss of 300 jobs.</p>
<p>The plant supplies most of the engines and rear-wheel drive components for Chrysler pickup trucks, Jeep Cherokees and Grand Cherokees, the Viper sports car, and other models.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, talks aimed at resolving two strikes against General Motors Corp. continued Wednesday. Those strikes have forced GM to halt production of its Chevrolet Malibu and Oldsmobile Cutlass cars in Oklahoma City and some pickup trucks at a plant in Pontiac, Mich.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
