<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570055" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Harvard Industries files for bankruptcy.</title>
<headline>Harvard Industries files for bankruptcy.</headline>
<dateline>WILMINGTON, Del. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Harvard Industries Inc and nine affiliates, including Doehler-Jarvis Inc, filed for Chapter 11 protection on Thursday in the U.S. Bankruptcy Court in Delaware, a court spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Harvard's Chairman, John Adams, said the action was precipitated by continued operating losses at the company's Doehler-Jarvis subsidiary, and the need to reorganize its capital structure.  </p>
<p>&quot;We believe this filing to be a prudent action, which will ultimately ease Harvard's debt burden, increase the company's liquidity, and permit us to focus on our highly successful core businesses,&quot; Adams said.</p>
<p>Harvard has secured a commitment for $175 million in Debtor-In-Possession financing, which includes the pre-petition facility, enabling it to support continuing operations at its subsidiaries, pay its suppliers on an ongoing basis, and continue prompt delivery of automotive components to customers.</p>
<p>Harvard did not identify the source of the D-I-P financing.</p>
<p>&quot;We intend to propose full payment to our suppliers as part of our plan, and expect to emerge from the process with substantially reduced debt,&quot;  Adams said.</p>
<p>&quot;Harvard Industries is open for business today and will be in the future.  We intend to meet our obligations to our customers, our vendors, our employees and our shareholders ....&quot;  </p>
<p>The company listed assets of $478.6 million and liabilities of $708.1 million, of which $598.1 million is in fixed, liquidated unsecured debt with 12,000 holders, court papers say.</p>
<p>Court papers describe at least $300 million of the debt as 12 percent senior notes due 2004 and 11-1/8 percent senior notes due 2005.</p>
<p>Court papers say &quot;the obligations of Harvard Industries Inc under the 12- and 11-1/8 percent senior notes are guaranteed by each of its debtor subsidiaries.&quot;</p>
<p>Harvard Industries is an original equipment manufacturer of automotive parts and accessories.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WILMINGTON, Del."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
