<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570073" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US corporate debt issues still stifled, junk aside.</title>
<headline>US corporate debt issues still stifled, junk aside.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Billions of dollars of railroad and U.S. government securities kept corporate bond issuers suppressed on Thursday but for a $250 million seven-year issue from Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc, dealers said.</p>
<p>High-yield bond issues were more insulated from Treasury volatility, however, and at least two issues will price.</p>
<p>Despite the lull in high-grade issuance, syndicate officials said the market appears to have some equilibrium as investors were themselves largely sidelined. But the Lehman issue was likely to grab sufficient demand at its current price talk of 78 to 80 basis points over the curve.  </p>
<p>Distribution of the $29 billion three- and ten-year notes, sold in auctions with lackluster to poor demand, occupied taxable fixed-income players, according to several syndicate officials. That is also not to forget a possible Federal Reserve rate hike this month, they added.</p>
<p>&quot;There's no reason to believe we'll get anything more than we've seen for the week,&quot; one capital market official said. &quot;Dealers have been a major driver in the new issue market and they're busy putting away Treasuries.&quot;</p>
<p>Norfolk Southern Corp's upcoming $3.0 billion multi-tranche offering also capped activity, some said.  </p>
<p>Turning to junk bond offerings, fund managers noted pricing power has been slipping away from them to the sell side following two weeks of marked improvement. Still, one manager said buyers are more selective than not.</p>
<p>&quot;The new issue market is mixed right now,&quot; said one fund manager. &quot;There have been both credit and pricing reasons to stay away from deals, but for the most part we've seen strong credits coming to our doorstep.&quot;</p>
<p>Mail order food products company Colorado Prime Corp priced on the wide side of price talk on Thursday, reflecting selectivity, according to another manager.</p>
<p>In the new issue on Thursday, Cityscape Financial Corp is expected to price $300 million 144A seven-year B1/single-B rated senior notes via CIBC Wood Gundy Securities. Price talk on the issue is around 11-1/2 percent.</p>
<p>Also, GST Telecom's GST Equipment Funding Inc may price its $230 million 144A 10-year senior secured notes at 13.00 percent to 13-1/4 percent on Thursday through a Morgan Stanley &amp; Co syndicate. The issue has a three-year prefunded structure, sources said.</p>
<p>((--Al Yoon, 212-859-1672))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
