<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570033" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: SEC overstates case in enforcement action-lawyers.</title>
<headline>SEC overstates case in enforcement action-lawyers.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Securities and Exchange Commission has overstated case law in at least one of the enforcement actions it brought in the last two years against municipal market participants, a committee of bond lawyers reported on Thursday.</p>
<p>The enforcement subcommittee of the National Association of Bond Lawyers drew the conclusion in a 49-page report analyzing whether the SEC is holding bond lawyers, bond dealers and other muni market participants to a higher enforcement standard than players in the corporate securities market.</p>
<p>The subcommittee, whose report was prepared by John McNally, a partner with Hawkins, Delafield &amp; Wood, analyzed SEC actions involving Orange County, Calif.; bond lawyers Thorn, Alvis, Welch Inc.; Maricopa County, Ariz.; CS First Boston; and other municipalities nationwide.</p>
<p>In a recent SEC complaint against First Boston, for instance, SEC alleged that the firm and two of its investment bankers responsible for underwriting an Orange County bond issue had failed to fulfill their &quot;duty to assure&quot; that information in the official statement for the deal was not false or materially misleading.</p>
<p>But McNally's panel concluded that the First Boston complaint overstates the case law and principles set out in a 1988 SEC interpretation of the responsibilities of municipal underwriters.</p>
<p>&quot;An underwriter does not have a 'duty to assure' that a disclosure document is accurate,&quot; the subcommittee said.</p>
<p>The panel concluded that the SEC has not gone beyond existing legal standards concerning parts of its Orange County Report on the activities of the Orange County board of supervisors.</p>
<p>&quot;The Orange County report argues that because the investments in the pools were extremely risky, and because the county was dependent on the income from the pools to balance (its) discretionary budget, and because supervisors either knew or were reckless in not knowing of such risk and dependency, the supervisors therefore had a duty ... to assure accurate disclosure was made to investors regarding this material information,&quot; the subcommittee said.</p>
<p>&quot;In so concluding, the SEC is reiterating a standard that it has previously articulated regarding the conduct of individual members of a board of directors of a corporation. If an individual board member knows, or is reckless in not knowing, of a material misstatement or omission, that person must aggressively act to correct the misleading information,&quot; the subcommittee said.</p>
<p>McNally is scheduled to outline the report at a two-day NABL conference beginning Thursday here.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
