<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570142" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Giddings &amp; Lewis rejects Harnischfeger bid.</title>
<headline>Giddings &amp; Lewis rejects Harnischfeger bid.</headline>
<dateline>FOND DU LAC, Wis. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Giddings &amp; Lewis Inc said Thursday its directors unanimously rejected a $19 a share takeover offer from Harnischfeger Industries Inc and termed the bid inadequate and not in the best interests of shareholders.</p>
<p>In another development, Giddings &amp; Lewis said it has had preliminary discussions with other parties regarding their potential interest in a possible transaction involving the company. It said it has entered into confidentiality and standstill agreements with interested parties and is responding to due diligence requests.  </p>
<p>The parties were not identified.</p>
<p>Giddings &amp; Lewis said its board gave careful consideration several factors which led to rejection of Harnishfeger's offer, including an opinion of Credit Suisse First Boston Corp, the company's financial advisor, that the offer was not adequate from a financial point of view.</p>
<p>Giddings &amp; Lewis said it recommends shareholders not tender any shares to Harnischfeger.  </p>
<p>Giddings &amp; Lewis also said its board concluded that the interests of shareholders would best be served by continuing to explore actively all strategic alternatives. The company's management and financial advisors have been instructed to review options, it said.</p>
<p>Harnischfeger launched an unsolicited bid for Giddings &amp; Lewis shares at $19 a share on April 28.</p>
<p>Giddings &amp; Lewis said it is filing with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission its recommendation to reject the offer.</p>
<p>Giddings &amp; Lewis is a large supplier of industrial automation products and machine tools. Harnischfeger is an international holding company with business segments involved in the manufacture and distribution of equipment for underground mining, surface mining, pulp and papermaking and materials handling.</p>
<p>		     ((Chicago newsdesk 312 408 8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I32754">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FOND DU LAC, Wis."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
