<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570177" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: COMEX copper called to open slightly higher.</title>
<headline>COMEX copper called to open slightly higher.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>COMEX copper futures were seen opening slightly higher Thursday, in line with LME copper prices, despite a small rise in LME warehouse copper stocks.</p>
<p>COMEX July was seen opening unchanged to up 0.50 cent a pound from Wednesday's close at 110.45 cents, after trading a 110.45-110.95 cent range in overnight ACCESS trade.</p>
<p>LME copper stocks rose 950 tonnes to 152,925 tonnes Thursday, while COMEX copper stocks were down 723 short tons Wednesday to 44,982 short tons.</p>
<p>While volatility has slipped in the past 10 days, the uptrend in COMEX July copper since mid-April was still intact, traders said, with the July/September spread remaining firmly in backwardation around 3.20 cents a pound.</p>
<p>The potential for supply shortfalls in both Chile and the U.S., combined with the current tight global stock situation may help the contract to test its highs at 113.65 cents again soon, analysts said.</p>
<p>The strike continues at Chile's Quebrada Blanca copper mine and there is a possibility that a drought in southern Chile may reduce electricity supplies for Chile's copper mines, analysts said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile in the U.S., the impasse continues in the contract talks at Phelps Dodge's Chino mine in New Mexico and Kennecott's smelter in Utah remains closed.</p>
<p>With world refined copper stocks representing less than three week's supply, prices are seen remaining firm, analysts said. ((--Clive McKeef, New York Commodity Desk 212-859-1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
