<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570100" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Empire of Carolina sets $16 mln investment.</title>
<headline>Empire of Carolina sets $16 mln investment.</headline>
<dateline>DELRAY BEACH, Fla. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Empire of Carolina Inc said Thursday private investors have agreed to invest up to $16 million for newly issued Empire convertible preferred.</p>
<p>The company said the investors, HPA Associates LLC and EMP Associates LLC, have funded a $5 million bridge loan to provide the toy maker with additional liquidity during the period prior to the closing of the preferred stock investment.</p>
<p>Empire of Carolina's line of basic toys includes Big Wheel ride-on toys, Grand Champions collectible horses, Buddy L cars and trucks, and Power Driver ride-ons. Its Holiday Products Division produces and markets decorative seasonal items.  </p>
<p>Upon completion of the investment, the investors will own securities convertible into or exercisable for a substantial majority of Empire of Carolina's outstanding stock, it said.</p>
<p>The company said the bridge loan is repayable upon the closing of the preferred stock investment under with the securities purchase agreement covering the investement.</p>
<p>It said the principals of HPA Associates, Charles S. Holmes and James J. Pinto, have substantial experience with investments in publicly traded companies. Holmes and other HPA employees will provide the company with support to help continue the turnaround of its factory in Tarboro, N.C.  </p>
<p>The agreement provides that the investors will purchase $11 million of newly issued convertible preferred stock by June 5 and the company may elect to issue an additional $5 million of preferred to the investors within 180 days.</p>
<p>The preferred, which bears no dividend, will be convertible into common at $1.25 per share and will vote on all matters on an as-if-converted basis, the company said.</p>
<p>Upon funding of the bridge loan, the investors got five million warrants to purchase common at $1.375 per share. The warrants are forfeitable under certain circumstances if the $11 million preferred stock investment is not completed.</p>
<p>If the company elects to issue the additional $5 million of the preferred stock, the investors will be issued an additional 2.5 million warrants upon closing.</p>
<p>It also said Charles Holmes and Lenore Shupeck will assume two of five seats on its board, and its Stockholder Rights Agreement was amended to facilitate the proposed investment.</p>
<p>It said the preferred stock transaction is subject to undisclosed closing conditions and the company can give no assurance it will be completed; and, in the event it is not completed, there can be no assurance that cash generated from operations will fund continued operations.</p>
<p>((-- New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610.))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I49410">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DELRAY BEACH, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
