<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570125" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Brown's Famous Footwear April same store sales off.</title>
<headline>Brown's Famous Footwear April same store sales off.</headline>
<dateline>ST. LOUIS, Mo. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brown Group Inc said Thursday that April same store sales for its Famous Footwear division dropped 4.4 percent, which followed a 9.3 percent increase in March.</p>
<p>Sales for Famous Footwear in April were $60.3 million, up 0.3 percent.</p>
<p>For the first quarter, Famous Footwear same store sales rose 3.5 percent, which was &quot;slightly higher than planned,&quot; Harry Rich, chief financial officer, said in a statement.  </p>
<p>&quot;Athletic footwear and children's shoes performed well throughout the quarter, and women's casual shoes and sandals also sold well until poor April weather dampened that business,&quot; Rich said.</p>
<p>Brown Group said its Naturalizer division's sales decreased 2.4 percent in April to $11.1 million, and its same-store sales were down 1.9 percent.</p>
<p>For the first quarter, Naturalizer's sales fell 6.3 percent to $30.9 million and same-store sales dropped 5.5 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Fresh spring merchandise, including sandals and casual footwear, sold well in the Naturalizer Retail stores, helping offset continuing lower dress shoe sales,&quot; Rich said.</p>
<p>((Reuters Chicago Newsdesk (312) 408-8787))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ST. LOUIS, Mo."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
