<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570262" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Blair's new cabinet agrees legislative programme.</title>
<headline>Blair's new cabinet agrees legislative programme.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The new Labour cabinet on Thursday agreed a 17-month legislative programme to enable Prime Minister Tony Blair to stamp his modernising philosophy on Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;We have agreed the Queen's Speech,&quot; deputy Prime Minister John Prescott told journalists at the end of the first meeting of Blair's governing team.</p>
<p>&quot;It reflects all those priorities that we had in the general election -- that of education, of crime, of jobs, of decentralisation, of devolution,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Prescott was referring to the speech, written by the government, which Queen Elizabeth will read next Wednesday when she opens the first session of the parliament that was chosen at the May 1 election.</p>
<p>In the new parliament, Labour has a massive 179-seat majority which it will use to push legislation through -- a stark contrast with the end of the last parliament when Prime Minister John Major's Conservatives were in a minority.</p>
<p>&quot;These are great times,&quot; Blair told Labour members of parliament on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have the chance to do something quite special, possibly even quite spectacular for the future of our country.&quot;</p>
<p>Aides said Blair will live up to his election pledge to make education &quot;the passion of my government&quot; by including no fewer than three bills on the subject in the Queen's Speech.</p>
<p>But much legislative time and effort are likely to be expended on devolution: Blair has promised to hold referendums on setting up Scottish and Welsh mini-parliaments within months.</p>
<p>The government will also indicate its determination to help the people it claims suffered under the Conservatives.</p>
<p>Blair aides said the Queen's Speech would set up a commission to work out proposals for a national minimum wage, detail plans to get unemployment down and foreshadow a policy document on freedom of information.</p>
<p>Legislation to ban political parties from accepting funds from foreigners is also expected following allegations that overseas businessmen had bankrolled the Conservatives to curry favour with ministers.</p>
<p>Following the cabinet meeting, Blair prepared for a meeting later on Thursday with his Irish opposite number John Bruton.</p>
<p>Bruton told BBC radio ahead of the meeting that the election of a British government with a secure majority is a &quot;great opportunity&quot; to move the Northern Irish peace process forward.</p>
<p>In the week it has been in power, the Blair government has surprised observers with its speed of action.</p>
<p>Finance minister Gordon Brown on Tuesday announced plans to hand control over interest rates to the Bank of England and foreign secretary Robin Cook has rushed to mend fences with Britain's European Union partners.</p>
<p>In a sign he proposes to govern pragmatically, Blair on Wednesday appointed Sir David Simon, chairman of British Petroleum, as minister for trade and competitiveness in Europe.</p>
<p>The Conservatives, who lost almost half their seats in an election debacle that had historians stumped for precedents, are meanwhile preparing for a leadership battle after Major's decision to step down.</p>
<p>Six of Major's former cabinet colleagues have now declared they will be candidates to become opposition leader.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
