<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570295" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: OPTIONS - European holiday mutes Bund volatility.</title>
<headline>OPTIONS - European holiday mutes Bund volatility.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A holiday in much of continental Europe left Bund volatility suffering from limited trade, although it swung around in the early part of the session as the underlying futures headed down, traders said.</p>
<p>Implied volatility of the June Bund options traded on LIFFE was vacillating either side of 5.0 percent by 1445 GMT, brokers said, after briefly heading to 5.2 percent earlier on.</p>
<p>&quot;Vol was better bid in the morning,&quot; said a trader at a European bank on the LIFFE floor. &quot;But once the futures clawed back up, vol moved back to be unchanged.&quot;</p>
<p>Germany and France were closed for the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>June Bund futures were down 0.10 at 101.66, off the day's low of 101.31. September futures were down 30 basis points at 100.45.</p>
<p>Traders said volume was slight, with most activity confined to the June puts, where the 101.00 and 100.50 strikes vied for the most trade.</p>
<p>In the September series, a combination trade was noted, where the 99.00 puts were bought and the 102.00 calls were sold.</p>
<p>LIFFE data show 3,600 puts traded at the 99.00 strike and the same number of calls at the 102.00 strike.</p>
<p>-- International Bonds Unit + 44 171 542 6137</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
