<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570284" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Gold snaps higher but only to hit resistance.</title>
<headline>Gold snaps higher but only to hit resistance.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S.-inspired wave of fund buying shook gold out of its lethargic state on Thursday afternoon but only to bump it into a wall of resistance, dealers said.</p>
<p>Some players were surprised by the move which sent bullion prices to nearly one-month high of $345.15 an ounce, given large short positions which have kept opinions biased to the downside.</p>
<p>&quot;It took everyone by surprise. It was a bit of a shake-out almost,&quot; said one London dealer.</p>
<p>After an uneventful European session thinned by the Ascension Day holiday, bullion snapped up to an afternoon fix of $343.75 from $342.40 and a London close of $340.60/$341.10.</p>
<p>&quot;The weaker dollar may have something to do with it. The market was just stale, stuck in a narrow range for so long that it had to break one way or the other,&quot; said the dealer.</p>
<p>&quot;But if I had to put money on it I would have guessed it was the other way,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Another dealer pointed to silver for jump-starting the precious metals complex after it cruised through the $4.75 resistance area, triggering buy-stops placed just above it.</p>
<p>Gold's upright performance above the key $340.00 level recently has impressed analysts and fresh gains on Thursday might have stirred shorts to take cover against a bigger hike.</p>
<p>In New York, Comex June gold futures contract stood $2.60 higher at $345.00 and struggling to overcome a pressure point.</p>
<p>The potential impact from speculators could be to the upside, dealers said. The funds had made money in gold earlier in the year and were not running unusually deep open positions.</p>
<p>&quot;They tried to push it lower. Without a huge open position, the risk next time could be to the upside,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>But gold experts still maintain the view that spikes towards the top of the trading range between $336.15 and $345.00 have to be seen as a sell and a chance to increase short positions.</p>
<p>Silver burst higher from its cosy range after having been ignored since its bounce last week. It was quoted at $4.83/4.85, up a sharp 10-cents and the highest level since April 17.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no fundamental reason,&quot; said one dealer, adding that silver was just chasing gold's technical rally.</p>
<p>Platinum and palladium were both firmer, at $376.50/$377.50 and $158.00/$159.00, up $4.75 and $2.50 respectively.</p>
<p>Dealers noted Japanese buying in platinum early on.</p>
<p>But no signs of an end to the deadlock in Russian platinum group metals (PGM) sales to Japan emerged despite a Russian official's comments on Wednesday that talks were about to begin.</p>
<p>-- Clelia Oziel, London Newsroom +44 171 542 8071</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
