<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570282" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: ERM has nothing to offer UK economy now - analysts.</title>
<headline>ERM has nothing to offer UK economy now - analysts.</headline>
<byline>Rosemary Bennett</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The new British government may want to consider re-entering the Exchange Rate Mechanism if it is eager to sign up to European Economic and Monetary Union, but to join the currency grid at this stage defies all economic logic, analysts say.</p>
<p>Economists in London's financial district on Thursday poured scorn on a report that the pound might join the European exchange rate grid at 2.50 marks, saying it ran against all economic sense as well as Labour Party policy.</p>
<p>&quot;It is beyond belief that the government would even be thinking about rejoining the ERM at this stage,&quot; said David Mackie, UK economist at JP Morgan.</p>
<p>&quot;It would restrict the room for manoeuvre incredibly and the authorities would be forced to do things they would very definitely not want to do.&quot;</p>
<p>Labour party and Treasury officials said they were puzzled by a report by agency Bridge News that Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown might be attracted to re-entering the ERM at a central rate of just 2.50 marks.</p>
<p>&quot;The government has no intention of rejoining the ERM. Mr Brown has made that clear on other occasions going back a year ago,&quot; a Treasury spokesman said.</p>
<p>The report gave no date for rejoining the grid but existing Labour pledges, particularly a referendum on a single currency would make early entry impossible anyway.</p>
<p>&quot;Joining the ERM at this stage ignores the rather obvious obstacle of requiring the consent of the people,&quot; said Alex Garrard, UK economist at UBS.</p>
<p>He said EMU and ERM membership would more likely be an issue for a second Labour term. With a huge 179 seat majority, Prime Minister Tony Blair will have no need to seek re-election until 2002.</p>
<p>Furthermore, only two days ago Brown granted the Bank of England operational control over interest rates. To rob it of a large chunk of its hard won powers would be irrational, economists said.</p>
<p>And given that the British economy is way ahead of most of its European partners in the business cycle -- signs of overheating have already been detected in the retail and services sector -- to embark on a course of monetary relaxation in order to push sterling lower would be dangerous.</p>
<p>The pound stood at around 2.77 marks on Thursday, well above the 2.50 mark desired entry level suggested by the report.</p>
<p>Even if the ruling Labour party were keen to sign up to EMU, it has until now appeared to adopt the previous government's position that membership of the ERM is not a necessary condition for EMU membership.</p>
<p>The Maastricht Treaty states that a two year period within the ERM is a necessary condition for EMU membership, but former Chancellor of the Exchequer Kenneth Clarke, along with Sweden, has argued that the wide 15 percent bands now operating in the ERM make it meaningless.</p>
<p>Britain's historical relationship with the ERM is an unhappy one. It conducted an informal policy of shadowing the mark from 1987 which helped fuel the economic boom as the government kept interest rates low in order to prevent the pound from appreciating against the mark.</p>
<p>In October 1990 -- after a summer in which the pound was talked up by politicians and aides -- sterling joined the ERM at a central rate of 2.95 marks.</p>
<p>But the economy was already heading into recession and because the government was tethered by its ERM membership and the need to keep the pound at its set level, it could not cut interest rates as swiftly and sharply as it needed to.</p>
<p>The membership was short-lived. Less than two years later in September 1992, the pound was ejected from the system after a summer of bruising speculative attacks in the currency markets.</p>
<p>&quot;The implicit exchange rate tie from 1988 was a disaster and the membership of the ERM was a disaster. I can't see any attraction in signing up again,&quot; said Mackie.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7715</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
