<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570287" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Dlr slides in Europe as yen and Swiss franc rally.</title>
<headline>Dlr slides in Europe as yen and Swiss franc rally.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar ended over one pfennig and one yen lower in Europe as jitters about Japanese foreign exchange intervention buoyed the yen and talk of a broad-based start to European monetary union lifted the Swiss franc.</p>
<p>Thin trading conditions in Europe exaggerated the intraday swings as most of continental Europe, including Germany, was out for the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>The yen's recovery is being fuelled by what many perceive as thinly-veiled official warnings more yen weakness will be opposed.</p>
<p>&quot;The Japanese are warming us up for the fact that interest rates there may change,&quot; said Tony Norfield at ABN Amro.  </p>
<p>Norfield, who is a treasury economist at ABN Amro, said the Japanese authorities had clearly allowed market interest rates to tick higher as well as reminding traders the Bank of Japan has $220 billion of reserves with which to defend their currency.</p>
<p>&quot;This has seen Japanese investors cut a lot of overseas bond positions and was probably partly behind sterling's fall today too,&quot; said Norfield.</p>
<p>At 1530 GMT, the dollar was trading at 123.70/80 yen compared with 124.90/95 late Wednesday. Against the mark, it was trading at 1.7069/74 compared with 1.7210/15 late yesterday.  </p>
<p>The yen's latest push higher was fuelled by comments from senior Japanese Ministry of Finance official, Eisuke Sakakibara -- know in the markets as &quot;Mr. Yen.&quot; Sakakibara said that based on past performances the dollar/yen's average annual range could allow its scope to go as low as 103 yen this year.</p>
<p>&quot;For a man as clued-in to the market as Sakakibara, you don't mention specific levels like that without knowing their likely impact,&quot; said a trader at a U.S. house here.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, another Ministry of Finance official said Japan was prepared to use its huge foreign exchange reserves promptly if the yen continued to weaken excessively.  </p>
<p>Dollar/yen has risen up to 10 percent this year alone to a 56-month high at 127.46 earlier this month.</p>
<p>Analysts said the dollar's plight was not helped by a benign assessment of inflation from the U.S. Federal Reserve in its regular Beige Book report late Wednesday, further dampening speculation of another imminent U.S. interest rate rise.</p>
<p>Sterling was a big loser in early trading, meantime, after a news report cited a ruling UK Labour Party source as saying a return to Europe's exchange rate mechanism at a central rate of 2.50 marks by 2001 was possible. Sterling was trading about 2.82 marks before the report and fell as low as 2.7654 on Thursday.  </p>
<p>The UK Treasury later denied the talk but analysts said the more Euro-friendly tone of the new UK government would keep talk of a lower sterling target in the market. Others say interest rate speculation is shifting against the pound and the government will be happy with a weaker unit.</p>
<p>&quot;Sterling's vulnerability does not come from the direction of poor policy credibility but from the size of the sterling overvaluation and the prospect of fiscal, not monetary tightening,&quot; said Avinash Persaud, head of currency research at JP Morgan. He said the European stance of the new government will also lead to a fall of the pound's EMU safe-haven status.  </p>
<p>The fall of the dollar and the rising prospect of a broad-based EMU, possibly with Italy and the UK, helped the Swiss franc higher as the prospect of a weak euro pushed funds to the low-inflation haven of Switzerland, said analysts.</p>
<p>--Mike Dolan, London newsroom +44 171 542 6762</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
