<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570250" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: IBM to pay Sears $450 million for rest of Advantis.</title>
<headline>IBM to pay Sears $450 million for rest of Advantis.</headline>
<dateline>SOMERS, N.Y.</dateline>
<text>
<p>International Business Machines Corp. said Thursday it agreed to buy the rest of the Advantis computer services company from Sears, Roebuck &amp; Co. for $450 million, moving to bolster its fast-growing service business.</p>
<p>IBM, the world's biggest computer maker, currently owns 70 percent of Advantis and said it would fold the unit into its Global Services arm, the fastest growing part of its business.</p>
<p>Sears, the nation's second-largest retailer, said the sale of its 30 percent Advantis stake would help it focus on its core business. It expects to book a pretax gain of about $150 million on the sale.</p>
<p>Based in Schaumburg, Ill., Advantis was formed in late 1992 to provide computer network and telecommunications services to customers based in the United States. IBM's Global Services unit is based in Somers, N.Y., about 40 miles north of New York City.</p>
<p>&quot;Because we believe network computing will contribute significantly to IBM's future success, we decided that acquiring full ownership of Advantis was increasingly important to our network computing strategy,&quot; IBM Global Services Senior Vice President Dennie Welsh said.</p>
<p>In a presentation to Wall Street analysts on Wednesday, IBM Chairman Louis Gerstner emphasised that services and software were the growth engines for IBM, whose 1996 revenues of $76 billion made it the nation's sixth biggest company.</p>
<p>IBM's first-quarter earnings of $1.2 billion -- about flat with a year earlier but stronger than Wall Street analysts had expected -- included a strong performance from its services business, where revenues jumped 28 percent to $4.1 billion.</p>
<p>IBM Global Services had sales of $22.9 billion in 1996, and is the largest provider of information technology services in the world.</p>
<p>For Sears, the move is its latest out of non-retail businesses. Sears has spun off or sold its Allstate insurance, Dean Witter brokerage and Prodigy online businesses over the last five years.</p>
<p>&quot;The sale of the Sears equity stake in Advantis reflects our continuing effort to focus our resources on our core businesses,&quot; Sears Chief Financial Officer Alan Lacy said.</p>
<p>Sears said the pretax gain would be recorded when the sale is completed.</p>
<p>The sale is subject to approval by regulators and other conditions, the companies said in a statement.</p>
<p>IBM stock jumped $6.50 to $168.625 in active trading on the New York Stock Exchange after two Wall Street firms raised their price targets for the stock.</p>
<p>Sears rose 50 cents to $50.25 also on the NYSE.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOMERS, N.Y."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
