<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570268" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Mr Yen knocks dollar, London shares steady.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Mr Yen knocks dollar, London shares steady.</headline>
<byline>Ron Askew</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar found a fragile poise against the yen by midday on Thursday after sliding earlier when comments from Japan's &quot;Mr Yen&quot; stirred fears of central bank intervention.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, London shares clawed back most of the losses they suffered in early trade following a big tumble on Wall Street overnight. But trade was light as London was the only key financial centre in Europe not closed for the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>Influential Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara -- Mr Yen to the markets on account of his influence -- undermined the dollar's value against the yen when he said the past year's movements raised the chance that the Japanese currency could strengthen, possibly to 103 per dollar.</p>
<p>The U.S. unit slipped from around 124.70 yen just before the remarks to a low of 123.70 and stood at 123.77 at 1100 GMT.</p>
<p>&quot;People are on tenterhooks about whether we actually see any intervention,&quot; said Nigel Richardson, economist at Yamaichi. &quot;People are aware there's a chance of some kind of intervention if they're really serious about (yen weakness).&quot;</p>
<p>On Wednesday intervention fears gripped the market and shook the dollar after a Japanese agency report that the G3 nations -- Japan, the United States and Germany -- were studying the possibility of concerted selling of dollars for yen.</p>
<p>&quot;The fear of intervention is clearly rising, but the success of the mere threat to intervene is probably enough to keep the G3 from actually executing intervention for now,&quot; said Klaus Baader, international economist at Deutsche Morgan Grenfell.</p>
<p>Although Germany -- keen to boost exports and spur economic growth -- is thought to be less troubled than Japan by the dollar's current levels, the Sakakibara shock waves rippled through dollar/mark too. It fell to a 1.7097 mark low from late Wednesday's 1.7210, although it was back at 1.7140 by 1100 GMT.</p>
<p>Analysts said the interest rate scenario was also working in the yen's favour, as speculation grew of Japanese tightening. In the United States, by contrast, Wednesday's &quot;Beige Book&quot; release gave no indication that the Fed would have to raise rates fast, they said.</p>
<p>In its latest Beige Book on business conditions, the Federal Reserve said the U.S. economy expanded moderately over the last two months while wages and retail prices were generally subdued.</p>
<p>Fed policymakers will use the findings when they meet on May 20 to consider whether to tighten credit, after raising rates at their last meeting in March for the first time in more than two years.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, the British Treasury moved quickly to dampen speculation that Britain planned to rejoin the EU's Exchange Rate Mechanism (ERM) at a central rate of 2.50 marks in 2001.</p>
<p>Responding to an overnight news agency report, which quoted a Labour Party source as saying sterling should rejoin the ERM at 2.50 marks, a Treasury spokeswoman said: &quot;There is no truth in it at all.&quot;</p>
<p>But the market remained suspicious that the Labour Party -- which swept into power last week -- would be happy to see the pound weaken from the levels which have inflicted such pain on Britain's exporters.</p>
<p>The pound lost around four pfennigs overnight on the report carried by Bridge news agency. It then recouped some of the losses but was still sickly at midday when it stood at around 2.7790 marks.</p>
<p>Sterling left the ERM in September 1992, after the government found it impossible to keep the currency near the then 2.95 central rate. The system was designed as a precursor to a single European currency.</p>
<p>London stocks turned mixed by late morning as a 139.67 points fall on Wall Street because of a sharp fall in Treasury bonds was shrugged off. The positive factors that produced a series of record highs this week continued to underpin sentiment.</p>
<p>A tumble in BTR shares after a profit warning from Britain's biggest conglomerate was also shrugged aside and the FTSE 100 was down just 3.1 points at 4,534.4 at around 1100 GMT, after dropping some 20 points shortly after the opening.</p>
<p>Declining stocks exactly balanced gainers in thin trading of just 219 million shares -- with activity depressed by the Ascension day holiday across much of Europe.</p>
<p>BTR said the pound's strength would hit first-half 1997 sales by 300 million pounds ($487 million) if the currency stayed at its current high levels.</p>
<p>But, noting last Friday's rise in some exporting stocks as sterling wobbled, dealers said more sustained weakness in the currency could create a buying opportunity.</p>
<p>&quot;Some of these overseas earners could start to look very interesting,&quot; one senior dealer said.</p>
<p>STOCK PRICES AT 1100 GMT</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 was down 3.1 points at 4,534.4.</p>
<p>The Paris CAC-40 index was closed for Ascension Day. It ended down 8.62 points at 2,643.31 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Frankfurt's DAX index was also closed for Ascension Day. It ended down 16.30 points at 3,551.98 on Wednesday</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 1100 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar stood at 1.7140 marks compared with 1.7210 late in Europe on Wednesday. It was at 123.77 yen compared with 124.93.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold was fixed at $342.40 after closing at $340.85 an ounce in London on Wednesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
