<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570291" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britons stressed and confused, survey finds.</title>
<headline>Britons stressed and confused, survey finds.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britons are stressed out, confused about what to eat and know they should exercise but don't, a survey published on Thursday found.</p>
<p>Nearly a third smoke although most want to give up, and despite knowing sunbathing can be dangerous they still admire a tan, the survey by the Office for National Statistics found.</p>
<p>Sixty-nine per cent of women and 62 per cent of men reported experiencing a &quot;moderate&quot; or &quot;large&quot; amount of stress in the past year.</p>
<p>Sixty-eight percent of 4,645 adults surveyed  said experts could not agree on what a healthy diet was, and 32 percent said they were confused about &quot;what is supposed to be healthy and what isn't&quot;.</p>
<p>Thirty-one per cent of men and 29 per cent of women were current cigarette smokers. &quot;Almost two-thirds of current smokers would like to give up,&quot; the survey said.</p>
<p>A quarter of those surveyed knew that healthy exercise meant 30 minutes of physical activity five days a week, but a quarter exercised less than once a week.</p>
<p>Thirty-two per cent of those aged 16 to 54 said they had used illegal drugs at some time. Among those aged 19 to 21, 74 percent of men and half of all women had.</p>
<p>&quot;When asked whether they would use a condom with a new partner, 67 per cent of women and 58 per cent of men said that they would always do so, while 17 per cent of women and 31 per cent of men said it would 'depend',&quot; the survey said.</p>
<p>Just under half of women questioned agreed that &quot;having a suntan makes me feel healthier&quot; and &quot;having a suntan makes me look more attactive&quot;.</p>
<p>That is despite dermatologists' warnings that sun or sunbed exposure can cause cancer and premature wrinkles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
