<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570244" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Investors snub TIPS as U.S. deficit shrinks.</title>
<headline>Investors snub TIPS as U.S. deficit shrinks.</headline>
<byline>Roanne Daniels</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Treasury Department's new darlings -- inflation-linked notes floated last January -- have fallen prey to bullies on Wall Street as a shrinking federal deficit and low inflation make the securities weaklings.</p>
<p>The 10-year notes were originally called TIPS, an acronym for Treasury Inflation Protected Securities, but frustrated dealers battling an illiquid market soon came up with their own creative labels. None of them are very nice.</p>
<p>Some traders simply reversed the acronym TIPS to SPIT, saying that was what the securities were worth.</p>
<p>One trader said he was betting that the securities would no longer be offered five years from now.</p>
<p>Since the notes appeal mostly to retirees trying to preserve their nest eggs on inflation-adjusted terms, another dealer called TIPS buyers &quot;buy, hold and die&quot; investors.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen very, very low customer demand. What there is is of a very limited variety and not enough to justify the amount of issuance the Treasury is trying to do in this type of programme,&quot; a trader at a major U.S. investment bank said.</p>
<p>In defence of the securities, Deputy Assistant Treasury Secretary Roger Anderson told Reuters he believes the securities will lower borrowing costs -- saving taxpayers' dollars -- and that liquidity will improve with time.</p>
<p>&quot;We view the development of the index securities market as a long-term project. We didn't expect them to be the investment of choice for absolutely everybody overnight,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Economists opposed to the securities said TIPS endanger the liquidity and flexibility of the Treasury bill and coupon markets as they take a small piece out of a shrinking pie.</p>
<p>Last week's agreement between the White House and Congressional Republicans to balance the nation's budget by 2002 heightened concern over a dwindling pool of government debt.</p>
<p>&quot;TIPS is to remind you this is the tip of the iceberg. It is a big problem and we want to be sure it isn't something that sinks liquidity and the rest of the Treasury market,&quot; said Robert Brusca, chief economist at Nikko Securities Co. International Inc.</p>
<p>Anderson said this year the Treasury has cut back its supply of two- and three-year bills and notes, but the impact of the index-linked notes on supply so far is unclear.</p>
<p>&quot;It's hard to say -- some of it has been due to index securities and some of it has been due to the shrinking deficit (which) has caught us by surprise,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Economists claim that the Treasury has issued TIPS for political, not cash flow, reasons and said the timing was poor as inflation was near its modern lows at the date of issuance.</p>
<p>&quot;If you look at the government auction, TIPS are not really necessary from an issuance standpoint. The Treasury is doing it for political reasons to try to give an inflation gauge and people aren't trading TIPS issues,&quot; said Michael Strauss, chief economist at Sanwa Securities (USA) Inc.</p>
<p>Nations typically issue price-linked securities when inflation is habitually high or above trend as a way of betting price growth will slow and validating political calls for less inflation.</p>
<p>However, when TIPS debuted last Jan. 29, the Consumer Price Index showed inflation at roughly 3.3 percent compared with a year earlier -- well below the 25-year average of 4.0 percent, economists said. As of March, the CPI had shrunk to 2.8 percent.</p>
<p>Foreign investors and central banks, which account for a large chunk of Treasury bill and coupon sales, have shown little interest in TIPS due to lack of liquidity, relatively wide spreads, and inability to speculate, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;You are never going to convince foreigners to buy TIPS the way they buy Treasuries. They need liquidity and with the deficit the way it is, you won't be able to issue TIPS in the amounts needed,&quot; the U.S. investment bank dealer said.</p>
<p>Also worrying investors was recent speculation about the accuracy of the CPI.</p>
<p>A commission headed by Stanford University professor Michael Boskin concluded last December that CPI overestimates consumer inflation by about one percentage point annually.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
