<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570275" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SNAPSHOT - BTR profit warnings in last 3 years.</title>
<headline>SNAPSHOT - BTR profit warnings in last 3 years.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>BTR's profit warning earlier on Thursday is the latest in a string of result alerts that have dented investors confidence in the conglomerate.</p>
<p>Following is a list of BTR's profit warnings in the last three years.</p>
<p>- September 8, 1994 - BTR says profit margins have come under pressure due to overcapacity in its markets. Shares fall 44 pence to 338 pence.</p>
<p>- March 9, 1995 - BTR reports a 10.8 percent jump in 1994 profit and promises more of the same in 1995. Analysts call last autumn's profit warning unnecessary.</p>
<p>- December 5, 1995 - BTR says 1995 profits will come in below market expectations citing as weak Australian housing market and sluggishness in U.S. and European car manufacturing. Shares fall 14 pence to 320 pence.</p>
<p>- May 16, 1996 - BTR expects lower first-half operating profit due to a poor performance of Polymer Taiwan. Shares down 14 pence at 297 pence.</p>
<p>- May 8, 1997 - BTR warns first-half 1997 profits will be hit by the strong pound and market weakness in Australia and Germany. It is the second warning by chief executive Ian Strachan, who took over from Alan Jackson in January 1996.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
