<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570211" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INTERVIEW-Sun TV tests new retail strategy.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW-Sun TV tests new retail strategy.</headline>
<byline>Hugh Bronstein</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sun Television and Appliances Inc's interim chief executive said the company hopes to turnaround its retail operations with a new strategy to be tested over the next month.</p>
<p>Interim chief executive R. Carter Pate said he plans to turn the company around without laying off more employees or closing more stores. Pate took the helm late Tuesday after the resignation of president and chief executive James Copitzky and its chief financial officer Steven Martin.  </p>
<p>The company reported a fourth quarter net loss of $34.1 million, which included restructuring charges of $14.7 million. For the year it reported a loss of $45.3 million, including $16.7 million in restructuring charges.</p>
<p>Pate is a managing partner with Price Waterhouse Business Turnaround Services. He joined Sun Television in February to oversee the company's turnaround.</p>
<p>Next week Pate said the company will launch new advertising, marketing and customer service initiatives in the company's three Cincinnati stores.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're revamping what our stores look like and how our employees are trained to sell,&quot; Pate said.</p>
<p>By mid-month, Pate said he will be evaluating the success of the Cincinnati effort - which includes pricing guarantees, advertising initiative and redesigned interiors -  and planning its exportation to the company's other stores.</p>
<p>Sun employs about 3,300 in 41 consumer electronic and appliance stores in Ohio, Pennsylvania, West Virginia, and Kentucky and in its corporate offices and distribution center in Columbus.  </p>
<p>Pate declined to say how much the effort will cost or how his turnaround might manifest itself in earnings or margins in the months to come. He said he sees no turnaround charges above the $16.7 million the company recently incurred.</p>
<p>In January the company said it would close nine under- performing stores and eliminate more than 1,000 full-time positions.  </p>
<p>&quot;I am not going to allow distractions such as divestitures, mergers and acquisitions to interfere with the single goal of putting this company back on solid financial ground and stop the erosion of the same store sales,&quot; Pate said.</p>
<p>Sun said its comparable store sales for the fourth quarter fell 26.6 percent from the same period of the previous fiscal year. Gross margin was 16 percent, compared with 23.6 percent for the fourth quarter last year.</p>
<p>Sun said its margins were pressured by inventory liquidations associated with its store closings.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're not liquidating inventory any more, so you're not going to see the margin erosion problems we had in the fourth quarter due to store liquidation,&quot; Pate said.</p>
<p>Announcement of the departing officers came with the company's release of its year-end results, in which it reported a loss of $2.60 a share, compared to a profit of $0.38 a share in fiscal 1996.</p>
<p>Although he holds the titles of Sun CEO and president, Pate is paid by Price, which was contracted for the turnaround.  </p>
<p>&quot;I'm going to stay in this role long enough to stabilize and get this company back on its feet,&quot; Pate said. &quot;Then we will begin the search for a CEO.&quot;</p>
<p>Pate said he plans to hire a new CFO within two months.</p>
<p>Sale of assets also figure into his plans.</p>
<p>&quot;We bought some real estate properties that did not make sense,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He did not give a dollar figure for the real estate he wants to sell.</p>
<p>&quot;Sale of non-essential real estate is part of the strategy,&quot; Pate said. &quot;This figures into correcting balance sheet problems that have plagued this company for the last year-and-a-half.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I64800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
