<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570274" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - UK's Kwik Save aims to halt sales fall.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - UK's Kwik Save aims to halt sales fall.</headline>
<byline>Jo Winterbottom</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>British low price high street food retailer Kwik Save Group Plc turned in steady half year profits on Thursday and said it was encouraged by progress in its restructuring.</p>
<p>But the stock market took fright at a fall in current sales of six percent, even though the company said this was offset by a rise in underlying gross margins.</p>
<p>Kwik Save, in which Hong Kong's Dairy Farm holds nearly 30 percent, said first half pretax, pre-exceptional profits were 44.8 million pounds ($72.7 million) compared with 44.2 million pounds previously, and paid out an unchanged interim dividend of 5.95 pence per share.</p>
<p>It said that sales from existing stores in the first seven weeks of the second half were down six percent, but added that an increase in underlying gross margins had continued, offsetting the effect of lower sales.</p>
<p>But its shares slid to be 11.5 pence lower at 296.5 pence by 0830 GMT after touching a low of 295 pence.</p>
<p>&quot;The sales picture remains dire and it is difficult to see how the company is going to turn the corner until the sales line responds,&quot; said one analyst who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>Kwik Save's group marketing director Phil Smith said stopping the fall in sales was the priority and would affect profits.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly our priority is to stabilise the short-term sales position,&quot; he told Reuters, adding that full year profits would be &quot;very much driven by our success in stabilising the sales position.&quot;</p>
<p>Kwik Save started a three-year &quot;new generation&quot; restructuring programme in November which included plans to close 107 stores and focus on building own-brand and improving quality and price.</p>
<p>&quot;There is an underlying decline in our customer numbers, which the new neneration programme squarely addresses,&quot; Smith said.</p>
<p>The company said in a statement it was encouraged by progress and that it looked forward to &quot;building on the momentum for change achieved thus far.&quot;</p>
<p>Kwik Save, which has been squeezed between discounters and the leading supermarket chains, has launched its own-label range as part of the radical shake-up. It hopes it will eventually account for 20 percent of sales.</p>
<p>Smith said the company faced a challenge but was addressing the issues.</p>
<p>He highlighted plans to increase own-label sales, overhaul products offered and expand ranges along with introducing pre-packaged fruit and vegetables in stores which do not have a concession for this range.</p>
<p>But he ruled out any departure from Kwik Save's discount tradition to push sales ahead.</p>
<p>&quot;Absolutely not. The core of our offer is to offer quality foods at discounted prices in accessible stores,&quot; Smith said.</p>
<p>He said Kwik Save's competitors were &quot;almost everybody, in equal measure.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The people who are the movers and the shakers in the industry are clearly the ones with whom...we have the most competitive tussle on our hands,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But he ruled out any moves by Kwik Save into banking or financial services, as some of the big four supermarket chains have done.</p>
<p>&quot;Absolutely not...there is an integrity in our strategy that focuses on selling our customers the foodstuffs that they want at the lowest possible cost,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I64100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
