<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570246" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Living Centers, GranCare set $1.8 billion merger.</title>
<headline>Living Centers, GranCare set $1.8 billion merger.</headline>
<dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
<text>
<p>Living Centers of America Inc. and GranCare Inc. said Thursday they agreed to a $1.8 billion merger that will create the second-largest long-term care provider in the United States.</p>
<p>Under the agreement, Living Centers shareholders will receive $40.50 a share in cash. After a recapitalization, GranCare shareholders will own 49.5 percent of the new company, Apollo Management LP, an investment group, will own 39.3 percent and Living Centers shareholders 11.2 percent, the companies said.  </p>
<p>The merged company will operate 330 facilities with more than 38,000 beds in 21 states, providing long-term care, drug and rehabilitation services, assisted living and speciality health care services.</p>
<p>Houston-based Living Centres provides health care services to senior citizens. GranCare, based in Atlanta, offers speciality medical and long-term care services.</p>
<p>As part of the recapitalization, Apollo will invest $200 million to buy newly issued stock in the new company.</p>
<p>The board of the combined company will include two directors from Living Centers' board, four directors from GranCare and four members named by Apollo. The new board will select a management team of executives from both companies, the companies said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I95100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HOUSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
