<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570272" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - BTR warns on profits, shares slump 11.8 pct.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - BTR warns on profits, shares slump 11.8 pct.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>BTR Plc, Britain's biggest conglomerate, saw its shares nosedive on Thursday after it issued a profit warning just as the market believed the company had the worst behind it.</p>
<p>The widely diversified conglomerate, which is in the final stages of a major restructuring, said the pound's strength would hit first-half 1997 sales by 300 million pounds ($486.7 million) if the currency stayed at its current high levels.</p>
<p>The impact on operating profits would be about 35 million pounds, said BTR, which focuses on industrial manufacturing and engineering operations.</p>
<p>Besides the impact of the strong pound, BTR said it was also suffering from weak markets in Germany and Australia, where the group posts about 30 percent of its sales. This meant that excluding the currency effect, underlying operating profit would be &quot;somewhat lower&quot; than in the first half last year.</p>
<p>The profit warning comes just two months after BTR reported better-than-expected 1996 results and said it was making good progress in getting its act together.</p>
<p>BTR shares dropped 31-1/2 pence, or 11.78 percent, to 236 pence in late morning trade after they shot up early in March on the favourable full-year results.</p>
<p>Analysts reduced profit estimates for this year by about 10 percent to around 1.2 billion pounds.</p>
<p>&quot;Even without sterling, the company is still facing large problems in some of its markets and with some of its products,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>BTR's profit warning also showed that the conglomerate's restructuring, which already saw the weeding out of many of its underperforming operations, is not complete yet.</p>
<p>&quot;They are turning things around, but it is a big ship to turn -- it will take time,&quot; said this industry watcher.</p>
<p>BTR's chief executive Ian Strachan, who took over the helm last year, said the group's divestment programme was over 80 percent complete and that new investments in the core business were in hand.</p>
<p>&quot;The degree of change which BTR is undergoing is far-reaching,&quot; he said in a trading statement made in conjunction with BTR's annual shareholders meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;It cannot happen overnight and the speed at which the strategy begins to show through in the bottom line will continue to be influenced partly by factors outside our control, such as the business cycle or the fluctuation of currencies,&quot; Strachan added.</p>
<p>($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
