<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570277" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Gokal given 14 year prison sentence for BCCI fraud.</title>
<headline>Gokal given 14 year prison sentence for BCCI fraud.</headline>
<byline>Alexander Smith</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A British court on Thursday sentenced former shipping tycoon Abbas Gokal to 14 years in prison for his part in the crash of the Bank of Credit and Commerce International (BCCI), the biggest fraud in banking history.</p>
<p>&quot;These frauds...are as serious as any likely to come before these courts...No lesser period would suffice to mark the gravity of the conduct of which you have been convicted,&quot; judge Richard Buxton said.</p>
<p>He gave Gokal four years for conspiring to account falsely and 10 years for conspiracy to defraud. These will be served consecutively, despite a mitigating plea by defence lawyer Colin Nicholls for a concurrent sentence.</p>
<p>Earlier Buxton ordered Gokal, the former chairman of Mideast shipping and trading group Gulf Group, to pay 2.94 million pounds ($4.8 million) and also imposed a costs order against the Pakistani businessman.</p>
<p>Gokal was found guilty at London's Central Criminal Court in April, following a trial lasting nearly five months.</p>
<p>He is the fifth person to be convicted for his part in the downfall of BCCI, which collapsed in 1991 with debts of more than $12 billion after evidence emerged of widespread money laundering.</p>
<p>&quot;These were not victimless crimes,&quot; Buxton told Gokal, adding that the victims included the many depositors in BCCI who lost a large part of their investments and in some cases their life savings.</p>
<p>&quot;Those deposits were used at least in part to provide funds for the endless advances made by BCCI to your companies, in circumstances in which you knew that there was little or no prospect of the advances being repaid,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Gokal, 61, had with BCCI officials been found to have masterminded a massive fraud totalling around $1.2 billion. Buxton said Gokal was &quot;an intelligent, sophisticated and unscrupulous man&quot; who put the his own interests and his family's before all else.</p>
<p>Chris Dickson, the Serious Fraud Office (SFO) lawyer heading the BCCI inquiry team, told Reuters it was clear Gokal was central to the conspiracy.</p>
<p>&quot;It enabled him to fund a hugely wealthy lifestyle for him and his family at the expense of many ordinary depositors who lost everything. Fourteen years is totally appropriate,&quot; Dickson said.</p>
<p>Dickson said the sentence was &quot;the longest in living memory&quot; for a fraud in Britain and the case underlined the professionalism of the SFO and the police who had worked on the case.</p>
<p>The SFO, which investigates and prosecutes major financial frauds, has been criticised in the past for failing to achieve convictions in several high-profile frauds. In fact it has a success rate of around 63 percent.</p>
<p>Jerry Ohlson, head of the City of London Police fraud squad, told Reuters that he was entirely satisfied with the outcome of the case not only because of the lengthy sentence but also because Gokal had been ordered to pay costs.</p>
<p>This, said Ohlson, would at least give some satisfaction to the many victims of the BCCI collapse and would also send a message to others.</p>
<p>&quot;Would-be fraudsters need to think twice before committing these crimes,&quot; he said outside the Old Bailey, the central criminal court in London.</p>
<p>The case set a precedent but Ohlson said he did not believe there would be another fraud of the scale of BCCI. &quot;That type of crime would be more difficult to commit as a result of better regulation and the level of international co-operation we have now.&quot;</p>
<p>The SFO has another BCCI case due to start later in the year and the battle by liquidators Deloitte &amp; Touche to claim back the BCCI losses is expected to continue for some time.</p>
<p>There are civil cases pending against Gokal and his Gulf shipping and trading group and there is also the possibility of action against him in Pakistan.</p>
<p>So far creditors of BCCI have received some $2.65 billion, around a quarter of their claims, and a further 10 percent is expected to be paid within the next year.</p>
<p>But the cost of pursuing those responsible for the fraud has been huge. Prosecuting counsel Anthony Hacking told the court that in the Gokal case the SFO's costs alone had been 4.3 million pounds.</p>
<p>This did not include the cost to the taxpayer of Gokal's defence, for which he was given legal aid. If Gokal fails to pay the confiscation order of 2.94 million pounds against him within two years, he will have to serve an additional three years in prison.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
