<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570251" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Airways to cut unprofitable routes.</title>
<headline>US Airways to cut unprofitable routes.</headline>
<dateline>ARLINGTON, Va.</dateline>
<text>
<p>US Airways Group Inc. said Thursday it would cut unprofitable routes and close some facilities in a sweeping restructuring aimed at cutting costs at the troubled airline.</p>
<p>The carrier has fallen behind other airlines, which have been slashing costs for the last four years. It also has been seeking to reach a cost-cutting deal with its pilots, and on Wednesday said it would furlough 103 of its 5,000 pilots as part of routine work assignments.</p>
<p>US Airways said it will end jet service in September to nine cities and eliminate other unprofitable routes.</p>
<p>The airline will ground 22 aircraft and by summer 1998 plans to cut capacity by about 6.5 percent.</p>
<p>Arlington, Va.-based US Airways said the steps were necessary whether it ultimately decides to turn itself into a global carrier or a regional airline.</p>
<p>The company said some layoffs were expected, but that it will work closely with union leaders and employee groups to minimise the impact on employees.</p>
<p>The company made no estimate of the cost savings from the plan and did not mention any one-time charges.</p>
<p>US Airways said it hoped labour talks would allow it to put in place a competitive cost structure. Pilots and the company have been negotiating pay and other issues for several months.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, billionaire investor Warren Buffett, whose Berkshire Hathaway Inc. owns $358 million of U.S. Airways preferred stock, said in a statement, &quot;Now is the time to act.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I believe these actions represent a level of foresight and a sense of urgency essential to its future,&quot; he said. Berkshire Hathaway's holdings give it about 10 percent of US Airways' voting rights.</p>
<p>&quot;The company's new management is ready to act in the best interests of all shareholders, employees and communities served... If the labour groups have the will, I know management has the ability to make this airline into the global competitor everyone wants it to be,&quot; Buffett said.</p>
<p>US Airways said cities where jet service will be ended as of Sept. 4 are Albuquerque, N.M.; Austin and San Antonio, Texas; Bangor, Maine; Cincinnati, Ohio; Daytona Beach, Fla.; Islip, N.Y.; Melbourne, Fla., and Newburgh, N.Y.</p>
<p>The company also plans to close its Los Angeles pilot and flight attendant crew base by February, with affected employees being transferred to other bases. US Airways also maintains flight crew bases in Baltimore, Boston, Charlotte, N.C., Philadelphia, Pittsburgh and Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>The airline also said maintenance facilities in Roanoke, Va., and Greensboro and Winston-Salem, N.C., will be phased out by the end of next year except for the Winston-Salem landing gear shop, which will remain open.</p>
<p>Reservations centres in Nashville, Tenn., and Utica, N.Y., will be closed by Oct. 1. US Airways also operates reservations centres in Dayton, Indianapolis, Orlando, Fla., Pittsburgh, San Diego, Syracuse, N.Y., and Winston-Salem, N.C.</p>
<p>&quot;While we recognise that US Airways has made great strides in many areas in the past year, other areas remain unchanged. The time has come to move ahead by beginning to put in place operational changes that enable us to become more efficient,&quot; Chief Executive Stephen Wolf said earlier this week in a message to employees.</p>
<p>US Airways said on Wednesday it cut U.S., Canadian and San Juan round-trip fares by as much as 45 percent.</p>
<p>US Airways stock jumped $2 to $33.75 on the New York Stock Exchange in afternoon trading.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ARLINGTON, Va."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
