<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570283" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Eurobonds quiet amid widespread European holiday.</title>
<headline>Eurobonds quiet amid widespread European holiday.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The primary market ground to a halt on Thursday with many European countries closed for a holiday.</p>
<p>Syndicate managers expected little pick-up in activity on Friday ahead of the weekend.</p>
<p>Among today's limited issuance, Lehman Brothers brought a self-led $300 million five-year FRN at 35 basis points over three-month LIBOR during the afternoon while International Finance Corp issued a 100 million Polish zloty two-year zero coupon bond via ING Barings.</p>
<p>The IFC notes were reoffered at 70 percent of face value, giving an annualised yield of around 19.5 percent.</p>
<p>Peru was said to be planning a dollar Eurobond, its  first offering on international markets since the mid-1980s, bankers said.</p>
<p>No mandate has yet been awarded for the deal which some dealers said could be for up to $500 million.</p>
<p>Last July Peru said it planned to issue $75 million in Euronotes before the end of the year.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, Imperial Chemical Industries said it was watching international bond markets with a view to refinancing part of a $8.5 billion loan taken out to buy Unilever's specialty chemicals division.</p>
<p>ICI is a rare Euromarket borrower, with just a few deals outstanding. They are a brace of 100 million stg bonds due 2003 and 2005, the last of which was launched in 1987.</p>
<p>Standard &amp; Poor's Corp cut ICI's long-term credit rating to A- from A+ after news of the acquisition. Moody's Investor Service cut ICI to A3 from A2.</p>
<p>Pakistan ministry of finance officials said it planned to launch a Samurai bond of around 10 billion yen with a three- to five-year maturity by early next year.</p>
<p>A Pakistani delegation was in London to meet investors ahead of the launch of a three-year dollar FRN, expected to be launched on May 20.</p>
<p>-- Dan Lalor, London newsroom +44 171 542 8863</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
