<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570263" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Gokal ordered to pay for BCCI fraud, sentence due.</title>
<headline>Gokal ordered to pay for BCCI fraud, sentence due.</headline>
<byline>Alexander Smith</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A British court on Thursday ordered Abbas Gokal, former head of the biggest single borrower from the failed Bank of Credit and Commerce International (BCCI), to pay 2.94 million pounds ($4.8 million) for conspiring to account falsely and conspiracy to defraud.</p>
<p>Mr Justice Buxton ruled at London's central criminal court, the Old Bailey, that if Gokal failed to pay the fine, he would be ordered to serve three years in prison.</p>
<p>Gokal is due to be sentenced by Buxton later and faces a maximum prison sentence of 17 years. He was the fifth person to be convicted for his part in the biggest known banking fraud.</p>
<p>&quot;In the event of not complying with this order he will serve a period of three years,&quot; he said, adding that this penalty would run consecutively with any prison sentence.</p>
<p>But Buxton did not impose a compensation on Gokal as had been requested by the prosecution.</p>
<p>Gokal was found guilty in April of conspiring to account falsely and of conspiracy to defraud following a trial lasting nearly five months.</p>
<p>BCCI collapsed in 1991 with debts of more than $12 billion after evidence emerged of widespread money laundering. Thousands of people lost their savings in the biggest fraud in banking history.</p>
<p>Gokal, 61, had with BCCI officials been found to have masterminded a massive fraud totalling around $1.2 billion.</p>
<p>Liquidators Deloitte &amp; Touche are pursuing claims against various parties as a result of the bank's demise.</p>
<p>There are civil cases pending against both Gokal and his Gulf shipping and trading group and further action is expected against him in Pakistan.</p>
<p>So far creditors of BCCI have received some $2.65 billion, around one quarter of their claims, and a further 10 percent is expected to be paid within the next year.</p>
<p>Investigating and prosecuting those responsible for the collapse of BCCI has cost around 15 million pounds, including the four million pound cost of Gokal's case.</p>
<p>Some estimates put the total cost of the Gokal trial, including the legal aid he received for his defence, at closer to 10 million pounds.</p>
<p>BCCI's symbiotic relationship with Gokal's Swiss-based Mideast Gulf group meant the fortunes of the two were inextricably linked.</p>
<p>At the time of his conviction, Chris Dickson, the SFO lawyer heading the BCCI inquiry team, said Gokal's actions had &quot;brought despair to hundreds of thousands of ordinary people who put their savings into BCCI&quot;.</p>
<p>One of the individual losers was Anant Shah, who lost the money he had saved for a bone marrow transplant for his son. The biggest loser was the Western Isles Council in Scotland, which was owed 24 million pounds.</p>
<p>The SFO found documents signed by Gokal in a London safe deposit box showing he and his two brothers owned and controlled the companies involved in the fraud.</p>
<p>The prosecution had said that the sums received from BCCI supported Gokal's lavish lifestyle. Gokal travelled by company jet and owned several luxury cars, including two Rolls-Royces.</p>
<p>It said Gokal had needed large sums of money for his ailing business empire when the recession started to bite during the 1980s. BCCI funded him with such large amounts that much of the lending had to be disguised because the bank was breaking guidelines.</p>
<p>Gokal, who denied the charges against him, fled from his company base in Geneva, Switzerland, to Pakistan in 1992 after Gulf collapsed.</p>
<p>He was arrested by German police at Frankfurt airport in July 1994 when the plane he was travelling on landed for refuelling on a flight from Karachi to the United States. He was extradited to Britain and has been in custody since his arrival in December 1994. ($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
