<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570271" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - Evening Standard - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Evening Standard - May 8.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>NOW BLAIR HALTS HOSPITAL CLOSURES</p>
<p>Tony Blair has honoured one of his key pledges by announcing a halt to all hospital closure plans in London, until a review of health care needs in the capital has been carried out.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>HANDS OFF PENSION PERKS BROWN TOLD</p>
<p>Managers of workplace pension schemes have warned Chancellor Gordon Brown not to tamper with their tax perks. Dr Ann Robinson, director-general of the National Association of Pension Funds, has said that any change to the existing arrangements would harm pensioners and company profits.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BANK MARKET STAFF FACE SWITCH TO TREASURY</p>
<p>Following Gordon Brown's decision to switch control of interest rates to the Bank of England, 81 staff in the Bank of England's market operations division are waiting to hear if they will be transferred to the Treasury or retained at the Bank.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>STERLING SUFFERS A 'BLAIR POLICY' SCARE</p>
<p>Reports that the Blair government is to pursue a lower pound stg led to a massive sell-off of the British currency overnight. At one point, in trading in New York, sterling fell over two cents against the dollar and four pfennigs against the mark.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>NATPOWER PLUGS INTO CHINESE POTENTIAL</p>
<p>Britain's National Power has set up a new subsidiary, National Power Pacific Company, and plans to invest up to 186m stg, to take advantage of China's rapidly growing power needs. The new subsidiary will work with the Chinese concern Power Pacific, investing in power plants on the mainland of up to 200 megawatts in size.</p>
<p>-- BMC +44 171 377 1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
