<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570361" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SBC Warburg places 80 mln BTR shares - dealers.</title>
<headline>SBC Warburg places 80 mln BTR shares - dealers.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>SBC Warburg was placing 80 million shares in BTR Plc at 219p per share on Thursday, well below the market price, dealers said.</p>
<p>The stock was 40p lower at 227-1/2p by 1112 GMT.  </p>
<p>Turnover was 56 million shares by that time.</p>
<p>&quot;Saying it didn't comment on trading matters, an SBC Warburg spokeswoman said: &quot;We have been active two-way traders in BTR shares today&quot;.</p>
<p>The stock plunged earlier after the company issued a profit warning said sterling's strength would hit first-half 1997 sales by 300 million stg if the currency stayed at its current high levels.</p>
<p>&quot;Someone's just seen the profits warning and said 'Get me out of this stock' and not really bothered about the price,&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>In its warning, BTR said the impact on operating profits would be about 35 million stg.</p>
<p>Besides the impact of strong sterling, BTR said it was also suffering from weak markets in Germany and Australia, which provide about 30 percent of sales. This meant that excluding the currency effect, underlying operating profit would be &quot;somewhat lower&quot; than in the first half last year.</p>
<p>Conglomerates analysts reduced profit estimates for BTR Plc by about ten percent following the warning.</p>
<p>Forecasts for this year were cut to about 1,200 million stg from 1,330-1,350 million and for next year to about 1,300-1,320 from 1,465-1,470, they said.  </p>
<p>There were 4.024 billion ordinary BTR shares in issue as of March 31, 1997. BTR market capitalisation is around 9.21 billion stg with the shares trading at 229p.</p>
<p>An 80 million share placing at 219p represents around 1.9 percent of BTR's market capitalisation, according to Reuters Securities 3000.</p>
<p>-- Louise Ireland, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
