<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570368" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - Showers spoil holiday for much of W. Europe.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Showers spoil holiday for much of W. Europe.</headline>
<byline>Christopher Lyddon</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Grey showery unsettled weather has marred the Ascension Day holiday for much of western Europe.</p>
<p>Although still relatively light, the rain is welcomed by farmers still eyeing crops nervously after a prolonged dry spell.</p>
<p>Showers continue across western Europe and are likely to spread east in coming days.</p>
<p>Farmers in some countries reckon most of their immediate problems have been solved by the showery weather. But it is too late for Portugal's winter crops, the country's main farmers' group said.</p>
<p>And water industry sources have said it would take prolonged heavy rain to solve the longer term water supply situation.</p>
<p>The big grain belt south of Paris saw a break in the rain on Thursday morning but the afternoon will be overcast and showery as a new weather system moved east, the state weather service Meteo France said.</p>
<p>French farmers can expect more rain, especially in western France, on Thursday with blustery weather across most of the country until at least Saturday, it said.</p>
<p>The outlook for Friday was for showers, mostly in the north, and a strong westerly wind but mild temperatures in the maize-growing southwest where farmers are busy sowing.</p>
<p>Saturday would see less frequent showers across most of France with some sunny spells, followed by warmer weather up to 24 degrees and a few bursts of rain on Sunday.</p>
<p>Farmers have expressed relief at the rain which arrived at the weekend and helped to break up hard soil after four months of dry weather and drought fears. But underground water resources needed for irrigation remain far below normal -- up to 50 percent in some areas.</p>
<p>Showers continued overnight across the agricultural areas of eastern England, with more coming.</p>
<p>East Anglia, one of Britain's most important grains and sugar beet producing areas, got two to three millimetres of rain between 2100 GMT Wednesday and 0900 GMT on Thursday morning, a spokesman for the London Weather Centre said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are showers there now. There's going to be more throughout the day and more through the next few days,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Threatened frost has not affected the area. &quot;No frost or air frost has been reported from any of our stations (in East Anglia),&quot; he said. &quot;There's been very little frost across England and Wales overnight.&quot;</p>
<p>Recent rain will not save Portugal's winter cereal crops, ravaged by drought, and the main farmers' group has urged the Socialist government to compensate farmers, its president said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Rain levels have been more than 50 percent below normal this year,&quot; Jose Andrade, president of the Confederation of Portuguese Farmers (CAP), told Reuters in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Recent rain has been sporadic and will have no effect on the cereal harvest this summer. The overall situation is extremely worrying, especially for cattle rearing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Italy's Minister of Agriculture Michele Pinto on Wednesday estimated crop damage in central northern Italy due to recent bad weather at between two and four trillion lire.</p>
<p>Pinto was speaking at question time in Italy's lower chamber of parliament following recent drought and frost which have affected large areas of Italy.</p>
<p>Significant rains are erasing drought conditions in western Europe and rainfall will also develop through the east in the next couple of days, bringing an end to the current mild spell, independent forecaster Weather Services Corp said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Major corn areas of western Europe have seen helpful rain and more is due in the region, spreading into parts of the east.</p>
<p>Significant rain has also fallen in parts of Spain, though lingering showers there will taper off the next few days, it said.</p>
<p>In its latest three-to-five day outlook for western Europe WSC forecast a chance of showers regionwide on Saturday, then mostly in the west on Sunday and the southwest on Monday. Temperatures will be cool, then milder.</p>
<p>Germany and central Europe will see showers on Saturday, ending on Sunday, and dry weather on Monday, with warming temperatures.</p>
<p>There will be rain, drizzle and fog in the British Isles on Saturday, showers and drizzle on Sunday and a few showers on Monday. Conditions will be cool, then trending milder again.</p>
<p>Showers in Mediterranean Europe should be limited mostly to Spain, where temperatures will be near normal. It will be dry and warmer over the remainder of the region.</p>
<p>--London newsroom +44 171 542 7928</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
