<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570350" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Physical zinc market seen wary after price spike.</title>
<headline>Physical zinc market seen wary after price spike.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A few zinc consumers may jump in the physical market following Thursday's spike in futures prices to 4-1/2 year highs, but many are likely to be cautious, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;We might see a bit of panic buying when Europe returns next week,&quot; one said, referring to the Ascension Day holiday on Thursday that is expected to dampen business on Friday also.</p>
<p>Activity has been moderate in the physical market over the past couple of week after a bout of shortcovering in late March and could remain relatively slow as summer approaches, he added.</p>
<p>Fund buying pushed three months zinc $41 higher on Thursday morning to a peak $1,328 on the London Metal Exchange, the highest since October 1992.</p>
<p>Many physical buyers are likely to hold back, since several times they had been advised to buy on price spikes when prices later eased. &quot;Consumers have burned their fingers before...they can be a bit cautious,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Another trader said: &quot;I think consumers will back off and there'll be selling into it.&quot;</p>
<p>Premiums were steady, with high grade duty-paid metal at $25/$35 above LME cash, cif Rotterdam, and CIS material at level to $5 above LME cash, unchanged over the past several weeks.</p>
<p>Good offtake has been seen from the steel industry, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;The steel sector was going through a destocking phase over the last six months. But now they will have to rebuild the stocks as well as take care of ongoing needs,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>The physical market may be slow through the summer, but should see a good second half, one trader said. &quot;I have high hopes for the third and fourth quarters,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>--Eric Onstad, London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
