<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570379" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Hedgehog barbecue enrages British animal activists.</title>
<headline>Hedgehog barbecue enrages British animal activists.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>British hedgehog-welfare activists vowed on Thursday to scupper plans by a self-styled &quot;king of the Gypsies&quot; to hold a traditional Gypsy barbecue where the small woodland animals would be grilled on skewers and marinated in honey.</p>
<p>Former bare-knuckle fighter Bartley Gorman is selling tickets for a Gypsy festival on his land in Uttoxeter, central England, in July. Attractions include Gypsy music around traditional campfires, and barbecued hedgehog.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to get this stopped,&quot; said Anne Jenkins of Britain's Hedgehog Preservation Society.</p>
<p>&quot;It gives people ideas and we have to make sure that this is stopped because we want to prevent this idea catching on,&quot; she told Reuters. &quot;The fad is growing for exotic food, you can go down city high streets and buy ostrich steak, alligator stew and so on. We don't need hedgehogs appearing, it's a bit sick.&quot;</p>
<p>Jenkins said the society's members would prefer to have the festival stopped by using British laws against the breeding or trapping of hedgehogs. &quot;But if we have to call our people out to picket it, we will,&quot; she added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
