<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570335" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Tanker inspections can threaten safety - Intertank.</title>
<headline>Tanker inspections can threaten safety - Intertank.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tanker inspection regimes are becoming burdensome and can threaten safety rather enhance it, a senior shipping official said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The inspection regime on the world's tanker fleet is putting huge pressures on the ships' personnel,&quot; said Captain Graham Cowling, speaking on behalf of the independent tanker organisation Intertanko.</p>
<p>&quot;The inspector-initiated accident where ships' staff are so busy attending to the requirement of the inspector that the safety of the tanker operation is overlooked is a real possibility,&quot; Cowling told an industry conference.</p>
<p>&quot;Tankers operate in one of the most heavily regulated and inspected industries in the world,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Cowling, fleet manager of MOL Tankship Management Ltd, said that &quot;it is not uncommon for a vessel to be inspected by a flag state, port state control, oil major vetting and terminal inspector, all during one call.</p>
<p>&quot;If the vessel's port stay is 24 hours and each inspection lasts for a minimum of six hours, this amounts to 24 hours of inspections during a 24-hour call,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We (Intertanko) feel that it should not be necessary for four different authorities to inspect a tanker during an operational period when the masters, officers and crew need to be alert, fully committed to their duties and properly rested beforehand,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Cowling suggested it may be possible to inspect a tanker during a short sea voyage or before or after the critical loading or discharging operation.</p>
<p>&quot;The industry needs to re-examine when and where inspections can be safely carried out,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He added that only five percent of all oil pollution into the sea was from tankers, and that in the last 20 years the amount of pollution from tanker operations had fallen by 85 percent and the amount from tanker accidents had declined by 50 percent.</p>
<p>Cowling also said navigators were sometimes still relied on inaccurate charts dating back to the last century, and that at some U.S. ports tankers were expected to berth at terminals made from timber and built early this century.</p>
<p>&quot;It has become increasingly difficult for these terminals to safely accommodate large tankers. And yet it is the tanker owner who must take the risk and face huge penalties if the tanker is blown off the terminal and then causes a pollution incident,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Oslo-based Intertanko represents 250 owners operating 1,740 tankers or 80 percent of the world's independent tanker fleet.</p>
<p>--Michael Rank, London newsroom +44 171 542 4088</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
