<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570384" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Sugar - Market eyes aftermath of May raws deliveries.</title>
<headline>Sugar - Market eyes aftermath of May raws deliveries.</headline>
<byline>Jeremy Smith</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>World prices for raw sugar could push higher if all the cargoes received from last week's unexpectedly large delivery against May futures can be quickly placed, sugar sources said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The physical delivery totalled a hefty 339,950 long tons, which included 260,000 of Paranagua raws from one of the largest Brazilian producers. The balance came from north Brazil and three central American nations.</p>
<p>The size of the delivery, the absence of Thailand and the presence of south Brazil as origins have all been talking points in the trade since details of the expiry first hit the market.</p>
<p>&quot;People were extremely surprised there was so much sugar available,&quot; said one trader. U.S. trade house Cargill was the receiver of all the sugar.</p>
<p>The news could spark an upturn in world prices provided all the sugar found homes, sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;Technically the market still looks weak and a turnaround will only be seen if the recent delivery of 360,000 tonnes into the May raws has a home to go to,&quot; said brokerage GNI in its Wednesday report.</p>
<p>&quot;If Cargill have got homes for all of it, I think it's reasonably friendly to the market,&quot; the trader said.</p>
<p>The Black Sea and Egyptian Mediterranean have been cited as likely destinations for the raw sugar and both featured this week in Cargill freight orders.</p>
<p>Shipbrokers have said Cargill's active sugar chartering from Brazil has caused the supply of handy-size vessels to tighten in South America as a whole.</p>
<p>The heavy delivery with its suggestions of abundant supply produced an initial slump in the New York market but prices rebounded slightly as it emerged that at least some of the sugar could be early new crop deliveries.</p>
<p>Traders said this would be early for new crop shipments from Paranagua but still feasible, provided the port was not overloaded shipping other commodities such as soybeans. Brazil is expecting a bumper crop this year.</p>
<p>London traders have cited local Brazilian sources as saying while there is plenty of new crop sugar available, some difficulties have been seen getting it to ports.</p>
<p>The appearance of new crop south Brazilian sugars against the May contract now means July will see more cargoes delivered when it expires on June 30 -- but Thais are unlikely to be seen unless futures prices are higher.</p>
<p>&quot;What it does mean is that you will see a lot of Brazils coming into the tape for July,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;You certainly won't see Thais in the tape, not at these levels...the futures price would have to go up a lot for Thais to sell into the tape.&quot;</p>
<p>London traders quoted May/July Thai raw sugar cargoes at a premium of around 60 points bid over July futures but no offers, although Asian sources have cited premiums of 65/70 points bid/offer.</p>
<p>Last week cargoes for May deliveries were quoted at 10 points over the now-expired May contract, which went off the board on April 30 at 20/30 points over July.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 8064</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
