<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570393" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's Ofwat eyes possible changes to tariff basket.</title>
<headline>UK's Ofwat eyes possible changes to tariff basket.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's water industry watchdog Ofwat suggested changes to the way charges can change year-on-year in a consultation paper published on Thursday.</p>
<p>Ofwat head Ian Byatt said that within a basket which is used to calculate tariffs, one group of customers should not be expected to subsidise others, a process known as &quot;rebalancing.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that charges should be more directly linked to costs and said the review was &quot;a key step in the next review of price limits,&quot; due by the end of the century.</p>
<p>Ofwat also suggested that large industrial users should be taken out of the basket calculation and that there should not be a change to separate price limits for water and for sewerage services.</p>
<p>Ofwat also said that the difference in costs between metered and unmetered bills &quot;should be no greater than the extra costs of providing a metered supply,&quot; which it put currently at no more than 27 stg.</p>
<p>Ofwat also suggested the possibility of introducing measures such as peak-time tariffs to ensure costs more closely matched demand.</p>
<p>Ofwat said responses to the document should be made by July 18.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I17000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
