<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570392" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Sony continues to soar in London on results.</title>
<headline>Sony continues to soar in London on results.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in Sony Corp were sharply higher in London on Thursday, after jumping in Tokyo earlier in response to record profits and robust sales, dealers here said.</p>
<p>By 0940 GMT, Sony was trading at 9,855 yen, up 135 yen, after gaining 90 yen in Tokyo to close at 9,720.</p>
<p>&quot;The figures were obviously good and we've seen some buyers around,&quot; one dealer said. &quot;But with most of Europe on holiday, the volume hasn't been massive. Most of the institutions just aren't around.&quot;</p>
<p>Although London markets are open, most other major European bourses, including those in Germany, France, and the Netherlands, are closed today in observance of the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>The Japanese electronics giant reported group net profits of 139.46 billion yen ($1.12 billion) in the year to March, up 2.6-fold from the previous year, aided by the weak yen, which fell about 15 percent against the dollar during the period.</p>
<p>The company also predicted further growth in the current year.</p>
<p>Dealers said Sony could see some selling pressure in the next few days if the shares breach the 10,000 yen level.</p>
<p>&quot;We think the shares will go through 10,000 but after that a few sellers should emerge,&quot; another dealer said. &quot;The market may take the view that most of the good news is out and that it is time to take profits at that point.&quot;</p>
<p>Sony shares have risen by over 3,000 yen or nearly 46 percent over the past 12 months, outperforming the Nikkei 225 index by about 54 percent, according to data from Reuters Securities 3000.</p>
<p>-- Dale Faulken, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34540">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
