<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570300" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Smet buys Perishables Transport from Sommer Holdin.</title>
<headline>Smet buys Perishables Transport from Sommer Holdin.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Perishables Transport Company(PTC) has been bought from Sommer Holdings by German industrialist Franz Smet, the latter said in a statement.</p>
<p>The transaction covers PTC's airfreight and roadfreight facilities, staff and business, while Sommer Holdings will absorb PTC's smaller ocean operation into its WTA general freight forwarding company, the statement added.</p>
<p>The value of the transaction was not disclosed.</p>
<p>PTC employs 60 staff at its Heathrow and Gatwick centres. The Heathrow centre compromises a 24,000 sq ft facility including rapid blast chillers and storage for 300 pallets in nine temperature zones.</p>
<p>It said PTC offers a full range of perishables transport services including customs clearance, import breakbulk, storage and chilled distribution utilising a large, modern fleet of refrigerated air-ride vehicles. It operates regular inbound refrigerated road services from Europe, and also provides quality control monitoring of inbound produce.</p>
<p>Smet said:&quot;There is an investment programme already in place which will see the installation of state-of the-art rapid blast chillers within weeks. This programme will not only be maintained. but stepped up. We have bought PTC to develop it.&quot;</p>
<p>In 1994, Smet bought another perishables traffic specialist, Unifresh. The statement said it is planned to exploit synergies between the two companies, but there is no immediate plan to amalgamate their operations. - Reuters Air Cargo Newsroom Tel+44 171 542 7706 Fax:5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
