<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570310" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - Buoyant UK retail sales demand govt action.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Buoyant UK retail sales demand govt action.</headline>
<byline>Mike Peacock</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's high streets continue to enjoy near-boom conditions, suggesting Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown has some way to go in terms of taking the heat out of the economy, a survey out on Thursday showed.</p>
<p>Britain's top employers group, the Confederation of British Industry, said retail sales grew at their fastest rate in five months in April.</p>
<p>It surveyed 15,000 retailers and found 59 percent said sales were higher than the same time last year. Only 17 percent said sales were down. What is more, the same balance of retailers forecast another jump in sales in May.</p>
<p>&quot;The survey shows an encouraging growth in all sectors signalling that consumer confidence is now improving fortunes right across the retail trade,&quot; said Alastair Eperon, chairman of the CBI's distributive trades survey panel.</p>
<p>The problem for Britain's new economic policymakers is that the experience on the high street stands in marked contrast to that of Britain's manufacturers.</p>
<p>Official figures out on Wednesday, showed manufacturing output dropped by 0.1 percent in March and is only 1.4 percent up on the same time last year. Consumer spending, meanwhile is growing freely, at about four percent year-on-year.</p>
<p>That all adds up to a highly skewed economic recovery.</p>
<p>Chancellor Brown wasted no time tightening policy this week, raising interest rates by a quarter-point to 6.25 percent after only five days in office.</p>
<p>But that might not be the right policy prescription. Stephen Hannah, head of research at IBJ International, said further interest rate rises would probably only serve to propel the superstrong pound still higher.</p>
<p>That would raise manufacturers' export prices further but cut the prices of imported goods, encouraging Britain's spendthrift to consumers to part with even more of their hard-earned cash.</p>
<p>What is needed is tax rises, economists say, and that leaves all eyes on Brown's first budget, due within two months.</p>
<p>&quot;If the CBI survey proves to be accurate, the annual growth rate of retail spending will have remained above four percent for the fourth consecutive month in April,&quot; said Darshini David, UK economist at HSBC Markets.</p>
<p>But with manufacturers feeling the pinch from the pound's stellar, 19 percent rally over the last nine months, &quot;the answer lies in a fiscal rather than monetary tightening,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Brown has pledged one tax rise and one cut in his budget -- the windfall tax on privatised utilities and a cut in VAT on heating fuel to five percent. But economists expect much more.</p>
<p>Despite promising to leave income tax rates unchanged, Brown could tighten the personal allowances on which no income tax is paid. He could also cut, or abolish, tax relief on home loan payments, Hannah said.</p>
<p>If retailers are enjoying a mini-boom, it is nothing compared to the explosion in British house prices.</p>
<p>Jeremy Hawkins, senior economic adviser at BankAmerica, said the CBI survey has a good track record in curtainraising the official sales figures. They are not due for two weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;It suggests demand is picking up,&quot; he said, adding that a wave of IRA bomb threats during the election campaign may have kept some consumers away from the high street. &quot;The risk is underlying demand is even stronger than reported.&quot;</p>
<p>The CBI said furniture and carpet retailers, booksellers and stationers, hardware, china and DIY stores, grocers and clothing shops reported the greatest growth in sales -- precisely the areas that benefit most when consumer sentiment improves.</p>
<p>&quot;The gains in these areas may partly reflect spending associated with the gains in housing turnover,&quot; said Michael Saunders, UK economist at Salomon Brothers. &quot;It may also reflect the use of money from the Alliance and Leicester windfall.&quot;</p>
<p>If consumer spending was not already buoyant enough, two weeks ago the Alliance &amp; Leicester paid out shares worth about 2.5 billion pounds ($4 billion) as it converted itself into a bank.</p>
<p>With a whole host of building societies set to follow suit, a grand total of 22 billion pounds will be handed out to millions of consumers over the summer.</p>
<p>($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
