<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570307" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Dutch PM to talk Europe with Britain's Blair.</title>
<headline>Dutch PM to talk Europe with Britain's Blair.</headline>
<byline>David Ljunggren</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dutch Prime Minister Wim Kok will be hoping the new British government's honeymoon with the European Union is still thriving when he arrives on Friday for talks on a crucial EU summit next month.</p>
<p>Kok and Prime Minister Tony Blair will focus on the mid-June meeting of the Inter-Governmental Committee (IGC), where the 15 EU leaders will vote on a treaty on further European integration.</p>
<p>The Netherlands, which holds the revolving EU presidency until the end of June, has taken a cautiously optimistic line on the new British government which is trying hard to be seen as more cooperative than the defeated Conservatives.</p>
<p>Dutch Foreign Minister Hans van Mierlo adopted an optimistic tone, saying Britain's European partners hoped to benefit from the feeling that new roads were opening up.</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps one of these roads leads a bit more directly to Europe,&quot; he said, adding that he was not expecting any quick or radical changes.</p>
<p>Although Britain has made clear the days of antagonism are over, the truth remains that the ruling Labour Party's position on a number of crucial issues hardly differs from those adopted by the Conservatives, who were soundly defeated in the polls a week ago after 18 years of unbroken rule.</p>
<p>Labour is adopting a wait-and-see policy on whether to sign up to a single European currency and is pressing for an end to a damaging EU ban on British beef exports imposed last year amid a scare over mad cow disease.</p>
<p>The Conservatives had threatened to torpedo the IGC summit unless the EU agreed to change its fisheries policy but Labour has ruled out any suggestion of sabotage.</p>
<p>This new-style approach to European affairs was underlined when Foreign Secretary Robin Cook paid a flying visit to Paris and Bonn on Wednesday to say Britain wanted to be at the heaart of Europe.</p>
<p>The Bonn-based General Anzeiger greeted the trip but said there was no sign Blair would drop his opposition to majority decision-making and give up the principle of unanimity on key issues such as foreign and justice policy.</p>
<p>&quot;It is much too early to talk about a new European spring,&quot; the paper concluded.</p>
<p>Kok and Blair are both reformers who moved their parties toward the centre of the political spectrum by rejecting socialist dogma.</p>
<p>But it remains to be seen whether the new British premier shares his Dutch counterpart's enthusiasm for European integration.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
