<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570339" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Storehouse shares stand at 2-1/2 year low.</title>
<headline>Storehouse shares stand at 2-1/2 year low.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in British clothing and childrens wear retailer Storehouse Plc sank to their lowest for 2-1/2 years on Thursday, amid market speculation that the group may have been trading poorly since Christmas.</p>
<p>Profit forecasts for Storehouse, owner of Bhs clothing and houseware chain and Mothercare, have been downgraded in the past couple of months to around 118 million stg for the current year. But analysts said the share price drop could be pointing to a profit shortfall.</p>
<p>The shares, which were down 2.5 pence at 207 by 1205 GMT, have underperformed the FT-All Share by 35 percent over the past six months, according to data from Reuters Securities 3000.</p>
<p>&quot;There are rumours in the market they have been trading very poorly, but no one knows why,&quot; said one retail analyst.</p>
<p>The company, which is in &quot;closed season&quot; ahead of annual results on May 22, was not immediately available comment.</p>
<p>The childrens wear market is known to be tough, which could be hitting Mothercare, but Bhs traded well over Christmas, analysts said.</p>
<p>In January, Storehouse reported a nine percent sales increase in the six weeks to December 24, although it said Mothercare was disappointing.</p>
<p>The group has staged a strong recovery from troubles caused by overexpansion in the 1980s, slimming down to its two main brands from an empire, which included Habitat, Blazer and Richards. It also has a franchise business, which is expanding rapidly overseas.</p>
<p>Last year, it made profits before tax and exceptional charges of 108.7 million stg.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Storehouse said it had promoted Stephen Tague to managing director of its Bhs chain.</p>
<p>Tague, who joined Bhs as stores operations director in 1994, will be responsible for Bhs's operations and report to Storehouse chief executive Keith Edelman.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I6560002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
