<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570397" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Bruton appeals to IRA for full-hearted ceasefire.</title>
<headline>Bruton appeals to IRA for full-hearted ceasefire.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irish Prime Minister John Bruton said on Thursday the IRA's political wing should be admitted to all-party talks on the future of Northern Ireland next month if the guerrilla group announced an immediate, genuine ceasefire.</p>
<p>Bruton was speaking ahead of talks in London later in the day with Tony Blair, which will be the new British prime minister's first meeting with a fellow head of government.</p>
<p>He told BBC radio the new Blair government, with a 179-seat majority in parliament and five years of government in front of it, represented &quot;a great opportunity&quot; to move things forward in Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>Bruton said now was the time for an Irish Republican Army (IRA) ceasefire &quot;clearly accompanied by a political change of heart and deeds matching that political change of heart&quot;.</p>
<p>It should be one &quot;where people looking into their eyes, so to speak, can see that in their hearts this time they mean it.&quot;</p>
<p>In that case, Bruton said, there was no reason why Sinn Fein, the ira's political arm which won two seats in Britain's May 1 election, should not join all-party talks on the future of the province quickly.</p>
<p>&quot;If there was a ceasefire now and if it was one that was really full-hearted and you could see that if was full-hearted ...I see no reason why they should not be in the talks when the talks resume (on June 3),&quot; Bruton said.</p>
<p>The talks, chaired by former U.S. senator George Mitchell, began last June but had made little progress by the time they were temporarily halted ahead of the British election.</p>
<p>The outgoing British Conservative government always insisted the IRA should begin to dismantle their huge stocks of weapons and explosives before being admitted to the all-party talks.</p>
<p>But no such insistence appeared in Blair's Labour Party election manifesto, which committed his government to reconciliation of republican aspirations for a united Ireland and loyalist insistence that Northern Ireland remain British.</p>
<p>The IRA called a ceasefire in its 25-year war to oust Britain from Northern Ireland in September 1994, but continued to prepare for further violence.</p>
<p>The ceasefire ended in February last year with a bomb blast in the Docklands area of east London which killed two people.</p>
<p>During the run-up to the British election, the IRA repeatedly snarled up Britain's rail and road networks by warnings -- sometimes genuine, sometimes not -- of bombs planted on busy motorways or rail junctions.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
