<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570323" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - OPEC freeze talk helps oil but trouble looms.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - OPEC freeze talk helps oil but trouble looms.</headline>
<byline>Mark Thompson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Signs that OPEC is preparing to freeze its production ceiling when it meets next month in Vienna helped steady oil prices on Thursday but traders said the cartel was storing up trouble for the future by failing to tackle widespread quota-busting.</p>
<p>World benchmark Brent crude oil for June delivery gained seven cents to $18.23 a barrel by 1223 GMT after the president of the Organisation of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC), Abdullah Salem al-Badri, said he expected the group to stick to its 25.03 million barrels per day (bpd) ceiling.</p>
<p>Al-Badri, also Libya's oil minister, said demand was not strong enough to support any increase in the 11-member cartel's output which reached 27.05 million bpd in April, according to a Oil prices, which have fallen almost $7 a barrel since the turn of the year, could suffer further if members did not respect individual allocations, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are overproducing, yes, but I have contacted everyone and I hope we will have cooperation,&quot; he told Reuters while attending a conference in Iran.</p>
<p>Senior oil traders said a rollover in June would have little market impact unless the group managed to solve the almost intractable problem of rampant overproduction which has lifted supply more than two million bpd above its self-imposed ceiling.</p>
<p>Seven OPEC ministers have scheduled talks in the central Iranian city of Isfahan later on Thursday to discuss quota-busting but concrete proposals seemed as distant as ever.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly recognising a problem exists is part of the battle but it will be interesting to see whether this meeting under the roof of a hardline state might exert a little discipline,&quot; said Peter Gignoux, head of the energy desk at brokers Smith, Barney in London.</p>
<p>Rising exports from Iraq, which returned to the world oil market in a limited capacity last December under a United Nations $2 billion oil-for-food exchange, and accelerating output growth at new foreign company operated fields would make any restraint extremely difficult, traders said.</p>
<p>And the mechanics of an agreement to narrow the gap between actual output and the ceiling would be near-impossible.</p>
<p>&quot;Proportional cuts based on current output are the only realistic possibility yet agreeing these encourages and rewards quota-breaking,&quot; said Geoff Pyne, oil analyst at UBS Global Research.</p>
<p>&quot;The second problem is that even if OPEC did manage to agree cuts, this would stimulate non-OPEC supply, further reducing demand for OPEC oil.&quot;</p>
<p>Without OPEC action, analysts predict prices will resume this year's downtrend towards the end of June, undermined by higher crude production, a seasonal slowdown in demand and a surge in stocks, currently rising by as much as two million bpd.</p>
<p>And with the U.N. widely expected to renew the Iraqi sales agreement for another six months when it expires on June 7, oil markets can look forward to even higher volumes from Baghdad as the value of its barrels fall.</p>
<p>Any signs the U.N. may be able to overcome United States opposition to Iraq's request for an increase in the $2 billion cash ceiling could provoke a price slide much sooner.</p>
<p>&quot;This battle will heat up during May and might provoke a few jitters in the market, especially if the pro-Iraqi coalition including France, China and Russia appears to succeed,&quot; said Washington-based consultants Petroleum Finance Co.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="OPEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
