<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570308" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: LIFFE/CBOT link seen boosting US interest in Bunds.</title>
<headline>LIFFE/CBOT link seen boosting US interest in Bunds.</headline>
<byline>Lisa Wilson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Traders in London are cautiously optimistic that a new link between the world's two busiest derivatives exchanges, due to start on Friday, will improve U.S. investor interest in German Bunds.</p>
<p>However, they said liquidity must rise quickly in order to fan the sparks of initial interest.</p>
<p>Starting Friday, the London International Financial Futures and Options Exchange (LIFFE) and the Chicago Board of Trade (CBOT) are putting their leading contracts -- the Bund and the T-bond futures -- into a linkup which will allow open outcry trading of both contracts on both exchanges.</p>
<p>&quot;It could bring new people into the market, and maybe more U.S. locals who don't really like the existing electronic trading,&quot; said a trader at a European bank. &quot;People will dip their toes in the water, but they'll want to see good liquidity and good size soon.&quot;</p>
<p>To help nurture the project, a dozen traders from LIFFE will take up positions in the CBOT's Bund pit, where they will provide liquidity and expertise, according to LIFFE's chairman Jack Wigglesworth when he was in Chicago last week.</p>
<p>Traders said one of the attractions of open-outcry versus domestic-based electronic systems, is that investors will be able to see the flows in and out of the markets.</p>
<p>&quot;That's quite important, when you're trying to encourage new business,&quot; said a trader at a U.S. bank on the LIFFE floor.</p>
<p>Traders said U.S. investors are showing heightened interest in Bunds, as a means of gaining a foothold in the new euro-denominated market once European Economic Union (EMU) takes place in 1999. The Bund, as the benchmark European bond contract, has a strong chance of being the basis of the new euro bond.</p>
<p>The link has been a long time in the making -- nearly a year behind schedule -- after an agreement to form an alliance with the CBOT was reached in December 1995. Technical and operational problems, particularly due to clearing, have delayed it.</p>
<p>Even the final week towards the launch had its problems. There was a last minute panic on Tuesday as the U.S. regulatory body, the Commodity Futures Trading Commission (CFTC) had failed to grant approval with only days to go before the start.</p>
<p>CBOT president Thomas Donovan wrote an acerbic letter to the CFTC, before approval was received later that evening.</p>
<p>&quot;The withholding of CFTC approval until this unacceptably late date is another vivid illustration of the competitive disability the agency has imposed on U.S. exchanges,&quot; said Donovan in his letter.</p>
<p>From a historical point of view, LIFFE's last foray into T-bonds does not, on the face of it, bode well for the new link. LIFFE's own T-bond futures and options contracts were suspended in 1993 after volume had slowed to a trickle.</p>
<p>Traders said since then interest in U.S. products has strengthened and now contracts traded here will be fully fungible with those in the U.S.</p>
<p>&quot;People trading through LIFFE will get more out of this than the U.S. guys,&quot; said a broker at a major British brokerage. &quot;A lot of news breaks overnight in Europe, so by the time the U.S. starts to trade the Bunds, the major moves of the day will already have been made.&quot;</p>
<p>Open outcry hours for the Bund futures and options on the CBOT are 1620 London local time to 2000 London local time (1520-1900 GMT on Friday). LIFFE products will also trade during the CBOT's evening pit session between 0020 London local time and 0305 London local time.</p>
<p>The CBOT's T-bond products will trade via open outcry on LIFFE between the hours of 0730 and 1300 London local time (0630-1200 GMT).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
