<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570387" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK pension group warns against corporate tax rise.</title>
<headline>UK pension group warns against corporate tax rise.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The National Association of Pension Funds (NAPF) on Thursday warned Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown against cutting into tax advantages granted to pension funds.</p>
<p>Speaking at the association's annual conference at Harrogate, NAPF director general Ann Robinson expressed &quot;deep concern&quot; at the spectre of the abolition of Advanced Corporation Tax (ACT), a tax break enjoyed by pension funds and other tax-exempt dividend recipients.</p>
<p>&quot;This would be ill-advised - a serious mistake,&quot; Robinson said.</p>
<p>The NAPF is worried that Labour pledges not to raise individual income tax would leave it little choice but to look to corporations to fill the gap.</p>
<p>Pension funds are currently given a 20 percent tax credit on dividends, a policy that the NAPF supports on the grounds that tax is eventually paid on pension income received by individuals.</p>
<p>&quot;Imposing a tax on dividends to pension funds has the effect of imposing double taxation on individuals&quot; Robinson said.</p>
<p>ACT is levied from a company's gross profits at the same time as dividends are paid to shareholders.</p>
<p>It can be offset against a company's corporation tax liability, which means that it does not increase a company's overall tax burden.</p>
<p>Tax-exempt organisations, such as pension funds, benefit from a higher rate of ACT because they can claim more cash back from the government, so they would bear the financial brunt of any government plan to drop the rate.</p>
<p>If ACT was abolished, the NAPF believes that profitable corporations would have to divert funds to their own pension funds to make up any shortfall - thus reducing corporation tax revenue to the government.</p>
<p>Also, reductions in pension fund revenues among local authorities and other public service sector pension funds could result in &quot;higher taxes or reduced services to the public&quot;, Robinson said.</p>
<p>The NAPF believes that a cut in ACT would also make more difficult the government's plans for so-called stakeholder pensions.</p>
<p>&quot;You simply won't get stakeholder pensions if you tax, tax, tax,&quot; Robinson said.</p>
<p>-- James Saft, London Newsroom +171 542 2734</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150214">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
