<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570363" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - T-bonds pin hopes on 109-00 support.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - T-bonds pin hopes on 109-00 support.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>June T-bond futures continued to drift lower in automated trade but would find initial support nearby at 109-00,03 on Thursday, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a reasonable support area between 109-19 and 109-24 which should have helped yesterday but didn't and that suggests to me it has a bit more downward drift on it,&quot; Marc Ostwald, technical strategist at London Bond Broking, said.</p>
<p>He pegged the next support level at an area of congestion around 109-00,03 and said this was likely to be tested.</p>
<p>Daily charts show the market hit a 109-00 high on April 29 before shooting higher</p>
<p>T-bonds were quoted at 109-03 at 1049 GMT, down 7/32.</p>
<p>Ostwald said if the market broke 109-00,03 it would look for support at an old chart high from March 27 at 108-23, and to 108-18, lows on March 24 and 25.</p>
<p>But he expected these levels to contain it in the near term.</p>
<p>&quot;I think people are basically on hold because they know they (T-bonds) might get quite a lot lower if the Fed raises rates next time round,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said if the market were to reverse direction and head higher it would aim for 110-03, the high of Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment this market is looking for buyers and it's not finding them, so we're going to push down through the various levels until we find some buyers coming in,&quot; Ostwald said.</p>
<p>Francoise Skelley, head of global trading technical analysis at Credit Suisse First Boston in London said she saw the recent upmove as corrective. &quot;For me critical medium-term resistance is in the 110-11 to 111-11 band,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>She noted the recent high was 110-10. &quot;Where bonds have stopped is where they should have stopped if it's to be a continuation of the downmove.&quot;</p>
<p>She saw potential for an acceleration to the downside to 108-16,12.</p>
<p>But she also said the market could get a short-term bounce, in which case 109-21,24 would cap it.  </p>
<p>At the short end, September Eurodollars were quoted at 93.820, down 0.020 from Wednesday's settlement in Chicago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
