<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570312" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: More convergence seen for British gilts.</title>
<headline>More convergence seen for British gilts.</headline>
<byline>Deepthi Wickremasinghe</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Convergence between gilts and German bunds is set to continue, with any sign of a more pro-European stance from the new British government likely to encourage further tightening of differentials (spreads), analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The overnight slide in sterling was likely to help gilts pull the spread over bunds towards 100 basis points, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is certainly more scope for outperformance in the gilt market and sterling weakness overnight would support that argument,&quot; said Phyllis Reed, European bond strategist at BZW in London.</p>
<p>At around 1200 gmt, the 10-year gilt/bund yield spread was at 144 basis points, having narrowed from 181 when Labour's Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown announced measures to give the Bank of England independence in monetary policy on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The currency fell by four pfennigs to the pound following a Bridge News report on comments from an unnamed Labour Party source that sterling should rejoin Europe's exchange rate mechanism (ERM) in 2001 at a rate of 2.50 marks. Sterling is currently trading at 2.7796 marks.</p>
<p>Reed said the majority of the sterling weakness had been linked to the comments on the ERM and this, coupled with a negative correlation between sterling and gilts in the past, would support further gilt/bund convergence.</p>
<p>Joanne Collins, senior market strategist at Nomura International also said there was further spread narrowing on the way under a more pro-European scenario.</p>
<p>&quot;Since gilts have been benefiting from being seen as an EMU (Economic and Monetary Union) safehaven in the past, it is a bit of a win/win situation,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Collins set an initial convergence target of 125 basis points with further moves towards ERM membership taking the spread through there to 100.</p>
<p>&quot;Once we get that full commitment, and if it becomes clear that we will be accepted, then 100 may not be the limit by any means,&quot; she said, citing Danish bonds as an example, where the spread over bunds is currently 60 basis points.</p>
<p>Craig Shute, fixed income analyst at Bear Stearns in London, said in the six days it has held office the newly elected British government seemed to be pursuing quite pro-European policies and recommended investors buy on weakness in the gilt market.</p>
<p>&quot;If you look at how Spain and Italy have performed since the middle of last year, there has been phenomenal convergence in stark contrast to gilts,&quot; he said. &quot;If it now looks like the UK is adopting a more friendly approach to Europe then the gilt market probably has some catching up to do relative to Spain and Italy and the core European markets.&quot;</p>
<p>Reed said while the British government might not be immediately ready to take sterling back into the ERM, a move in that direction would benefit gilts.</p>
<p>&quot;Even a small shift towards a pro-European stance will help gilts and if you combine this talk about the ERM with the move towards granting the Bank of England more independence, it does look like they are moving closer to Europe,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Analysts recommend investors look at the five-year area of the gilt curve.</p>
<p>&quot;The flattening between fives and 10s has been too dramatic,&quot; said Reed.</p>
<p>Collins agreed five-year gilts offered good value in gilts relative to both the long and short ends of the curve.</p>
<p>&quot;At the short end there is too much rate tightening priced in and that will have to unwind at some point which will also benefit the five-year sector by comparison,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
