<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570346" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Scientists probe HRT in biggest study of women.</title>
<headline>Scientists probe HRT in biggest study of women.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>British cancer researchers said on Thursday they were looking into the effects of hormone replacement therapy (HRT) in the biggest study of women's health ever undertaken.</p>
<p>They said their survey of one million women would answer questions about whether HRT caused breast cancer, protected against heart disease and whether there was any difference between HRT drugs.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the main concerns about HRT has been whether it has an effect on breast cancer,&quot; Dr Valerie Beral, head of the Imperial Cancer Research Fund's cancer epidemiology unit, told a news conference.</p>
<p>There is clear evidence that HRT helps prevents osteoporosis, the weakening of the bones that often comes with age. There is also clear evidence that it can add to an increase in blood clots and cancer of the uterus.</p>
<p>But HRT greatly diminishes some of the worst symptoms of the menopause such as mood swings, hot flushes and, more serious, the increasing tendency for women to show &quot;male&quot; patterns of sickness such as higher rates of heart disease.</p>
<p>Beral said HRT did not have major effects on cancer and heart disease. &quot;We do know there's absolutely nothing drastic going on one way or another,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The trouble is that HRT can make the breasts of menopausal women look &quot;younger&quot;. After menopause breasts are filled with fat that is easy to see through, but before, and with HRT, glands are active and often look opaque to mammograms.</p>
<p>For screeners, this makes it harder to detect tumours in the breasts of women taking HRT.</p>
<p>Julietta Patnick, national coordinator of the NHS breast screening programme, said 1.5 million women aged 50 to 64 were invited each year for beast cancer screening each year in Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;They often ask us questions related to HRT and potential links to breast cancer,&quot; she said. &quot;Unfortunately, we don't know the answers to the questions they ask.&quot;</p>
<p>All these women would be given a questionnaire about HRT, with detailed questions about which type they used, if any, and other health factors such as weight, smoking and drinking.</p>
<p>Beral said some surprising findings had already emerged.</p>
<p>&quot;We found to our surprise that one in three of women being screened was taking HRT,&quot; she said, adding that HRT use had probably more than doubled since 1990 in Britain.</p>
<p>Beral estimated a study of one million women would turn up 6,000 cases of breast cancer and 6,000 heart deaths by 2001 -- enough to determine what links, if any, there were with HRT.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll certainly have enough figures to come up with fairly definitive results by 1999,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>To date the largest study has been an ongoing survey of 100,000 nurses in the United States, which covers a wide range of health issues.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
