<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570423" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: Cypriots protest against plans to scrap gay ban.</title>
<headline>Cypriots protest against plans to scrap gay ban.</headline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than a hundred bearded monks, priests and their supporters protested outside Cyprus's parliament on Thursday against plans to scrap a century-old law banning homosexuality.</p>
<p>&quot;Only an irresponsible or misinformed society would legalise an immoral act which affects the sanctity of marriage and family. It is a source of misery, guilt and infectuous diseases for those who indulge in it,&quot; said Savvas Michaelides, one of the priests who organised the protest.</p>
<p>Brandishing placards reading &quot;No to sodomy&quot; and &quot;homosexuality = misery, guilt and AIDS&quot; some 120 priests and members of the public blocked the parliament entrance in Nicosia for about an hour, vowing to return in larger numbers next week.</p>
<p>Cyprus has come under pressure from the Council of Europe to legalise homosexuality after the European Court of Justice in 1993 ruled in favour of a Cypriot campaigning to scrap the law, which dates from 1889.</p>
<p>Cypriot officials have publicly agreed with scrapping the controversial law, which criminalises homosexual activity and carries prison sentences between five and 14 years.</p>
<p>Moves to decriminalise homosexuality have been pending approval in parliament for the past two years, with all indications of a decision on it before the start of the summer recess in July.</p>
<p>But any move to change will come under strong opposition from the influential Greek Orthodox Cyprus Church. They say decriminalising homosexuality would violate traditional values.</p>
<p>Gay rights campaigners say opponents are misinformed.</p>
<p>&quot;They think we are monsters from outer space,&quot; said Alecos Modinos, the architect who took Cyprus to the European court. &quot;We are ordinary people who were not made homosexuals. We were born homosexuals.&quot;</p>
<p>The protesters remained unconvinced. &quot;God is against it. He proved it when he destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah,&quot; said Evagoras Ermogenides, 39, referring to the biblical cities referred to in the Old Testament. &quot;We must safeguard our morals.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
