<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570435" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Lebanese to bombard pope with appeals.</title>
<headline>Lebanese to bombard pope with appeals.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Tarnowski</byline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul will be bombarded by appeals, exhortations and open letters from all sides of the political spectrum when he visits Lebanon this weekend on his first trip to the Middle East.</p>
<p>Even the pro-Iranian Hizbollah (Party of God) has handed a memorandum for the pope to the Vatican embassy urging a Moslem-Christian dialogue and what it calls a more balanced Vatican attitude to the Middle East conflict.</p>
<p>Human rights groups, Christians opposed to the Syrian-backed government and the commander of a pro-Israeli militia in south Lebanon are also seeking the pope's ear.</p>
<p>Lawyers for Samir Geagea, a former Christian militia leader jailed for murder, have written an open letter telling the pope he is being persecuted because Lebanon has failed to achieve Moslem-Christian reconciliation since the 1975-90 civil war.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri, a billionaire Sunni Moslem, has called the pope's visit historic and said he is proud that Lebanon is the first country in the region to welcome him.</p>
<p>The 32-hour visit starting on Saturday includes a brief meeting with mainstream Moslem spiritual leaders but no encounters with Christian opposition politicians.</p>
<p>Hizbollah, the Shi'ite movement that runs welfare programmes in Beirut while fighting a guerrilla war to oust Israeli troops from south Lebanon, welcomed the pope and wished him a successful visit to Lebanon where Moslems hold a clear majority.</p>
<p>Hizbollah drew the pope's attention to the sufferings of the Palestinian people and Israeli efforts to Judaise Jerusalem.</p>
<p>But its spiritual leader, Sheikh Mohammed Hussein Fadlallah, was cooler towards the Vatican, saying its establishment of diplomatic ties with Israel was premature and criticising John Paul for having asked God to bless Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;I would like to hear him denounce the eviction of Palestinians from their homeland,&quot; Fadlallah told as-Safir newspaper in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;I would like him to call for a Moslem-Christian dialogue on a world scale so we can realise that from the religious, humanitarian and moral standpoint Islam and Christianity are identical,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Mainstream Moslem religious leaders have said little about the visit but a fundamentalist Sunni sheikh accused authorities in March of preparing to treat the pope like God.</p>
<p>Sheikh Saeed Shaaban threatened to swamp the pope's open-air mass on Sunday by summoning the faithful to prayer at the site.</p>
<p>He withdrew the threat after being threatened with prosecution.</p>
<p>Three human rights groups said in open letters to the pope that arbitrary detentions take place in Lebanon and detainees are illegally transferred to Syria or Israel.</p>
<p>Syria has 35,000 troops in Lebanon and Israel holds a border strip comprising about 12 percent of Lebanese territory.</p>
<p>Lebanese Christians from Australia also sent the pope a letter protesting about alleged illegal detentions and torture and demanded the withdrawal of both foreign armies from Lebanon.</p>
<p>A Christian opposition bloc including exiled ex-president Amin Gemayel and former army commander General Michel Aoun has drawn up a list of grievances centring on their demand for the withdrawal of Syrian and Israeli forces.</p>
<p>Cardinal Nasrallah Sfeir, the Maronite patriarch, is expected to give it to the pope. Newspapers said it complains of the &quot;Syrianisation&quot; of Lebanon, loss of sovereignty, human rights infringements and restriction of liberties.</p>
<p>But the toughest statement came from General Antoine Lahd, commander of the South Lebanon Army (SLA) militia that helps Israeli troops control their occupation zone in the south.</p>
<p>Lahd, a Maronite Christian and former Lebanese army brigadier, is accused of treason by Beirut but in an open letter to the pope he threw the accusation back at the government.</p>
<p>He said Lebanon was &quot;ruled by a handful of petty tyrants forced by Damascus on the people against their will. These are mere puppets in Syria's hand, but they control the country tightly and terrorise people through a series of police agencies....&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
