<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570401" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Reuters historical calendar - May 14.</title>
<headline>Reuters historical calendar - May 14.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the major events to have occurred on May 14 in history:</p>
<p>1246 - English barons under Simon de Montfort heavily defeated forces under Henry III at the battle of Lewes in the Barons' War of England.</p>
<p>1316 - Charles IV, Holy Roman Emperor, born. King of Bohemia from 1346-1378, he became Holy Roman Emperor from 1355. Known as a man of peace, he enlarged his power through diplomacy and marriage.</p>
<p>1509 - Venetians were defeated at the battle of Agnadello in Italy by the French in the War of the League of Cambrai.</p>
<p>1610 - Henry IV of France, the first Bourbon king, was assassinated by religious fanatic Francois Ravaillac while travelling through Paris.</p>
<p>1643 - Louis XIV acceded to the throne of France at the age of four years eight months on the death of his father Louis XIII. His mother, Anne of Austria, became regent. He reigned until his death in 1715.</p>
<p>1796 - Edward Jenner became the first British physician to perform a successful vaccination, innoculating an eight-year-old boy against smallpox, thus laying the foundation for modern immunology.</p>
<p>1811 - Paraguay proclaimed its independence from Spain.</p>
<p>1885 - Otto Klemperer, German musical director and conductor, born in Breslau. In his early career he championed modern works.</p>
<p>1912 - August Strindberg, influential Swedish playwright, died. Best known for his &quot;Miss Julie&quot; and &quot;The Father&quot;.</p>
<p>1921 - In the United States, Florence Allen became the first woman judge to sentence a man to death. Frank Motto was tried on a murder charge and executed on August 20.</p>
<p>1940 - Two thirds of the Dutch city of Rotterdam was destroyed by German bombing, killing almost 1,000 people and making at least 80,000 homeless.</p>
<p>1948 - The state of Israel was proclaimed at 4 p.m., eight hours before the British mandate in Palestine was to end.</p>
<p>1955 - The Warsaw Pact was signed by the Soviet Union, Albania, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, East Germany, Hungary, Poland and Romania.</p>
<p>1963 - Kuwait became the 111th member of the United Nations.</p>
<p>1965 - Queen Elizabeth unveiled a memorial to the late U.S President John F. Kennedy on a field at Runnymede, the site west of London where the Magna Carta was signed in 1215.</p>
<p>1968 - The Czechoslovak government announced widespread liberalising reforms under leader Alexander Dubcek.</p>
<p>1973 - America's Skylab I space laboratory was launched into earth orbit by the last Saturn Five booster rocket.</p>
<p>1987 - Lieutenant-Colonel Sitiveni Rabuka seized power in a bloodless military coup in Fiji.</p>
<p>1988 - Iraqi jets bombed the Seawise Giant - the world's biggest ship - and three other tankers at the Larak oil terminal in Iran on the Strait of Hormuz.</p>
<p>1989 - In Argentia's general election, Peronist leader Carlos Menem swept to power beating ruling Radical Party candidate Eduardo Angeloz.</p>
<p>1989 - Tens of thousands demonstrated for democratic reforms in Peking's Tiananmen square, on the eve of a visit to the country by Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev.</p>
<p>1991 - Jiang Qing, widow of Chinese Communist Party chairman Mao Zedong and leader of the 'Gang of Four', committed suicide.</p>
<p>1991 - In South Africa, Winnie Mandela was sentenced to six years imprisonment for complicity in the kidnapping and beating of four youths, one of whom died. She was freed pending appeal.</p>
<p>1993 - American newspaper magnate William Randolph Hearst Jr. died after a heart attack. He was 85 and editor-in-chief of Hearst Newspapers and chairman of the executive committee of the Hearst Corporation.</p>
<p>1994 - Noisy parades and celebrations enveloped the 700-strong Palestinian police force as it patrolled Jericho on the first full day of Palestinian self-rule after nearly three decades of Israeli occupation.</p>
<p>1995 - The Dalai Lama proclaimed six-year-old Gedhun Choekyi Nyima as the 11th reincarnation of the Panchen Lama, Tibet's second most senior spritual leader.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
