<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570427" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish PM says religious education rights issue.</title>
<headline>Turkish PM says religious education rights issue.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's Islamist Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan said on Thursday that denying pupils the right to attend Moslem religious schools amounted to a human rights abuse, the state-run Anatolian news agency reported.</p>
<p>&quot;Respect for human rights is the issue we will highlight most when resolving the problem of education in our country,&quot; said Erbakan, the first Islamist to lead 99 percent Moslem Turkey since it became a secular republic in 1923.</p>
<p>&quot;It is the most natural right of people to teach their religion to their children from a young age...This is a right recognised in the United Nations and European human rights declarations,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is recognised throughout the world.&quot;</p>
<p>Erbakan was speaking in opposition to a plan demanded by the powerful army that compulsory education be increased to eight years in the same school from the current five.</p>
<p>This would effectively shut down the middle section of state religious schools, which now begin to take pupils at 11.</p>
<p>Turkey's secularists, particularly the military, believe that the religious &quot;imam hatip&quot; schools are used as a breeding ground for activists in Erbakan's Welfare Party.</p>
<p>Erbakan came to power last year after narrowly coming first in general elections with only 21 percent of the vote.</p>
<p>But his coalition with a conservative party has shown cracks under fierce pressure from the secularist generals after he proposed mild Islamist reforms earlier this year.</p>
<p>The eight-year education plan was among demands set out by the military-government National Security Council (MGK) in February.</p>
<p>Erbakan, also a member of the MGK, was a signatory to the council's list of demands, but he has been criticised since for not implementing any of them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
