<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570406" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: OPEC Apr output rises to 27.05 mbpd - Reuter survey.</title>
<headline>OPEC Apr output rises to 27.05 mbpd - Reuter survey.</headline>
<byline>Mark Thompson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>OPEC output jumped again in April as Iraqi exports climbed, dealing a fresh blow to the cartel's discredited quota system and signalling the end of a recent trend towards thinner world supply in the second quarter.</p>
<p>Wellhead crude oil production from the Organisation of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) rose 200,000 barrels per day (bpd) to 27.05 million bpd in April from a revised 26.85 million in March, a survey by Reuters of OPEC officials, oil companies and analysts found.</p>
<p>Seven OPEC ministers have scheduled a meeting for Thursday in the central Iranian city of Isfahan amid growing concern that the 11-member group's official 25.03 million bpd ceiling will become increasingly irrelevant in coming months, further damaging prices and revenues.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a lot of oil in the market place both from us and from non-OPEC (producers) so some form of moderation is required,&quot; OPEC Secretary-General Rilwanu Lukman said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>World benchmark Brent crude oil has fallen nearly $7 since early January to around $18 a barrel, dashing OPEC's hopes of a repeat of last year's windfall income.</p>
<p>Iraq led the charge in April, lifting exports under the United Nations oil-for-food swap by around 150,000 bpd to 750,000 bpd as Baghdad's customers lapped up extra barrels offered at bigger discounts than in March.</p>
<p>With oil traders expecting Kirkuk Blend shipments from the Turkish port of Ceyhan to rise at least 15,000 bpd in May, Iraq looks set to leave its 1.2 million bpd quota even further behind.</p>
<p>&quot;The dip in crude supplies in the second quarter seen in the last two years is unlikely to materialize in 1997, keeping this year's supply outlook fairly robust,&quot; said Washington-based consultants Petroleum Finance Co (PFC).</p>
<p>But Iraq was only one of six members to pump more in April, with lower output restricted to OPEC's Gulf trio of lynchpin Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and the UAE, although all three remained above quota.</p>
<p>Nigerian production resumed its upward trend, hitting 2.14 million bpd in April despite communal protests which disrupted Shell's operations for a second month running.</p>
<p>Shell lost some 90,000 bpd for about five days but the fall was modest compared to March -- when 210,000 bpd was shut in for a 10-day period -- and countered by increased pumping from other joint venture operators Chevron and Mobil.</p>
<p>Iran and Indonesia also recorded increases last month, rising to 3.71 million and 1.43 million bpd respectively, the latter after March's total was depressed by an unexpected refinery closure.</p>
<p>Libyan production edged up to 1.44 million bpd, boosted by rising output at the Repsol-operated Murzuk field, which reached 50,000 bpd mid-month.</p>
<p>Monitors put the UAE down slightly in April at 2.25 million bpd, but still 100,000 bpd over quota.</p>
<p>Production dipped in Saudi Arabia and Kuwait but both countries were also still running ahead of official allocations at 8.10 million and 2.09 million bpd respectively.</p>
<p>Venezuela, which will be represented at Thursday's meeting by oil minister Erwin Arrieta, continued to shun its OPEC quota of 2.359 million bpd by pumping 3.16 million bpd in April, a shade below the March total.</p>
<p>The Reuter survey seeks a best estimate of wellhead flows in OPEC countries based on the views of officials, industry monitors and analysts inside and outside member countries.</p>
<p>OPEC quotas are based on supply to market, defined to exclude movements to, but not sales from storage.</p>
<p>Table of average of findings from the Reuter survey are as follows:</p>
<p>		  APR	MAR	FEB     3 MTH AV   QUOTA</p>
<p> Algeria	0.85     0.85     0.84     0.85	0.750</p>
<p> Indonesia    1.43     1.40     1.38     1.40	1.330</p>
<p> Iran	   3.71     3.65R    3.69     3.68	3.600</p>
<p> Iraq	   1.32     1.18     1.15     1.22	1.200</p>
<p> Kuwait	 2.09     2.10     2.09     2.09	2.000</p>
<p> Libya	  1.44     1.43     1.40     1.42	1.390</p>
<p> Nigeria	2.14     2.12     2.15     2.14	1.865</p>
<p> Qatar	  0.56     0.56     0.56     0.56	0.378</p>
<p> S.Arabia     8.10     8.12     8.05     8.09	8.000</p>
<p> UAE	    2.25     2.26     2.28     2.26	2.161</p>
<p> Venezuela    3.16     3.18     3.18     3.17	2.359</p>
<p> Total	 27.05    26.85    26.77    26.89     25.033</p>
<p>Figures, in million bpd, exclude condensate and NGLs. Quotas apply to supply, not wellhead output. Saudi and Kuwaiti data include Neutral Zone. (R) = revised.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 7930</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="OPEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
