<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570494" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Justice Dept. begins probe of CIA nominee.</title>
<headline>U.S. Justice Dept. begins probe of CIA nominee.</headline>
<byline>James Vicini</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Justice Department is in the early stages of investigating the failure of George Tenet, President Clinton's nominee to head the CIA, to disclose his part interest in stocks and property inherited from his father, Clinton administration officials said Wednesday.</p>
<p>Two Justice Department officials said the preliminary inquiry had been under way for more than a week, and the White House had been aware of the matter at the time of Tenet's nomination.</p>
<p>The officials said the inquiry could possibly lead to the appointment of an independent counsel, depending on the results. In his current job as deputy director of the CIA Tenet is covered under the independent counsel law.</p>
<p>A White House official said the matter involved telephone company stock and real estate in Athens, Greece that Tenet became joint owner of with his mother and brother after his father died.</p>
<p>The official said Tenet, who worked on the White House National Security Council staff from 1993 to 1995, had been unaware until 1994 that he was among the owners of the stock and unaware of the details of the real estate in Greece.</p>
<p>Tenet then informed a White House ethics officer and was told he had to remove himself from issues involving those matters. The official said Tenet also amended his financial disclosure forms.</p>
<p>&quot;The White House was aware of this and actually advised the Department of Justice of it at the time the president nominated Tenet,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe he is fully qualified for the job, that it will not reflect adversely on him and that he will be confirmed by the Senate,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>The official said the chairman and the vice-chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee, which must approve the nomination, had been informed, and that the committee knew about it when it approved Tenet as deputy director.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't at this point, from what we know about it, look that serious,&quot; Sen. Richard Shelby, an Alabama Republican and chairman of the panel, told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe we have a good nominee and we're waiting to go forward,&quot; Shelby said. &quot;I think it's basically an investigation of some family stocks and maybe some family property.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Mr. Tenet's indicated to us he thinks it's basically worked out,&quot; the senator said.</p>
<p>The committee's senior Democrat, Sen. Bob Kerrey of Nebraska, said: &quot;It does not seem that serious to me (and) doesn't appear to endanger the nomination.&quot;</p>
<p>A CIA spokeswoman had no comment.</p>
<p>Clinton tapped Tenet for the chief spymaster job after a bruising fight with Senate Republicans over the abortive nomination of Anthony Lake, the president's first-term national security adviser.</p>
<p>Lake had his own problems with the Justice Department. In February he agreed to pay $5,000 to settle allegations he violated conflict-of-interest laws by failing to sell four energy stocks after joining the White House in 1993.</p>
<p>Tenet is a former staff director of the Intelligence Committee who later became senior intelligence adviser on the National Security Council staff under Lake. His first day of confirmation hearings Tuesday was marked by no problems.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
