<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570424" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: U.S.-Turkish-Israeli axis worries Lebanon.</title>
<headline>U.S.-Turkish-Israeli axis worries Lebanon.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri, in an apparent reference to a proposal for U.S.-Turkish-Israeli wargames, said on Thursday no military manoeuvres would stop Lebanon seeking the return of its territory occupied by Israel.</p>
<p>&quot;We are acquainted with what we hear about military or political manoeuvres. We will continue to insist on our right to have our land back,&quot; Hariri said in a speech at the opening of the pan-Arab Golf tournament in Beirut.</p>
<p>&quot;I want the Lebanese people not to be taken by these political games nor by the military manoeuvres, these things may try to play with our nerves but we will stand firm in our positions,&quot; Hariri said.</p>
<p>He appeared to be referring to talks this week between Turkish Deputy Chief of Staff General Cevik Bir and Israeli Defence Minister Yitzhak Mordechai. Bir discussed joint naval exercises with Israel and the United States.</p>
<p>Lebanese Foreign Minister Faris Bouez also said in a statement published on Thursday that Lebanon was deeply concerned with the U.S.-Turkish-Israeli alliance.</p>
<p>&quot;We can not separate this from what is being said about a political-military encirclement or a political-military alliance aimed at encircling the positions of some Arabic countries,&quot; the leftist As-Safir newspaper quoted Bouez as saying.</p>
<p>Lebanon, which is formally at war with Israel, is closely allied with Syria which has 35,000 troops on its territory. The two countries' peace negotiations with Israel have been stalled since last year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
