<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570475" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - NYMEX crude faces resistance, may slide.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - NYMEX crude faces resistance, may slide.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>---------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>NEARBY MONTH CLOSE * SUPPORT * RESIST  * RSI-14 * MA-10 * MA-20</p>
<p> NYMEX CRUDE  19.62 * 19.44   * 20.00   *   44   * 19.90 * 19.81</p>
<p> HEATING OIL  53.08 * 52.70   * 54.30   *   42   * 55.23 * 54.93</p>
<p> GASOLINE     60.92 * 60.05   * 61.65   *   44   * 61.99 * 61.73</p>
<p>----------------- VIEWS FROM THE MARKET - May 8 ---------------</p>
<p>+ NYMEX crude oil futures face strong resistance and this is expected to keep a lid on prices.</p>
<p>+ First resistance is expected around $19.95/$20.00 then $20.20, while support is expected to weigh in first at $19.44 then $19.08.  </p>
<p>NYMEX crude oil futures face strong obstacles in any attempt to stage further gains and traders and chartists said these hurdles have lent the market a bearish tone.</p>
<p>June crude closed four cents a barrel down on Wednesday at $19.62 while June gasoline gained 0.61 cent a gallon to end at 60.92. June heating oil lost 0.45 cent to 53.08.</p>
<p>Scott Siller at MCM in New York saw strong hurdles for the market to overcome before moving higher and said this currently made him pessimistic.</p>
<p>&quot;I am bearish the market overall,&quot; he said, adding that his first selling level lay at $19.95.</p>
<p>This lies just above the tops of the highs formed by the consolidative pattern of the past four trading days.</p>
<p>A bearish rising wedge pattern which had formed from the beginning of last month had been decisively broken to the downside, he said, and added that prices would have to break once again above the rising trendline at the bottom of that wedge before looking optimistic again.</p>
<p>This trendline currently crosses the price action at $20.20, which also corresponds to his 50-day moving average, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;If we get above $19.95 we will try for $20.20,&quot; he said. &quot;We may see a bounce to that area and then sell off from there. It would take a move above $20.20 to get more optimistic.&quot;</p>
<p>The next target above that level lay at $20.75, he said. This corresponds to a falling trendline dating from the high of January 9.</p>
<p>On the downside, he said, $19.08 was an important number to watch.</p>
<p>A break through this level, reached on April 4 and almost touched again on April 10 and 17, would usher in new eight-month lows.</p>
<p>Cliff Green at Trend Analysis in the U.K. saw support at $19.40. This is slightly below the $19.44 short-term low point reached last Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Expect immediate recovery attempts to be restricted by resistance waiting at $20.00/$20.10 then $20.50/$20.55 with fresh tests of $19.40 (support) and possibly $19.05/$19.10 likely in the coming days, which if decisively breached could extend falls closer to the $18.60 region,&quot; he said in a weekly report released late on Wednesday.</p>
<p>He saw resistance for June gasoline at 62.00 cents a gallon then 63.20/63.50. &quot;Expect local supports at 59.30/59.50 to come under renewed attack in the shorter term which if now breached would clearly damage the positive tone.</p>
<p>-- Nicholas Shaxson, London newsroom +44 171 542 8167</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
