<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570496" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Oklahoma executes 22-year-old convicted murderer.</title>
<headline>Oklahoma executes 22-year-old convicted murderer.</headline>
<dateline>MCALESTER, Okla. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 22-year-old convicted murderer was executed by lethal injection in Oklahoma on Thursday, the youngest person put to death since capital punishment resumed in the United States in 1976, officials said.</p>
<p>Scott Carpenter had pleaded no contest to first-degree murder in the February 1994 stabbing death of bait shop owner A.J. Kelley near Lake Eufaula, Oklahoma.</p>
<p>He waived his appeals and was executed shortly after midnight, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;He had no last words,&quot; prison spokeswoman Lee Mann said.</p>
<p>The execution was witnessed by four members of the victim's family, including his granddaughter and daughter-in-law, hours after state legislators amended a law to allow extended family of a victim to witness an execution.</p>
<p>Kelley, 56, was stabbed from behind in the neck at the Duchess Creek Bait and Grocery Store during an apparent robbery, prosecutors said.</p>
<p>Carpenter had pumped $37 worth of gas into a pick-up truck and took a sandwich, soda, cigarettes and chewing tobacco to the cash register. He then lured Kelley into the bait shop's minnow room and stabbed him. Kelly was found by two men, one a retired Oklahoma City detective, who walked in on the crime.</p>
<p>The men provided police with information, including a license plate number, used to capture Carpenter about an hour later, prosecutors said.</p>
<p>Even though Carpenter waived his appeals, death penalty opponents said prosecutors should have insisted on a review of the case by a higher court to ensure the death penalty was an appropriate sentence.</p>
<p>&quot;It seems the best way to correct for mistakes would be to let the appeals process run,&quot; Richard Dieter, executive director of the Death Penalty Information Centre said. &quot;I think the state has an interest to protect against mistakes.&quot;</p>
<p>The execution was the first this year and the ninth since capital punishment resumed in 1990 in Oklahoma, where 136 men and four women remained on death row, Mann said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MCALESTER, Okla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
