<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570491" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Phone calls the main topic at Oklahoma bomb trial.</title>
<headline>Phone calls the main topic at Oklahoma bomb trial.</headline>
<byline>Judith Crosson</byline>
<dateline>DENVER 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prosecutors on Wednesday laid the groundwork to prove their claim that Timothy McVeigh used a telephone calling card under a false name to shop for materials to make the bomb that destroyed the Oklahoma City federal building.</p>
<p>The elaborate presentation included questioning 27 telephone company executives and an FBI computer specialist who assembled the phone records and said that the calls were made to chemical companies and firms that sell racing fuel or plastic barrels.</p>
<p>CBS News reported that prosecutors had found McVeigh's prints and handwriting on documents associated with the calling card. Prosecution sources said those documents have not yet been introduced into evidence, but were expected to be made public soon.</p>
<p>One call on the telephone card was also made to the company that rented McVeigh the truck that the government claims contained the bomb. The last call on the card was made two days before the bombing.</p>
<p>Government prosecutors are trying to prove that McVeigh and accused co-conspirator Terry Nichols used the pre-paid telephone card issued in the name of &quot;Daryl Bridges&quot; to carry out some elements of the plan, from shopping for components to make the bomb to renting a truck to house it. Nichols will be tried separately at a later date.</p>
<p>The defence objected throughout the phone company executives' testimony, arguing that the records were not accurate and that some were no longer available.</p>
<p>Federal Judge Richard Matsch has admitted the phone records based on the condition that prosecutors can establish their relevance. The judge also cautioned the jury about what he called the limitations of the phone records, noting they could be inaccurate. &quot;They may or may not be correct,&quot; the judge told the jurors.</p>
<p>The pre-paid telephone calling card was found during a search of Nichols' home in Herington, Kansas, just days after the bombing.</p>
<p>The bomb blew up in front of the Alfred P. Murrah building in Oklahoma City on April 19, 1995, killing 168 people.</p>
<p>The phone company records sharply contrasted with the drama of Tuesday's session when McVeigh's sister Jennifer testified that her brother wrote her in the weeks before the bombing that &quot;something big is going to happen&quot;. She said she burned the letter on his instructions.</p>
<p>After the phone company employees finished, another bombing victim took the stand, shifting the focus back to the human element. Capt. Lawrence Martin who worked in the Army recruiting office in the Murrah building told of seven colleagues who died in the blast and described how a piece of glass became lodged in his face. He received a medical discharge from the Army.</p>
<p>McVeigh has pleaded not guilty, and if convicted faces the death penalty.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DENVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
