<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570487" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Philippine president urges U.S. to extradite woman.</title>
<headline>Philippine president urges U.S. to extradite woman.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippine President Fidel Ramos called on Washington on Wednesday to live up to a new extradition treaty and hand over a woman wanted in a multimillion dollar securities fraud in the Philippines.</p>
<p>Ramos, who was heading a trade delegation to California, also urged the United States to fulfil its promises to Filipinos who fought in the U.S. armed forces during the Second World War.</p>
<p>Asked at a news conference about the recently concluded U.S.-Philippine extradition treaty, Ramos said the agreement had been ratified by the Philippine legislature.</p>
<p>&quot;In fact, the agreement is being tested now. We are asking for the extradition of a woman involved in a big bank fraud,&quot; he said. Aides identified the woman as Marilyn Nite.</p>
<p>&quot;We have begun to implement it on our side; the United States must now do its part,&quot; said Ramos.</p>
<p>He acknowledged the situation had been complicated somewhat by the fact that Nite had married an American.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for the U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) in San Francisco said a woman she identified as Marilyn Hermosisima Nite, 39, had been arrested by INS agents on April 27 on a charge of overstaying her U.S. visa.</p>
<p>Nite was arrested in Newark, 20 miles (32 kms) southeast of San Francisco, INS spokeswoman Sharon Rummery said.</p>
<p>The Philippine government filed papers on Tuesday seeking Nite's extradition to face fraud charges, Rummery said. Nite, who was in custody, was due to appear before a U.S. Magistrate in Fresno on Friday, she said.</p>
<p>Nite, the former president of Bancapital Development Corp., an unlicensed dealer in government securities, was one of four people charged with fraud in the Philippines in 1994 in connection with a Philippine Treasury bill scandal.</p>
<p>The four were accused of defrauding the Bank of Commerce of $6 million worth of undelivered T-bills.</p>
<p>In a wide-ranging news conference at the Los Angeles City Hall, Ramos was also asked about the status of Philippine Second World War veterans.</p>
<p>&quot;Filipino veterans who served in the U.S. Army were promised everything while they were fighting -- justice, just like other GI's for defending the Pacific,&quot; he said. &quot;But they did not get that from the United States.&quot;</p>
<p>However, he said, &quot;there is growing momentum in (the U.S.) Congress of support for them.&quot;</p>
<p>He was referring to the Filipino Veterans Equity Bill which is still in the early stages of committee debate in both the Senate and the House of Representatives.</p>
<p>Under the bill, Philippine veterans would be granted the same pension, benefits and health care given American military veterans.</p>
<p>&quot;There are about 75,000 of them. They are getting older and weaker and many are probably not going to survive longer on this Earth,&quot; said Ramos. &quot;We are hoping and praying for them.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
