<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570431" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli shekel little changed vs dollar, basket.</title>
<headline>Israeli shekel little changed vs dollar, basket.</headline>
<dateline>TEL AVIV 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Israeli shekel's representative rate was fixed almost unchanged against the dollar and the basket of key foreign currencies on Thursday in mixed and balanced trade, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The market was very stable today with slightly more conversions of dollars into shekels. The basket remained above the lower edge of the trading band and the Bank of Israel was not seen in the market,&quot; said Guy Levi at Bank Leumi.</p>
<p>The central bank has been intervening regularly in the market to support the currency basket, which has been trading at the bottom end of its band for three months.</p>
<p>&quot;The main gainer was the yen, which rose against the shekel following the yen's rise against the dollar,&quot; Levi added.</p>
<p>The representative rate for the dollar was fixed at 3.4030 shekels against 3.4040 on Wednesday. The basket, composed of the dollar, mark, pound sterling, French franc and yen, was fixed at 3.6840 shekels against 3.6829 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>On the crosses, the shekel traded against the yen at 2.7444 shekels per 100 yen compared with 2.7208 on Wednesday, and against the mark at 1.9861 shekels compared with 1.9779 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>In the late afternoon, the dollar was trading at 3.4040 shekels.</p>
<p>- Dan Gerstenfeld, Tel Aviv newsroom, 972-3-537-2211</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEL AVIV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
