<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570456" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NOTICE OF SALE - New Jersey Educational Facilities.</title>
<headline>NOTICE OF SALE - New Jersey Educational Facilities.</headline>
<text>
<p>REVISED SUMMARY NOTICE OF SALE</p>
<p>				  $8,970,000*</p>
<p>	    New Jersey Educational Facilities Authority</p>
<p>				 Revenue Bonds</p>
<p>		 Rowan University Issue, Series 1997C</p>
<p>(Formerly designated as Rowan College of New Jersey Issue) NOTICE IS HEREBY GIVEN that the  Executive Director of the  New   Jersey   Educational    Facilities   Authority    (the Authority'') will receive SEALED BIDS with  respect to the Authority's $8,970,000*  aggregate principal  amount of  New Jersey Educational Facilities Authority Revenue Bonds, Rowan University  Issue,  Series  1997C  (the  Bonds'')  at  the  Authority's  office  located  at  101  College  Road   East, Princeton, New  Jersey  08540  (the  Authority's Office'') until 11:00 a.m., local time, on (the Bid Date''), and then  and there, such  bids will be publicly opened and announced for  the purchase of all  (but not less than all) of the Bonds.</p>
<p>The Bonds will  mature on  each July  1 beginning  July 1, 1999 through and including July 1, 2021.</p>
<p>Unless all Bids applicable to the Bonds are rejected, such Bonds will be awarded at or prior to 5:00 p.m., local  time, on the  Bid Date  at the  Authority's Office  to the  bidder bidding such interest rate or rates and purchase price which will produce the lowest rest cost (TIC) to the Authority over the life of the Bonds. True'' interest cost shall be determined for each bid by doubling the  semiannual  interest  rate,   compounded  semiannually,   necessary   to discount the debt service payments from the payment dates to May 1, 1997 and to the price bid, including the discount  or premium, if any, and excluding accrued interest.</p>
<p>The Bonds  are  subject to  optional  redemption  prior to maturity  and  may  be  subject  to  extraordinary  optional redemption and mandatory  sinking fund  redemption, as  more fully described in the Revised  Official Notice of Sale  and Supplement to Preliminary Official Statement.</p>
<p>The Bonds are offered when, as, and if issued and received by  the  successful  bidder,  subject  to  the  approval  of legality  by  DeCotiis,  Fitzpatrick  &amp;Gluck,  Trenton,  New Jersey,  Bond  Counsel  to  the  Authority.  Copies  of  the Preliminary Official  Statement dated  March 27,  1997,  the  Revised  Official   Notice  of   Sale  and   Supplement   to Preliminary Official Statement, and the Revised Official Bid Form may be obtained from the Authority's office (telephone: 609/987-0880; facsimile: 609/987-0850), from the Authority's Financial Advisor, A.H. Williams &amp;Co., Inc., 392 Springfield  Avenue,  Summit,  NJ07901  (908/522-8818)  or  1631   Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA 19103  (215/731-2415), or from  the Authority's bond counsel (609/278-1900).</p>
<p>Dated: May 7, 1997</p>
<p>				  Rafael Perez</p>
<p>			     Executive Director</p>
<p>	    New Jersey Educational Facilities Authority</p>
<p>	  *Subject to adjustment</p>
<p>			  (From The Bond Buyer)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
