<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570449" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: Jordan launches 10-year plan to tackle poverty.</title>
<headline>Jordan launches 10-year plan to tackle poverty.</headline>
<dateline>AMMAN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jordan will embark from July on a 10-year programme with international donor support costing around 698 million dinars ($985 million) to help alleviate widespread poverty, officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The plan, presented to King Hussein in a meeting on Wednesday, includes restructuring the national aid fund for low income families, infrastructure, and financing small projects and training schemes.</p>
<p>The projects aim to raise living conditions of the poor and involve spending 178 million dinars in the first three years and an extra 520 million dinars over the next seven years.</p>
<p>Planning Ministry officials, without specifying criteria, say the proportion of the 4.2 million population living in poverty has been stable over the last five years at 21 percent.</p>
<p>Independent economists say it is substantially higher. The World Bank says Jordanians' real wages have diminished over the last decade but avoids giving estimates.</p>
<p>The programmes are expected to be financed in part by World Bank aid and loans and support from individual countries.</p>
<p>The erosion in living standards has climbed to the top of the political agenda since bread riots broke out last August in the underdeveloped south.</p>
<p>The dismantling of price subsidies on bread drew attention to widening social gaps and poverty in poorer areas, officials and economists say.</p>
<p>A team that surveyed the needs of outlying rural and nomadic areas has focused on providing assistance to 28 areas including shanty towns and 13 Palestinian refugee camps close to large, heavily populated centres.</p>
<p>Projects to improve living conditions in refugee camps by building roads, sewage and sanitation plants have been allocated 173 million dinars over 10 years.</p>
<p>Needs of shanty towns have been estimated at 64 million dinars while aid to small-scale infrastructure projects has been put at 33 million dinars.</p>
<p>Three hundred local councils from a total of 460 across the kingdom were targeted as in dire need of help and allocated 145 million dinars.</p>
<p>($1=0.7080 dinars)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMMAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
