<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570425" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turk Yasarbank aims 20 pct asset growth in 1997.</title>
<headline>Turk Yasarbank aims 20 pct asset growth in 1997.</headline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's Tutunculer Bankasi Yasarbank, a medium-scale private commercial bank, aims to increase its assets by 20 percent in dollar terms, its general manager Nadir Topcuoglu said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are planning to increase our assets to at least $1.8 billion this year from $1.5 billion (at end-1996),&quot; Topcuoglu told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;However, I don't think that there will be a sharp increase in profits. Because we are trying to complete a series of investments in 1997,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He added that developments in the first quarter were in line with the growth plans and there was no need for a revision in the 1997 targets.</p>
<p>Topcuoglu said their aim was a broad client base in loans by addressing a large number of small and medium-scale firms rather than concentrating on a few big corporates.</p>
<p>The bank also sought to increase deposits and foreign trade activities this year, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;We are planning to increase our capital by September,&quot; Topcuoglu said, but did not give the amount of the planned capital rise.</p>
<p>The bank, which changed its name from Tutunbank to Yasarbank last year, doubled its capital to 10 trillion lira earlier this year.</p>
<p>Yasarbank, with 78 domestic branches and a banking subsidiary in Berlin, Germany, is mainly owned by Turkey's food, brewery and paint group Yasar Holding.</p>
<p>Topcuoglu said the bank was also planning to secure a $30 million syndicated loan this year, but did not elaborate.</p>
<p>-- Osman Senkul, Istanbul newsroom +90-212-2750875</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
