<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570418" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Child killed by bomb from Turkish army site.</title>
<headline>Child killed by bomb from Turkish army site.</headline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>(Updates with police finding bombs in house search)</p>
<p>One child was killed and four were hurt when a bomb they found on an army shooting range in Turkey's eastern province of Erzurum exploded, security officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The state-run Anatolian news agency said police searched nearby houses following the incident and found two sacks full of unexploded bombs, rocket launchers and mortar bombs.</p>
<p>&quot;One child was killed, another four were injured as a bomb went off,&quot; a security official told Reuters by phone. He gave no further details.</p>
<p>Four-year-old Fedia Ogurce died in the blast which occurred after the children took the bomb home. Four other children in the family, aged between six and 12, were badly hurt and taken to hospital.</p>
<p>Police detonated the bombs found in Pasinler near an ancient castle, Anatolian said. Police have arrested two people in connection with the explosives.</p>
<p>Turkey's Third Army Corps is based near Erzurum and troops from the province sometimes join the fight against rebel Kurds in the nearby southeast of Turkey.</p>
<p>More than 22,000 people have been killed in over 12 years of fighting between government troops and guerrillas of the Kurdistan Workers Party (PKK) seeking self-rule in the mainly Kurdish southeast.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
