<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570468" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Stocks hold their ground; little tax selling seen.</title>
<headline>Stocks hold their ground; little tax selling seen.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stocks found their footing in early trading Thursday as an expected wave of tax-related selling on a proposed capital gains tax cut failed to materialise.</p>
<p>Shortly after 10 a.m. EDT, the Dow Jones industrial average, which tumbled 140 points Wednesday, was up 8.43 points at 7,094.08.</p>
<p>Stocks were expected to be hammered following news late Wednesday that the proposed capital gains tax, as part of a proposed federal budget agreement, would be effective May 7.</p>
<p>Republican chairmen of the congressional tax-writing committees said they would propose setting that date as the effective date for a lower capital gains tax.</p>
<p>The tax cut is expected to be part of a tax package this year and was included in a broad outline of a budget agreement to balance the budget by 2002 reached Friday between congressional leaders and the White House.</p>
<p>&quot;There is still not a guarantee that the tax cut will go into effect,&quot; said Ricky Harrington, technical analyst at Interstate/Johnson Lane. &quot;Other factors are outweighing it, such as strong economic momentum.</p>
<p>&quot;I was surprised that the market came back over the past couple of weeks. It's still in a manic phase,&quot; he said. &quot;If volume slows on pullbacks and no selling comes in, you could get another move higher.</p>
<p>&quot;But the situation is fluid,&quot; Harrington added. &quot;Volatile. The only thing you can be sure of is that this volatility will continue.&quot;</p>
<p>Investors did not rush to sell, and it appeared that Wall Street was putting a positive spin on the tax angle of the proposed budget deal.</p>
<p>Longer-term, the tax cut will be bullish for stocks, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts expect the current top capital gains tax rate of 28 percent will end up anywhere from the 19.8 percent that Senate Republicans proposed early this year to 21 percent.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott has said there would be room to cut the top rate to under 20 percent.</p>
<p>Stocks also tracked bonds, which rallied on news that weekly jobless claims held steady, a possible sign that the economy's growth was slowing.</p>
<p>The Labour Department said 347,000 Americans filed for new jobless benefits in the week ended May 3. That figure was unchanged from the previous week.</p>
<p>The only time claims were higher this year was in the week ended Jan. 4, when they stood at 365,000.</p>
<p>Wall Street economists had forecast initial claims of 334,000 for the latest week.</p>
<p>Analysts said that the direction of interest rates would be a more important near-term factor for the stock market than the capital gains tax reduction.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
