<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570454" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Cockroaches may contribute to inner-city asthma.</title>
<headline>Cockroaches may contribute to inner-city asthma.</headline>
<byline>Gene Emery</byline>
<text>
<p>BOSTON, Reuter - The lowly cockroach may contribute to the high level of asthma among many U.S. inner-city children, a new study has concluded.</p>
<p>Researchers gave allergy tests to 476 asthmatic children in eight U.S. inner cities and tested their bedrooms for cat hair, dust mites and cockroach remains.</p>
<p>They found that 37 percent of the youngsters were allergic to cockroach allergen, compared to 35 percent who had a reaction to dust mites and 23 percent who were hypersensitive to cat dander.</p>
<p>The researchers, led by Dr. David Rosenstreich of the Albert Einstein College of Medicine in New York City, also found that 85 percent of the bedrooms had cockroach protein particles vs. 63 percent with cat dander and 49 percent with dust mites.</p>
<p>&quot;Our data confirm earlier reports showing that cockroaches are an important urban source&quot; of particles that spark an allergic asthmatic attack, the Rosenstreich team said in Thursday's New England Journal of Medicine.</p>
<p>When they cross-checked their data, the researchers discovered that the rate of hospitalization for asthma was unusually high among children who were sensitive to cockroach remains and who had the high levels of cockroach proteins in their bedrooms.</p>
<p>The hospitalization rate was more than three times higher than for youngsters with allergies to cats or dust mites.</p>
<p>The children allergic to cockroach proteins also logged 78 percent more trips to the doctor for asthma, had more days of wheezing, missed more days of school, and kept their parents awake more nights due to their asthma.</p>
<p>The results, the researchers wrote, &quot;suggest that reducing exposure to cockroach protein particles should be an important component of plans for the management of asthma.&quot;</p>
<p>Getting rid of cockroaches in the inner city by using safe insecticides and nontoxic traps &quot;should be evaluated as a method of reducing morbidity due to asthma in this population,&quot; they said.</p>
<p>In an editorial, Drs. Thomas Platts-Mills of the University of Virginia and Melody Carter of Emory University said keeping food and water away from the insects, routine cleaning and using insecticides can reduce the number of cockroaches.</p>
<p>But with asthma rates rising in different countries and environments, they said, &quot;it seems unlikely that reducing exposure to cockroaches, dust mites or animal dander alone will effectively control the increase in this disease.&quot;</p>
<p>The children tested in the Rosenstreich study came from St. Louis, Baltimore, Chicago, Cleveland, Detroit, Washington, D.C., and the Bronx and East Harlem in New York City.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
