<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570575" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Rain spreading from western Europe into east - WSC.</title>
<headline>Rain spreading from western Europe into east - WSC.</headline>
<dateline>LEXINGTON, Mass. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Significant rains are erasing drought conditions in western Europe and rainfall will also develop through the east in the next couple of days, bringing an end to the current mild spell, independent forecaster Weather Services Corp said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Major corn areas of western Europe have seen helpful rain and more is due in the region, spreading into parts of the east.</p>
<p>Significant rain has also fallen in parts of Spain, though lingering showers there will taper off the next few days, it said.</p>
<p>In its latest three-to-five day outlook for western Europe WSC forecast a chance of showers regionwide on Saturday, then mostly in the west on Sunday and the southwest on Monday. Temperatures will be cool, then milder.</p>
<p>Germany and central Europe will see showers on Saturday, ending on Sunday, and dry weather on Monday, with warming temperatures.</p>
<p>There will be rain, drizzle and fog in the British Isles on Saturday, showers and drizzle on Sunday and a few showers on Monday. Conditions will be cool, then trending milder again.</p>
<p>Showers in Mediterranean Europe should be limited mostly to Spain, where temperatures will be near normal. It will be dry and warmer over the remainder of the region.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LEXINGTON, Mass."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
