<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570586" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - Washington Post front - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Washington Post front - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Washington Post carried the following stories on its front page on May 8:</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - The Army accused the most senior enlisted man Sgt. Maj. of the Army Gene McKinney of having committed adultery with a female soldier and propositioning three other servicewomen.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>SPOTSYLVANIA, Va. - Detectives intensified their search for the driver of a white pickup truck seen cruising the Lisk sisters' neighborhood before their disappearance, while FBI divers and other investigators scoured a river about 35 miles away where the girls' bodies were found.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>SPOTSYLVANIA, Va. - The deaths of two sisters put residents on alert in this rural county where scared children play computer games behind locked doors and door-to-door salesmen are reported to the sheriff.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - Thirteen weeks before he died, Jack Kent Cooke changed his will to deny fourth wife Marlene Ramallo Cooke any part of his estate, but the document creates a charitable foundation to help gifted and underprivileged children.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>KINSHASA, Zaire - The president Zairians revile left the country and may not return, while rebel forces tightened a noose around the capital.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - Switzerland served as Nazi Germany's chief foreign source of credit and equipment during World War II, sustaining Adolf Hitler's war machine long after German financial resources were exhausted, according to a scathing U.S. government report.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - More than four years after overwhelmingly rejecting a referendum that would have established the death penalty in the District, a majority of residents now favor capital punishment for those who kill police officers, according to a new poll.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
