<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570523" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME live cattle calls mixed, feeders steady to off.</title>
<headline>CME live cattle calls mixed, feeders steady to off.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Early calls on CME live cattle futures ranged from 0.100 cent per lb lower to 0.100 higher while feeder cattle were called steady to 0.100 cent lower, livestock analysts said.</p>
<p>Further fund rolling, selling of June and buying of August, was expected to make for mixed price action. The &quot;Goldman roll&quot; started Wednesday and should continue another couple of days, traders said.</p>
<p>Apparent topping in wholesale beef prices is also expected to weigh on sentiment and offset recent strength in the cash cattle market, they said.</p>
<p>Retailer beef demand for Memorial Day is near an end which will likely lead to topping action in cash cattle, they said.</p>
<p>The market is also expected to start looking ahead to next week's USDA Cattle on Feed report. Placements of cattle on feed in April was well above a year ago and total on feed supplies are much larger, several analysts said.  </p>
<p>Analysts' feedlot placement estimates for April were running  as high as 127.5 percent of a year ago and on-feed estimates as high as 111 percent.</p>
<p>Feeder cattle futures were also expected to show a somewhat easier tone. Feeders look overbought, especially with fed cattle expected to be nearing a  near-term top. This should reduce demand for replacement feeders, they said.</p>
<p>Profit margins at feedyards do not look as good going into late summer as they previously had. Expectations for higher corn futures should also weigh on the market, they said.</p>
<p>The latest CME feeder cattle index rose $0.04 to $73.24 per cwt.</p>
<p>((Jerry Bieszk 312-408-8725))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
