<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570584" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Novellus to buy Varian's thin film unit.</title>
<headline>Novellus to buy Varian's thin film unit.</headline>
<dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Novellus Systems Inc said it planned to buy Varian Associates Inc's Thin Film Systems business for $150 million cash.</p>
<p>The Thin Film Systems unit makes and sells equipment for the physical vapor deposition market, which is a key technology in the production of advanced semiconductor logic and memory devices, Novellus said.</p>
<p>&quot;This move expands our portfolio of important metal deposition technologies and gives Novellus a critical mass of talent to aggressively compete for leadership in the device interconnect market,&quot; Novellus Chairman Richard Hill said.</p>
<p>With this acquisition, Novellus said it could provide customers with the entire set of deposition processes required for 0.25-micron devices and below.</p>
<p>According to industry research, the market for physical vapor deposition products was expected to grow from $1.5 billion to more than $3 billion by the year 2000, fuelled by increasing levels of device interconnection, it said.  </p>
<p>Varian said in a separate statement the sale included the unit's manufacturing facility in Palo Alto, Calif., as well as other sales and service facilities.</p>
<p>Varian said it would continue to be a supplier of semiconductor manufacturing equipment after the sale.</p>
<p>John Chenault, Novellus executive vice president, would assume management of the new business.</p>
<p>The transaction was expected to be completed within about 30 to 45 days, Varian said.</p>
<p>((New York newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34350">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34420">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JOSE, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
