<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570581" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - New York Times business - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - New York Times business - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York Times reported the following business stories Thursday:</p>
<p>* While Democrats and Republicans discussed the details of the Federal budget plan, Republicans said May 7, 1997 would be the effective date of any reduction in taxes on capital gains.</p>
<p>* The U.S. Federal Communications Commission approved a landmark restructuring of telephone charges which would raise prices for some services and lower them for others.</p>
<p>* The government reported that American business productivity grew at a two percent rate in the first quarter.</p>
<p>* Viacom reported a first quarter loss but the loss was below analysts forecast because of a strong performance by MTV and the &quot;Private Parts&quot; movie release helped offset weakness at the Blockbuster unit.</p>
<p>* Imperial Chemical said it would buy Unilever's specialty chemical division for $8 billion cash.</p>
<p>* News Corp quarterly earnings rose sharply helped by the re-release of the &quot;Star Wars&quot; trilogy and boosted by adding New World Communications Group TV stations.</p>
<p>* Transitional Hospitals received a $639 million hostile takeover offer from Vencor, after rebuffing a private offer from Vencor and agreeing to a friendly merger pact with privately-held Select Medical.</p>
<p>* Four drug makers whose blood products allegedly infected thousands of hemophiliacs with AIDS in the early 1980s will pay about $670 million under a settlement approved by a federal judge.</p>
<p>* Ad spending by auto makers, traditionally the largest advertising spenders, rose 9.4 percent last year.</p>
<p>* The Dow Jones fell 139.67 points to 7,085.65, following previous rallies based on the outlook for earnings, inflation and interest rates.</p>
<p>* A U.S. report said the Swiss government failed to honor an agreement which to return hundreds of millions of dollars in assets which Nazis looted from Holocaust victims and European banks. The study also criticized the U.S. government for not pushing the Swiss hard enough at the end of the war to account for the gold.</p>
<p>* New York state's plan to put all of its three million Medicaid recipients in managed care plans is facing hurdles.</p>
<p>* A report, discounted by some analysts, that Japanese, German and U.S. central banks were preparing to sell the dollar caused the currency to decline.</p>
<p>* Market place: It is tough to know if Nine West has more problems with accounting or investor relations.</p>
<p>* Officials in Texas border towns blame the North American Free Trade Agreement for the relatively depressed economy in these areas.</p>
<p>((New York newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
