<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570578" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - Wall Street Journal - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Wall Street Journal - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following stories were reported in Thursday's electronic version of The Wall Street Journal:</p>
<p>* Negotiators from Chrysler and the United Auto Workers reached a tentative accord which could end a nearly month-long engine-plant strike but several local union officials say they will urge members to vote against the pact.</p>
<p>* Borland filed a suit against Microsoft alleging unfair competition and illegal recruiting tactics.</p>
<p>* For the first time Fuji Photo will begin making film in the United States.</p>
<p>* The U.S. Federal Communications Commission moved to overhaul subsidiaries to telephone companies but delayed a decision on continuing to provide subsidies to consumers in high-cost regions.</p>
<p>* In the first quarter, productivity grew at a two percent annual rate, the largest gain in three years.</p>
<p>* Effective Monday, six of the Dow Jones Utility Average's 15 stocks will be new, in one the average's biggest changes.</p>
<p>* The Dow Jones industrials fell 139.67 points to 7,085.65 while the dollar fell.</p>
<p>* PNC Bank is in talks to acquire Oppenheimer &amp; Co for up to $500 million in cash, stocks and options, according to people familiar with the matter.</p>
<p>* Premier Laser Systems Centauri, the fist laser for dental work involving hard tissue, was approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.</p>
<p>* Donna Karan's quarterly net profit fell 87 percent in the most recent quarter.</p>
<p>* Three top AT&amp;T officials from the wireless-services operation left to form a joint venture with Craig McCaw, their former boss.</p>
<p>* Honda Motor is suing Republic Industries to block Republic's pan to acquire multiple Honda and Acura dealerships, alleging the company wanted to control as much as 20 percent of Honda's U.S. sales volume.</p>
<p>* The Toronto Stock Exchange delisted Bre-X Minerals stock while Canadian police met to work on their probe into the company's Busang site.</p>
<p>* J.P. Morgan combined its individual and institutional asset-management units, appointing Ramon de Oliveira to lead it.</p>
<p>* Heard on the Street: Shareholders of Nine West, until recently a Wall Street darling, learned Tuesday that the company is under investigation by the SEC. But some investors are asking why they were kept in the dark as the company's shares went into freefall over the last several weeks.</p>
<p>* Credit markets: Bonds suffered their worst loss in almost two months as economic statistics showed evidence of rising labor costs, while an auction of Treasury securities fared poorly.</p>
<p>(New York newsdesk 212-859-1610)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
