<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570504" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Airways to cut routes, close facilities.</title>
<headline>US Airways to cut routes, close facilities.</headline>
<dateline>ARLINGTON, Va. 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>US Airways Group Inc. on Thursday said it will stop flying some of its most unprofitable routes, close excess facilities and ground 22 aircraft as part of an efficiency program.</p>
<p>As a result of the plan, service to nine cities will be eliminated. Some employee furloughs are expected, but the company said it will work with union leaders and employee groups to minimize the impact on personnel.  </p>
<p>US Airways said that from Sept. 4, it would end service to the following cities; Albuquerque, N.M., Austin, Texas, Bangor, Me; Cincinnati, Ohio; Daytona Beach, Fla.; Islip, N.Y.; Melbourne, Fla.; Newburgh, N.Y.; and San Antonio, Texas. Other schedule changes are expected in the future, it said.</p>
<p>It said the moves would reduce its summer 1998 capacity by 6.5 percent from this summer's level.</p>
<p>The company also said it plans to phase out by the end of 1998 its maintenance facilities on Roanoke, Va., and Greensboro and Winston-Salem, N.C. Maintenance operations in Charlotte, N.C., Pittsburg, Pa., and Tampa, Fla., will be expanded to handle work done at the locations that are closing.</p>
<p>US Airways also said it plans to close by February 1998 its Los Angeles pilot and flight attendant crew base. Reservation centers in Nashville, Tenn., and Utica, N.Y., will be closed by Oct. 1, 1997, the company said.</p>
<p>The company made no estimate of the cost savings from the plan, nor any one-time costs connected to its implementation. It said it is committed and hopeful that labor talks will enable it to put in place a competitive cost structure.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ARLINGTON, Va."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
