<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570570" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - Daily Variety - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Daily Variety - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following stories appeared in Thursday's Daily Variety:</p>
<p>* United Paramount Network chairman and chief executive Lucie Salhany said she had decided not to renew her contract this fall after an embattled three years at the helm.</p>
<p>* Bruce Willis and Gaumont stole the show on opening night of the 50th Cannes Film Festival, as thousands of people massed outside the Palais des Festivals to watch the traditional ascent up the red-carpeted stairs that signals the start of the world's premier film fest.</p>
<p>* Universal Pictures, in negotiations for Latin American and Spanish rights to Betty Kaplan's &quot;Dona Barbara&quot;, now intends to seek out more foreign co-financing and split rights deals, Universal chairman Casey Silver said.</p>
<p>* General Electric's NBC is set to announce its fall lineup on Monday.</p>
<p>* The re-release of the &quot;Star Wars&quot; trilogy and acquisition of the New World Communications Group helped Rupert Murdoch's News Corp lift net earnings 38 percent to $291 million in the March quarter.</p>
<p>* James Woods has signed a deal to star in John Carpenter's &quot;Vampires&quot;, a contemporary horror thriller which has been scheduled by Largo Entertainment for a June 2 start.</p>
<p>* Writer David Kelley and producing partner Howard Baldwin will share receive the hockey script &quot;The Game&quot;, which Walt Disney Pictures bought.</p>
<p>((New York newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
