<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570511" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. stock index futures begin weak, turn mixed.</title>
<headline>U.S. stock index futures begin weak, turn mixed.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most U.S. stock index futures began weak but soon turned mixed amid ideas Wednesday's losses were overdone.</p>
<p>June Standard and Poor's 500 futures slipped to 810.60 overnight, but dipped only to 814.25 in day session trade. Floor sources said commission house buying around 815.00 helped boost prices into positive territory.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like they want to rally it up a little bit,&quot; one S&amp;P 500 futures trader said. &quot;People got caught short a little bit here,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>June had posted sharp losses on Wednesday.  </p>
<p>A weak T-bond futures tone spilled into S&amp;Ps early, but June T-bonds were stabilizing near unchanged. S&amp;P traders said they were keeping an eye on T-bonds and the 108-24/32 level in June T-bonds, which is the seven-percent yield equivalent.</p>
<p>Traders also said a weak dollar was an early drag on stock index futures.</p>
<p>One firm pegged June S&amp;P 500 fair value at 3.45 points premium to cash, buy programs at 4.50 points premium to cash or wider and sell programs at 2.70 points premium to cash or narrower.  </p>
<p>Traders said the market could chop around Thursday amid a lack of fresh economic news and after recent steep moves. On Monday, June rallied to a new record high at 838.00 and extended that record to 838.40 in the subsequent GLOBEX session.</p>
<p>But those gains unravelled on Wednesday, bringing the contract back below the 820.00 level.</p>
<p>By 0946 CDT/1446 GMT, June S&amp;Ps had rallied through resistance at 822.80 and 823.30-823.60 to post a new daily high at 825.50.  </p>
<p>Technicians called Wednesday's losses a down day in the overall uptrend, and said the market's characteristic resilience would re-emerge.</p>
<p>At 0948 CDT/1448 GMT, June S&amp;P 500s rose 6.10 points to 823.75, Midcap 400s rose 1.50 to 268.20, Russell rose 1.90 to 363.50, Value Lines rose 4.80 to 729.00, NYSE Composite rose 3.10 pts to 429.10, Nasdaq rose 15.50 points to 929.25, and Nikkei 225 rose 210.0 to 20,115.0. ((DerivativesDesk(312)408-8750)) E-mail:derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
