<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570597" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Big countries differ on regulating electronic money.</title>
<headline>Big countries differ on regulating electronic money.</headline>
<byline>Aaron Pressman</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Major industrial nations on Wednesday agreed to disagree over how best to regulate the rapidly-evolving but embryonic market for electronic money.</p>
<p>In a report issued after months of deliberations, the Group of Ten industrial countries said it would be premature to establish international guidelines for overseeing electronic money, leaving regulators to develop national standards on their own.</p>
<p>&quot;(There was) a broad consensus on the importance of flexibility in national approaches -- an endorsement that countries can pursue a number of different broad public policy approachs,&quot; Deputy Treasury Secretary Lawrence Summers said.</p>
<p>That conclusion was perhaps not surprising given the different approaches that various countries have taken to regulation in the field.</p>
<p>While the United States has largely taken a hands-off approach, others, such as France and Germany, have established tighter controls over electronic money.</p>
<p>Electronic money includes a variety of computer-based payment schemes, such as smart cards which can be filled with &quot;virtual cash&quot; and used to make small purchases.</p>
<p>The G-10 report recommended that regulators carefully monitor developments in e-money and be prepared to take appropriate action if needed.</p>
<p>&quot;We are standing carefully by the barn door making sure the horse doesn't get out but not standing idly by -- quite to the contrary,&quot; bank regulator and Comptroller of the Currency Eugene Ludwig told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;If one were to overregulate, one could stifle innovation, restrain the private sector, and all the benefits of this innovation could be lost,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>According to the report, electronic money does not pose much risk yet to law enforecment agencies. But in the longer term, it could be used for money laundering, tax evasion and other financial crimes.</p>
<p>It may have benefits as well, the report said.</p>
<p>Electronic money could make economies more efficient by reducing cash handling costs and improving speed and convenience for consumers, the report noted. &quot;It is still unclear, however, how quickly these products will spread in the G-10 countries,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>The 11 nations that comprise the G-10 are Belgium, Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the Netherlands, Sweden, Switzerland, Britain and the United States.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GTEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
