<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570590" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Analysts, traders hail CVRD auction.</title>
<headline>Analysts, traders hail CVRD auction.</headline>
<byline>Ian Simpson</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's auction of state-run mining giant Companhia Vale do Rio Doce (CVRD) is a milestone for economic reform in Latin America's biggest country, analysts and traders said Wednesday.</p>
<p>The sale of 41.7 percent of the company Tuesday to a consortium, headed by Brazilian steel maker Companhia Siderurgica Nacional and financed by NationsBank and other financial institutions, also set the stage for auction of other state firms.  </p>
<p>&quot;It means one big thing is out of the way and they can focus on reforms and privatization,&quot; said Lucia Skwarek, head of Latin American equities at UBS Securities.</p>
<p>&quot;It is enormously important for the market -- it sets a really good tone for the rest of the year.&quot;</p>
<p>ING Barings analyst Mirela Rappaport called the sale &quot;a landmark in Brazil's economic history.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;By transferring CVRD to the private sector, Brazil sends the world an important message regarding its commitment to economic liberalization and modernization,&quot; she wrote in a report.  </p>
<p>The reformist administration of President Fernando Henrique Cardoso sold the controlling stake in CVRD, the world's biggest iron ore exporter, for $3.12 billion. The privatization was the largest in Latin American history.</p>
<p>The government battled a wave of court orders and years of opposition to sell the stake in CVRD, considered the crown jewel in Brazil's huge state-run sector.</p>
<p>The final price was 20 percent above the minimum bid. However, CVRD preferred shares fell 6.47 percent to 26 reais in Sao Paulo amid profit-taking and some disappointment the premium was not higher.  </p>
<p>Mariana Albuquerque, Latin American economist at Lehman Brothers, said the auction was a tremendous boost for privatization of state-run electric companies and telephone company Telebras SA.</p>
<p>Those sales could start late this year or in 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;It just builds momentum for the ... privatizations that Cardoso has on the agenda, including telecommunications,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Alburquerque added that the CVRD sale could mean opponents would fight even harder to block the sale of Telebras.  </p>
<p>However, &quot;as far as foreign investors are concerned, they will realize that (Brazil's) is a serious government and it is ready to deal with that kind of opposition,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The sale also converts CSN, the head of the winning consortium, into one of the most powerful natural resources companies in Latin America, Morgan Stanley analysts Hillary Peruzzi said.</p>
<p>CSN, already the biggest steel producer in Latin America, will have major holdings in ore, gold, aluminum, transportation, steel and pulp and paper through the CVRD stake.</p>
<p>&quot;CVRD was already a world leader in mining and metal production and CSN was already Latin America's biggest steel company,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;Now they are a very power company with a lot of holdings over Latin American natural resources.&quot;</p>
<p>Through CVRD minority stakes, CSN will have pieces of almost all the other big Brazilian steel companies, including Companhia Siderurgica de Tubarao,  Acominas, Usiminas and Cosipa.</p>
<p>CVRD faces two more phases of privatization. The government will sell a five percent stake to company employees and will carry out a public offering of its remaining holdings.</p>
<p>((--Wall Street desk, (212) 859-1879))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
