<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570599" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Conservation group warns N. American forests in peril.</title>
<headline>Conservation group warns N. American forests in peril.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Croft</byline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Only 5 percent of U.S. and Canadian forests are protected from logging and mining and three-quarters of the region's forests are threatened with extinction, the World Wildlife Fund said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Releasing a new study that raised the alarm about North America's forests, the conservation group urged the U.S. and Canadian governments to at least double the amount of forest protected by national parks and wilderness areas by 2000.</p>
<p>&quot;The Earth Summit Two is coming up in June and we are asking both our governments to make a commitment to the global community in protecting these areas,&quot; Dominick DellaSala, director of forest ecology with the World Wildlife Fund in the United States, told a news conference.</p>
<p>World leaders are due to meet at the United Nations in New York next month for a conference marking the fifth anniversary of a landmark Rio de Janeiro environmental summit.</p>
<p>The World Wildlife Fund said North America's forests were among the most spectacular on earth but were &quot;disappearing at an alarming rate&quot; due to logging and other human activities.</p>
<p>The study -- released before the World Wildlife Fund's &quot;Forests for Life&quot; conference in San Francisco this week -- found that one third of 52 forest regions in the United States and Canada had numbers of species and habitats that were &quot;globally outstanding.&quot;</p>
<p>The outstanding forests ranged from northern California's Klamath-Siskiyous, which had more conifer species and rare plants and animals than any similar forest in the world, to southern and central Appalachia's temperate forests, one of two such regions on Earth with more than 2,500 plant species.</p>
<p>&quot;You don't need to fly to Amazonia to witness some extraordinary forests. We've got some right here in our home,&quot; DellaSala said.</p>
<p>But the fund said three-quarters of North America's forests were at risk of becoming extinct or so degraded they could not maintain a rich variety of plant and animal species.</p>
<p>Arlin Hackman, an official with the World Wildlife Fund in Canada, said Canada had a big responsibility in managing forests on a global scale since it had about 10 percent of the earth's forests within its borders. &quot;We're cutting about one million hectares (2.5 million acres) a year in our country,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The World Wildlife Fund urged the U.S. and Canadian governments to at least double the amount of protected forest by 2000 and to make sure protected forests represented a broad variety of habitat types and species.</p>
<p>It also encouraged timber companies in the United States and Canada to have their forests certified as well-managed and environmentally friendly under the principles of the Forest Stewardship Council, an independent body founded in 1993.</p>
<p>Some timber companies use certification as a marketing tool to sell to environmentally-aware consumers.</p>
<p>About 1.6 million acres (650,000 hectares) of forest are currently certified in the United States but none are certified in Canada, the World Wildlife Fund said.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like to see a tripling of certification in the United States and Canada by 1998,&quot; DellaSala said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
