<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570592" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: AFL-CIO says U.S. budget deal unfair to workers.</title>
<headline>AFL-CIO says U.S. budget deal unfair to workers.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>AFL-CIO president John Sweeney said Wednesday the budget deal worked out between the White House and Republican-led Congress is unfair to workers and will exacerbate income inequality.</p>
<p>&quot;An economic boom built on the rising productivity of American workers produced the revenue surge that made the budget deal possible,&quot; the union chief said.</p>
<p>&quot;Yet tax cuts for those who had benefitted most from the boom took priority over the needs of working families,&quot; he said. In a statement issued by the executive council, the union said the budget plan would exacerbate income inequality and that the AFL-CIO would lobby lawmakers to change parts of the budget plan they see hurting working families.</p>
<p>Sweeney told reporters following a meeting of the executive council that the union would launch a lobbying effort to ensure that health care, workplace safety, transportation and protection of housing and the environment were priorities in the budget.</p>
<p>The AFL-CIO executive council also vowed that the union would continue grass-roots lobbying efforts to fight &quot;to change the parts of the deal that create greater inequality and to change the political atmosphere that led to its making.&quot;</p>
<p>Sweeney said the union would also &quot;aggressively&quot; fight trade negotiation legislation that does not include language that allows U.S. officials to include labour and environmental issues in trade agreements.</p>
<p>The so-called fast track trade negotiation authority would allow U.S. trade officials to negotiate deals without fear they will later be changed by Congress. Lawmakers would be allowed to vote yes or no but not amend an agreement.</p>
<p>Sweeney said a number of lawmakers who supported the North American Free Trade Agreement are having second thought and may not support the fast track bill which would allow U.S. officials to negotiate an expansion of NAFTA to include Chile.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
