<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570588" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE-Badfinger great Pete Ham shines on posthumous album.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Badfinger great Pete Ham shines on posthumous album.</headline>
<byline>Matthew Lewis</byline>
<dateline>HARTFORD 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>One of rock music's most exciting archival finds is also one of the saddest.</p>
<p>A new album of previously unreleased songs by the late Pete Ham, leader of 1970s British group Badfinger, is winning rave reviews even as it reminds listeners of how much was lost when Ham committed suicide in 1975, at the age of 27.</p>
<p>For Dan Matovina, who produced the Rykodisc album &quot;7 Park Avenue&quot;, unearthing and restoring Ham's home recordings was both an honour and a technical challenge.</p>
<p>&quot;The tapes were in greatly decayed condition,&quot; the San Mateo, Calif.-based Matovina told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Matovina and many critics believe that the Welsh-born Ham, whose group was discovered by the Beatles and originally signed to their Apple Records label, ranks in the top echelon of rock songwriters, along with John Lennon, Paul McCartney, the Who's Pete Townshend and Ray Davies of the Kinks.</p>
<p>During its brief existence as a recording unit from 1969 to 1974, Badfinger scored worldwide hits with the Ham-penned &quot;No Matter What,&quot; &quot;Day After Day&quot; and &quot;Baby Blue.&quot;</p>
<p>Matovina, 39, discovered the Ham tapes -- whose existence had only been vaguely rumoured -- in 1992 after interviewing Ham's brother, John, in Swansea, South Wales, while researching a biography on the ill-fated Badfinger.</p>
<p>Matovina's biography, &quot;Without You: The Tragic Story of Badfinger,&quot; will be published later this year. The album was released in February.</p>
<p>&quot;(John Ham) told me he had some of Pete's demo tapes, and that I was free to listen to them,&quot; said Matovina, who is an authorised designate of Ham's estate.</p>
<p>Ham's other surviving relatives include a daughter, Petera Ham, who was born to his girlfriend, Anne Herriott, a month after he died. Petera now lives in Glasgow, Scotland.</p>
<p>EIGHTEEN NEW SONGS</p>
<p>Matovina's restoration work -- which included sonically cleansing the original mono master tapes -- features 18 never-heard songs that measure up to Badfinger's best work.</p>
<p>Particularly striking is the sharp contrast between Ham's brightly melodic muse and Badfinger's appallingly dark history.</p>
<p>Depressed over business problems, Ham hanged himself at his home in Weybridge, England on April 24, 1975.</p>
<p>History tragically repeated itself in November 1983 when bandmate Tom Evans -- who co-wrote with Ham &quot;Without You,&quot; a number-one single for Harry Nilsson in 1972 -- committed suicide in the same manner.</p>
<p>&quot;Badfinger's story is the most tragic story in rock 'n' roll,&quot; said Ken Sharp, Philadelphia-based author of the recently published book &quot;Power Pop! Conversations with the Power Pop Elite.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Half the band killed themselves because of outside problems, managerial problems, business problems,&quot; Sharp told Reuters. &quot;But I think Pete is really the shining light in the world of power pop as a writer, and he would have accomplished so much more, had he lived.&quot;</p>
<p>Sharp defines &quot;power pop&quot; as concise, melodic, energetic, guitar-driven rock.</p>
<p>During his brief life, the prolific Ham amassed a large backlog of tunes which Badfinger, because of its democratic songwriting structure, never got around to recording.</p>
<p>HITS THAT NEVER WERE</p>
<p>&quot;7 Park Avenue,&quot; named after Badfinger's London studio and residence, is packed with hit singles that never were, including the wistful &quot;Coppertone Blues,&quot; the elegant &quot;Sille Veb&quot; (the name of Ham's then-girlfriend spelled backwards) and the driving &quot;I Know That You Should.&quot;</p>
<p>The album's final two songs, &quot;No More&quot; and &quot;Ringside,&quot; are among the last Ham ever wrote, and can be read as virtual suicide notes.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't face the mirror anymore,&quot; Ham sings in &quot;No More.&quot; What's disturbing about this song is its upbeat, catchy melody -- almost as if the author could not restrain his power pop impulses even when he had one foot in the grave.</p>
<p>Matovina sighs when asked why an artist as gifted as Ham would want to take his own life.</p>
<p>&quot;He became depressed over issues of dealing with the music business,&quot; he said. &quot;He basically was a sensitive type who could not handle the harshness of the music business and what it entailed to stay within it.&quot;</p>
<p>Ham's suicide note included a bitter reference to Badfinger's American manager, Matovina said. &quot;At the time of his death, he had no outlet for his music. His career was locked up in lawsuits that he had nothing to do with.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It was just a lot of factors that came down, that one particular night that he killed himself...It's very likely that if he had been helped at the right time, he would still be alive today.&quot;</p>
<p>Ham would have turned 50 on April 27 of this year.</p>
<p>Matovina said because of the business problems that plagued Badfinger, &quot;We lost a chance to have another Beatles...They could never have had the impact of the Beatles, but musically they could have satisfied us with many records up to the quality level of the Beatles.&quot;</p>
<p>Some critics have argued that Badfinger's 1971 album, &quot;Straight Up,&quot; is as good as many Beatles albums.</p>
<p>Badfinger's surviving guitarist Joey Molland lives in Shorewood, Minn., and occasionally performs as part of a three-piece Badfinger. Original drummer Mike Gibbons lives in Florida and is working on a solo album.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARTFORD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
