<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570526" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX crude called higher tracking IPE Brent.</title>
<headline>NYMEX crude called higher tracking IPE Brent.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX crude was called five to ten cents higher Thursday tracking gains by Brent futures on London's IPE and expiry-related buying of gas oil there.</p>
<p>New signs that OPEC will maintain its production ceiling when it meets next month in Vienna were deemed by dealers to be neutral for oil prices here.</p>
<p>&quot;We are following the strength in London. The OPEC news maintains the status quo, so I don't see it being a factor,&quot; said Victor Yu, vice president at Refco Inc in New York.</p>
<p>Refined products were called steady to 0.25 cent a gallon higher.  </p>
<p>June Brent was five cents higher at $18.21 a barrel on the IPE while May gas oil was 50 cents higher at $168.00 a tonne.</p>
<p>Gasoline ended with healthy gains Wednesday on talk of refinery snags and after oil inventory data showed tightening supplies. Dealers said gasoline is becoming the oil complex's linchpin.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, June unleaded gasoline ended up 0.61 cent at 60.92 cents a gallon after rising to session high of 61.65 cents. June crude settled four cents a barrel lower at $19.62 while June heating oil finished 0.45 cent a gallon lower at 53.08 cents.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically its unleaded that is holding us up, so if gasoline doesn't break down then crude won't,&quot; said a New York crude dealer.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, OPEC President Libyan Oil Minister Abdullah Salem al-Badri said on Thursday he expected the group to stick with its 25.03 million bpd output ceiling when OPEC meets in Vienna in June.</p>
<p>He said the quota would be maintained for another six months until end-1997 despite widespread quota busting which has carried output almost two million bpd above official allocations.</p>
<p>Seven OPEC ministers have scheduled talks in Isfahan later on Thursday to discuss quota violations which have helped knock $7 a barrel off oil prices since the turn of the year.</p>
<p>-- New York Energy Desk, 212-859-1620</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
