<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570571" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S.March air cargo at 2 yr high says Tokyo-Mitsubishi.</title>
<headline>U.S.March air cargo at 2 yr high says Tokyo-Mitsubishi.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The index of U.S. air cargo trade activity rose 5.3 pct to 485.6 in March, its strongest gain since 6.8 pct in March 1995, Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi said.</p>
<p>In its latest Foreign Trade survey of air freight carriers, seaports and trucking firms, the bank said imports made the strongest contribution to this overall advance.</p>
<p>The index of future U.S. air cargo business rose to 550.4 in March, up 1.5 pct from February's 542.0 reading.</p>
<p>The index (1989=100) is an equally-weighted composite index of current U.S. export and import air cargo activity that is not seasonally adjusted.</p>
<p>&quot;The import side seems likely to continue strong and that should help keep overall air cargo industry demand growing,&quot; Michael Niemira, an economist with the bank, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Given the strength of the U.S. economy...there's an expectation of additional firmness in import-driven domestic demand,&quot; Niemira added.</p>
<p>The economist added, however, that the strong pace of U.S. air cargo trade activity in March may not be sustained in coming months. Nor, said Niemira, do industry participants themselves expect strength of this overall magnitude over the next three months.</p>
<p>Exports also were strong in March, but were running at less than half the pace of imports in generating air cargo activity, according to the bank's commentary in its Foreign Trade survey.</p>
<p>The report quoted one major European-based air cargo executive who noted that, although U.S. export growth was strong during March, it slowed noticeably in early April.</p>
<p>Another domestically-based air cargo official observed that there also were seasonal capacity problems for all combination carriers (passenger/cargo carriers) due to extraordinarily strong advance bookings on international passenger flights.</p>
<p>Commenting on the 5.3 pct March advance in its index for U.S. air cargo trade activity, the bank said this far outstripped February's 0.2 pct rise and compared with a 2.3 pct decline in January.</p>
<p>The air cargo current-conditions import index soared 7.4 pct in March over February, while the bank said its export index &quot;rose by a strong&quot; 3.3 pct.</p>
<p>The February readings were relatively flat with a 0.4 pct gain in export cargo activity and an unchanged import reading in that month, the bank's data show.</p>
<p>The index for air cargo export business rose 1.4 pct to 611.9 in March from 603.4 in the prior month. On the same basis, the index for air cargo export expectations edged up 0.7 pct to 667.6 from 663.0.</p>
<p>Air cargo import business index rose to 430.7, representing an even four pct advance over February's 414.0 level, while the import expectations index climbed 3.1 pct to 433.2.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
