<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570500" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Plains cattle trade quiet after sales -feedlots.</title>
<headline>US Plains cattle trade quiet after sales -feedlots.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Plains feedlot cattle markets were quiet early Thursday, with most of this week's showlists close to being sold out, feedlot sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have no bids, no offers and no cattle left to sell,&quot; a Texas Panhandle area feedlot manager said.</p>
<p>Most cattle left on showlists after two weeks of brisk packer buying are mostly likely light-weight animals, a Kansas cattle feeder said.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not many 1,200 lb cattle left out there this week,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Any sales Thursday would be thin, sources said.  </p>
<p>The bulk of this week's sales were done at $69.00 per cwt on Tuesday, although there were a few sold Monday at $68.00.</p>
<p>At $69.00, owners probably earned about $60.00 to $70.00 per head, a Kansas source said.</p>
<p>Fed cattle prices the past two weeks were buoyed by strong beef demand as retailers reportedly booked beef to be featured in Memorial Day holiday advertising features, sources said.</p>
<p>Lower beef prices on Wednesday suggested that the holiday buying could be starting to wind down, they said.</p>
<p>Beef prices Wednesday were quoted down $0.74 to $1.10 per cwt on 280 fabricated loads sold, USDA reported.</p>
<p>((Bob Janis 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
