<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570680" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Irish pound steady, unmoved by sterling woes.</title>
<headline>Irish pound steady, unmoved by sterling woes.</headline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Irish pound was steady  against sterling and expected to maintain current levels on Thursday in what dealers called quiet mid-morning trade.</p>
<p>The Irish pound was trading at 0.9290 sterling at 1025 GMT after briefly breaching 0.9300. At 1500 GMT a day earlier -- before sterling's overnight slide -- the Irish central bank quoted the punt at 0.9231 sterling.</p>
<p>Dealers said the Irish pound's stability was surprising, given sterling's four pfennig dive overnight after a newswire report quoted an unnamed Labour source saying Britain wanted sterling to rejoin the Exchange Rate Mechanism at 2.50 marks. The Treasury denied the report.</p>
<p>&quot;We thought Irish/sterling was going to go a bit lower after the sterling drop but it appears to have found its footing for the minute,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;If anything, the market is a bit short of Irish pounds and that is keeping it bid. One would have expected it a bit lower against the mark, given the way sterling is at the moment but there looks to be an overhang of Irish pound positions,&quot; a second dealer said.</p>
<p>He said the Irish pound, trading at 2.5880 marks at 1025 GMT, was likely to hold between 2.58 and 2.60 marks but head towards 2.57 in the longer term as the short positions unwound.</p>
<p>Against sterling, a range of 0.9250 and 0.9350 was likely in what dealers deemed a welcome pause for thought after the market's recent rollercoaster ride.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't see any significant movement for the minute unless sterling/mark collapses. And sterling/mark appears to have settled itself down,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Ascension Day holiday in parts of continental Europe was also helping to keep trade thin but the risk of accompanying volatility appeared remote, dealers said.</p>
<p>Dealers agreed the Irish pound was now locked below 2.60 marks, with sellers swooping in as soon as that level looked remotely close.</p>
<p>-- Tony Roddam, Dublin Newsroom +353 1 676 9779</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
