<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570639" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss take Nazi gold report in stride.</title>
<headline>Swiss take Nazi gold report in stride.</headline>
<byline>Greg Calhoun</byline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Switzerland on Thursday cautiously accepted a U.S. report criticising its World War Two gold dealings with Nazi Germany but tried to focus attention on its recent efforts to make amends.</p>
<p>The report, released in Washington on Wednesday, concluded that some of the gold the Nazis took from individual Holocaust victims was melted down and sold to Switzerland along with gold the Nazis looted from occupied countries.</p>
<p>The seven-month review compiled by Undersecretary of Commerce Stuart Eizenstat and the State Department's chief historian also blamed the postwar Swiss and U.S. governments of the time for their insensitive handling of the issue.</p>
<p>The Swiss government and banking sector have often seemed caught off guard by recent revelations about Swiss dealings with the Nazis or by criticisms of their efforts to identify and return the unclaimed assets of Holocaust victims.</p>
<p>But this time the Swiss had a rapid and measured reaction only a short time after the report was released.</p>
<p>&quot;The Federal Council (cabinet) welcomes the efforts of those responsible for the report to present facts objectively,&quot; Swiss Foreign Minister Flavio Cotti said at a news conference in Berne.</p>
<p>But he said the Eizenstat study failed to recognise the tight situation neutral Switzerland faced during World War Two.</p>
<p>&quot;On first reading (there is) lacking an appropriate appreciation of the extremely difficult situation in which our country found itself at that time, militarily and in terms of supplies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Cotti also stressed the fact that the report praised Switzerland for recent steps taken to make peace with its wartime past.</p>
<p>&quot;We want the truth and justice. Investigations must be conducted openly and without conditions in all countries affected. Switzerland is ready for this and has already introduced the necessary steps,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Swiss are hoping that steps taken recently to atone for the wartime past will make it easier to ward off new criticism, which was not expected to end with the publication of this report.</p>
<p>Swiss banks are still under fire over their handling of unclaimed accounts left by Holocaust victims.</p>
<p>The government has lifted bank secrecy for two independent panels, one hunting for unclaimed accounts and another writing a broad history of the Swiss role as a financial centre during World War Two.</p>
<p>Beat Balzli, Swiss author of a book about the country's dealings with Nazi Germany, said he expected a report pending from the so-called Commission of Experts to show the Swiss not only imported gold bars but also bought jewelry taken from Holocaust victims.</p>
<p>The neutral Alpine republic has not only been seeking to set the record straight about its World War Two behaviour but has also looked for ways to make some monetary atonement for its past.</p>
<p>In recent months it has set up a Holocaust memorial fund with 265 million Swiss francs ($182 million) in donations from banks and businesses.</p>
<p>&quot;The advantage that we have at present is that Switzerland has already taken decisive steps,&quot; Thomas Borer, a senior government official heading a Swiss task force looking into the Nazi gold controversy, said on national television.</p>
<p>&quot;...We are in much better position to respond to attacks on Switzerland based on the issue of morality.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;If you judge Switzerland you shouldn't do it so much on how Switzerland behaved 50 years ago. You should judge Switzerland by the steps it took over the last months.&quot; ($ = 1.456 Swiss Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
