<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570667" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Gary Oldman, Michael Jackson hit Cannes festival.</title>
<headline>Gary Oldman, Michael Jackson hit Cannes festival.</headline>
<byline>John Follain</byline>
<dateline>CANNES, France 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Gary Oldman packed an explosive punch in his first turn behind the camera, splattering the Cannes festival on Thursday with a heavy dose of violence, profanity and drug addiction in working-class London.</p>
<p>&quot;Nil By Mouth&quot;, the first film to run in the May 7-18 competition, won widespread acclaim for its riveting and partly-autobiographical portrait of a family which holds together only thanks to its women.</p>
<p>Oldman, a former Cannes juror who also plays an agent of an evil empire in Luc Besson's science-fiction spectacular &quot;The Fifth Element&quot;, unveiled on Wednesday, competes for the Golden Palm prize with the film he has scripted and directed.</p>
<p>&quot;I wanted to do something that represents me, where I lived and grew up,&quot; the 39-year-old Oldman, who starred in Stephen Frears' &quot;Prick Up Your Ears&quot; and Francis Ford Coppola's &quot;Bram Stoker's Dracula&quot;, said of a story which drifts in and out of characters' lives in an intricate plot.</p>
<p>&quot;The language is brutal. But I didn't see the point of making a piece that represents a culture and people that I have known, and then watering it all down,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>With scenes of domestic violence echoing Ken Loach's &quot;Ladybird, Ladybird&quot;, Oldman's is a bare-knuckle portrait starring Ray Winstone of a drink and heroin fuelled family which manages to sustain its existence through a series of odd jobs and shady deals.</p>
<p>Oldman's lighting and camera-work make for stifling, dark interiors in pub scenes and turns outside shots into near-gloom.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a harsh world, harshly portrayed. But the jury can expect a tough, powerful piece of drama which hints at a rare directorial talent. You have been warned,&quot; enthused industry magazine Moving Pictures.</p>
<p>Score-writer Eric Clapton described the film as &quot;the perfect depiction of what it's like to be an alcoholic&quot;.</p>
<p>Fellow singer Michael Jackson will later on Thursday cast the French Riviera competition in the shade when he climbs the red carpeted steps of the Palais des Festivals for a midnight screening of the 38-minute short &quot;Ghosts&quot;, starring Jackson and based on his song 2 Bad.</p>
<p>The first script for &quot;Ghosts&quot; was written in 1993 by best-selling author Stephen King but the project was dropped because of controversy over allegations of sexual misconduct by Jackson.</p>
<p>Oscar-winning Stan Winston, who directed &quot;Terminator 2&quot; and designed the dinosaurs of &quot;Jurassic Park&quot;, promises a Jackson no one has ever seen before in a film which blends drama and dance while transforming the character into multiple ghostly figures.</p>
<p>Alongside &quot;Nil By Mouth&quot;, Thursday's other competition entry, &quot;The Prince of Hamburg&quot; by Italy's Marco Bellochio is a harrowing account of a 19th century prince's stark choice between his life or heroism after he disobeyed orders as a cavalry commander.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANNES, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
