<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570677" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: INTERVIEW - France's right banks on growth - Borotra.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - France's right banks on growth - Borotra.</headline>
<byline>Christine Tierney</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>France's ruling centre-right coalition is much more confident in the country's ability to compete internationally than the Socialists who are proposing defensive solutions, Industry Minister Franck Borotra said.</p>
<p>The Socialists' &quot;defeatist&quot; policies, in turn, would make French industry even less competitive, he said in an interview to discuss the conservatives' platform ahead of the May 25-June 1 parliamentary election.</p>
<p>&quot;Rather than create the right conditions to stimulate economic activity and increase wealth, they want to establish policies of redistribution as opposed to growth,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The dilemma facing France isn't how to slice up the pie, it's how to make it bigger, create new wealth and improve the competitiveness of companies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>While growth will not fix all of France's economic problems, notably its record 12.8 percent jobless rate, it will do more to solve them than the redistribution envisaged by the Socialists through such measures as shorter work-weeks, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;A reduction in the work-week to 35 hours from 39 without modifying salaries represents around 12 percent of the wage cost -- it would wipe out the advantages of cuts in labour charges. That's not negligible in terms of competitiveness,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The centre-right coalition of the RPR/UDF parties wants to help industry through deregulation and further cuts in labour charges and to diminish the state's role in the economy by pursuing its privatisation programme, including the partial sale of France Telecom, he said.</p>
<p>After President Jacques Chirac called the snap two-round election, the government postponed the sale of France Telecom shares by four weeks to early June. &quot;We just need to win the elections and press the button and it's go,&quot; Borotra.</p>
<p>The Socialists would revert to their past policy of &quot;neither privatising, nor renationalising&quot;, depriving companies like Thomson-CSF and France Telecom of the partnerships and capital they need to compete in a global economy, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Socialists don't have faith in France's ability to take up the challenge of global competition and that's why they're proposing an administered economy,&quot; he said. &quot;That's a very important difference between the economic approaches of the right and the left.&quot;</p>
<p>The approach to public finance is another major difference. Borotra said the Socialists' plans to cancel privatisations and forego some 50 billion francs ($9 billion) of proceeds and to create new jobs using 70 billion francs of public funds will require either a big tax increase or swell the public debt.</p>
<p>&quot;We would revert to the faulty logic that you can grow while running a big deficit,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The state has a role as a regulator and it has to fulfill its responsibilities, notably as a guarantor of solidarity. But in terms of the economy, it needs to make way for the entities that can expand it, that is private sector companies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>While the centre-right government wants to rein in the state's role in the economy and clean up public finances, it has not abandoned the notion of public service to which the French people are deeply attached, Borotra said.</p>
<p>&quot;We shouldn't confuse the public service mandate with the organisation of public services,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The state will retain control of France Telecom and will remain 100 percent owner of Electricite de France (EDF), the utility which operates the nuclear electricity programme designed to make France self-sufficient in its energy needs.</p>
<p>&quot;Our attitude is one of pragmatism. In areas where competition will improve quality and lead to lower costs, why deprive ourselves? That's the case for France Telecom. But in areas involving strategic interests, such as (railways) SNCF and EDF, we're taking measures to streamline and cut costs but we're not changing the structure of the public service,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>($ = 5.790 French Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
