<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570661" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: Portuguese port workers to join ITF week of action.</title>
<headline>Portuguese port workers to join ITF week of action.</headline>
<dateline>LISBON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Portuguese port workers and seafarers will join an International Transport Workers' Federation (ITF) week of action starting on May 12, and may halt work on substandard ships, a union spokesman said.</p>
<p>The ITF has announced it will hold a week of industrial action across Europe against flag of convenience (FOC) ships from May 12 to May 16.</p>
<p>&quot;Port workers and seafarers will organise teams to visit individual ships and if they are found to be substandard will ask the ship authorities to remedy the problem. If they do not do so, dockers could stop work on that ship,&quot; said Mario Falgueiro, spokesman of the Federation of Dockers' Unions.</p>
<p>Falgueiro told Reuters that his Federation had given a formal 10-day notice of a strike by Portuguese port workers between May 12 and 16, but added that this was simply a legal step required if workers expected to halt activities.</p>
<p>The union spokesman said that port workers would not cease work if they found no substandard ships or if ship authorities complied with their requests to improve standards on board.</p>
<p>He said that dockers and seafarers were likely to visit oil tankers, many of which carried flags of convenience.</p>
<p>The term flag of convenience refers to ships flying the flag which is not the national flag of the country of the owner and the ITF has long said FOC registers tend to have more substandard ships and poorer wages than national registers. --David Brough, Lisbon newsroom +351-1-3538254</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LISBON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
