<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570631" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: New Mobutu-Kabila summit crucial for peace - U.S.</title>
<headline>New Mobutu-Kabila summit crucial for peace - U.S.</headline>
<byline>Paul Taylor</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. special envoy Bill Richardson said on Thursday that a fresh summit between beleaguered Zaire President Mobutu Sese Seko and advancing rebel leader Laurent Kabila was crucial to ensure a peaceful transfer of power.</p>
<p>After talks with French officials, Richardson said there was a good chance the two men would hold a second meeting mediated by South African President Nelson Mandela next week to prevent the civil war in Zaire ending in a bloodbath in Kinshasa.</p>
<p>A first summit aboard a South African warship last Sunday was inconclusive, with Mobutu insisting he wanted to hand over to a democratically elected president, and Kabila refusing to stop his troops' relentless advance towards the capital.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the probability is high for a second meeting and I'm also encouraged that this second meeting will produce a result that does not involve a violent end, and that includes also an inclusive transitional government,&quot; Richardson said.</p>
<p>He told a news conference he expected Mobutu to return to the Zairean capital eventually after a summit meeting with other French-speaking African leaders in Gabon on Thursday.</p>
<p>That contradicted suggestions in Zaire that the veteran strongman, in power for 32 years, was on his way into exile.</p>
<p>The French Foreign Ministry said the question of whether Mobutu, who owns a sprawling luxury villa on the French Riviera, would live in exile in France was &quot;not topical&quot;.</p>
<p>Richardson, Washington's ambassador to the United Nations, said he had tried during his 10-day mission to Africa to bring pressure on both sides to negotiate a &quot;soft landing&quot; enabling an orderly transition and democratic elections.</p>
<p>He denied widespread reports of a power struggle between the United States and France over Zaire, saying they were working closely together, and insisted the fact that neither President Jacques Chirac nor Foreign Minister Herve de Charette had made themselves available to meet him was not a snub.</p>
<p>Instead, the envoy met senior presidency and foreign ministry officials, stressing that Washington wanted Paris to be &quot;partners in leadership&quot; in Africa.</p>
<p>The former Democratic congressmen even ventured a few words of French to tell a reporter that France and the United States were united in their objective of seeking a peaceful settlement.</p>
<p>Richardson said he had sought to bring &quot;constructive pressure&quot; on Kabila, whose rebel forces have swept across Zaire from the east and are now reported advancing on the capital, to avoid a military solution to the conflict.</p>
<p>Asked what leverage Washington had to persuade Kabila not to seize Kinshasa by force, he said Zaire would need help from international lending agencies for post-war reconstruction.</p>
<p>&quot;If there's a peaceful, inclusive transitional government, I think Zaire will be able to attract international support. If the transfer is violent, I believe Zaire will have difficulty attracting the international suppport that it needs to rebuild itself,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The U.S. envoy said he was returning to Washington later on Thursday to report to President Bill Clinton on his mission.</p>
<p>Asked why he was going home after declaring that the next few days were critically important, Richardson said: &quot;There shouldn't always be outsiders settling Africa. I think Africans can settle it for themselves with the help of the United Nations...and of South Africa.&quot;</p>
<p>Richardson gave a guarded impression of Kabila, with whom he said he had held two tough meetings.</p>
<p>He said the rebel leader had taken the peace negotiations seriously and pledged to allow the United Nations to investigate massacres of refugees in rebel-held areas and to be flexible on the deadline for returning Hutu refugees to Rwanda.</p>
<p>&quot;Well, he's an interesting man, very street smart. He's somebody that I believe needs to realise that he has to behave responsibly if he's to get the support of the international community,&quot; the U.S. envoy added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
