<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570652" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Thibault De Silguy hopes Britain joins euro.</title>
<headline>Thibault De Silguy hopes Britain joins euro.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Yves Thibault de Silguy, European Commissioner responsible for monetray affairs, said in a radio interview on Thursday that a majority of countries would be ready to join the euro in 1999.</p>
<p>He said if there was uncertainty on France's intentions concerning the euro, with the opposition Socialist party wanting to put conditions on the country's entry, that could lead to higher French interest rates.</p>
<p>He told Europe 1 radio that he hoped Britain would join the euro and said the decision was up to Britain.</p>
<p>Asked to comment on conditions the Socialists want to impose -- interpreting the budget criteria as trends and not fixed figures, entry of Italy and Spain from the start, abolition of stability pact -- Thibault de Silguy said &quot;There are conditions in the Maastricht Treaty, there is no reason to add.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;If the criteria of the Maastricht Treaty .... are respected, the single currency will come to exist,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that a majority of countries will be ready to pass to the single currency if its comes into force on January 1, 1999,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said it was false that the stability pact would stunt employment growth or even cost jobs, as some politicians claim.</p>
<p>&quot;The Stability Pact has been decided and adopted, it is out of the question to adjust it. If we start to tamper with it we put into doubt the entire process,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The pact is called a pact of stability and growth. Reducing public deficit, sound public finances is a prime and essential condition to economic growth,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said that the process of monetary unity had arrived in a extremely sensitive period and said it was necessary not to create any uncertainties.</p>
<p>&quot;If a government would let it be known that it would question the policy of reducing public deficits, that would cause doubts on the markets. That would lead to a substantial rise in interest rates,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said that economic growth was returning to Europe. Growth of 1.6 percent in 1996 was expected to rise to three to four percent in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;What we expect in Brussels, what people expect abroad, in Europe is that the winner (of the French election) will continue the policy of reducing public deficits and of keeping a lid on inflation because that is the condition to growth,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said that statements by the new Labour government in Britain were &quot;encouraging&quot;, concerning the social chapter and the independence of the central bank.</p>
<p>&quot;That is a clearly positive element, new and encouraging,&quot; Thibault de Silguy said.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment the position of the British government is clear, it is highly impropable that they will join on January 1, 1998. It is in their interest and in the interest of Europe that they will participate but the decision is up to the English,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
