<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570662" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Paris says has no sign Mobutu planning exile.</title>
<headline>Paris says has no sign Mobutu planning exile.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>France has no indication that Zaire's embattled President Mobutu Sese Seko could be planning exile in France, where he has a Riviera villa, the foreign ministry said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not know the intentions of President Mobutu, so the possibility of exile is not a current question,&quot; ministry spokesman Foreign Ministry Jacques Rummelhardt told Reuters.</p>
<p>Mobutu, who came to power in 1965, went to Gabon on Thursday for a mini-summit with a handful of fellow French-speaking African presidents to try to find a peaceful end to the war.</p>
<p>Rummelhardt noted that Mobutu &quot;has come here in the past for medical treatment&quot;. Mobutu underwent surgery for prostate cancer in Switzerland last August and has spent several months convalescing in a luxury villa overlooking the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>Zaire's Information Minister Kin-Kiey Mulumba rejected suggestions that Mobutu's departure for Gabon was a veiled flight into exile and said the veteran leader would return to his capital after the meeting.</p>
<p>Bill Richardson, U.S. ambassador to the United Nations, was in Paris on Thursday for talks on the Zaire crisis after a trip to the region last week.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
