<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570635" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: FOCUS-Bank Austria 1996 net down 39 pct.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Bank Austria 1996 net down 39 pct.</headline>
<byline>Janet McBride</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austria's largest bank Bank Austria on Thursday reported a surprise 39 percent drop in 1996 net profit and lifted the veil on how its new alliance with ex-rival Creditanstalt was working out.</p>
<p>In a statement, released into a void with the Vienna market closed for a public holiday, Bank Austria said 1996 group net tumbled to 1.587 billion schillings from 2.587 billion despite a one percent rise in operating profit to 5.397 billion.</p>
<p>Bank Austria traced the sharp drop in 1996 group net profit to the removal of two subsidiaries from its consolidated accounts and other unspecified adjustments. A spokesman said he could not add to the firm's statement.</p>
<p>The bank revealed that first quarter operating profit, consolidated for the first time to include most Creditanstalt units, was 3.565 billion schillings.</p>
<p>No comparative figure was provided but the statement described the performance of parent company Bank Austria AG as &quot;very satisfactory&quot;. Its operating profit increased 29 percent to 1.395 billion schillings.</p>
<p>The nation's two top banks formally came under one roof in March as part of a 17 billion schillings deal that gave Bank Austria the state's 70 percent stake in Creditanstalt ordinary voting shares.</p>
<p>The merger -- Austria's biggest since World War Two -- created a banking giant with assets valued at 1,550 billion schillings at the end of March.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very difficult to read anything into the first quarter figures because there is nothing to compare them against,&quot; said Kleinwort Benson analyst James Alexander.</p>
<p>He added that Creditanstalt had probably made a big contribution to the headline figure thanks to its record 2.11 billion schillings operating profit in the first quarter.</p>
<p>Analysts expressed surprise at the drop in 1996 group net profit, which came in well below forecasts of around 2.5 billion schillings and failed to match the 1.709 billion posted by the parent company.</p>
<p>&quot;One can only assume that Bank Austria has reduced some of its industrial holdings,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>Bank Austria will hold a news conference on its 1996 performance on May 15.</p>
<p>The statement called the improvement in the group's 1996 operating profit &quot;thoroughly positive&quot; and noted the increase was closer to 2.5 percent adjusted for the sale in November of British leasing firm Sovereign Finance plc.</p>
<p>&quot;(Trading arm) Bank Austria Handelsbank managed to improve its operating result considerably. The development of foreign units was very satisfactory and they made a significant contribution to the group's result,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>A decline in group interest surplus to 12.957 billion schillings from 13.044 billion in 1995 was due to unfavourable market conditions and the exclusion of Sovereign.</p>
<p>It said the parent company's first quarter earnings had received a boost from higher income from currency and securities business. Its trading surplus rose to 428 million schillings from 141 million the previous year.</p>
<p>Bank Austria made no mention of its dividend plans. In March chief executive Gerhard Randa forecast the 1996 dividend would be up on 1995's 10 schillings per share.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81403">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
