<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570676" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Borotra says Renault/Peugeot merger is a bad idea.</title>
<headline>Borotra says Renault/Peugeot merger is a bad idea.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Industry Minister Franck Borotra said a merger between the two French car groups Renault K and PSA Peugeot Citroen would be &quot;a very bad idea&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a very bad idea... They have almost the same strengths and the same weaknesses. It is not certain that with people who have the main weaknesses you can make a system that is more efficient,&quot; Borotra told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>He added that the two companies had &quot;profoundly different&quot; corporate cultures.</p>
<p>Both French companies are struggling to cut their cost base and become more competitive in an increasingly fierce market.</p>
<p>Peugeot and Renault had jointly asked the government for help in a scheme to allow older employees to retire early and hire younger workers.</p>
<p>Some commentators have suggested the two French groups could better combine than stay apart.</p>
<p>Borotra said that he was convinced that there would be &quot;scope for two general French car companies on the European market&quot; after the year 2000.</p>
<p>He added Renault and Peugeot had to &quot;cut their cost price, streamline the production system and be present on export markets.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;That is why I have told Renault it should return as soon as possible to break-even in 1997 or certainly in 1998. The restructuring measures taken by the company management are indispensable to avoid running up losses and putting the future of the company at stake,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The French government is with 46 percent the largest shareholder in Renault. Renault in February announced the closure of its plant in Vilvoorde, Belgium, in a quest to cut costs.</p>
<p>-- Paris newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
