<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570621" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: DASA plans to spend no cash in Lagadere deal.</title>
<headline>DASA plans to spend no cash in Lagadere deal.</headline>
<byline>Svea Herbst-Bayliss</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's Daimler-Benz Aerospace AG (DASA) does not plan to spend any cash to finance a planned strategic cooperation with Lagardere of France, DASA's chief executive said on Thursday.</p>
<p>DASA head Manfred Bischoff said the deal, which covers missiles, space and defence electronics, would mostly have benefits for Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;No money will flow in this deal,&quot; he told reporters. But he said Lagardere, a defence-to-publishing group, would probably need to pay something for its stake in DASA's LFK missile unit.</p>
<p>DASA, a unit of German industrial giant Daimler-Benz AG, and Lagadere announced on Wednesday they had signed a strategic cooperation to help them compete better with the powerful North American defence firms.</p>
<p>DASA plans to remain on the sidelines of Lagardere's bid to buy defence electronics group Thomson-CSF, which is being offered for privatisation in France.</p>
<p>It has promised &quot;total and unconditional support&quot; for Lagardere's bid but Bischoff stressed: &quot;We will not pay for anything nor will we finance anything.&quot;</p>
<p>If Lagardere however lost out in the two-horse race for Thomson to Alcatel Altshom, changes could be made in the DASA-Lagardere deal, Bischoff said. &quot;Fundamental changes could occur in the defence electronic area,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bischoff said the Lagardere alliance would be in place by the middle of next year, at the latest. Eager to improve the European industry's competitiveness, he has tried several times to broker similar deals only to see them fall apart.</p>
<p>Bischoff called the deal &quot;a very interesting solution&quot; that could help to reshape the European aerospace and defence industry. By pooling resources, DASA and Lagardere could grow enough to compete successfully with larger U.S. groups, Bischoff said.</p>
<p>&quot;Now we need to start planning the details,&quot; Bischoff said. But he added that &quot;there were still many obstacles&quot; which could make sorting out the details more difficult.</p>
<p>In space cooperation, the activities of Matra Marconi Space (MMS) -- a venture owned 51 percent by Lagardere and 49 percent by General Electric Co Plc of Britain -- will be combined with DASA's.</p>
<p>The cooperation would cover satellites, launch vehicles and orbital infrastructure.</p>
<p>DASA and MMS will be equal partners in a business with worldwide sales of $3 billion, ranking it third behind Lockheed Martin Corp and Boeing Co.</p>
<p>In missiles, Matra BAe Dynamics -- a joint venture between Lagardere and British Aerospace -- will take a 30 percent stake in DASA unit LFK and become its strategic partner.</p>
<p>The deal should open DASA's business, hit by a tight German defence budget, to foreign markets and tie it in to Europe's leading missiles grouping. It would also leave room for consolidation in the German missiles industry.</p>
<p>DASA and Lagardere intend to combine certain areas of their defence electronics businesses in several steps to create a company of equal partners.</p>
<p>Bischoff promised that no German jobs should be lost through this alliance and said the deal might ultimately create new jobs.</p>
<p>The deal may be welcomed by Daimler-Benz shareholders since it will help DASA to move out of non-core businesses and focus on its plane-making activities.</p>
<p>DASA is a member of the Airbus passenger aircraft and Eurofighter combat jet projects.</p>
<p>--Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
