<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570614" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Suffolk Cnty, NY lawmakers might probe LILCO deal.</title>
<headline>Suffolk Cnty, NY lawmakers might probe LILCO deal.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Suffolk County, New York, legislators expect to decide on Thursday whether to hire a law firm and a team of consultants to probe a partial takeover of Long Island Lighting Co, a spokesman said.</p>
<p>The county legislators already have authorized spending up to $200,000 to hire such firms. &quot;Several members of the legislature are concerned, though they are not prejudging, and they want to get all the facts and information,&quot; said Warren Greene, a spokesman for the lawmakers.  </p>
<p>Gov George Pataki has proposed what would be the nation's biggest tax-exempt bond sale -- $7.3 billion -- to buy assets from LILCO and Brooklyn Union Gas, which plan to merge. The bonds would be sold by the Long Island Power Authority, which the state created in 1986 to acquire LILCO.</p>
<p>The Republican govenor on Wednesday night planned to hold a news conference in the Village of Northport in the Town of Huntington, which is located in Suffolk County. Greene said that before a town meeting, scheduled to follow the news conference, the governor was expected to meet with the county legislators.  </p>
<p>Republicans hold an 11 to 7 majority in the body, and the County Executive, Robert Gaffney, opposes its plans.</p>
<p>&quot;There's finally meaningful, tangible relief on the horizon and now the legislature is thinking of delaying it even further so the county executive is deadset against it,&quot; said Tim Ryan, a spokesman for Gaffney.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the governor said he expected the news conference to focus on Pataki's proposal, which he has said would cut by 20 percent rates for Long Islanders, who now pay some of the highest in the United States. No new information was expected to be released, added the spokesman, Mike McKeon.  </p>
<p>The Democrat-led Assembly, which has been holding hearings on the deal, plans to hold at least two more, one on May 14 and one on June 5. LILCO chairman William Catacosinos is expected to testify at the May 14 hearing in Albany, but LILCO could not immediately say whether he will go.</p>
<p>Assemblyman Paul Tonko, an Amsterdam Democrat who chairs the committee on energy, said the process was open-ended. &quot;We may need to do some more (hearings), then we have to compile what we have heard, then there will be ongoing discussions,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Among the issues he raised was whether the deal would enrich LILCO shareholders. &quot;The ratepayer is asked to hold the LILCO structure harmless and to actually put more hard cash into the hands of the leadership and the executive of LILCO,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He also cited concerns about whether the huge bond issue, which would be offered in a series of sales, would drive up how much the state was forced to pay in interest on its own debt, and whether LILCO would get preferential treatment over its competitors.  </p>
<p>&quot;When you're talking about a 33-year deal, you don't want to lock a Long Island ratepayer into a situation that is going to hinder them more than help them.&quot;</p>
<p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, D-Manhattan, could block the deal as he serves on the Public Authorities Control Board, which approves and coordinates bond sales by state authorities. Rumors that the board might take up the LILCO deal at a meeting next week could not be immediately confirmed.</p>
<p>The energy and enivronment committee of the Suffolk County legislature recommended that the body select Scott Hempling, a Silver Springs, Maryland, law firm, which specializes in utility matters, and Boston-based consultants, LaCapra Associates, which has broad experience in the area.</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
