<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570618" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Police arrest in 11 in blow to Sicilian Mafia.</title>
<headline>Police arrest in 11 in blow to Sicilian Mafia.</headline>
<dateline>PALERMO, Sicily 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police on Thursday said they had arrested 11 suspected leading members of the Mafia's bloody Corleonesi clan in what could prove a further severe blow to its supremacy in the world of Sicilian organised crime.</p>
<p>The arrests, ordered by prosecutors in the Sicilian capital Palermo, netted 11 so-called &quot;men of honour&quot; whose ties to Cosa Nostra were exposed by Mafia turncoats, investigators said.</p>
<p>Chief among them was Mario Salvatore Grizzaffi, nephew of jailed Corleonesi clan leader and Mafia &quot;boss of bosses&quot; Salvatore &quot;The Beast&quot; Riina.</p>
<p>State television said the operation had &quot;decapitated&quot; the Corleonesi, many of whose historical figures have followed Riina to jail since he was captured in January 1993 after almost a quarter of a century on the run.</p>
<p>Judicial sources said Grizzaffi, 31, was suspected of having sat at Mafia summits with Riina's son Giovanni, arrested last year and now serving a jail term for Mafia membership.</p>
<p>Prosecutors allege that the 11, ranging in age from 27 to 67, had also sheltered Mafiosi on the run, stored weapons and blackmailed businessmen.</p>
<p>Giuseppe Micalizio, deputy head of the elite DIA anti-Mafia squad, said evidence from turncoats, including defectors from Riina's own clans, had exposed the suspects' links to the Mob.</p>
<p>Grizzaffi and five of the other men arrested had no previous criminal record.</p>
<p>&quot;These are people from a variety of backgrounds. Some are farmers, some of them artisans and and others were in the earth-moving business,&quot; Micalizio told Italian radio.</p>
<p>The innocence of the pursuits is typical of how the Mafia has operated in Sicily, concealing a multi-billion dollar empire of crime behind the facade of a modest lifestyle and a deadly code of &quot;Omerta&quot;, or silence.</p>
<p>In a separate operation on Wednesday, police said they had confiscated assets worth more than one trillion lire ($590 million) from a jailed Sicilian construction company owner, Vincenzo Piazza.</p>
<p>Piazza, who has been in prison for three years on charges of links with the Mafia, officially declared a gross monthly income of 1.8 million lire ($1,000) in 1989.</p>
<p>Riina, who declared himself a &quot;simple peasant&quot; when he was arrested, held what was arguably the bloodiest sway ever over the Mafia.</p>
<p>His clan, from the hilltop town of Corleone immortalised in Hollywood's Godfather movies, ranked as &quot;country cousins&quot; to the dominant Palermo families until the 1970s.</p>
<p>Its irresistible rise was achieved through a reign of terror which shook even the Mob and, many investigators say, encouraged terrified fellow Mafiosi to seek protection from the state by turning themselves in to give evidence.</p>
<p>Corleonesi control of Cosa Nostra culminated in the killings in 1992 of top anti-Mafia judges Giovanni Falcone and Paolo Borsellino in an all-out war on the state.</p>
<p>Public outrage at the killings spurred the most serious police assault on the Mafia since the days of Fascist dictator Benito Mussolini.</p>
<p>Riina's arrest was followed by that of his brother-in-law Leoluca Bagarella and, last year, of the Corleonesi's suspected &quot;military chief&quot;, Giovanni Brusca.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PALERMO, Sicily"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
