<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570672" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Juppe quizzes Jospin as French vote race tightens.</title>
<headline>Juppe quizzes Jospin as French vote race tightens.</headline>
<byline>Alister Doyle</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe lashed out at the opposition Socialists on Thursday amid signs of unease in his centre-right coalition as the left scents an upset win in France's snap parliamentary election.</p>
<p>Juppe sent Socialist party leader Lionel Jospin, expected to publish an article in French newspapers on Friday, four questions he said everyone was asking about Jospin's programme ahead of the May 25-June 1 poll.</p>
<p>&quot;How will you finance the Socialist programme without considerably raising the taxes of each French person?&quot; Juppe asked. Jospin says he can avoid tax rises with a programme that includes creating 700,000 jobs and cutting working hours.</p>
<p>In a statement, faxed from the prime minister's office, Juppe also asked how the Socialists would avoid a &quot;massive return of clandestine immigration&quot; if it carried out a pledge to scrap tough new laws extending police powers to crack down.</p>
<p>He said Jospin should also spell out how he would &quot;avoid a crisis for Europe&quot; if he appointed Communist ministers to a cabinet. The Communists say they should get seats in a left-wing coalition.</p>
<p>Finally, Juppe said the Socialists were split on whether to nationalise or privatise and asked which way Jospin would go.</p>
<p>Juppe on Thursday won endorsement from a French European Commissioner who dropped his impartiality to warn that Socialist conditions for joining a single European currency from 1999 could create uncertainty and push up interest rates.</p>
<p>Yves Thibault de Silguy, a conservative in charge of EU monetary affairs, also said he believed the Socialists would be committed to a single currency if they won and that their policy would be little different from the present government's.</p>
<p>Jospin has said that he will not impose extra austerity if needed to meet budget deficit targets for qualifying for the euro. He has also set conditions including entry of Italy and Spain from the start and that the euro should not be overvalued.</p>
<p>&quot;If a government lets people think that it will review the policy of reducing public deficits, it can lead to problems, notably on the markets, and translate into substantial interest rate rises,&quot; De Silguy told Europe 1 radio.</p>
<p>Asked about Jospin's conditions, he said: &quot;There are conditions in the Maastricht Treaty, there is no reason to add.&quot;</p>
<p>Juppe quizzed Jospin a day after President Jacques Chirac sought to revive Juppe's lacklustre campaign with an article in regional newspapers that included an assault on the left-wing and an appeal for voters' trust and support.</p>
<p>The Socialists brushed off Chirac's intervention as a desperate plea and Jospin said he was growing confident of an upset win. Opinion polls show the centre-right has lost almost all of its early lead.</p>
<p>Ex-president Valery Giscard d'Estaing exposed a rift in Juppe's coalition by saying late on Wednesday that he had advised Chirac not to dissolve parliament and take the risk of calling elections almost 10 months early.</p>
<p>He urged Chirac to shift to bolder, simpler policies after a parliamentary election and hinted he should not reappoint Juppe, shown by opinion polls to be deeply unpopular, even if the centre-right won.</p>
<p>&quot;The right doubts its success and feeds speculation about the future of Mr Juppe,&quot; the French daily Le Monde said.</p>
<p>But the race has yet to fire French people's imagination, with many believing neither side has the key to their main concern -- unemployment. &quot;When's it going to begin?&quot; the daily France-Soir asked in a front-page headline.</p>
<p>Chirac and Juppe attended a ceremony on Thursday, an Ascension Day holiday, to lay a wreath at the tomb of the unknown soldier beneath the Arc de Triomphe to mark the end of World War Two in Europe.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
