<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570673" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Fiat return on sales up in March - analysts.</title>
<headline>Fiat return on sales up in March - analysts.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italian industrial giant Fiat saw a return on sales of 4.4 percent in March this year, with an average for the first quarter of 1997 of 2.6 percent, analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Fiat, which held a presentation for analysts late on Wednesday, expected return on sales growth to be maintained into the second quarter with levels close to the March rate, analysts who attended the meeting said.</p>
<p>In March 1996, the carmaker's ROS reached 3.4 percent. The first quarter ROS was said to be &quot;in line with the data of 1996.&quot;</p>
<p>Fiat executives, including managing director Paolo Cantarella and the heads of Fiat Auto, farm machinery maker New Holland and truck maker Iveco, also detailed profitability of the divisions in the first three months of 1997, analysts said.</p>
<p>At New Holland return on sales stood at 10.5 percent, while ROS at Fiat Auto was stable at 1.2 percent and at Iveco it fell to 0.6 percent from 4.7 percent previously.</p>
<p>Analysts said the group did not give forecasts for the year but expected that growth in volumes would have a positive impact on net and gross operating margins.</p>
<p>They said the company explained disappointing first quarter results as due in part to weak demand in the car sector in January and February, when full effects of Italian government incentives for the car market had not filtered through.</p>
<p>The first quarter also felt the effects of problems at Iveco whose margins were being squeezed.</p>
<p>For the whole year, the group aimed to improve return on investment through disinvestment on non strategic activities and cost control, analysts said.</p>
<p>In particular it intended the impact of operating costs on turnover at Fiat Auto to fall to 10 percent compared with 11.2 percent for the whole of 1996, while a fall in that ratio had been evident at Iveco since the start of this year.</p>
<p>Fiat ordinary shares were down 1.19 percent at 5655 lire by 1115 GMT, against a background of a fall of nearly one percent in the blue-chip Mib30 index of major Italian stocks.</p>
<p>--Milan bureau +392 66129507</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
