<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570675" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French election - main party economic policies.</title>
<headline>French election - main party economic policies.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are highlights of the the main parties' economic policies seeking power in France's parliamentary election on May 25 and June 1.</p>
<p>The ruling centre-right coalition parties, RPR and UDF, have a joint manifesto. The Socialist and Communist parties have an electoral pact but not a joint manifesto.</p>
<p>RPR/UDF:</p>
<p>- France to join single European currency on time on January 1, 1999.</p>
<p>- The RPR/UDF government has pledged to take whatever steps needed to bring the public deficit to three percent of gross domestic product this year to meet Maastricht treaty criteria</p>
<p>- Future rises in public spending will be limited to no more than the increase in inflation and deficits will continue to be reduced in coming years.</p>
<p>- Income tax and local business taxes will be cut, as will employers' social security and other charges to boost jobs</p>
<p>- Welfare state will be overhauled, but manifesto restates commitment to social welfare model, reimbursement of medical costs, free choice of doctors by patients</p>
<p>- Minimum unemployment benefit (RMI) to be maintained</p>
<p>- Apprenticeships and technology training for young people to be emphasised</p>
<p>- Savings plan &quot;Livret Emploi&quot; (jobs passbook) to be created to steer savings toward small businesses. Small businesses to have official paperwork cut &quot;by two-thirds&quot;</p>
<p>- Trade unions and business will be urged to negotiate on reducing working hours to spur job creation, though there is no commitment to maintaining same pay for fewer hours</p>
<p>- Age limit for receiving family allowances to be raised</p>
<p>- &quot;Consolidation of retirement system&quot; to be continued, the manifesto says. The government has passed a law introducing private pension funds to complement existing universal pensions</p>
<p>- The government has also pledged to press ahead with privatisations, including partial sale of France Telecom</p>
<p>SOCIALIST PARTY:</p>
<p>- European monetary union supported, but with conditions. Italy and Spain should be in at the start, EMU entry criteria should be read in terms of the trend, euro must not be overvalued, there must be a European economic government and euro zone countries should be bound by solidarity and growth pact, rather than an &quot;austerity pact&quot;. Party officials say Socialists want to review the EU's budget &quot;stability pact&quot;</p>
<p>- Socialist leader Lionel Jospin says opposes a new round of austerity in order to meet Maastricht criteria, wants negotiations on a political solution with Germany</p>
<p>- 700,000 jobs to be created, half of them in the public sector, financed without raising spending. Money to come from scrapping of existing subsidies job schemes</p>
<p>- working week to be cut gradually to 35 hours from 39 without loss of salary</p>
<p>- budget for research to be raised to 2.5 percent of GDP</p>
<p>- entrepreneurs, small businesses to be helped by developing tax system favourable to risk investment for young companies and simplifying administrative procedures</p>
<p>- payroll charges to be cut, cost shifted onto enlarged CSG levy, VAT on basic goods to be lowered, housing tax burden on lower income groups to be eased, wealth tax raised</p>
<p>- reform welfare system, via control of health spending in negotiated way and free care for low income households</p>
<p>- existing pensions system to be bolstered. Jospin has pledged to repeal the law introducing private pension funds</p>
<p>- education to be the top budget priority</p>
<p>- French public service model to be preserved. Security, education, transport, health, post and telecoms are services which must be guaranteed to all French people.</p>
<p>Party spokesman Francois Hollande has said state would keep 100 percent of France Telecom, though the party does not rule out opening up capital of some companies</p>
<p>- environmentally, public transport to be priority, tax on fuels to be adjusted to fit pollution criteria, moratorium on nuclear plant construction, closure of &quot;superphoenix&quot; fast- breeder reactor, Rhine-Rhone-Saone canal project to be scrapped</p>
<p>- administrative checks on company layoffs to be reestablished</p>
<p>COMMUNIST PARTY:</p>
<p>Party leader Robert Hue outlined main policy points in speech on April 25:</p>
<p>- opposes European single currency project, believes January 1, 1999 launch date cannot be met and wants referendum on issue. wants renegotiation of EMU, other forms of monetary cooperation</p>
<p>- wants to create 1.5 million jobs in two years, cut working week to 35 hours without salary loss, retirement at 60 but at 55 for women and people in tough jobs</p>
<p>scrap &quot;Juppe reforms&quot;, 14.6 percent social charge on company financial revenues and speculation earnings to raise 192 billion francs</p>
<p>- cut in VAT and fuel excise duties as well as in income tax on low incomes plus reduction in relief for capital income as well as reform of local business tax to generate 100 billion in extra revenue</p>
<p>- emergency plan against poverty and exclusion, funded by quadrupling of wealth tax, which says would bring in 30 billion francs</p>
<p>- raise minimum wage by 1,000 francs a month and later by 1,500 for all salaries below 15,000 francs a month and raise minimum unemployment benefit (RMI). (minimum wage at present is 37.91 francs per hour).</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
