<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570785" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britain racing to make up lost time in Europe.</title>
<headline>Britain racing to make up lost time in Europe.</headline>
<byline>David Ljunggren</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The new Labour government is racing to make up for lost time in Europe by adopting a much more conciliatory tone but it will be some time before Britain gains the influence it is seeking, analysts and diplomats said.</p>
<p>Labour, determined to end the festering antagonism which marred relations with the European Union during the last years of Conservative rule, has already unveiled a raft of measures designed to show the bad old days are gone.</p>
<p>And new Foreign Secretary Robin Cook hardly bothered to rearrange the pens on his desk before he shot off on Wednesday for a one-day visit to France and Germany, two European powerhouses which had long given up on the Conservatives.</p>
<p>Cook said Britain intended to play a leading role in Europe and wanted to work with its partners to reform the 15-nation bloc at a crucial EU summit in Amsterdam next month.</p>
<p>But German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel adopted a cooler tone, dismissing suggestions Britain could immediately join the dominant well-established Franco-German partnership which is the driving force behind the European Union.</p>
<p>&quot;Inside the EU, the French and Germans feel happier about working in a tandem. They have been used to having the other big European country against them,&quot; said a political analyst at one major Western embassy.</p>
<p>Experts said that although Paris and Bonn would be delighted by the new noises from London, they would require firm evidence of Britain's new intentions.</p>
<p>&quot;You need more than a positive tone. Being at the heart of Europe implies certain behaviour and actions. We shall see,&quot; a senior official at the EU's executive commission told the Financial Times newspaper.</p>
<p>And this could cause problems, since Labour's line on major EU issues does not differ much from that of the Conservatives.</p>
<p>The new government intends to wait and see on whether to join a single currency, has refused to sign an agreement on dropping border controls and wants to overhaul the way the EU controls its fishing industry.</p>
<p>&quot;There isn't a lot of change when you really get down to fundamentals, even on Europe and the need to cooperate,&quot; said Colonel Terence Taylor, deputy director of the International Institute for Strategic Studies think-tank.</p>
<p>Taylor said Labour still stood a good chance of defusing some of the tensions stoked up by the Conservatives.</p>
<p>&quot;This can be achieved with change of style which was not achieved by previous administration,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Sir Timothy Garden, director of the Royal Institute of International Affairs, said Labour was unlikely to take any radical steps in the near future.</p>
<p>&quot;I would have thought we'd see a more constructive engagement in Europe with some changes in approach to issues which are not directly counter to national interests,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Labour also has to deal with a protracted row over a damaging EU ban on beef exports imposed last year after fears that mad cow disease could spread to humans.</p>
<p>&quot;The great question is what happens later this month in Amsterdam. They can duck some things, but they will have to start looking at hard decisions. Fishing could be a problem and beef certainly will be,&quot; said the diplomat.</p>
<p>&quot;The question is not: Are Labour going to get what they want?' It is: Are they going to give?'&quot;</p>
<p>Labour's new tone on Europe was reflected in Wednesday's appointment of British Petroleum chairman Sir David Simon -- a strong supporter of a single European currency -- as minister for trade and competitiveness in Europe.</p>
<p>And Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown took a major step on Tuesday towards fulfilling requirements laid down for a single European currency by giving the Bank of England freedom to set interest rates.</p>
<p>But European partners will still want to see more evidence that a Labour administration can make a difference.</p>
<p>&quot;Labour can't surprise anyone tomorrow, but perhaps they can surprise in six months' time. They need to do a good job of selling their arguments in Europe,&quot; said the diplomat.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
