<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570799" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: BHP says money not the point of share issue.</title>
<headline>BHP says money not the point of share issue.</headline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's The Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (BHP) said on Thursday its plan to make a non-renounceable rights issue was part of a shareholder scheme and was not a capital-raising effort.</p>
<p>BHP spokesman Michael Spencer said immediately after the plan was announced to the Australian Stock Exchange earlier that BHP did not know how much the issue would raise.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not a capital-raising,&quot; Spencer told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not possible to estimate how many people will take up the scheme,&quot; he said, adding that A$636 million would be raised if every shareholder took up their entitlement.  </p>
<p>BHP said the number of shares to be issued was not expected to exceed 36.5 million.</p>
<p>BHP told the exchange the purpose of the issue of ordinary shares was to provide eligible shareholders with the opportunity to buy additional small parcels of shares up to a maximum value of A$2,400 per shareholder.</p>
<p>The new shares would rank equally for dividends.</p>
<p>The issue price would be determined over the period May 12 to May 16 inclusive, at a 2.5 percent discount to the weighted average price of shares sold on the market.  </p>
<p>The issue follows BHP's decision last year to halve the company's dividend reinvestment and bonus share schemes.</p>
<p>The issue is similar to those offered by other companies to their shareholders, BHP's Spencer said.</p>
<p>&quot;Interest in these sorts of schemes has been expressed at annual general meetings over a period of time and a number of other companies have them,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Melbourne bureau 613-9286-1421</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
