<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570769" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Gilts to retrace gains, support at 112-16.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Gilts to retrace gains, support at 112-16.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>June gilt futures on Thursday are likely to continue to retrace their recent sharp gains, with a soft Bund market contributing to the weak tone, analysts said.</p>
<p>Chartists see a number of support points below 113-00, including the 112-25,26 area and the 112-16 zone. The main upmove -- more than two and a half points on Tuesday -- has left the market overbought, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;After the surge in gilts Tuesday the market is having a breather,&quot; said an analyst at a European bank in London. &quot;112-16 and Tuesday's breakout point at 111-04,06 are two supports to note.&quot;  </p>
<p>June gilts on LIFFE at 0724 GMT were at 112-30, down 11/32 from the prior close.</p>
<p>Lynn Brannigan, technical analyst at MCM Yieldwatch, said he saw the chance of a bigger pullback.</p>
<p>&quot;I see a greater retracement, essentially down to 112-03, which is the 62 percent of the rally from 111-02 to 113-24.&quot;</p>
<p>He pegged the initial retracement level at 112-25, 38 percent of the 111-02 to 113-24 upmove on Tuesday.</p>
<p>He said the move lower would unwind daily technicals which he saw as overextended, but said gilts still had scope to test higher.  </p>
<p>The 112-16 area noted by the European bank analyst was where the market found good support on February 12 and February 24.</p>
<p>An overnight four-pfennig slide in the pound -- following a news agency report quoting an unnamed Labour party source saying sterling should rejoin Europe's Exchange Rate Mechanism (ERM) in 2001 at a rate of 2.50 marks -- was also weighing on gilts.</p>
<p>The short sterling strip showed modest losses, down one basis point at 93.41 for June, down two basis points at 93.17 for September and down three at 93.98 for December contracts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
