<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570739" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS - Mr Yen knocks dlr, stg rallies on ERM denial.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Mr Yen knocks dlr, stg rallies on ERM denial.</headline>
<byline>Ron Askew</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar slid  against the yen on Thursday as comments from Japan's &quot;Mr Yen&quot; stirred fears of central bank intervention.</p>
<p>And a sterling rally was helped when reports it was to rejoin the EU's Exchange Rate Mechanism (ERM) at 2.50 marks were officially denied. Sterling was trading Thursday morning at about 2.78 marks.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, London shares opened lower after Wall Street tumbled overnight, though trade was light as London was he only key financial centre in Europe not closed for the Ascension Day holiday.</p>
<p>Influential Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara -- Mr Yen to the markets -- undermined the dollar's value against the yen when he said the past year's movements raised the chance the Japanese currency could strengthen, possibly to 103 per dollar.</p>
<p>The U.S. unit slipped a yen in value from around 124.70 yen just before the remarks to a low of 123.70.</p>
<p>&quot;People are on tenterhooks about whether we actually see any intervention,&quot; said Nigel Richardson, economist at Yamaichi. &quot;People are aware there's a chance of some kind of intervention if they're really serious about (yen weakness).&quot;</p>
<p>On Wednesday intervention fears had gripped the market and shaken the dollar after a Japanese wire report that the G3 nations -- Japan, the United States and Germany -- were studying the possibility of concerted selling of dollars for yen.</p>
<p>&quot;The fear of intervention is clearly rising, but the success of the mere threat to intervene is probably enough to keep the G3 from actually executing intervention for now,&quot; said Klaus Baader, international economist at Deutsche Morgan Grenfell.</p>
<p>Although Germany -- keen to boost exports and spur economic growth -- is thought less troubled then Japan by the dollar's current levels, the Sakakibara shock waves rippled through dollar/mark too. It fell to a 1.7097 marks low from late Wednesday's 1.7210, though was back at 1.7130 by 0900 GMT.</p>
<p>Analysts said the interest rate scenario was also working in the yen's favour, as speculation grew of Japanese tightening. In the United States, by contrast, yesterday's Beige Book release gave no indication the Fed would have to raise rates fast, they said.</p>
<p>In its latest Beige Book on business conditions, the Federal Reserve said the U.S. economy expanded moderately over the last two months while wages and retail prices were generally subdued.</p>
<p>Fed policymakers will use the findings when they meet on May 20 to consider whether to tighten credit, after raising rates at their last meeting in March for the first time in more than two years.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, the British Treasury moved quickly to dampen speculation that Britain planned to rejoin the EU's Exchange Rate Mechanism (ERM) at a central rate of 2.50 marks in 2001.</p>
<p>Responding to an overnight news wire report, which quoted a Labour Party source as saying sterling should rejoin the ERM at 2.50 marks, a Treasury spokeswoman said: &quot;There is no truth in it at all.&quot;</p>
<p>The pound lost around four pfennigs overnight on the report carried by Bridge news agency although it has since recouped around half a pfennig.</p>
<p>Earlier, Goldman Sachs chief economist Gavyn Davies said that such rumours were inevitable given the new Labour government's more pro-European stance.</p>
<p>Sterling left the ERM in September 1992, after the government found it impossible to keep the currency near the then 2.95 central rate. The system was designed as a pre-cursor to a single European currency.</p>
<p>London shares opened lower, back-tracking from Wednesday's record close and unsettled by the latest sharp fall on Wall Street.</p>
<p>The FTSE 100 index was down 17.0 points at 4,520.5 in early business but had rallied to stand almost unchanged by 0900 GMT.</p>
<p>Dealers said the market was due a consolidation after this week's record-breaking advance but said the market's undertone was still firm.</p>
<p>After being down some 55 points as London closed on Wednesday, the Dow ended 139.67 points down at 7,085.65, depressed by a sharp fall in Treasury bonds after weak demand in the latest auction and a report showing rising labour costs.</p>
<p>STOCK PRICES AT 0900 GMT</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 was down 0.4 of a point at 4,537.1 .</p>
<p>The Paris CAC-40 index was closed for Ascension Day. It ended down 8.62 points at 2,643.31 on Wednesday</p>
<p>Frankfurt's DAX index closed for Ascension day. It ended down 16.30 points at 3,551.98 on Wednesday</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 0900 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar stood at 1.7130 marks compared with 1.7210 late in Europe on Wednesday. It was at 123.82 yen compared with 124.93.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold was at $342.60 in early Europe after closing at $340.85 an ounce in London on Wednesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
