<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570713" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Next French government faces stark Thomson choice.</title>
<headline>Next French government faces stark Thomson choice.</headline>
<byline>Marcel Michelson</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The next French government faces a stark choice about the sale of a controlling stake in defence electronics group Thomson-CSF for which two final bids were made on Wednesday.</p>
<p>On the one hand it has an offer by electric engineering group Alcatel-Alsthom and privately-owned Dassault Industries which would make Thomson-CSF the key French defence contractor with a possible link to aerospace group Aerospatiale as well.</p>
<p>Already valued at 23 billion francs ($4 billion), Thomson-CSF would regroup the other companies' defence activities and become the main European defence group by sheer size. It would have a strong card to play in a European restructuring.</p>
<p>On the other hand the government has an offer by Lagardere Groupe, which was the preferred bidder in a previous sale attempt. It has the support of British Aerospace Plc and Germany's Daimler Aerospace but would not leave Thomson-CSF intact.</p>
<p>Under the Lagardere plan, British Aerospace would get indirect control over Thomson's missiles businesses through the Matra BAe Dynamics (MBD) joint venture with Lagardere's Matra Defense Espace unit.</p>
<p>Britain's GEC Plc has signed memoranda of understanding with both bidders after it was barred by the government from making its own bid because of national security interests.</p>
<p>Financial analysts have said Lagardere's alliances could help it win over Alcatel.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Jean Arthuis said on Wednesday evening that the government still planned to announce a decision before June 30, but the bids would be locked up until after the two-round parliamentary election of May 25 and June 1 which puts the future of French defence in the hands of the voters.</p>
<p>The opposition Socialist Party has made it clear that it would not continue with the privatisation of Thomson-CSF.</p>
<p>While they too will be faced with the need to restructure the defence industry because of falling orders and strong concentration in the U.S. industry, a Socialist government is more likely to take an active part in a restructuring involving state groups Thomson-CSF, Aerospatiale and perhaps arms maker GIAT.</p>
<p>Aerospatiale is currently in merger talks with combat-plane maker Dassault Aviation and is also involved in the restructuring of the Airbus plane-making consortium.</p>
<p>If the current centre-right coalition would win, and opinion polls give it a narrow lead over a combination of the Socialist and Communist parties, the decision is not straightforward.</p>
<p>The government of Alain Juppe last year prefered a bid by Lagardere over one of Alcatel because it found the first bid to have a better industrial logic.</p>
<p>It had to suspend the decision on the sale of Thomson SA -- which included both the Thomson-CSF stake and consumer electronics group Thomson Multimedia (TMM) -- after a public outcry and a negative Privatisation Commission advice about the sale by Lagardere of TMM to Daewoo Electronics of South Korea for a symbolic franc.</p>
<p>If Juppe were to stay Prime Minister after the election, the government will have to act upon the instruction of President Jacques Chirac who has said he wanted a strong French defence industry to play a leading role in a European restructuring -- which leaves both options open.</p>
<p>If Juppe's government were to be replaced with a new team to underline the President's commitment to a new start after the snap parliamentary, election the decision could swing either way.</p>
<p>With Philippe Seguin, current speaker of parliament, as Prime Minister there could be a bigger stress on the French interests and he could prefer the Alcatel bid. Alcatel has said it would negotiate with GEC and Dasa in a second stage.</p>
<p>If a free-marketeer such as Alain Madelin got a say in the decision there could be a preference for the more encompasing Lagardere deal which is strongly market-oriented.</p>
<p>And if former Prime Minister Edouard Balladur were to return to office, his preference would be somewhere between Seguin and Madelin and neither Alcatel nor Lagardere is an obvious winner. ($ = 5.790 French Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640026">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
