<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570733" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Gold likely to remain under pressure.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Gold likely to remain under pressure.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>--------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p> SPOT     NY CLOSE  * SUPPORT * RESIST * RSI14 *   MA10 *   MA30</p>
<p> GOLD   341.20/1.70 *  338.50 * 345.00 *    46 * 340.49 * 344.29</p>
<p> SILVER   4.74/4.76 *    4.70 *   4.85 *    46 *   4.70 *   4.78</p>
<p> PLAT   372.05/23.05*  370.00 * 380.00 *    49 * 373.17 * 370.86</p>
<p>-----------------VIEWS FROM THE MARKET - May 8----------------</p>
<p>Gold prices were expected to remain under pressure after failing to make a concerted show on the upside this week, analysts said.</p>
<p>However, with most of Europe closed for Ascension Day, only light business was forecast, at least until New York opens.  </p>
<p>GOLD</p>
<p>Rallies earlier this week were turned back as speculators took the chance to cover shorts on the initial dip but use the area over $343.00 per ounce to take profits and increase existing short positions.</p>
<p>&quot;This is still a market in which to use any rally as a profit opportunity,&quot; a technical analyst said.</p>
<p>Gold was under mild pressure on Wednesday following its upside failures at the beginning of the week, and news construed as bearish did not help sentiment either.</p>
<p>Dealers said some central banks had sold small tonnages of gold recently. &quot;They are not much, up to five to 10 tonnes. They are not big sales,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>The authoritative Gold Fields Mineral Services Ltd (GFMS) in its Gold 1997 publication released on Wednesday hinted that conditions in the market were remarkably similar now to those prevailing immediately before the 1993 second quarter bull market.</p>
<p>However, that was largely dismissed in favour of more detailed comments in the book which said the market was understandably concerned about the possibility of central bank gold sales and that the risk would not diminish as European Monetary Union approached.</p>
<p>Also causing concern was fresh comment elsewhere about the sale of gold for relatives of Holocaust victims, albeit that the tonnages would be small.</p>
<p>Resistance remains in place at $343.50, with several dealers and analysts also expecting sell orders from producers to be triggered above that level as well.</p>
<p>Support a $338.50 has not been fully tested yet.</p>
<p>At 0730 GMT gold was indicated at $342.20/$342.60 compared to a London close of $340.60/$341.10.  </p>
<p>SILVER</p>
<p>Interest in silver has noticeably diminished over the past week after the market failed to make anything of a reasonably interesting technical position following a bounce last week, analysts said.</p>
<p>A week ago silver was balanced between probing lower to take stops out or pushing on for a test of resistance.</p>
<p>In the event nothing happened, although analysts said technically the background remained positive.</p>
<p>It disappointed on Wednesday, but in its daily comment brokers Rudolf Wolff commented, &quot;We continue to favour upside strength considering last week's bounce.&quot;</p>
<p>On the Comex July chart, Wolff placed resistance at $4.817 -- the previous resistance line from the last monthly descending triangle -- which has to be overcome before there can be a confident assault on the initial reversal resistance at $4.915.</p>
<p>At 0730 GMT silver was indicated at $4.76/$4.78, up three cents from Wednesday's London close.</p>
<p>PLATINUM</p>
<p>A report on Wednesday from Moscow that talks with Japan would begin soon to end a five-month blockade of PGM shipments from Russia had only a brief price impact.</p>
<p>The price looked comfortable between $371 and $378 pending definitive news from Russia, analysts said.</p>
<p>A consideration has to be the potential for volatility created by tightness in the market, especially palladium.</p>
<p>The backwardation has stretched palladium lease rates to about 17 percent for one-two months, dealers said.</p>
<p>At 0730 GMT platinum was indicated at $375.00/$376.00 compared with Wednesday's close of $371.75/$372.75.</p>
<p>--Brian Spoors, London Newsroom +44 171 542 8058</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
