<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570794" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: NZ bonds end with soft tone after promising start.</title>
<headline>NZ bonds end with soft tone after promising start.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>----------------------(Snapshot at close)-----------------------</p>
<p>Figures in brackets compare against previous day's close</p>
<p>FUTURES					  PHYSICAL YIELD (PCT)</p>
<p>90-DAY BILLS (JUN) 92.82 (PREV 92.86)  90-DAYS  6.85 (PREV 6.89) 3-YR BONDS   (JUN) 92.45 (PREV 92.45)  02/00    7.43 (PREV 7.42)</p>
<p>10-YR BONDS  (JUN) 92.28 (PREV 92.29)  11/06    7.71 (PREV 7.67)</p>
<p>OVERNIGHT CASH 6.05 PCT   (PREV 6.00)  US 5-YR  6.64 (PREV 6.55)</p>
<p>NZD/USD    0.6845/55 (PREV 0.6834/41)  US 10-YR 6.76 (PREV 6.67)</p>
<p>TWI		    67.87 (PREV 67.95)  US 30-YR 6.96 (PREV 6.90)</p>
<p>----------------------------(May 8)-----------------------------</p>
<p>* NZ yields finish slightly weaker after quiet day</p>
<p>* Short end manages a small rally</p>
<p>* Mkt consensus remains for easier RBNZ stance in June</p>
<p>New Zealand yields gave up their small early gains to finish with a soft tone on Thursday, after what dealers said had been a quiet session.</p>
<p>The mid bonds, initially boosted by local buying interest and a NZ$100 million five-year eurobond issued by Sweden overnight, ended a basis point higher in yield at 7.43 percent.</p>
<p>The 11/06 maturity ended three basis points higher in yield at 7.70 percent after a promising start in which it virtually ignored selling in U.S. Treasuries.  </p>
<p>Weakness in shorter dated Australian debt had not helped sentiment. That market weakened as Reserve Bank of Australia governor Ian Macfarlane ruled out a policy easing and warned about wages growth.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is a little reluctant to buy actually. It looks like it might just drift off in the next day or two, particularly the long end -- that's starting to get a little nervous about what might happen in the States, and I think that's probably wise,&quot; one dealer said.  </p>
<p>The U.S. Federal Reserve next meets on May 20 and analysts say the market seems divided over the prospects of a hike in official interests rates.</p>
<p>New Zealand short rates managed to finish a touch stronger, with the physical 90-day bank bills down four basis points to 6.85 percent and the front futures contract up one to 92.87.</p>
<p>The currency's Trade-Weighted Index ended eight basis points lower at 67.87.  </p>
<p>Dealers said Reserve Bank of New Zealand governor Don Brash had put the brakes on the market's recent easing bias by telling a parliamentary committee on Wednesday that at this stage, the bank's assumptions for monetary conditions remained unchanged.</p>
<p>Brash was seen monitoring economic data until the bank's June monetary policy statement, but the market consensus still favoured an easier stance in that statement.</p>
<p>-- Catherine McCaw, Wellington newsroom (64 4) 471 4275</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
