<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570796" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Short Australian debt weighed down by hawkish RBA.</title>
<headline>Short Australian debt weighed down by hawkish RBA.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>----------(Snapshot at 12.00 P.M./0200 GMT)-----------------</p>
<p>FUTURES					  CASH YIELD</p>
<p>90-DAY BILLS  (JUN) 93.98  (- 0.06)    6.03    (UNCH)</p>
<p>3-YR T-BONDS  (JUN) 93.03  (- 0.09)    6.92    (+ 0.08)</p>
<p>10-YR T-BONDS (JUN) 92.155 (-0.025)    7.82    (+ 0.02)</p>
<p>AUD/USD  0.7790 (PREV 0.7756) US 30-YR  6.96   (6.96 NY)</p>
<p>---------------------(May 8)--------------------------------</p>
<p>*Short-dated Australian bond and bill futures were weak going into the lunchtime recess after RBA governor Macfarlane ruled out a policy easing and warned about wages growth.</p>
<p>*April labour force report much in line with expectations.  </p>
<p>Short-dated Australian bond and bill futures were weak going into the lunchtime recess after Reserve Bank governor Ian Macfarlane ruled out a policy easing and warned about wages growth.</p>
<p>Testifying to a parliamentary finance committee Macfarlane said there would be no economic gain from another cut in official interest rates given that the central bank's revised expectations for growth to four percent for calender 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;They are happy with the level of interest rates where they are. They see them as conducive to economic recovery,&quot; said David de Garis, treasury economist at ANZ banking group.  </p>
<p>June bill futures eased to around 93.98, equating to a cash rate of 6.02 percent and just above current 6.0 percent official interest rates.</p>
<p>Falls were heavier among further forward bill contracts with the December position dropping to a low of 93.53 percent at one stage and virtually pricing in a 50 basis point tightening by the end of the year.</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank also said that recent wages data, which showed annual growth at 4.6 percent, was uncomfortably high and any further acceleration would threaten inflation and need a policy response.  </p>
<p>&quot;Unless wage growth abates, forget a rate cut,&quot; said Hans Kunnen, chief economist at Colonial State Bank. &quot;They are of the view that previous rate cuts will stimulate activity and they are not going to cut again unless wages growth comes back within their comfort zone.&quot;</p>
<p>The April labour force report was also released, while Macfarlane was testifying, which saw employment rise 37,100, roughly in line with median expectations, while the unemployment rate stayed at 8.7 percent as forecast.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said he was relieved to see the employment rise, and saw considerably lower jobless if the expansion continues.  </p>
<p>----------------------(SPREADS)---------------------------------  AUD VS   3-YR	   10-YR	* AUD 3-YR/10-YR SPREAD</p>
<p> USD	 41 (+ 01)   106 (- 06) * FUTURES    88   (- 05)</p>
<p> CAD	159 (- 08)   118 (- 09) * CASH	 91   (- 05)</p>
<p> NZD	-53 (+ 09)   +11 (+ 02) *</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>The local market gave up some ground on its yield differential to the dollar bloc during the morning.</p>
<p>U.S. and Canadian debt weakened on Wednesday amid poor responses to their respective 10-year note sales.</p>
<p>The local yield curve continued to flatten sharply.  </p>
<p>------------------------(TECHNICALS)------------------------- FUTURES	*SUP/RES     *SUP/RES 2ND *RSI    *MA-10 *MA-20</p>
<p>10-YEAR (JUN)*92.14-92.18 *92.08-92.28 *53 PCT *92.12 *92.11 3-YEAR  (JUN)*93.03-93.06 *92.95-93.12 *49 PCT *93.11 *93.11 90-DAY  (JUN)*93.97-94.01 *93.92-94.08 *47 PCT *94.04 *94.03 -------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>-- Colin Brinsden 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
