<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570735" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - British Business - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - British Business - May 8.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by  The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>DAILY TELEGRAPH</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>TOYOTA TO INCREASE INVESTMENT IN UK</p>
<p>Toyota have announced more investment in Britain, spending 60 million stg to double engine production. The group also suggested that it may build a second manufacturing plant in Europe, probably the continent. Hiroshi Okuda, president of Toyota, insisted that a more pro-European Labour government had not influenced his decision. The committment to spend more in Britain has been welcomed by trade and industry secretary Margaret Beckett.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>FELIX CHIEF QUITS AFTER DALGETY TAKES DIVE</p>
<p>Felix catfood group Dalgety has said it plans to cut its dividend by a third due to production mistakes and poor trading. Chief executive of the petfood division, Nigel Garrow, resigned with immediate effect. Dalgety is now set to begin a second restructuring programme since the 440 million stg acquisition of Quaker's petfood business in 1995. Garrow could received compensation of up to 360,000 stg.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>WHITBREAD MIXES 400 MILLION STG EXPANSION COCKTAIL</p>
<p>Brewing, pubs and leisure group Whitbread has announced it will create 5,000 jobs this year with a capital expenditure programme of 400 million stg a year. 250 outlets with the managed pub division will be created, which accounts for half the spending. The other half will be divided among Whitbread's restaurant and leisure formats. Soon-to-be chief executive David Thomas says he plans to make Travel Inn the biggest budget hotel in Britain.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE TIMES</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>SAINSBURY TO START OFFERING MORTGAGES</p>
<p>J Sainsbury is to begin offering its own mortgages and personal loans to its customers from this summer. Chief executive Dino Adriano revealed the plan as he announced that pre-tax profits in the year to March 8 had fallen 15 per cent to 651 million stg. The group was the first supermarket to launch its own bank, which cost 6.3 million stg. Adriano admitted that the bank is expected to lose a further 15 million stg this year.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>ICI PLANNING SELL-OFFS TO FUND FIVE BILLION STG UNILEVER DEAL</p>
<p>Chemicals group ICI has begun a three-year three billion stg disposal programme to finance the five billion stg acquisition of Unilever's specialty chemicals business. Chairman of ICI, Ronald Hampel, said the deal creates a new ICI for the new century. Chief executive Charles Miller Smith masterminded the acquisition, saying the deal broadened the scope of ICI's global business.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>SUTHERLAND TO SUCCEED SIMON AS BP CHAIRMAN</p>
<p>Former Director-General of Gatt, Peter Sutherland, is set to succeed Sir David Simon as the chairman of British Petroleum. The appointment was made on an interim basis after Simon's resignation to become competition minister in the new Labour Government. Sutherland will take the post on an interim basis. He has been a deputy chairman of BP since 1995 and is also chairman of Goldman Sachs.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE GUARDIAN</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BIG GUNS LINE UP IN BATTLE FOR DEFENCE FIRM</p>
<p>British Aerospace has said it will provide 300 million stg worth of backing for Lagardere in its efforts to buy the French government's 58 per cent stake in Thomson CSF, the French defence electronics group. Another company which has given unconditional backing for the offer is Germany's Deutsche Aerospace, part of Daimler-Benz. The outcome of the fight will be crucial to the restructuring of Europe's defense and space industries.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>ROYAL BANK HOPES TO PICK UP BIG PROFIT AT TESCO</p>
<p>According to Royal Bank of Scotland executives, supermarket- based financial services are set to reap huge profits for high street banks. RBS has also announced record half-year profits of 369 million stg. RBS will launch a bank will Tesco and will announce details of a credit card in July. George Mathewson, chief executive, said he expects the venture to contribute a substantial proportion of RBS's annual profits.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>POWERGEN PLANS 150 MILLION STG SURGE INTO FUTURE</p>
<p>PowerGen, the electricity generator, is to set up a 150 million stg power station which is capable of developing world- beating technology. The venture is shared equally with Siemens, the engineering group. Meanwhile, National Power, PowerGen's largest rival, is planning to invest 180 million stg in China over three years, conducted through a venture with Hong Kong- based Power Pacific.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>THE INDEPENDENT</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BUOYANT STERLING ERODES INDUSTRY GROWTH</p>
<p>Official figures suggest that the strong pound is gradually eroding growth in manufacturing, with manufacturing output falling unexpectedly in March and declining in all sectors expect engineering. Figures for car sales show that the consumer spending spree continues, highlighting the contrast between the strength of home demand and weakness on the export front. Economists are split between those who call for an increase in interest rates and those who do not.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BSKYB UNVEILS BT INTERACTIVE TV LINK-UP</p>
<p>BSkyB and British Telecom have unveiled a partnership to create a 265 million stg company to subsidise the introduction of electronic set-top box technology. The new company will be called British Interactive Broadcasting and BT said they are interested in floating it if its plan to create the dominant platform for digital pay-TV catches the public imagination. BIB will not be able to offer a service until next spring.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>BG  IN RENEWED EFFORT TO DELAY GAS COMPETITION</p>
<p>BG, formally British Gas, is set to lobby the Government in an effort to delay the next stage of domestic competition. The issue had been put to John Battle, the new energy minister, before the general election. This comes after BG failed to persuade gas industry regulator, Clare Spottiswoode, to drop her plans to bring forward domestic competition. Spottiswoode hopes for national competition to begin in full next April.</p>
<p>--BMC +44-171-377-1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
