<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570723" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: PROTEST PILOT LANDS AT WRONG CYPRUS AIRPORT.</title>
<headline>PROTEST PILOT LANDS AT WRONG CYPRUS AIRPORT.</headline>
<byline>Michele Kambas</byline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>New finance for Cyprus Airways is in jeopardy because a pilot refused to work 10 minutes overtime and landed at the wrong airport.    The Cypriot</p>
<p>government on Wednesday threatened to withhold support for a loan sought by the cash-strapped national carrier.    &quot;This was</p>
<p>foolish, irresponsible and arrogant behaviour which in the final analysis undermines the company itself and undermines the Cypriot economy,&quot; finance minister Christodoulos Christodoulou told reporters.</p>
<p>Pilots union PASIPI is enforcing work-to-rule measures to protest the transfer of some work from Cyprus Airways to Eurocypria, its charter subsidiary.</p>
<p>On Monday a flight carrying 153 passengers landed in the western resort of Paphos instead of Larnaca on the southern coast, after a technical hitch delayed departure from Zurich for two hours.</p>
<p>According to the airline, the plane would have needed five to six minutes to fly the 150 km between Paphos and Larnaca. Instead, buses and taxis were used to ferry the passengers to a resort at the other end of the island, while the pilot spent the night in a luxury hotel.</p>
<p>Finance minister Christodoulou issued a stern warning for unions to clean up their act.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been an application from Cyprus Airways for a new loan guaranteed by the government of tens of millions of pounds. It will not be handled favourably if this will continue to be the behaviour of those guiding employees in Cyprus Airways,&quot; he warned.</p>
<p>Airline officials could not immediately disclose details of the loan sought.</p>
<p>The incident comes against a backdrop of dismal 1996 financial results, growing calls for the deregulation of flights to the holiday island and high hopes that tourism will improve in 1997 after a drop in arrivals of five percent in 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;This is unacceptable. It is not just the economic damage, which comes to several thousand pounds. It is the damage to the image of the airline,&quot; Cyprus Airways spokesman Tassos Angeli said.</p>
<p>Monday's incident is just the latest in a long string of labour disputes plaguing the national carrier which is 80-percent state owned. Twenty percent is traded on the Cyprus stock exchange.</p>
<p>Last month caterers banned from watching television by management caused a 45 minute delay to an outbound Gulf Air flight.</p>
<p>They went on strike for an hour when they found their TV set had gone missing.</p>
<p>Last week the Cyprus Airways group announced a preliminary consolidated pre-tax loss of 2.15 million pounds (4.2 million) in 1996, compared to a pre-tax profit of 5.03 million pounds in 1995. The company has blamed falling load factors and increased fuel prices for the decline.</p>
<p>The share price has fallen from a high of 1.22 pounds in February 1996 to close at 27.25 cents on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Senior airline officials have pledged to start a restructuring programme to boost productivity.  (=0.50 pounds) -- Nicosia newsroom 357 2 365089</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
