<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570736" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Researchers &quot;build&quot; vaccine against colon cancer.</title>
<headline>Researchers &quot;build&quot; vaccine against colon cancer.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. researchers said on Wednesday they had synthesised a molecule that could act as a vaccine against colon cancer.</p>
<p>Prashant Deshpande and Samuel Danishefsky of the Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research in New York, writing in the science journal Nature, said their findings might be a short cut to developing cancer vaccines.</p>
<p>Vaccines usually use a weakened or partial version of the infectious agent to prime the body's immune system against the real thing. With cancer -- where a vaccine would be used to fight existing disease rather than prevent it -- this approach does not work.</p>
<p>Instead, researchers are trying to find which chemicals on the surface of a tumour will activate the immune system.</p>
<p>Deshpande's group said they knew of one such chemical, known as an antigen, isolated from the surface of a colon cancer tumour by other researchers.</p>
<p>But the antigen, named KH-1, is hard to produce in amounts large enough to make a vaccine.</p>
<p>Deshpande said his team had developed a way of building an artificial version of KH-1 piece by piece from its molecular components and using the natural antigen as a blueprint.</p>
<p>&quot;Our lab has developed a methodology where we can use glycols -- a form of sugar -- as a starting material,&quot; he said in a telephone interview. &quot;We build it up bit by bit...in a very concise and systematic fashion.&quot;</p>
<p>Another team at Sloan-Kettering said they had already started tests to see if the chemical could be used as a vaccine.</p>
<p>&quot;I took his compound and linked it to a protein,&quot; said Govindaswami Ragupathi, who is working on several of Sloan-Kettering's potential cancer vaccines.</p>
<p>He explained that the artificial antigen alone was too small for the body to recognise, but the protein made it big enough.</p>
<p>&quot;Then I vaccinated five mice -- they made antibodies against this compound.&quot;</p>
<p>The next step will be to see if KH-1 can actually help shrink tumours in mice. Then it can be tested on humans, who often react very differently from rodents.</p>
<p>Ragupathi's team is also testing a potential artificial vaccine for breast cancer.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
