<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570768" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BTR skids following profits warning.</title>
<headline>BTR skids following profits warning.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in BTR Plc were indicated down 17p to 250-1/2 BY 0725 GMT, after the industrial holdings company said on Thursday that the strong pound and weak conditions in key markets, would dent sales and operating profits.</p>
<p>&quot;BTR has joined a long list of companies that has seen its bottom line suffer because of sterling's strength,&quot; one market maker said.</p>
<p>&quot;Considering a lot of their business is abroad, no one should be too surprised but the shares will take a bit of a hit today.&quot;  </p>
<p>On the basis of current exchange rates, sales are expected to reduce by around 300 million stg and operating profit by about 35 million stg compared with the first half in 1996, the company said.</p>
<p>The company also said first-half operating profits would be below last year's figure, even before currency factors, due to weakness in German and Australian markets, which account for 30 percent of its business.</p>
<p>&quot;Exchange rates have, as we expected, reduced the sterling value of sales and profits earned overseas when translated from their local currencies,&quot; BTR said in a statement ahead of its annual meeting, due to start at 1000 GMT.</p>
<p>Analysts said the downbeat trading statement had come as little surprise, however.</p>
<p>&quot;BTR has been undergoing a major restructuring which is still not complete,&quot; one analyst who wished to remain anonymous said.</p>
<p>&quot;Even without sterling, the company is still facing large problems in some of its markets and with some of it products. They are turning things around but it is a big ship to turn -- it will take time.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Dale Faulken, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
