<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570741" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Europe domestic equity fund inflows slow in March.</title>
<headline>Europe domestic equity fund inflows slow in March.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Net flows into European domestic equity mutual funds slowed in March from the highs recorded at the beginning of the year, according to a report by JP Morgan.</p>
<p>It estimated aggregate inflows into European domestic funds came in at $2.4 billion, almost half the February intake.</p>
<p>The report said international equity funds remained the clear favourite in the region, with Italy, Germany and the UK all recording strong inflows, which it said suggested further retail support for equity markets.</p>
<p>After a record intake of over one billion sterling in February, net subscriptions by UK funds to domestic equities fell to 723 million sterling. But it said this remained a strong figure at almost double the 1996 monthly average.</p>
<p>The report said UK investors showed great interest in international equities, which saw a 75 percent increase in net subscriptions to 335 million sterling -- the highest level in nine months.</p>
<p>&quot;European equity funds remained the retail investors' clear favourite but suffered net selling by institutional investors who preferred funds investing in Japanese equities,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>UK retail investors accounted for over one billion sterling, or 80 percent, of total new subscriptions to all categories in the country.</p>
<p>French domestic equity mutual funds suffered small net redemptions in March following two consecutive months of net subscriptions at the beginning of the year which had raised hopes of a turnaround in investment in French SICAVs.</p>
<p>Nevertheless the three month average returned to the black for the first time since September 1994. French bond funds also suffered net redemptions in March, and the report said President Jacques Chirac's decision to call an early election was likely to result in weak April figures too.</p>
<p>German equity fund subscriptions tailed off in February, and net subscriptions to Italian domestic equity funds slowed again in March. But JP Morgan said both countries saw continued strong interest in international equities.</p>
<p>Italian fixed income funds suffered a sharp fall in subscriptions to just over four trillion lira -- their lowest intake since April 1996.</p>
<p>Spanish inflows into pure equity funds slowed to a quarter of the February level, while fixed income funds also saw an easing in net subscriptions after two consecutive record months.</p>
<p>-- Andrew Gill, London newsroom +171 542 5887</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
