<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570758" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INTERVIEW - Kwik Save eyes stabilising sales.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW - Kwik Save eyes stabilising sales.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>British discount supermarket chain Kwik Save Group Plc has a priority of stabilising sales, which are currently falling, group marketing director Phil Smith told Reuters in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly our priority is to stablise the short-term sales position,&quot; Smith said.</p>
<p>Kwik Save said that like-for-like sales were down six percent in the first seven weeks of the second half which began on March 16, but added that an increase in underlying gross margins had continued, offsetting the effect.</p>
<p>&quot;There is an underlying decline in our customer numbers, which the New Generation programme squarely addresses,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Kwik Save announced the programme of store closures and innovations in November aimed at turning around its flagging fortunes as it was squeezed by discounters and the leading supermarket chains.</p>
<p>Smith said the company faced a challenge but added that it was addressing the issues.</p>
<p>He highlighted plans to increase own label sales, overhaul the product offer and expand ranges along with introducing pre-packaged fruit and vegetables in stores which do not have a concession for this range.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I64100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
