<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570774" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Bunds to crumple if 101.45 support goes.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Bunds to crumple if 101.45 support goes.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>June Bund futures on LIFFE were clinging onto initial support at 101.45 in early trade on Thursday but face a deeper decline if that level gives way, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The only way you'd get dragged through those lows is if the T-bonds do something untoward this afternoon,&quot; David Wood, independent technical analyst near London, said.</p>
<p>Bunds were quoted at 101.50 at 0645 GMT, down 0.26 in the session after gapping down to an open of 101.59 from Wednesday's low at 101.67. A holiday in Germany may thin trade.</p>
<p>Wood said support at 101.45 came from the May 2 low.  </p>
<p>Wood said if 101.45 did evaporate the contract would head for the 101.14 area, the top of the range from the week of April 17 before the contract shot up.</p>
<p>Analysts at Royal Bank of Scotland in London said in face of light trading volumes over the Ascension Day holiday, value areas will hold trading -- 101.70 to 101.82 above and 101.62 to 101.50 below.</p>
<p>&quot;Bunds are still favoured to dip a little lower to fill the hourly chart gap to 101.21, but the long term bull market is still intact in the channel that comes in today at 100.82 to 102.20,&quot; they said in a research note.  </p>
<p>Wood said the bottom of the gap at Wednesday's low would likely hold the upside this session.</p>
<p>September Euromarks were quoted at 96.72 at 0705 GMT, unchanged from Wednesday's pit settlement.</p>
<p>Analysts said the resistance at overhead supply at 96.74 continues to dampen trade, making it difficult for the contract to make significant headway.</p>
<p>Initial support comes in at the lows of the last few sessions at 96.72 but a retest of the supports at 96.60 was likely over the next few weeks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
