<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570706" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: United News agrees to take stake in DTN.</title>
<headline>United News agrees to take stake in DTN.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>United News &amp; Media Plc has agreed to take a 30 percent stake in DTN if that consortium wins a licence for UK digital terrestrial television (DTT) services, United said on Thursday.</p>
<p>United said the cost of the stake would be a maximum of 120 million pounds ($195 million) over a four-year period. DTN is wholly owned by NTL Inc.  </p>
<p>United News agrees to take stake in DTN =2</p>
<p>DTN has applied for three licences to operate DTT multi-channel services when they are launched in Britain next year.</p>
<p>It faces stiff competition from British Digital Broadcasting, a heavyweight consortium grouping BSkyB, Carlton and Granada. The Independent Television Commission is expected to award the licences in the next few weeks.</p>
<p>Digital terrestrial television would offer viewers at least 30 channels and is broadcast from land-based transmitters to rooftop aerials. It is seen as an attractive option for Britons who do not want to sign up for 200-channel digital satellite or cable packages.</p>
<p>United News &amp; Media already has extensive television interests through its two regional commercial stations, Anglia and Meridian, plus its stake in the recently launched Channel 5 terrestrial station.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
