<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570725" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: PRESS DIGEST - GREEK GENERAL NEWS - MAY 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - GREEK GENERAL NEWS - MAY 8.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leading stories in the Greek general press:</p>
<p>KATHIMERINI</p>
<p>--Prime Minister Costas Simitis went on the offensive yesterday in his address to his party's MPs, directing harsh comments to the 32 deputies who had written a letter expressing their reservations about the government's handling of Greek-Turkish relations. Simitis criticised the 32 for ignoring party avenues for dissent and undermining the democratic procedures existing within the party.</p>
<p>--Former president of the republic Constantine Karamanlis yesterday responded to the charges by former king Constantine that Karamanlis urged him to organise a coup, saying they were &quot;unworthy of comment&quot;.</p>
<p>--Moves by the government yesterday to placate workers at the ailing firms of Softex and Elefsis Shipyards appear to have fallen short of satisfying unionists' demands.</p>
<p>ELEFTHEROTYPIA</p>
<p>--Simitis assured his party deputies at yesterday's meeting that Greece would not renegotiate its sovereign rights and that a step-by-step approach would continue if Turkey accepted the Greek terms. </p>
<p>--The leader of New Democracy Costas Karamanlis maintains his silence as his uncle - former president and ND founder Constantine Karamanlis - lashes out at pro-royalists in the party ranks.  </p>
<p>TA NEA</p>
<p>--Foreign Minister Theodoros Pangalos went on the attack against those - Education Minister Gerasimos Arsenis - who still harboured designs on the leadership of the country, saying &quot;some have not said we lost, but we have lost for the moment&quot;. He said the letter from the 32 deputies on Greek-Turkish relations had hindered the negotiations. </p>
<p>--Residents on the holiday island of Corfu have taken to arming themselves following a rash of attacks from sea-borne bandits from neighbouring Albania.</p>
<p>ELEFTHEROS TYPOS</p>
<p>--The relationship between late PASOK founder and president Andreas Papandreou and Dimitra Liani is a story worthy of Hollywood, says a Greek-American producer.</p>
<p>--Policemen will decide today wheher they will go on strike for the first time in the history of the Greek police force. Police marched through Athens yesterday demanding wage and institutional reforms.</p>
<p>ETHNOS</p>
<p>--&quot;Nostalgia for a bankrupt institution&quot; must end, former president Karamanlis said to pro-royalists in the conservative opposition New Democracy party. </p>
<p>--Maria Petrakis, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
