<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570788" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</title>
<headline>Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>RESERVE BANK DEFENDS COMMITMENT TO REDUCING UNEMPLOYMENT</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank Governor, Ian McFarlane, has defended the bank's commitment to reducing unemployment.</p>
<p>There've been industry calls for another cut in official interest rates to stimulate employment.</p>
<p>But Mr McFarlane has told a Parliamentary committee hearing in Sydney that the effects of three cuts in the last half of last year have yet to fully flow through.</p>
<p>And while inflation is at the low end of their target range, he says wage increases are still higher than they should be.</p>
<p>Mr McFarlane says continuing low inflation is needed to ensure long term growth.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>CENTURY ZINC PROJECT ENDORSED</p>
<p>The Century Zinc project in Queensland's Gulf Country has been approved, more than seven years after the resource was discovered.</p>
<p>The Native Title Tribunal's arbitration team, sitting in Mount Isa, endorsed the agreement reached between native title claimants, the state government and the mining company.</p>
<p>The arbitration team heard legal argument that it no longer had the power to order whether confidential documents presented to the Tribunal this week should remain confidential.</p>
<p>Those documents include the project agreement itself and documents relating to a claim by some native title claimants that the state government had not acted in good faith during negotiations.</p>
<p>The Tribunal's Paul Seaman QC said he'd leave the questions raised today to be tested by general law.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HANSON EXPECTS MORE SUPPORT AFTER NATIONALS' BACKFLIP</p>
<p>The Leader of the One Nation party, Pauline Hanson, says she expects the National Party's apparent backflip on Native Title to translate into increased support for her party.</p>
<p>National Party Leader Tim Fischer has been forced to accept John Howard's plan after it was approved by Federal Cabinet yesterday.</p>
<p>Miss Hanson, speaking on ABC talkback radio in Western Queensland says she's suprised and disappointed by the National party's actions.</p>
<p>She says people are sick of being ignored by the government and a tremendous lot had been done for the Aboriginal race.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>O'CHEE SATISFIED ON NATIVE TITLE</p>
<p>National Party Senator Bill O'Chee says he's now satisfied with the Prime Minister's undertakings on native title.</p>
<p>Senator O'Chee had threatened to quit the National Party and become an Independent, if Mr Howard's 10-point response to Wik did not include full extinguishment of native title on pastoral leases.</p>
<p>But Senator O'Chee told ABC Radio, Mr Howard has given the Nationals assurances on three important areas, including extinguishment.</p>
<p>Senator O'Chee says Queensland's previous Labor Government passed legislation stating that native title was extinguished over pastoral leases.</p>
<p>He says that's going to be validated in the 10-point plan as a legislative act.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>STOWAWAYS' FAMILY MUCH RELIEVED</p>
<p>The family of the twin teenage girls found on Cape York after they'd jumped ship with a Malaysian sailor says it's much relieved the girls are heading home to New Zealand today.</p>
<p>Australian authorities have decided to deport the three.</p>
<p>The twins' brother, Andrew Ingham, says since his sisters Sarah and Joanne made front page news the family home's been under seige by the media.</p>
<p>The girls hade been stowed away on the ship since February, and Mr Ingham says the ordeal has been very stressful for the family.</p>
<p>He says everyone at home is very happy and much relieved.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>PURPOSELESS ABORIGINAL CHILDREN COMMITTING SUICIDE</p>
<p>A professor of politics at Sydney's Macquarie University says Aboriginal children as young as ten are committing suicide - and no other society in the world is showing up incidences of suicide at such early ages.</p>
<p>Professor Colin Tatz has been awarded a grant to try and find ways of alleviating the problem.</p>
<p>He says many young Aboriginal people suffer a sense of purposelessness, with no expectations in life.</p>
<p>He says they want to change their lives but don't know how they can.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
