<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570728" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: &quot;Mr Yen&quot; sends dollar/yen sliding in early Europe.</title>
<headline>&quot;Mr Yen&quot; sends dollar/yen sliding in early Europe.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar slumped against the yen in early Europe as comments from Japan's &quot;Mr Yen&quot; stirred up bubbling market fears of central bank intervention.</p>
<p>Influential Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara pulled the rug out from under dollar/yen's feet when he said the past year's movements raised the chance the Japanese currency could strengthen, possibly to 103 per dollar.</p>
<p>The U.S. unit swooped from around 124.70 yen just before the remarks to a low of 123.70.</p>
<p>&quot;People are on tenterhooks about whether we actually see any intervention,&quot; said Nigel Richardson, economist at Yamaichi.</p>
<p>&quot;People are aware there's a chance of some kind of intervention if they're really serious about (yen weakness),&quot; said Richardson, who is an international economist at Yamaichi.</p>
<p>Intervention fears gripped the market and shook the dollar on Wednesday after a Japanese wire report that the G3 nations -- Japan, the U.S. and Germany -- were studying the possibility of concerted selling of dollars for yen.</p>
<p>&quot;The fear of intervention is clearly rising, but the success of the mere threat to intervene is probably enough to keep the G3 from actually executing intervention for now,&quot; said Klaus Baader, international economist at Deutsche Morgan Grenfell.</p>
<p>Although Germany -- keen to boost exports and spur economic growth -- is thought less troubled then Japan by the dollar's current levels, the Sakakibara shock waves rippled through dollar/mark too. It fell to a 1.7097 marks low from late Wednesday's 1.7210/15, though was back at 1.7118/23 by 0810 GMT.</p>
<p>Mark/yen felt the force of the upbeat Japanese currency, skidding to 72.25/28 from 72.57/59.</p>
<p>Analysts said the interest rate scenario was also working in the yen's favour, as speculation grew of Japanese tightening. In the U.S., by contrast, yesterday's Beige Book release gives no indication the Fed will have to raise rates fast, they said.</p>
<p>In its latest Beige Book on business conditions, the Federal Reserve said the U.S. economy expanded moderately over the last two months while wages and retail prices were generally subdued.</p>
<p>Fed policymakers will use the findings when they meet on May 20 to consider whether to tighten, after raising rates at their last meeting in March for the first time in more than two years.</p>
<p>&quot;The story of moderate growth reduces expectations of an interest rate rise in the future, and undermines the dollar. Compare that with Japan, where there's talk about economic recovery coming through and talk about an early rate rise,&quot; said Yamaichi's Richardson.</p>
<p>Japanese vice finance minister Tadashi Ogawa moved, however, to dampen those expectations. Japan's current monetary stance was appropriate, though some saw the rise in long-term interest rates as reflecting a brighter economic outlook, he said.</p>
<p>Ogawa said Sakakibara's comment had not been a prediction of future market movements.</p>
<p>Sakakibara had in fact remarked that dollar/yen had moved an average of 23 yen per year in the past 10-year period, meaning the yen would strengthen to around 103 to the dollar if it gained 23 yen from current levels, Ogawa told a news conference.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, sterling settled far beneath previous European closing levels after diving overnight on a report quoting an unnamed Labour Party source as saying the pound should rejoin Europe's exchange rate mechanism in 2001 at a rate of 2.50 marks.</p>
<p>The UK Treasury said there was no truth in the report.</p>
<p>Sterling was quoted at 2.7854/64 marks and $1.6260/67 at 0847 GMT versus late Wednesday's European levels of 2.8151/61 and $1.6366/75.</p>
<p>-- Abigail Levene, London Newsroom +44-171-542-8968</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
