<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570791" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RBA knocks back short Australian debt hit again.</title>
<headline>RBA knocks back short Australian debt hit again.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>----------(Snapshot at 4.35 P.M./0635 GMT)------------------</p>
<p>FUTURES					  CASH YIELD</p>
<p>90-DAY BILLS  (JUN) 93.96  (- 0.08)    6.03    (UNCH)</p>
<p>3-YR T-BONDS  (JUN) 93.05  (- 0.07)    6.90    (+ 0.06)</p>
<p>10-YR T-BONDS (JUN) 92.175 (-0.005)    7.80    (UNCH)</p>
<p>AUD/USD  0.7782 (PREV 0.7756) US 30-YR  6.96   (6.96 NY)</p>
<p>---------------------(May 8)--------------------------------</p>
<p>*Australian debt futures ended above the day's lows, but the short end was still down sharply on the day, after RBA governor Macfarlane ruled out a further policy easing.</p>
<p>*Long end seen benefiting from next Tuesday's budget.  </p>
<p>By Colin Brinsden</p>
<p>In the space of two days, the Reserve Bank of Australia has dampened the bullish pre-budget sentiment that had been running through the bond market at the start of the week, particularly at the short end.</p>
<p>On Wednesday the central bank said nothing, when there was a glimmer of hope that it might announce an interest rate cut, while on Thursday it said more than enough to suggest that an easing was off the cards, and even warned of a tightening.</p>
<p>RBA chief Ian Macfarlane said there would be no economic gain from another cut, prompting short debt futures to sink.  </p>
<p>In his first semi-annual testimony to parliament, governor Macfarlane also warned that wages growth was uncomfortably high and that it would take policy action on a further acceleration.</p>
<p>June bill futures dropped to 93.96, equating to a cash rate just above current 6.0 percent official rates, while the sell-off was heavier for further forward positions with the December bills virtually pricing in a 50 basis point tightening.</p>
<p>But &quot;The governor's statement, while ruling out a rate cut, which was already a low probability anyway, does not necessarily make an early rate rise any more likely,&quot; said Bruce Freeland, chief economist at Commonwealth Bank of Australia.  </p>
<p>&quot;We continue to expect unchanged monetary policy over 1997, with a tightening in the first quarter of 1998,&quot; he added. The long end, meanwhile, finished little changed in anticipation of a bond-friendly budget next Tuesday, but were still over 10 basis points above the sub-7.70 percent 10-week low seen earlier this week.</p>
<p>&quot;Current sub-8.0 percent bond yields should remain broadly unchanged over the next month of so, before climbing to around 8.50 percent by year end as the RBA begins a short tightening cycle,&quot; Annette Beacher, senior economist at Citibank Australia.  </p>
<p>Some analysts are predicting a substantial budget headline surplus approaching A$10.0 billion, which is expected to lead to very low or a net zero issuance.</p>
<p>&quot;This should be a positive for the bond market over 1998, although U.S. weakness could still lead to higher yield later in 1997,&quot; CBA's Freeland added.</p>
<p>April labour force data were released, while Macfarlane was testifying, and saw employment rise 37,100 and the unemployment rate stayed at 8.7 percent, much in line with forecasts.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said he was relieved to see the employment rise, and saw considerably lower jobless if the expansion continues.  </p>
<p>----------------------(SPREADS)---------------------------------</p>
<p> AUD VS   3-YR	   10-YR	* AUD 3-YR/10-YR SPREAD</p>
<p> USD	 40 (UNCH)   105 (- 07) * FUTURES    87.5 (- 05.5)</p>
<p> CAD	160 (- 07)   117 (- 10) * CASH	 90   (- 06)</p>
<p> NZD	-56 (+ 06)   +07 (- 02) *</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Against other dollar bloc bonds the market was fairly mixed, narrowing against the long end of both Canada and the U.S. which both saw poor responses to 10-year bond auctions on Wednesday. The yield curve flattened again, with the three/10-year bond futures spread standing at its lowest level since late March.</p>
<p>------------------------(TECHNICALS)-------------------------</p>
<p>FUTURES	*SUP/RES     *SUP/RES 2ND *RSI    *MA-10 *MA-20</p>
<p>10-YEAR (JUN)*92.14-92.18 *92.08-92.28 *54 PCT *92.12 *92.11</p>
<p>3-YEAR  (JUN)*93.03-93.06 *92.95-93.12 *48 PCT *93.11 *93.11</p>
<p>90-DAY  (JUN)*93.92-93.97 *93.88-94.01 *47 PCT *94.04 *94.03</p>
<p>-------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
