<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570757" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - BTP failure above 129 points to pullback.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - BTP failure above 129 points to pullback.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>June BTP futures on LIFFE are likely to retain a soft undertone on Thursday after the market stopped at 129.00 exactly early in the session, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's failure to hold over 129.00 suggests a pullback to 128.60-40,&quot; said Francoise Skelley, head of global trading technical analysis at Credit Suisse First Boston in London.</p>
<p>She said there was an hourly upchannel line there and it was also an upbreak point.</p>
<p>June BTPs at 0750 GMT were at 128.76, down 0.47 from the prior close after touching a 129.00 high earlier.  </p>
<p>Raynard Cheng at First Chicago said he saw immediate pressure at the 128.70 level, which the market was testing early on Thursday. He pegged resistance in the 129.00-10 area.</p>
<p>&quot;I expect the market to weaken further and probe below 128.70 and the next support will be at 128.40,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But that level (128.40) is a strong barrier to a one-and-a-half point decline to 127.00.&quot;</p>
<p>Cheng said the short-term uptrend had been broken and had reached its reverse overnight.</p>
<p>&quot;But if the market surprised me to rally above the 129.00-10 area we are looking for 129.40, 129.80 after that,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Skelley said Wednesday's move past 129.05 resistance, which had been a pair of highs in mid-April, and then above 129.30, had been a false break. The market touched 129.35 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>She said a move below 128.40 would add to the bearish pressure and would target 128.15 immediately.</p>
<p>June Eurolire were also weighed down, trading at 93.20, down 0.05.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
