<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570790" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Broadcasting Corp Morning Update.</title>
<headline>Australian Broadcasting Corp Morning Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>6 PERCENT WAGE RISE WANTED BY CONSTRUCTION UNION</p>
<p>The Construction Union says it will seek wage rises of at least six per cent for its members across Australia in enterprise agreements.</p>
<p>A meeting of the union's officials in Hobart has set six per cent as the least state offices should be able to achieve in enterprise bargaining.</p>
<p>But Secretary, John Sutton, says members in New South Wales, Victoria and Western Australia should expect bigger increases which local economies can withstand.</p>
<p>He says the union's approach is economically realistic, and agreement to a six per cent rise has already been reached with employers in Queensland and South Australia.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MAN FOUND IN HEAVY SEAS BY USE OF NIGHT VISION</p>
<p>A man missing for more than 10 hours in rough seas off Caloundra overnight has been found after a massive search.</p>
<p>The 26-year-old man from Deception Bay was found off the east coast of Bribie Island clinging to his overturned dingy by a rescue helicopter.</p>
<p>Seven rescue vessels started searching for the man after his fishing companion was found on a navigation beacon by a passing ship late yesterday.</p>
<p>Sergeant Richard Bartley from the Water Police says the man was freezing cold when found and is now on his way to Redcliffe Hospital.</p>
<p>He says the use of night vision technology proved crucial in the rescue.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>NATIONAL DAY OF ACTION AT UNIVERSITIES</p>
<p>The National Union of Students has planned rallies and marches in most major centres around Australia today in a National Day of Action against funding cuts to higher education.</p>
<p>Union president John Carey says the battle against the introduction of up front fees and last year's budget cuts are the main issues.</p>
<p>Mr Carey says students want the budget cuts reversed, and will maintain pressure on the Coalition through to the next election.</p>
<p>The Day of action has the support of academics, and National Tertiary Education Union president, Carolyn Allport says in most centres, it will be a joint student-staff action.</p>
<p>Doctor Allport says the Union fully supports the fight against upfront fees, saying student anger is entirely justified.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BEAZLEY CONCERNED ABOUT AIRPORT COSTS AND CHARGES</p>
<p>The Federal Opposition says it doubts whether costs and charges will be monitored when the new owners of the Brisbane, Melbourne and Perth airports take control.</p>
<p>This follows yesterday's announcement that the three airports had been sold for a total of three-point-four billion dollars.</p>
<p>Labor leader Kim Beazley says he's concerned costs and charges to users of the airports are set to rise as the new owners seek returns on their investments.</p>
<p>Mr Beazley says he doubts whether the Government will police the issue.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>NEW DEMOCRACY CLASSES FOR SCHOOL STUDENTS</p>
<p>The Federal Government is to spend more than 17-million dollars to encourage schools to educate young people between years four and 10 about Australia's democracy.</p>
<p>Schools Minister David Kemp says studies have shown a high level of ignorance among the population about the Constitution and the role of the Governor-General.</p>
<p>Dr Kemp says with Australia about to engage in a national debate about the constitution, it's important young people understand how the system works and the implications of any changes.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BHP DESCRIBED AS THE &quot;BIGOTED AUSTRALIAN&quot;:  MP</p>
<p>Mining giant BHP has come under further attack following its decision to close-down steelmaking in Newcastle, this time for alleged discrimination.</p>
<p>During debate in the New South Wales parliament last night, Government backbencher, Tony Stewart described BHP as the &quot;bigoted Australian&quot;</p>
<p>He quoted from what he said was a confidential BHP memo written in 1992, claiming its wording promoted discriminatory, pro-Anglo Saxon employment policies.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>STOWAWAYS AND SAILOR FOUND IN RUGGED BUSHLAND</p>
<p>Twin teenage girls and their Malaysian companion, who jumped ship off North Queensland more than two weeks ago are in Cairns this morning for questioning by police and immigration officials.</p>
<p>Joanne and Sarah Ingham were invited onboard a cargo ship in New Zealand four months ago but fell asleep and awoke to find themselves at sea.</p>
<p>They hid from the Captain, while sailing to Australia via Singapore.</p>
<p>While off north Queensland the two girls and a Malaysian seaman jumped overboard, hid from search planes and drifted for 40 hours to Cape York Peninsula.</p>
<p>They were found in rugged country by a group of Aboriginal people near Coen.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>LOSS, GRIEF AND TRAUMA CONFERENCE IN SYDNEY</p>
<p>More than 500 health and welfare professionals will attend a conference in Sydney over the next three days dealing with the issues of loss, grief and trauma.</p>
<p>The conference will be opened by former New South Wales Coroner Kevin Waller.</p>
<p>There'll be a special session on the Port Arthur massacre presented by the Tasmanian police psychologist.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>DEATH PENALTY CLAIMS EXAGGERATED:  FOREIGN AFFAIRS</p>
<p>The department of Foreign Affairs says reports that a 25-year-old Australian who's facing drug charges in the Middle East could face a death sentence have been exaggerated.</p>
<p>Flight attendant, Julia Alexander, from Melbourne has been in custody in Sharjah in the United Arab Emirates for three months on charges involving valium and marijuana.</p>
<p>Department spokesman, Tony Melville, says the Australian Consul General in Dubai has provided information to local officials about Australia's attitude towards soft drugs.</p>
<p>He says Ms Alexander's facing a maximum sentence of about four or five years in jail, which by Australian standards, is very high.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
