<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570797" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian stocks follow Dow lower, ICI plunges.</title>
<headline>Australian stocks follow Dow lower, ICI plunges.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>------------------(Snapshot 10.20 a.m./0020 GMT)---------------</p>
<p>AORD		 2503.2   -14.4   DJIA (cl)     7085.65 -139.67</p>
<p>SPI sycom cl     2510.0   -11.0   US 30yr (cl)     6.96  +0.07</p>
<p>10yrbond futs    92.130  -0.050   Gold NY 341.25 Lon fix 341.10</p>
<p>AUD	 $0.7791 (Wed  $0.7762)  CRB Index	246.61  +0.57</p>
<p>NIKKEI	  20,013.20 -132.02   FTSE cl	  4537.5  +18.2</p>
<p>S&amp;P500(Globex)   816.10   -1.55   NZSE40	  2329.76   +1.39</p>
<p>--------------------------(May 8)------------------------------</p>
<p>*Stocks follow Wall Street lower, ICI shares plunge on parent's sale plan, BHP goes ex-div. Vol 42.23 million, value A$147.98 million, 505 stocks traded, 193 steady, 89 up, 223 down.  </p>
<p>Australian stocks fell on Thursday's opening after the plunge on Wall Street with market leader BHP weighing on market as it went ex-dividend.</p>
<p>Shares in chemical group ICI Australia tumbled after its parent ICI PLc announced plans to sell its stake.</p>
<p>The All Ordinaries index fell from its record close on Wednesday. At 10.20 a.m. (0020 GMT) the index was 14.4 points lower at 2,503.2. June share price index futures were 11 points down at 2,510, but at a 6.8 point premium to the physical index.</p>
<p>Brokers said the market was likely to consolidate after recent gains as it digested RBA comments.  </p>
<p>Brokers said the market was holding up, well despite the 140 point fall on Wall Street.</p>
<p>&quot;I think this is demonstrating there is not a lot of sellers out there,&quot; said John Bowie-Wilson, dealer at BHP Equities.</p>
<p>Traders said the near 10 percent tumble in ICI Australia was over done. The chemical group's shares fell after ICI Plc said on Wednesday it would sell its 62.4 percent stake.</p>
<p>The market was closely watching comments from by Reserve Bank governor Ian Macfarlane to a federal government committee.</p>
<p>Macfarlane has told the committtee that he current rates are accommodating a pick up in the economy.  </p>
<p>Most sectors were lower, but rises were recorded by the media, gold, energy and other metal sectors.</p>
<p>In other market news, Australian bonds weakened after the RBA statement on monetary policy. The June 10-year bond futures contract fell to 92.125 from 92.160, while June bill futures also declined.</p>
<p>The Australian dollar was steady after the RBA comments.</p>
<p>At 11.05 a.m. (0105 GMT), the dollar was trading at US$0.7783/88 compared with around US$0.7780/85 just before Macfarlane addressed the committee.  </p>
<p>--------------------------(TECHNICALS)--------------------------</p>
<p>Short-term range    Support   Restnce   RSI-14  MA-10  MA-20</p>
<p>AORD   2495/2530     2480	2515	67.33   2490   2452</p>
<p>SPI    2495/2530     2485	2530	64.11   2498   2453</p>
<p>------------------------KEY ACTIVES-----------------------------</p>
<p>*BHP A$17.82 (-.26) 17.70/17.86 Vol: 5,056,566</p>
<p>BHP falls as stocks goes ex-dividend</p>
<p>*ICI Australia A$11.20 (-1.24) 10.80/11.50 Vol: 162,464</p>
<p>Shares fall as parent puts major stake on the market</p>
<p>*News Corp Ltd A$6.06 (steady) 6.00/6.10 Vol: 670,185</p>
<p>Media giant steady despite Q3 profit jump</p>
<p>*NAB A$18.10 (-.04) 17.90/18.18 Vol: 491,417</p>
<p>*ANZ A$8.35 (-.02) 8.32/8.39 Vol: 551,203</p>
<p>Banks slip after recent gains</p>
<p>*CRA A$19.41 (+.06) 19.30/19.41 Vol: 174,530</p>
<p>Miner gaint gains as broader resources find support</p>
<p>*Coles A$6.40 (-.04) 6.94/6.44 Vol: 379,027</p>
<p>Retailer shares slip after group reports 6.5 pct rise in Q3</p>
<p>sales and says see second half profit growth.</p>
<p>-- Kevin Morrison 61-2 9373-1813</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
