<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570715" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Sony posts record profit on robust sales, weak yen.</title>
<headline>Sony posts record profit on robust sales, weak yen.</headline>
<byline>Kayako Watanabe</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japanese electronics giant Sony Corp on Thursday unveiled record group profits for the last business year, aided by robust global sales and a weak yen, and predicted further growth in the current year.</p>
<p>&quot;Our group sales, operating profit and net profit during the 1996/97 business year all reached the highest levels in Sony's history,&quot; the company said in a statement. Parent sales and operating profit were also the highest on record.</p>
<p>Sony's group net profit was 139.46 billion yen ($1.12 billion) in the year to March, up 2.6-fold from the year before. Parent current profit was 85.73 billion yen ($691 million), a three-fold increase from the previous year.</p>
<p>Net profit is equal to current profit, which is pre-tax, minus taxes and extraordinary profits and losses.</p>
<p>The strong earnings result, which came after the Tokyo stock market closed, may not be a great surprise to the market, which already pushed Sony's shares briefly to a record high of 9,800 yen on Thursday. The shares ended at 9,720 yen in Tokyo, up 90 yen from Wednesday's close.</p>
<p>&quot;Larger group sales were due to higher sales in Japan, the United States, Europe and other areas as well as the yen's depreciation,&quot; Sony said in the statement.</p>
<p>In 1996/97 the yen fell about 15 percent against the dollar and weakened against other foreign currencies as well.</p>
<p>Sony said the yen's fall against other major currencies, which makes Japanese exports more competitive abroad, raised its 1996/97 group sales by about 520 billion yen ($4.19 billion).</p>
<p>Sony said that sales rose in all its business areas including electronics, entertainment, insurance and financing.</p>
<p>Sales of the company's cutting-edge 32-bit home game player, the PlayStation, contributed to a 24.3 percent group in its group revenue in the electronics sector.</p>
<p>In the entertainment sector, group operating revenue grew 23.1 percent to 1.02 trillion yen ($8.2 billion) in 1996/97.</p>
<p>Sony's entertainment revenues come largely from its troubled Hollywood film-making unit, Sony Pictures Entertainment, and its recording unit, Sony Music Entertainment.</p>
<p>&quot;Sales in the music group continued to rise despite the weak retail environment in the United States, primarily due to favourable sales growth outside Japan,&quot; Sony said.</p>
<p>One notable success was Canadian pop diva Celine Dion's &quot;Falling Into You,&quot; which has sold more than 21 million copies since its March 1996 release, it said.</p>
<p>Sales in the pictures group rose significantly, aided by continued strength in television operations and the success of videos such as &quot;Jumanji&quot; and &quot;Matilda.&quot;</p>
<p>The blockbuster romantic comedy &quot;Jerry Maguire,&quot; which has grossed $150 million at the U.S. box office, also contributed to the year's favourable results, Sony said.</p>
<p>&quot;All of those positive factors, in addition to the yen's depreciation, more than offset the disappointing box office results of several films released during the year,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Sony said that it expected group net profit to grow further to 160 billion yen ($1.29 billion) and parent current profit to increase to 100 billion yen ($806 million) in 1997/98. (1$=124 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
