<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570770" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Goldman Sachs' Davies says dollar caused stg fall.</title>
<headline>Goldman Sachs' Davies says dollar caused stg fall.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sterling's overnight decline is a consequence of a dollar fall rather than a rumour Britain would rejoin the EU's exchange rate mechanism at a rate of 2.50 marks, Goldman Sachs economist Gavyn Davies said.</p>
<p>&quot;What's happened overnight is that the dollar has come down and the pound is trading down against the yen and the deutschemark in line with the dollar. I suspect that's the main thing that's going on,&quot; he told BBC radio 4's Today programme.</p>
<p>Davies is widely tipped to be appointed to the newly created post of second Bank of England deputy governor.  </p>
<p>Sterling plummeted by around four pfennigs following a report from Bridge news agency which quoted an unnamed source in Britain's ruling Labour Party saying that sterling should rejoin the ERM in 2001, at a central rate of 2.50 marks, well below its current rate.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we are going to get that sort of rumour persistently now because the government obviously is doing things which bring it closer to the European Union and I think this kind of rumour is going to occur,&quot; Davies said.  </p>
<p>Asked if he wanted to be deputy governor, Davies said: &quot;I've got a great job at Goldman Sachs.&quot;</p>
<p>But he added that the posts on the new Bank of England monetary policy committee, announced by Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown Tuesday, would attract high calibre candidates because of the central bank's new power to decide the level of interest rates.</p>
<p>&quot;Under the old regime, if these people had simply been advising the Governor what to advise the Chancellor, there might well have been a problem in getting people,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think now that nine people will be setting interest rate policy in the UK that doesn't apply and I think you'll get very good people who will be very willing to do this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>--Cheryl Juckes +44 171 542 5109</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
