<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570703" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BTR warns on profits, shares slump.</title>
<headline>BTR warns on profits, shares slump.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON</dateline>
<text>
<p>BTR Plc, Britain's biggest conglomerate, saw its shares nosedive Thursday after it issued a profit warning just as the market believed the company had the worst behind it.</p>
<p>The widely diversified conglomerate, which is in the final stages of a major restructuring, said the pound sterling's strength would hurt first-half 1997 sales by 300 million pounds ($486.7 million), if the currency stayed at its current high levels.</p>
<p>The impact on operating profits would be about 35 million pounds ($56.8 million), said BTR, which focuses on industrial manufacturing and engineering operations.</p>
<p>The profit warning comes just two months after BTR reported better-than-expected 1996 results and said it was making good progress in getting its act together.</p>
<p>BTR shares dropped 31.5 pence (51 cents), or 12 percent, to 2.36 pounds ($3.83) in late morning trade after they shot up early in March on the favourable full-year results.</p>
<p>Analysts reduced their profit estimates for this year by about 10 percent to around 1.2 billion pounds ($1.9 billion).</p>
<p>&quot;Even without sterling, the company is still facing large problems in some of its markets and with some of its products,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>BTR's profit warning also showed that the conglomerate's restructuring, which already saw the weeding out of many of its underperforming operations, is not complete yet.</p>
<p>&quot;They are turning things around, but it is a big ship to turn -- it will take time,&quot; said this industry watcher.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I48100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
