<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570822" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian jobs rise a relief, prospects improving.</title>
<headline>Australian jobs rise a relief, prospects improving.</headline>
<byline>John Mair</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's labour force remained sluggish in April, despite data released on Thursday showing a strong rise, but policy-makers and economists remain optimisitc that conditions will improve as 1997 progresses.</p>
<p>Employment rose by 37,100 in April, right in line with market expectations and reversing a fall of 33,900 in March, official data showed.</p>
<p>However, the rise did not make a dent in the unemployment rate which remained steady at 8.7 percent.  </p>
<p>Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) Governor Ian Macfarlane, appearing before a parliamentary committee to report on monetary policy, said he was relieved to see such a rise.</p>
<p>&quot;It's quite a high figure, but we needed a high figure and we're relieved to see it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Despite the rise, conditions still remain sluggish.</p>
<p>Over the past 12 months, total employment levels have risen by around 132,000, or roughly 11,000 new jobs a month, below the 15,000 to 20,000 jobs a month economists say is needed to start making inroads into unemployment.  </p>
<p>&quot;Overall the trends remain sluggish, with total employment barely increasing, and full-time employment in outright decline, HSBC Markets economist Anthony Thompson said.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said that unemployment was a concern, but that it was also a lagging indicator of activity and the leading indicators suggested an improved 1997. It was also difficult to make accurate assessments on just a few months' data, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;What can be said with reasonable confidence is that employment growth has been weak over the past year or more, but that leading indicators like vacancies are signalling some strengthening in future employment conditions,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We cannot be sure how robust that will be, but some employment pick up would be consistent with the firmer growth picture we anticipate,&quot; Macfarlane said.</p>
<p>Economists agreed, saying that signs of strength in the housing and retail sectors suggested labour demand should begin picking up as the pace of activity picked up.</p>
<p>&quot;The labour market forward indicators are consistent with this expected upswing,&quot; Citibank Australia economists said.  </p>
<p>The prospect of firmer economic growth, and subsequent employment demand, meant that another rate cut to follow the three in the middle of last year was unlikely, despite continuing high unemployment.</p>
<p>&quot;We now just await confirmation of the expected pick up in employment growth in the official statistics over the next few months,&quot; HSBC's Thompson said.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said that with the economy expected to grow at around four percent in 1997, there was no economic gain to be had from a further rate cut, but he agreed that unemployment should be lower.  </p>
<p>&quot;We agree with everyone, if you've got inflation of 2.5 percent and unemployment of 8.75 percent, the thing that needs to be improved is the unemployment, not the inflation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe the most successful way of doing that is by achieving a long-lasting expansion,&quot; he said, rather than short term bursts of rapid growth followed by recession.</p>
<p>For this reason, improvement would be slow, but it would be more sustainable, he said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
