<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570814" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: NZ to query China about Antarctic fishing fleet.</title>
<headline>NZ to query China about Antarctic fishing fleet.</headline>
<byline>Simon Louisson</byline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Zealand said on Thursday it would ask China about reports from conservation groups that Beijing is building a 200-boat fishing fleet to exploit lucrative toothfish grounds in the Southern Ocean.</p>
<p>&quot;We have no information about the Chinese fleet ourselves but...it is something we will be asking the Chinese authorities for some comment on,&quot; senior Foreign Affairs official Stuart Prior told a news conference. &quot;Clearly it would be a development of some significance.&quot;</p>
<p>The World Wildlife Fund said it had information from the conservation monitoring group Traffic that China was building the fleet to cash in on the lucrative species.</p>
<p>China has not signed the 1980 Convention on the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources (CCAMLR), which is designed to protect the environment in that region.</p>
<p>Toothfish, first named five years ago as the Patagonian toothfish, was identified as a rich commercial catch only two years ago. It is a long fish with a large mouth and believed to be bottom dwelling, living off cod. It lives for up to 25 years.</p>
<p>In Japan it is sold as &quot;mero&quot;, fetching US$7,000 a tonne.</p>
<p>The issue would be discussed at the Antarctic Treaty Consultative meeting in Christchurch this month.</p>
<p>&quot;The matter is of very considerable significance for the Antarctic Treaty because the treaty is imposing considerable compliance costs on countries, commercial organisations, tourist operators, and if they see operators working without those costs, you have an incredible situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Fishermen had used U.S. data, declassified since the end of the Cold War, to show the seabed in detail for the first time.</p>
<p>Ilegal ships, flying flags of convenience but reported to be from Norway, Spain and the United States have been based in Madagascar, Mauritius and Namibia.</p>
<p>Other boats, mainly from Europe, are reported to be heading towards the Antarctic.</p>
<p>New Zealand had already begun talks with France, Australia and South Africa about sharing information about how to control the problem but Prior said control was difficult because of the vast distances involved.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
