<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570807" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian stocks fall, but cling above 2,500 level.</title>
<headline>Australian stocks fall, but cling above 2,500 level.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian share market fell on Thursday but remained above the key psychological level of 2,500 despite market leader BHP going ex-dividend and Wednesday's drop on Wall Street.</p>
<p>The market was also depressed by the tumble in ICI Australia shares, which fell almost 10 percent, after news its British parent ICI Plc planned to sell its A$2.0 billion (US$1.55 billion) holding in the chemical group.</p>
<p>The All Ordinaries index ended 12.9 points lower at 2,504.7 after briefly dipping below 2,500. Trade topped A$760 million.</p>
<p>Brokers said the market is likely to continue its muted response to the wild swings in the Dow industrials.</p>
<p>&quot;It was quite a good day. The Dow has been rocketing up the past couple of days while our market has only been drifting so you wouldn't expect it to come off hard,&quot; said Greg Matthews, director of equities at fund managers Mercantile Mutual.</p>
<p>Traders said the Australian bourse is also benefiting from woes in other Asian stockmarkets.</p>
<p>&quot;We are seeing funds flow in from America and Europe and other parts of Asia as markets in other parts of Asia are performing so badly,&quot; Matthews said.</p>
<p>The falls in ICI and BHP alone knocked over five points off the index. BHP topped the turnover lists for the majors with over A$140 million worth of shares traded.</p>
<p>Rupert Murdoch's media empire News Corp reported a stronger than expected third quarter result, but this wasn't enough to stem the loss with the rest of the market.</p>
<p>Brokers said the jobs data and comments by RBA governor Ian Macfarlane had no effect on the market. Macfarlane said there would be no economic gain from another interest rate cut.</p>
<p>Australian employment numbers rose 37,100 in April, however the rise did not dent the unemploment rate, which remained at 8.7 percent.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$0.77)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
