<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570840" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RBA says Australia recovery ensured without rate cut.</title>
<headline>RBA says Australia recovery ensured without rate cut.</headline>
<byline>Michael Perry</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) on Thursday ruled out an imminent cut in interest rates, citing a pick up in economic growth, but warned uncomfortably high wages growth could fuel inflation and threaten the recovery.</p>
<p>&quot;Financial conditions are not impeding the expansion of the economy at present,&quot; central bank governor Ian Macfarlane told a parliamentary hearing on Thursday.</p>
<p>Macfarlane also said long-lasting economic expansion would help reduce Australia's stubbornly high unemployment rate, adding there would be no economic gain from another rate cut.</p>
<p>In its first semi-annual monetary policy report, released ahead of Macfarlane's testimony, the RBA said its current monetary policy, which saw three rate cuts in the second half of 1996 but none in 1997, was fuelling economic growth.</p>
<p>&quot;The bank's assessment is that the current level of cash rates is accommodating the pickup in activity without prejudicing continued low inflation,&quot; the bank said.</p>
<p>The RBA said lower interest rates should support interest-sensitive areas such as housing and non-residential construction and help household and business cash flows.</p>
<p>Official cash rates are currently around six percent, and recent low inflation and high unemployment data has prompted market speculation that there was scope for another reduction.</p>
<p>But Macfarlane said there would be no gain from a rate cut.</p>
<p>&quot;We do believe we are going to have four percent growth over '97, we do believe that that will continue, and we don't believe we will gain anything by having another movement at the moment.&quot;</p>
<p>Macfarlane said the effects of the 1996 rate cuts had yet to fully feed through the economy, which grew 3.1 percent in 1996, adding he would be disappointed if rates were tightened.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be disappointing or surprising if a reversal were to occur in the immediate term,&quot; said Macfarlane, adding the bank's policy on interest rates was traditionally pre-emptive and that cuts were normally followed by a period of stability.</p>
<p>&quot;We have tended in Australia to make our movements in monetary policy, I think, quite early -- the word there is pre-emptive -- to do two or three quickly then to have it followed a period of stability,&quot; Macfarlane said.</p>
<p>Macfarlane also said that the bank would not tighten monetary policy if the economy expanded at four percent and the balance of payments worsened.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't tighten or loosen monetary policy because of the balance of payments,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>However, the central bank warned that the dark cloud on the Australian economy was wages, which Macfarlane said were growing at an &quot;uncomfortably high&quot; level and could threaten the country's low inflation rate.</p>
<p>Underlying inflation rate was 2.1 percent in the year to March, within the bank's two-three percent target range.</p>
<p>&quot;If we want to have a balanced recovery we should be having at this stage of the game lower wages growth than we are getting,&quot; Macfarlane said.</p>
<p>&quot;A significant acceleration of aggregate wages in response to stronger economic growth would...threaten faster inflation -- to which monetary policy would have to respond.&quot;</p>
<p>However, Macfarlane said the bank's inflation range was not set in stone and that it would tolerate movements as long as inflation remained on average within the range.</p>
<p>The Australian Bureau of Statistics on Thursday reported that Australia's April unemployment rate was 8.7 percent, unchanged from March and that monthly employment growth was 37,100, reversing a big fall seen in March.</p>
<p>The central bank said reducing unemployment was a priority. &quot;The most successful way to bring down the unemployment rate is to foster a long-lasting expansion,&quot; Macfarlane said.</p>
<p>&quot;We think we have got the prospect of a long recovery this time. We are looking out three, four or five years and we want to make sure we manage this one in such a way that we get the longest recovery we can...&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
