<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570803" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FOCUS - Australia economy pick up sees rates on hold.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Australia economy pick up sees rates on hold.</headline>
<byline>John Mair</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia all but ruled out a cut in interest rates after hawkish testimony to a parliamentary committee by Governor Ian Macfarlane painted a picture of strengthening growth and rising wages.</p>
<p>Thursday's news dented debt markets, which had begun to consider the possibility of a rate cut, and surprisingly failed to provide much benefit to the dollar.</p>
<p>But if Macfarlane ruled out a rate cut, he also implied that if wages stayed under control there was no need for official rates to rise from their current six percent any time soon.  </p>
<p>&quot;The semi-annual monetary policy statement by the Reserve Bank Governor plus responses to questions make it clear that the Reserve Bank sees the cash rates on lengthy hold at six percent,&quot; UBS Australia chief economist Stephen Roberts said.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said with the economy expected to grow at around four percent in 1997 as the impact of the three rate cuts in 1996 flowed through, there was no economic benefit to be gained from a further cut in official interest rates.  </p>
<p>&quot;We believe in the period ahead that we will see an improved rate of growth, which we see as something more like four percent through 1997 than the three percent we saw over 1996,&quot; Macfarlane told the committee.</p>
<p>The current level of interest rates was accomodative of this expected pick up, he said.</p>
<p>Apart from stronger growth, the RBA expressed some concerns about the pace of wages growth. First quarter data released last week showed annual growth of 4.6 percent, above the 4.5 percent level at which they are seen becoming a threat to low inflation.  </p>
<p>&quot;Overall it is difficult to escape the conclusion that wage bargains and average wage outcomes are somwhat higher than they really should be in an economy chareacterised by low inflation and quite high unemployment levels,&quot; Macfarlane said.</p>
<p>Wages appear to be the key to rates given the outlook for growth, as Macfarlane warned that further accleration threatening low inflation would lead to higher rates.</p>
<p>&quot;So long as wages do not accelerate, the RBA implies, rates do not need to increase,&quot; HSBC chief economist John Edwards said.  </p>
<p>But while there was no need for a rise as long as wages remained in check, there appeared little chance of a rate cut.</p>
<p>&quot;We do believe we are going to have four percent growth over '97, we do believe that that will continue, and we don't believe we will gain anything by having another movement (in rates) at the moment,&quot; Macfarlane said in response to a question.</p>
<p>There had been growing speculation of a rate cut in recent weeks, but Westpac senior economist John Peters said the &quot;unambiguously hawkish&quot; testimony confirmed the rate cut cycle was over, with the next expected move being a rate hike towards the middle of 1998.  </p>
<p>In financial markets the testimony hurt short-dated debt securities most.</p>
<p>The implied yield for June bank bill futures rose from just below six percent to just above the cash rate, but the sell off was heavier in December bills which have now risen to almost 50 points over the cash rate -- implying a tightening by year end.</p>
<p>But the dollar, which has been undermined at times by rate cut speculation since the last cut was delivered in December, failed to derive any benefit from the news, closing the local session at US$0.7776/81 after opening at US$0.7770/75.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
