<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570887" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-RBA says current rates stance helps growth.</title>
<headline>RTRS-RBA says current rates stance helps growth.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) said on Thursday that its current monetary policy stance was helping economic growth.</p>
<p>The central bank said that the current level of rates was accommodating an economic pick-up and there were signs that economic growth was increasing.</p>
<p>The manufacturing sector was, however, the exception to the generally firmer picture.</p>
<p>Inflation was likely to remain low in the near-term, the RBA also said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The bank's assessment is that the current level of cash rates is accommodating the pickup in activity without prejudicing continued low inflation,&quot; the RBA said.</p>
<p>&quot;While potential wages developments are a source of longer term uncertainty for the inflation outlook, the immediate prospects are that inflation will remain low,&quot; it said</p>
<p>&quot;So far in 1997 there have already been some indications that the pace of growth is picking up, particularly in areas of construction investment, housing and consumer spending,&quot; the central bank's semi-annual statement on monetary policy said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
