<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570855" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Great Central optimistic on Barton Deeps.</title>
<headline>Great Central optimistic on Barton Deeps.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A feasibility study was underway to bring the new Barton Deeps prospect at the established Jundee gold mine in Western Australia into production, Great Central Mines Ltd said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Great Central's general manager of exploration, Dermot Ryan, said the study so far indicated that a 5.0 metre by 5.5 metre decline which could produce 600,000 tonnes of ore at 150,000 ounces of gold a year.</p>
<p>Total proven and inferred reserve at Barton Deeps were 4.369 million tonnes of ore at 12.1 g/t of gold for 1.698 million ounces of gold, he said at the Bell Commodities gold conference.  </p>
<p>Ryan's comments update the company's March 31 quarterly report, which said that underground development of Barton Deeps mineralisation was expected to start in July this year with the decline starting from near the base of the Barton open pit.</p>
<p>Ryan said it was expected the Barton Deeps resource would be extended.</p>
<p>At March 31 the total Jundee resource was estimated at 3.37 million ounces while the company's other main deposit, Bronzewing, contained an estimated 3.57 million ounces of gold.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
