<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570885" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-RBA says wages growth may be getting too high.</title>
<headline>RTRS-RBA says wages growth may be getting too high.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) said on Thursday that there were signs that wages growth was becoming uncomfortably high, with aggregate data suggesting that the pace of wages growth has picked up.</p>
<p>The central bank, which closely watches wages growth to manage its inflation target of 2-3 percent, said in a report that any acceleration in wages would threaten inflation and this would require a policy response.</p>
<p>It also said in a report that the favourable inflation outlook was underpinned by the exchange rate. Employment can be expected to strengthen over the year, the RBA added.  </p>
<p>&quot;Aggregate wages data, which encompass workers on award wages, enterprise agreements and other bargaining agreements, suggest that the overall pace of wages growth has picked up recently,&quot; the RBA said.</p>
<p>&quot;These figures will need to be closely watched to assess the extent to which they represent a significant change in trend but, taken at face value, they suggest that wages growth is becoming uncomfortably high,&quot; the central bank said.</p>
<p>&quot;A significant acceleration of aggregate wages in response to stronger economic growth would directly curtail job creation,&quot; it said.  </p>
<p>&quot;It would also threaten faster inflation - to which monetary policy would have to respond - and thereby put at risk the potential for faster non-inflationary growth,&quot; the RBA said.</p>
<p>&quot;Lessening of wages growth would, on the other hand, enable faster growth without risk of acceleration in inflation,&quot; the bank said.</p>
<p>It did note that the recent result of the safety-net review by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission delivered only a moderate increase in award wages which would be helpful to the inflation outlook.  </p>
<p>The RBA noted employment growth had lagged behind the overall pace of economic activity.</p>
<p>&quot;Nonetheless, the number of job vacancies has increased and employment can be expected to strengthen as the general pace of activity picks up over the course of the year,&quot; the bank said.</p>
<p>&quot;On its own, however, faster economic growth will not do enough to reduce unemployment significantly, unless it is accompanied by moderation in growth of labour costs,&quot; the bank said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2 9373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
