<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570808" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FOCUS-Star Wars boosts News Corp profit.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Star Wars boosts News Corp profit.</headline>
<byline>Paul Tait</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rupert Murdoch's global media empire News Corp Ltd announced on Thursday a sharp rise in third-quarter profits, helped by the successful re-release of the Star Wars movie trilogy.</p>
<p>Net profit before abnormal items for the three months to March 31 rose to A$376 million from A$281 million, a rise of around 34 percent, said News Corp, which is based in Australia but also listed in London and New York.</p>
<p>Net profits after abnormals were A$330 million, up from A$77 million in the same period last year.  </p>
<p>But the results received a lacklustre market reception. News' shares ended at A$6.01, off five cents on the day amid continuing uncertainty about U.S. satellite TV operations.</p>
<p>Largely responsible for the rise were News Corp's Fox Television and Fox Films and its successful re-release of Star Wars, which has generated a total of US$249 at the box office since the first of the three movies was released in January.</p>
<p>Filmed Entertainment revenues rose sharply to A$1.138 billion from A$584 million, although its operating income had a more modest rise from A$82 million from A$63 million in the same period a year earlier.  </p>
<p>But analysts warned News Corp's next two big-budget disaster movies -- &quot;Volcano&quot; and &quot;Titanic&quot; -- may erode News' profits in the final quarter and early in the next financial year.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall it's not all good news for News,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>&quot;Volcano&quot; reportedly cost about US$100 million to make but had a cumulative gross of US$27 million to May 5.</p>
<p>The release of &quot;Titanic&quot;, reputedly the most expensive movie ever made, has been pushed back past the traditional U.S. opening date of July 4.  </p>
<p>Murdoch last year predicted that News could achieve a 20 percent profit rise for the year to June 30, 1997, a forecast that was not borne out by first-half results.</p>
<p>One Sydney-based analyst estimated News would report a net profit of A$1.64 billion before abnormals for the 1996/97 year, while others said the latest profit was not enough to make them change forecasts already in line with Murdoch's prediction.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall, the result is at the higher end of market expectations but it's not enough to get people excited,&quot; one Melbourne-based analyst said.  </p>
<p>News said its British newspapers and satellite television unit BSkyB also made significant contributions to profits, while the main reversals came from its book publishing arm HarperCollins and Australasian newspaper and pay television.</p>
<p>There was an abnormal loss of A$46 million for the quarter -- related in part to the end of the CD-ROM publishing divisions at HarperCollins and News International -- compared with a A$204 million loss in the previous comparable quarter.  </p>
<p>News Corp shares fell despite the third quarter result, with analysts saying investors were still wary of investing in News Corp until it sorts out its U.S. satellite TV business American Sky Broadcasting (ASkyB).</p>
<p>Uncertainty surrounds News Corp's ASkyB plans following its tie-up with Echostar Communications Corp. The venture has run into several problems since the deal was announced in February.</p>
<p>&quot;The prevailing issue remains ASkyB and until that issue is resolved satisfactorily it is going to remain a big problem for them,&quot; a Sydney analyst said. -- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
