<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570876" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FULL TEXT-RBA's semi-annual monetary statement.</title>
<headline>FULL TEXT-RBA's semi-annual monetary statement.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following is the full text of the introduction of the RBA's Semi-Annual Statement on Monetary Policy:</p>
<p>The economy moved through a period of slower growth in 1996 during which inflationary pressures eased significantly. The March quarter CPI result confirms that underlying inflation has returned to an annual rate of close to two percent, and the prospects of inflation remaining low in the near future appear to be good. With some surplus capacity existing there is scope for the economy to grow more quickly in 1997 without generating significant inflationary pressures, provided growth in labour costs is not excessive.</p>
<p>So far in 1997 there have already been some indications that the pace of growth is picking up, particularly in areas of construction investment, housing and consumer spending. Growth is being supported by several factors including the effect of the three policy easings in the second half of 1996, which brought cash rates down by 1.5 percenage points. The impact of those cash rate reductions on home mortgage borrowers has been reinforced by a significant compression of intermediaries' interest margins in that area. The lower interest rates now in place should be supportive of interest-sensitive areas of activity, particularly housing and non-residential construction, as well as helping household and business cash flows.  </p>
<p>Other factors favourable to growth at present include the strong US economy, moderately rising commodity prices, and an historically good level of business profitability in many industries.</p>
<p>Conditions in the manufacturing sector have been an exception to this generally firmer picture, with profitability under pressure and investment intentions declining. The pressure on profitability reflects a combination of rising wage costs and flat selling prices, which continue to be constrained in many parts of the manufacturing sector by strong international competition. With the exchange rate having risen in trade-weighted terms, pressures on competitiveness have intensified during the past year. Looking ahead, however, a number of areas of domestic manuafcturing are likely to benefit from the expansion in housing and non-residential construction now under way.</p>
<p>Employment growth has lagged behind the overall pace of economic activity. Total employment has been growing at a rate of around one per cent in the past year, concentrated in part-time jobs. Nonetheless, the number of job vacancies has increased and employment can be expected to strengthen as the general pace of activity picks up over the course of the year.</p>
<p>The favourable near-term outlook for inflation is being underpinned by continued help from the exchange rate in holding down import prices.  </p>
<p>Also helpful to the outlook is the result of the recent Safety-Net Review by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission, which delivered only moderate increases in award wages. However, other developments in labour costs are of more concern for the longer-term inflation outlook. Wage increases under enterprise bargaining continue to be in the four to five percent range, figures which appear high in a climate of two percent inflation and eight-and-a-half percent unemployment. Aggregate wages data, which encompass workers on award wages, enterprise agreements and other bargaining arrangements, suggest that the overall pace of wages growth has picked up recently. These figures will need to be closely watched to assess the extent to which they represent a significant change in trend but, taken at face value, they suggest that wages growth is becoming uncomfortably high.</p>
<p>The capacity of the economy to grow faster while maintaining low inflation will depend importantly on future behaviour of wages. A significant acceleration of aggregate wages in response to stronger economic growth would directly curtail job creation. It would also threaten faster inflation -- to which monetary policy would have to respond -- and thereby put at risk the potential for faster non-inflationary growth. Lessening of wages growth would, on the other hand, enable faster growth without risk of acceleration in inflation.</p>
<p>While potential wages developments are a source of longer-term uncertainty for the inflation outlook, the immediate prospects are that inflation will remain low. The Bank's assessment is that the current level of cash rates is accommodating the pick-up in activity without prejudicing continued low inflation.</p>
<p>(ENDS)</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
