<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570859" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: INSTANT VIEW-Australian April labour force data.</title>
<headline>INSTANT VIEW-Australian April labour force data.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian employment rose 37,100 in April and the unemployment rate was 8.7 percent, official figures showed, much in line with market expectations.</p>
<p>Fulltime employment rose by 28,400 in the month.</p>
<p>Median forecasts had centred on a rise of a 35,000 and an unemployment rate of 8.7 percent.</p>
<p>A selection of economists immediate reactions to the data follow.  </p>
<p>MATTHEW DRENNAN, ECONOMIST, AXIOM FUNDS MANAGEMENT:</p>
<p>&quot;The numbers are pretty neutral for the markets. Just as you couldn't believe the big fall in employment last month, you can't believe the size of the rise this month. Employment growth is clearly stumbling along at about 10,000 a month. But the other indicators are still encouraging for the Reserve Bank as we move out later this year.&quot;  </p>
<p>DAVID DE GARIS, TREASURY ECONOMIST, ANZ BANKING GROUP:</p>
<p>&quot;They are right on the nose of market expectations and they are pretty consistent with a recovery in the economy. It seems that there is growth there and it seems that employment will be modestly up over the next couple of quarters.&quot;  </p>
<p>DAVID LANSLEY, TREASURY ECONOMIST, NATIONAL AUSTRALIA BANK:</p>
<p>&quot;On a trend basis, it (employment) is dead flat...I think you really have to take it into context with listening to (Reserve Bank of Australia governor) Macfarlane as well, and Macfarlane has basically ruled out any rate cuts where the economy is now. I think it just reinforces our view that the next move will be up, but it's certainly well down the track this year...The picture (on employment) is a little more complex but we are a bit softer than the bank and official forecasts, but not dramatically so...We have still got a clear recovery coming through.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 937</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
