<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570871" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Star Wars success boost News Corp profits.</title>
<headline>Star Wars success boost News Corp profits.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rupert Murdoch's global media conglomerate News Corp Ltd posted a sharp rise in third-quarter profits on Thursday, the force of its profits driven by the re-release of the Star Wars movie trilogy.</p>
<p>News Corp, based in Australia but also listed in London and New York, said net profit before abnormal items for the three months to March 31 had risen to A$376 million (US$293 million) from A$281 million, a rise of around 34 percent.</p>
<p>Net profits after abnormals were A$330 million, up from A$77 million in the same period last year.</p>
<p>Largely responsible for the rise were News Corp's Fox Television and Fox Films and its successful re-release of the updated Star Wars trilogy.</p>
<p>&quot;Since being released at the end of January Star Wars has generated US$138 million at the domestic box office, with the two sequels adding another US$111 million to date,&quot; News said.</p>
<p>Operating income from its Filmed Entertainment division, which includes Fox Films, rose to A$82 million from A$63 million in the same period a year earlier, News said.</p>
<p>Filmed Entertainment revenues rose to A$1.138 billion from A$584 million.</p>
<p>News said its British newspapers and satellite television unit BSkyB also made significant contributions to profits.</p>
<p>The main drags on profits came from News' book publishing arm HarperCollins and Australasian newspaper and pay television, the group said.</p>
<p>There was an abnormal loss of A$46 million for the quarter, compared with a A$204 million loss in the previous comparable quarter. The loss related in part to the end of the CD-ROM publishing divisions at HarperCollins and News International.</p>
<p>&quot;These results reflect strong double digit earnings increases at all of the company's core operating segments with the exception of Book Publishing,&quot; News said.</p>
<p>&quot;HarperCollins' results were off against last year reflecting weaker U.S. industry trends.&quot;</p>
<p>Murdoch last year predicted that News could achieve a 20-percent profit rise for the year, a forecast that was not borne out by first-half results. Thursday's figures put the group back on track to achieve that rise.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
