<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570843" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-RBA says any CPI overstatement less than US.</title>
<headline>RTRS-RBA says any CPI overstatement less than US.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Reserve Bank of Australia governor Ian Macfarlane said on Thursday he believed any overstatement of inflation in Australia's official data was a fair bit less than the 1.1 percent estimated as the overstatement in the United States.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a tiny little bit of overstatement, but I doubt that it has implications for monetary policy,&quot; he told a parliamentary committee when asked about the level of overstatement in Australia's consumer price index data.  </p>
<p>Macfarlane was asked by former Labor Treasurer Ralph Willis how large the overstatement was in Australia and if it had any implications for monetary policy.</p>
<p>Willis referred to the report on the overstatement of inflation in the United States by Stanford University economist Michael Boskin.</p>
<p>Boskin estimated that the U.S. CPI overstated inflation by 1.1 percent.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said Boskin's 1.1 percent estimate was controversial and many there estimated as lower.  </p>
<p>He said the situation in the United States was different from that in Australia because it did not change its basket of CPI goods as often as Australia.</p>
<p>Macfarlane said any overestimate of inflation would have more implications for fiscal policy, because many benefits are indexed to inflation through the CPI.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
