<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570854" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian dlr rallies, RBA/data rule out rate cut.</title>
<headline>Australian dlr rallies, RBA/data rule out rate cut.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian dollar rallied past US$0.7790 resistance at the midsession after upbeat jobs data and a hawkish policy statement from the Reserve Bank eclipsed all thought of an easing in the foreseeable future.</p>
<p>Employment bounced 37,100 in April to more than compensate for March's shock 33,900 fall and soothe concerns further weakness would have trigger a rate cut from the RBA.</p>
<p>RBA governor Ian Macfarlane, asked about the data during Parliamentary testimony, said he was relieved by the rise and saw no economic gain out of cutting rates again given the bank's belief that economic growth would hit 4.0 percent in 1997/98.  </p>
<p>By 12.15 pm (0215 GMT) the local dollar had bounded to US$0.7793/98 from an early US$0.7775/80 and US$0.7756/61 late here Wednesday.</p>
<p>Traders said fresh offers had emerged at 78 cents with U.S. and Japanese sellers to the fore, and may cap the currency at least for the remainder of the local day.</p>
<p>The dollar had edged higher overnight in anticipation of an upbeat economic outlook for Macfarlane, who was giving his first semi-annual statement on monetary policy, and bull were not disappointed as he surprised some by confidently predicting four percent growth in the year ahead.  </p>
<p>The report from the central bank said there were already signs of a pick up in activity, particularly in housing, construction and consumer spending, and the low interest rates already in place would support this.</p>
<p>The outlook for inflation was favourable in the near-term aided by the strong dollar and the recent moderate settlement of the Living Wage claim. However, aggregate wages growth had risen to levels which were uncomfortably high and any further significant acceleration would require a policy response.</p>
<p>The market took all this as confirmation rates were probably on hold for the rest of the year and yields backed-up.  </p>
<p>&quot;Macfarlane thinks interest rates are not too high, not too low but just right -- at least for now,&quot; said John Edwards, chief economist at HSBC markets.</p>
<p>&quot;Another rate cut is ruled out if the economy grows as the RBA expects, but with continued low inflation a rate increase is unlikely in the near term,&quot; was how he summed it up.</p>
<p>The futures market abandoned all hope of an easing and began to think of a tightening next year with the June 90-day bill contract off seven basis points to 93.97 and the December contract losing nine to 93.56, implying a rate of 6.44 percent against the current official cash rate of 6.00 percent.  </p>
<p>That all but removed one potential threat to the dollar's interest advantage over the US$ and should underpin its recent floor at US$0.7720.</p>
<p>However, analysts still felt it likely the Federal Reserve would hike U.S. rates at its policy meeting on May 20 and this threat would make it hard for the dollar to sustain a rally past last week's US$0.7860 high.</p>
<p>On the crosses, the currency was unable to make ground on a firmer yen, which had benefited from rises in Japanese stock and bond prices this week, and stood steady at 97.39/49 yen from 97.38/48 late here Wednesday.  </p>
<p>The dollar did extend a bounce against sterling as soft U.K. economic data forced the market to reined back expectations of further interest rate hikes there. It was up at 0.4823/28 stg from from 0.4740/46 late Wednesday.</p>
<p>In trade weighted terms the dollar edged up to 60.5 from a previous 60.3 close.</p>
<p>Dealers noted the RBA's Macfarlane had sounded relaxed with the strength of the currency on a TWI basis saying the bank had long tolerated significant swings in the currency. The comment should help ease concerns the RBA might intervene if the dollar rose further on the TWI. -- Wayne Cole 61-2 9373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
