<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570861" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Long-lasting growth key to cutting jobless - RBA.</title>
<headline>Long-lasting growth key to cutting jobless - RBA.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) Governor Ian Macfarlane said on Thursday the central bank was interested in cutting Australia's high unemployment rate and that long-lasting growth was the best way of reducing it.</p>
<p>He said he saw the prospects for an economic recovery lasting another three, four or five years.</p>
<p>&quot;The most successful way to bring down the unemployment rate is to foster a long-lasting expansion,&quot; Macfarlane told a federal committee when asked why he should not cut rates again now that inflation was low and unemployment was still high.  </p>
<p>&quot;We consider the totality of the economy when we make our decision about monetary policy and we certainly are interested in trying to bring down the rate of unemployment,&quot; Macfarlane told a parliamentary hearing.</p>
<p>&quot;We agree with everyone, if you've got inflation of 2.5 percent and unemployment of 8.75 percent, the thing that needs to be improved is the unemployment, not the inflation.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe the most successful way of doing that is by achieving a long-lasting expansion.&quot;</p>
<p>Figures released earlier showed unemployment still stuck at 8.7 percent in April and employment rising by 37,100.  </p>
<p>Macfarlane said to ensure lasting economic recovery all economic data had to be &quot;in balance&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;We think we have got the prospect of a long recovery this time. We are looking out three, four or five years and we want to make sure we manage this one in such a way that we get the longest recovery we can...,&quot; Macfarlane said.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment most things are under reasonable sort of control. Certainly inflation looks good, but we have to look wider than that...,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;One of the things we have to look at, which is very important, is wages. It is a bit disturbing that the one bit of the expansion that is out of whack is that we have wages growth which is higher than any of the other economies that are running a 2.0 percent inflation rate.</p>
<p>&quot;If we want to have a balanced recovery we should be having at this stage of the game lower wages growth than we are getting.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
