<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570841" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: FOCUS - Pepsico to sell its NZ jewels.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Pepsico to sell its NZ jewels.</headline>
<byline>James Gray</byline>
<dateline>AUCKLAND 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pepsico Inc is to sell the jewel in its international crown through an initial public offering (IPO) of shares in its 122 New Zealand restaurants, the new company, Restaurant Brands NZ Ltd, said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The float of 85 million shares between NZ$1.80-2.20 each will value the company at NZ$187 million (US$128 million) if the institutional tender prices them at the top of the range.</p>
<p>This will put the company among New Zealand's top 40 by market capitalisation and will make it the largest public offer since Tranz Rail last June.</p>
<p>Funds raised would be employed to effectively buy the businesses from the parent, forming a stand alone unit.</p>
<p>Pepsico's rationale for selling was that it considered franchisees achieved a better outcome from running restaurants.</p>
<p>The Purchase, New York-based food and beverage giant plans to divest KFC, Taco Bell and Pizza Hut in the U.S. but Collier said the move to go public here was a separate issue.</p>
<p>KFC and Pizza Hut are two of the three largest fast food chains in New Zealand, the other being McDonalds.</p>
<p>Restaurant Brands chief executive Jim Collier told a news conference the offer was the only opportunity for investment in the fast food industry on the local market.</p>
<p>New Zealand had been chosen because its chains were principally owned by the parent, with just nine owned by small, independent franchisees.</p>
<p>Secondly, there was the success of KFC in New Zealand.</p>
<p>&quot;Pound for pound, KFC (NZ) is probably the most successful KFC business anywhere in the world,&quot; he said. &quot;It is effectively the crown jewels.&quot;</p>
<p>Total sales last year were NZ$221 million, 80 percent from KFC and 20 percent from Pizza Hut.</p>
<p>Collier said there was substantial potential in Pizza Hut due to the rapid growth in home delivery sales.</p>
<p>Since 1992 KFC's compound annual growth rate in sales was 12 percent and compound earnings were 18 percent.</p>
<p>For every NZ$100 spent by New Zealanders on food, NZ$20 is spent in restaurants and on takeaways and $80 in supermarkets -- a low fast food proportion by Australian and the U.S. standards.</p>
<p>&quot;Social forces are taking us there and we believe that percentage will grow. That will underpin growth in the fast food market for a long time to come,&quot; Collier said.</p>
<p>Restaurant Brands would not totally sever its links with Pepsico -- it would have access to its global advertising resources and would pay it six percent of sales in royalties.</p>
<p>It also has first right of refusal to start up the Taco Bell Mexican-style fast food chain in New Zealand.</p>
<p>Restaurant Brands is effectively taking over the business half-way through its financial year to November.</p>
<p>Based on those remaining six months, a 4.6 cents per share dividend is planned for this year and an 11.4 cent payout is forecast for the full 1998 year.</p>
<p>Sales totalled NZ$220.6 million in 1996 and are forecast to rise to $232 million in 1997 and $254.9 million in 1998.</p>
<p>Net profit after tax is expected to come in at NZ$11.3 million in 1996/7, and $13.9 million in 1997/8.</p>
<p>Chairman Bill Falconer also chairs St Lukes a shopping mall owner, and Hellaby Holdings Ltd, which has interests in retailing.</p>
<p>The public offering, which is underwritten by Pepsico, closes on May 13 for retail investors and on June 3 for institutions. Listing is expected on June 4.</p>
<p>US$1 = NZ$1.44</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I66100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AUCKLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
