<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570813" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FOCUS-RBA's Macfarlane sees six pct jobless limit.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-RBA's Macfarlane sees six pct jobless limit.</headline>
<byline>Bernard Hickey</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian economy, even if it expands at full pace for several more years, would struggle to push the unemployment rate below six percent, Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) Governor Ian Macfarlane said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Effectively pencilling in his view on where he thought Australia's natural rate of unemployment was, Macfarlane told a parliamentary committee that genuine structural reform was needed to push that limit any lower.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a very difficult task,&quot; Macfarlane said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Over a very long period, if you had complete success in running a long and sustainable expansion you should get back to that lowest unemployment rate you had in the previous expansion,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said he was referring to the unemployment rate of about six percent reached in late 1989, before it bounded back up to a high of 11.2 percent in November 1992.</p>
<p>The unemployment rate has since dropped to a trough of about 8.4 percent in September 1995, but has stubbornly remained at or above this apparent limit since then.  </p>
<p>Jobs data for April showed seasonally adjusted unemployment was steady at 8.7 percent.</p>
<p>Answering persistent queries from conservative and Labor parliamentarians alike about what the bank could do about unemployment, Macfarlane said structural reform was needed for cuts below the six percent level.</p>
<p>He nominated the British, U.S. and New Zealand economies as examples of those who have managed to cut unemployment to levels of around five percent.</p>
<p>These countries operated deregulated labour markets and had reformed much of their economies, often at some pain, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The evidence does seem to suggest that the deregulated systems do produce better results in terms of lower unemployment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Australia would have to look at deregulating its labour markets and social security systems further if it wanted to make these extra inroads into unemployment, he said.</p>
<p>Macfarlane acknowledged that these changes were often painful and evoked a noisy reaction.</p>
<p>&quot;I accept that a heavily deregulatory path does have its shortcomings, but I think a commitment has to be made to making that decision,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>In the meantime, the Reserve Bank would focus on sustainable growth as the best way to cut unemployment, rather than pumping up growth for an employment payoff that would dissolve along with the resulting inflation.</p>
<p>Macfarlane essentially rejected the view put by some parliamentarians that the RBA could afford to cut rates again because inflation was under control.</p>
<p>&quot;Our view is that we are playing the long run, we do believe we are going to have four percent growth over '97, we do believe that that will continue, and we don't believe we will gain anything by having another movement at the moment.&quot;  </p>
<p>Macfarlane's hawkish view on economic growth was backed up by his comments on wages, where he said wages set by the decentralised enterprise bargaining sector should not rise beyond their current four to five percent.</p>
<p>However, he noted that the wages growth generated by the newly deregulated sector may have peaked, as managers adjusted to the new system and only agreed to wage deals they could afford. &quot;It could be that a peak in enterprise bargains (wages growth) has been reached,&quot; he said in his testimony.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
