<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570828" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Force with News only briefly - analysts.</title>
<headline>Force with News only briefly - analysts.</headline>
<byline>Paul Tait</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The force may have been with News Corp so far this year but more earthly dangers await Rupert Murdoch's global media empire, analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>News Corp announced on Thursday a 34 percent rise in net profit before abnormals to A$376 million in the three months to March 31, driven largely by Fox Television and Fox Film's re-release of the Star Wars movie trilogy.</p>
<p>Net profits after abnormals were A$330 million, up from A$77 million in the same period last year.  </p>
<p>British newspapers and BkyB also produced significant profit contributions, while News' book publishing amd Australasian newspaper and pay television were the main drags on profit, News said.</p>
<p>Murdoch last year predicted that News could achieve a 20 percent profit rise for the year to June 30, 1997, a forecast that was not borne out by first-half results.</p>
<p>A Sydney-based analyst estimated News would report a net profit of A$1.64 billion before abnormals for the 1996/97 year.</p>
<p>&quot;They are probably going to achieve (the 20 percent profit growth),&quot; the analyst said.  </p>
<p>Other analysts said the third quarter profit was not enough to make them change their forecasts.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall, the result is at the higher end of market expectations but it's not enough to get people excited,&quot; a Melbourne-based analyst said.</p>
<p>Filmed Entertainment revenues rose sharply to A$1.138 billion from A$584 million, although its operating income had a more modest rise from A$82 million from A$63 million in the same period a year earlier.  </p>
<p>Analysts, however, say the film arm will crash back down to earth in the last quarter and early in the next financial year because of two disaster movies -- &quot;Volcano&quot; and &quot;Titanic&quot;.</p>
<p>The geologically-challenged &quot;Volcano&quot; reportedly cost about US$100 million to make but had a cumulative gross of US$27 million to May 5.</p>
<p>The release of &quot;Titanic&quot;, reputedly the most expensive movie ever made, has been pushed back past the traditional U.S. opening date of July 4.</p>
<p>&quot;Titanic won't affect them this year but Volcano will be a loss-maker,&quot; a Melbourne analyst said.  </p>
<p>&quot;There's no way film will be the same next year.&quot;</p>
<p>News Corp shares fell despite the strong third quarter result.</p>
<p>Analysts said investors were still wary of investing in News Corp until it sorts out its U.S. satellite TV business American Sky Broadcasting (ASkyB).</p>
<p>Uncertainty surrounds News Corp's ASkyB plans following its tie-up with Echostar Communications Corp. The venture has run into several problems since the deal was announced in February.  </p>
<p>&quot;The prevailing issue remains ASkyB and until that issue is resolved satisfactorily it is going to remain a big problem for them,&quot; a Sydney analyst said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34430">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
