<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570889" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China demands action on Japan MP in islands row.</title>
<headline>China demands action on Japan MP in islands row.</headline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>China urged Japan on Thursday to take action against a Japanese parliamentarian for landing on one of a group of disputed islands in the East China Sea.</p>
<p>Japan &quot;should take action against the people who illegally landed on the Diaoyu Islands&quot;, Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Shen Guofang told a news briefing without specifying what type of action Beijing had in mind.</p>
<p>Shingo Nishimura, a conservative member of Japan's main opposition New Frontier Party, and three other people on Tuesday landed on one of the islands, called the Senkakus in Japanese and the Diaoyus in Chinese, to inspect security and hold a brief commemorative ceremony.</p>
<p>The Japanese prefecture of Okinawa administers the disputed islands, which are also claimed by Beijing's arch-rival Taiwan.</p>
<p>The dispute over the uninhabited outcrops in the East China Sea threatened to put China and Japan on a new collision course just as ties were returning to normal.</p>
<p>Japan has claimed the islands since 1895, while China says it has owned them for centuries. Waters around the islands are rich fishing grounds and are believed to contain oil and gas reserves.</p>
<p>Shen, the Chinese spokesman, said there were certain differences between China and Japan over the islands but that Beijing advocated holding talks to resolve those differences.</p>
<p>Japan has been quick to distance itself from Nishimura's group, which included former cabinet minister Shintaro Ishihara, author of the 1980s nationalist treatise &quot;A Japan That Can Say No&quot;.</p>
<p>But Shen said Tokyo was not trying hard enough and should take effective measures to prevent illegal landings in future.</p>
<p>In Taipei, Taiwan demonstrators threw eggs and scuffled with police while trying to storm Japan's de facto embassy in Taipei on Thursday to protest against the landing.</p>
<p>The islands ignited nationalist passions in Chinese communities in Hong Kong and Taiwan last year after a Japanese right-wing group built a makeshift lighthouse there.</p>
<p>The lighthouse drew vessels carrying Taiwan and Hong Kong protesters, several of whom briefly landed on the islands. A Hong Kong activist drowned last September when he jumped into stormy waters near the islands to press China's claim.</p>
<p>The latest episode has been an embarrassment for Japanese Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto, who hopes to exchange visits with Chinese counterpart Li Peng this year to mark the 25th anniversary of bilateral ties.</p>
<p>In recent months, Beijing-Tokyo ties, including a resumption of Japanese aid, have got back on track after they were frozen over China's nuclear testing.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
