<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570893" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Dlr stays weak below 125 yen by late Tokyo.</title>
<headline>Dlr stays weak below 125 yen by late Tokyo.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar remained weak, hovering below 125 yen by late afternoon Tokyo on Thursday on sales partly due to a rise in Japanese market interest rates and reported comments by a senior official at the Ministry of Finance (MOF), dealers said.</p>
<p>But the greenback was supported near 124.60 yen during Asian trading time on sporadic bids from importers.  </p>
<p>Eisuke Sakakibara, director-general of the Ministry of Finance's International Finance Bureau, was quoted by Jiji news agency as saying he is worried about increasing investments in foreign bonds by Japanese investors.</p>
<p>It said he told a parliamentary committee meeting: &quot;There are some foreign bonds which carry interest rates of five to six percent. But they would not yield anything if the yen were to rise by six yen against the dollar. Investments must be made with sufficient consideration given to foreign exchange risks.&quot;</p>
<p>His comments caused some brief sales by traders in the afternoon, keeping sentiment bearish for the dollar.  </p>
<p>&quot;Sakakibara's comments came out when the dollar was seen recovering a little, so the comments pushed the dollar down again. But I think the impact is limited for now,&quot; a dealer at a European bank said.</p>
<p>The yield of the key 182nd JGBs briefly rose to 2.500 percent in late trade, up from 2.425 percent on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is somewhat sensitive to moves in interest rates, whose rise may indicate that the Japanese economy is cheering up,&quot; a city bank dealer said. But he said he was not yet sure if the strength in the Japanese economy was genuine.  </p>
<p>In addition to sales in reaction to a rise in Japanese market interest rates, sales by U.S. operators were detected, dealers said.</p>
<p>In the morning, life insurers were said to be buying dollars for yen around 124.90 yen. But after the greenback clearly broke through that level in the afternoon, importers were seen to be buyers, supporting the dollar near 124.60 yen.</p>
<p>A dealer in Singapore said the dollar was likely to hover around its current levels for the time being, but if the Fed failed to raise rates at its meeting later this month, it could come off to 120 yen.  </p>
<p>The dollar tumbled against the yen in reaction to Sakakibara's latest comments that it is possible for the yen to strengthen to 103 yen to the dollar. A city bank dealer said the dollar fell sharply to around 123.70 yen following his comments. By 0707 GMT, the dollar stood at 124.00/05 yen.</p>
<p>The dealer in Singapore said the pound was still being sold due to uncertainties over the direction the new Labour government would take, after an overnight report quoting an unnamed Labour source saying sterling should rejoin Europe's exchange rate mechanism (ERM) in 2001 at a rate of 2.50 marks, well below its current rate.  </p>
<p>But a bank dealer in Tokyo said short-covering pushed up the pound later in the day, adding that sterling remains an attractive currency to buy in view of relatively high British interest rates.</p>
<p>The dollar fell against the mark mostly in tandem with falls in the dollar/yen rate. But a Japanese bank dealer said some Swiss operators were keen to sell dollars for marks in the afternoon in an attempt to set off stop-loss sales near 1.7170 marks.</p>
<p>--- Tokyo Treasury Desk, +81-3-3432-8584</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
