<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570818" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RBA confidence fails to rub off on Australian dlr.</title>
<headline>RBA confidence fails to rub off on Australian dlr.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian dollar edged higher Thursday, but the modest rally was less than convicing given the Reserve Bank had all but removed the risk of another rate cut.</p>
<p>RBA governor Ian Macarlane raised eyebrows with a confident prediction of 4.0 percent GDP growth in 1997/98 while ruling out another easing as unwarranted. The upbeat note echoed in April employment data which bounced by 37,000, a huge relief to A$ bulls who had feared a weak outcome would force the RBA to cut.</p>
<p>&quot;Macfarlane thinks interest rates are not too high, not too low but just right -- at least for now,&quot; said John Edwards, chief economist at HSBC markets.  </p>
<p>By 4.40 pm (0640 GMT) an indecisive dollar was hovering at US$0.7776/81 from an early US$0.7770/75 and US$0.7756/61 late here Wednesday.</p>
<p>It had probed as high as US$0.7799 in the wake of the jobs data, but traders said fresh offers emerged there with U.S. investment banks selling in size while hedge funds and Tokyo securities houses dumped AUD/yen.</p>
<p>The failure to clear 78 cents on such unambiguously favourable news spoke volumes about how bearish sentiment had become, and left dealers looking to sell into any strength for an eventual re-test of the recent floor at US$0.7720.  </p>
<p>The dollar had edged higher overnight in anticipation of an upbeat economic outlook from the RBA and Macfarlane, who was giving his first semi-annual statement on monetary policy.</p>
<p>The bank's report emphasised there were signs of a pick up in activity, noteably in housing and consumer spending, and the low interest rates already in place would support this.</p>
<p>The outlook for inflation was favourable in the near-term, aided by the strong dollar and the recent moderate settlement of the Living Wage claim. However, it warned aggregate wages growth had risen to levels which were uncomfortably high and any further acceleration would require a policy response.  </p>
<p>The market took all this as confirmation rates were on hold for the rest of the year and yields backed-up across the curve.</p>
<p>&quot;It's clear the RBA sees cash rates on lengthy hold at 6.0 percent,&quot; said UBS Australia economist Stephen Roberts, adding a cut was now a very remote possibility.</p>
<p>&quot;The April labour force data backed up the RBA view of the economy almost perfectly,&quot; he noted. Employment bounced 37,100, matching market forecasts and compensating for March's shock 33,900 fall. This still left the unemployment rate stubbornly high at 8.7 percent but most analysts agreed with Macfarlane's view the rate would fall, albeit slowly, as growth picked up.  </p>
<p>The futures market abandoned all hope of an easing and began to contemplate a tightening next year with the December 90-day bank bill contract losing nine basis points to 93.56, implying a rate of 6.44 percent against the present 6.00 percent.</p>
<p>That removed a domestic threat to the dollar's interest advantage over the US$ and dealers felt it should at least help underpin the currency's recent floor around US$0.7720.</p>
<p>However, they also reckoned the Federal Reserve would hike U.S. rates to 5.75 percent at its policy meeting on May 20 and this threat would make it hard for the dollar to sustain a rally past last week's US$0.7860 high.  </p>
<p>&quot;Australian cash rates at 6.00 percent provide little or no differential benefit compared with U.S. and British short term rates,&quot; noted Roberts at UBS.</p>
<p>On the crosses the currency lost more ground to the yen, which had benefited from rises in Japanese stock and bond prices this week, to stand at 97.08/18 from 97.38/48 late Wednesday.</p>
<p>The dollar managed a bounce against sterling as market suspicions the new Labour government favoured a softer pound were fed by an unsourced report quoting an unnamed Labour official saying sterling should join the ERM in 2001 at a rate of 2.5000 marks.  </p>
<p>But dealers also had suspicions about the report, noting neither the ERM or the mark would exist in 2001 since the single currency would have replaced them.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the dollar firmed to 0.4812/19 stg from from 0.4740/46 late Wednesday. In trade weighted terms the dollar eased to 60.2 from a previous 60.3 close.</p>
<p>Dealers noted the RBA's Macfarlane had sounded relaxed with the strength of the dollar on a TWI basis saying the bank had long tolerated significant swings in the currency. The comment should help ease concerns the RBA might intervene if the dollar rose further on the TWI. -- Wayne Cole 61-2 9373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
