<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570896" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila shares ebb lower at close, off day's low.</title>
<headline>Manila shares ebb lower at close, off day's low.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>------------------------- May 8 -----------------------------</p>
<p>* Blue chips mixed as foreign investors stay out</p>
<p>-------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Manila shares recovered part of the sharp losses from early trade but ended lower than the previous day's level as the market remained tentative, brokers said.</p>
<p>The composite index closed at 2,682.10, which is 12.30 points or 0.46 percent lower than Wednesday's close. The index fell to a low of 2,654.20 in early trade.</p>
<p>&quot;We recovered somewhat after an initial selldown on the blue chips,&quot; Allan Araullo of Regina Capital Development Corp said.  </p>
<p>Jose Maria Ricardo Garcia, vice president of Diversified Securities, said the market remained cautious even if selling pressure from foreign houses had abated by midsession.</p>
<p>&quot;People are very tentative ... There was just some buying support in select shares from the locals,&quot; Garcia said.</p>
<p>Oil refiner Petron Corp closed 20 centavos higher at 8.50 pesos and phone giant Philippine Long Distance Telephone gained 10 pesos to 755 pesos.</p>
<p>Ayala Corp B dipped 25 centavos to 17 pesos.  </p>
<p>The mixed performance of the blue chips indicates a consolidation mood in the market, Araullo said.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors are looking for reasons to come back to the market,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>-- RAMONCITO DELA CRUZ (63 2) 841-8938 Fax 817-6267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
