<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570939" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Sterling recovers from overnight lows, seen higher.</title>
<headline>Sterling recovers from overnight lows, seen higher.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sterling made a healthy recovery during Asian trade on Thursday after its sharp sell-off in New York overnight, and was seen heading higher in the near term, Singapore dealers said.</p>
<p>The British unit was actively bought from the 1.6140 dollars level in Asia after dropping on a news agency report suggesting the Labour Party supported a weaker sterling.</p>
<p>&quot;There's been a lot of short-covering of sterling and sterling/mark. The investment houses that were selling sterling in New York last night were buying it back this morning and have continued to do so,&quot; a European bank dealer said.</p>
<p>Sterling fell more than two cents overnight after a Bridge News report quoted a Labour Party source saying sterling should rejoin Europe's exchange rate mechanism in 2001 at a rate of 2.50 marks, well below its current level of 2.7840.</p>
<p>The U.K. Treasury said there was no truth in the report.</p>
<p>The dealer said the sterling's recovery was helped by the dollar's overall weakness against major currencies on Thursday.  </p>
<p>Stop-loss buying orders were triggered from 1.6210 to 1.6250 in cable and from the 2.7820 level upwards on the sterling/mark cross, the dealer said, adding that sterling could easily head back up to 1.6350-1.6400.</p>
<p>&quot;At this stage, the market's just susceptible to comments from politicians and news. They're really waiting to see what the official Labour Party position is on the level of the pound,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom (65-8703080)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
