<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570966" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Shanghai A index falls 5.14 pct ahead of close.</title>
<headline>Shanghai A index falls 5.14 pct ahead of close.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Shanghai A share index was down 80.360 points or 5.14 percent to 1,482.290 ten minutes ahead of the close as major institutional investors sold on concerns that Beijing could take steps to cool down the market, brokers said.  </p>
<p>Official financial newspapers have recently published a series of articles warning investors of risks in the stock markets.</p>
<p>A leading Chinese economist was also quoted in Thursday's Shanghai-based Business News as saying the time had come to consider listing state shares and institutional shares, which are currently banned from being traded.</p>
<p>One Hong Kong newspaper said on Thursday that China's Ministry of Finance was considering increased stamp taxes for trading stocks from the current 0.3 percent to 0.4 or 0.5 percent.</p>
<p>Brokers said these factors had all increased investor concern over a possible government crackdown, which made some big institutions offset their large positions, resulted in sharp losses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
