<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570917" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan's 'Mr Yen' pulls rug out from under dollar.</title>
<headline>Japan's 'Mr Yen' pulls rug out from under dollar.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's &quot;Mr Yen&quot; sent the dollar sliding on Thursday, stoking fears of central bank intervention when he said it is possible the Japanese currency could rise as high as 103 to the dollar.</p>
<p>Senior Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara, whose power to move markets with his words has earned him the sobriquet &quot;Mr Yen&quot;, told a parliamentary panel that a stronger yen was possible given past foreign exchange fluctuations.</p>
<p>&quot;Looking at currency fluctuations over the past 10 years, (the dollar-yen rate) moved at an annual average of 23 yen per dollar. This year, the yen weakened up to 127.50 yen to the dollar. If you subtract 23 yen, it is theoretically possible for the yen to strengthen to about 103 yen,&quot; Sakakibara said.</p>
<p>Sakakibara's comment triggered a flood of dollar sales, causing the U.S. currency to drop as low as 123.42 yen in Tokyo from around 124.75 shortly before he spoke. The dollar had closed at 124.97 yen in New York on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Currency traders saw the remarks, which came on the heels of a report on Wednesday by Kyodo news agency that the United States, Germany and Japan had started to prepare for joint intervention to prop up the weak yen, as evidence of a strenuous effort by Japanese authorities to talk down the dollar.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course, 103 yen is unbelievable, but his (Sakakibara's) comments are gradually becoming more concrete and serious,&quot; one commercial bank dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;They (Japanese officials) are likely to be satisfied if it gets near 120 yen, hopefully without joint intervention.&quot;</p>
<p>The finance ministry downplayed Sakakibara's remark, saying it was not to be taken as a forecast of exchange rate movements.</p>
<p>&quot;(Sakakibara's comment) is not something that indicates a prediction of future market movements,&quot; vice finance minister Tadashi Ogawa told reporters shortly after the comment was made.</p>
<p>Sakakibara, director-general of the ministry's International Finance Bureau, also said he feared individual Japanese investors were putting too many funds into foreign bonds and foreign currency deposits without considering currency risks.</p>
<p>Asked if there was a danger of individual Japanese assets, estimated at around 1,200 trillion yen ($9.7 trillion), flowing overseas after the liberalisation of foreign exchange laws, Sakakibara said:</p>
<p>&quot;When looking at individual's foreign bond investments and foreign currency deposits, I'm worried that people are investing without thorough consideration to currency risks, although it is up to them to make the...investments.&quot;</p>
<p>Similar remarks reported by Jiji news agency earlier in the day were already dampening sentiment for the greenback, as were a rise in Japanese market interest rates.</p>
<p>The dollar has risen 10 percent so far this year against the yen, reaching a 56-month high of 127.47 yen on May 1.</p>
<p>Financial leaders from the Group of Seven (G7) leading industrialised countries met in Washington at the end of April and said they would monitor exchange rates and cooperate as appropriate, adding that currency values should reflect fundamentals and excess volatility was undesirable.</p>
<p>The G7 comprises Japan, the United States, Germany, Britain, France, Italy and Canada. ($1=123 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
