<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570926" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Shanghai copper ends mostly up on LME gains.</title>
<headline>Shanghai copper ends mostly up on LME gains.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shanghai copper futures ended mostly up on Thursday on overnight gains on the London Metal Exchange (LME), traders said.</p>
<p>The most activly traded August 1998 contract ended up at an intraday low of 23,450 yuan ($2,827) per tonne, rising 90 yuan. It opened at a high of 23,600 yuan per tonne.</p>
<p>May was unchanged at 23,300 yuan, June rose 20 to 23,400, July 120 to 23,470, September 130 to 23,480, October 110 to 23,400 yuan.</p>
<p>Combined volume fell to 29,550 tonnes from 30,460 tonnes.  </p>
<p>Copper opened higher but profit-taking prevented the red metal from rising further for most of the session.</p>
<p>Traders said LME gains on Wednesday had spurred the confidence of long position holders but local copper met strong selling pressure at high levels.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors took advantage of the LME gains to liquidate their long positions at high levels,&quot; one trader said, adding investors were unsure what direction the market would take.</p>
<p>LME copper traded in a sideways band on Wednesday but after a positive close at $2,368/70 were forecast to test overhead resistance on Thursday.  </p>
<p>The physical price is around 23,300 yuan per tonne in the Shanghai area.</p>
<p>Trading sources predicted a rise in physical prices in the short term on rumours that a shipment of about 1,000 tonnes of copper had been held up at Shanghai port. The market talk could not be confirmed with customs authorities.</p>
<p>Traders said active domestic A shares were attracting the attention of many investors.</p>
<p>&quot;More and more investors want to enter the stock market for quick profits,&quot; a second trader said.  </p>
<p>Analysts said they expected copper to move above the key support level of 23,000 yuan in the next few days.</p>
<p>Aluminium ended up. May rose 30 yuan to 15,300, June 50 to 15,600, July 300 to 15,900 and the first traded August 1998 contract ended at 16,050.</p>
<p>Combined volume rose to 1,340 tonnes from 800 tonnes.</p>
<p>($1=8.2934 yuan)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
