<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570919" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Cambodian king says ready to face genocide tribunal.</title>
<headline>Cambodian king says ready to face genocide tribunal.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cambodia's King Norodom Sihanouk says he is prepared to face trial alongside Pol Pot and other Khmer Rouge leaders to fight charges he was partly responsible for the killing fields rule of the late 1970s.</p>
<p>Sihanouk, in an interview in Beijing on Wednesday with staff of his monthly bulletin, said he had always firmly supported the idea of holding an international tribunal to try the guerrilla leaders for the abuses of their 1975-79 regime.</p>
<p>&quot;I will ask the international tribunal, once it is set up, to judge me equally and at the same time as (Khmer Rouge leaders) Pol Pot, Ieng Sary, Ta Mok, Son Sen, Nuon Chea, Khieu Samphan, etc,&quot; he said in the interview, released on Thursday.</p>
<p>Sihanouk firmly denied responsibility for the crimes against humanity committed under Pol Pot's regime and said he was ready to set aside his royal immunity from prosecution.</p>
<p>&quot;I will not fail to appear in person before this international tribunal,&quot; said the 74-year-old monarch, who is in China for medical treatment.</p>
<p>The king's pledge was prompted by continued accusations from opponents that Sihanouk must share part of the blame for the excesses of the Khmer Rouge, whose regime killed more than one million people through execution, starvation, disease and overwork.</p>
<p>The king's critics argue the Maoist-inspired group could not have toppled the Lon Nol republican government in 1975 without the support of Sihanouk after his ouster in 1970 by Lon Nol.</p>
<p>Sihanouk gave a detailed defence against the charges and noted he had been kept under palace arrest and many of his children and relatives killed during Pol Pot's rule.</p>
<p>Lawyers and researchers funded by the U.S. State Department believe the Khmer Rouge leadership are liable for trial on charges of genocide and other crimes against humanity.</p>
<p>U.N. human rights officials have said Cambodia should set up some form of truth commission, like those in South Africa and Latin Ameria, to ensure that the lessons of its past are not lost on future generations.</p>
<p>Vietnamese forces in 1979 toppled the Khmer Rouge, who later spearheaded the fight against a Hanoi-backed Phnom Penh regime. The rebel group reneged on a 1991 U.N.-brokered peace pact and had been fighting the government formed after 1993 elections.</p>
<p>Ieng Sary, former deputy premier and foreign minister, split with hardliners loyal to Pol Pot in August. Thousands of guerrillas have since defected to the government, leaving only a small force in the north.</p>
<p>Ieng Sary had been sentenced to death in absentia for his role in Pol Pot's regime. He joined the government only after receiving a pardon from Sihanouk, but could still technically be tried by a new tribunal.</p>
<p>But analysts doubt he or any other of the surviving top leaders, who are still at large, will be brought to justice.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
