<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570914" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan parliament passes minority Ainu rights law.</title>
<headline>Japan parliament passes minority Ainu rights law.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan on Thursday passed a law to preserve the culture of aboriginal Ainu people, the first legislation acknowledging the existence of an ethnic minority in a country that has long identified itself as monoracial.</p>
<p>The law passed by parliament to preserve the traditions of the Ainu, once hunter-gatherers who have inhabited northern Japan since prehistoric times, replaces a controversial 1899 statute that activists say has long served to discriminate against Ainu.</p>
<p>The legislation stops short, however, of designating the Ainu as an indigenous ethnic group, an omission reflecting the government's fear of future legal challenges on aboriginal rights to land and natural resources.</p>
<p>A non-binding resolution attached to the bill, however, designates the Ainu, whose population of about 25,000 live mainly on Japan's northernmost main island of Hokkaido, as an indigenous ethnic group.</p>
<p>Ainu, who have since World War Two fought to scrap the old bill aimed at assimilating them, stepped up their campaign to have their culture recognised in 1986 after then-prime minister Yasuhiro Nakasone told parliament Japan was a monoracial country.</p>
<p>&quot;The old Hokkaido Former Aborigine Protection Law was created without the prior knowledge of the Ainu, but the new law by and large reflects Ainu aspirations,&quot; said Shigeru Kayano, Japan's first and only Ainu member of parliament.</p>
<p>Kayano said his people would push for full recognition as indigenous inhabitants, saying, &quot;Japan should not be the only place in the world which does not recognise aboriginal rights.&quot;</p>
<p>The law sets up funds to study and transmit Ainu culture to future generations. But Ainu activists say it does not go far enough in restoring the culture and rights they have lost over the centuries.</p>
<p>Jiro Sasamura, head of the 15,000-member Ainu Association of Hokkaido, called the legislation &quot;only the first phase&quot; in the Ainu campaign.</p>
<p>For centuries, Japanese traders and warriors massacred or exploited the Ainu, discriminating against them as primitive hunter-gatherers.</p>
<p>In 1868, when Japan opened itself to the outside world after two-and-a-half centuries of isolation, it became official Japanese policy to abolish the culture of the Ainu, whose language and religious ceremonies were banned.</p>
<p>When Japan ratified the U.N. Human Rights Charter in 1979, the government reported to the United Nations that there was no minority race in Japan. The government retracted the statement in 1991.</p>
<p>The Ainu, along with Japan-born Koreans and Chinese and &quot;burakumin&quot;, a hereditary &quot;untouchable&quot; caste, have suffered varying degrees of unequal treatment as tiny minorities in the country of 124 million.</p>
<p>The average income of an Ainu in Hokkaido was 3.02 million yen ($24,100) in 1993, compared with 5.55 million yen ($44,400) for the average Hokkaido resident. ($=125 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
