<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570915" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan opposition parties to demand new cabinet.</title>
<headline>Taiwan opposition parties to demand new cabinet.</headline>
<byline>Alice Hung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan's opposition lawmakers said on Thursday they would demand that the president appoint a new premier, escalating a political showdown amid a mounting public outcry over the island's worsening social order.</p>
<p>Lawmakers from the main opposition Democratic Progressive Party and the fledgling New Party sought support for a motion asking President Lee Teng-hui to call for a complete cabinet reshuffle and replace incumbent Premier Lien Chan.</p>
<p>&quot;Public discontent is boiling. We want President Lee to name a new premier,&quot; Chen Chung-hsin, deputy secretary-general of the pro-independence Democratic Progressive Party, told Reuters in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very inappropriate for the president to retain Lien Chan as premier and find a few scapegoats to take responsibility,&quot; Chen said. &quot;This is not what the public wants. It's simply unacceptable.&quot;</p>
<p>A New Party official, who declined to be identified, said the party would support the Democratic Progressive Party's case.</p>
<p>Under Taiwan's political system, such a motion to the president would not be legally binding.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Lee asked Lien to make some changes in cabinet positions next week in an effort to appease a public outcry over a spate of violent crimes. But he declined to accept Lien's resignation offer.</p>
<p>The discovery of the naked body of 17-year-old Pai Hsiao-yen, daughter of actress Pai Ping-ping, floating in a river last week caused a public outcry.</p>
<p>Police said 17-year-old Pai Hsiao-yen had been kidnapped and murdered. Her killers remained at large.</p>
<p>The murder followed a string of violent crimes since 1996.</p>
<p>More than 50,000 people marched in Taipei on Sunday to protest against Pai's murder and demand the resignation of Lien and a cabinet reshuffle.</p>
<p>Government spokesman Su Chi criticised the opposition, saying the parties had made a political issue of the murder of Pai Hsiao-yen.</p>
<p>Chen of the Democratic Progressive Party said: &quot;The public has demanded a change. The ruling Nationalist Party cannot ignore the voice of the people.&quot;</p>
<p>As pressure for a new cabinet intensified, a popular Taiwan cabinet member announced his resignation on Thursday.</p>
<p>Ma Ying-jeou, minister without portfolio, said in a statement he had tendered his resignation &quot;due to change of political ethics, obstacles in reforms and growing public discontent.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Before the reforms can be achieved, political mores have already changed, with (officials) struggling for powers, taking credits and shunning responsibility,&quot; said the former justice minister, one of the most popular officials on the island.</p>
<p>State media have speculated that the ruling party wanted Ma to replace Interior Minister Lin Feng-cheng, who has been under fire for the recent upsurge in violent crime.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
