<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570931" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Reaction to Japan tax rise seen fading in July - EPA.</title>
<headline>Reaction to Japan tax rise seen fading in July - EPA.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A fall in consumption in reaction to the rise in Japan's sales tax on April 1 is expected to last until the end of June, with little effect being felt after July, the Economic Planning Agency (EPA) said on Thursday.</p>
<p>It said its findings were based on a survey of stores in regional cities, including department stores, chain stores, consumer electronics stores and car dealers.</p>
<p>&quot;The reaction is slightly bigger than we first thought,&quot; an EPA official told reporters.  </p>
<p>He said a consumer rush in late March, ahead of an increase in the tax to five percent from three percebnt, was bigger than first expected and thus the ensuing reaction would be larger.</p>
<p>Stores which were more affected by the rush were likely to suffer a greater fall in consumption, he said.</p>
<p>Sales for the first half of April showed that department stores and consumer electronics stores were expected to show a 10 to 20 percent drop year-on-year and chainstores were expected to show a five to 20 percent drop.</p>
<p>But the survey also said the reaction would be greatest immediately after the tax increase and the size of the fall should shrink with time.  </p>
<p>A similar survey within Tokyo showed car dealers expect substantial negative sales growth year-on-year after May but expect a recovery from the July-September quarter.</p>
<p>Department stores in Tokyo saw strong consumer demand in March, especially for luxury goods such as kimonos. Consumption in April was expected to be down around 10 percent year-on-year.</p>
<p>Chainstores in Tokyo experienced only a slight rise in demand ahead of the tax rise and are expected to show only a slight drop for April from a year earlier.</p>
<p>Consumer electronic stores are expected to see a drop of around 10 percent in April from a year earlier, the survey said, adding that strong demand for computers meant overall demand for electronics goods remained firm.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
