<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="570950" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shenzhen stocks end down on clampdown fears.</title>
<headline>Shenzhen stocks end down on clampdown fears.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Worries over a possible government crackdown on China's soaring stock markets caused Shenzhen's A and B share indices to close sharply lower on Thursday, analysts said.</p>
<p>The domestic currency A share index plunged 31.87 points or 5.97 percent to end at 501.92 on turnover of 20.2 billion yuan, following a record high close of 533.78 points on Wednesday with turnover of 21.3 billion yuan.</p>
<p>The foreign currency B share index fell 6.13 points or 3.35 percent to 176.61 on turnover of HK$215.08 million, against Wednesday's HK$233.63 million.  </p>
<p>&quot;Talk of an imminent clampdown is swirling around the market, and trading is expected to be very volatile towards the end of the week,&quot; an analyst at China Guotai Securities said.</p>
<p>The A share index has surged 47 percent since the beginning of 1997 to Thursday's close, while the B index has risen 22 percent over the same period.</p>
<p>China's official securities newspapers have repeatedly called for strengthening risk controls.</p>
<p>&quot;Investor jitters over recent strong A share gains affected the B share market,&quot; an analyst at J&amp;A Securities said.  </p>
<p>Upcoming B share offers also drained some funds from the B share market, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Many investors are selling in preparation for subscribing to the new share offerings,&quot; the J&amp;A analyst said.</p>
<p>Pesticide maker Hubei Sanonda Co Ltd, Shandong Chenming Paper Holdings Ltd and Nanjing Posts &amp; Telecommunications Equipment Co Ltd will each offer 100 million B shares for listing in Shenzhen this month.</p>
<p>However, analysts said they expect the three new stocks to perform well on their listing debuts, which will likely boost investor sentiment.  </p>
<p>&quot;Investors are snatching up new share issues, likening them to money trees,&quot; the J&amp;A analyst said.</p>
<p>Most analysts said they were confident that the underlying trend remains bullish.</p>
<p>China's gross domestic product (GDP) is expected to grow 9.6 percent year-on-year in the first half of 1997, with retail price inflation seen at two percent, according to a recent forecast by the State Economic and Trade Commission.</p>
<p>&quot;Unless the government comes out with harsh measures, I am quite confident that the (A and B) indices will rise significantly in the medium-term,&quot; the J&amp;A analyst said.  </p>
<p>Shenzhen Great Ocean Shipping Co Ltd was the worst performer in the B share market, dropping HK$0.28 or 7.41 percent to HK$3.50.</p>
<p>In the A share market, institutional investors dumped large capitalisation Shenzhen Development Bank towards the end of the session, analysts said.</p>
<p>The stock fell 4.21 yuan or 8.61 percent to 44.69 on volume of 49.2 million shares, making it the most actively traded A share.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
