<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571029" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan activists in scuffle over island landing.</title>
<headline>Taiwan activists in scuffle over island landing.</headline>
<byline>Kevin Chen</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan demonstrators threw eggs and scuffled with police while trying to storm Japan's de facto embassy in Taipei on Thursday to protest against a landing by four Japanese on a disputed East China Sea island.</p>
<p>Ten protesters, shouting &quot;down with Japanese militarism&quot; and &quot;Japan has no right to occupy the Diaoyu Islands&quot;, tried to deliver a petition to Japan's Interchange Association.</p>
<p>The association, which represents Tokyo in the absence of diplomatic ties, shut its gate and refused to accept the letter.</p>
<p>Chou Ching-chun, head of the Taiwan Diaoyu Islands Defence Action Committee, pelted the gate with his shoes. One protester, Hsiao Yun-shan, 74, fell during the scuffle and was taken to hospital with minor injuries.</p>
<p>No arrests were made during the protest, the second in two days in Taiwan over the islands.</p>
<p>The Japanese-administered islands are called Senkaku by Japan and Diaoyu by China. They are claimed by Tokyo, Beijing and Taipei.</p>
<p>Japanese legislator Shingo Nishimura and three other people landed on one of the islands on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The act drew protests from China and Taiwan and ignited nationalistic passions in Chinese communities in Hong Kong and Taiwan.</p>
<p>Waters surrounding the islands are rich fishing grounds and are believed to contain oil and gas reserves.</p>
<p>Japan has claimed the islands since 1895, while China says it has always owned them.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, activists stormed the visa office of the Interchange Association, pelting it with eggs and forcing staffers and visa applicants to take cover.</p>
<p>The dispute was rekindled last year when a right-wing group from Japan built a makeshift lighthouse on the islands.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
