<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571004" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Tokyo stocks end flat after wavering narrowly.</title>
<headline>Tokyo stocks end flat after wavering narrowly.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tokyo stocks ended nearly flat on Thursday after the key index teetered around the 20,000 barrier for most of session.</p>
<p>Brokers said the market was weighed down by profit-taking, but gained support from purchases of laggard issues, mainly by foreign investors.</p>
<p>The 225-share Nikkei average was 12.91 points or 0.06 percent higher at 20,061.81. June Nikkei futures were down 20 points at 20,060.</p>
<p>&quot;Relatively cheap issues and some blue chips such as Sony Corp were bought actively,&quot; said Harushige Kobayashi, Yamaichi Securities deputy general manager.  </p>
<p>Mitsubishi Chemical Corp shed 12 yen to 408 in trade which totalled 6.50 million shares, making it the fourth-most heavily traded stock.</p>
<p>A broker at a &quot;Big Four&quot; brokerage who was a large seller of Japan's largest comprehensive chemical maker said it was easy for profit-taking to emerge above the Nikkei average's 20,000 threshold, and recent high-flyers were the most vulnerable.</p>
<p>Toyota group firm Denso Corp fell despite news of a share repurchase plan announced on Wednesday. It lost 100 yen to finish at 3,030.  </p>
<p>Investors had bought Denso on speculation, brokers said, and used the announcement as an excuse to sell.</p>
<p>By sector, services, land transport, miscellaneous manufacturers, automobiles and retailers were the main gainers. Rubber, securities, real estate, precision instruments and communications were at the top of the list of declining issues.</p>
<p>Brokers said the May options settlement on Friday was likely to pass fairly smoothly and the Nikkei average would not be affected much.</p>
<p>--Masako Iijima, Tokyo Equities Desk (+81-3-3432-9052)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
