<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571085" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Hyundai hopes to win Vietnam licence soon.</title>
<headline>Hyundai hopes to win Vietnam licence soon.</headline>
<byline>Yeom Yoon-jeong</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea's largest carmaker Hyundai Motor Co expects to finally win approval to build a joint venture plant in Vietnam in the first half of this year, a company spokesman said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The possibility to get the licence in the first half is much over 50 percent from an earlier 50-50 percent chance,&quot; said spokesman Min Kyong-hwan. &quot;The Vietnamese government is starting to favour Hyundai.&quot;</p>
<p>Hyundai Motor, a flagship affiliate of South Korea's largest conglomerate Hyundai Group, said it would invest about $220 million in the joint venture plant, in which the company is expected to hold a 65 percent stake.</p>
<p>The plant, which will be located near Ho Chi Minh City, will be able to make 10,000 vehicles a year.</p>
<p>If Hyundai wins the licence, Min said Hyundai would boost local production of auto components by extending technical tie-ups. Korean autoparts manufacturers are expected to enter the new market with Hyundai.</p>
<p>Hyundai was supposed to become the 15th foreign carmaker to be licensed in Vietnam by the end of 1996.</p>
<p>However, Vietnam's Prime Minister Vo Van Kiet has opposed Hyundai's southern Vietnam project, arguing that the 14 foreign joint ventures already licensed were enough for the time being.</p>
<p>But Hyundai Motor now believes it will win a licence after Deputy Minister for Industry Nguyen Xuan Chuan said this week the Korean company would stand &quot;a better chance&quot; of seeing its application approved if Chrysler Corp abandoned the country's crowded market.</p>
<p>Local media in Vietnam have reported that Chrysler has abandoned its plans for a $192-million factory near Ho Chi Minh City, because Vietnam has licensed too many foreign carmakers.</p>
<p>The U.S. car giant has until July to take up a construction licence which it was granted two years ago. It has not yet officially declared whether it would walk away.</p>
<p>Seven ventures are already producing cars in Vietnam, and Ford Motor Co of the United States is planning to roll out its first vehicle from a $102-million plant near Hanoi this year.</p>
<p>Min said Hyundai would be able to compete with other foreign carmakers on price despite its late arrival in Vietnam.</p>
<p>&quot;Initially, we are targeting buyers who can only afford low-priced passenger cars such as the sub-compact Accent,&quot; he said. &quot;We will go there with commercial vehicles well-suited for narrow and poor roads.&quot;</p>
<p>Some 37,000 vehicles of all types were sold in Vietnam last year and cars accounted for 35 percent of the total.</p>
<p>&quot;Vietnam will be an important production site for us to advance into Indochina. In addition to saving labour and transportation costs, we are able to secure a foothold in the region,&quot; Min said.</p>
<p>Like other South Korean carmakers seeking to diversify their export markets, Hyundai has been expanding overseas production.</p>
<p>The first sub-compact Accent and van Grace will roll out from a Turkey joint venture in July. Hyundai invested $22.5 million in the plant, which has an annual production capacity of 50,000 vehicles.</p>
<p>Hyundai spent $1.1 billion on its wholly-owned Hyundai Motor India to produce 200,000 Accents. Production is expected to start from August, 1998.</p>
<p>Another joint venture assembly line for 1.5-tonne trucks is under construction in Malaysia with production also expected to begin in August next year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I5010025">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
