<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571012" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Sony 96/97 entertainment oper revenue up 23.1 pct.</title>
<headline>Sony 96/97 entertainment oper revenue up 23.1 pct.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japanese electronics giant Sony Corp said on Thursday that group operating revenue from its entertainment business in fiscal 1996/97 rose 23.1 percent from a year earlier to 1,023 billion yen.  </p>
<p>Sony's entertainment revenues come largely from its troubled Hollywood film-making unit, Sony Pictures Entertainment, and its record unit, Sony Music Entertainment.</p>
<p>Sony said the yen's year-on-year decline against other major currencies increased its 1996/97 group sales by about 520 billion yen.</p>
<p>&quot;If the value of the yen had remained the same as in the previous year, group sales would have been approximately 520 billion yen lower than the reported figure&quot; of 5.66 trillion yen, Sony said in a statement.  </p>
<p>Sony said it had set its earnings estimates for the current financial year, which started on April 1, based on an assumed exchange rate of 115 yen per dollar. The dollar was quoted around 124.80 yen as of 0640 GMT on Thursday.  </p>
<p>&quot;Sales in the music group continued to rise despite the weak retail environment in the United States, primarily due to favourable sales growth outside Japan,&quot; Sony said.</p>
<p>Most notable was Celine Dion's &quot;Falling Into You&quot;, which had sold more than 21 million units since its March 1996 release, it said.</p>
<p>Sales in the pictures group increased significantly year-on-year, mainly benefiting from continued strength in television operations, including U.S. network prime-time, daytime and game show programming, as well as the success of sell-through videos such as &quot;Jumanji&quot; and &quot;Matilda&quot;, it said.</p>
<p>The blockbuster romantic comedy &quot;Jerry Maguire&quot;, which has grossed $150 million at the U.S. box offce, also contributed to the year's results, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;All of those positive factors, in addition to the yen's depreciation, more than offset the disappointing box office results of several films released during the year,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>In the electronics business, Sony enjoyed a 24.3 percent year-on-year increase in its group revenue to 4.39 trillion yen. It said the sales of its cutting-edge 32-bit home game player, the PlayStation contributed to the growth.  </p>
<p>In a geographical breakdown, group sales and operating revenue in Japan topped the list at 3.43 trillion yen in 1996/97, up 12.9 percent year-on-year, followed by U.S.'s 1.80 trillion yen, up 31.9 percent.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, group sales and operating revenue in Europe rose 24.7 percent to 1.14 trillion yen.</p>
<p>But Sony said operating income in the United States fell 4.5 percent in 1996/97 due to substantial losses at a semiconductor manufacturing equipment subsidiary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34540">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
