<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571046" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai stocks extend losses, sentiment bearish.</title>
<headline>Thai stocks extend losses, sentiment bearish.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thai stocks extended recent losses on Thursday morning as continued sales of blue chips, primarily by foreign investors, wiped 1.89 percent off the market by lunch and breached support at the 615-620 level, traders said.</p>
<p>Opening at a 5-1/2 year low, the SET Index shed another 11.87 points to 614.70 by midday. The SET 50 fell 0.84 points or 1.83 percent to 45.12. Turnover was 1.44 billion baht.</p>
<p>&quot;There was some support above 615 but I don't think it will last. I think selling pressure may increase when London opens in the afternoon,&quot; said a trader at National Finance and Securities.  </p>
<p>Traders said they suspected local retailers had picked up bank stocks being dumped by foreigners in the mid-session, preventing a straight fall in the market.</p>
<p>But sales of bank stocks intensified prior to the break taking the SET index to near session lows.</p>
<p>There were few new factors in the market but investors remained primarily concerned about lower economic growth and poor corporate earnings prospects in the sector.</p>
<p>Finance stocks, dogged by loan quality and liquidity concerns as well as negative earnings growth projections, shed another 3.88 percent.  </p>
<p>Union Asia Finance's decision to issue new shares, and worries about how merging firms will resolve tax issues, were also weighing against the sector, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Union Asia's capital increase seems to be negative short term news. People are ignoring the long term view that finance firms are in a consolidation stage and need to expand their equity base,&quot; the trader said.</p>
<p>How the government will address a potential budget deficit is a further cause of concern, analysts said.</p>
<p>Bangkok Bank lost two baht to 162, Thai Farmers shed three to 110, Phatra lost one to 39.50.</p>
<p>--James Mclean (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
