<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571097" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shenzhen B index falls at noon on A share slide.</title>
<headline>Shenzhen B index falls at noon on A share slide.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shenzhen's B share index was down at midday on Thursday on a slide in A shares caused by concerns that Beijing could take measures to cool the market down, analysts said.</p>
<p>The foreign currency B share index fell 3.12 points or 1.71 percent to 179.62 on turnover of HK$79.16 million.  </p>
<p>&quot;Investors are worrying that the B share market may be affected if the government imposes clampdown measures on the A share market,&quot; an analyst at J&amp;A Securities said.</p>
<p>The domestic currency A share index dropped 9.77 points or 1.83 percent to 524.02 on turnover of 10.4 billion yuan after closing at an historic high of 533.78 points on Wednesday.</p>
<p>New B share offers diverted some funds from the B share market, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of our customers are selling their stocks in preparation for subscribing to the new share offerings,&quot; the J&amp;A analyst said.  </p>
<p>Pesticide maker Hubei Sanonda Co Ltd, Shandong Chenming Paper Holdings Ltd and Nanjing Posts &amp; Telecommunications Equipment Co Ltd have announced they will each offer 100 million B shares for listing in Shenzhen this month.</p>
<p>But analysts also said they expected the three new stocks to perform well on their listing debuts, which are likely to boost sentiment.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors are grabbing any new share issues, likening them to money trees,&quot; the analyst said.  </p>
<p>The B index is unlikely to fall much further in the next few sessions, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The B index is supported by the 10 day average of 178 points,&quot; an analyst at China Guotai Securities said. &quot;There should be a period of fluctuation in the near future given the wary mood, but the big picture still shines.&quot;</p>
<p>China's gross domestic product (GDP) is expected to grow 9.6 percent year-on-year in the first half of 1997, with retail price inflation seen at two percent, an official newspaper on Tuesday quoted a forecast by the State Economic and Trade Commission as saying.  </p>
<p>Television tube maker Shenzhen SEG Co Ltd was the sharpest loser in the B share market, falling HK$0.70 or 6.86 percent to HK$9.50.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
