<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571077" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Rights group condemns Cambodian TV station attack.</title>
<headline>Rights group condemns Cambodian TV station attack.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>An international human rights group on Thursday condemned a deadly weekend attack on a state television studio, saying it was politically motivated and could herald more violence between Cambodia's main parties.</p>
<p>&quot;Human Rights Watch today strongly condemned the armed attack Sunday on the office of Television of Kampuchea (TVK) in the southern city of Sihanoukville,&quot; the U.S.-based rights group said in a statement.</p>
<p>The group said the attack was the latest in a series of armed confrontations between the leading coalition government parties, the royalist FUNCINPEC and the ex-communist Cambodian People's Party. It added that &quot;violence is clearly escalating in the period prior to national elections (due next year)&quot;.</p>
<p>It said overseas donors at an annual meeting on Cambodia in July &quot;should link future loans and budgetary support to effective steps taken by the leaders of the two parties to end political violence and to punish those reponsible&quot;.</p>
<p>Police in Sihanoukville have said seven men attacked the television studio with grenade and rifle fire on Sunday, killing one staffer and injuring two others.</p>
<p>The attack reportedly came after the station chief refused to air a videotaped speech by a spokesman of the royalist FUNCINPEC party criticising the rival Cambodian People's Party (CPP) of Second Prime Minister Hun Sen.</p>
<p>Co-Premier Prince Norodom Ranariddh, leader of FUNCINPEC, condemned the attack earlier this week, while party officials have denied responsibility.</p>
<p>But analysts noted that the prince has accused Information Minister Ieng Mouly of bias against his party and of giving more air time on state television and radio to the CPP.</p>
<p>U.K.-based Amnesty International said on Wednesday it feared for the safety of senior Information Ministry officials working in the provinces following the attack.</p>
<p>The two parties formed an uneasy coalition government after U.N.-run polls in 1993.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
