<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571039" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Popular Taiwan official resigns ahead of reshuffle.</title>
<headline>Popular Taiwan official resigns ahead of reshuffle.</headline>
<byline>Lawrence Chung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A popular Taiwan cabinet member announced his resignation on Thursday ahead of a planned government reshuffle in response to growing public outcry over a spate of violent crime.</p>
<p>Ma Ying-chiu, minister without portfolio, said in a statement he had tendered his resignation to Premier Lien Chan &quot;due to change of political ethics, obstacles in reforms and growing public discontent.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Before the reforms can be achieved, political mores have already changed, with (officials) struggling for powers, taking credits and shunning responsibility,&quot; said the former justice minister, one of the most popular officials on the island.</p>
<p>Ma also quelled speculation that he planned to run for Taipei mayor.</p>
<p>The former justice minister had been tipped by the ruling Nationalist Party to run in the 1998 mayoral election against incumbent mayor Chen Shui-bian from the opposition Democratic Progressive Party.</p>
<p>Instead, Ma said he would join other private individuals and groups to promote social reforms and pursue academic studies.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan is a pluralistic society... and reforms do not necessarily have to be led by the government,&quot; he said in a statement.</p>
<p>The premier's office said it had not received Ma's official resignation.</p>
<p>But Wu Poh-hsiung, secretary-general of the ruling Nationalist Party, said he would respect Ma's decision.</p>
<p>Public discontent over the government's failure to improve social order has erupted since police discovered the body of renowed actress Pai Ping-ping's teenage daughter on April 28, floating naked in a river.</p>
<p>Police said 17-year-old Pai Hsiao-yen was kidnapped and murdered. But the killers remained at large.</p>
<p>The murder followed a string of violent crimes that have occurred since 1996.</p>
<p>More than 50,000 people marched in Taipei on Sunday to protest against Pai's murder and demand the resignation of Lien and a cabinet reshuffle to take responsibility.</p>
<p>The protest prompted President Lee Teng-hui, who doubles as chairman of the ruling Nationalist Party, to call for a partial reshuffle of the cabinet on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Lien had also tendered his resignation to Lee, but was asked to stay on.</p>
<p>Lien was expected to deliver a list of reshuffled cabinet positions for approval during next Wednesday's central standing committee meeting.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
