<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571090" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Russia-Japan PGM talks may be held end-May - traders.</title>
<headline>Russia-Japan PGM talks may be held end-May - traders.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Market talk has surfaced that long-delayed talks between Russia and Japanese customers on the renewal of export contracts for platinum group metals (PGM) may start at the end of this month, traders said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Some Japanese precious metal traders said they had heard from sources at Russia's PGM export agency, Almazjuvelirexport (Almaz), that a mission would be visiting Japan at the end of May, although a time schedule had yet to be decided.</p>
<p>&quot;A source at Almaz told me they were likely to come to Japan for the export-contract talks for 1997, probably at the end of May,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Some traders were sceptical because a visit by officials of the agency to Japan for export contract negotiations has already been delayed many times.</p>
<p>Japan is the world's largest PGM consumer and Russia provides about 60 percent of global supplies.</p>
<p>Contract talks between the two countries are usually held in mid-December, but have been held up by Moscow's failure to pass a decree setting out 1997 PGM export quotas.</p>
<p>In Moscow on Wednesday, Almaz said it believed the government decree had been signed at last.</p>
<p>&quot;It happened in the last few days, although we have not yet received a copy of the decree,&quot; said Sergei Gorny, deputy director of the agency, adding that he could not therefore fully confirm that the decree had been signed.</p>
<p>Japan, unable to rely on term contract supplies from Russia, has boosted purchases of palladium in the Zurich spot market tightening the market considerably, traders said.</p>
<p>They said supply tightness, reflected in the persistently high lease rates, were not expected to ease significantly until after Russia resumes sales.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if the mission arrives in Japan at the end of May, the first shipments to Japan under long-term contracts will probably be in July,&quot; an official at a bullion house said.</p>
<p>Palladium is used in catalytic converters for automobiles. But its main use is in electronics, which accounts for 60 percent of Japan's imports.</p>
<p>Japan's cumulative palladium imports in the first three months of 1997 amounted to 26.81 tonnes, up from 20.54 tonnes in the same period a year earlier, according to the latest data from Japan's Ministry of Finance.</p>
<p>Traders said the higher imports could be attributed to concern over Russian metal supplies, and were not signs of stronger Japanese demand.</p>
<p>-- Keiko Takagi, Tokyo Commodities Desk +81-3-3432-7431</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
