<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571088" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore rubber ignores Thai news, trade quiet.</title>
<headline>Singapore rubber ignores Thai news, trade quiet.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Singapore rubber market on Thursday shrugged off as a non-event the announcement by Thailand it was raising its intervention price for RSS3 grade rubber to 29 baht a kg from 27.50 baht, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The only news in the market was the Thai news. But no one traded on the announcement,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's totally discounted by the trade. Nobody bothered with it,&quot; another dealer said, adding the rest of the market was trading about five baht lower.</p>
<p>Holidays in Indonesia and Malaysia added to the gloomy mood in the market, the traders said.  </p>
<p>&quot;I have not received any calls from the big boys so far. We'll see what happens in the afternoon,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was no business done in the morning. It was pretty dull so far,&quot; a dealer added. Traders said firmer prices in Japan may give a slight boost to prices in the afternoon session.</p>
<p>At 0430 GMT, June RSS3 was indicated unchanged at 108.00 U.S. cents a kg. June RSS1 was indicated at 156.00-158.00 Singapore cents (US$1.08-$1.09) a kg from 156.00 cents. June TSR20 was indicated at 151.25 Singapore cents (US$1.05) a kg from 150.00 cents. -- (US$1-S$1.44) Rene Pastor (65-8703305)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
