<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571186" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan reform to up fund inflow--Sakakibara quoted.</title>
<headline>Japan reform to up fund inflow--Sakakibara quoted.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's plan to reform its financial sector will eventually boost the capital flow into the country, senior Ministry of Finance official Eisuke Sakakibara was quoted as saying by a business daily.</p>
<p>Sakakibara, director-general of the ministry's International Finance Bureau, was quoted in Thursday's edition of the Nihon Keizai Shimbun as saying that reform of Japan's rules on banking and brokerage services would not lead to a rush of offshore deposits given the total cost after tax.</p>
<p>&quot;We cannot simply say the reform of the Foreign Exchange Control Law will bring about a capital outflow or a weaker yen, but in the medium to long term it is certain that both capital outflow and inflow will increase,&quot; he said in an interview.</p>
<p>Sakakibara predicted that the reforms in Japan would prompt overseas financial institutions to manage individual investment in Japan and domestic firms to offer more competitive products.</p>
<p>&quot;The reforms will trigger the introduction of more attractive products and activate markets, which in turn will lead to a capital inflow,&quot; he was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto unveiled plans last November for a five-year &quot;Big Bang&quot; to liberalise Japan's financial markets and catch up with reforms carried out more than a decade ago in Europe and North America.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
