<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571136" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Moody's cuts S'tomo Life financial strength rating.</title>
<headline>Moody's cuts S'tomo Life financial strength rating.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Moody's Investors Service announced on Thursday that it had downgraded its insurance financial strength rating for Sumitomo Life Insurance Co to Baa1 from A3.  </p>
<p>The outlook for Sumitomo Life's rating is negative, Moody's said in a statement.</p>
<p>Moody's said the downgrade reflected its view that Sumitomo Life would continue to be challenged by deteriorating asset quality at the company itself and at affiliated non-bank financial institutions, the insurer's relatively low level of latent reserves and the vulnerability of its investment income to volatile market conditions.</p>
<p>Moody's said it believes Sumitomo Life's earnings and capital formation will be somewhat constrained and its financial flexibility, including the level of hidden gains on securities, remains low relative to other major life insurance companies.  </p>
<p>Moody's said it expects Japanese life insurers, including Sumitomo Life, to face more challenges as the Japanese government implements insurance deregulation in an environment of prolonged asset deflation and low interest rates.</p>
<p>The method for resolving the problem of failed Japanese life insurers is uncertain and that could place an additional financial burden on surviving life insurers, including Sumitomo Life, if more life insurance companies were to fail in the future, Moody's said.</p>
<p>But it said it believed Sumitomo Life's financial strength remained adequate, supported by a well-established and significant presence in Japan's life insurance market and a strong affiliation with the Sumitomo group.</p>
<p>Moody's said Sumitomo Life maintained good liquidity and its operating fundamentals were in line with those of its primary competitors.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
