<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571190" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish court adjourns Islamist mayor case.</title>
<headline>Turkish court adjourns Islamist mayor case.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Turkish court on Thursday adjourned the trial of a former mayor from Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan's Welfare Party on charges of serious public order offences for organising an Islamist, anti-Israeli protest.</p>
<p>&quot;Given the evidence, the court has decided to keep the defendants in custody. The next hearing will take place on June 6,&quot; Judge Turgut Okyay told the court.</p>
<p>Mayor Bekir Yildiz and five others are in custody because of their role in a &quot;Jerusalem Night&quot; rally in January in Ankara's Sincan district, which enraged secularists who regarded the protest as a call for the implementation of Islamic sharia law.</p>
<p>The rest of the 11 people on trial were released last month but the charges against them remain the same. The mayor faces three to five years in jail.</p>
<p>Yildiz and Iranian ambassador Ali Reza Bagheri spoke on a stage draped with a banner of the late leader of the militant Palestinian group Islamic Jihad, Fathi Shqaqi.</p>
<p>Iran and much of the Arab world have expressed unease at Turkey's growing defence ties with the Jewish state. A deal signed last year has allowed Israeli air force jets to train in the ample air space of Turkey, a Moslem but secular country.</p>
<p>Tanks toured Sincan several days after the Jerusalem protest in an apparent warning to Islamists from the secular army.</p>
<p>Erbakan, under pressure from the powerful military, has toned down his colourful rhetoric since becoming Turkey's first Islamist prime minister in June last year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
