<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571145" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: FORECAST-Japan March c/a surplus to fall yr/yr.</title>
<headline>FORECAST-Japan March c/a surplus to fall yr/yr.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's current account surplus for March is expected to show a fall from a year earlier, with economists forecasting on average a drop of around 17 percent.</p>
<p>Predictions of the surplus in the current account, the broadest measure of trade in goods and services, ranged from 703.4 billion yen to 1.17 trillion yen, compared with a 1.24 trillion yen surplus a year earlier.</p>
<p>The data will be released at 8.50 a.m. on Wednesday, May 14 (2350 GMT Tuesday).</p>
<p>Economists said there would be a fall would be in line with the drop in March in Japan's merchandise trade surplus, which makes up much of the current account surplus.</p>
<p>Japan's customs-cleared trade surplus slid 26.8 percent in March from a year earlier to 818.34 billion yen, the Finance Ministry said on April 17.</p>
<p>The March trade surplus fell on a surge in imports to meet high demand ahead of a rise in the sales tax on April 1.</p>
<p>Some economists whose forecasts were at the lower end of the range also said that in addition to high imports which brought the trade surplus down, they expected repatriation of investment income to be less than last year.</p>
<p>&quot;Things are better here this year so there's probably less need (to bring money home),&quot; said Peter Morgan, an economist at HSBC James Capel.</p>
<p>Economists said, however, that the fall in March would be the last for several months as the current account surplus is set for sharp rises in April, May and June.</p>
<p>Some expect these rises will exacerbate trade tensions with the United States, which has repeatedly warned Japan that it will not tolerate large increases in the surplus and that Tokyo should not return to relying on exports for growth.</p>
<p>&quot;Trade friction can only get worse,&quot; said Russell Jones, chief economist at Lehman Brothers.</p>
<p>&quot;The trade surplus is going to explode in the second quarter when the oil bill collapses and raw material inventories dissipate,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Oil imports are expected to fall dramatically with the end of winter, as are imports of raw materials, which fed the pre-sales tax demand.</p>
<p>But most economists said that while they expect the United States to make a lot of noise, they do not expect hysterics.</p>
<p>&quot;The surplus is only 1.4 percent of GDP and it won't really be a cause for concern until it exceeds 2.0 percent,&quot; said Kazutoshi Aratake, an economist at Nikko Research Center. The following is a breakdown of economists' forecasts:</p>
<p>    DAIWA BANK RESEARCH		1.09 trillion yen</p>
<p>    GOLDMAN SACHS			703.4 billion yen</p>
<p>    HSBC JAMES CAPEL		   981.0 billion yen</p>
<p>    INDUSTRIAL BANK OF JAPAN	 1.08 trillion yen</p>
<p>    KANKAKU RESEARCH		   1.09 trillion yen</p>
<p>    LEHMAN BROTHERS		    1.09 trillion yen</p>
<p>    MERRILL LYNCH			1.07 trillion yen</p>
<p>    NIKKO RESEARCH		     1.02 trillion yen</p>
<p>    NOMURA RESEARCH		    1.17 trillion yen</p>
<p>    SAKURA SECURITIES		  1.03 trillion yen</p>
<p>    YAMAICHI RESEARCH		  1.10 trillion yen</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
