<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571172" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Ogawa Sec says no plan to apply for liquidation.</title>
<headline>Ogawa Sec says no plan to apply for liquidation.</headline>
<dateline>OSAKA, Japan 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Ogawa Securities Co Ltd said on Thursday it has no plan at present to stop doing business.</p>
<p>An official at the small Osaka-based brokerage, which is an affiliate of Yamaichi Securities Co Ltd, told Reuters that it was operating as normal on Thursday morning.</p>
<p>The mass-circulation daily Sankei Shimbun reported in its Thursday edition that Yamaichi plans to liquidate the affiliate. The paper did not give a source for the report.</p>
<p>It said Ogawa would be the third Japanese brokerage to be liquidated since the end of World War Two, and the first since the 1978 failure of Kyoto Securities.  </p>
<p>Sankei said that Ogawa, founded in 1881, suffered a one billion yen loss earlier this year in connection with margin trading by a non-bank financial firm.</p>
<p>The paper said that the securities industry would for the first time use its joint deposit insurance system to protect clients of Ogawa from possible losses on assets deposited with the broker, mainly deposits put up for margin trading.</p>
<p>The insurance system, set up in 1968 with donations from about 250 member brokerages, had a balance of 35 billion yen as of the end of February, Sankei said.</p>
<p>A Yamaichi spokesman in Tokyo said: &quot;What I can say at the moment is that nothing has been decided yet.... No policy has been set. If we set any policy, we will quickly make it public.&quot;  </p>
<p>Ogawa president Tokuo Namba told Reuters in Osaka: &quot;Yamaichi told us it has been mulling various schemes but has not come up with any final conclusion. We will make a public announcement when the right time comes. At present, there is no final conclusion.&quot;</p>
<p>He added: &quot;Our capital adequacy ratio was at 150 percent as of the end of April and has not reached a danger zone.&quot;</p>
<p>Last month, Yamaichi, which is one of Japan's top four brokerages, told Reuters it was mulling various options for assisting its financially troubled affiliates and that a merger of the affiliates could be one option.</p>
<p>Yamaichi said at the time that it would make a decision on steps to assist the struggling affiliates as soon as possible.</p>
<p>The affiliates include a medium-sized Tokyo-based brokerage, Naigai Securities Co Ltd, and three Osaka-based brokerages -- Naito Securities Co Ltd, Daichu Shoken and Ogawa.</p>
<p>Sankei reported that Yamaichi had given up on the idea of providing assistance to Ogawa or merging it with other affiliates due to likely criticism from its own shareholders.</p>
<p>Yamaichi itself is facing a business slump. On Wednesday, it announced a group net loss of 172.11 billion yen for the year to March 31 after a profit of 19.47 billion yen the previous year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OSAKA, Japan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
