<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571122" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Time is right to list China state shares-economist.</title>
<headline>Time is right to list China state shares-economist.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The time has come for China to list state shares and institutional shares to help domestic stock markets cool down, the Business news on Thursday quoted leading Chinese economist Xiao Zhuoji as saying.</p>
<p>The shares, currently non-tradeable, make up the bulk of the company shares in existence in China, and constitute the ownership of the state in the firms.</p>
<p>Some officials have expressed concern about the selling of state assets, and the consequent diminution of control by the state over the economy.</p>
<p>&quot;The circulation of the state shares and institutional shares is a problem to be solved sooner or later,&quot; Xiao said. &quot;Now is the good opportunity to list these shares, so they can cool down the overheating stock markets.&quot;</p>
<p>The number of state and institutional shares is estimated to be at least three or four times the number of domestic A shares currently listed on China's two stock markets, brokers said.</p>
<p>China's domestic A shares have risen over 40 percent since the beginning of this year despite successive official warnings to investors on the risks of equity investment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
