<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571158" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: PRESS DIGEST - Thai newspapers - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Thai newspapers - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Thai press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>TOP STORIES</p>
<p>- Finance Minister Amnuay Viravan says he will launch an inquiry into the people, officials and events surrounding the collapse of the Bangkok Bank of Commerce, which will be bailed out to the tune of 176 billion baht. His announcement, made during a contract signing ceremony allowing the Industrial Finance Corporation of Thailand to manage the BBC, is aimed at giving the public a full picture on why the BBC was allowed to rack up almost 80 billion baht in doubtful debts although banking authorities were aware of its rotten financial status in 1992 and 1993. (THE NATION)</p>
<p>- Although government and opposition members have joined together to investigate whether &quot;Madame PK&quot; does in fact own a large plot of land in Nakhon Ratchasima province, they are left with totally different opinions on the matter. While New Aspiration Party members conclude that no such person owns the controversial plot in the province, Democrat MPs say the issue is far from over. (THE NATION)</p>
<p>	 + + + +</p>
<p>BUSINESS</p>
<p>- The new listing rules chalked out by the Stock Exchange of Thailand (SET) are expected to come into force by the third quarter of this year. The SET has designed the regulations so as to encourage more large-sized companies to list on the bourse, while forcing smaller companies to register on the Over the Counter market. (BUSINESS DAY)</p>
<p>- Deputy Prime Minister and Industry Minister Korn Dabaransi has made significant moves towards the purchase of natural gas from Indonesia's Natuna gas field through the participation of PTT Exploration and Production Plc. For the planned purchasing deal, the PTTEP has been encouraged to hold an 11 to 15 percent stake in the vast gas field with an estimated investment cost of US$900 million. (THE NATION)</p>
<p>-- Bangkok newsroom (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
