<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571131" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: FEATURE-China grain transport moving from burlap to bulk.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-China grain transport moving from burlap to bulk.</headline>
<byline>Scott Hillis</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chinese port, grain and transportation authorities are planning a shift from burlap to bulk that aims to modernise the grain transport system with the addition of thousands of new trucks, ships and railcars.</p>
<p>China is awash in grain after two years of record harvests, but much of that cereal is languishing in production areas, unable to find its way to market because of a creaky transport system, officials said in recent interviews.</p>
<p>China's main method of moving grain throughout the country was the cheap but labour-intensive and inefficient burlap sack, said World Bank official Alan Piazza, who follows Chinese grain issues.</p>
<p>&quot;China has something like three billion burlap bags,&quot; Piazza told reporters. &quot;The government has not shown itself to be agile in manipulating reserves.&quot;</p>
<p>The World Bank was lending China more than $300 million to support a project to shift away from transporting grain in sacks to moving it in special bulk railway cars, ships and trucks, Piazza said.</p>
<p>Chinese dock workers took 10-14 days to fill a 30,000-tonne ship with sacks of corn, while a bulk loading system could fill a 60,000 tonne ship in 36 hours, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It no longer makes economic sense,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>TRAINS, TRUCKS AND TRANSPORT SHIPS</p>
<p>The project would focus on upgrading northeastern ports -- such as Dalian in Liaoning province -- near major corn and wheat growing areas, Piazza said.</p>
<p>The World Bank money would help to install bulk grain handling facilities in several major ports and buy more than 1,400 bulk railcars, more than 1,000 trucks and 10 bulk cargo ships.</p>
<p>&quot;The principle benefit is the ability to move grains at a lower cost and in larger volumes from grain surplus areas of China to deficit areas,&quot; a project summary says.</p>
<p>Record harvests in 1996 and 1995 have overwhelmed storage capacity in the northeast, forcing the central government to order the shipment of millions of tonnes of corn and other grains to the south at great cost.</p>
<p>Official figures show China harvested 490 million tonnes of grain in 1996, shattering the previous year's record 466 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Corn traders especially would benefit from the project, Piazza said.</p>
<p>China reaped a record corn harvest of 119 million tonnes in 1996. But poor transport trapped that grain in the northeast, far from big markets in the south -- particularly the pig farms along the Yangtze River, he said.</p>
<p>The project had won bank approval and technical details and a timetable for implementation were being worked out by Chinese officials, another World Bank official said.</p>
<p>PROJECT TO HELP IMPORTS</p>
<p>The new bulk equipment would also make it easier to handle imports, Piazza said, adding that China would see net purchases from abroad of at least 20 million tonnes of grain a year within the next 20 years.</p>
<p>&quot;You're looking at around 40 million tonnes and 60 million tonnes for a credible high-end estimate,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>China imported 12 million tonnes of grain in 1996, down 42 percent from the previous year, official figures show.</p>
<p>The growing popularity of meat among increasingly affluent Chinese would help to fuel demand for feed grain, especially corn, Piazza said.</p>
<p>&quot;They're going to be very, very hard-pressed to keep up with demand,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>China should take steps to further open its grain markets to imports, he said. This would help to allay shortages at home while reducing Beijing's huge trade surplus with the United States, he added.</p>
<p>SELF-SUFFICIENCY STILL A CONCERN</p>
<p>A recent report by a research group under the Chinese Academy of Sciences also called for lowering the degree of self-sufficiency and raising grain imports.</p>
<p>China's grain shortfall would hit 50 million tonnes by 2030 with total consumption at 700 million, it said.</p>
<p>However, China was unlikely to raise its import ceilings in the near future because of concerns over self-sufficiency, officials involved in drafting the report said.</p>
<p>Self-sufficiency was still a big concern for China, in large part because Beijing had drawn lessons from U.S. bans on wheat exports to its Soviet communist foe in the 1980s, Piazza said.</p>
<p>China has sounded a note of caution in estimates for grain output this year, attributing the two past record harvests to unusually clement weather.</p>
<p>Piazza said China still had much room to improve yields, and gloomy predictions by Malthusians such as Lester Brown of the WorldWatch Institute that China's huge population would soon suck up world grain output were off base.</p>
<p>Land surveys showed Beijing had consistently underestimated its total cropland by up to one-third, he said. That meant per acre output statistics were artificially high and seemed to show China had reached a grain production peak.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
