<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571184" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: China Unicom held talks with HK Tel -paper.</title>
<headline>China Unicom held talks with HK Tel -paper.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>China United Telecommunications Corp (China Unicom) said it had held talks with Hong Kong Telecommunications Ltd about the possibility of buying a stake in the locally-listed company, newspapers reported on Thursday.</p>
<p>The Chinese concern had talked with Hongkong Telecom last year but no agreement had been reached, China Unicom president Li Huifen was quoted by the Hongkong Standard as saying.</p>
<p>Unicom hoped to resume the talks, she was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>She said the possibility of future cooperation with HongKong Telecom would not be ruled out, even if the plan to acquire a stake in the company was not successful, the newspaper reported.  </p>
<p>The South China Morning Post quoted Li as saying China Unicom was interested in taking a stake in Hongkong Telecom, although she understood the difficulties associated with such a deal.</p>
<p>&quot;This would need to be coodinated by the central (Chinese) government with final approval from the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office (of China),&quot; the newspaper quoted Li as saying.</p>
<p>Officials at Hongkong Telecom were not immediately available to comment.</p>
<p>China Unicom is a joint venture of 16 major Chinese organisations, led by the ministries of power, railways and electronics industry.  </p>
<p>It was set up in 1994 to compete with the Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications, which previously had a monopoloy in providing telephone services.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Hongkong Telecom's share price rose HK$0.10 to HK$14.20 on speculation it is seeking a Chinese partner, which is considered positive for the company's future as the British colony reverts to Chinese rule on July 1.</p>
<p>Cable and Wireless Plc, which holds 58.5 percent of Hongkong Telecom, on Wednesday fended off market talks that Chinese interest might take a stake in its Hong Kong unit, saying it would be business as usual through the territory's handover.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843 6590</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
