<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571168" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BURMA: FEATURE-Burma's monks, students lie low in the hot season.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Burma's monks, students lie low in the hot season.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Edwards</byline>
<dateline>MANDALAY, Burma 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mandalay lies quiet under the scorching sun of central Burma's hottest and driest months just weeks after some of the country's worst religious unrest in years.</p>
<p>As temperatures soar the Buddhist faithful head for the shade at the temples and pagodas that dot the landscape across the vast plains around this city.</p>
<p>The monks, too, appear for now to be sitting the hot season out. At the Mahagandhayon monastery in Amarapura, a few miles down the Irrawaddy River, most have left for home villages to await the arrival of the summer monsoon.</p>
<p>The same mood of quiet pervades in Rangoon where major universities remain closed following student upheaval in December.</p>
<p>But in both cities the sense of unease is tangible.</p>
<p>&quot;It's definitely getting worse,&quot; says a Western diplomat. &quot;The students are at home now,&quot; says a Rangoon resident, adding ominously, &quot;...but they've got lots of ideas in their heads.&quot; BURMA'S STUDENTS, MONKS REMAIN KEY TO DEMOCRACY MOVEMENT</p>
<p>Burma's students and monks, in many respects, continue to represent the conscience of this troubled nation.</p>
<p>Both had key roles in the pro-democracy protests between 1988-90. Both deny links with the opposition leader Aung San Suu Kyi, but both continue to play parts in the same political drama opposite the iron-fist rule of a military junta, the State Law and Order Restoration Council, or SLORC.</p>
<p>When monks in this city went on a rampage in March attacking Moslems and damaging mosques it was reported the trouble had been sparked by the appearance of a crack on a highly venerated Buddha image at the nearby Mahamuni Paya pagoda.</p>
<p>Other reports said it started following rumours that a Buddhist girl had been molested by Moslems.</p>
<p>Whatever the cause the violence quickly spread to other cities, reflecting what observers say is Burma's deep current volatility.</p>
<p>&quot;The SLORC was lucky,&quot; said a Rangoon-based diplomat. &quot;This could have got out of hand.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There are three elements here they have to worry about, the students, the monks and the NLD (National League for Democracy). If any two were to combine this whole place could explode.&quot; MILITARY RULERS SAY SITUATION MANIPULATED BY POLITICS</p>
<p>Today, few signs of the recent trouble are left. Barricades around mosques and night curfews had been removed in most areas. But mindful of the dangers of talking out loud, people are unwilling to speak.</p>
<p>Taxi drivers are reluctant to take foreign passengers to some mosques. Other city residents prefer to sit on the fence.</p>
<p>&quot;You know what our government's like,&quot; says an onlooker at one of Mandalay's main Moslem gathering places. &quot;I don't know you and you don't know me.&quot;</p>
<p>Burma's military rulers say the unrest and other events over the past eight months, including Washington's recent decision to impose sanctions, are deliberate acts aimed at blocking Burma's accession this year to the ASEAN regional bloc.</p>
<p>It's an arguement which is plausible. Malaysia and Indonesia, two dominantly Islamic countries and existing Association of South East Asian Nation members, may well have viewed the anti-Moslem violence with unease.</p>
<p>Washington, too, has stated its opposition to Burma's membership of the organisation. Diplomats say the United States and other countries may find dealing with a Burma inside ASEAN more difficult than dealing with it now.</p>
<p>&quot;If I was (Aung San) Suu Kyi, I'd be worried what might happen after July,&quot; said one foreign analyst. &quot;Wouldn't you?&quot; Burma could be admitted as early as July at ASEAN's annual meeting.</p>
<p>SLORC RANKS MAY BE SPLIT OVER ASEAN</p>
<p>A further factor in the complex equation is speculation that elements within SLORC's own upper ranks may be split over the merits of ASEAN membership, and working against joining.</p>
<p>According to some eyewitness accounts monks involved in the recent troubles had guns or wore military boots, suggesting those opposed to ASEAN membership may have been trying to use the violence to their advantage.</p>
<p>All in all, students, monks, military, NLD -- a group which Western analysts say must work together if the country's ills are to be righted -- it's a situation which has many people worried.</p>
<p>&quot;Over the last few months there have been worrying signs that there are some people who think that the problems can only be resolved through violent means,&quot; said Aung San Suu Kyi at a news conference in late April.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's a reflection of the general malaise of Burmese society... You cannot expect a society where there is rampant injustice to be a happy one.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BURMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANDALAY, Burma"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BURMA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
