<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571163" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PRESS DIGEST - Shanghai newspapers - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Shanghai newspapers - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major political and business stories in local newspapers, prepared by Reuters in Shanghai. Reuters has not checked the stories and does not guarantee their accuracy.</p>
<p>- SHANGHAI SECURITIES NEWS - China now has 15 million investors in the stock markets, more than one percent of the total population, but most of them lack psychological preparation for the risks involved, a commentary says.</p>
<p>- Shanghai has sold 2.876 billion yuan worth of treasury bonds in the issue beginning on May 1, accounting for 56.62 percent of the total amount planned for sale in the Shanghai area.</p>
<p>- BUSINESS NEWS - Japan's NEC and China's Huahong Microelectronics Co have signed a $1 billion deal to build an integrated circuit production facility in Shanghai.</p>
<p>- China economist Xiao Zhuoji said now would be a suitable time to list state shares and institutional shares on the stock markets, which would cool down the markets.</p>
<p>- The first train running on the direct rail link between Shanghai and Hong Kong will make its inaugural journey from Shanghai on May 19.</p>
<p>- Shanghai newsroom: telephone: (86-21) 6279-7004 fax: 6279-7174</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
