<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571109" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Shanghai B shares down at noon on cautious mood.</title>
<headline>Shanghai B shares down at noon on cautious mood.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shanghai's B share index was down at midday on Thursday with investors concerned about the increasing possibility that the securities authoritives will take measures to cool down the markets, brokers said.</p>
<p>The B index fell 0.935 points or 0.95 percent to 97.271 points on volume of 13.686 million shares worth $9.844 million, compared with $12.788 million on Wednesday.</p>
<p>China's official newspapers have continued to publish articles warning of the risks of investment in the stock markets.  </p>
<p>&quot;Most domestic investors are worried that the B shares will tumble along with the A shares if the government takes measures to crackdown on the speculative A share markets,&quot; said one broker.</p>
<p>&quot;More and more investors are blindly buying shares, and sooner or later Beijing will work out measures to curb the A share markets,&quot; said another broker. &quot;The B share market will certainly be affected.&quot;</p>
<p>Of 43 B shares, 41 traded, with 26 down, six flat and nine up.  </p>
<p>Wing Sung was the biggest loser on poor 1996 results, falling $0.018 or 5.99 percent to $0.282 on volume of 69,500 shares.</p>
<p>Market barometer Shanghai Lujiazui Finance &amp; Trade Zone Development was the most actively traded on profit-taking, shedding $0.010 or 0.62 percent to $1.608 on volume of 1.8 million shares.</p>
<p>Shanghai's A share index tumbled on the same concerns, brokers said.</p>
<p>The index slipped 21.669 points or 1.39 percent to 1,540.981 on volume of 495.5 million shares worth 7.6 billion yuan.  </p>
<p>The SSE30 blue chip index fell 68.812 points or 1.56 percent to 4,344.235 points.</p>
<p>Xiamen Engineering Machinery was the worst performer, dipping 0.58 yuan or 6.60 percent to 8.20 yuan on volume of 1.7 million shares.</p>
<p>--Shanghai newsroom (86-21) 6279-7004</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
