<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571118" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK govt rejects plan to favour small developers.</title>
<headline>HK govt rejects plan to favour small developers.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Hong Kong government has rejected proposals by the Consumer Council to offer preferential treatment to smaller property developers and extend more curbs on property speculation through legislation.</p>
<p>In a statement received on Thursday, the government said such further measures would contradict its free market policy which has long governed the residential property market.</p>
<p>&quot;The government adopts the principle of fair competition and does not discriminate against large or small developers in the tendering procedures for housing projects controlled or sponsored by the government,&quot; Dominic Wong, Secretary for Housing, said in the statement.</p>
<p>Wong also said measures already in place to curb speculation were sufficient.</p>
<p>&quot;We have already obtained the cooperation of property developers in adopting a series of voluntary measures...to curb speculative activities,&quot; Wong said.</p>
<p>&quot;The measures have been very effective, there is no need to consider legislation at present.&quot;</p>
<p>In mid-January, property developers opted to bar companies that buy uncompleted flats from changing company directorships before the signing of sales and purchase agreements.</p>
<p>Speculators have been using shell companies to buy flats before selling the companies and changing directorships to get around restrictions on quick reselling.</p>
<p>Skyrocketing property prices have been a major source of public anger in recent months, forcing the government to introduce ways to put more flats on sale and curb speculation.</p>
<p>Flats can now be pre-sold 15 months before completion, up from 12 months, and developers must offer them in batches no smaller than 20 percent of the total number available.</p>
<p>But the government said it agreed with other proposals made by the Consumer Council, including the rezoning of more industrial land for residential use and speeding up of procedures for the approval of private housing projects.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6441</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
