<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571128" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK stocks open sharply lower on Wall Street slide.</title>
<headline>HK stocks open sharply lower on Wall Street slide.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong stocks opened sharply lower on Thursday with the Hang Seng Index dropping 158 points, or 1.16 percent, to 13,447 within the first few minutes of trade after the Dow industrials tumbled overnight.</p>
<p>&quot;The market just followed Wall Street, which slid on fears of an interest rate rise,&quot; said Peter Lui, institutional sales trader at NAVA SC Securities.</p>
<p>The Dow dropped 139.67 points, or 1.93 percent, to 7,085.65 on Wednesday, hit by a rise in the benchmark 30-year U.S. bond yield which jumped back towards seven percent.</p>
<p>Disappointing first quarter U.S. productivity data and a sagging dollar pushed the 30-year bond down 29/32 on Wednesday to yield 6.96 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;But consistent buying on Hong Kong Telecom is helping to check the slide on the blue-chip index,&quot; Lui said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong Telecom rose HK$0.15 to HK$14.35 with 9.8 million shares worth HK$141 million changing hands.</p>
<p>Brokers said heavy buying in the stock was fuelled by newspaper reports that China United Telecommunications Corp held talks with Cable &amp; Wireless Plc about buying a stake in Hongkong Telecom.</p>
<p>By the end of the first hour of trade, the Hang Seng had recovered to 13,508, down 97 points or 0.71 percent on selective buying in blue chips. Turnover was HK$3.86 billion.</p>
<p>HSBC Holdings narrowed its losses to HK$1.00 at HK$206.00 after an early fall to HK$204.00.</p>
<p>Michael Ng, dealing director at Sassoon Securities, said movement in the blue-chip index alone was not that significant as buyers were turning to individual quality counters or speculative stocks.</p>
<p>Cheung Kong eased HK$0.75 to HK$72.75 and Sun Hung Kai Properties lost HK$1.25 to HK$89.50.</p>
<p>The Hang Seng Chinese Enterprise Index, which tracks the 26 H-shares, dropped 1.67 points, or 0.15 percent to 1,141.76.</p>
<p>Jilin Chemical was unchanged at HK$1.57 after recent gains while Jingwei Textile added HK$0.087 to HK$1.79.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
