<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571111" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila says waives additional U.S. sugar quota.</title>
<headline>Manila says waives additional U.S. sugar quota.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Philippines said on Thursday it does not want to export additional sugar to the United States for crop year 1996/1997 (Sept/Aug).</p>
<p>&quot;Pursuant to the decision of the sugar board expressed today on account of our stock situation, may we waive whatever additional quota we may still have under quota year 1996/1997,&quot; Gamboa said in a letter to U.S. Agricultural Attache John Wade.</p>
<p>On March 12, the U.S. government increased the Philippine sugar quota by 27,411 tonnes for crop year 1996/1997. The original allocation was 219,000 tonnes at the start of the crop year.  </p>
<p>The U.S, in order to help some countries, imports sugar under fixed quotas at a premium over market prices.</p>
<p>Wilson Gamboa, chairman of the Sugar Regulatory Administration, said the Philippines accounts for 13.5 percent of the total U.S. sugar quota.</p>
<p>The Philippines is yet to complete its present sugar quota to the U.S.</p>
<p>&quot;We undertake...to fill up completely our regular quota for the current quota year 1996-1997,&quot; Gamboa said in a letter to Wade, a copy of which was given to reporters.  </p>
<p>Gamboa said the three-man sugar board, whose members include a representative from the planters and millers, approved to waive the country's share of any additional U.S. quota because domestic harvests between May 4 and August 30 this year was expected to total 87,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Local sugar farmers had harvested 1.671 million tonnes raw sugar between September 1, 1996 to May 4 this year.</p>
<p>Sugar production may reach 1.758 million tonnes in the present crop year, he said. Gamboa had earlier projected output at 1.8 million tonnes for the crop year ending August.</p>
<p>&quot;The sugar board does not want to punish further the farmers by requiring them to set aside a portion of their remaining production to go into export which of course commands lower price by at least 70 to 90 peso per 50-kg bag compared to NFA prices,&quot; Gamboa said.</p>
<p>Under present rules, farmers are required to set aside 15 percent of their harvests for export to the U.S., which at present are bought by traders at 520 pesos per kg, he said.</p>
<p>The state-owned National Food Authority (NFA) launched last February a sugar buying programme to bid up local prices. The agency buys a 50-kg sugar bag at 610 pesos.</p>
<p>-- MANILA NEWSROOM (63 2) 841-8936, FAX 817-6267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100136">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
