<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571155" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: PRESS DIGEST - Singapore - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Singapore - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are top stories from selected Singapore newspapers. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>THE STRAITS TIMES:</p>
<p>- The 11 People's Action Party leaders who won 13 defamation lawsuits against opposition politician Tang Liang Hong have asked the High Court for Singapore $12.9 million in damages.</p>
<p>- Singapore's schools are doing their best to put in place television aerials ahead of the launch of the National Education programme on May 17.</p>
<p>- Disguised as visa applicants, about 20 activists entered Japan's de facto consulate in Taipei to protest against a Japanese legislator landing on the disputed Senkaku/Diaoyu islands.</p>
<p>- Two Singaporeans were executed in Kaohsiung in Taiwan for smuggling 150 kg of heroin from Thailand into the island.</p>
<p>- Singapore's annual budget surplus is set to exceed S$10 billion for the first time with over S$8 billion generated in the first nine months of the fiscal year ending in March.</p>
<p>- Hock Hua Bank Bhd signed an agreement to sell its 51.81 percent stake in a local bank for around S$110.2 million.</p>
<p>THE BUSINESS TIMES:</p>
<p>- A strong cast of Chinese and Singaporean companies are aong the major contenders for a huge residential project to be built at the Kowloon airport railway station worth an estimated Singapore $2.8-$3.7 billion.</p>
<p>- Property developers are seeking to maximise yields by building cluster houses and strata bungalows -- landed housing with condominium facilities.</p>
<p>- The Thai government has given its tentative approval for a national merchant fleet worth S$144.4 million over the next four year.</p>
<p>- Property and construction group Lim Kahh Ngam Ltd is considering selling the Hotel Equatorial site and is looking around for property to develop a commercial build in Singpaore.</p>
<p>- Auric Pacific is looking for a group executive director less than two weeks after a friendly takeover put control of the company into the hands of Indonesian congolomerate Lippo.</p>
<p>- Keppel Fels' U.S. based subsidiary, Amfels Inc, has clinched S$86.7 million deal to build a drilling rig for Chiles Offshore Inc of Houston.</p>
<p>- Precision engineering company Uraco Holdings said it had no business dealings with CAM International Holdings, which is under investigation after two of CAM's director were accused of cheating the firm of millions of dollars.</p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom 65-8703080</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
