<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571225" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy opposition look to seize election initiative.</title>
<headline>Italy opposition look to seize election initiative.</headline>
<byline>Crispian Balmer</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy's centre-right Freedom Alliance opposition is looking to regain the political initiative by winning control of key city councils, including Milan and Turin, in second round local elections being held this weekend.</p>
<p>First round ballots 11 days ago showed Silvio Berlusconi's centre-right bloc inching ahead in a number of large cities.</p>
<p>They also exposed Prime Minister Romano Prodi's dependence on his hard-left ally, the Communist Refoundation, whose support could be vital if the ruling centre-left Olive Tree coalition is to see off Berlusconi's challenge.</p>
<p>Some 5.43 million Italians, just over a tenth of the electorate, are eligible to vote in Sunday's contests between the two front runners in races where no-one took more than 50 percent at the first ballot.</p>
<p>In all, run-off contests are being held for 77 mayors and five provincial presidents, with the key battles being fought in the wealthy northern cities of Milan, Turin and Trieste.</p>
<p>Freedom Alliance candidates led in both Turin and Milan in the April 27 vote, buoying the centre-right just over a year after their general election defeat by the Olive Tree.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the start of the long march towards the reconquest of the country,&quot; former prime minister Berlusconi told an election rally in Milan last weekend.</p>
<p>&quot;A coalition of powers is increasingly threatening our well-being, our democracy, our future and the freedom of our children,&quot; he added, dropping his recent, more conciliatory political tone and reverting to tough, anti-government rhetoric.</p>
<p>The Olive Tree might still emerge victorious, despite unpopular economic policies which have revolved around bitter budgetary medicine as it fights to prepare Italy for the launch of Europe's planned single currency in 1999.</p>
<p>However it will need the support of Communist Refoundation voters to succeed.</p>
<p>Refoundation, which provides Prodi's margin of control in the lower house of parliament, showed strongly in the first round ballot, often taking more than 10 percent of the vote when it presented independent candidates.</p>
<p>&quot;Where we stand with the Olive Tree, we win, where they go alone... they lose,&quot; said Refoundation leader, Fausto Bertinotti.</p>
<p>Refoundation has struck a deal with the centre-left candidate and current mayor in Turin, Valentino Castellani, for Sunday's election, but its offers to link up with the Olive Tree hopeful in Milan, Aldo Fumagalli, have been spurned.</p>
<p>The party has advised its supporters to abstain in Milan, opening the way for Freedom Alliance candidate Gabriele Albertini, who took 40.7 percent of the vote on April 27, to take control of Italy's second city.</p>
<p>But Sunday's elections, at least in the north, could also be decided by how supporters of the Northern League vote. The separatist party was badly bloodied in the first round, losing power in a host of cities and provinces, including Milan.</p>
<p>Mercurial party leader Umberto Bossi urged his followers not to vote for the &quot;Rome&quot; parties on Sunday. &quot;We'll send everybody off to the mountains,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
