<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571227" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Aegon Q1 profits seen rising 17 percent.</title>
<headline>Aegon Q1 profits seen rising 17 percent.</headline>
<dateline>THE HAGUE 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Insurer Aegon is expected to announce a rise in first quarter 1997 net profit of 17 percent to nearly 381 million guilders next week, with a higher dollar seen boosting strong underlying growth, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts estimates for the result, due next Thursday, ranged between 363.5-405 million guilders versus 325.6 million guilders during the first quarter of 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Profits in the first quarter have been getting an extra boost from the higher dollar,&quot; said Dennis Ederzeel of Delta Lloyd Bank. The dollar was trading at 1.6515 to the guilder at the end of March 1996 against 1.89 guilders a year later.</p>
<p>&quot;An increase of the dollar by some 10 percent should push Aegon's profits three to four percent higher,&quot; said Ederzeel.</p>
<p>Some analysts said that profit growth was expected to accelerate in the remainder of the year as profit margins are always somewhat pressured at the start of a new year due to the way the company books increases in premiums.</p>
<p>Profits rose by 12.6 percent in the first three months of 1996 and 15.7 percent during the first half, and then increased 16.6 percent and 18.5 percent respectively during the first nine months and the full-year of 1996.</p>
<p>Analysts said profits would also get an extra upward push during the second half of 1997 from the acquisition in the making of the insurance activities of U.S. Providian Corp.</p>
<p>The intended acquisition is expected to be finalised by June or July, 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;Aegon is a very good buy,&quot; said Tom Muller of NIBStrating Securities.</p>
<p>Muller expected the insurer to show a net profit rise of some 20 percent for the whole of 1997.</p>
<p>Muller said that the strong increase in investment income (as result of the good investment climate in the share market) and the boost from the stronger dollar would flatten somewhat in the remainder of the year as those factors have had a positive influence in part of 1996 as well.</p>
<p>Bart van der Feen of Rabo Securities was even more upbeat on Aegon's full-year profit, forecasting a rise of 25 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;This should be possible if the Providian acquisition is finalised before the second half of 1997,&quot; Van der Feen said.</p>
<p>Analysts said organic growth of Aegon's life insurance business should continue in its normal pace.</p>
<p>Results in non-life were increasing, analysts said, partly because of the precautionary measures Aegon was taking to combat car theft.</p>
<p>-- Wendy Braanker, Amsterdam newsroom +31 20 504 5000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="THE HAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
