<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571211" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israelis say U.S. Holocaust report only a start.</title>
<headline>Israelis say U.S. Holocaust report only a start.</headline>
<byline>Howard Goller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli officials fighting to recover assets looted by the Nazis from Holocaust victims said on Thursday a U.S. study criticising Switzerland had uncovered an affair that contaminated all of Europe.</p>
<p>The study, made public on Wednesday, criticised Switzerland for banking Nazi gold during and after World War Two and gave evidence that some gold the Nazis sold to the Swiss was taken from Holocaust victims.</p>
<p>&quot;I have a feeling there wasn't a bar of gold going around Europe then which didn't have at least one golden tooth torn from the mouth of a Jewish victim,&quot; Avraham Burg, chairman of the quasi-governmental Jewish Agency, told Israel Radio.</p>
<p>The Jewish Agency has for two years campaigned for the return of looted assets to the heirs of Holocaust victims. The Nazis under Adolf Hitler systematically killed six million Jews during World War Two, many in death camps.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that only the first chapter is over,&quot; Burg told Israel's army radio. &quot;This is a story of a Europe contaminated by the plunder of Jewish victims.&quot; He demanded further action to recover looted assets throughout Europe.</p>
<p>The seven-month study said the Reichsbank had an account for melted-down loot from death camp victims, such as rings, coins and gold teeth, and sold some of this along with gold taken from occupied countries to finance the German war machine.</p>
<p>&quot;I am acting now to establish an international commission of inquiry because we are not speaking only of gold, we are not speaking only of Switzerland. All of Europe is contaminated,&quot; Burg said on Thursday.</p>
<p>In a statement, the Jewish Agency demanded:</p>
<p>- Sealing any vaults in the West containing tainted money and gold so that &quot;every last cent&quot; could be returned to Jewish hands.</p>
<p>- All governments involved in the post-war transfer of funds must open their archives so that looted assets can be located for the heirs of Holocaust victims.</p>
<p>- The governments must finance an international investigation of the archives.</p>
<p>U.S. Undersecretary of Commerce Stuart Eizenstat, who helped compile the report, said he favoured holding an international conference this year on the flow of Nazi assets after the war and said it would be important to have German records available to trace them.</p>
<p>Britain's new Labour government offered on Tuesday to host an international conference, and Switzerland welcomed the idea.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
