<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571207" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: PRESS DIGEST - Lebanon - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Lebanon - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Lebanese press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>AN-NAHAR</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Hariri accused Lebanese intelligence agencies of destroying civilian institutions.</p>
<p>- Iran's Foreign Minister Velayati handed President Hrawi an invitation to attend the Islamic summit meeting in Tehran in December, and an invitation to Prime Minister Hariri to visit Tehran in June.</p>
<p>- General Lahd, commander of the pro-Israeli South Lebanon Army militia said in an open letter to the pope that Lebanon is becoming a dectatorship.</p>
<p>AS-SAFIR</p>
<p>- Israeli warplanes raided south Lebanon and west Bekaa.</p>
<p>- Syrian President Assad received Lebanese parliament Speaker Berri in Damascus.</p>
<p>- Shi'ite Moslem Sheikh Fadlallah, who is widely seen as spiritual guide of the pro-Iranian Hizbollah, said: &quot;I hope the Pope will condemn Israel's massacres in south Lebanon&quot;.</p>
<p>- Foreign Minister Bouez said the structure of the United Nations including the security council must be reveiwed.</p>
<p>AL-ANWAR</p>
<p>- Bouez said Lebanon is watching the U.S.-Israeli-Turkish alliance with deep concern.</p>
<p>AD-DIYAR</p>
<p>- Hrawi opened meeting of the U.N.'s Economic and Social Commission for Western Asia (ESCWA).</p>
<p>- Hariri met Syrian Vice President Khaddam in Damascus.</p>
<p>NIDA'A AL-WATAN</p>
<p>- The council of Maronite bishops said the Pope's impending visit to Lebanon has united the Lebanese people.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
