<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571253" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Worldwide Advertising &amp; Media Digest - May 8.</title>
<headline>Worldwide Advertising &amp; Media Digest - May 8.</headline>
<text>
<p>------------------------- WAM ------------------------</p>
<p>....REUTERS WORLDWIDE ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA DIGEST.....</p>
<p>------------------- May 8, 1997------------------</p>
<p>Reuters news from around the world on Advertising, Marketing, Media, the Internet, Brand-name Products and Consumer Trends</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>ADVERTISING &amp; MARKETING:</p>
<p>LONDON - Britain's advertising industry expects the newly elected Labour government to act quickly on its promise to ban tobacco advertising, but it is more concerned about a precedent being set for the regulation of other kinds of advertising.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MILAN - Italian advertising agencies had a year of growth in 1996 and the outlook for 1997 is positive, says the Italian Association of Advertising Agencies.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - France faces the dilemma of breaking its own laws or depriving French TV viewers of seeing next year's World Cup finals if it allows U.S. brewer Anheuser-Busch to advertise at the World Cup venues.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MILAN - Italian advertising company Publitalia, part of broadcaster Mediaset, will show revenue growth &quot;superior to market growth&quot; in the first half of this year, its chairman Giuliano Adreani says.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>MEDIA &amp; THE INTERNET:</p>
<p>SYDNEY - Rupert Murdoch's global media empire News Corp Ltd announces a sharp rise in third-quarter profits, helped by the successful re-release of the Star Wars movie trilogy by its Fox Films unit.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - The number of people who watch television at least once a day in France rose in the first quarter of 1997 compared with the same period last year, French audience measurement body Mediametrie says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>LONDON - British Digital Broadcasting (BDB), a UK consortium of television giants bidding for rights to offer digital terrestrial TV services, says it is in talks for collaboration with British Interactive Broadcasting (BIB). BIB, a newly formed satellite TV group seeking to provide services such as home banking and shopping as part of its television offerings, and BDB both include British Sky Broadcasting as a member.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PHOENIX - Move over, Mickey Mouse. Rupert Murdoch's Twentieth Century Fox studio is looking to muscle in on one of Walt Disney Co.'s prized possessions -- animated feature films. Fox says it is preparing to fire its first salvo later this year with the release of &quot;Anastasia,&quot; based on the Russian princess of the same name.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - The French have been slow to catch the Internet/multimedia bug but nearly a fifth plan to connect in the next two years and buy multimedia equipment, a study published by measurement institute Publimetrie and educational television channel La Cinquieme says.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>BRAND-NAME PRODUCTS MARKETS:</p>
<p>TOKYO - Japanese electronics giant Sony Corp reports record group profits for the last business year, aided by robust global sales and a weak yen, and predicts further growth in the current year. &quot;Larger group sales were due to higher sales in Japan, the United States, Europe and other areas as well as the yen's depreciation,&quot; Sony says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>SHANGHAI - Revlon Inc says it will begin production of its ColorStay brand of lipstick in Shanghai, marking the first manufacturing venture in China by the U.S. cosmetics company.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Curiosity got the better of about 10,000 people in Frankfurt as car maker Mercedes-Benz opened up an unusual six-storey cube in the city centre to show off its new A-class compact vehicle.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - With eight months to go before France fully opens up its telecommunications market, national operator France Telecom is already facing competition from specialised service companies offering call-back services, call box services and Internet telephony.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>TOKYO - Sony Computer Entertainment Inc says it expects to ship 18 million units of its game console PlayStation in the global market in 1997/98. Sony says its net sales of game machines and software would reach 650 billion yen ($5.2 billion) in 1997/98, up from an estimated 400 billion yen in 1996/97.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>LONDON - Brewer to leisure group Whitbread Plc plans to open another 250 high street restaurants and pubs this year at a cost of some 400 million pounds ($648.9 million), creating about 5,000 jobs, chief executive designate David Thomas says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>SEOUL - South Korea's largest car maker, Hyundai Motor Co., expects to win approval to build a joint venture plant in Vietnam in the first half of this year, a company spokesman says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>NEW YORK - Fuji Photo Film Co will start making film in the United States, raising the stakes in its competition with Eastman Kodak Co, the Wall Street Journal says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>CHICAGO - Flushed with the enormous success of its Teenie Beanie Babies marketing push, McDonald's Corp. is hoping to repeat with its upcoming kids promotion featuring the hit Sky Dancers toys.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>CARACAS - Vehicle sales in Venezuela rose 192 percent in April to reach 11,980 units, compared to 4,098 over the same period a year ago, Venezuela's Automobile Chamber says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - Software piracy rose 20 percent in 1996 compared with the year before, with about one of every two new business software applications being pirated, according to a study by the Software Publishers Association and the Business Software Alliance.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>CONSUMER TRENDS:</p>
<p>LONDON - Nostalgia, classic brands and alcoholic drinks that &quot;don't give you a hangover&quot; are going to be big consumer trends in the future,&quot; American &quot;futurologist&quot; Marian Salzman, of the TBWA ad agency, says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MILAN - Italian wine exports to Japan had a boom year in 1996 with sales up 60.2 percent on 1995 for a total value of 94.62 billion lire ($55.7 million), the Lombardy Foreign Trade Centre reports. Increasing visits to Italy by Japanese tourists is boosting the appreciation of Italian cuisine and wines, says Paolo Makiyama, chairman of the Milan office of the International Nikken trading company.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>-- London Advertising Newsdesk +44 171 542 2792</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>See full stories on Reuters Advertising &amp; Media Briefing. And why not visit our Internet site at http://www.bizinfo.reuters.com?</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>($ = 0.616 British Pounds)</p>
<p>($ = 124.7 Japanese Yen)</p>
<p>($ = 1699 Italian Lire)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
