<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571219" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: PRESS DIGEST - Spain - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Spain - May 8.</headline>
<text>
<p>Headlines from major national newspapers. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>EL PAIS</p>
<p>- Public prosecutors will only support successor to state prosecutor Juan Ortiz Urculo that will punish &quot;rebel&quot; prosecutors.</p>
<p>- Ruling Popular Party accuses ex-director of tax agency of pardoning debts of La Caixa.</p>
<p>EL MUNDO</p>
<p>- Creation of new tax to finance health divides government.</p>
<p>- Only two of seven accused in &quot;Costa Polvoranca&quot; crime are sentenced.</p>
<p>- Disciplinary action brought against Barcelona magistrate for sexually harassing civil servant.</p>
<p>DIARIO 16</p>
<p>- Public prosecutors get mad with government.</p>
<p>- Snow returns to Spain.</p>
<p>ABC</p>
<p>- Socialist party paid 199 million pesetas to company Prensa Sur, co-owner of Andalucia Post from 1988 to 1992.</p>
<p>CINCO DIAS</p>
<p>- Rise in price of pork threatens to close meat companies.</p>
<p>- Constitutional doubts over compensation for traffic accidents.</p>
<p>EXPANSION</p>
<p>- Government believes inflation can fall in May to 1.5 percent.</p>
<p>- Competition Defence body dismantles distribution monopoly of Tabacalera.</p>
<p>GACETA DE LOS NEGOCIOS</p>
<p>- Electricity law liberalises tariffs for all consumers.</p>
<p>- Catalan president Jordi Pujol brands as serious failure lack of accord on revision of health financing system.</p>
<p>- Argentaria storms through 7,00 pesetas on stock market.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
