<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571224" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: Portugal's Petrogal sees rising profit.</title>
<headline>Portugal's Petrogal sees rising profit.</headline>
<dateline>LISBON 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>State-controlled energy company Petrogal-Petroleos de Portugal said it saw profits rising sharply between 1997 and 2000.</p>
<p>The company, which made a profit of 6.6 billion escudos in 1996 after losing 11.9 billion the year before, expects to boost the profit figure to 9.8 billion escudos in 1997.</p>
<p>Profits should climb to 20.4 billion in 1998 and 30.7 billion in 1999.</p>
<p>But company chairman Manuel Ferreira de Oliveira warned that forecasts were very difficult in the energy business where factors extraneous to the company -- particularly oil prices -- could boost or reduce the figure by 10 billion escudos in any one year.</p>
<p>He told the Lisbon bourse in a presentation that investment in 1997 was seen at between 40 and 50 billion escudos, little changed on the 44.3 billion escudos invested in 1996.</p>
<p>He said that complying with new European Union rules on pollution control would need total investment of 40 to 50 billion escudos between 1998 and 2003.</p>
<p>He added that the return to profit in 1996 had been achieved largely thanks to a fall in financial costs, which were 11 billion escudos down on the previous year.</p>
<p>($1=173 escudos)</p>
<p>--Lisbon bureau 3511-3150035</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LISBON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
