<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571238" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German construction talks end with shaky pact.</title>
<headline>German construction talks end with shaky pact.</headline>
<byline>John Gilardi</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Arbitration talks for about 1.3 million German construction workers ended on Thursday with a shaky compromise deal between unions and employers that calls for lower sick-pay benefits and a modest wage increase.</p>
<p>The pact, which calls for workers to receive only 80 percent of gross pay during the first three weeks of sick time and a 1.3 percent wage increase beginning April 1, must now be approved by both the IG Bau trade union and industry employers.</p>
<p>Officials on both sides questioned whether the leadership of the industry employer group or the IG Bau trade union would approve the deal reached after 20 hours of talks led by Heiner Geissler, a member of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian Democratic party, that ended on Thursday morning.</p>
<p>They also noted the deal was approved on a 5-4 vote, reflecting the failure of leaders on both sides to reach a comprehensive pact. The deal also failed to reach an agreement on wages for east German construction workers.</p>
<p>Both sides now have 14 days to decide on the arbitration deal. If the deal collapses on both sides, the union then can take industrial action, according to officials at the talks.</p>
<p>The last round of talks broke down without a conclusive agreement in early April, prompting the appointment of Geissler as an independent arbitrator as union officials threatened industrial action and workers staged major protests.</p>
<p>Geissler said the deal reached on Thursday calls for sick pay to return to 100 percent for the remaining three weeks of the six weeks of annual sick pay that German workers receive.</p>
<p>He also said the so-called &quot;13th month&quot; salary received by German workers would only be paid out at about 77 percent of a month's salary and a new lower wage group would be established to create new jobs at a time of record German unemployment.</p>
<p>But unions had, among other demands, called for wage increases of 2.9 percent and continued full pay during sick leave against the objections of employers, who had demanded no wage increase and a halving of the 13th month pay.</p>
<p>IG Bau leader Klaus Wiesenhuegel said at the end of the talks he was not sure whether the union's full wage commission would approve the deal, saying he was concerned the reduced sick-pay benefits would be rejected by union members.</p>
<p>The employer group's leader, Wilhelm Kuechler, also said he was not certain whether the deal would be approved by its members, who have often complained about the union's wage demands at a time of recessionary industry conditions.</p>
<p>Politicians and union leaders had given mixed views ahead of the talks, with officials on both sides pessimistic about the likely outcome.</p>
<p>The talks were held as thousands of union workers took to the streets of Frankfurt on Wednesday, blocking a major highway crossing amid threats for further demonstrations.</p>
<p>The importance of the talks was highlighted by the release last week of two new studies on the construction sector, the country's largest industry, that made clear Germany's builders must reckon with a further two years of declining construction spending.</p>
<p>--Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
