<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571249" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FEATURE - Novel services steal a march on France Telecom.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Novel services steal a march on France Telecom.</headline>
<byline>Marcel Michelson</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>With eight months to go before France fully opens up its telecommunications market, national operator France Telecom is already facing competition from specialised service companies.</p>
<p>Call-back services, call box services and Internet telephony are stealing customers by making use of the difference in cost of local and long-distance calls.</p>
<p>With a call-back service, a client calls a local number for making an international call.</p>
<p>A call box uses a local line to connect to a private system of international connections, and with Internet telephony the client pays only the local rate to the server of the Internet Access Provider.</p>
<p>The volume of traffic is still limited and France Telecom and other operators are re-structuring prices by cutting international and long-distance rates.</p>
<p>WHY DO INTERNATIONAL CALLS COST SO MUCH?</p>
<p>International calls have been expensive for two reasons. First, they were set in a bilateral agreements between the two countries involved. Governments fixed the rates for their national operators within the framework of the Geneva-based International Telecommunications Union (ITU).</p>
<p>Secondly, the costs of setting up the infrastructure were high.</p>
<p>&quot;For international calls you had to make important investments. In undersea cables, in satellites or by taking a stake in a cable consortium or satellite grouping,&quot; said a France Telecom spokesman.</p>
<p>&quot;Nowadays, those investments have been made and the cost of international calls is less than it used to be.&quot;</p>
<p>Multinational companies were the first to complain about their international phone bills and started to play off national operators against each other to get the best deal. Services to multinational companies became the first of the liberalised areas in telecommunications and operators are joining up to offer the best possible service.</p>
<p>France Telecom is part of the Global One grouping with Deutsche Telekom and Sprint Corp. British Telecom, MCI and Spain's Telefonica are in the Concert alliance.</p>
<p>The Swiss, Dutch, Swedish national operators are joined in Unisource in which until recently Telefonica also took part.</p>
<p>AT&amp;T has a joint venture with Unisource.</p>
<p>The business services market is a multi-billion dollar market and fiercely competitive. The residential market is less competitive, but the new services have been taking away some customers.</p>
<p>THE CALL BOX</p>
<p>Immigrant families in France spend large amounts on calling home in Algeria, Vietnam and other countries.</p>
<p>In the popular quarters of Paris, such as in the 19th and 20th arrondisements where many immigrants live, people queue for a long time to use a phone box and talk to the family for the duration of a pre-paid phone card.</p>
<p>For the past few weeks they have been offered an alternative in a small shop on the Boulevard de Belleville.</p>
<p>Its windows are filled with little signs and destinations, like a travel shop, but here the prices are in francs per minute.</p>
<p>Call Box is an English service brought to France by entrepreneur Andy Cudworth who lives above his first shop in Paris.</p>
<p>By having its telephone boxes inside the shop, Call Box gets round the French law that leaves the monopoly on telephone booths in the hands of France Telecom.</p>
<p>A Call Box user sees an international call taken through the local network to a private one which takes it to the destination, allowing big discounts on the official France Telecom rates.</p>
<p>Cudworth has four shops in Paris and is opening one each in Lille, Marseilles and Toulon.</p>
<p>After the immigrants, he plans to target the tourist market by offering discount services to Japanese or U.S. tourists, opening shops near landmarks such as the Sacre Coeur or the Louvre.</p>
<p>CALL BACK SYSTEMS GET MORE USER FRIENDLY</p>
<p>There are about 20 companies in France who offer so-called call-back services.</p>
<p>Here a client calls a computer, mostly based in the U.S., then hangs up so the computer can call back. The system makes use of the difference between the international rate for calling from France to the U.S. and the rates for calls originating in the U.S.</p>
<p>Telegroup France is the market leader, followed by USA Global Link and Transworld. The subsidiary of Telegroup Inc, due to be listed on Nasdaq later this month, started its services in France in 1993.</p>
<p>Telegroup Inc, with $210 million in 1996 sales, is smaller worldwide than USA Global Link which claims $1 billion in sales.</p>
<p>In France, Telegroup has 40,000 subscribers with monthly sales of $1.2 million.</p>
<p>Since early 1997 it has been offering Global Access Direct, which is a more client-friendly service. It does not need the procedure of hanging up and waiting for a return call and it can also be used with any phone and not just at the main address.</p>
<p>Under Global Access Direct a caller calls a switchboard in the Paris suburb of Boulogne-Billancourt. The switchboard calls the U.S. switchboard and arranges the call-back in 10 seconds while the client remains on the line.</p>
<p>&quot;It's more expensive than classic call-back but far more client-friendly,&quot; a spokeswoman for Telegroup said.</p>
<p>With Global Access Direct, a customer calling New York pays 1.67 francs per unit (about a minute) to Telegroup and the local rate of 0.615 francs per unit to France Telecom.</p>
<p>Under the classic call-back, a user would pay 2.46 francs to France Telecom for the first call to New York and for the rest 1.67 francs per unit to Telegroup.</p>
<p>A standard call via France Telecom costs 2.46 francs per unit.</p>
<p>&quot;It is getting more and more difficult for call-back operations. With the rise in the dollar and the France Telecom call rate cuts there is less of a margin to use,&quot; the spokeswoman added.</p>
<p>At France Telecom, a spokesman said that all call-back traffic combined was still less than one percent of total calls.</p>
<p>He said a recent decision by the European Union on VAT, applying the VAT rates of the country which originated the call-back call, instead of the call-back country, would also deal a blow to these services.</p>
<p>This means that U.S. based call-back services have to charge France's 20.6 percent VAT rale to French customers.</p>
<p>INTERNET TELEPHONE</p>
<p>The Internet world-wide network of connected computers has been the clearest illustration that the price differences between local and long-distance rates are hard to maintain.</p>
<p>On the Net -- owned by nobody, controlled by nobody but using existing telecom infrastructure owned by the operators -- surfing is always at the local rate, whether to Paris, Peking or Passadena.</p>
<p>Once the user has made connection with the Internet Access Provider, the world is open at a local call rate.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, people have been developing software to allow telephony using the microphone -- and sometimes also a little camera -- of the personal computer. Calls are also possible from a computer to a normal telephone.</p>
<p>British researchers Philips Tarifica say the Internet will force price cuts on call rates. A report said British Telecom would lose $105 million in annual revenue, France Telecom some $94 million and Deutsche Telekom $173 million.</p>
<p>France Telecom, however, is not viewing Internet telecommunications as a pure threat.</p>
<p>Last month the company signed a deal to test an Internet telephony system developed by Lucent Technologies Inc that uses conventional phones instead of computers.</p>
<p>The Lucent Internet Telephony Server SP is a combination of software and hardware that enables phone companies to route calls through the Internet.</p>
<p>USA Global Link, a company which started as a call-back service, is investing $500 million on a big launch into Internet telephony with a market float scheduled for the fourth quarter of 1997.</p>
<p>Using Lucent technology, the company plans to install switchboards at 1,008 locations around the world, bypassing national phone gateways and using the Internet without loss of quality.</p>
<p>It plans to start services in the third quarter of 1997 in Australia, Brazil, Britain, France, Germany, Hong Kong, Japan, South Korea, Singapore and Taiwan.</p>
<p>Company chairman Christopher Hartnett told Reuters that the company was moving out of call-back activities because of lower rates.</p>
<p>&quot;All telephony should come back to cost based pricing,&quot; he said, noting Global Link could undercut Deutsche Telekom by 60 percent on local calls and 80 percent on international calls.</p>
<p>France Telecom said it feared neither the Internet nor Internet telephony.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe in Internet and we think that in the future part of the telephone calls will be made over the Internet. We are studying the technologies with industrialists and other operators,&quot; a spokesman said, adding that use of the Internet was increasing the use of the French telecommunications infrastructure.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
