<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571213" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: PRESS DIGEST - Jordan - May 8.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Jordan - May 8.</headline>
<dateline>AMMAN 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Jordanian press on Thursday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>AL-DUSTOUR</p>
<p>- King Hussein gives go ahead to proceed with a 431 million dinar ($609 million) &quot;social safety&quot; net programme over the coming years. &quot;We hope to attain self-sufficiency in the near future,&quot; the monarch says.</p>
<p>- Head of the centrist National Constitutional Party Abdul Hadi al-Majali says Jordan fears solving the Palestinian refugee issue at its expense; says Palestinian Authority has to define who is a Palestinian to avoid duality of loyalty.</p>
<p>AL-RAI</p>
<p>- King Hussein stresses the need to improve living conditions of Jordanians and easing suffering of disadvantaged groups in society; 431 million dinars allocated to projects to include 173 million dinars to refugee camps and 145 million dinars to local councils.</p>
<p>- Foreign minister says no rift in ties with Israel and stresses Jordanian-Israeli ties are not passing through a crisis; stresses that Jordanian water rights issue was behind the cancellation of the meeting with Israeli officials along the border last Tuesday.</p>
<p>AL-ASWAQ</p>
<p>- Crown Prince Hassan calls for rehabilitating Arab economies taking into consideration the location of the region at the crossroads of East and West.</p>
<p>- In two separate festivals which were attended by thousands, both the Ministry of Religious Affairs and the Moslem Brotherhood mark Islamic New Year.</p>
<p>- King says there will be a new effort to raise living standards of Jordanians.</p>
<p>JORDAN TIMES</p>
<p>- King receives a call from Israeli President Ezer Weizman who briefs monarch on his talks with Palestinain leader Yasser Arafat.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMMAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
