<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="571218" id="root" date="1997-05-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BAHRAIN: ANZ Investment Bank to lead Pakistan bond issue.</title>
<headline>ANZ Investment Bank to lead Pakistan bond issue.</headline>
<dateline>MANAMA 1997-05-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>ANZ Investment Bank has been mandated to lead a three-year bond issue by Pakistan, Holger von Paucker, the bank's general manager for the United Kingdom and Europe, said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>A roadshow to sell the bullet maturity bond to institutional and private investors started earlier this week, he said in a statement distributed after a press conference in Manama.</p>
<p>It will include Bahrain, Abu Dhabi, Singapore, Tokyo, Seoul, London and New York and represents the first opportunity for investors to gain new Pakistani government exposure after elections in February, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The floating rates notes are expected to raise a minimum of $100 million...Though early reports from the roadshows indicates interest among investors that could well push this figure higher&quot;, von Paucker said.</p>
<p>The indicative spread of the notes, which will be listed on the Luxembourg Stock Exchange, is Libor plus 375-425 basis points per year, he said. The tentative launch date is May 20 and the tentative close date is May 30.</p>
<p>&quot;We have chosen the Gulf as a key point in our roadshow because of the high interest shown among investors here in our previous investment roadshows,&quot; said Gordon Wood, the bank's director of distribution. &quot;We expect to raise close to one third of the total amount from the Gulf states alone&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BAHRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANAMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BAHRAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
