<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608148" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Thiessen says economy strong, job rate to improve.</title>
<headline>Thiessen says economy strong, job rate to improve.</headline>
<dateline>CALGARY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canada's economy is fundamentally strong and unemployment should gradually improve within the next year despite recent data showing an apparent drop in consumer confidence, Bank of Canada Governor Gordon Thiessen said on Friday.</p>
<p>Thiessen rejected speculation that a recent decline in Canada's retail sales and imports revealed a vulnerable economy.</p>
<p>&quot;There are always going to be some ups and downs (in the numbers),&quot; Thiessen told reporters following a speech to a Calgary business group.  </p>
<p>The underlying fundamentals of the economy are better than they have been in years, Thiessen added.</p>
<p>Thiessen said the improving economy should lead to an employment pickup within the next 12 to 18 months as businesses expand their part-time and full-time work forces in response to increased sales.</p>
<p>Canada's current unemployment rate stands at 9.6 percent for April.</p>
<p>&quot;Unemployment always lags a little bit further behind...but I think you're going to see, as this year goes by, we're going to see some better employment numbers,&quot; Thiessen said.</p>
<p>((Paul Simao, Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8104))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CALGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
