<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608194" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX Hub natgas mostly ends higher on late rally.</title>
<headline>NYMEX Hub natgas mostly ends higher on late rally.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX Henry Hub natgas futures mostly ended near session highs Friday in fairly active trade, driven by a late wave of technical buying and short covering when some key points were breached, market sources said.</p>
<p>June rallied 8.9 cents to close at $2.285 per million British thermal units after dipping to $2.185 on the open. July settled seven cents higher at $2.294. Other months ended mixed, with some 1999s down slightly.</p>
<p>&quot;Once we broke $2.25 (basis June), the locals went after the shorts and hit some (buy) stops,&quot; said a Midwest trader. NYMEX is closed Monday for the U.S. Memorial Day holiday.  </p>
<p>But despite the sharp move higher and more bullish technical picture, many remained skeptical current levels can be sustained, with little heating or cooling load forecast right into early June.</p>
<p>&quot;The shorts got squeezed, but I think futures have disassociated from cash. If you look at the weather, there's no demand anywhere,&quot; said one East Coast trader.</p>
<p>Revised 6-10 day forecasts released Friday were still calling for normal to slightly below-normal weather for most of the nation, with above-normal temperatures expected only in the Northwest and parts of the Southeast.</p>
<p>Technical traders said the market was still range-bound though another run at resistance was expected early next week. They still pegged June support and resistance at $2.15 and $2.30, respectively. Major buying was likely at the $2.05 double bottom and good selling expected at the $2.43 contract high.</p>
<p>In the cash, Gulf Coast weekend prices eased slightly to the $2.14-2.19 area. Midcon pipes were off a few cents to the high-$1.90s. New York city gate weekend gas also was down slightly to the low-$2.40s.</p>
<p>Planned work on Mobil's Mary Ann gas processing plant in Coden, Ala., has cut the plant's total processing capacity of 380-390 mmcfd. About 120 mmcfd should be back by early next week, with the balance due back in about two weeks.</p>
<p>The NYMEX Henry Hub 12-month strip jumped 5.5 cents to $2.319. NYMEX Henry Hub volume was unavailable late Friday.</p>
<p>On the KCBT, June finished 6.5 cents higher at $2.11, while deferreds ended up by four to 5.5 cents. The East/West spread widened by 2.4 cents to 17.5 cents (NYMEX premium). KCBT said 825 lots traded, up from Thursday's total of 367.</p>
<p>((J Silha, New York Power Desk 212-859-1624))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
