<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608143" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: CBRS confirms Ontario ratings with stable outlook.</title>
<headline>CBRS confirms Ontario ratings with stable outlook.</headline>
<dateline>MONTREAL 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian Bond Rating Service on Friday said if confirmed Ontario's long- and short-term debt ratings at AA and A-1+ respectively with a continued stable outlook for both.  </p>
<p>In confirming the ratings, the Montreal-based bond rating agency noted the province managed to managed to better its deficit target for a second year because of higher-than-projected revenues.</p>
<p>CBRS also noted that the province's 1997 budget included a C$650 million contingency fund, assumptions of economic growth below those of the private sector and interest rate assumptions higher than those of the private sector.</p>
<p>The agency said Ontario's economy, the largest of any province in Canada, is performing quite well with auto and housing sectors doing very well.  </p>
<p>Ontario's fiscal situation continues to improve at a steady pace, but at C$6.6 billion and C$108 billion the province's deficit and overall debt remain high, CBRS said. As a result, the agency said it will continue to monitor Ontario's ratings as it progresses towards a balanced budget.</p>
<p>CBRS said it will take at least another three fiscal years to achieve a balanced budget in Ontario and the province's high level of debt will remain a challenge. The agency is also concerned about the C$30 billion in government-guaranteed debt of Ontario Hydro, which is owned by the province.</p>
<p>((Jeffrey Hodgson (416) 941-8105, e-mail: jeffrey.hodgson@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MONTREAL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
