<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608177" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Elk Hills oil output at 67 pct after fire -U.S DOE.</title>
<headline>Elk Hills oil output at 67 pct after fire -U.S DOE.</headline>
<dateline>BAKERSFIELD, Calif. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) Friday said crude oil production from the huge Elk Hills Naval Petroleum Reserve had been restored to 67 percent capacity following a fire on Monday.</p>
<p>The field normally produces 60,000 barrels per day (bpd) of crude oil, with 46,000 bpd sold by DOE to California refiners. The remaining output is shipped to Chevron Corp, which owns 22 percent of the field.</p>
<p>Production halted Monday when a wildfire from nearby property burned power lines that supply electricity to pumps and other production equipment.</p>
<p>Of the 40,000 bpd produced Friday, shipments to outside customers totaled 24,000 barrels, Chevron received 5,500 barrels, and the remaining 10,500 barrels going to tanks for later shipment.</p>
<p>The Elk Hills Reserve, one of the 11 largest oil and gas fields in the lower 48 states U.S states, is being sold by DOE later this year. The field holds estimated crude oil reserves of about one billion barrels.</p>
<p>((David Brinkerhoff, Los Angeles bureau, +1 213 380 2014))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAKERSFIELD, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
