<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608150" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: &quot;Guru&quot; amuses, confuses with satirical biz babble.</title>
<headline>&quot;Guru&quot; amuses, confuses with satirical biz babble.</headline>
<byline>Christopher Wilson</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>At first glance one might be forgiven for taking &quot;The Book That's Sweeping America&quot; as yet another bland North American management tome bristling with business babble and evangelical slogans.</p>
<p>Such books are a dime a dozen and if they fail to reach the bestseller lists, they may at least achieve cult status or a place on the mahogany bookshelf (usually unread).</p>
<p>This book, cunningly written under the nom de plume Stephen Michael Peter Thomas, is published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc., the bluest of blue-chip business publishers and purveyors of such self-congratulatory bestsellers as &quot;Warren Buffett's Way&quot;, &quot;Soros on Soros&quot; and &quot;Bloomberg by Bloomberg&quot;.</p>
<p>The cover picture of the smartly tailored &quot;author&quot; languidly perched upside down in a leather clubeasy chair is just the sort of thing one might expect from a Lee Iacocca, or a Michael Ovitz -- or Bloomberg or Soros for that matter.</p>
<p>The book's core theoretical &quot;learnings&quot; -- leadership is hard; communication is important; change is different; people are human, the future is tomorrow -- are only marginally more outrageous than some of the blindingly obvious claptrap that passes for serious wisdom uttered by management consultants and many of today's CEOs.</p>
<p>There are many bad writers churning out serious management books.</p>
<p>Fortunately &quot;The Book That's Sweeping America&quot; is not at all serious. It is true that the author, Boston-based consultant John Butman -- forget the Stephen Michael Peter Thomas psuedonynm for the moment -- is a very funny writer running riot with his subject.</p>
<p>Suggested management training courses include joining a bomb disposal squad, changing a car tire at 80 miles an hour, taking charge of a &quot;big ship&quot; (preferably an oil tanker) as it hurtles toward a reef; and the intriguingly titled &quot;Roll the Product Marshmallow across the Hot Coals of Development&quot;.</p>
<p>This exercise exhorts executives to push a marshmallow across a bed of white-hot coals using their noses. To make it more challenging, the author suggests, &quot;team members should be stripped naked, blindfolded, and lashed together with a high-speed, fire-resistant T-3 data cable.&quot;</p>
<p>Such merciless spoofs of management games as well as reckless swipes at business jargon, organizational structure and some sage advice on creating a &quot;humorless workplace&quot; and &quot;gender-neutral clothing guidelines&quot; had this reviewer chortling out loud on a flight from Winnipeg to Calgary, during which I read the book in a single sitting.</p>
<p>Having created corporate images for such gigantic concerns as Gillette, and written speeches for captains of industry such as the late great An Wang and Reebok's CEO Paul Fireman, author Butman is familiar with the top echelons of business.</p>
<p>His vignette of meeting &quot;faith-based finance&quot; guru Dr. Vree Patchouk (apparently loosely modelled on Deepak Chopra) at his English country pile, is hysterical.</p>
<p>Take the following gem:</p>
<p>&quot;With little effort, I could hear the sound of a butler polishing priceless Asprey silver in the dining room adjacent. I could hear the voices of workmen as they pulled a high-speed ISDN line through the 18th century walls to improve Internet response time...the first thought that came to mind was 'I wonder how much money this guy makes a year.?'&quot;</p>
<p>Like all good satire, &quot;The Book That's Sweeping America&quot; taps into some powerful realities. It will appeal to the disaffected of the business world in much the same way the cartoon strip &quot;Dilbert&quot; strikes a cord in any corporate cubicle denizen who has been senselessly trampled by management.</p>
<p>Yet Wiley is clearly cautious about biting the hand that feeds. In searching for the desirable crossover market -- between the business book reader and mass market book buyer -- it has marketed the book by creating a whole persona around the fictional author Stephen Michael Peter Thomas.</p>
<p>While this is amusing, particularly at bookstore signings, it is also confusing.</p>
<p>Some reviewers immediately get it, others have not responded well. &quot;A strangely unfunny April Fools Day spoof,&quot; huffed one reviewer in London's Financial Times.</p>
<p>Wiley might have done better not to take the joke too far.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
