<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608173" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Transportation sees Q1 oper loss.</title>
<headline>U.S. Transportation sees Q1 oper loss.</headline>
<dateline>ELMSFORD, N.Y. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Transportation Systems Inc said it expects to report an operating loss of almost $275,000 in the first quarter.</p>
<p>It said the operating loss will be more than offset by a gain of about $1.2 million from the sale of two discontinued segments of its business in the first quarter.</p>
<p>The company said it expects to return to &quot;overall profitability&quot; in the second quarter ended June.  </p>
<p>The company said 1997 results should be helped by the expansion of its Armstrong Freight Services unit and the acquisition of BancPro Transportation.  </p>
<p>&quot;Regarding the outlook for the first half of 1997, the gain of approximately $1,200,000 from the sale of the entertainment subsidiaries and ASI (Automated Solutions Inc)  will be reported in the first quarter of 1997 and will more than offset an expected first quarter operating loss of almost $275,000 as a result of costs expended in consolidating the trucking and package delivery divisions,&quot; U.S. Transportation chief executive officer Michael Margolies said in a company statement.  </p>
<p>&quot;These same divisions will fuel a return to overall profitability in the April - June quarter of 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;We are confident that our bottom-line performance will steadily improve during 1997,&quot; Margolies said.</p>
<p>U.S. Transportation representatives were not available for further comment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ELMSFORD, N.Y."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
