<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608151" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Continental, pilot negotiations heating up.</title>
<headline>Continental, pilot negotiations heating up.</headline>
<byline>James Pierpoint</byline>
<dateline>HOUSTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Continental Airlines Inc. has met initial demands from its pilots' union for a 38 percent wage increase as talks on a new contract heated up, a spokesman for the Houston-based carrier said on Friday.</p>
<p>But the pilots in closed-door negotiations have sought up to 100 percent increases that would cost the carrier an estimated $1.4 billion over the next three years, airline spokesman Ned Walker said.</p>
<p>&quot;We offered a 38 percent increase over three years, which is exactly what they've asked for publicly,&quot; Walker said. &quot;What they've asked for publicly and what they've proposed to us are inconsistent.&quot;</p>
<p>Under the airlines' proposal, the union said, pay for a 10-year Continental pilot flying narrow-body aircraft would rise from to $130 an hour in July 2002 $112 an hour in July 1997. That's well short of the current $163 an hour for counterparts at American Airlines, who negotiated a 9 percent wage increase and stock options in a contract ratified on May 5, the union said.</p>
<p>&quot;The company is not even offering anything with regards to closing the gap between Continental pilots' pay and the industry standard,&quot; said Mike Hynes, a union officer and 17-year Continental narrow-body pilot.</p>
<p>Continental chairman Gordon Bethune said at the company's annual meeting on May 16 that negotiations were going well and he expected to have an agreement by July 1, when the current contract expires.</p>
<p>But that same day both sides asked for a federal mediator to enter the talks and the union painted a less rosy picture of how negotiations were going.</p>
<p>&quot;We're so far apart, the only way we are going to get a deal is in mediation,&quot; said Len Nikolai, a 32-year Continental veteran and president of the Independent Association of Continental Pilots.</p>
<p>The first meeting with mediator Harry Bickford was set for next Wednesday in Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>At a union board meeting this week, the pilots named a coordinator to begin working full-time on strike preparations in the event talks break down in the months ahead, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It takes six months to a year to get ready&quot; for a strike, Nikolai said. &quot;Sooner or later, this pilot group will run out of patience&quot; if no agreement is reached.</p>
<p>Negotiators have reached agreement on most non-economic sections of the contract covering the 4,000 Continental pilots, but the two sides remain far apart on terms for 1,000 Continental Express pilots, he said.</p>
<p>Nikolai said he was puzzled by the slow pace of talks, which opened in April with both sides pledging to ink a new pact well before June 30.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't know if there is a Delta deal out there or if the company is trying to compress (the negotiations) to get a good deal,&quot; he said, referring to persistent rumors of a possible merger of Continental and Delta Air Lines Inc.</p>
<p>Bethune said at the annual meeting that Continental, which held talks with Delta last year, was not now seeking a partner.</p>
<p>If Continental, the nation's fifth largest airline, does merge with another airline, Nikolai said, its pilots likely would continue to work under the pact now being negotiated.</p>
<p>&quot;If we sign an inferior contract and then merge with somebody, we've just hosed ourselves,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HOUSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
