<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608176" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dominion Bridge holders challenge managers.</title>
<headline>Dominion Bridge holders challenge managers.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A group of shareholders displeased with the management of Dominion Bridge Corp The Committee to Revitalize Dominion Bridge Corporation,  said Friday it plans to initiate a written consent solicitation with the Securities and Exchange Commission to oust the company's senior management.</p>
<p>The Committee said it has also filed a lawsuit in Federal district court in Wilmington, seeking to, among other actions, void the election of directors at the company's 1997 annual meeting, because of certain false and misleading disclosures made prior to the 1997 annual meeting.  </p>
<p>The Committee said that Dominion Bridge is poorly managed and its senior executives have lost virtually all credibility, and stockholders have borne the brunt of this mismanagement, as evidenced by Dominion Bridge's share price, which has plummeted in the past two years.</p>
<p>The Committee said that Dominion Bridge needs a new team of senior executives to return it to profitability and, ultimately, to improve the value of stockholders' investment.</p>
<p>Representatives from the company were unavailable for comment late Friday afternoon.</p>
<p>Dominion Bridge is a Toronto-based engineering firm. For the the six months ended May 15, the company reported a loss of $1.5 million on revenues of $257.5 million, versus a profit of $4.2 million on revenues of $105 million in the year-earlier period.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
