<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608245" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Late NYMEX Hub natgas holds gains after soft open.</title>
<headline>Late NYMEX Hub natgas holds gains after soft open.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX Henry Hub natgas futures held gains late Friday in fairly active trade, helped by technical buying and short covering after downside momentum stalled shortly after the open, market sources said.</p>
<p>At 1400 EDT, June climbed 5.4 cents at $2.25 per million British thermal units after dipping early to $2.185. July was 4.1 cents higher at $2.265. Most others also were up.</p>
<p>&quot;Cash was lower today, but it bounced back before the close (of nominations). They've tried to take it down a few times this week but it holds every time,&quot; said one Texas-based trader, adding the bias may be up next week.  </p>
<p>The move higher surprised some, who expected mild weather forecasts next week and a long holiday weekend to lead to long liquidation, particularly with June slated to go off the board Wednesday.</p>
<p>NYMEX will be closed Monday for the U.S. Memorial Day holiday.</p>
<p>Forecasts next week are calling for normal to slightly below-normal weather for the upper two-thirds of the nation, with some above-normal temperatures expected in Texas and parts of the Southeast.</p>
<p>Technical traders said recent ranges were intact, with June support and resistance still seen at $2.15 and $2.30, respectively. Major buying was expected at the $2.05 double bottom and good selling was likely at the $2.43 contract high.</p>
<p>In the cash, Gulf Coast weekend prices eased slightly to the $2.14-2.19 area. Midcon pipes were off a few cents to the high-$1.90s. New York city gate weekend gas also was down slightly to the low-$2.40s.</p>
<p>Planned work on Mobil's Mary Ann gas processing plant in Coden, Ala., has cut the plant's total processing capacity of 380-390 mmcfd. About 120 mmcfd should be back by early next week, with the balance due back in about two weeks.</p>
<p>NYMEX said 23,741 contracts traded at 1330 EDT. Hub open interest on May 22 rose 1,835 contracts to 210,652.</p>
<p>On the KCBT, June gained 3.5 cents to $2.08, while most deferreds were steady to four cents higher. The East/West spread widened by 1.9 cents to 17.0 cents (NYMEX premium). KCBT open interest on May 22 rose 89 lots to 2,898.</p>
<p>((J Silha, New York Power Desk 212-859-1624))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
