<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608280" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: TALKING POINT-Exec shakeup seen boosting CBS.</title>
<headline>TALKING POINT-Exec shakeup seen boosting CBS.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Benkoe</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>While the broadcasting industry Friday was rocked by the executive-suite shakeup at Westinghouse Electric Corp's CBS unit, Wall Street predicted the moves would be a boost to the slumping television network.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a significant positive for the stock specifically, and for the the company,&quot; said Niraj Gupta, an analyst at Schroder Wertheim.  Shares rose 2-1/8 to 19-1/8.</p>
<p>&quot;The bottom line is that the performance was unacceptable at the television stations,&quot; said Gupta.  &quot;The assets have been underperforming for years.&quot;  </p>
<p>He noted that first quarter stations revenue fell four percent at the unit.</p>
<p>Westinghouse said Friday that Peter Lund, president of its CBS television and cable group, resigned, and Mel Karmazin, head of its radio division, will be chairman and chief executive of a new CBS station group.</p>
<p>The moves come as Westinghouse prepares to split off its industrial businesses from the media company this fall.</p>
<p>Giving Karmazin control of the 14 CBS-owned and operated television stations would be an immediate shot in the arm, analysts said.  </p>
<p>&quot;He's worshipped by the financial community,&quot; said John Reidy at Smith Barney. &quot;He did a fabulous job at Infinity.&quot;</p>
<p>As the chairman of Infinity Broadcasting, he built the company up as the leading radio station operator in the U.S. before selling it to Westinghouse for about $4.9 billion. With the sale, Karmazin became a major Westinghouse shareholder.</p>
<p>Reidy warned, though that, &quot;This is a new and different kind of challenge&quot; for Karmazin.</p>
<p>The company said all of its television and radio stations will be consolidated into a single organization as part of a corporate reorganization.  </p>
<p>Lund quit when Westinghouse chairman Michael Jordan took control of the TV station away from Lund, reports said.</p>
<p>The changes come in advance of the network affiliates meeting next week in Los Angeles.</p>
<p>Executives in the advertising community defended Lund's performance.  &quot;He's a great broadcast executive,&quot; said Robert Igiel, executive vice president at Young &amp; Rubicam.  &quot;His greatest strength was as a team builder.  He put a great team in place, and let them do their thing.  It's a tragedy and a great loss to CBS.&quot;  </p>
<p>Igiel agreed that the CBS stations business &quot;has been a disaster for a long time,&quot; but said it was a poor move to take the division away from Lund.  &quot;Blaming it on Peter is not right,&quot; Igiel said.  &quot;He was just putting together a new team,&quot; including Leslie Moonves as president of CBS Entertainment and Sean McManus at CBS Sports.</p>
<p>The announcement of the shakeup came a day after CBS presented its fall TV lineup to advertisers at Carnegie Hall on Thursday.  The slate of shows was generally well received. Rumors of the reshuffling spread like a wildfire at a party at Tavern on the Green restaurant after the presentation.  </p>
<p>&quot;It was like a game of telephone,&quot; said Betsy Frank, executive vice president at Zenith Media.</p>
<p>Bob Flood, senior vice president at DeWitt Media Inc, said advertisers who were in the audience at Carnegie Hall sensed something amiss.  In the past, Lund and Joe Abruzzese, president of CBS Television Network Sales, ran the presentation together.  On Thursday, Lund was conspicuously absent from the stage.</p>
<p>Some advertisers chided CBS, and Jordan in particular, for poor timing.  </p>
<p>&quot;It could have been handled in a much more prudent manner,&quot; said Flood.  &quot;It could have been announced two weeks from now.&quot;</p>
<p>Regardless, advertising executives said they were impressed by the CBS presentation.</p>
<p>&quot;It was easily the strongest of the six network presentations,&quot; said Frank.  &quot;CBS was clearly different from the other networks after seeing so many programs that targeted the same demographic of a young, more urban audience.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;As opposed to (Walt Disney Co's ABC, they definitely went in with a strategy,&quot; said Flood.  </p>
<p>&quot;They wanted to establish some franchise nights, identifiable programming nights like comedy on Wednesdays and Fridays for teens.&quot;</p>
<p>Advertisers said that the strongest shows appeared to be the new Steven Bochco police drama, &quot;Brooklyn South,&quot; which will air in place of &quot;Chicago Hope&quot; on Monday nights at 2200 ET, and &quot;The Gregory Hines Show,&quot; running Fridays at 2100 ET.</p>
<p>Advertisers said the normally jaded audience at Carnegie Hall was moved by the clip from the Hines comedy about a widower and his 12-year-old son, and the chemistry between the actors.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
