<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608286" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Most IMM currency futures close slightly higher.</title>
<headline>Most IMM currency futures close slightly higher.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most IMM currency futures closed slightly higher, pulling away from the daily peaks on the heels of the passage of the U.S. balanced budget agreement by the Senate, traders said.</p>
<p>They said the outcome of the Senate's vote was largely expected but may have contributed to profit-taking in June yen and June marks.</p>
<p>&quot;You have a lot of commercial longs,&quot; one futures trader said. &quot;So any time prices pull back a little, you see profit-taking.&quot;  </p>
<p>He also said firms and dealers were adjusting positions ahead of the three-day U.S. holiday weekend. Currency futures closed Friday's session at 1200 CDT/1700 GMT, and cash trading wound down about 1100 CDT/1600 GMT.</p>
<p>All U.S. trade will be closed on Monday. U.K. markets will also be shut on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm still bullish yen, but people are just willing to sell here in the near term,&quot; another trader said, adding that one major U.S. dealer bought 1,000 June yen at $0.008680.</p>
<p>Once again, traders said the direction of the cash cross rates would have a significant effect on key currency futures.  </p>
<p>Some cited the continued buying of yen against marks as a supportive factor towards June yen.</p>
<p>&quot;The cash mark/yen was oversold, but there is no sign that the trend is reversing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Cash marks also fell under light pressure against Swiss francs, as the cash rate edged towards the 82.50 centime level. June Swiss francs slightly extended gains above Thursday's high of $0.7150 after trading inside Thursday's ranges for most of the morning.</p>
<p>June marks eased to a low of $0.5911, slightly below the pivot point of $0.5912.  </p>
<p>Canadian and Australian dollar futures continued to grind lower. One U.S. dealer sold 1,000 June Australian dollars at $0.7680, a floor source said.</p>
<p>At the end of pit trade, June yen was up $0.000010 at $0.008664, marks were up $0.0001 at $0.5915, Swiss francs were up $0.0047 at $0.7146, sterling rose $0.0122 to $1.6348, Canadian dollars were off $0.0016 at $0.7285, Australian dollars were off $0.0120 at $0.7653 and Mexican pesos were off $0.000150 at $0.125850. ((Derivatives desk 312-408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
