<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608278" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Disk drive shrs continue drop on Seagate EPS cuts.</title>
<headline>Disk drive shrs continue drop on Seagate EPS cuts.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stocks of disk drive companies continued their decline Friday after two brokerages cut their estimates on Seagate Technology Inc and on investor fears that disk drive prices will decline further, traders said.</p>
<p>Also fueling the decline was news late Thursday from Innovex Inc, a maker of electrical components, that Read-Rite Corp had cancelled some orders.</p>
<p>Salomon Brothers today cut its fiscal fourth quarter earnings estimate on Seagate to $1.02 a share from $1.12 due to lower average selling prices and revenue assumptions.</p>
<p>Seagate shares were off 2-1/8 to 40.  </p>
<p>Among other disk drive makers, Western Digital lost 3-1/8 to 53-7/8, Quantum Corp fell one to 37-3/8, and Read-Rite eased 1-7/8 to 20-1/8.</p>
<p>Disk drive stocks were the most active on both the NYSE and the NASDAQ and helped push down PC maker shares.</p>
<p>Robertson Stephens &amp; Co analyst Patrick Tenney also cut his fourth quarter estimate on Seagate, to $1.00 a share from $1.12, and his fiscal 1998 estimate, to $4.50 from $4.68.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe Seagate is seeing some price competition, particularly on high-performance disk drives in the retail distribution channel,&quot; Tenney wrote in a note to clients.  </p>
<p>Competition is increasing in the high-end drive business.</p>
<p>Tenney said he believes Seagate will continue to dominate in the higher-end but that new products from Quantum, Western Digital, International Business Machines Corp and Fujitsu Ltd are beginning to show more emphasis on high-end products, which will erode some of Seagate's market share.</p>
<p>Salomon Brothers analysts John Dean and Michele Rothacher said they expect disk drive stocks to continue to be volatile in the near term.  </p>
<p>&quot;We believe that investors should view any big pull-backs in the disk drive stocks as buying opportunities,&quot; they wrote.</p>
<p>Salomon said Quantum, Seagate and Western Digital will likely trade around a multiple of 10 times earnings.</p>
<p>Even though Salomon expects &quot;some enhanced competition in the drive arena in 1997,&quot; and a return to &quot;somewhat more aggressive pricing,&quot; its long-term view on disk drive stocks remains optimistic.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302019">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34440">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34531">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
