<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608289" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Fed's Meyer downplays finance fears of small firms.</title>
<headline>Fed's Meyer downplays finance fears of small firms.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Federal Reserve Governor Laurence Meyer on Friday played down fears that consolidation of the banking industry and financial modernization might crimp the flow of credit to small businesses.</p>
<p>&quot;The market for small business loans ... seems to work rather well,&quot; he said in a speech prepared for delivery to a conference in New York on small business finance.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is a merger or other event that reduces the supply of profitable loans to small businesses, other banks seem to step in and provide this credit, and there is every reason to expect that such responses will continue,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The U.S. banking industry has been consolidating at a rapid rate over the last 15 years, and Meyer said that trend is likely to continue or accelerate in response to the removal of restrictions on interstate banking and branching.</p>
<p>That has led to fears that small businesses that depend heavily on local banks for finance and other services could lose out. Meyer though said that the situation was complex.</p>
<p>&quot;Mergers appear to reduce small business lending by the participants, but this decline appears to be offset in part or in whole by an increase in lending by other banks,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Meyer also pointed to forecasts that thousands of small banks will survive and said those predictions made sense.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, given the heavy dependence of small bsuinesses on banks, Meyer said that banking regulators needed to be &quot;sensitive&quot; to antitrust issues when considering mergers and acquisitions of banks in the same local market.</p>
<p>He saw banks continuing to play a big role in providing finance to small businesses in the future, although their share of that market might fall in response to technological advances in such areas as information processing.</p>
<p>The types of developments that might ... reduce bank market share in small business lending are proceeding rather slowly at present, but may accelerate in the future,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But he added, &quot;No matter how many advances there are ... there will likely remain a significant role for bank-borrower relationship lending to ... small businesses.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
