<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608291" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US OPTIONS FOCUS/Pre-holiday mood cuts index trade.</title>
<headline>US OPTIONS FOCUS/Pre-holiday mood cuts index trade.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Trading in major U.S. stock index options, hampered earlier this week by Tuesday's Federal Reserve meeting, was slowed again on Friday by skeleton staffs and a pre-holiday mood, traders said.</p>
<p>U.S. financial markets will be closed Monday for Memorial Day.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not a thing going on,&quot; one dealer in S&amp;P 100 index .OEX and S&amp;P 500 .SPX options said.</p>
<p>The solid rally in stocks failed to ignite much action in the options, he noted.  </p>
<p>By 1130 CDT/1630 GMT, the OEX was up 5.19 at 825.85 and the SPX was up 5.16 at 840.82. June S&amp;P 500 futures were up 3.05 at 843.30.</p>
<p>The bellwether Dow industrial average .DJI was up 40 at nearly 7,299.</p>
<p>In the OEX, the busiest options were the June 800 put, which traded about 2,100 contracts, and the June 880 call, which traded around 1,350.</p>
<p>The most active SPX option was the June 750 put, with volume of 4,500 contracts. The option, which had open interest of 24,728 contracts, was down 3/8 at 9/16.  </p>
<p>Overall, by 1130 CDT/1630 GMT, SPX put volume was 11,072 compared to 4,517 in calls. In the OEX, put volume outpaced call volume by 10,015 to 7,985.</p>
<p>The head of one options trading desk in Chicago said he expected volume to drop off even more after U.S. Treasury bonds close at 1300 CDT/1800 GMT. T-bond futures close at 1210 CDT/1710 GMT.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not a whole lot of volume, and I have a hunch that after bonds close there will be nothing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Volatilities eased slightly as the market moved higher and ahead of the long holiday weekend, traders said.  </p>
<p>The Chicago Board Options Exchange's volatility index .VIX was down 0.37, or 1.75 percent, at 20.63. The VIX is priced off certain OEX options.</p>
<p>The VIX was at its lowest level since early May and had risen through the 24 level on Monday and Tuesday ahead of the Federal Reserve's Open Market Committee meeting.</p>
<p>Once the FOMC left interest rates unchanged Tuesday, volatilities crumbled as the market bounced higher.</p>
<p>((Gregory Crawford, 312 408 8750))</p>
<p>E-mail: derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
