<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608258" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Global Intellicom expects profit this year.</title>
<headline>Global Intellicom expects profit this year.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Global Intellicom Inc said Friday it expects to turn a profit this year after losing more than $1 million in 1996.</p>
<p>The company said it lost more than $1.6 million in the first quarter of 1997, but deals struck recently with International Business Machines Corp and Sun Microsystems Inc will contribute toward positive year-end earnings.</p>
<p>Global, a computer software and hardware producer, said it expects that revenues for 1997 could exceed $100 million, with most of it coming in the third and fourth quarters. First quarter revenues were $11.1 million, it said.</p>
<p>Global said its Speech Solutions Inc unit has a deal to be IBM's sole provider of voice tools for use with IBM's voice-type speech engine.</p>
<p>Global said its Nevcor Inc unit has a deal to become an authorized Sun workstations distributor. The deal also names Global as a builder of Sun workstations. The machines will be sold with Sun support, but under a private label, it said.</p>
<p>Another subsidiary, Natcom Inc, has been named as a reseller of Sun's Solaris and Java workstations systems.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
