<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608227" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX oil sector ends down, unleaded's role eyed.</title>
<headline>NYMEX oil sector ends down, unleaded's role eyed.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX crude oil futures prices tumbled at the end of the day to settle broadly lower, pulling products down in kind, as a last batch of long position were liquidated to close the session ahead of the holiday weekend.</p>
<p>NYMEX will closed Monday in observance of Memorial Day.</p>
<p>July crude oil lost 23 cents to settle at $21.62 a barrel, trading in a range between $21.97 and $21.53.</p>
<p>Unleaded gasoline for July delivery ended at 64.90 cents a gallon, off 0.20 cent. July heating oil shed 0.37 cent, closing at 57.48 cents.</p>
<p>The oil complex will be looking ahead to next week's inventory data to determine whether demand in unleaded gasoline will lend enough support to lead the complex in the short term, one analyst said.</p>
<p>With peak demand season for unleaded gasoline at hand at this weekend's unofficial beginning of summer, crude oil will be taking a back seat to unleaded.</p>
<p>&quot;The key thing to look at is to see if demand (in unleaded gasoline) is going to meet all these expectations we've put on the market,&quot; said Refco analyst Victor Yu.</p>
<p>&quot;People are going to be scrutinizing the APIs (American Petroleum Institute inventory report). If they feel gas isn't doing as well as it should, we could have a good selloff&quot; in the complex, Yu said.</p>
<p>Unleaded gasoline futures have shown some promise, posting successively higher session highs, Yu said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the market has more upside potential than downside. Gasoline continues to perform well; it looks like it's going to be the market leader,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The complex opened weaker Friday after attempts on Thursday to extend price gains were unsuccessful, which tagged the complex with sentiment for declines headed into the three-day weekend.</p>
<p>However, news at the opening bell of a leak in the crude pipeline link between the Louisiana Offshore Oil Port (LOOP) and the onshore Capline pipeline system - causing a temporary shutdown of the pipeline - limited the downside and kept the complex firmer for most of the morning.</p>
<p>Traders quickly shrugged off the news once confident the disruption was minor, and many liquidate positions before midday to take an early exit.</p>
<p>Prices then drifted aimlessly into the close, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was that one little rally we had in the morning - partly from (buy) stops, partly from the LOOP story. Once that fell off, the market pretty much died under its own weight,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>((--C. Thompson  New York Energy Desk 212.859.1761))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
