<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608228" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chase Telecom readies $125 mln junk bond offering.</title>
<headline>Chase Telecom readies $125 mln junk bond offering.</headline>
<byline>Douglas Brown</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chase Telecommunications Inc, a startup wireless personal communications services (PCS) company, plans to launch a $125 million high-yield bond offering in the next few weeks, according to a source familiar with the deal.</p>
<p>Chase stands to become the first company holding primarily &quot;C Block&quot; auction licenses, to successfully tap the high-yield bond market, analysts said.  </p>
<p>NextWave Telecom Inc and Pocket Communications Inc, two other C block license winners, have withdrawn high-yield offerings in recent months due to poor investor demand and market conditions, they said.</p>
<p>The Federal Communications Commission's PCS auction last year, also known as the C Block auction, gave preference to entrepreneurial companies in the hopes of broadening competition in the PCS market.  </p>
<p>But becuase of the shaky financial standing of many of the winners, Wall Street has been hesitant to provide them with significant financing, forcing them to form alliances with more established companies.</p>
<p>Chase won licenses to provide PCS services primarily in the state of Tennessee, an area covering approximately 6.3 million population equivalents (POPs) in the C Block auction.</p>
<p>The company was founded by a group of entrepreneurs, including Anthony Chase, its current president and chief executive officer.  </p>
<p>Chase has also received financing from large PCS players such as PrimeCo Personal Communications and Qualcomm Inc</p>
<p>Chase currently hopes to sell $125 million (face value) of zero coupon bonds in a 144a private placement via Credit Suisse First Boston. To sweeten the deal, market sources said the company is also likely to give high-yield investors an undisclosed amount of warrants to purchase common stock.</p>
<p>Proceeds from the transaction will be used to construct the company's PCS network, which is projected to begin operations in the second quarter of 1998, the source said.  </p>
<p>Chase has an agreement to provide PCS services using the brand name of PrimeCo, a joint venture between AirTouch Communications Inc and several regional bell telephone companies.</p>
<p>Following the high-yield offering, PrimeCo stands to acquire a 13 percent stake in Chase in exchange for providing various services as well as through converting a $2 million outstanding loan.</p>
<p>Qualcomm, a developer of PCS technology and equipment, has also agreed to provide Chase with $25 million in notes in exchange for warrants to purchase 10 percent of the company's stock, following the offering. The transaction will bring Qualcomm's potential stake in Chase to roughly 13 percent, following the offering, the source said.</p>
<p>Qualcomm will also provide $119 million of vendor financing to Chase following the transaction, the source said.</p>
<p>-U.S. Corporate Bond Unit, 212-859-1662</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
