<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608240" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US OPTIONS FOCUS-Office Depot highlights slow day.</title>
<headline>US OPTIONS FOCUS-Office Depot highlights slow day.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Equity options trading was broadly scattered with generally light volumes ahead of the holiday weekend, traders said Friday.</p>
<p>The market will be closed Monday for Memorial Day.</p>
<p>&quot;There's just very little going on,&quot; said Hank Nothnagel, head of the options trading desk at Everen Securities.</p>
<p>Office Depot Inc options continued to be a highlight as the five-day hearing in Washington on the company's proposed merger with Staples Inc drew to a close.  </p>
<p>The Federal Trade Commission has gone to court to try to end the merger, which it contends would lead to higher prices.</p>
<p>Office Depot options have been fairly active all week as the hearing before U.S. District Court Judge Thomas Hogan progressed, with investors focusing mainly on the July series.</p>
<p>Hogan has said he will rule by mid-June on whether to grant the government a preliminary injunction to halt the merger.</p>
<p>The increased Office Depot option activity has driven implied volatility levels sharply higher, over 100 in some cases.  </p>
<p>On Friday, volatilities in the July options ranged from the mid-70's to just over 100.</p>
<p>The heaviest action was in the July 20 and 17-1/2 calls, which traded about 8,500 and 6,300 contracts, respectively.</p>
<p>The July 20 call, which was up 1/16 at 1-1/2, had open interest of 40,238 contracts, including an addition of 4,109 on Thursday.</p>
<p>The July 17-1/2 call, which gained 3/16 to 2-9/16, had open interest of 33,158.  Nearly 3,900 contracts were added Thursday.  </p>
<p>On the put side, the most active Office Depot option was the June 15 with volume of 1,115.</p>
<p>Michael Schwartz, a managing director at Oppenheimer &amp; Co, said some of the July 17-1/2 and 20 call trading was spreads.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like some professionals are putting on some debit spreads for about $1 to make $1.50,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The July 17-1/2 calls were trading at 2-5/8 and the July 20s at 1-1/2 in late action.</p>
<p>The orginal merger agreement, announced last September, valued Office Depot shares at about 22-1/4.  </p>
<p>Schwartz added that the fact that few Office Depot October or January options traded suggested investors expected the merger question to be resolved by the July expiration, which is on July 19.</p>
<p>Office Depot shares were up 1/4 at 17-1/4 Friday afternoon. Staples rose 5/8 to 21-5/8.</p>
<p>((Gregory Crawford, 312 408 8750))</p>
<p>E-mail: derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
