<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608254" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CSCE coffee ends down on light profit-taking.</title>
<headline>CSCE coffee ends down on light profit-taking.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CSCE coffee futures ended mostly lower in thin pre-holiday trade on Friday, as speculators took profits following two straight sessions of hefty gains, dealers said.</p>
<p>Benchmark July arabicas fell 3.45 cents per lb on the day, to 256.85 cents, after ranging from 262.25 to 255.50. Second-position September closed 3.90 cents lower, at 226.05 cents, while the back months finished down 3.65 to up 0.50.</p>
<p>Coffee prices headed lower at the outset, defying the pre-opening call, as speculators cashed in after the market's recent explosive rally.</p>
<p>But persistent buying by locals near the lows limited losses and kept prices in a relatively narrow range, they added.</p>
<p>Despite today's downturn, industry sources said a continued supply crunch was likely to keep the market well underpinned in the coming months.</p>
<p>&quot;It was just a small round of profit-taking today,&quot; said Allendale analyst Jim Cordier. &quot;Profit-taking could get into Tuesday's trade, but the fundamentals are still supportive. I think you'll be looking at August or September until you see any help on tight supplies.&quot;</p>
<p>Technically, Cordier said July would probably find good support at the 250.00-cent level.</p>
<p>On the upside, traders pegged resistance at 262.00 cents, followed by July's life-of-contract high set Thursday of 265.00 cents.</p>
<p>Traders continued to monitor weather forecasts for top-grower Brazil. A cold front moved into Brazil's coffee belt, but no damaging cold is expected, private forecaster Weather Services Corp said Friday. Low temperatures this morning ranged from the upper 40s to low 50s F (9-15 C), they said.</p>
<p>WSC said low temperatures will turn cooler on Sunday into early next week, but not cold enough to cause damage &quot;as there are no additional cold airmasses biulding out of Argentina.&quot;</p>
<p>Volume reached an estimated 6,050 lots.</p>
<p>The CSCE will be closed Monday in observance of the U.S. Memorial Day holiday, reopening on Tuesday. London's LIFFE market is also closed for a holiday on Monday.</p>
<p>((--Patricia Avidan, New York Commodity Desk 212 859 1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
