<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608399" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-RED SOX RAP 19 HITS TO BEAT YANKEES 8-2.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-RED SOX RAP 19 HITS TO BEAT YANKEES 8-2.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Wil Cordero had five hits and Mike Stanley blasted a three-run homer as the Boston Red Sox pounded out 19 hits to beat the New York Yankees 8-2 on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a good win for us,&quot; Red Sox manager Jimy Williams said. &quot;The pitching and defence gave the opportunity for the offence to get on track.&quot;</p>
<p>Cordero had a double and three singles in his first five at-bats. He had a shot at a perfect 6-for-6 day, but Yankees third baseman Wade Boggs made a tough backhanded play on a grounder in the eighth inning to deny Cordero a six-hit game. He singled in the ninth.</p>
<p>Tim Naehring was 4-for-6 for Boston, and Mo Vaughn had three hits, including a 430-foot solo homer into the upper deck in right.</p>
<p>New York's David Wells (4-3) lasted 5-1/3 innings and surrendered five runs and 12 hits.</p>
<p>The Red Sox snapped a three-game losing streak and won for only the second time in 12 games. The Yankees lost their fourth straight game.</p>
<p>&quot;Baseball is a season of streaks and we'll get out of it,&quot; Yankees manager Joe Torre said. &quot;We're being too tentative at the plate and taking too many pitches. We were a little spoiled in the beginning. We were getting the hits when we needed them.&quot;</p>
<p>Paul O'Neill was 3-for-4 for the Yankees.</p>
<p>In Cleveland, Albie Lopez pitched seven strong innings and Manny Ramirez and Pat Borders had two-run singles in an eight-run fifth inning as the Cleveland Indians routed the Kansas City Royals 9-1 on Thursday.</p>
<p>Lopez, who has replaced the injured Jack McDowell in the rotation, has allowed just one run over 12 innings in winning his last two starts.</p>
<p>&quot;The last two starts showed (manager) Mark Hargrove what I can do,&quot; Lopez said. &quot;I am used to being a starter my whole career. All I ever wanted to do was go out there every five days.&quot;</p>
<p>Kansas City has lost six straight games and has scored just one run in the last 20 innings.</p>
<p>The Indians (23-20) pounded Jose Rosado (3-3) for six runs and six hits in 4-1/3 innings and moved to three games over .500 for the first time this season.</p>
<p>&quot;Guys are starting to get confidence in each other, not confidence in themselves, but with each other,&quot; Hargrove said. &quot;We've been getting good pitching and some timely hits.&quot;</p>
<p>At Texas, Juan Gonzalez homered twice and drove in five runs to power the Texas Rangers to a 10-7 victory over the Oakland Athletics.</p>
<p>John Burkett (3-3) pitched five ineffective innings but was credited with the win for Texas, which is 10-4 in its last 14 games.</p>
<p>&quot;It's always nice to score early, but I guess it was one of those days where the entire pitching staff was in a command slump,&quot; Texas manager Johnny Oates said.</p>
<p>Burkett allowed six runs and nine hits with three walks and five strikeouts before giving way to four relievers, including John Wetteland, who pitched a perfect ninth for his 11th save.</p>
<p>&quot;I've been around and seen some things, but this was something different,&quot; Burkett said. &quot;I pitched terrible, but the guys supported me. I feel very fortunate.&quot;</p>
<p>Oakland starter Willie Adams was ripped for four runs and four hits with two walks in one inning.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
