<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608335" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-JUVENTUS MARK CENTENARY WITH 24TH TITLE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-JUVENTUS MARK CENTENARY WITH 24TH TITLE.</headline>
<byline>Chris Endean</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Juventus marked their centenary year with a 24th Italian league championship on Friday, recovering from a goal down to secure the title winning point in a 1-1 draw against Atalanta in Bergamo.</p>
<p>Mark Iuliano's 54th minute equaliser, after Filippo Inzaghi's first-half opener for Atalanta had threatened to spoil the party, put Juventus beyond the reach of second placed Parma.</p>
<p>With 64 points from 33 matches, Juventus are seven points clear of Parma who have just two matches left to play.</p>
<p>&quot;The most remarkable thing about this championship is that it falls in our centenary year,&quot; said club president Vittorio Chiusano, adding &quot;there could not be a better way to celebrate our 100th year.&quot;</p>
<p>The Italian championship is the third title Juventus have won this season after the Intercontinental Cup and the European Supercup.</p>
<p>Next Wednesday, the Turin side will have the chance to add the European Cup when they attempt to retain the title they won last season against Germany's Borussia Dortmund in Munich.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a year that will go down in history,&quot; said coach Marcello Lippi.</p>
<p>The match finished in farcical fashion, when the referee was forced to suspend the match for 15 minutes after Juventus fans prematurely invaded the pitch thinking the game was over.</p>
<p>Police cleared the field and the two sides were brought back out from the changing rooms -- some had already swapped shirts -- to play the remaining three minutes.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone thought the match was over,&quot; admitted Lippi, &quot;to restart a match after the players were back in the changing room and taking off their shirts, I can't remember anything like it.&quot;</p>
<p>With Lippi resting several first team players ahead of the Munich final, including Frenchman Didier Deschamps and Croat Alen Boksic, Juventus hardly started like champions-elect -- and fell behind in the 19th minute.</p>
<p>The league's leading scorer Inzaghi chested down a deep cross from Fausto Rossini and shot across Angelo Peruzzi into the far corner for his 23rd goal of the season.</p>
<p>The goal allowed Inzaghi to equal the 1984 feat of former Juventus great Michel Platini by scoring a goal against 15 different serie A teams in a single season.</p>
<p>Alessandro Del Piero, playing his first full match in three months, had the ball in the net in the 29th minute for an apparent equaliser -- but was ruled off-side.</p>
<p>In the next 10 minutes, Atalanta keeper Davide Pinato pulled off three fine saves to deny France's Zinedine Zidane and Italy's Christian Vieri -- the last, a superb reflex effort.</p>
<p>The pattern looked like continuing after the break when the goalkeeper again denied Vieri, turning his bobbling shot just round the post.</p>
<p>From the resulting corner, Pinato again blocked a point-blank header from Ciro Ferrara, but he could only look on helplessly as unsung defender Iuliano headed home the rebound to put his side back on course for the title.</p>
<p>From that moment, the result was never in doubt -- although Peruzzi was forced to pull off a brilliant reflex save from a header by former Italy international Gianluigi Lentini in the 58th minute.</p>
<p>When the referee blew the final whistle for real, thousands of fans crowded into Turin's city centre to celebrate their home town's success.</p>
<p>Juventus players will be allowed a short period of celebration before a training session planned for Saturday starts the build-up to Wednesday's European Cup final.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
