<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608358" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: RALLYING-MAKINEN HOLDS OVERNIGHT LEAD IN RALLY OF ARGENT.</title>
<headline>RALLYING-MAKINEN HOLDS OVERNIGHT LEAD IN RALLY OF ARGENT.</headline>
<dateline>CORDOBA, Argentina 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tommi Makinen, the reigning world champion, ended the first day of the Rally of Argentina on Thursday at the head of a three-way fight for the lead with Briton Colin McRae and Spaniard Carlos Sainz chasing hard.</p>
<p>Makinen, of Finland, moved to the front of the event on the third stage and built a 12 second lead over his two main title rivals with the quickest time on the fourth, but then saw his advantage slowly chipped away through the remaining four stages of the day.</p>
<p>McRae, who set the fastest times on the sixth, seventh and eighth stages as the teams returned to their base in the city of Cordoba, north of Buenos Aires, was just eight seconds behind at the end of the opening leg.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't want to push too hard this morning,&quot; said the Subaru driver, who will take the lead of the championship if he wins the event. &quot;We'll keep pushing, but at the moment I'm happy with our position. There is still a long way to go.&quot;</p>
<p>Sainz had led the rally after the second stage, but after damaging his Ford while driving through water on the third stage, he slipped down to third place before a spirited recovery saw him set the fastest time on the fifth stage and end the day 13 seconds behind Makinen.</p>
<p>Briton Richard Burns marked his impressive return to the championship with Mitsubishi by ending the day fourth overall, with former champion Juha Kankunnen, of Finland, fifth placed on his debut outing for the Ford team.</p>
<p>The huge local interest in the event caused chaos on the opening stages when spectators poured onto the rally route, forcing organisers to delay the running of the rally by more than an hour as they cleared them to safe viewing points.</p>
<p>The second leg of the rally, which runs to the west of Cordoba on Friday, is the longest of the event with 10 stages totalling 180 kilometres before the teams arrive back in Cordoba for their overnight halt.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CORDOBA, Argentina"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
