<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608332" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: MOTOR RACING-BOESEL EDGES TRACY OUT OF POLE FOR ST LOUIS 300.</title>
<headline>MOTOR RACING-BOESEL EDGES TRACY OUT OF POLE FOR ST LOUIS 300.</headline>
<dateline>MADISON, Illinois 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's Raul Boesel had just enough speed Friday to edge the tour's hottest driver, Canadian Paul Tracy, out of the pole for Saturday's inaugural St Louis 300 CART race.</p>
<p>Boesel, a former world sports car champion, grabbed his third CART pole -- but first since 1994 in Milwaukee -- with a 24.324-second lap. He averaged 187.963 mph (302.489 kph) in a Reynard Ford around the brand new, four-turn, 1.27 mile (2.04 km) oval just east of St Louis.</p>
<p>Earlier in the session, Tracy, the current CART points leader and winner of the last two races, held the provisional pole with a time of 24.353 seconds in a Penske Mercedes-Benz.</p>
<p>&quot;I knew that my first lap was almost the same as Tracy's,&quot; said Boesel. &quot;I knew that I had to go a hair faster, pace myself, especially because sometimes I try to go into turn one too deep and end up losing speed coming out.&quot;</p>
<p>Tracy was disappointed at losing the pole position. &quot;I felt that we had more potential in the car, we felt we could squeeze a little (speed out), but the track was slick (in turns one and two) where CART put some sealer to keep it from breaking up.</p>
<p>&quot;As it wore off later in the session it gave the guys who ran later an extra advantage.&quot;</p>
<p>But all in all Tracy was not too upset. &quot;I've got more points now after five races than I had the entire last season.&quot; He leads the series with 65 points to American Scott Pruett's 61.</p>
<p>Third fastest in the session was another Brazilian, Mauricio Gugelmin. Driving a Reynard Mercedes-Benz in 24.374 seconds, he narrowly missed his first CART pole. &quot;My second lap was a heck of a lap. We came up just a few hundredths (.05) short.&quot;</p>
<p>Rounding out the top five were two Canadians, Greg Moore at 24.496 and rookie Patrick Carpentier at 24.546. Both drove Reynard Mercedes-Benz.</p>
<p>Twenty-seven drivers will start the 236-lap, 299.72 mile (482.3 km) race on Saturday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADISON, Illinois"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
