<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608378" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: SOCCER-TOP FOUR CLASH ON RUSSIA'S DAY OF RECKONING.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-TOP FOUR CLASH ON RUSSIA'S DAY OF RECKONING.</headline>
<byline>Alastair Macdonald</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's championship race could be a lot clearer after this Saturday when the top four teams meet each other a third of the way through the season.</p>
<p>With leagues in the West already winding up, Russian leaders Dynamo Moscow have a chance to prove that this really could be their year after decades of disappointment when they travel to Volgograd to face second-placed Rotor.</p>
<p>Champions Spartak Moscow, struggling for form after a succession of key injuries, must work hard to keep in touch with the leaders. They host Rostselmash Rostov, who are level on points with Spartak in third place, three points behind Dynamo.</p>
<p>Rotor Volgograd, whose scoreless draw at bottom club Fakel last week let Dynamo go top for the first time in two years, need a victory over the Muscovites if they are to convince the sceptics they are real contenders. They are now a point behind.</p>
<p>One of the best-supported sides in Russia and famous victors over Manchester United in 1995, Rotor led for much of last season before succumbing to the pressure. They finished third.</p>
<p>Dynamo, the police and KGB club which dominated Soviet football before and after World War Two, are perennial underachievers who last won the title in 1976.</p>
<p>But they have not conceded a goal for five games and, with a Cup semifinal against Zenit St Petersburg coming up on Tuesday, the next four days will tell whether thoughts of their first double in 60 years are realistic or just another pipe-dream.</p>
<p>Rostov marksman Alexander Maslov, Russia's top scorer last season, will be a threat to Spartak's hopes of a fifth title in six years and to their plans for a confidence-building run-up to next season's Champions' League. Maslov again tops the goalscoring table, along with Dynamo's Oleg Terekhin.</p>
<p>Spartak will be without inspirational captain and playmaker Ilya Tsymbalar for at least another month. Winger Andrei Tikhonov, Russia's 1996 Player of the Year, is also still out.</p>
<p>Among other moments of truth on Saturday, 1995 champions Alania Vladikavkaz will be in deep trouble if they fail to take full points at home to second-bottom Tyumen. Alania, last year's runners-up, are in ninth place after an awful start.</p>
<p>In the Moscow derby, fifth-placed Torpedo face Lokomotiv, who are seventh. The two normally compete for wooden spoon among the capital's Big Five, but both have bigger ideas this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
