<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608385" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: OLYMPICS-SYDNEY HITS BACK AT IOC CHIEF SAMARANCH.</title>
<headline>OLYMPICS-SYDNEY HITS BACK AT IOC CHIEF SAMARANCH.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sydney's top politician on Friday told Juan Antonio Samaranch to mind his own business after complaints by the International Olympic Committee (IOC) chief over a proposed city hotel bed tax to help fund the 2000 Games.</p>
<p>New South Wales premier Bob Carr, whose state government is funding much of the massive construction costs involved in staging the Sydney Games, said the bed tax was a local issue and had nothing to do with the IOC.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Samaranch runs the IOC. By all accounts he does an exemplary job,&quot; Carr told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;But we're building the Olympics. We're building the facilities and we're entitled to say to the hotels in the CBD (central business district): 'You'll make a contribution'.&quot;</p>
<p>Speaking in Monaco on Thursday, Samaranch said the IOC was unhappy over plans to impose a 10 percent bed tax, starting from September 1 this year, for hotels, motels and guests houses in central Sydney.</p>
<p>The tax is projected to raise A$64 million (US$50.07 million) a year, offsetting a projected A$3.2 billion bill for buiding Olympic facilities, about two-thirds of which is being met from the public purse.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not happy with the tax and the hotels are also not happy,&quot; Samaranch said. &quot;We can do nothing -- only tell the organisers that we are not happy.&quot;</p>
<p>Several of Sydney's five-star hotels have joined forces in a campaign urging the government to scrap the proposed tax.</p>
<p>Overall, Sydney's budget and plans for the Games were well received by the IOC and international sporting federations during meetings in Monaco earlier this week.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
