<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608390" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NHL ICE HOCKEY-RED WINGS ROMP PAST AVALANCHE 6-0 FOR 3-1 LEAD.</title>
<headline>NHL ICE HOCKEY-RED WINGS ROMP PAST AVALANCHE 6-0 FOR 3-1 LEAD.</headline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Igor Larionov and Kirk Maltby each scored twice and Mike Vernon recorded a whitewash as the Detroit Red Wings moved within one win of the Stanley Cup finals by romping past the defending champion Colorado Avalanche 6-0 Thursday.</p>
<p>After a mass brawl on the ice late in the third period, an enraged Marc Crawford, the Colorado coach, tried to climb over a glass barrier to get at the laughing Detroit coach, Scotty Bowman.</p>
<p>&quot;Emotions got a little bit out of whack at that particular time, and you say some stupid things,&quot; said Crawford, who was cursing at Bowman as he tried to reach him. &quot;You just get caught up in emotions of the moment.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;He was pretty emotional. I guess I've been that way before,&quot; said Bowman.</p>
<p>&quot;His eyes were coming out of his head. He was really excited.&quot;</p>
<p>The Red Wings posted their third straight win for a 3-1 lead in the best-of-seven series, which returns to Colorado for Game 5 on Saturday. Only 13 of 156 teams since 1939 that have faced 3-1 deficits have come back to win their series.</p>
<p>Detroit continued to get big contributions from its &quot;Russian Unit&quot; as Vyacheslav Kozlov and Sergei Fedorov scored the other goals.</p>
<p>The Russian contingent, which also includes defencemen Vladimir Konstantinov and Viacheslav Fetisov, had accounted for six straight Red Wing goals before Maltby beat Patrick Roy on a breakaway in the final minute of the second period to build a 5-0 lead.</p>
<p>Detroit is 11-0 in the playoffs when a member of the Russian Unit scores a goal.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll beat them Saturday (back in Denver) and come back here,&quot; said Colorado star winger Claude Lemieux. &quot;This isn't over. Why we came out flat I don't know. They got two lucky goals early and it changed the game.&quot;</p>
<p>Vernon turned aside only 19 shots for his fifth career playoff shutout and first since Game 1 of the 1995 Western Conference quarter-finals against San Jose. He also handed the Avalanche their first postseason shutout since a 3-0 loss to Philadelphia in Game 6 of the 1985 Wales Conference finals, when the franchise was still the Quebec Nordiques.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't have many shots to stop and almost no real quality chances,&quot; said Vernon, who won the Stanley Cup with Calgary in 1989. &quot;The guys had the puck up the other end almost all of the first two periods.&quot;</p>
<p>Colorado was pushed to the brink of playoff elimination for the first time since moving from Quebec two years ago. Roy surrendered five goals on 25 shots and was replaced by Craig Billington to start the third period.</p>
<p>The Red Wings dominated the first period, using five power plays to build a 14-2 advantage in shots. It was the second time in the series Detroit has limited the Avalanche to two shots in a period.</p>
<p>Larionov opened the scoring at 1:52 on the first power play and made it 2-0 just five minutes later. The Red Wings killed off the first two Avalanche power plays in the second period and Kozlov made it 3-0 with his third goal in two games.</p>
<p>Again on the power play, Fedorov made it 4-0 at 16:54 of the second period and Maltby's goal off a giveaway with 47 seconds to go in the period opened a 5-0 cushion. Maltby had only two goals in the regular season.</p>
<p>Vernon was at his best in the second period, when the Avalanche collected 13 of their 19 shots.</p>
<p>Maltby lifted a loose puck under the crossbar 5:25 into the third period to close the scoring before the game degenerated into a series of brawls.</p>
<p>These resulted in eight fighting majors, 10 misconducts and game misconducts to Rene Corbet of the Avalanche and Shanahan and Martin Lapointe of the Red Wings. Referee Paul Devorski whistled 194 minutes in penalties in the third period alone.</p>
<p>The fight with 2 1/2 minutes left in the game began after Corbet slashed Larionov in the leg.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not the way we wanted the game to end,&quot; said Maltby. &quot;We were on a roll tonight and scoring goals, but it got kind of ugly at the end there, it got a little out of control. It will make for an interesting game on Saturday.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The first seven penalties (actually six) were called against us,&quot; said Roy. &quot;How can that be? This was the same official that worked the game on March 26 when the fight happened. He wanted to controal the game but didn't.&quot;</p>
<p>On March 26 in Detroit's 6-5 overtime win over Colorado, Roy and Vernon fought at centre ice, and Roy wound up with a bloody nose. Lemieux was beaten bloody by the Wings' Darren McCarty in that incident.</p>
<p>Detroit finished 2-for-11 with the extra man after going 2-for-15 in the first three games of the series. Colorado went 0-for-6 on the power play, falling to 2-for-18 in the series.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
