<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608374" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-HOWLEY AND TOWNSEND TO ADVANCE TEST CLAIMS.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-HOWLEY AND TOWNSEND TO ADVANCE TEST CLAIMS.</headline>
<byline>Mark Stokes</byline>
<dateline>DURBAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rob Howley and Gregor Townsend have a golden opportunity to advance their claims as the halfback combination for the test series when the British Lions open their South African tour in Port Elizabeth on Saturday.</p>
<p>Welsh scrumhalf Howley and Scotland flyhalf Townsend will be dictating tactics in a near test-strength back line when the Lions take on an Eastern Province invitation side at the Boet Erasmus stadium.</p>
<p>Of the seven three-quarters on show in Port Elizabeth, fullback Neil Jenkins, centres Scott Gibbs and Jeremy Guscott and the halfback pairing are all likely candidates for the Lions test match line-up.</p>
<p>The classy Howley, one of the star players in this year's Five Nations championship, is a virtual certainty for the Lions test team and his scrumhalf duel with Springbok Joost van der Westhuizen is expected to be one of the highlights of the series.</p>
<p>The gifted Townsend, occasionally prone to glaring errors, is celebrating his return to stand-off after spending most of the last two seasons at either inside or outside centre for both club and country.</p>
<p>&quot;I've been playing all of my recent rugby at inside centre and that isn't my favourite position. Getting back to stand-off is just great,&quot; Townsend said.</p>
<p>The 24-year-old Townsend is certainly keen to secure the flyhalf berth for the tests. &quot;That's the ultimate aim and that's why everyone is here -- we all want to get into the test team and to win the series against South Africa,&quot; he said. &quot;Saturday's game is very important for the whole tour -- it's against untested opposition in unknown territory.&quot;</p>
<p>Lions coach Ian McGeechan, who also coaches Townsend's club Northampton, will be watching his halfback combination on Saturday with particular interest.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously, it's important that he (Townsend) settles into it and that we get a good halfback relationship going. It's vital too that Gregor manages the game well.</p>
<p>&quot;We've been working a lot on the options of the other players and Gregor has a role to play in that.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DURBAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
