<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608306" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: S&amp;P says Czech Republic's single-A rating stable.</title>
<headline>S&amp;P says Czech Republic's single-A rating stable.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Standard &amp; Poor's on Friday said its single-A sovereign debt rating of the Czech Republic is unshaken by the recent crown selling pressure.</p>
<p>The agency noted potential turmoil with the Czech Republic economy has been accounted for in its rating, which was affirmed with a stable outlook last month.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously (problems) of this type in the market are important and often are caused by some underlying problems in the economy which we have identified and incorporated in our A rating,&quot; said Helena Hessel, a director in S&amp;P's sovereign ratings group.  </p>
<p>Further, Hessel said the strong financial position of the Czech government has not been significantly damaged by the central bank's crown intervention. Government reserves used probably totaled about $1 billion, Hessel said, compared with the more than $12 billion in reserves held at the end of 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;They are a net creditor,&quot; she said. &quot;Of course, this position has been weakening over last couple of days...but so far it seems they haven't used really a tremendous amount of reserves.</p>
<p>&quot;It is tremendous but they had an incredibly liquid position,&quot; she added.  </p>
<p>The Czech central bank (CNB) intervened on behalf of the crown four times in the past week in an effort to ward off a wave of speculative selling in the currency. In addition to interventions, the CNB has raised its Lombard lending facility to 50 percent from 14 percent, its repo rate to 75 percent from 12.9 percent, and cut off non-residents to the country's money markets.</p>
<p>While the government's position is supportive of a stable investment grade sovereign rating, Hessel also said economic problems behind the crown battle will prevent the rating from &quot;moving ahead.&quot;</p>
<p>((--Al Yoon, 212-859-1672))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
