<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608345" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: CYCLING-WUST WINS GIRO STAGE AS CIPOLLINI SURRENDERS.</title>
<headline>CYCLING-WUST WINS GIRO STAGE AS CIPOLLINI SURRENDERS.</headline>
<byline>Mike Price</byline>
<dateline>MONDRAGONE, Italy 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mario Cipollini created the surprise of the Giro d'Italia on Friday by failing to win the seventh stage from Lanciano.</p>
<p>The Italian sprinter, odds on for his fourth victory in seven days, stopped pedalling in the last 300 metres of the 210-km stage and free-wheeled over the line amid the dust from the winning wheels of German Marcel Wust.</p>
<p>With Giro leader Pavel Tonkov and his rivals among the 126 riders who finished en masse, there was no movement in the overall standings.</p>
<p>The flat-out finish along the beach road of this Tyrrhenian holiday town was made for a Cipollini blast, and throughout the final lap on the 5.4 kms finishing circuit he was lurking near the front of the strung-out field.</p>
<p>Then, as the milling bunch sprinted for the line, the Tuscan surrendered, sat up and watched as they sped past, with Wust edging out Italians Mirko Rossato and Endrio Leoni.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not wish to compete when I know that I am beaten,&quot; said Cipollini, who has held the mauve jersey of most consistent finisher since the Giro began a week ago.</p>
<p>&quot;He did not win because he has lost two important team mates,&quot; said Wust, referring to Gian Matteo Fagnini (eliminated on Tuesday) and Thursday's crash victim Mario Scirea.</p>
<p>&quot;He usually succeeds because he has such a good team to help pace him into a winning position. It was a great win for me because I rate Cipollini among the world's three best sprinters.&quot;</p>
<p>Wust had three stage successes in the 1995 Vuelta a Espana, but this was his first Giro victory.</p>
<p>He crashed out of the Giro last year when it started in Greece, and did not reach France in the 1992 Tour de France. He broke his collarbone in the opening stage at San Sebastian.</p>
<p>With an undulating 203 kms route on Saturday's eighth stage to Cava de Tirreni, near Salerno, Tonkov and his team are ready for challenges to his five-day hold on the overall leader's pink jersey.</p>
<p>&quot;I anticipate many will attack. We must try to control the race but I do not want my team to get too tired,&quot; he said, particularly mindful of the final week in the Dolomite mountains.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MONDRAGONE, Italy"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
