<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608370" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-FALKIRK AND KILMARNOCK REPLAY FINAL 40 YEARS ON.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-FALKIRK AND KILMARNOCK REPLAY FINAL 40 YEARS ON.</headline>
<byline>Phil Gordon</byline>
<dateline>GLASGOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Falkirk and Kilmarnock will turn the clock back 40 years when they meet in the Scottish F.A. Cup Final at Ibrox on Saturday.</p>
<p>The match is a repeat of the 1957 final which Falkirk won after a replay and is only the seventh final since then not to feature either of the Old Firm of Rangers or Celtic. Falkirk have not reached the final since 1957 while Kilmarnock's only appearance since then came in 1960 when they lost to Rangers.</p>
<p>The occasion has caught the imagination and although both clubs exist on small gates, the match is a 50,000 sell-out even though it is live on television. All the tickets were snapped up weeks ago as both provinicial towns grab their moment of fame.</p>
<p>Falkirk, relegated from the premier division a year ago, stunned Celtic in the semifinals to reach the final and are bidding to prove that the smaller clubs can still be successful.</p>
<p>They will take 21,000 fans to the match -- half the town's population and dream of taking part in the European Cup Winners' Cup next season.</p>
<p>Indeed 34-year-old winger Kevin McAllister, who spent six years in London with Chelsea, would like to go back to Stamford Bridge next season with Falkirk.</p>
<p>&quot;I would love to go back there for a European tie as a Falkirk player,&quot; he said this week, &quot;It might be a dream but we dreamed of beating Celtic to get to the final and that dream came true.&quot;</p>
<p>The 1957 Cup win was Falkirk's only major honour in their 121-year history, while Kilmarnock's second and last cup win came in 1929.</p>
<p>In modern times their only honour came in 1965 when they were champions and while Kilmarnock have been quoted by Ladbrokes as 9-4-on favourites to win the Cup, Falkirk believe their name is already on the trophy.</p>
<p>They point to a string of uncanny omens, chiefly that the opponents back in 1957 were Kilmarnock and that this season, like then, they beat Berwick and Raith Rovers on their way to the final.</p>
<p>If any more evidence were needed, Falkirk manager Alex Totten watched that 1957 final as a schoolboy. Five months ago he was out of work after being sacked by a Scottish premier division club. That club? Kilmarnock.</p>
<p>Falkirk are rated as 13-8 hopefuls for the trophy after starting the season as 100-1 outsiders.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GLASGOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
