<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608391" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-METS' BOBBY JONES IS FIRST N.L. 8-GAME WINNER.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-METS' BOBBY JONES IS FIRST N.L. 8-GAME WINNER.</headline>
<dateline>PHILADELPHIA 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bobby Jones became the National League's first eight-game winner and was one of three Mets with three hits as surging New York routed the Philadelphia Phillies 10-3 Thursday.</p>
<p>Jones (8-2) allowed three runs over seven innings on eight hits and a walk with three strikeouts in winning his fifth straight decision. He held Philadelphia to one run over the first five innings as the Mets, who have won nine of their last 12 games, built a 10-1 lead.</p>
<p>&quot;It's definitely not something I expected, to have this many wins so soon,&quot; Jones said. &quot;It's great to get off to a good start. I'm throwing the ball as well as I ever have. I'm very comfortable and I've had good location on all my pitches.&quot;</p>
<p>John Olerud, Edgardo Alfonzo and Jones played key roles in an eight-run third inning that broke open a tight game. Bernard Gilkey, Alex Ochoa and Rey Ordonez added two hits apiece as the Mets banged out 15 hits against five Philadelphia pitchers.  The win also moved New York four games over .500 for the first time since 1992.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a fluke thing,&quot; added Jones of his hitting. &quot;The ball just hit the bat, it's one of those things I guess.&quot;</p>
<p>Phillies ace Curt Schilling (6-4) was tagged for nine runs and nine hits in 2 2/3 innings, walking three and striking out three. His earned run average jumped from 3.18 to 4.13.</p>
<p>Schilling, who was pitching on just three hours' sleep after his wife gave birth to his first daughter, didn't blame the lack of rest for his performance.</p>
<p>&quot;My pregame routine was a little skewed, but I'm incredibly disappointed, because I felt good coming out of the pen,&quot; Schilling said.</p>
<p>&quot;Every mistake I made they hit. I was ready to pitch and I thought it would be a pitchers' duel, but only one pitcher showed up.&quot;</p>
<p>Olerud got his ninth homer for New York while ex-Met Rico Brogna homered for Philadelphia.</p>
<p>In San Francisco, Mark Gardner allowed four hits over six innings en route to his sixth straight victory and J.T. Snow had a double and three RBI as the Giants beat the Colorado Rockies 7-2.</p>
<p>Gardner (6-1) allowed a pair of solo homers, walked three and struck out three in extending the longest winning streak of his career. The Giants have won seven of his last eight starts and his winning streak is the longest by a Giant since Dave Burba's eight-game string in 1993.</p>
<p>&quot;Pitching in big games I try not to change the way I pitch,&quot; Gardner said. &quot;Every game is important. I just try to maintain composure and pitch my game.&quot;</p>
<p>Rich Rodriguez and Doug Henry combined to hold Colorado scoreless over the final three frames.</p>
<p>Colorado starter John Thomson (0-3) was tagged for four runs and seven hits in 5 2/3 innings.</p>
<p>Ellis Burks and Jeff Reed got the Colorado homers.</p>
<p>In Montreal, Adrian Brown's first major-league homer, a three-run shot in the seventh inning, helped rally the Pittsburgh Pirates to a 9-3 victory over the Expos.</p>
<p>&quot;I was sitting on a changeup all the way,&quot; said Brown, who was recalled from Double-A Carolina last Friday. &quot;The first two at-bats, he (Carlos Perez) threw me a fastball and then a change, so I was looking for it.&quot;</p>
<p>Added Brown: &quot;Special, like a dream come true for me. I'll remember this one.&quot;</p>
<p>Joe Randa also homered for Pittsburgh while Darrin Fletcher and Mike Lansing had solo shots for Montreal.</p>
<p>Jon Lieber (2-5) broke his five-game losing streak and won for the first time in six starts since April 20. He allowed three runs and walked one with seven strikeouts in six innings as the Pirates posted their second straight win after a four-game losing streak.</p>
<p>Perez (4-4) lost his third straight decision and is winless since April 30. He gave up four runs and five hits with five walks and three strikeouts in 6 2/3 innings for Montreal, which suffered its third straight loss.</p>
<p>In San Diego, Joey Hamilton allowed one run over seven innings and hit his second career home run and Tony Gwynn added three hits as the Padres stopped the Los Angeles Dodgers 4-1 for their fourth straight victory.</p>
<p>Hamilton (3-1) allowed four hits, walked three and struck out five to notch his second straight win since returning from the disabled list last week. The right-hander's only mistake was Todd Zeile's leadoff homer in the second inning.</p>
<p>The four-game winning streak is the Padres' longest of the season. They also extended their win streak over Los Angeles to seven games.</p>
<p>Hideo Nomo (5-3) gave up four runs and eight hits over seven innings for the Dodgers, who have lost five straight for the first time since July 1995.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHILADELPHIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
