<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608387" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-JAPANESE SEEK PROBE OF YANKEES FOR IRABU TAMPERING.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-JAPANESE SEEK PROBE OF YANKEES FOR IRABU TAMPERING.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The New York Yankees' efforts to sign Japanese pitcher Hideki Irabu took another twist Friday when the Commissioner's Office of Japan accused the team of tampering.</p>
<p>Major League Baseball announced it has started an investigation after receiving a formal request to determine whether the Yankees contacted Irabu and his representatives before they had the rights to him.</p>
<p>The Yankees sent $3 million in cash, outfielder Ruben Rivera and minor-league pitcher Rafael Medina to San Diego on April 22 for the rights to Irabu, minor leaguers Homer Bush and Gordon Amerson and a player to be named.</p>
<p>Baseball's Executive Council then formally aproved the trade, pending final approval from the Commissioner's Office in Japan. The trade is also contingent upon the Yankees signing Irabu by May 31.</p>
<p>&quot;The New York Yankees have been advised of this correspondence and the Commissioner's Office has begun its process,&quot; said acting commissioner Bud Selig.</p>
<p>&quot;It is incumbent on Major League Baseball, by virtue of our treaty with Japanese Baseball, to ascertain that all dealings with Mr Irabu were conducted fairly and within the rules of the agreement.&quot;</p>
<p>The New York Times reported that even if tampering was found to have taken place, it is unlikely to void the trade. The newspaper said that a more likely scenario would have the Yankees being fined and surrendering draft choices.</p>
<p>Various reports in the New York area have said the Yankees are close to signing Irabu to a four-year deal worth between $12 million and $13 million.</p>
<p>The Padres owned the rights to Irabu, who has been called the &quot;Nolan Ryan of Japan&quot; because of an overpowering fastball, as a result of their working agreement with Irabu's Japanese team, the Chiba Lotte Marines.</p>
<p>But Irabu steadfastly proclaimed his desire to pitch only for the Yankees and was prepared to sit out the entire season if he was not traded to New York. Irabu was 12-6 and led the Japanese Pacific League with a 2.40 ERA last season.</p>
<p>Rivera and Medina are both on the disabled list and have not pitched this season.</p>
<p>The tampering charges come with the Yankees already fighting another legal battle with Major League Baseball. The Yankees and adidas have filed a lawsuit over baseball's protests against a 10-year, $95 million marketing deal between the sports apparel company and the Yankees.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
