<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608380" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: SOCCER-PERU DECLINE TO SEND TOP PLAYERS TO COPA AMERICA.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-PERU DECLINE TO SEND TOP PLAYERS TO COPA AMERICA.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Peru excluded all of their regular internationals when they named their squad for the Copa America on Friday and announced they intended to use the tournament to give experience to younger players.</p>
<p>A Peruvian Football Federation (FPF) official also confirmed that Freddy Tenero would take charge of the team rather than national team coach Juan Carlos Oblitas.</p>
<p>The Copa America, which will be held in Bolivia in June, is sandwiched between the South American qualifying matches for next year's World Cup in France.</p>
<p>One round of qualifiers will be played just three days before the Copa's first games while another round takes place a week after the final.</p>
<p>As a result, several countries, including Colombia and Argentina, have warned they are likely to follow the Peruvian example. However, world champions Brazil, who do not play in the qualifiers, have already named a full-strength squad.</p>
<p>The Peruvian squad is similar to the one which took part in last year's Olympic qualifying tournament in Argentina, when only under-23 teams could be fielded. The Peruvians failed to qualify for Atlanta.</p>
<p>The FPF named 21 players and said that a striker from the regular international squad would be added at a later date.</p>
<p>Squad:</p>
<p>Goalkeepers - Leanardo Butron (Cristal), Juan Flores (Sport Boys), Miguel Miranda (Municipal)</p>
<p>Defenders - Jose Reyna (Alianza), Jose Chacon, Orlando Prado (both Pesquero), Manuel Marengo, Miguel Rebosio (both Sporting Cristal), Giuliano Portilla (Universitario), Alfonso Dulanto (UNAM, Mexico)</p>
<p>Midfielders - Cesar Rosales (Alianza), German Munoz (Cienciano), Leonardo Uehara (Loretana), Frank Palomino (Melgar), Alex Magallanes, Martin Hidalgo, Erick Torres (all Sporting Cristal), Eddie Carazas, Marko Ciurlizza (both Universitario)</p>
<p>Forwards - Aldo Cavero (Cienciano), Paul Cominges (Melgar)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
