<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608371" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: GOLF-ELS SEEKING TO GET ON LEVEL TERMS WITH WOODS.</title>
<headline>GOLF-ELS SEEKING TO GET ON LEVEL TERMS WITH WOODS.</headline>
<byline>Brian Creighton</byline>
<dateline>WENTWORTH, England 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African Ernie Els believes once he kick-starts his golf game back into high gear he will be on level terms with American sensation Tiger Woods.</p>
<p>But first he must shake off the mini-slump that has seen him miss three halfway cuts in his last eight events on the U.S. Tour, where he is based.</p>
<p>After a three-week break in South Africa, he has returned to familiar ground, the Wentworth course outside London where he has won the World Matchplay title for the last three years.</p>
<p>The fair-haired giant, now ranked eighth in the world, begins the British PGA championship on Friday trying to go one better than his second place in 1994 and ought certainly to draw inspiration from his playing partners, Nick Faldo and Bernhard Langer, who between them have won the title seven times.</p>
<p>Els's press interview on Thursday drew the inevitable questions about Woods, the 21-year-old phenomenon who won the Masters by a record 12 shots last month and the Byron Nelson Classic last Sunday, giving him five wins since he turned pro last summer.</p>
<p>&quot;I can play close to that level,&quot; Els insisted. &quot;I know my game, I have the talent and I've been up there before.</p>
<p>&quot;When you have a couple of disappointments in majors, and it could happen to Tiger, then you start thinking it is not so easy.</p>
<p>&quot;We shall see. It will be interesting to see what he can do at the U.S. Open (next month). You are not going to run away with that tournament. And the (British) Open at Troon will also be different.&quot;</p>
<p>But he did concede Woods was streets ahead of everybody at the moment. &quot;He is an unbelievable player right now. I don't think when he was in his teens anyone thought he would be at this level at this point in his career.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment everything is going his way,&quot; Els added. &quot;He has a lot of things going for him. He is a confident young man with a lot of talent, probably the most I have ever seen.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the other players were playing catch-up. &quot;I think we have to try to get to his level. Tiger is the best we have seen since Jack Nicklaus, who hit the ball 30 yards further than anyone else. He had that special aura about him.</p>
<p>&quot;Now Tiger has it. We needed that to make us wake up and take it a little more seriously,&quot; Els, the 1994 U.S. Open champion, said.</p>
<p>Els, who is a full member of both the U.S. and European Tours - he played in Europe for three years - has been working here this week with famed coach David Leadbetter, who made his name changing Faldo's swing back in the mid-1980s and who has worked with most top players since then.</p>
<p>&quot;He is helping me because I have not been in the right position at the top of my backswing,&quot; Els said.</p>
<p>&quot;My backswing has been a little flat. My legs were sliding through a little bit. I was hitting it too early or too late.</p>
<p>&quot;Now my backswing is where I want it and I just have to release the club onto the ball. I'm hitting my irons well, but I am still blocking a few drives.&quot;</p>
<p>He has been inconsistent this year. &quot;Every time I played a tournament something was not up to scratch.</p>
<p>&quot;In the company we keep these days, you have to have everything, your driving, putting, short game.</p>
<p>&quot;When one thing is not there you are going to have a problem and it has happened to me,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WENTWORTH, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
