<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608368" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-ENGLAND AND SOUTH AFRICA PREPARE FOR FIRST MEETING.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-ENGLAND AND SOUTH AFRICA PREPARE FOR FIRST MEETING.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>England face unfamiliar opponents at an unfamiliar home ground when they play South Africa in an international friendly at Old Trafford on Saturday.</p>
<p>Manchester United's home has not staged an England match since 1938 when Northern Ireland were beaten 7-0 and before that it had only been used once before in 1926 when Scotland beat England 1-0.</p>
<p>It is only the second home match England have played away from London in 31 years, Wembley not being available because the third division promotion playoff final between Swansea and Northampton is being played there on Saturday.</p>
<p>Saturday's match is also the first between England and South Africa, the reigning African champions, who are on a short tour of Europe.</p>
<p>Both teams will be using the game as a pointer to their upcoming World Cup qualifiers with England manager Glenn Hoddle fine-tuning his plans before their group two qualifier in Poland next week.</p>
<p>Already some spice has been added to the clash with South African coach Clive Barker saying England had less flair and imagination than his own team.</p>
<p>&quot;You have a problem with flair and I think we have more talented players than you do,&quot; said Barker.</p>
<p>&quot;We have more players who are comfortable on the ball while you have more organisation and strength. In the long run, I believe talent will prevail, you need flair to break team's down.</p>
<p>&quot;In the 1950s and 1960s I thought England were going to be one of football's great world powers. But you have under-achieved.&quot;</p>
<p>South Africa have certainly achieved in the few years they have been back in mainstream soccer since the end of the apartheid years and clinched the African championship last year.</p>
<p>They have some highly skilled individuals like Doctor Khumalo, John &quot;Shoes&quot; Moshoeu and Lucas Radebe who plays in England with Leeds United.</p>
<p>England may have lacked some flair and sparkle since Hoddle took over from Terry Venables but five of the six games played under Hoddle have been World Cup qualifiers and only one a friendly. And of those six, only one has been lost.</p>
<p>Hoddle, who will be without Liverpool pair Robbie Fowler and Steve McManaman for Saturday's game, the Poland game and the three matches England are due to play in the Tournoi de France next month and will be looking to Paul Gascoigne for a solid performance in the England midfield.</p>
<p>Gascoigne, who has not played for England since appearing against Georgia last November, seems to have recovered fitness and lost weight on the eve of his 30th birthday.</p>
<p>Hoddle announced earlier this week that Gascoigne would definitely start the match.</p>
<p>&quot;Paul is delighted he is playing and he has worked very hard to get back into form.</p>
<p>&quot;He's 30 on Tuesday and has a great future. He's at his peak if he gets it right mentally and physically can have another three or four years at the top.&quot;</p>
<p>Thge only other dsefinite starter is Manchester United defender Philip Neville, who makes his second England appearance a year after his debut in China.</p>
<p>Alan Shearer will lead the attack at a ground where he is always booed by Manchester United fans unhappy he twice snubbed their club and signed for Newcastle United.</p>
<p>Andy Cole could also start alongside Shearer up front on his home ground for a match England ought to win against a side largely untested against European opposition.</p>
<p>Lineups:</p>
<p>To be announced</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
