<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608397" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: GOLF-FAXON LEADS FORT WORTH, WOODS IS IN THE HUNT.</title>
<headline>GOLF-FAXON LEADS FORT WORTH, WOODS IS IN THE HUNT.</headline>
<dateline>FORT WORTH, Texas 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brad Faxon continued his spring-long hot streak on Thursday, firing a seven-under-par 63 to lead after the first round of the Colonial golf tournament on Thursday.</p>
<p>He held a one-shot lead over a trio of golfers, Justin Leonard, Paul Goydos and Jim Furyk.</p>
<p>But the man all eyes were focused on was Tiger Woods, the 21-year-old Masters champion who fired a three-under-par 67, well within striking distance of the first-day leaders.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't really play all that well,&quot; said Woods, who followed his Masters victory with another triumph last Sunday in his first tournament since Augusta.</p>
<p>&quot;I drove it great, but my irons were not that good, and I had a lot of 20 and 30-foot putts for birdies,&quot; Woods said. &quot;I had to be very defensive on the greens today.</p>
<p>&quot;Any score under par here is a good one. I think this can be a very tough course, especially when the wind blows,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Woods birdied holes one, three and seven, bogeyed number 10, but birdied the par-4 17th hole.</p>
<p>Faxon has already recorded four top five finishes this spring, including a victory at the Freeport McDermott Classic in early April. He said Thursday's round was another addition to his hot streak.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a good round. I had everything go my way,&quot; Faxon said. &quot;I was pretty relaxed and my distances were good. If I hit a shot off line, it was the right distance and I had a lot of (birdie) chances.&quot;</p>
<p>After a fairly slow start with birdies on holes two and five, Faxon shot a 30 on the back nine. He birdied holes 11-13, then closed out his round with birdies on holes 17 and 18, making a 10-foot birdie putt on the final hole.</p>
<p>&quot;You have to hit a lot of different shots out here,&quot; Faxon said. &quot;The wind often makes up your mind for you.&quot;</p>
<p>It wasn't high winds, but slow play which almost cost Woods during Thursday's front nine. When his group arrived on the ninth tee, they were informed by an official to speed up or they would be timed for possible slow play violations.</p>
<p>When the players reached their drives in the 9th fairway, Woods said he was confused between Janzen's and Morse's shots. As a result, he hit out of turn, playing his approach shot when it was Janzen's turn to hit.</p>
<p>&quot;I was very apologetic to Lee for hitting out of turn. I thought Lee's ball was actually John's,&quot; Woods said.</p>
<p>In stroke play, there is no penalty for hitting out of turn, provided a player hits his own ball. In match play, the penalty is loss of the hole.</p>
<p>Leonard, who lives nearby, said Thursday's round was one of his best in front of his friends and family. He won the Buick Classic last year, but has never come close to winning a professional event in his home state.</p>
<p>&quot;I always want to play well in front of my family. Sometimes I think I take it too seriously at home,&quot; Leonard said.</p>
<p>Defending Colonial champion Corey Pavin shot a one-over 71 and is in danger of missing the cut unless he goes low on Friday's second round.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FORT WORTH, Texas"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
