<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608366" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: GOLF-DARCY AND CLARKE SHARE EARLY LEAD.</title>
<headline>GOLF-DARCY AND CLARKE SHARE EARLY LEAD.</headline>
<byline>Brian Creighton</byline>
<dateline>WENTWORTH, England 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irishmen Eamonn Darcy and Darren Clarke upstaged European golf's luminaries by firing six-under-par opening rounds of 66 as the British PGA Championship began on Friday.</p>
<p>But Bernhard Langer, winner of the Italian Open and Benson and Hedges International already this month, stayed hot on their heels by returning a 67 in pursuit of his fourth PGA title and his third in five years.</p>
<p>South African Ernie Els, a European Tour member though based on the U.S. Tour, carded a 69 on the Wentworth course where he has won the World Matchplay title the last three years, while Nick Faldo shot a 70.</p>
<p>Langer, Els and Faldo played together and all birdied the par-five 18th hole.</p>
<p>Spaniard Jose Maria Olazabal, the 1994 champion, began with a level-par 72 but his compatriot, Ryder Cup captain Seve Ballesteros, slipped to a four-over 76 to put himself in danger of missing the halfway cut for the seventh time in nine events this year.</p>
<p>Britons Colin Montgomerie and Ian Woosnam and defending champion Costantino Rocca of Italy were late starters.</p>
<p>Darcy, a 44-year-old former Ryder Cup hero, and Clarke, seeking a Cup debut this year, set the pace with fine rounds over the 6,957-yard layout which the players feel is playing longer than ever this year.</p>
<p>Darcy, who still takes painkillers every day he plays for back trouble which threatened three years ago to end his career, began with four birdies in the first six holes.</p>
<p>He dropped a shot at the eighth by three-putting from 20 feet but collected three more birdies on the back nine, almost holing his four-iron tee shot at the 186-yard 10th. He finished an inch away.</p>
<p>Darcy said it was so cold and damp before he started at 0740 (0640 GMT) that after 20 practice shots he went for physiotherapy and was rubbed down with something called &quot;Tiger Balm&quot; to warm him up.</p>
<p>&quot;Three years ago I thought I was gone,&quot; he said of his back trouble, which improved after manipulation just when he thought fusion therapy would be necessary.</p>
<p>The genial Irishman is best known for sinking a tricky downhill putt against Ben Crenshaw for a crucial point at Muirfield Village in 1987 as Europe scored their first victory on American soil to retain the Ryder Cup.</p>
<p>He felt he could have been even better than his 66. &quot;I hit a lot of good shots today,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clarke, a burly 28-year-old from Northern Ireland, had an erratic round and suffered for attempting some aggressive tee shots that went astray.</p>
<p>But he had a stroke of good fortune at the long 12th where his drive hit a tree and bounced out to the centre of the fairway. He then struck a four-iron approach to 30 feet and holed the putt for an eagle three.</p>
<p>He birdied the other three par-fives holes including the tough 571-yard 17th with a 20-footer.</p>
<p>Clarke is eighth on the Ryder Cup table after finishing third, seventh and 12th over the last three weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;I keep my head a little better than I used to,&quot; he said of his new-found consistency. &quot;I'm better at grinding out scores and I accept the bad shots better.&quot;</p>
<p>Langer, who was level on five under par with English Ryder Cup player David Gilford and Swede Robert Karlsson, made two 20-foot birdie putts.</p>
<p>Darcy and Langer agreed that the dogleg 17th hole was unfair. The hole swings to the left but to try and cut over the dogleg risks finishing in heavy rough.</p>
<p>&quot;The problem is the hole slopes the wrong way, from right to left and there is also heavy rough on the right side,&quot; Langer said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WENTWORTH, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
