<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608344" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: GOLF-DARCY AND CLARKE HOLDING OFF THE BIG NAMES.</title>
<headline>GOLF-DARCY AND CLARKE HOLDING OFF THE BIG NAMES.</headline>
<dateline>WENTWORTH, England 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irishmen Eamonn Darcy and Darren Clarke fired early six-under-par 66s that resisted the best efforts of a classy international field at the British PGA Championship on Friday.</p>
<p>But the big names were lining up behind with Bernhard Langer, winner of the Italian Open and Benson and Hedges International titles already this month, and Ian Woosnam level with three others on 67.</p>
<p>They shared third place with Englishmen David Gilford and Andrew Sherborne, Scotsman Gary Orr and giant Swede Robert Karlsson.</p>
<p>Frank Nobilo of New Zealand, and Denmark's 1996 European Rookie of the Year Thomas Bjorn were among those on 68 with Colin Montgomerie and Ernie Els on 69 and Nick Faldo, titleholder Costantino Rocca, Swede Jesper Parnevik and Fijian Vijay Singh in a big group on 70.</p>
<p>Spaniard Jose Maria Olazabal, the 1994 champion, began with a level-par 72 but his compatriot, Ryder Cup captain Seve Ballesteros, slipped to a four-over 76 to put himself in danger of missing the halfway cut for the seventh time in nine events this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WENTWORTH, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
