<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608361" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: CRICKET-MARSH HITS CAREER-BEST 142 IN KENT FIGHTBACK.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-MARSH HITS CAREER-BEST 142 IN KENT FIGHTBACK.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kent captain Steve Marsh lashed a career-best 142 and shared in a record last-wicket stand of 183 to transform his team's fortunes against Sussex on Friday.</p>
<p>Marsh inspired a tail-end revival in which Kent's last two wickets added 243 to snatch the initiative on the third day of the four-day county championship match at Horsham.</p>
<p>Kent's second innings had declined to 197 for eight, a lead of only 178, when wicketkeeper Marsh launched his compelling fightback.</p>
<p>He added 60 in 24 overs for the ninth wicket with Zimbabwe leg-spinner Paul Strang, who contributed 17, then put 183 for the 10th wicket with Ben Phillips, who hit an unbeaten 65.</p>
<p>Marsh, whose previous highest score was 127 against Essex at Ilford last season, made his 142 from 216 balls, blasting 13 fours and three sixes.</p>
<p>Kent finished with 440 all out and Sussex, needing 422 to win, were 31 for one at the close.</p>
<p>Another wicketkeeper in fine batting form was Jack Russell, whose unbeaten 91 lifted Gloucestershire's first innings from the overnight 87 for seven to 290 all out against Essex at Gloucester.</p>
<p>England international Russell and Tim Hancock put on 108 for the championship leaders' eighth wicket, before Essex replied with 136 for four, of which Australian Stuart Law struck 60 not out.</p>
<p>Somerset pace bowler Andy Caddick gave a reminder to England's test selectors by increasing his match haul to seven wickets against Yorkshire at Taunton.</p>
<p>He followed his first innings six for 103 with an early second innings wicket after Somerset had declared 103 behind in an attempt to make up for lost time in the rain-hit match.</p>
<p>South Australian Darren Lehmann, having reached three figures overnight, went on to 177 in Yorkshire's 306 all out. Somerset declared at 203 for five and the visitors closed at 124 for two -- 227 ahead.</p>
<p>Leicestershire opener Darren Maddy spurred the champions with 103 as they reached 305 for six in reply to Surrey's first innings of 278 at Leicester.</p>
<p>Maddy's 100 came up in 237 balls, and he and Vince Wells (56) put on 131 for the first wicket.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
