<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608347" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: CRICKET-PAKISTAN WORRIED ABOUT EASING UP IN FINAL.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-PAKISTAN WORRIED ABOUT EASING UP IN FINAL.</headline>
<dateline>MOHALI, India 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistan captain Rameez Raja is worried his team may ease up in the Independence Cup final against Sri Lanka after their victory-to-savour over arch-rivals India.</p>
<p>&quot;That's what we don't want,&quot; Raja said on Friday in Mohali, where Pakistan play the World Cup champions on Saturday in the first match of a best-of-three final at the limited overs tournament.</p>
<p>Pakistan were elated after beating India in Madras on Wednesday in the league stage.</p>
<p>&quot;Winning against India meant a lot to us after the fury we faced when we went back home,&quot; Raja said in a reference to events after Pakistan's quarter-final defeat by India at Bangalore in last year's World Cup.</p>
<p>&quot;We can safely go back home now,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Raja said the final would in all probability be a high-scoring affair on the easy-paced Mohali pitch.</p>
<p>Pakistan opener Saeed Anwar, who flayed India in Madras with 194, the highest individual score in a one-day international, said the Mohali game could well be a face-off between Sri Lankan opener Sanath Jayasuriya and Pakistan's Shahid Afridi.</p>
<p>Both have a reputation for thunderous batting in the early overs, but Raja played down Afridi's role.</p>
<p>&quot;He is a young Pathan with a lot of talent, with an extremely good temperament. But we have to keep him under control. You know how a Pathan is,&quot; Raja said of Afridi, in an apparent reference to martial Pathans' reputation for impetuousness.</p>
<p>Pakistan are to play Sri Lanka in Calcutta next Tuesday in the second match of the final, with a third game on Wednesday in Calcutta if the teams are level 1-1.</p>
<p>India and New Zealand bowed out at the end of the league stage of the tournament commemorating the 50th anniversary of India's independence from Britain.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOHALI, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
