<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608319" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Lazard Freres &amp; Co names Steven Rattner Deputy CEO.</title>
<headline>Lazard Freres &amp; Co names Steven Rattner Deputy CEO.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lazard Freres &amp; Co said Friday it had named Steven Rattner as deputy chief executive officer, reporting to Chairman and Chief Executive Michel David-Weill.</p>
<p>Rattner is an investment banker and managing director specializing in media mergers. He will oversee day-to-day management of the firm with David-Weill, Lazard said.</p>
<p>The announcement follows reports of a succession crisis at the merchant bank and comes just weeks after the departure of the firm's top dealmaker, Felix Rohatyn, who resigned to become U.S. ambassador to France.  </p>
<p>The firm, with operations in Paris, New York and London, also said it had formed a management committee composed of the heads of its three departments and other top administrators.</p>
<p>Kendrick Wilson, head of mergers and acquisitions; Damon Mezzacappa, head of capital markets, and Norman Eig and Herbert Gullquist, who head Lazard Asset Management, were all named vice chairmen. They will serve on the management committee with Steven Golub, who was named chief financial officer, and Melvin Heineman, a managing director and Lazard's chief administrative officer.</p>
<p>David-Weill and Rattner will also sit on the committee.</p>
<p>Rattner was a reporter for the New York Times before leaving to become an investment banker with Lehman Brothers Kuhn Loeb Inc in 1982. He left Lehman for Morgan Stanley and was hired by Lazard Freres in 1989, according to Lazard.</p>
<p>((--Wall Street Desk 212 859 1881))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
