<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608304" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Nortel Inversora says plans ADS offering.</title>
<headline>Nortel Inversora says plans ADS offering.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nortel Inversora SA said Friday it plans to offer six million American depositary shares in a secondary offering.</p>
<p>Nortel said its selling shareholders, who invested in the company when it was formed in 1990, will receive all proceeds from the offering.</p>
<p>Nortel's investors include Italy's Stet SpA, France Telecom, Argentine conglomerate Perez Companc SA and J.P. Morgan &amp; Co Inc. Sales by the shareholders will be made on a pro forma basis, Nortel said.  </p>
<p>Nortel, which owns 60 percent of Telecom Argentina, said each of the shares represents 1/20th of one of its series B preferred shares.</p>
<p>It said the series B preferred shares are non-voting except in limited circumstances, and can be redeemed at the option of the holders.</p>
<p>The company said underwriters of the offering will be granted an option to buy an additional 900,000 shares to cover over-allotments.</p>
<p>Nortel said it plans to apply to list the shares on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>The managers for the offering are J.P. Morgan Securities Inc, Credit Suisse First Boston Corp, Lehman Brothers Inc and Credit Lyonnais Securities Inc.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
