<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608389" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NBA BASKETBALL-BULLS GET LOW-SCORING WIN OVER HEAT.</title>
<headline>NBA BASKETBALL-BULLS GET LOW-SCORING WIN OVER HEAT.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Michael Jordan shook off three horrible quarters to score 14 points in the final 6:27 and the Chicago Bulls cranked up the defence to beat the Miami Heat 75-68 Thursday in the lowest scoring NBA playoff game ever.</p>
<p>The win, which gave the defending champion Bulls a 2-0 lead in the best-of-seven Eastern Conference finals, replaced a 74-71 game between Syracuse and Fort Wayne on April 7, 1955 as the lowest-scoring in NBA playoff history.</p>
<p>Game 3 is Saturday afternoon in Miami.</p>
<p>Jordan, who once scored 63 points by himself in a playoff game, was 2-of-12 from the field and had only nine points just before the midpoint of the fourth quarter. But he finished with 23 by dominating the game's crucial moments, from the field and at the free-throw line.</p>
<p>&quot;I played like doo-doo,&quot; said Jordan. &quot;It's simple. I made some free throws down the stretch. Other than that they did it without me tonight. I missed some easy shots. It was an ugly performance by me. It wasn't pretty basketball but at least we get out of here with two wins.&quot;</p>
<p>Scottie Pippen also had 23 points for Chicago, which shot just 35 percent (23-of-64) from the field.</p>
<p>&quot;I got off to a good early start,&quot; said Pippen. &quot;If you take that away, I played as lousy as anyone else. You have to realise that (Miami's Pat) Riley has coached against this triangle (offense) many times. He knows how to take the ball out of Michael's hands.</p>
<p>&quot;No matter how physical it gets, we have to play our game. The important thing is that we are winning.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There is not much good to say about this game, except that we won,&quot; said Bulls coach Phil Jackson. &quot;I told them after three quarters that whoever scored 14 points would have a chance to win the game. Bad shooting has just been the tone of the series.&quot;</p>
<p>Tim Hardaway had 15 points and Alonzo Mourning 14 for Miami, which hit just 33 percent (25-of-74) from the floor.</p>
<p>&quot;If we can get the same type of shots we got tonight in Miami, I'll be happy,&quot; Riley said.  &quot;We got some good looks, we just didn't make the shots. Both teams are playing very well defensively.&quot;</p>
<p>The game also saw the lowest scoring first half in playoff history. Chicago led 39-29 at the break, and the 68 combined points were one fewer than the New York Knicks and New Jersey Nets produced on April 29, 1994.</p>
<p>In the first half, Jordan managed just seven points on 1-of-7 shooting.</p>
<p>The Heat pulled within a basket on several occasions in the third quarter but were unable to take the lead. They trailed 45-43 with 3:27 left in the period, but Jamal Mashburn missed a 3-pointer. After a Chicago turnover, Mourning missed a driving layup that would have knotted the contest.</p>
<p>After Mourning's miss, Jordan penetrated but dished off to Pippen, who buried a 3-pointer for a 48-43 lead. The Heat were unable to get closer than four the rest of the quarter.</p>
<p>In the fourth quarter, the Heat drew within 55-54 on a 3-pointer by Dan Majerle with 6:30 to go in the game. The Bulls called timeout and, on their first possession after the break, Pippen threw up a wild 3-point attempt.</p>
<p>But Jordan, who finished with nine rebounds, came up with the loose ball and laid it back in for a three-point advantage.</p>
<p>Isaac Austin hit a reverse layup in the key to bring Miami within 57-56 but Pippen answered by draining a pair of free throws with 5:29 to go. Austin hit an 11-foot turnaround jumper with Dennis Rodman all over him to again bring Miami within a point.</p>
<p>But Jordan hit a clutch 17-footer with 4:45 to play, pushing the lead back to 61-58.</p>
<p>The Heat misfired again at the offensive end and Jordan grabbed the rebound and was fouled. He made both free throws for a five-point lead, then got a steal and penetrated into the key as the Heat defenders collapsed on him.</p>
<p>Jordan dished the ball to a wide-open Ron Harper, who buried a 3-pointer to give Chicago a 66-58 lead.</p>
<p>After a free throw by Hardaway brought Miami within seven, Jordan hit two more free throws and the Heat never drew any closer than five the rest of the way.</p>
<p>Chicago got just nine points on 3-of-13 shooting from its bench as Toni Kukoc, Brian Williams and Steve Kerr combined for four points.  REUTER  230503 GMT may 97</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
