<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608327" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. stocks up but trading starting to wane.</title>
<headline>U.S. stocks up but trading starting to wane.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. stocks held to early morning gains on Friday, but traders expected activity to ease sharply going into a three-day holiday in the United States.</p>
<p>The Dow industrials jumped over 50 points shortly after the market open, prompting the New York Stock Exchange to place curbs on index-arbitrage trading.</p>
<p>In the absence of fresh economic data, traders said stocks were buoyed by small-capitilization shares and by bonds, as the key 30-year benchmark Treasury stayed just under a seven percent yield.  </p>
<p>&quot;The scenerio is looking like moderate economic growth, the bonds don't look like they are going to break through seven percent and the small-cap stocks are starting to catch fire,&quot; Bill Allyn, head of trading at Jeffries and Co said.</p>
<p>The Dow was up 48 points at 7306, the Nasdaq composite was up four points at 1377 and the Russell 2000 index of small capitalization shares was up 1.43 points at 373.</p>
<p>The long bond was up 2/32 at a 6.99 percent yield.</p>
<p>But volume was light and promised to get lighter with U.S. markets shut Monday for Memorial Day. &quot;Things should be pretty much over by mid-afternoon as people go home,&quot; a trader said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
