<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608355" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-BITTER HODGSON QUITS INTER EARLY.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BITTER HODGSON QUITS INTER EARLY.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Englishman Roy Hodgson  confirmed his decision to resign immediately as coach at beaten UEFA Cup finalists Internazionale Milan, club sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>They said Hodgson, who is moving to English club Blackburn next season, had informed Inter chairman Massimo Moratti that he was quitting with two crucial games left in the serie A season.</p>
<p>The decision was largely symbolic given Hodgson's move to the former English Premier League champions, which was announced in February.</p>
<p>But it highlighted the bitterness Hodgson has felt in a successful but rocky 18 months with Inter.</p>
<p>On Wednesday night, fans pelted him with coins and cigarette lighters as he left the pitch after Inter lost the UEFA Cup final to German club Schalke in a penalty shoot-out at the San Siro stadium.</p>
<p>He also had a brief but very public altercation with Inter's Argentine midfielder Javier Zanetti, who resented being substituted in the dying minutes of extra time.</p>
<p>Club sources said Hodgson's place on the bench would be taken for the remainder of the season by goalkeeping coach Luciano Castellani. Gigi Simoni, formerly of Napoli, is due to join Inter as the fulltime coach next season.</p>
<p>The remaining two matches, at home to Napoli on Sunday and at Bologna on June 1, will decide whether Inter finish second and thus secure a European Cup berth next season.</p>
<p>With Juventus needing just a point to clinch the league title on Friday evening, Inter lie third in the table, eight points behind the leaders and two behind second-placed Parma.</p>
<p>They could still overtake Parma to clinch second place.</p>
<p>Although Inter have had a successful season, Hodgson, who joined in October 1995 from a much-praised stint as Swiss national coach, has not enjoyed a happy relationship with fans, media and senior figures within the club.</p>
<p>He handed Moratti his resignation 24 hours after the defeat against Schalke but was asked to sleep on it.</p>
<p>&quot;I reassured him (Hodgson) of my faith in his abilities and I hope that his sense of discouragement will pass and that he will lead Inter in our last two games of the season,&quot; Moratti was quoted as saying in Friday's Gazzetta Dello Sport newspaper.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm sorry that the fans consider Hodgson the guilty party, I think they exaggerated,&quot; Moratti said. &quot;I know Hodgson well, he doesn't deserve such a mortification.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
