<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608388" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NHL-AVALANCHE COACH MARC CRAWFORD FINED $10,000.</title>
<headline>NHL-AVALANCHE COACH MARC CRAWFORD FINED $10,000.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colorado Avalanche coach Marc Crawford completely lost his temper Thursday night in Game 4 of the Western Conference finals, and it will cost him $10,000, the National Hockey League announced on Friday.</p>
<p>Crawford was fined for conduct &quot;dishonorable, prejudicial to or against the welfare of the league,&quot; the NHL said.</p>
<p>Crawford's explosion occurred in the fight-filled third period of Colorado's 6-0 loss to the Detroit Red Wings. The defending Stanley Cup champion Avalanche trail the best-of-seven series, 3-1.</p>
<p>Following one melee, Crawford and Detroit coach Scotty Bowman exchanged heated words across the glass partition that separates the players' benches.</p>
<p>&quot;As a result of Colorado Avalanche coach Marc Crawford's actions at the 17:42 mark of the third period when he had to be physically restrained from entering the Detroit players' bench, a fine of $10,000 was assessed today by the National Hockey League,&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously, emotions got out of whack,&quot; Crawford explained after the game. &quot;You say some stupid things, they say some stupid things. It happens. It happened to us earlier in the playoffs. Nobody's proud of it, but it's part of the game.&quot;</p>
<p>Even Bowman, the coach with the most wins in NHL history, appeared surprised by the emotional nature of Crawford's attack.</p>
<p>&quot;He was pretty emotional,&quot; Bowman said. &quot;I guess I've been that way before, too. But his eyes were coming out of his head. He was pretty excited.&quot;</p>
<p>NHL Senior Vice President Brian Burke said: &quot;Although Mr Crawford has since apologised to the league for his behaviour, this does not excuse the fact that his actions were totally inappropriate.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
