<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608419" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: SOCCER-NO GULLIT IN DUTCH SQUAD FOR SOUTH AFRICA.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-NO GULLIT IN DUTCH SQUAD FOR SOUTH AFRICA.</headline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chelsea player-manager Ruud Gullit will not make a farewell appearance for the Netherlands in a friendly against South Africa in Johannesburg on June 4.</p>
<p>The match is part of celebrations to mark the fifth anniversary of the inauguration of Nelson Mandela as president and there had been speculation that Gullit would play one last match for the Dutch national team to honour Mandela.</p>
<p>Gullit and Mandela have been friends since the former AC Milan star dedicated his 1987 European Footballer of the year prize to Mandela, who was then still in jail. He later presented the prize to him in person after Mandela was freed.</p>
<p>Gullit, who has not played for the Netherlands since winning his 65th cap in May 1994, is still officially listed as a player, but laughed off suggestions he would appear for Chelsea in last week's English F.A. Cup final against Middlesbrough which his team won 2-0. </p>
<p>He has also strongly hinted he will not play again next season, unless needed in an emergency.</p>
<p>A Dutch football association (KNVB) spokesman said on Thursday Gullit had been invited to attend the match but that there had never been any plans to include him in the Dutch team.</p>
<p>Ajax players will not be available for the match as they will be on tour in South America and Arsenal striker Dennis Bergkamp will also miss the match because of his fear of flying.</p>
<p>Squad:</p>
<p>Goalkeepers: Ed de Goey (Feyenoord), Ruud Hesp (Roda JC).</p>
<p>Defenders: Michael Reiziger (AC Milan), Johan de Kock (Schalke 04), Arthur Numan (PSV), Ferdy Vierklau (Vitesse).</p>
<p>Midfielders: Wim Jonk, Philip Cocu (PSV), Giovanni van Bronckhorst, Jean-Paul van Gastel (Feyenoord), Aron Winter (Inter Milan), Clarence Seedorf (Real Madrid).</p>
<p>Strikers: Roy Makaay (Vitesse), John Bosman (Twente), Boudewijn Zenden (PSV) Pierre van Hooijdonk (Nottingham Forest).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
