<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608434" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: SOCCER-RONALDO HOPES FOR STYLISH LEAGUE SWANSONG.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-RONALDO HOPES FOR STYLISH LEAGUE SWANSONG.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ronaldo hopes to sign off from a memorable first season in Spanish soccer with a bang on Saturday as he plays what may be his last league game for Barcelona before returning to Brazil to join the national side.</p>
<p>The 20-year-old striker could hardly have chosen a better stage. His club faces Deportivo Coruna in a game that could well decide Spain's second European Cup place for next season.</p>
<p>With four games left to play, leaders Real Madrid are currently five points ahead of Barcelona, with Deportivo seven points further back.</p>
<p>The game comes after a week in which the Brazilian uncharacteristically lashed out at refereeing that he believes to be pro-Real.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing's changed. (Real) Madrid are still favoured by the referees,&quot; said Ronaldo in reference to the award of a disputed penalty against Valladolid during their 1-0 defeat at Real.</p>
<p>The comments drew a swift response from Real players, but at the same time struck a chord amongst Spanish fans who have harboured the same suspicions for generations.</p>
<p>Normally Ronaldo lets his feet do the talking.</p>
<p>His 33 goals already this season put him far ahead in both the Spanish goalscoring table and in the European leagues' Golden Boot competition.</p>
<p>Ronaldo's goals -- and the sensational way in which he has scored them -- made him FIFA's player of the year and have drawn attention from big-spending Italian and English clubs.</p>
<p>Although Ronaldo could stay on in Spain for the next league game with Hercules and is likely to return to Spain for June 28's Cup final with Real Betis, it is by no means certain he will return to Barcelona next season.</p>
<p>An ideal swansong for would be a win over Deportivo, a side with six Brazilian players.</p>
<p>For the visitors -- who will be reinforced by the return of star midfielder Rivaldo from suspension -- the game will provide a chance for them to repay some of the grief caused by Barcelona in the 1993-94 season.</p>
<p>Deportivo saw the championship snatched from them at the last gasp three years ago, but a win on Saturday would leave them still with a chance of reaching their first European Cup competition.</p>
<p>A draw would benefit neither side, and would instead all but hand Real Madrid their 27th Spanish title.</p>
<p>A Barcelona victory would put pressure on Real, who travel to Athletic Bilbao the following evening without suspended strikers Davor Suker and Predrag Mijatovic and with teenage sensation Raul Gonzalez doubtful because of injury.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
