<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608437" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: TENNIS-IVANISEVIC CRAMMING FOR FRENCH OPEN.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-IVANISEVIC CRAMMING FOR FRENCH OPEN.</headline>
<byline>Steve Keating</byline>
<dateline>DUESSELDORF, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Like a student studying for a big exam, Goran Ivanisevic has spent this week at the World Team Cup cramming for the French Open.</p>
<p>The hard serving Croatian was the first man on the court on Wednesday morning and the last one off in the evening playing two doubles matches, a singles and a total of six sets. A day earlier the world number four began the eight-nation tournament by playing in two matches and five sets.</p>
<p>&quot;This tournament is great preparation for the French and when you beat a French Open champion and one of the best clay court players in the world like Michael Chang, it gives you confidence,&quot; said Ivanisevic, twice a winner this season. &quot;I feel good and I'm playing well.&quot;</p>
<p>So well in fact, that Ivanisevic, with each match, is looking more-and-more as if he could be the man to beat when play begins at the French Open on Monday.</p>
<p>Indeed, if not for a broken finger that sidelined him for three weeks in the middle of the European clay court season he might be the odds on favourite heading into Paris, based on his current form.</p>
<p>Returning from the injury 10 days ago, the hard-serving Croat powered his way into the semifinals at Italian Open before losing to eventual champion Alex Corretja of Spain.</p>
<p>At the World Team Cup he has won all his matches, with the exception of a doubles clash with the U.S., including an impressive a three-set decision over world number two and 1989 French champion Chang.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm surprised by my play,&quot; said Ivanisevic, who broke the middle digit in his right hand when he jammed it in a door. &quot;Everything looks under control and I'm looking forward to Roland Garros, it's wide open.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it is the most wide open Roland Garros ever.&quot;</p>
<p>Ivanisevic had thought the unscheduled layoff would seriously harm his buildup to Roland Garros but in his absence no one has stepped forward to dominate the clay court campaign.</p>
<p>Thomas Muster, long regarded as the King of Clay, has not won on the surface this season.</p>
<p>World number one Pete Sampras has yet to win a match on clay this year and had to pull out of the World Team Cup this week with a thigh strain.</p>
<p>Number two, Chang, a finalist in 1995, has also struggled on the slow surface, losing in the first round in Rome and Atlanta.</p>
<p>Defending champion Yevgeny Kafelnikov has not been as successful as Ivanisevic at fighting his way back from a similar injury while Andre Agassi, Boris Becker, Todd Martin and Michael Stich have all pulled out of the event with various aches and pains.</p>
<p>&quot;The break was welcome after a gruelling indoor season,&quot; said Ivanisevic, who has reached the finals twice at Wimbledon but never advanced past the quarter-finals at the French Open. &quot;But you can't read too much into these results.</p>
<p>&quot;Two years ago I came here won every match, was having a great clay court season then went to the French Open and lost in the first round.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel good and I'm playing well but I don't want to put too much pressure on myself.</p>
<p>&quot;The French Open starts Monday and it's a different world.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUESSELDORF, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
