<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608441" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-THE TALE OF LIPPI AND THE OLD LADY.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-THE TALE OF LIPPI AND THE OLD LADY.</headline>
<byline>Alan Baldwin</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>When Marcello Lippi became coach of Juventus three years ago, he immediately went to visit his father's tomb in his home town of Viareggio.</p>
<p>Salvatore Lippi had died three years previously, at a time when his son had been fired as coach of Cesena and was out of work.</p>
<p>&quot;I know that you never liked this team (Juventus) because you considered it the symbol of power,&quot; the coach whispered at the graveside.</p>
<p>&quot;But wait and see. You will be pleased by the signature I gave today,&quot; he added, narrating the tale in a new book &quot;My soccer, my Juve&quot; out this month in Italy.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that if he could reply to me today, the old man would have agreed.&quot;</p>
<p>Fans of the club who are on course to celebrate their 100th anniversary this year with the Italian, European and world club titles, certainly have no doubts.</p>
<p>Lippi, a former player for the Communist-organised Red Star Viareggio boys' team, is happily wed to a club that has for the best part of a century been the symbol of Italian capitalism, owned by the Agnellis of Turin car giant Fiat.</p>
<p>The chants of &quot;Marcello Lippi&quot; echo around the huge Stadio delle Alpi in Turin at every match and are sure to be heard in Munich next Wednesday when holders Juventus play Borussia Dortmund in their second European Cup final in two years.</p>
<p>The arrival of the now 49-year-old former Sampdoria libero has ushered in an era of extraordinary success at the club nicknamed &quot;La Vecchia Signora&quot; (The Old Lady).</p>
<p>In his first season in charge, after persuading a disenchanted Gianluca Vialli not to leave, Lippi took Juventus to the league title, Italian Cup and UEFA Cup final.</p>
<p>In his second, they won the European Cup and Italian Supercoppa clash between champions and cup winners.</p>
<p>In his third season, they have won the Intercontinental Cup and have their 24th league title virtually sewn up.</p>
<p>Wednesday could see them complete the treble.</p>
<p>His staggering success has virtually made redundant the need to vote for the best coach in Italy -- there has been no competition.</p>
<p>Not bad for a man from a poor family who left school at 16 and never made the national team.</p>
<p>So what makes up &quot;Lippismo&quot;, a term already coined by Italians to define the secret of his success?</p>
<p>The answer seems to be a subtle mixture of patience, pragmatism and a mastery of team psychology.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that the indispensable requirements to succeed on technical and tactical, athletic and sporting levels is a calm state of mind,&quot; he says in his book.</p>
<p>Lippi's training methods are seen as among the toughest in serie A and are based on personal training systems tailor-made to each player's requirements rather than to the team as a whole.</p>
<p>A family man, married to Simonetta and with a daughter Stefania and son Davide, Lippi rarely hangs around after matches and prefers instead to drive straight home to Viareggio on the Tuscan coast where he was born and grew up.</p>
<p>As a player, he played for Sampdoria from 1970 to 1980, and ended his career at serie B Pistoiese and serie C Lucchese, before returning to Sampdoria as youth coach.</p>
<p>He moved to minor league club Pontedera as coach and then Siena, Pistoiese and Carrarese before his big break in 1989 when first division Cesena approached him.</p>
<p>He took them to 12th in serie A in his first season, turning down an offer from Atalanta at the end of it, but was then sacked the following year as the team floundered.</p>
<p>Lippi claims the main problem that season was the arrival of Brazilian Silas, who was not accepted by a group of players, and which led to dressing-room tensions.</p>
<p>Lucchese gave him a job the next season in serie B from where he moved to Atalanta and Napoli in serie A, taking the unfancied Neapolitans into the UEFA Cup.</p>
<p>Juventus general manager Luciano Moggi is from Naples and knew straight away that this was the man for him.</p>
<p>In his early days as a coach, Lippi was deeply superstitious and used to wear the same light suit, tie, jeans and moccasins at every match, regardless of the weather.</p>
<p>It is one habit he has now abandoned, but Dortmund should be aware of another that provides an insight into the remarkable Juve team spirit.</p>
<p>&quot;Before the start, I go into the players' room and there we celebrate what is perhaps the only collective ritual,&quot; he explains in his book. &quot;We hug each other and then all reply to the shout that the captain gives us.</p>
<p>&quot;What kind of a shout it is is a changing room secret and I'm afraid I cannot reveal what it is.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
