<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608418" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: MOTOR RACING-ALESI QUICKEST AS BENETTON RECOVER.</title>
<headline>MOTOR RACING-ALESI QUICKEST AS BENETTON RECOVER.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Collings</byline>
<dateline>BARCELONA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Frenchman Jean Alesi, much maligned after a poor start to the year with Benetton, bounced back by clocking the fastest time in Friday's opening free practice sessions for Sunday's Spanish Grand Prix.</p>
<p>Alesi, in his Renault-powered car, clocked a best time of one minute 19.566 seconds on the Circuit de Catalunya to raise hopes of his first podium finish of the year.</p>
<p>In hot conditions -- the track temperature was 37 degrees Celsius -- he was just two-tenths of a second quicker than his nearest pursuant Jacques Villeneuve of Canada in a Williams.</p>
<p>For Alesi, under pressure with Benetton and linked to the new Prost team in widespread paddock rumours, it was a relief to enjoy some long-awaited success.</p>
<p>&quot;We worked through a very good programme of testing last week here at this circuit and it has paid off,&quot; he said. &quot;We did not have the same problems we had elsewhere and, if we can keep this up in qualifying on Saturday, I will be very confident for the race.&quot;</p>
<p>Alesi's Benetton team mate Gerhard Berger of Austria also enjoyed much-improved fortunes after his desultory Monaco Grand Prix performance and he clocked the fifth fastest time of the day.</p>
<p>&quot;We have had a lot of trouble with tyre temperatures and we seem to have overcome this today,&quot; he said. &quot;But we shall have to wait and see if we are as competitive again in qualifying.&quot;</p>
<p>Both men were almost outshone for effort and enthusiasm, however, by the youth of the Jordan Peugeot team as German Ralf Schumacher, 21, and Italian Giancarlo Fisichella, 24, took third and fourth positions on the overnight practice grid.</p>
<p>Schumacher, developing a reputation for raw courage and raw speed, said: &quot;I am satisfied. There are no big problems but we need to make some improvement to both ends of the car.</p>
<p>&quot;But I am more familiar with this circuit than I have been with others and that makes it easier for me. It also gives me more confidence.&quot;</p>
<p>Fisichella, who has developed a healthy and competitive duel with Schumacher within the team this year, also indicated that he could go faster. After scoring points in the last two races, the young Italian said: &quot;I was held up by traffic on my last run, so I could have gone faster.&quot;</p>
<p>Villeneuve said his car felt strange compared to the way it worked in the winter during testing and attributed this to the much hotter weather.</p>
<p>He said the team were making adjustments to solve his problems and he remained confident of finishing well to score points for the first time in three races and reviving his challenge to Michael Schumacher, of Ferrari, in the drivers' championship.</p>
<p>The older Schumacher, twice world champion, was seventh fastest behind Briton David Coulthard in a McLaren and ahead of Johnny Herbert of Britain in a Sauber.</p>
<p>Herbert's new team mate Gianni Morbidelli of Italy, making his debut with the team after ousting compatriot Nicola Larini from the seat, suffered an embarrassing crash when he lost control of his car as he exited the pit lane.</p>
<p>&quot;I accelerated too hard and spun across the track into the wall opposite. It was my mistake,&quot; he said. &quot;I'm okay but I feel very bad to have damaged the car this way.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BARCELONA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
