<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608436" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-INTER REJECT HODGSON RESIGNATION, NEWSPAPER SAYS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-INTER REJECT HODGSON RESIGNATION, NEWSPAPER SAYS.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Beaten UEFA Cup finalists Internazionale Milan have rejected an immediate resignation offer from their departing English coach Roy Hodgson, an Italian newspaper reported on Friday.</p>
<p>Hodgson, who will manage English premier league Blackburn next season, was reported to have offered his resignation to Inter owner Massimo Moratti 24 hours after Inter lost the UEFA Cup final to German club Schalke in a penalty shoot-out at the San Siro on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But the sports daily Gazetta Dello Sport quoted Moratti as saying: &quot;I reassured him (Hodgson) of my faith in his abilities and I hope that his sense of discouragement will pass and that he will lead Inter in our last two games of the season, two games which can gain us Champions' League (European Cup) qualification.&quot;</p>
<p>Nonetheless, Inter spokesman Sandro Sabatini said on Friday it was still not clear whether Hodgson would withdraw his resignation and lead the team through to the end of the season.</p>
<p>With Juventus needing just a point to clinch the league title on Friday evening, Inter were third in the table, eight points behind the leaders and two behind second-placed Parma. They could still overtake Parma to clinch second place and a European Cup berth.</p>
<p>On Sunday Inter are at home to Napoli while on the last day of the season, June 1, they are away to Bologna.</p>
<p>Hodgson's resignation offer appeared to be a symbolic gesture since the English coach decided long ago he would leave Inter, announcing at the end of February that he would move to former premier league champions Blackburn at the end of the season.</p>
<p>Although Inter have had a successful season, reaching the UEFA Cup final and always in the top flight in Serie A, Hodgson has not enjoyed a happy relationship with fans, media and senior figures within the club.</p>
<p>On Wednesday night, fans pelted him with coins and cigarette lighters as he left the pitch. He had also had a brief but very public altercation with Inter's Argentine midfielder Javier Zanetti, who resented being substituted in the dying minutes of extra time.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm sorry that the fans consider Hodgson the guilty party, I think they exaggerated,&quot; Moratti said.</p>
<p>&quot;I know Hodgson well, he doesn't deserve such a mortification.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
