<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608470" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: UHIS TO ISSUE 800 MLN KROONS IN BONDS.</title>
<headline>UHIS TO ISSUE 800 MLN KROONS IN BONDS.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Uhispank will sign an agreement on June 2 with its western partners under which it issues 800 million kroons in bonds, it said on Friday.</p>
<p>The bonds will be quoted on the Luxembourg bourse and the amount of the first issue is 240 million kroons with a maturity of three years, it added in a statement.  </p>
<p>The bonds will be issued as part of the programme which enables Uhispank to borrow through the Luxembourg bourse according to its requirements.</p>
<p>The programme will be indefinite, but is renewable on an annual basis. The borrowing limits could be further increased in one year's time.</p>
<p>The interest charged on the first issue of 240 million kroons is the most favourable provided so far for the local commercial banks. The interest rate will be disclosed upon the signing of agreement.</p>
<p>On the Luxembourg bourse, the bonds will be brokered by major international banks and financial institutions, such as ABN Amro Hoare Govett, Chace Manhattan Bank AG, Chase Manhattan International Ltd, Merril Lynch International, Merita Bank Ltd and Nomura International, the bank said.</p>
<p>With fresh funds Uhispank plans to refinance its more expensive loans and direct additional means for the development of the bank's loan facilities.</p>
<p>-- Tallinn Newsroom, +372 630 8400, reuters@reuters.ee</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
