<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608413" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: TENNIS-PHILIPPOUSSIS BLASTS AUSTRALIA INTO FINAL.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-PHILIPPOUSSIS BLASTS AUSTRALIA INTO FINAL.</headline>
<byline>Steve Keating</byline>
<dateline>DUESSELDORF, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mark Philippoussis won the battle of the big serves over Goran Ivanisevic on Friday, blasting Australia into the finals of the World Team Cup.</p>
<p>The 3-0 win over Croatia left Australia on top of the Red Group standings after completion of their round-robin play and pushed them into the finals for the sixth time.</p>
<p>Australia, who have won the title only once, in 1979, will meet the winner of the Blue Group, either Spain or the Netherlands, in Sunday's final.</p>
<p>Philippoussis showed why his name is suddenly being mentioned among the favourites for the French Open as he out-aced Ivanisevic 14-0, overwhelming the world number four 6-1 6-2 in just 45 minutes.</p>
<p>&quot;I served the best I have in any of my matches here but I didn't do anything special,&quot; said Philippoussis. &quot;If I looked like a God out there today it was Goran who made me look like one.&quot;</p>
<p>With the French Open set to begin on Monday, Philippoussis is proving to be more than a strong arm and good looks.</p>
<p>The lanky Australian, who has become the leading heart-throb among female tennis fans, has demonstrated he is capable of adapting his power game to the slower surface, having claimed the first clay court title of his career three weeks ago in Munich with a win over Alex Corretja.</p>
<p>&quot;I think my chances are good,&quot; assessed Philippoussis, a second round loser last year in his first visit to the Paris grand slam event. &quot;There's no reason I can't play well on clay, I think I've shown already that I can.</p>
<p>&quot;Roland Garros is a little quicker and that suits me more.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't consider myself a favourite for Paris, even after my good results here, but I believe I can do some damage there.&quot;</p>
<p>After what had been a promising buildup to the French Open, Ivanisevic heads to Paris on a down note.</p>
<p>Sidelined for three weeks with a broken finger, he  made a successful return to competition 10 days ago, reaching the semifinals at the Italian Open.</p>
<p>He had continued to show good form at the World Team Cup, beating world number two and 1989 French champion Michael Chang of the United States, until his clash with Philippoussis.</p>
<p>&quot;He served well but not great,&quot; said Ivanisevic. &quot;I felt like a junior out there, he was serving 205, 206, 207kph and I'm serving 174, 175.</p>
<p>&quot;You have days when you're here and days when you're not. Today I wasn't here.</p>
<p>&quot;It was just a bad day.&quot;</p>
<p>Todd Woodbridge secured Australia's place in the final with 6-4 6-1 win over Sasa Hirszon.</p>
<p>Woodbridge and Mark Woodforde, the world's top ranked doubles team, then closed out the tie with 6-2 7-5 win over Ivanisevic and Hirszon.</p>
<p>The day began with a Red Group match left over from Thursday, Paul Haarhuis and Jacco Eltingh beating Magnus Larsson and Nicklas Kulti 6-2 6-3 in the doubles rubber to give the Netherlands a 2-1 win over Sweden and set up a showdown with Spain on Saturday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUESSELDORF, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
