<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608426" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-ITALIAN SERIE A FIXTURES THIS WEEKEND.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-ITALIAN SERIE A FIXTURES THIS WEEKEND.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Serie A matches scheduled for Sunday (league positions in parentheses, all kick-off times 1430 GMT):</p>
<p>Cagliari (14) v Sampdoria (5)</p>
<p>Cagliari are involved in a three-way relegation battle with Piacenza and Perugia while Sampdoria are in a three-way UEFA Cup tussle with Bologna and Udinese. Both sides will be close to full strength with Sandro Tovalieri and Roberto Muzzi leading the Cagliari attack and Vicenzo Montella and Roberto Mancini on duty up front for Sampdoria.</p>
<p>Fiorentina (11) v Reggiana (18)</p>
<p>With Fiorentina out of the UEFA Cup race and with Reggiana already relegated, this match counts for little. Argentine Gabriel Batistuta, at the centre of media speculation that he will leave Fiorentina, leads the attack, while Russian Igor Simutenkov leads the Reggiana front line.</p>
<p>Internazionale (3) v Napoli (13)</p>
<p>Inter need all three points to retain their outside chance of overtaking second-placed Parma to qualify for the Champions' League. Napoli need three points to be mathematically certain of avoiding relegation. Massimiliano Esposito and Nicola Caccia lead the Napoli attack while Inter's probable formation remains a mystery until it becomes clear whether the club's English coach Roy Hodgson will withdraw his resignation, offered on Thursday and rejected by the club.</p>
<p>Lazio (4) v Verona (17)</p>
<p>This should be easy for Lazio, all but mathematically certain of winning a UEFA spot. Verona have already been relegated. Igor Protti steps in for the suspended Pierluigi Marchegiani alongside Giuseppe Signori in the Lazio attack, while Filippo Maniero and Nicola Zanini go through the motions for the Verona attack.</p>
<p>Parma (2) v Bologna (6)</p>
<p>Parma need four points from their final two games to be sure of a Champions' League spot as runners-up, while Bologna are in the thick of a UEFA Cup tussle with Sampdoria and Udinese. Parma are at full strength with Enrico Chiesa and Argentine Hernan Crespo in attack, while Bologna will be without suspended Swedish striker Kennet Andersson, due to be replaced by 19-year-old Marco Schenardi alongside Davide Fontolan.</p>
<p>Perugia (16) v Roma (10)</p>
<p>Perugia are likely to be the more motivated here since they are still fighting a tremendous relegation battle with Cagliari and Piacenza, with all three sides on 34 points and with two of them seemingly destined for relegation. Roma, on the other hand, are out of the UEFA race and have only pride to play for. Dutchman Michel Kreek, Croat Milan Rapajic and Marco Negri lead the Perugia attack, while Roma will be without injured Argentine striker Abel Balbo and will look to Francesco Totti and Marco Delvecchio in his absence.</p>
<p>Udinese (7) v Piacenza (15)</p>
<p>Yet another game likely to prove decisive for the UEFA prospects of one side or the relegation prospects of the other. Udinese have the same points as Bologna, only one behind Sampdoria, and badly want the points to clinch a first-ever European qualification. Piacenza need the points in their three-way relegation battle with Perugia and Cagliari, all on 34 points. Udinese field all their big guns, with German Oliver Bierhoff, Paolo Poggi and Brazilian Amoroso leading the attack. All-Italian Piacenza look to Pasquale Luiso and Gian Pietro Piovani.</p>
<p>Vicenza (8) v AC Milan (9)</p>
<p>Both these sides are theoretically still in the UEFA Cup race but by Sunday evening both are likely to be out, despite the result of their own encounter. Roberto Baggio is out of the Milan side through injury, leaving Frenchman Christophe Dugarry to partner Liberian George Weah in attack. Vicenza, without injured Uruguyan Marcelo Otero, will be led by Roberto Murgita and Gabriele Ambrosetti.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
