<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608465" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: POLAND PRESSES FOR PLACE ON RUSSIA-NATO COUNCIL.</title>
<headline>POLAND PRESSES FOR PLACE ON RUSSIA-NATO COUNCIL.</headline>
<byline>Marcin Grajewski</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland on Friday underlined that it should have a place in a joint council between NATO and Russia which Moscow and the pact are to set up under a security accord to be signed next week.</p>
<p>&quot;Poland should be present whenever there are talks about relations between itself and NATO. We will strive for membership (in the council),&quot; Foreign Minister Dariusz Rosati told a news conference in Warsaw.</p>
<p>Some Polish politicians fear that if the council were confined to NATO and Russia, Moscow -- a vehement critic of the alliance's eastward expansion, would be closer to the pact than countries negotiating to join it and could slow the process.</p>
<p>Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary -- the former Soviet bloc's leaders in market reforms -- are expected to be recruited to NATO at its Madrid summit in July.</p>
<p>But Rosati said Poland, despite reservations about the Russia-NATO council, was looking forward to the signing of the so-called the Founding Act by President Boris Yeltsin and leaders of the 16 NATO countries in Paris on May 27.</p>
<p>&quot;By signing the document, Russia in fact agrees to the expansion of NATO,&quot; he said. &quot;The agreement will help reduce tensions in Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>He added that the agreement, which puts behind the Cold War past by defining new peaceful relations between Moscow and NATO, will calm Western fears of upsetting Russia and pave the way for the 16 countries legislatures to ratify enlargement.</p>
<p>&quot;This will positively influence the process of ratification of our NATO membership,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Russia-NATO accord provides for Moscow to have a say in matters directly affecting its security.</p>
<p>Moscow says it also offers binding guarantees that NATO will not build up its forces on the territory of new members and that the alliance will not base nuclear weapons there.</p>
<p>But Rosati said the agreement, the full planned text of which he knew, would in no way infringe Poland's rights as a future NATO member.</p>
<p>&quot;I can say with great satisfaction that the document does not limit our rights...and sets no preliminary conditions for our entry,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Rosati also said Poland fully supported efforts by Romania and Slovenia to be included among the first NATO entrants.</p>
<p>&quot;Poland is of the opinion that the more countries are in the first wave of new members, the better,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said it was fortunate that the presidents of Poland, Ukraine and Baltic republics would hold a summit in Tallinn, Estonia, on Tuesday, when the Paris agreement is to be signed.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a coincidence, but a most fortunate one. We will be able to send a positive signal,&quot; he said. -- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
