<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608420" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: SOCCER SHOWCASE-INJURED MATTHAEUS TO MISS BUNDESLIGA FINALE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER SHOWCASE-INJURED MATTHAEUS TO MISS BUNDESLIGA FINALE.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Warner</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bayern Munich face the last two games of the tight German championship race without libero and captain Lothar Matthaeus.</p>
<p>The 36-year-old former World Cup captain announced after training on Friday that he had no chance of being fit for Saturday's important home clash with VfB Stuttgart and next week's game at Borussia Moenchengladbach because of a thigh strain.</p>
<p>&quot;I wanted to play a part in the final run-in but it's going to be too much for me,&quot; Germany's most-capped international said.</p>
<p>&quot;I tried but my body won't play ball. The season is over for me. I'm bitterly disappointed to miss the finale after such a good season.&quot;</p>
<p>Bayern take on Stuttgart in the south German derby with just a one-point lead over their rivals Bayer Leverkusen who visit Cologne on Saturday.</p>
<p>The Bavarians could clinch a record 14th Bundesliga title if they beat Stuttgart and Leverkusen slip up at Cologne. Matthaeus is confident that the team can survive without his control at the back.</p>
<p>&quot;They survived without me in the victory in Rostock (last weekend),&quot; said Matthaeus who strained a muscle in his right thigh in a friendly match on May 6. &quot;The team is strong enough that they can play without their captain.&quot;</p>
<p>German international defender Thomas Helmer is expected to step into the libero role.</p>
<p>Stuttgart will be weakened by the loss of former World Cup defender Thomas Berthold who is suspended. But coach Joachim Loew can welcome back midfielder Andreas Buck from injury and defender Marco Haber after suspension.</p>
<p>All the 63,000 tickets for the game in Munich's Olympic stadium have been sold -- the 10th time this season that Bayern have enjoyed a capacity crowd.</p>
<p>Bayern's often controversial midfielder Mario Basler is so confident that the Bavarians will win the championship that he says he is prepared to bet serious money on the title coming to Munich for the third time in the 1990s.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be all over by Sunday,&quot; the German international said confidently. &quot;We are going to beat Stuttgart. That's 100 percent certain. And Leverkusen will lose against Cologne.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
