<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608455" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: BLUE CHIPS EXTEND RECENT MODEST GAINS.</title>
<headline>BLUE CHIPS EXTEND RECENT MODEST GAINS.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>* Total turnover slipped to 93,000 lats against 101,000 lats.</p>
<p>* Rietumu index closed up 2.12pct to 187.29. It grew 6.74 percent during the week.</p>
<p>* Most official list shares extended gains, Unibanka jumped to 3.30 lats from 3.21 lats on turnover of 20,900 lats.</p>
<p>* Valmiera Glassfibre led the secondary list on trade of 15,000 lats as it 1,55 lats from 1,49 lats.</p>
<p>Leading stocks on the Riga bourse extended price gains on Friday as investors were seen switching from vouchers to stocks, dealers said.</p>
<p>Total turnover slipped to 93,000 lats against 101,000 lats and Rietumu index closed up 2.12 percent to 187.29.</p>
<p>It grew 6.74 percent during the week.</p>
<p>&quot;The recent correction seems to have bottomed out as prices have been grwoing since Tuesday, showing the upward trend was here to stay,&quot; Robert Idelsons, Trasta Bank's securities department head, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The recovery was generated mainly by local funds, switching from vouchers into stocks,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;Foreign investors, who were waiting for the growth to pick up again, could return next week,&quot; Idelsons said.</p>
<p>Most official list shares extended gains.</p>
<p>Unibanka jumped to 3.30 lats from 3.21 lats on turnover of 20,900 lats.</p>
<p>Staburadze rose to 2.70 lats from 2.57 lats on turnover of 7,500 lats.</p>
<p>&quot;This price is close to Staburadze's current ceiling if compared to its potential,&quot; Trasta Idelsons said.</p>
<p>Valmiera Glassfibre led the secondary list on trade of 15,000 lats as it rose to 1.55 lats from 1.49 lats.</p>
<p>-- Riga newsroom, +371 721 52 40</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
