<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608448" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: DUIKER UP FURTHER AS LONRHO REAFFIRMS TALKS.</title>
<headline>DUIKER UP FURTHER AS LONRHO REAFFIRMS TALKS.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in Duiker Mining Ltd, a coal firm in the Lonrho Plc stable, continued their recent surge on Friday after a further cautionary notice that Lonrho and South African mining house JCI Ltd were in talks. </p>
<p>By 0810 GMT Duiker shares had leapt seven percent or 70 cents to 10.70 rand, building on its run this week which has seen it gain over 30 percent since last Friday.</p>
<p>Lonrho and JCI said on Friday they were still in preliminary talks to indentify any benefits from combining the two groups.</p>
<p>This follows confirmation on Monday that they were in talks on a possible merger which could create a mining company with market capitalisation of more than $3 billion.</p>
<p>The two companies on Friday warned their shareholders and that of Duiker Mining Ltd and Tweefontein United Collieries Ltd , whose only investment is a holding in Duiker, to exercise caution in their share dealings.</p>
<p>JCI recently enlarged its Tavistock coal division with the acquisition of Royal Dutch/Shell's South African coal business.</p>
<p>Tweefontein shares also gained, rising almost 10 percent to 160 rand in thin volume of 100 shares.  </p>
<p>&quot;The cautionary just reaffirms that (JCI and Lonrho) are seriously talking to each other and that the coal side is part of the deal,&quot; a dealer on the Johannesburg Stock Exchange said.</p>
<p>However, South African-listed shares in Lonrho pulled back 20 cents to 10.55 rand in what dealers said was a small retracement after a good run this week.</p>
<p>&quot;JCI initially went up on Monday but came off after that. Lonrho looks like its just retracing down in line with JCI,&quot; a dealer said. </p>
<p>Another said the bulk of volume in Lonrho had been in three foreign deals overnight.</p>
<p>    JCI was last off five cents at 41.45 rand.    </p>
<p>-- Nicole Mordant, Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
