<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608429" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: SOCCER-FRENCH LEAGUE PROGRAMME ON SATURDAY.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-FRENCH LEAGUE PROGRAMME ON SATURDAY.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Programme of matches in the French first division on Saturday, the final day of the league season (standings in parentheses, all kick-offs 1800 GMT):</p>
<p>Monaco (1) v Nantes (2)</p>
<p>If Nantes win they will qualify along with champions Monaco for the European Champions' League. Any other result will give Paris St Germain a chance to snatch back second place. Monaco have striker Anderson and defender Gilles Grimandi doubtful, while Enzo Scifo, Martin Djetou and Marco Grassi are out with injuries. For Nantes, Jean-Michel Ferri is injured.</p>
<p>Paris St Germain (3) v Strasbourg (5)</p>
<p>PSG depend on the result of Nantes' visit to Monaco but anything less than victory will probably leave them with the minor prize of a UEFA Cup place. PSG captain Rai is doubtful with thigh problem. Czech defender Jan Suchoparek is doubtful for Strasbourg.</p>
<p>Rennes (16) v Bastia (8)</p>
<p>The Corsicans, with defender Sebastien Perez back from suspension, can snatch a UEFA Cup berth if other results go their way. Rennes are difficult to beat at home where they have lost only twice all season.</p>
<p>Auxerre (7) v Nice (20)</p>
<p>Relegated French Cup winners Nice should be too weak for outgoing champions Auxerre who must win to stand any chance of qualifying for the UEFA Cup. For Auxerre, winger Bernard Diomede returns from suspension while Steve Marlet and Alain Goma are back after injury. Nice defender Olivier Fugen is suspended.</p>
<p>Metz (6) v Lille (18)</p>
<p>Currently occupying the third of France's three UEFA Cup berths, Metz, with midfielder Didier Lang back from suspension, cannot afford to lose as they could well cede that place to Auxerre or Bastia who are one point behind. Relegated Lille will be looking to go three games without defeat.</p>
<p>Le Havre (14) v Bordeaux (4)</p>
<p>Bordeaux, with full backs Patrick Colleter and Cyril Domoraud still unavailable, are in a good position to qualify for the UEFA Cup but cannot take it for granted as defeat could let in other teams. Midfielder Nicoals Huysman is back for Le Havre, unbeaten in last four games.</p>
<p>Lyon (9) v Marseille (10)</p>
<p>Marseille's last chance to ensure they do not complete the season without an away victory. They will be without suspended striker Xavier Gravelaine. Lyon, with 17-goal striker Alain Caveglia back after suspension, have an outside chance of snatching a UEFA Cup place if other results go their way.</p>
<p>Lens (13) v Caen (17)</p>
<p>Relegated Caen have scored five goals in their last two matches. Lens have won three and lost two of their last five games.</p>
<p>Cannes (15) v Nancy (19)</p>
<p>Relegated Nancy have Ireland striker Tony Cascarino back from international duty, while Cannes have five players doubtful with injuries.</p>
<p>Montpellier (11) v Guingamp (12)</p>
<p>Guingamp have a string of players unavailable through injury or international duty, including Poland defender Marek Jozwiak. But they welcome Monaco-bound playmaker Stephane Carnot and captain Richard Lecomte back from injury. Montpellier's veteran Franck Sauzee and Marseille-bound Serge Blanc are out with injuries.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MONAC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
