<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608442" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: SOCCER-TALE OF TWO SEASONS NOT LOST ON LAMBERT.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-TALE OF TWO SEASONS NOT LOST ON LAMBERT.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gray</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>This time last year, Paul Lambert was relaxing after another season with Motherwell in his native Scotland.</p>
<p>&quot;We'd just finished the season and we'd just managed to stay in the premier division. It was a big relief,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Now, Lambert is a Borussia Dortmund regular looking forward to a mouth-watering European Cup final against Juventus in Munich's Olympic Stadium.</p>
<p>The contrast between struggling against the drop in one of Europe's less glamorous leagues and playing for the biggest prize in continental club soccer just a year later is not lost on the midfielder.</p>
<p>&quot;It's unbelievable,&quot; said the 27-year-old, who arrived in Dortmund as a virtual unknown on a free transfer last summer.</p>
<p>At a club which had just been crowned German champions for the second successive time and was bursting with big-name stars, the signing of the Scot with only a couple of caps to his name was viewed with some surprise by both supporters and players.</p>
<p>But the former St Mirren man scored on his Bundesliga debut and hasn't looked back.</p>
<p>He took advantage of a series of injuries in the Dortmund side to establish himself in a defensive midfield role. Although stars like Portuguese midfielder Paulo Sousa recovered fitness, coach Ottmar Hitzfeld made sure Lambert stayed in the side.</p>
<p>&quot;He's a player you can always rely on and, above all, he's excellent when it comes to winning 50-50 balls,&quot; said Thomas Dieckhoff, a sports journalist on the local Westdeutsche Allgemeine Zeitung newspaper who follows Borussia.</p>
<p>In a heavy industrial area with few pretensions, players who work hard and give their all for the team are warmly received.</p>
<p>&quot;Although he plays fairly inconspicuously, he's also popular with the fans,&quot; Dieckhoff confirmed.</p>
<p>Supporters dressed in the distinctive black and bright yellow Dortmund shirt with Lambert's name and number 14 are now a common sight at the club's Westfalen Stadium.</p>
<p>When Lambert first heard Dortmund were interested in signing him, he jumped at the chance.</p>
<p>&quot;He knew the stadium from playing here in the UEFA Cup with Motherwell and he was very enthusiastic,&quot; Dortmund press spokesman Josef Schneck said.</p>
<p>&quot;He fitted in well with the team immediately and he's very highly regarded both within the side and by the fans,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;He's played almost every game for Dortmund this season -- and when he hasn't it's normally because he's been playing for the Scottish national side,&quot; Dieckhoff added.</p>
<p>Never more than a squad player for his country before the move to Dortmund, Lambert has now become a first-team regular. At Motherwell, he was always going to struggle in a country where the domestic focus is firmly on the two Glasgow giants.</p>
<p>&quot;If you're not playing for Rangers or Celtic, then you're never seen and you don't get picked,&quot; said Lambert, who has retained his strong Scottish accent despite a year away from home. &quot;Maybe that's a wee bit wrong but that's the way it is.&quot;</p>
<p>Coach Craig Brown deployed him to particularly good effect against Austria last month when he marked playmaker Andreas Herzog out of the game -- a task he had performed with similar aplomb when Dortmund played Werder Bremen earlier in the season.</p>
<p>Lambert feels he has improved through playing alongside the likes of Sousa and German international Andy Moeller.</p>
<p>&quot;They're brilliant,&quot; he said. &quot;You don't realise how good they are until you play with them.&quot;</p>
<p>Victory over Juventus would be the crowing glory in a great season for the player, who is by no means overawed at the prospect of taking on a team widely regarded as the best club side in Europe at the moment.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't bother me who we're up against,&quot; he said. &quot;It's just one team against another.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
