<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608528" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: ICO consumer, producer states end talks.</title>
<headline>ICO consumer, producer states end talks.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Major coffee exporting and consuming states on Friday wrapped up their week-long talks, which were overshadowed by Wednesday's decision by key producers to extend their export quotas for 12 more months.</p>
<p>Delegates to the International Coffee Organization's (ICO) bi-annual council meeting said discussions at the producer-consumer group centred on routine administrative matters.</p>
<p>The ICO is basically a producer-consumer consultative body aimed at promoting the development of the coffee sector.</p>
<p>But outside the conference room, the main talking point was the Association of Coffee Producing Countries' (ACPC) decision to stick to their quota programme despite the present rally in the world market on supply tightness.</p>
<p>The ACPC, also London-based, was created as a result of the institutional vacuum left by the collapse of the previous International Coffee Agreement, which regulated the market through a system of export controls.</p>
<p>The current pact, administered by the ICO, has no economic provisions.</p>
<p>The ACPC, anxious to defend prices after the present fever in the market abates, hammered out an accord on Wednesday to limit total exports by the 14 members to 52.75 million 60-kg bags for the 12 months from July 1.</p>
<p>This is about the same as the volume limit that they had set under current curbs expiring June 30.</p>
<p>The ACPC, led by Brazil, accounts for more than 70 percent of world production. Some ICO producer members such as Guatemala, Vietnam and Mexico are not ACPC members.</p>
<p>Officials of consumer governments said they were suprised at the ACPC decision to keep quotas now but insisted that the issue was not raised in the ICO forum.</p>
<p>&quot;The producers have a separate organisation, let's keep it separate,&quot; said consumer spokesman Walter Bastiannse of the Netherlands.</p>
<p>But some western roasters were more critical of the producer action, saying that it could back fire in the long run as the sharp price increase would stimulate over-production and prices would then collapse.</p>
<p>Consumers had expected the ACPC to loosen its export curbs to help cool their current rally and avoid any sharp fall in world consumption.</p>
<p>ACPC officials defended their move, saying that it was necessarily to maintain a renumerative price to the farmers and at the same time ensure sufficient supply to the market.</p>
<p>During the week, delegates from the 62-member ICO discussed progress of various coffee-related projects now underway in some member nations.</p>
<p>The debate heated up a bit early in the week when producer nations objected to a secretariat paper which raised the possibility of sharp price falls if the funds liquidated their massive positions. -- Jalil Hamid, London newsroom +44 171 542 4985</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100137">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
