<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608581" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Clean tanker rates seen struggling next week.</title>
<headline>Clean tanker rates seen struggling next week.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Clean tanker rates struggled to maintain momentum in the face of public holidays and may lose further momentum next week, brokers said on Friday.</p>
<p>The Middle East market was torpid with little enquiry and few fixtures, with 28,000-30,000 tonne gas oil cargoes to India sagging at around W175 and 30,000 tonne stems to Japan at W180.</p>
<p>Sparse activity in the 30,000 tonne Middle East market meant that owners continued to send tonnage in ballast to the Mediterranean, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;With a surplus of prompt tonnage in the Middle East Gulf area and enquiry so low, freight rates are not expected to rise in the coming weeks,&quot; said brokers E.A. Gibson in their weekly tanker report.</p>
<p>In the Med, enquiry exceeded suitable available tonnage towards the end of the week, with 27,500 tonne naphtha stems rising to around W235 and gas oil at W190/200.</p>
<p>Gas oil was steady at W205 in the inter-U.K./cont sector on reasonable enquiry, while there was good interest in shipping unleaded gasoline to the U.S. Typical trans-Atlantic rates were W165 for 60,000 tonnes and W210/220 on 33,000 tonnes, Gibson said.</p>
<p>In the Caribbean, 30,000 tonne rates have fallen by about 10 points but there may be sufficient demand to prevent a collapse, brokers said.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 4088</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
