<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608570" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Global LPG firm, boosted by strong naphtha, crude.</title>
<headline>Global LPG firm, boosted by strong naphtha, crude.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>International Liquefied Petroleum Gas (LPG) prices were strong in all centres this week as firm naphtha and crude, as well as good petrochemical demand in Asia, have seen levels rise even as the market enters its traditionally weakest period.</p>
<p>Naphtha has been kept strong by crude prices and, in Asia, by soaring term prices. Saudi Aramco has been negotiating since May 12 over the sale of about three million tonnes of A-180 naphtha in the East Asian market, and sources say buyers have paid a record premium of $17 a tonne over the Saudi naphtha formula.</p>
<p>This has led to a scramble for alternative feedstocks from consumers who can switch, such as petrochemical users.</p>
<p>&quot;The main Japanese demand is from the petrochemical side,&quot; said a Japanese trader. &quot;There have been several trades done this week, all from petchem buyers, and all for butane.&quot;</p>
<p>A cargo was reported traded at a fixed price of $213 a tonne cif Japan, although the exact size was not confirmed. &quot;It's not so common to see fixed price trade,&quot; said the trader. &quot;But for the petrochemical buyer it's much better as they can sell paper and hedge.&quot;</p>
<p>He added that there are several players who are willing to sell fixed price in Japan as they take regular contract cargoes which can push them into long positions and force them to free up storage space by selling spot.</p>
<p>But while Asian butane demand is rising, propane buyers remain relaxed. Buyers in Japan and South Korea traditionally take large volumes over the summer when prices are at their lowest to keep in storage for the peak winter consumption period. But the market in this sector is described as &quot;still very slow moving,&quot; with buyers still looking for lower prices later in the summer.</p>
<p>Trade is priced against Saudi Aramco's Contract Price (CP), and the expectation is that it will be lower in June than in May, effectively deferring spot trade at least until then. The CP is established by factoring in several elements, including three monthly tenders by Aramco. The first two of these for June, the T1 and T2 tenders were both rumoured to have seen propane sold in the range $157 to $159 a tonne. The third, T3, closes on Friday, with offers valid until early next week.</p>
<p>And on a spot basis, there were unconfirmed reports that prompt May trade had been done at CP -$10 or -$11 a tonne for propane, and at both CP -$5 a tonne and CP -$3.75 a tonne for butane.</p>
<p>On the basis of results so far, one trader predicts a propane CP of $167 a tonne for June, and a CP of $186 or $187 a tonne for butane.</p>
<p>Chinese prices for both propane and butane have softened steadily in recent weeks. The premium over the CP on a delivered China basis has fallen since early May, when supplies were much tighter than they are now, traders said. Product is discussed in the range CP +$50 to +$60 a tonne for the whole of June, down from a level in the first half of May up to CP + $80 a tonne.</p>
<p>Strong crude and naphtha have also kept North Sea propane prices high, and started attracting cargoes from the Mediterranean to Northwest Europe. There were rumours that a major Mediterranean seller had sold a 40,000 tonne propane cargo at between $185 a tonne and $190 a tonne cif NWE, and a trader for a Scandinavian company said the same seller had recently been offering a 14,000 tonne part-cargo in the region. Bids on the large cargo market were heard at $185 a tonne by the end of the week, against offers at $190 or even higher.</p>
<p>As well as strong crude and naphtha, a trader cited two separate factors boosting the North Sea propane market. First, some players have booked storage space in order to have high inventories in place for the winter, and are anxiously checking for the optimum tine to buy cheaply in the summer, as in the Japanese market. Since there is competition for this material, the price is prevented from falling as much as it otherwise might.</p>
<p>And second, there are some traders who have sold into petrochemical buyers and need to cover their short positions, a dealer said. He added that there is little direct petrochemical buying seen now, but there are still aggressive bids coming from the traders covering them which is also keeping levels up.</p>
<p>Butane in the North Sea was described as &quot;dead quiet, a hopeless, illiquid market with a complete absence of deals.&quot; The last trade seen was at $174 a tonne some time ago, but traders say that if a deal is done soon, it will probably be higher than this.</p>
<p>In the Mediterranean, the storage caverns at Lavera in southern France are undergoing some work which will carry on into June. A major regional seller said that both northern Europe and the U.S. are the key markets for its output at present, with the local market quiet. Most U.S. interest is coming from the Gulf Coast, although there is some possibility of moving material to Brazil.</p>
<p>Prices in the U.S. have been relatively steady, with propane at the Mont Belvieu, Texas hub still at around 35.75 to 36.00 cents a gallon. International cargoes are still arriving from, for example, Venezuela and Algeria to take advantage of the relative strength. From the North Sea, a trader said that &quot;for large cargoes there's just about an arbitrage, but for small cargoes, no.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Sebastian Alison, London Newsroom, +44 171 542 6412</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
