<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608512" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: BROKERS SLAM GREEK WATCHDOG'S FINES AS COVER-UP.</title>
<headline>BROKERS SLAM GREEK WATCHDOG'S FINES AS COVER-UP.</headline>
<byline>George Georgiopoulos</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Athens bourse members and individuals penalised by the Greek capital market commission for allegedly violating insider trading laws in the Delta Securities scandal said the fines were an effort to save face and cover up the real culprits.</p>
<p>&quot;The capital market commission's decision was expected. They were looking for scape goats. The responsibilities ...(for the Delta Securities scandal) rest with the Athens stock exchange and the people operating in and around it,&quot; Constantine Georgakis told Reuters.</p>
<p>Georgakis, president of construction firm Atemke was fined 150 million drachmas for alleged insider trading violations and manipulative practices in shares of cotton processor Magrizos .</p>
<p>The Delta Securities scandal rocked the bourse in November 1996 and shut down trading for four days after the firm defaulted with the clearing house for 2.6 billion drachmas.</p>
<p>Shares of Magrizos were at the core of the Delta scandal which also had state brokerages implicated, market watchers said. Magrizos shares are still suspended from trade.</p>
<p>&quot;We are surprised with the mentality of the commission which confirms that even today, despite the progress in the market, there is preferential treatment when it comes to applying the law,&quot; said managing director of Sigma Securities John Marcopoulos.</p>
<p>He countered that the commission was trying to save face and did not deal with the real responsibilities which rested with the clearing house.</p>
<p>&quot;There were more than 10 private and state brokerages involved in trades of Magrizos shares but the commission's decision does not touch upon them. The decision leaves us with a big question mark,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Marcopoulos' Sigma Securities was fined 50 million drachmas for alleged insider trading violations.</p>
<p>&quot;Seeking a catharsis, the commission picked on a trade in Parnassos which took all the blame for the crisis. Sigma executed only one trade in this share for a customer and there was no resulting benefit,&quot; Marcopoulos said.</p>
<p>Constantine Varipobiotis, a broker with Avax Securities, who was personally fined 100 million drachmas for insider trading, told Reuters: &quot;The commission's decision is on the wrong course. It is biased and damages the reputation of firms and individuals without any concern.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The only recourse, something which the commission itself is prompting, is litigation. I reserve my full legal rights.&quot;</p>
<p>Experienced marker watchers said the commision had not been fair in slapping fines but was only trying to save face.</p>
<p>&quot;The commission picked certain brokers and slapped fines to save face. It covered up for other firms which were deeply involved in the Delta scandal. This is no catharsis,&quot; an experienced market watcher told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It was the market itself that helped bring about a catharsis, a normalisation after the crisis and not the authorities,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Pavlos Vranas, managing director of Euroxx Securities which was fined 30 million drachmas for alleged insider trading violations told Reuters he did not wish to comment at this time, awaiting the rationale behind the commission's decision.</p>
<p>The commission fined Ionian Securities, a subsidiary of state Ionian Bank 90 million drachmas for alleged violations of insider trading and deals on share repurchase agreements. It was the only state brokerage to be fined.</p>
<p>&quot;We have no comment. The official reaction will come from Ionian Bank,&quot; Antonia Tzartzanou, head of the brokerage told Reuters. --Athens newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I43000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
