<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608520" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BCCI liquidator pursues six-year fight for victims.</title>
<headline>BCCI liquidator pursues six-year fight for victims.</headline>
<byline>Alexander Smith</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Victims of the biggest banking fraud in history won a symbolic victory in a British court on Friday but the six-year battle to claw back their losses is far from over.</p>
<p>The liquidators of Bank of Credit and Commerce International (BCCI) won an order for 2.94 million pounds against former shipping tycoon Abbas Gokal, who earlier this month was sentenced to 14 years in prison for his part in the BCCI fraud.</p>
<p>&quot;We are very pleased by the compensation order the court made this morning. However Abbas Gokal caused significant damage to BCCI and its creditors and we will continue to pursue his assets worldwide,&quot; liquidator Christopher Morris of accountants Deloitte &amp; Touche told Reuters.</p>
<p>If Gokal -- who fled to his native Pakistan from his company's Swiss base when BCCI collapsed in 1991 with debts of more than $12.0 billion -- does not pay, he faces an extra three years in prison.</p>
<p>But Gokal is just one of the potential sources of compensation to the victims of the BCCI fraud. The bank's depositors ranged from British local authorities to individuals who had deposited their savings with the bank and lost everything.</p>
<p>Morris, who describes work on the case as &quot;a process of attrition&quot;, said the liquidators have actions outstanding against BCCI's auditors Price Waterhouse and Ernst &amp; Young, as well as the Bank of England and Gokal's Gulf shipping group.</p>
<p>The liquidators are claiming $3.5 billion plus interest against Price Waterhouse, $1.6 billion plus interest against Ernst &amp; Young and 550 million pounds from the Bank of England, which regulated the British-based operations of BCCI.</p>
<p>Depositors have already received a 24.5 percent dividend, more than $2.0 billion in total, and Morris is confident the liquidators will make another payment of not less than 10 percent at the end of this year or the beginning of 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;It won't be the last, there will be at least one more,&quot; he said in an interview.</p>
<p>Some initial expectations of how much the BCCI depositors would get back in total were as low as 25 percent, although this risen over time. An average payout in liquidations is around five percent.</p>
<p>Morris says he believed there was a good case against both sets of auditors. And a judgement on the preliminary issues involved in the case against the Bank of England, regarding its duties to depositors, banks and the public, is also awaited.</p>
<p>The Bank of England case is widely expected to end up in the House of Lords, with either side likely to appeal any court judgement which does not go in its favour.</p>
<p>Further protective and more substantive writs are also likely to emerge in the next six weeks as the watershed date of July 2 approaches.</p>
<p>This will mark the six year anniversary of the decision to shut down BCCI in 1991. Its branches were closed three days later.</p>
<p>The law requires that any claim is made within six years and this is likely to spark a flurry of last minute activity to ensure that every avenue in the search to recoup money for depositors can be pursued in the future.</p>
<p>An update on exactly how well the liquidators are doing is expected to emerge in the near future when a progress report is made to Britain's Department of Trade and Industry (DTI).</p>
<p>The liquidators have been criticised in the past for running up multi-million pound bills in fees. But Morris denied the fees were excessive. &quot;The costs are commensurate with the mess,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>There are 30 to 40 temporary staff working on the case, sorting and indexing millions of documents, as well as 30 Deloitte &amp; Touche employees working on the English part of the liquidation.</p>
<p>BCCI's operations were split between Britain, Luxembourg and the Cayman Islands and this led to a &quot;pooling agreement&quot; and a &quot;credit and recovery sharing agreement&quot; between the various liquidators.</p>
<p>Morris said co-operation between the authorities around the world on BCCI had been largely good, but he singled out the U.S. and Britain's Serious Fraud Office and DTI for particular praise.</p>
<p>But despite this, he admitted that an ultimate resolution to the liquidation would be some way off. &quot;I shall probably be retired before that day arrives,&quot; the 55-year-old said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LUX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
