<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608552" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: WEEK AHEAD - Markets to focus on U.S., Japan data.</title>
<headline>WEEK AHEAD - Markets to focus on U.S., Japan data.</headline>
<byline>Tara FitzGerald</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Financial markets will look next week to U.S and Japanese economic data for hints on where interest rates are heading, economists said on Friday.</p>
<p>The outcome of the first round of French parliamentary elections should provide focus in Europe, but unless the left emerges with a surprise victory, markets should stay unruffled.</p>
<p>But analysts said data from Japan and the United States throughout the week may steal the show. Markets in Britain and the U.S. will be closed on Monday.</p>
<p>Interest rate speculation in both the United States and Japan will keep investors focused on their economic data, watching for signs of the health of the two economies.</p>
<p>The U.S. Federal Reserve left rates unchanged at a key meeting this week, shifting attention to the next policy meeting in July.</p>
<p>&quot;The sort of news we get from the U.S. over the next few weeks will be absolutely crucial to interest rate expectations...and I think people realise that if the economy does pick up strongly...then the Fed will be more inclined to tighten (rates) in July,&quot; Ian Harwood, head of strategy and economics at Dresdner Kleinwort Benson Secs in London, said.</p>
<p>Data due next week includes U.S. existing and new home sales on Tuesday and Friday respectively, U.S. durable goods on Wednesday and U.S. revised GDP on Friday. But they may not provide strong guidelines on the economy.</p>
<p>Traders said the focus was shifting to the key May payrolls data due on June 6. A strong showing there is likely to knock U.S. Treasuries.</p>
<p>Japanese markets have suffered from continuing volatility over the last week as speculation over a possible Japanese interest rate rise continued to plague markets. Economists said Japanese data would give some idea as to how the economy had fared after consumption tax was raised on April 1.</p>
<p>&quot;The figures show the first month when the tax hike has been in place, so one of the key questions is how the Japanese economy has responded to what has been quite an aggressive tightening of fiscal policy,&quot; said Keith Edmonds, chief analyst at IBJ International here.</p>
<p>Japanese data due next week include April preliminary industrial production on Thursday and unemployment and retail sales on Friday.</p>
<p>In Europe, economists expect a quieter week, except for the French election on Sunday, which will be followed by the second round of polls on June 1. Gerard Lyons, chief economist at DKB International in London, said a dramatic reaction to the French outcome was unlikely.</p>
<p>The centre-right coalition, which currently holds power in France, is widely tipped to clinch victory in a week's time, but with the absence of any polls until then markets are still in a limbo.</p>
<p>&quot;We will keep our eyes on the French election results, but provided it's clear that the centre-right will retain its majority I don't see any fall-out in the markets. But if the result is close then the markets will be very nervous ahead of the second round,&quot; Edmonds said.</p>
<p>No rate was change was expected from the Bundesbank Council meeting on Wednesday while in the UK, traders were more interested in Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown's announcement of the date of his mini-budget than any economic data.</p>
<p>-- International Bonds Unit, +44 171 542 4041.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
