<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608585" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Yachting: Peter Campbell's Rhumbline Column.</title>
<headline>Australian Yachting: Peter Campbell's Rhumbline Column.</headline>
<text>
<p>By Peter Campbell*</p>
<p>ADMIRAL'S CUP BOAT LAUNCHED IN SYDNEY</p>
<p>The latest Ragamuffin, the only locally built yacht in Australia's team for the 1997 Admiral's Cup will have its first sail on Sydney Harbour on Saturday before being air-freighted to England for the world's premier offshore teams racing regatta.</p>
<p>Team captain SYD FISCHER, chairman of Australian Development Corporation and Australia's only challenger for America's Cup 2000, will campaign the Farr 49 as the big boat in the team at Cowes. This will be Fischer's sixth time as captain of the Australian Admiral's Cup team.</p>
<p>This latest design by the U.S.-based Bruce Farr and Associates has been built by the West Gosford company, Boatspeed, and is another fine example of the state-of-the-art boat-building skills of this company headed by husband-and-wife team PETER and SARIE ULLRICH.</p>
<p>The new Ragamuffin will be joined at Cowes by two chartered yachts -- the Japanese-owned ILC40, G Net, which is being campaigned by a syndicate headed by Melbourne stockbroker JOHN CALVERT-JONES and Sydney marina owner and prominent yachtsman ROBIN CRAWFORD, and the U.S.-built Mumm 36, Sea, which will be skippered by STEVE KULMAR whose skills on the helm are only matched by those as CEO of his successful advertising agency.</p>
<p>KULMAR and Fraser Sails designer BRAD STEPHENS, along with other crew members, fly to Italy today to prepare Sea for the Mumm 36 world championships at Punta Ala in Italy, which they are contesting as part of their preparation for the Admiral's Cup. The Mumm 36 worlds start on June 1.</p>
<p>SYDNEY 36 NAMED SAILBOAT OF THE YEAR</p>
<p>The Sailboat of the Year award, announced on Thursday at the Sanctuary Cove Boat Show in Queensland, has gone to the IAIN MURRAY designed Sydney 36, built by Bashford International at Nowra on the NSW South Coast.</p>
<p>The Sailboat of the Year was among a long list of awards, mainly to powerboats. Olympic hero and avid boatowner KIERAN PERKINS presented the gold award to Queensland based Haines Marine Industries for their model Signature 610 Bow Rider, considered to be the ultimate new release of the 1997 season.</p>
<p>The Sydney 36 was designed by Iain Murray Associates as a smaller version of their Sydney-Hobart race winning 41-footer and has been raced successfully in Australia and overseas. Among the Sydney 36s currently racing is Bashfull, owned by Cruising Yacht Club Vice-Commodore HUGO VAN KRETSCHMAR and past Commodore DAVID FULLER.</p>
<p>WILD BULL ON THE RAMPAGE</p>
<p>Another new design sailing impressively is the Bull 9000, a high-performance nine-metre sloop designed by New Zealander GREG YOUNG and being built in Victoria by Hart Marine at Mornington.</p>
<p>The Bull 9000 is a designated race boat, set up for inshore and offshore racing, with a maximum sized cockpit for efficient crew work. Much of the design and engineering has been developed from New Zealand's winning America's Cup campaign in 1995.</p>
<p>The carbon fibre mast, built to carry either fractional or masthead spinnakers, was developed by CHRIS MITCHELL, designer of the winning 1995 America's Cup mast. The advanced keel was developed and tested by MURRAY LEYLAND of Team New Zealand.</p>
<p>Several Bull 9000s have been racing with success on Melbourne's Port Phillip and the first in Sydney, Wild Bull, is making its impact under the command of Ord Minet executive ROD SKELLETT, who previously raced the ill-fated Joint Venture.</p>
<p>SKELLETT and Wild Bull are currently leading the pointscore in the highly competitive Division D of the Cruising Yacht of Australia's Winter Series on Sydney Harbour -- the division designed by the club for high-performance small racing yachts such as the Mt Gay 30s and Mumm 30s.</p>
<p>However, strong competition is coming from RICHARD PERINI with his Mumm 30, Addiction. PERINI doesn't appear high on the pointscore at present having missed the opening race of the Winter Series, but with two wins out of three starts Addiction will be hard to beat through the season.</p>
<p>AROUND THE WORLD IN 71 DAYS</p>
<p>The trimaran Sport Elec, skippered by French sailor OLIVIER DE KERSAUSON early this week set a new around-the-world sailing record of 71 days, 14 hours and 18 minutes. DE KERSAUSONS also won the Jules Verne Trophy when he crossed the finish line, ending his official circumnavigation off Brest on the French Atlantic coast.</p>
<p>The previous record of 74 days 22 hours and 17 minutes was set in 1994 by New Zealander SIR PETER BLAKE aboard Enza, another maxi-multihull yacht.</p>
<p>Thousands greeted DE KERSAUSON at Brest, where he set out on March 4 on his fifth attempt at the record. His remarkable accomplishment returns the crown of circumnavigation speed to the French. Prior to Enza's record the Jules Verne Trophy had been held by BRUNO PEYRON in Commodore Explorer with a time of 79 days six hours and 15 minutes.</p>
<p>SWIFT SAIL TO THE SOLOMONS</p>
<p>Not quite as fast, but still exciting have been the rollicking rides before warm tradewinds by the 17 yachts competing in the long ocean race from Brisbane to Gizo in the Solomon Islands over the past couple of a days.</p>
<p>Race leader Millennium, skippered by Coffs Harbour yachtsman JOHN CLAYTON has strengthened her grip on line honours by logging a 24 hour run of 222 nautical miles. At last report she was 12 miles ahead of veteran Lake Macquarie yachtsman ALBY BURGIN sailing Alstar.</p>
<p>However, the fastest 24 hour run before the 20 knot south-easterly trades came from the New Zealand entry Blizzard, skippered by JOHN MILLER, which logged 225 miles. Sydney yachtsman and Capital Properties director GEORGE SNOW logged 209 miles in his Beneteau cruiser/racer Infinity II.</p>
<p>SNOW is sailing Infinity II on this Solomon Airlines sponsored race to Gizo while awaiting a new rig for his maxi yacht Brindabella which was dismasted in last year's Sydney-Hobart.</p>
<p>CAYARD AND LAW IN MATCH WINS</p>
<p>Australian PETER GILMOUR, now living in Japan to meet residency requirements to skipper the Nippon Yacht Club's challenger for America's Cup 2000, still holds second place in the Omega Match Race Rankings despite not competing in either of this week's international events -- the Royal Lymington Cup in England and the St Francis Match Race in San Francisco.</p>
<p>New Zealand America's Cup winning skipper RUSSELL COUTTS still heads the rankings, but GILMOUR is closer on the scoreboard after beating the Kiwi in the ACI Cup on the Adriatic coast of Croatia two weeks ago.</p>
<p>Winner of the Royal Lymington Cup was Britain's America's Cup skipper CHRIS LAW. PAUL CAYARD, who has been nominated as skipper of the St Francis Yacht Club's challenger in Auckland in 2000, won the San Francisco match race series.</p>
<p>CAYARD lost only two races in the 14 match double round robin series, losing twice to New Zealand America's Cup sailor MURRAY JONES who finished runner-up in the series.</p>
<p>*Peter Campbell is editor of Offshore Yachting magazine.</p>
<p>Sydney Newsroom 612-9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
