<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608543" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: IRA's Sinn Fein sharply increases N.Ireland vote.</title>
<headline>IRA's Sinn Fein sharply increases N.Ireland vote.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The IRA's political wing Sinn Fein increased its share of Northern Ireland votes to a record 17 percent on Friday in local elections which ended their Protestant rivals' domination of Belfast city council.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein, which seeks to end British rule of Northern Ireland, raised its share of the votes by nearly 5.0 percent, the third successive election at which it has increased its electoral support, which was 12 percent in 1993.</p>
<p>The main losers were Sinn Fein's idelogical opposites, Protestant Unionists who want the disputed province to remain part of the United Kingdom and who have held control over key city councils for decades.</p>
<p>&quot;This marks a new era for this city of Belfast, &quot; said Sinn Fein President Gerry Adams. &quot;We will end an era of domination and bring in a new, inclusive era,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein's showing raised the prospect of a Catholic Mayor being chosen for the first time in decades. Unionists won 25 seats to the council and Nationalists and their allies 26.</p>
<p>The party polled around 11 percent before 1990, 12 percent in the last such polls in 1993, 15 percent in a vote for a &quot;Peace Forum&quot; discussion body one year ago and 16 percent in Britain's May 1 elections.</p>
<p>But Sinn Fein's victory, which followed the election of Adams and associate Martin McGuinness to the British parliament this month, was contested by several parties which accused it of cheating.</p>
<p>&quot;There is only one party in this province which could mount a military-style operation and we all know who that is,&quot; said the SDLP's Mark Atwood.</p>
<p>He was referring to the Irish Republican Army, which is at war with Britain to end British rule. Sinn Fein says it is a separate organisation with a common goal.</p>
<p>Northern Ireland's chief electoral officer, Richard Bradley, said there were &quot;grounds for believing that the allegations are true&quot; and said an &quot;orchestrated campaign of postal and proxy votes&quot; had been uncovered.</p>
<p>He said an investigation was being carried out in Northern Ireland, where legend has it that the electorate follows the saying: &quot;Vote early and vote often.&quot;</p>
<p>Adams dismissed the allegations of cheating. &quot;That's a whinge and they should stop whingeing. I am telling you there has been no vote-rigging by Sinn Fein, he said.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein raised its share of Belfast city council seats by three to 13, equalling the number won by the mainstream Ulster Unionist Party. Councils administer health, education and other domestic matters.</p>
<p>The SDLP and Sinn Fein together captured for the first time the councils of Fermanagh and the dormitory town of Cookstown.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein's showing capped a week in which British government officials held talks with Adams and McGuinness for the first time since the IRA ended a 17-month ceasefire in February 1996 with a London bomb which killed two.</p>
<p>Further exploratory talks are to be held with the new British government but Sinn Fein is barred from Belfast peace talks until the IRA calls a complete end to a conflict in which 3,200 people have been killed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
