<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608514" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Oil price eases amid pre-holiday squaring.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Oil price eases amid pre-holiday squaring.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>World oil prices paused on Friday after recent hefty gains and ahead of a long weekend in the U.S. which is expected to shift summer driving-season demand for gasoline into a higher gear, traders and brokers said.</p>
<p>Brent crude oil futures in London for July delivery closed 18 cents lower at $20.00 a barrel</p>
<p>Most attention was focused on gasoline's progress. The Memorial Day holiday in the United States on Monday traditionally marks the shift of the summer gasoline season into top gear.</p>
<p>Some traders warned, however, that this year's season could disappoint.</p>
<p>&quot;In the last couple of days gasoline has certainly been the best performer,&quot; said Tony Machacek at Credit Lyonnais Rouse in London.</p>
<p>But he warned that bearish weekly U.S. gasoline inventory data released by the American Petroleum Institute (API) in the past couple of weeks provided some cause for concern. The data showed a weekly build in U.S. gasoline stocks of some 800,000 barrels.</p>
<p>&quot;The extent of the rise goes a little against the grain considering the API stocks build shown last week and this week,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>June NYMEX unleaded gasoline, which has led prices higher in the past few sessions, was 0.13 cent a gallon lower at 66.80 cents a gallon at 1944 GMT, but has still posted close to a three cent gain since Tuesday.</p>
<p>Fresh signs that Turkish troops were unlikely to withdraw soon from northern Iraq were having little immediate impact on the oil price, traders said.</p>
<p>Witnesses said a further 1,000 troops moved into Iraq overnight and officials on both sides of the conflict confirmed that the Turkish army has started to dig in after initial clashes with Kurdistan Workers Party rebels.</p>
<p>Diplomats played down reports that Iran, Syria and Iraq were building up forces on the borders of the Iraqi Kurdish region to help the rebels escape.</p>
<p>&quot;The market has discounted a lot of the uncertainty over the Turkish/Iraqi/Syrian rumours and although the current status is not enough in itself to drive prices higher, there is an underpinning to the market by these factors,&quot; said Charles Gray at Prudential-Bache Futures in London.</p>
<p>Also lurking in the background is the renewal, due next month, of the oil-for-food deal between the United Nations and Iraq.</p>
<p>The current accord allows Iraq to sell up to $2 billion of oil over six months in order to purchase food, medicine and other goods for its people suffering under U.N. sanctions imposed when Iraqi troops invaded Kuwait in August 1990.</p>
<p>U.S. ambassador to the U.N. Bill Richardson voiced misgivings on Thursday about the deal, although he id not reject approval for the plan.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there is general concern about the deal,&quot; Machacek said.</p>
<p>Traders said poor refining margins in Europe -- the difference between the price of crude oil and a basket of refined products -- have led to some cutbacks in crude oil throughputs.</p>
<p>While this factor had already largely been discounted from futures markets, it provided a negative backdrop.</p>
<p>						 May 23    May 22</p>
<p>						  close    close</p>
<p> Dated Brent				 $20.25    $20.14</p>
<p> IPE July Brent			    $20.00    $20.18</p>
<p> NYMEX July light crude		  $21.56    $21.86</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
