<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608525" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Pregnant IRA bomb suspect released on bail.</title>
<headline>Pregnant IRA bomb suspect released on bail.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A pregnant IRA bomb suspect was released on bail on Friday to spend the last days in hospital before she gives birth, British prison officials said.</p>
<p>Roisin McAliskey, 25, has been held in London's high security Holloway prison since last year pending possible extradition to Germany for questioning about an Irish Republican Army mortar attack on a British army base at Osnabreuck.</p>
<p>McAliskey, daughter of former radical Northern Ireland politician Bernadette McAliskey, nee Devlin, denies any part in the bombing in which buildings were damaged but no one was injured.</p>
<p>Her lawyers made an urgent bail application before a judge on Friday amid reports that she had developed complications in the last stages of her pregnancy.</p>
<p>A prison service spokesman, confirming that she had been released on bail, said the decision was based on medical advice that &quot;she could better prepare for the birth of her child in hospital.&quot;</p>
<p>Despite protests from the Irish republic and Roman Catholic politicians, Britain had refused repeated previous bail requests and insisted that she must remain in prison until her extradition case was heard.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
