<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608508" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: CZECH PM KLAUS SAYS SEES CROWN PRESSURE EASING.</title>
<headline>CZECH PM KLAUS SAYS SEES CROWN PRESSURE EASING.</headline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Czech Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus said on Thursday he believed that pressure from investors on the crown would ease next week when the political situation cools down when the current parliamentary session ends.</p>
<p>Klaus told Czech Television that he saw the central parity of the crown's mark/dollar basket as the currency's proper level.</p>
<p>&quot;I fully agree with the governor of the central bank (Josef Tosovsky) that the crown still should range around its basket parity... and that is what the central bank's policy is aimed at,&quot; Klaus said.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that when the political situation calms down, when the two-week parliamentary session, which radicalised the situation, is over, there will be a political cool down which will be very positively reflected in the exchange rate of the crown,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The crown, which has been under strong pressure for a week, in part due to political instability, fell to record lows of below six percent on the depriciation side of the basket on Thursday, prompting repeated central bank intervention.</p>
<p>The opposition Social Democrats presented their draft economic policy to the parliament on Wednesday, which included deficit budget spending, imposition of an import surcharge, slowing down privatisation and price deregulation, but it failed to push it through the chamber.</p>
<p>The three-party coalition government led by Klaus has been mulling replacing several of its ministers in light of economic downturn in early 1997 and declining public confidence in the cabinet's abilities to lead the country.</p>
<p>The crown was trading at -4.00 percent versus the basket parity at 1955 GMT, after the central bank's fixing at -3.00 percent.</p>
<p>-- Jan Lopatka, Prague Newsroom, 420-2-2423-0003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
