<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608517" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Wall Street boost Euro bourses, dollar idles.</title>
<headline>Wall Street boost Euro bourses, dollar idles.</headline>
<byline>Malcolm Davidson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Europe's major bourses ended the week with modest gains on Friday, underpinned by a firm start on Wall Street, while the dollar calmed following several days of sharp volatility.</p>
<p>U.S. shares bounced ahead in early trade, adding more than 50 points on the Dow Jones Industrial Average at one point, before slipping a little ahead of the three-day weekend in the United States.</p>
<p>Europe's three main bourses -- London, Paris and Frankfurt -- all ended up on the day.</p>
<p>French stocks made some of the best gains in Europe, rising 0.78 percent as investors bet on the ruling conservatives perfoming well in Sunday's first round of national parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>By the close the CAC 40 index was showing gains of 21.25 points to 2,762.90. Volume was 8.79 billion francs, swollen by trades related to the monthly settlement.</p>
<p>Most traders expect the bourse to rise to new highs if the ruling centre-right wins the election or slide as much as 10 percent if the Socialists and their allies get control of parliament.</p>
<p>They also cautioned that, whatever the final outcome, there may be bumpy moments between Sunday's first round and the runoff vote on June 1.</p>
<p>&quot;If the Socialists' share of the vote is high on Sunday, we'll see a negative knee-jerk reaction,&quot; said Merrill Lynch strategist David Bowers. &quot;Our view is that the conservatives will squeak home in the second ballot.&quot;</p>
<p>Among the active shares on Friday, Elf-Aquitaine rose 1.63 percent to 623 francs after announcing it would buy back a 0.7 percent stake sold by insurer Axa's UAP-Vie subsidiary. Elf said on Thursday it would buy back a 0.9 percent stake sold by Renault .</p>
<p>German shares hurdled the important 3,600 level, ending floor trade up 22.77 points at 3,602.19 points. The blue-chip index, underpinned by Wall Street's gains, remained buoyant in post-bourse IBIS electronic dealings and ended the day up 46.28 points at 3,621.72 points.</p>
<p>The market got a boost from two German state inflation reports that showed higher prices in May on a monthly basis but failed to ignite fears about inflation growth.</p>
<p>Firmer German debt prices and a higher dollar also helped to support the market.</p>
<p>Carmaker Volkswagen AG ended up 13 marks at 1,140 marks after briefly pushing through technical resistance at 1,150 marks.</p>
<p>Dresdner Bank, Germany's second largest bank, gained 1.02 marks to 62.82 marks after saying it was optimistic of higher full-year results following a 10 percent rise in first quarter profits.</p>
<p>London shares closed within striking distance of their all-time highs, cheered by the firm start on Wall Street.</p>
<p>But further gains next week are seen limited as some participants fear markets on both sides of the Atlantic may be on the verge of a downward correction.</p>
<p>&quot;The FTSE is still on the overbought side and I think there is going to be a sharp correction at some stage, perhaps starting next week,&quot; said Richard Marshall, strategist at Investment Research of Cambridge Ltd.</p>
<p>The FTSE 100 ended 10.0 higher to 4,661.8.</p>
<p>On the currency front, the dollar idled in late European trade, calming after its volatile spell as Japanese rate rise fears cooled.</p>
<p>Analysts said a slew of Japanese data next week would prove the key to whether the U.S. unit could maintain its composure.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of the volatility in FX markets has stemmed from shifting rate expectations in Tokyo, so it'll be important to look at the April figures, which are the first real indication of how the economy's performing after the increase in consumption tax,&quot; said Keith Edmonds, chief analyst at IBJ International in London.</p>
<p>Next week sees Japan release industrial production, retail sales and CPI figures for April. But players in London and New York were more focused on Monday's market holidays in their centres, traders said.</p>
<p>STOCK PRICES -- CLOSING INDICES</p>
<p>LONDON - The FTSE 100 closed up 10.0 points, or 0.21 percent, at 4,661.8.</p>
<p>PARIS - The CAC-40 index closed up 21.25 points, or 0.78 percent, at 2,762.90.</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - The DAX index closed floor trade up 22.77 points, or 0.64 percent, at 3,602.19. In later screen-based trade the IBIS DAX ended up 46.28 points at 3,602.19.</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 1600 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar stood at 1.6915 marks and 115.67 yen compared with 1.6947 marks and 116.05 yen in late European trade on Thursday.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold closed at $343.05, up $0.30 from Thursday. Silver ended six cents firmer at $4.75.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
