<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608515" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Bradford &amp; Bingley buys Mortgage Express.</title>
<headline>Bradford &amp; Bingley buys Mortgage Express.</headline>
<byline>Alexander Smith</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Bradford &amp; Bingley Building Society boosted its assets by 1.5 billion pounds ($2.4 billion) on Friday when it bought mortgage lender Mortgage Express for 64 million pounds from Lloyds TSB Group.</p>
<p>&quot;This was the big one. We resolved that it was important to get,&quot; Bradford &amp; Bingley chief executive Christopher Rodrigues told Reuters.</p>
<p>He left open the possibilty of further acquisitions, saying the society was interested &quot;in one or two areas&quot; but declined to be more specific.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think this will be the last one but equally we are not going to see a flurry,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Specialist lender Mortgage Express, which will become a wholly owned subsidiary of the group, will increase Bradford &amp; Bingley's assets to more than 18.5 billion pounds. The society will become Britain's second largest when the current round of conversions to publicly listed banks is over.</p>
<p>Lloyds TSB spokeswoman Geraldine Davies said the sale eliminated duplication with the high street bank's mortgage provider Cheltenham &amp; Gloucester, adding it was in the best interests of shareholders and Mortgage Express customers and staff.</p>
<p>Lloyds TSB said the profit before tax of 50 million pounds on the sale would be included in its half year results ending June 30.</p>
<p>Mortgage Express is based in north London and has 300 employees and more than 26,000 customers. Bradford &amp; Bingley said in the last three years the group had &quot;successfully turned around the sizeable non-performing lending portfolio and has created a well run, profitable business&quot;.</p>
<p>Bradford &amp; Bingley said the move represented a diversification for the society, which has trumpeted the benefits of its mutual status since a number of its competitors chose to become banks.</p>
<p>It was a sensible step forward for the society and did not represent a weakening of its commitment to mutuality, where the group is owned by its savers and borrowers rather than shareholders, it added.</p>
<p>Mortgage Express does not provide the same sort of home loans as the mainstream British mortgage providers, traditionally the building societies.</p>
<p>Instead it offers what are accepted to be more &quot;risky&quot; products such as buy-to-rent loans, mortgages for self-employed and contract workers, second home finance and negative equity loans.</p>
<p>It is a centralised lender, distributing its products through third parties and direct to the public. Bradford &amp; Bingley has paid 4.2 percent of asset value for it, in line with estimates.</p>
<p>There were also some industry sources who suggested Mortgage Express would dilute the quality of Bradford &amp; Bingley's mortgage book, making it more vulnerable to market downturns.</p>
<p>But Rodrigues dismissed any such suggestion.</p>
<p>&quot;I have every confidence that this will not cause a deterioration in the society's performance,&quot; he said in an telephone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;There is substantial value in the existing loan book and great potential for the specialist lending products Mortgage Express now sells,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The acquisition also gave the building society the skills to securitise parts of the balance sheet, which would help it to fund the growth of Bradford &amp; Bingley's existing business, he added.</p>
<p>This would mean greater freedom for Bradford &amp; Bingley in managing its balance sheet, and was likely to lead to securitisation of some of its Mortgage Express assets during the year.</p>
<p>Securitisation is a process of ring-fencing assets such as loans and then raising capital on the strength of them.</p>
<p>Mortgage Express went through a difficult period in the early 1990s. It stopped taking on new business at the height of the housing recession in 1991, when it was losing money at a rate of a million pounds a week, but has since recovered.</p>
<p>&quot;Over the past three years, the Mortgage Express team has successfully turned around the sizeable non-performing lending portfolio and has created a well-run profitable business,&quot; Rodrigues said.</p>
<p>&quot;You must look at Mortgage Express as what it is today and not what it was five years ago,&quot; he said, adding that Bradford &amp; Bingley had bought a business that was already properly provided for. ($ = 0.615 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
