<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608506" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVAKIA: SLOVAKS VOTE IN REFERENDUM BUT DOUBTS REMAIN.</title>
<headline>SLOVAKS VOTE IN REFERENDUM BUT DOUBTS REMAIN.</headline>
<byline>Jan Krcmar</byline>
<dateline>BRATISLAVA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Slovaks vote on Friday in two referendums which could determine their place in Europe but which have been cast in doubt by a row tied to a bitter feud between their president and prime minister.</p>
<p>A three-question referendum on NATO membership is accepted by both sides. But a separate referendum, sought by President Michal Kovac, on whether the president should be directly elected has thrown the process into doubt.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Vladimir Meciar's government sought unsuccessfully to have the question ruled illegal and Interior Minister Gustav Krajci issued new ballot papers with only the three questions on NATO membership.</p>
<p>But Kalman Petocz of the all-party Central Referendum Committee (UKR), which supervises the voting, said this could lead to the annulment of the entire referendum.</p>
<p>&quot;The only legal ballots are those previously approved by the UKR with its official seal and which contain all four questions as decreed by the president who ordered the referendum,&quot; Petocz added.</p>
<p>Slovakia, which became an independent state when Czechoslovakia split peacefully in 1993, has said it wants to be amomg the first post-communist countries to join Western European structures, including NATO and the European Union.</p>
<p>However, its chances have waned after repeated U.S. and EU criticism of the pace of democratic reform.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton, in a letter delivered to Kovac on Wednesday and released by his office, said more needed to be done to promote democracy.</p>
<p>&quot;More work needs to be done to promote an atmosphere of openness to opposing views and concerns of minorities,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Diplomats said the conduct of the referendums would be a test of Slovakia's democratic credentials.</p>
<p>&quot;We are carefully watching the way the referendums are being carried out, whether the authorities are guaranteeing a truly democratic poll,&quot; one western diplomat said.</p>
<p>&quot;That is the yardstick of democratic maturity and will again be a test of whether Slovakia is ripe for integration into western structures,&quot; the diplomat added.</p>
<p>The vote on presidential elections is seen as an attempt by the opposition to prevent Meciar from assuming presidential powers when the term of Kovac ends next March.</p>
<p>Under the present constitution, if parliament is unable to muster a three-fifths majority to elect a new president, which niether the ruling coalition or opposition can achieve, the presidential powers pass on the prime minister.</p>
<p>&quot;The government fears the 'yes' vote in both referendums would be a defeat for its current policies and is doing all it can to thwart the plebiscite,&quot; Jan Budaj, secretary of the opposition Democratic Union told a news conference on Thursday.</p>
<p>The government led by Meciar -- who has clashed with President Michal Kovac since Kovac helped bring a previous Meciar government down in 1994 -- has made several attempts to delay or postpone the presidential referendum.</p>
<p>The Constitutional Court this week rejected two government motions to declare the presidential referendum illegal.</p>
<p>Opposition parties called on voters to register but reject ballots with three questions and insist on papers with four.</p>
<p>The ballot on NATO membership asks: Are you in favour of Slovakia's membership in NATO? Are you in favour of the deployment of nuclear weapons on Slovak soil? Are you in favour of establishing military bases in Slovakia?</p>
<p>Some critics have suggested the questions have been phrased to elicit a vote against membership to provide the government with political cover when it fails to win an invitation to join.</p>
<p>The alliance is to hold a summit in Madrid at the beginning of July at which it will invite some former east bloc countries to apply for NATO membership. The Czech Republic, Poland and Hungary are widely expected to be invited.</p>
<p>-- Bratislava Newsroom, 421-7-521-8402</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRATISLAVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVAKIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
