<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608556" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Chase wary on US stocks, sees Dow peak around 7,500.</title>
<headline>Chase wary on US stocks, sees Dow peak around 7,500.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gill</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chase Manhattan Bank is wary about U.S. equity market prospects and expects the Dow to peak at around 7,500 later this year.</p>
<p>Mark Richardson, Chase chief investment officer of global asset management, told Reuters the U.S. market was unlikely to peak at the moment, but possibly at about 7,500 in August from about 7,300 at the moment.</p>
<p>He said the trigger for a correction could be the U.S. economy moving ahead too strongly, thus leading to higher rates, or more likely an erosion of margins due to rising unit labour costs and the strength of the dollar.</p>
<p>&quot;My problem with the U.S. market is that it is overvalued, but I have been saying that for the last 1,000 points,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>On U.S. rates, he said they would probably go up again, with July the obvious date following the Fed decision to leave rates unchanged at this week's meeting.</p>
<p>Gains in U.S. stocks had been in the large-cap area recently, largely because of their international exposure, while smaller cap domestic stocks had been static or falling.</p>
<p>&quot;These large cap stocks are on very high multiples. I have a certain amount of difficulty buying something like Coca-Cola, which is a super company, on a multiple of 40 with single digit growth,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He added he was wary about equity markets in general given the concerns about U.S. stocks, which were probably not going to do more than mark time for the rest of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;That being the case, it is hard to get too enthused about other markets,&quot; he said, adding that Chase, with $125 billion assets under management, had moved slightly underweight equities, and &quot;somewhat overweight&quot; bonds.</p>
<p>He said he was looking to alternative investments as a risk diversifier, pointing to hedge funds which were market neutral or with a low correlation to the U.S. market.</p>
<p>He added there were two warning flags he would be looking for in the U.S. market. Many players were convinced that the 401K money going into the U.S. equity market would stay invested in times of major uncertainty.</p>
<p>&quot;Let's just say that is not proven...If you are looking for meltdown that is the very obvious place to look.&quot;</p>
<p>Also, high liquidity levels could be squeezed if Japanese investors looked to repatriate their money after past heavy investment in the U.S. and other areas.</p>
<p>&quot;The Japanese had nothing to invest in at home. Their equity market has been flat on its back and bonds yield nothing.</p>
<p>&quot;If they start to repatriate because the dollar weakens or because their own equity market becomes attractive then you have the potential makings of a liquidity crunch outside Japan,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Japanese market was difficult to read, especially with concerns about second quarter economic performance, and despite a strong recent rally.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't believe it yet. It has flattered on one or two other occasions only to deceive. We remain underweight in Japan.&quot;</p>
<p>Chase was positive on Europe, but was taking a stock rather than country selection process.</p>
<p>&quot;If you look across the region you are talking about earnings growth of around 20 percent... (but) it is very stock specific, very spotty.&quot;</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +171 542 5887</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
