<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608536" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Euro oil swaps-CFDs ease back after earlier rocket.</title>
<headline>Euro oil swaps-CFDs ease back after earlier rocket.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European oil swaps were all firmer by varying degrees bar easier fuel oil and unchanged naphtha.</p>
<p>Brent CFDs rocketed higher earlier in the day on the back of physical cargo deal and retained some, but not all of the firmer tone towards the close. May 27-30 CFDs were ranged around 7 cents over July compared with 1.5 cents under July on Thursday, although at one point talk centred around 12 cents over July.</p>
<p>Dated Brent jumped nearly 20 cents on the back of a cargo loading June 9-11 went for July Brent +17 cents and May 27-30 CFDs traded at Brent +10 cents over July.</p>
<p>The sharp tug upwards on CFDs caught some in the market by surprise and prompted speculation as to the physical buyers' two week CFD position.</p>
<p>&quot;They (the physical cargo buyer) are long CFDs next week and short the week after,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>June 2-6 was also a touch stronger with July -12 cents heard done compared with -15 cents yesterday.</p>
<p>Heavy fuel lost about $1 a tonne, although at one point in the day swaps had drifted $2 off Thursday's levels. Trade was done at $82 but prices recovered with June pegged later at $82.50-83.00 and July $84.50-85.00.</p>
<p>Gasoline saw several June swaps concluded with $209.25, $209.50 and $209.75 all understood concluded. July was also thought done at $204.50.</p>
<p>Naphtha faced a quiet day on both swaps and physical markets. June was steady although both June and July did hover 50 cents higher on the back of firm crude.</p>
<p>&quot;It has been very quiet, but what little gains we were showing have been lost with crude losing ground,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 8980</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
