<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608500" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ESTONIA: GOVERNMENT SEES 4-5 PCT GDP GROWTH.</title>
<headline>GOVERNMENT SEES 4-5 PCT GDP GROWTH.</headline>
<dateline>TALLINN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Estonian government said on Friday that its new programme calls for four to five percent GDP growth and aims to hold inflation to 10-12 percent in 1997-98.  </p>
<p>&quot;A conservative fiscal policy, a liberal foreign trade policy suitable for a small country, enterpreneuship based mostly on private ownership and a tax policy and legislative environment that favours economic development will remain the basis of Estonia's economic policy,&quot; the government said.</p>
<p>Estonia's budget and monetary policy will continuously be based on a balanced state budget and currency board, the government said.</p>
<p>The 1998 state budget avoids the rise in tax burden and increases the stake of state investments in state costs.</p>
<p>The government also plans to sign a new memorandum with International Monetary Fund (IMF).  </p>
<p>The government will decrease the stake of direct taxes and increase the stake of indirect taxes, such as excise tax, the said.</p>
<p>The government will favour regional investments, and apply corporate income tax exemptions on investments made in poor regions.</p>
<p>To keep a lid on inflation and maintain economic stability, the government will continue a conservative foreign lending policy, it said.</p>
<p>It will also increase tax collection and reduce the size of the shadow economy and push for cooperation between tax, customs and policy authorities.</p>
<p>The government plans to reduce the state's stake in business and complete the privatisation of industrial, trade, transport and service companies and start the sell-off of infrastructure companies.</p>
<p>It also said that it will continue to seek entry into foreign markets through negotiations with the European Union, Russia, Central and Eastern European countries and other states.</p>
<p>Foreign policy goals include joining the World Trade Organisation this year, it said, adding that the law on customs tariffs needs to be passed fist.</p>
<p>EU integration will remain a top priority.</p>
<p>&quot;We will do everything possible to be in the first group of countries joining the European Union,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The cornerstone of security policy is integration into western defence organisations, NATO membership, and strengthening of the country's own defence abilities.</p>
<p>Estonia will actively continue participation in NATO's Partnership for Partnerhip programme and is ready to support other new NATO initiatives.</p>
<p>-- Eva Palu, Tallinn Newsroom, +372 630 8400, reuters@reuters.ee</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLINN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ESTONIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
