<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608547" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Dirty tanker rates seen staying firm next week.</title>
<headline>Dirty tanker rates seen staying firm next week.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Middle East very large crude carrier (VLCC) dirty tanker rates held firm on Friday with signs that the strength is likely to continue next week, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Looking at the VLCC list, certainly up until 15th June, tonnage is thin on the ground as it has been for a long time and even stretching up to the 20th of the month, choice from a charterer's point of view is very limited,&quot; said brokers Galbraith's Ltd in their weekly tanker report.</p>
<p>&quot;Charterers left with cargoes in this period will surely face higher freight rates. For the back end of June, the picture is not quite so clear but we see no reason for rates to fall from those prevailing today.&quot;</p>
<p>Brokers E.A. Gibson agreed, saying that &quot;with our projected tonnage figures only showing 37 vessels of about 11.3 million tons as being available over the next four weeks, we would expect the present trend to continue.&quot;</p>
<p>Mideast/Japan VLCCs were on Friday fixed at W70, with voyages to Rotterdam at W60 and to the Red Sea at W72.5.</p>
<p>Galbraith's said most of the deals took place on a couple of busy days in the middle of the week, and it was &quot;quite an extraordinary situation to see old ships achieving much higher Worldscale rates than their modern cousins.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The reason can simply be attributed to the fact that the young ships were the first to be booked -- thus leaving only older units available for charterers.</p>
<p>&quot;Owners of these units suddenly found themselves 'holding all the trump cards.'&quot;</p>
<p>West Africa/U.S. VLCCs continued to be fixed at W65, while 130,000 tonne vessels (Suezmaxes) fetched around W90/92.5.</p>
<p>In the Med/Black Sea, Suezmaxes achieved around W95 to U.K./Cont Med and trade on the 80,000 tonne Aframax market was brisk.</p>
<p>Galbraith's said that although recent deals have been around W110-120, &quot;one or two owners are starting to offer at pretty steamy numbers which might suggest increases in the forthcoming period.&quot;</p>
<p>The North Sea Aframax market dipped, however, to about W130/135, some 10 points down from last week.</p>
<p>The Caribbean Aframax market, which has been unusually firm for much of the year, remained resilient at W200, with some brokers taken by surprise each time it bounces back after a dip.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no doubt that natural demand is clearly established in this market but another reason might be the absence of re-lets from the lighterage companies -- for the last few months we have seen very few of these ships competing with other owners, as they are fully employed doing what they should be which is lightering the V's and U's (VLCCs and ULCCs) into the U.S. Gulf,&quot; said Galbraith's.</p>
<p>European fuel oil was also strong with 25,000 tonnes in the north rising to about W240 as the Russian Baltic export season begins.</p>
<p>Industry consultants Petro Logistics said exports from the Baltic and Black Sea in the first week of May totalled around 330,000 barrels per day (bpd), against about 170,000 bpd in the first week of January.</p>
<p>-- Michael Rank, London newsroom +44 171 542 4088</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
