<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608583" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Leaders seek to defuse N. Ireland march dispute.</title>
<headline>Leaders seek to defuse N. Ireland march dispute.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>David Trimble and John Hume, leaders of Northern Ireland's main pro-British and pro-Irish political parties, agreed on Friday to hold talks to try to defuse tension surrounding a hotly-disputed Protestant march.</p>
<p>They said that they would hold separate discussions with both sides of the dispute over the annual Orange Order parade from Drumcree church which last year sparked the worst civic violence for decades.</p>
<p>Trimble, head of the Ulster Unionist Party, which seeks to keep the province British, said in a statement that he would hold talks with the Orange Order, which holds a yearly march at Drumcree on the fringes of the southern town of Portadown.</p>
<p>Hume, head of the Social Democratic and Labour Party (SDLP) said he would be meeting Catholic residents of the Garvaghy Road area of Portadown, who see the parade passing by their houses as intimidation by their Protestant rivals.</p>
<p>Britain's new Labour government, which took office on May 1, says it wants an end to confrontation over the annual &quot;marching season&quot; by Protestants and has urged all communities to negotiate routes and take local sensitivities into account.</p>
<p>Police fear that this year's marching season could be violent because of deadlock in a year-old Northern Ireland peace process and guerrilla attacks by Irish republican and Protestant Loyalist extremists.</p>
<p>The parade is held on the last Sunday in July before the &quot;Glorious Twelth&quot; of July, the climax of the marching season when Protestants celerbate a 300-year-old Protestant victory over a Catholic king.</p>
<p>Last July police banned the parade by the Orange Order, a civil body founded to preserve Northern Ireland's Protestant traditions, after Garvaghy Road residents complained.</p>
<p>But the ban led to province-wide riots by Protestants and police reversed it in a move which ignited Catholic anger and was followed by a bomb attack by a shadowy Irish Republican group against a country hotel.</p>
<p>Trimble said the talks would be held in secret and asked the media not to press for details. He is a memebr of the Orange Order, many of whose membership refuse to alter what they call a birthright and peaceful tradition of marching.</p>
<p>Militant members of the Order allege that the Garvaghy Road residents are being used by Sinn Fein, political wing of Irish Republican Army (IRA) guerrillas fighting to end British rule of Northern Ireland. But Sinn Fein says it is not involved.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
