<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608544" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Reuters historical calendar - May 30.</title>
<headline>Reuters historical calendar - May 30.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the major events to have occurred on May 30 in history:</p>
<p>1431 - Condemned as a heretic by an English dominated church court, Joan of Arc was burnt at the stake at Rouen. She was canonised by Pope Benedict XV in 1920.</p>
<p>1498 - Christopher Columbus set sail with six ships from Sanlucar in Spain on his third voyage of exploration to discover the South Americas.</p>
<p>1536 - In England, King Henry VIII married his third wife, Jane Seymour, just 11 days after the execution of Anne Boleyn.</p>
<p>1574 - Charles IX, king of France from 1560, died. Remembered for his part in ordering the massacre of the protestants on St Bartholomews Day, he was succeeded by brother Henry III.</p>
<p>1593 - Christopher Marlowe, English playwright, who heavily influenced Shakespeare and wrote &quot;Tamburlaine the Great&quot;, was mysteriously killed in a fight in a London tavern.</p>
<p>1640 - Peter Paul Rubens, Flemish baroque painter, died in Antwerp. Famed for his &quot;Descent from the Cross&quot; and his mastery in oil paints, he was also a diplomat.</p>
<p>1744 - Alexander Pope, British poet and satirist, died in London. Best known for mock epic &quot;Rape of the Lock&quot;.</p>
<p>1778 - Francois Marie Arouet, better known as Voltaire, French novelist, historian, playwright, and philosopher, regarded as the embodiment of 18th century enlightenment, died in Paris.</p>
<p>1808 - Napoleon annexed Tuscany and gave it seats in the French Senate.</p>
<p>1842 - John Francis attempted to assassinate Queen Victoria as she rode in her carriage with Prince Albert down Constitution Hill in London.</p>
<p>1848 - The Piedmontese under Charles Albert  defeated the Austrians at the battle of Goito in the Italian War of Independence.</p>
<p>1848 - Under a treaty signed in February 1848 and ratified on this day by Mexico the United States received from Mexico New Mexico, California as well as parts of Nevada, Utah, Arizona and Colorado in return for a payment of 15 million dollars.</p>
<p>1909 - Benny Goodman, U.S. jazz clarinettist, born. He became a leading player with his own bands during the 1930's. He also commissioned works from classical composers including Bartok and Copland.</p>
<p>1911 - The first ever Indianapolis 500 motor race in the United States was run and won by Ray Harroun at an average speed of 74.59 miles per hour.</p>
<p>1912 - Wilbur Wright, pioneering aviator, died. Together with his brother Orville, they made the first ever flight in 1903.</p>
<p>1913 - The First Balkan war between Turkey and the Balkan states ended with the signing of the Treaty of London.</p>
<p>1942 - 1,047 R.A.F. bombers set off to bomb Cologne in the R.A.F.'s first 1,000 bomber raid of World War Two.</p>
<p>1959 - Iraq terminated its military assistance agreement (1954) with the United States as it violated its policy of positive neutrality.</p>
<p>1959 - The first experimental hovercraft, the SR-N1, was launched at Cowes off the Isle of Wight. The craft was designed by Sir Christopher Cockerell.</p>
<p>1960 - Boris Pasternak, Russian novelist and poet, famed for his &quot;Doctor Zhivago&quot;, died in Moscow.</p>
<p>1961 - General Rafael Trujillo, dictator of the Dominican Republic was cut down by machine gun fire on his way to his farm. He was 70.</p>
<p>1967 - Claude Rains, suave British film actor of stage and screen, died. Best known for his roles in the films &quot;Casablanca&quot; and &quot;Notorious&quot;.</p>
<p>1969 - The British Trans-Arctic expedition completed the first surface crossing of the Arctic Ocean.</p>
<p>1971 - Marcel Dupre, French organist and composer, died. He was organist of St Sulpice from 1934-1971.</p>
<p>1971 - U.S. probe Mariner 9 was launched on its mission to Mars. It became the first artificial satellite of Mars sending back more than 7,000 pictures.</p>
<p>1980 - The first Papal visit to France since 1814 took place when John Paul II arrived in Paris.</p>
<p>1981 - President Ziaur Rahman of Bangladesh was shot by a group of rebel officers in the government guest house at Chittagong in an attempted coup by Major General Manzur Ahmed.</p>
<p>1992 - The United Nations Security Council voted to impose sanctions against Serb-led Yugoslavia in a bid to halt the fighting in Bosnia.</p>
<p>1996 - In Britain, the marriage of Prince Andrew to the Duchess of York, known to millions as Fergie, ended by decree in a London court.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
