<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608643" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Who's who in Kabila's government.</title>
<headline>Who's who in Kabila's government.</headline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laurent Kabila, self-proclaimed president of the Democratic Republic of Congo, on Thursday night announced some of the members of his government.</p>
<p>Kabila had been under pressure to name veteran civilian politician Etienne Tshisekedi as prime minister but thus far has excluded him. Aides said Kabila's government was a &quot;presidential regime&quot; and would include no prime minister.</p>
<p>Here are brief details on the main ministers named so far.</p>
<p>Interior Minister Mwenze Kongolo: Soft-spoken and married to an American woman he met while studying at Temple University in the United States, Mwenze was working in a district attorney's office in Pennsylvania when he came into contact with other members of Kabila's alliance through the Internet. An ethnic Mukongo from the mineral-rich southern province of Katanga, he is a close confidant of Kabila.</p>
<p>Information Minister Raphael Ghenda: A lawyer and long-term exile, Ghenda spent 29 years abroad, mostly in France and Belgium, before returning to Zaire in November to join Kabila's rebellion. He is from the central Kasai region and the same Batetela ethnic group as murdered independence prime minister Patrice Lumumba. He is a reader of the works of late North Korean leader Kim Il Sung and runs re-education seminars for government officials. Despite heading the sensitive information department, he is not a member of Kabila's inner circle.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Mawampanga Mwana Nanga: Educated in the United States where he lived for more than 10 years, Mawampanga was studying economics at post-graduate level in Kentucky when he joined the alliance early this year. A basketball fanatic, Mawampanga is the brains behind the alliance's free market economic policies. He is a Mukongo from the coastal Bas Zaire province.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Bizima Karaha: Karaha, 29, is the youngest member of Kabila's inner circle. A Banyamulenge and an orphan, he is a pediatrician by profession who joined the alliance in December and rose quickly to become a confidant of Kabila. South African-educated, he is considered by Western diplomats as an uncompromising hardliner.</p>
<p>Public Service Minister Justine Kasavubu: Daughter of Zaire's first president, Joseph Kasavubu. She previously ran a vociferous anti-Mobutu campaign as a spokeswoman for Tshisekedi's Union for Democracy and Social Progress (UDPS) based in Brussels.</p>
<p>Mines Minister Mututulo Kambale: A former English language professor at the University of Beni in eastern Zaire, he trained in New York and ran a charity in North Kivu.</p>
<p>Planning Minister Babi Mbayi: Babi spent 10 years in France and joined the alliance last November, one month after Kabila launched his rebellion in eastern Zaire. In talks with businessmen and heads of parastatals on Monday, Babi said the alliance sought &quot;a free market social economy&quot; where competition would be encouraged but with rules about fair treatment of employees enshrined in law.</p>
<p>Post and Telecommunications Minister Kinkela Vikansi: A well known Kinshasa lawyer who as a student in the 1960s was at the forefront of the struggled against Mobutu's regime. He was imprisoned several times. Kinkela formed the hardline opposition Patriotic Front when Mobutu announced a return to multi-party politics in 1990.</p>
<p>Health and Social Affairs Minister Jean Baptiste Sonji: A medical doctor who was sacked from state-run mining company Gecamines for his anti-Mobutu stance. He is a member of Kinkela's party and now works at Kinshasa's main hospital.</p>
<p>Agriculture Minister Paul Bandoma: Has been a close ally of Tshisekedi and one of the key members of his UDPS. From Mobutu's northern Equateur region, Bandoma twice served as minister of defence under Tshisekedi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
