<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608699" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Three parties left in SAfrica Sunair sale - paper.</title>
<headline>Three parties left in SAfrica Sunair sale - paper.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Just three consortiums are left in the race for a 100 percent stake in the soon-to-be privatised South African regional airline Sun Air, Business Report said on Friday.</p>
<p>Air France, the Sanco-Ukhozi consortium and Maru Investments have all pulled out of the bidding, leaving only three consortiums in the race for the airline, the paper said.</p>
<p>The three -- namely the Virgin Atlantic -Bhekilanga consortium, Rethabile Comair and a consortium including Phoenix Venture Partners, Bidvest and the Women's Investment Portfolio -- confirmed on Thursday they would go ahead with their bids.</p>
<p>The three consortiums had presented their non-binding tender documents to BoE Natwest-Moseneke &amp; Partners, the advisers to Sun Air's restructuring committee on Thursday.</p>
<p>Transport department spokesman Didi Moyle said the tender documents would be evaluated by the Sun Air restructuring committee on Friday, before a cabinet oversight committee made a decision next Thursday.</p>
<p>Analysts have speculated that the deal could fetch 150-200 million rand but sources close to the deal said this week the amount could be far less, between 50 million rand and 90 million rand, according to a newspaper report.</p>
<p>Public Enterprises Minister Stella Sigcau has said no final decision had been taken on how to use the proceeds of the full privatisation of Sun Air, the second major selloff by the government following the sale of a 30 percent stake in Telkom earlier this year.</p>
<p>Sun Air has eight aircraft which it successfully operates on routes between Johannesburg, Cape Town and Durban.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
