<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608689" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Changing of the guard at Mobutu's unkempt palace.</title>
<headline>Changing of the guard at Mobutu's unkempt palace.</headline>
<byline>Nicholas Kotch</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Edmond Mbonga hopes Laurent Kabila will want to be surrounded by flowers if he decides to occupy the Mont Ngaliema palace.</p>
<p>Kabila's predecessor in Kinshasa's presidency, Mobutu Sese Seko, liked to have flowers everywhere before things started to fall apart in 1990, politically speaking, and he vacated the building in what is now called the Democratic Republic of Congo.</p>
<p>&quot;I used to change the flower arrangements on Mondays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Sundays. Mobutu's favourites were roses and chrysanthemums,&quot; Mbonga reminisced on Thursday.</p>
<p>He turned up outside the dishevelled palace with hundreds of presidency staff, ranging from gamekeepers to protocol officers. Nervously, they gathered around two senior members of Kabila's Alliance authorities, waiting to hear what their future would be.</p>
<p>Hundreds of combatants, who captured the capital of the country formerly known as Zaire on May 17, stood watching.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no need to be frightened,&quot; said Moise Myarugabo, secretary-general of Kabila's presidency which currently has no fixed abode.</p>
<p>&quot;ALL AT EASE&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We are all quite at ease,&quot; replied one of the crowd of civil servants, not quite convincingly.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to start registering all of you. We must get down to work but first we need to know the names of everybody in each department,&quot; Myarugabo continued.</p>
<p>The exercise was certain to take a long time.</p>
<p>&quot;In the maintenance department there were 293 of us,&quot; said Tanda Molamba, a 37-year-old gamekeeper who looked after the antelopes, waterbucks, chimpanzees and other animals which roamed the palace's gardens during Mobutu's heyday.</p>
<p>Employees of Mobutu's cabinet thought they numbered about 600 and the total workforce, including the secretariat and protocol departments, must have been well over 1,000.</p>
<p>NO PAY, NO WORK</p>
<p>This army of functionaries did virtually no work for the past few years. Mobutu stopped paying them regular salaries, some in 1996 and others as far back as 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;This year we haven't received anything. Last year we got about 200,000 Zaires (then worth about $1.25) a month,&quot; said Tanda, standing near the body of a Mobutu soldier who, judging by the smell, was killed several days ago.</p>
<p>&quot;We went on strike three or four times. Some of us were sacked or victimised,&quot; said Edouard Tshiyekele, challenging the assumption that all those who worked for Mobutu lived well.</p>
<p>But Tshiyekele admits life was good when he joined the presidency, as an official journalist, in 1971.</p>
<p>WORLD TRAVEL</p>
<p>&quot;We travelled all over the country and the world with Mobutu. It was fine until 1990 but then it became misery,&quot; he said, worried like others that Kabila will not re-employ them.</p>
<p>In 1990 Mobutu finally accepted multi-party politics, ending a 25-year period of absolute rule when to be inside the presidency, at whatever level, was a privilege.</p>
<p>After that landmark seven years ago, Mobutu felt uncomfortable at Mont Ngaliema. Residents of the vast city began to jeer him and shout insults at his convoy, a breathtaking offence in the old days.</p>
<p>The president spent more and more time in his home village in the north, Gbadolite, or in his villa in the South of France. When he ventured to the capital he stayed at Nsele, on the river near the airport, or inside the Camp Tshatshi barracks adjoining Mont Ngaliema.</p>
<p>TROOPS MOVE IN</p>
<p>Columns of Alliance troops, many of them English- and Swahili speakers from Rwanda, marched in single file into the presidency and the barracks on Thursday.</p>
<p>None of the Mont Ngaliema staff questioned by a correspondent had cruel words for Mobutu, who at 66 is stricken by cancer and in temporary exile in Togo.</p>
<p>&quot;I would like him to live but also to see the new reality under Mr Kabila. Mobutu had very bad advisers,&quot; said Mbonga.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
