<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608632" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Border closure blocks travel from Kabila's Congo.</title>
<headline>Border closure blocks travel from Kabila's Congo.</headline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laurent Kabila's security forces kept the borders of the Democratic Republic of Congo closed on Friday, despite pressure from foreign diplomats and dozens of journalists trying to leave.</p>
<p>Borders have been officialy closed since Kabila's rebel fighters drove out President Mobutu Sese Seko and seized Kinshasa on May 17. They renamed Africa's third largest country, formerly known as Zaire.</p>
<p>No explanation has been given for stopping people from leaving Kinshasa.</p>
<p>Journalists who have been prevented from travelling for five days said they could wait no longer for official permission to take a boat to Brazzaville, the capital of neighbouring Congo.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm leaving today, either in a boat or a coffin,&quot; said Robert Wiener, a producer with U.S.-based television station Cable News Network (CNN).</p>
<p>He said his team would leave with dug-out canoes that continue to cross the five km (three mile) Congo river between Kinshasa and Brazzaville regardless of the border closure.</p>
<p>A long line of cars and frustrated passengers stretches back from the port where hundreds of people are stranded.</p>
<p>Foreign embassies have intervened to try and get Kabila's Alliance for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire to open the borders and allow their nationals to leave, but to no effect.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no authority that seems able to reopen the border,&quot; said one Western diplomat.</p>
<p>The port is guarded by a handful of fighters who bar access to would be travellers, but are unable to say why the border is shut.</p>
<p>Alliance spokesman Gaetan Kakudji promised that the border would be opened soon, but previous pledges from senior officials have come to nothing.</p>
<p>&quot;I cannot set a date or time, I can only say the border will soon be reopened,&quot; Kakudji told reporters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
