<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608638" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: Zimbabwean shares end Friday weaker.</title>
<headline>Zimbabwean shares end Friday weaker.</headline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zimbabwean industrials lost 45.38 points on Friday as the euphoria of a number of good company results which came out on Wednesday quickly wore off.</p>
<p>Brokers predicted the bourse would see a further three weeks' slump before showing any signs of sustained recovery.</p>
<p>They said the rather gloomy economic outlook prevailing in the country, with inflation rising to 22.4 percent in the year to April from 19.9 percent in March, and interest rates expected to rise in tune, would continue putting a damper on share market activity.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is still waiting for good news before it can recover. Interest rates should come down for one thing,&quot; one broker said, adding that he actually expected them to go up in the coming week on inflationary pressures.</p>
<p>The key industrial index ended the day at 10,012.46, losing 15.72 points during the week.</p>
<p>Counters to lose included hotel and retail giant Meikles which dropped 180 cents to 2,420 while bankers NMB were down 100 cents to 3,100. Wood and glass product maker PGI lost 60 cents to 490, steel window manufacturers Radar eased 55 cents to 375 and haulage firm Clan were 10 cents weaker at 200.</p>
<p>Minings were were quiet with copper producer Mhangura and coal miners Wankie both trading unchanged. The seven share index closed at 1009.05, unchanged from Thursday, but eased 5.31 points on the week.</p>
<p>--Stella Mapenzauswa, Harare Newsroom: +263-4 72 52 27/8/9</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
