<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608671" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: NBS-Boland group shrs at new peaks.</title>
<headline>NBS-Boland group shrs at new peaks.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in some firms in the recently-merged NBS-Boland banking group were strong on Friday ahead of the reshuffling of some of its interests, dealers said.</p>
<p>They said the enlarged financial services operation, which is now South Africa's fifth largest banking group, looked to have further positive developments up its sleeve in view of a cautionary notice earlier this week.</p>
<p>&quot;People are interested because of the big reorganisation. You've got Samgro shares being suspended this evening. There are also rumoured to be more positive things in the pipeline,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>The group said on Wednesday that BOE Natwest Ltd, a stockbroking unit in the group, was in talks with Real Afrika Durolink. It gave no further details.</p>
<p>Shares in Samgro Investment Holdings Ltd, the pyramid holding of Boland Bank Holdings Ltd with a 66.5 percent stake, will be suspended at the close of trade on Friday.</p>
<p>By 0930 GMT Samgro shares were up 20 percent to 21 rand, with the low-voting &quot;N&quot; shares up 32.2 percent to a new year high of 16 rand, the biggest percentage gainer on the bourse. Volumes were, however, light.</p>
<p>Samgro's suspension is neccessary in terms of a Johannesburg Stock Exchange rule requiring a listed pyramid company to hold at least 50 percent of the shares of a subsidiary.</p>
<p>&quot;Flowing from the acquisition by NBS Holdings of the banking and financial services interests of Boland Bank Holdings in exchange for shares, the business of the latter will be wound up in the next few days and its shares distributed to shareholders,&quot; the company said.</p>
<p>Samgro will hold only 14.9 percent of the merged operations of NBS and Boland. It can expnd this to almost 35 percent through the exercise of its option on a further 23 million shares.</p>
<p>Boland and NBS shares were each up 100 cents to new year highs of respectively 63 rand and 94.50 rand.</p>
<p>Shares in the Board of Executors Ltd (BOE), which ealier this year bought a 22.2 percent stake of NBS while the NBS Boland group bought a 24.3 percent stake in BOE, also climbed, adding 150 cents to 149 rand.</p>
<p>BOE parent firm, BOE Corp Ltd in turn put on 110 cents to a new high of 10 rand.</p>
<p>-- Nicole Mordant, Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
