<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608655" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: S.African advisers to help &quot;bankrupt&quot; former Zaire.</title>
<headline>S.African advisers to help &quot;bankrupt&quot; former Zaire.</headline>
<byline>Ben Hirschler</byline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa will finalise plans next week to send a team of experts to Kinshasa to help reconstruct the economy of &quot;bankrupt&quot; former Zaire, Deputy President Thabo Mbeki said on Friday.</p>
<p>Laurent Kabila's government of the new Democratic Republic of Congo would give Pretoria a detailed list of requirements after the weekend, Mbeki told reporters at an investment conference.</p>
<p>Kabila's alliance had made a request for economic assistance during talks held last Sunday and had specifically sought the help of South Africa's central Reserve Bank, which would contribute representatives to the advisory team, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Apart from the political challenges they have got all of these other pressing economic challenges,&quot; Mbeki said.</p>
<p>&quot;The government is bankrupt. The currency has been rejected by the people. But it is not just a matter of printing new banknotes. It is a whole process of restoring a stable and credible financial system in the country.&quot;</p>
<p>Mbeki said South African experts had already begun studying the economic problems inherited from the regime of Mobutu Sese Seko, overthrown last weekend by Kabila's forces after a seven- month advance on the capital.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been looking as a matter of urgency at the state of the economy and public administration to try and identify what needs to be done,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He reiterated his support for Kabila and said it was unreasonable for the international community to expect him to rush into holding elections given the confusion in the country and the lack of any electoral roll of voters.</p>
<p>South Africa, which spearheaded attempts to ensure a peaceful transition in Zaire, is keen to see a stable economy emerge from the strife in Africa's third largest country.</p>
<p>Mbeki said this should include a position for former Zaire as the 13th member of the Southern African Development Community (SADC), the 12-nation grouping stretching from South Africa to Tanzania which aims to establish a free trade area by 2005.</p>
<p>Analysts believe former Zaire has huge economic potential which may at last be unlocked following the change of government.</p>
<p>Hopes centre on the mining industry -- Zaire was once the world's largest copper producer -- which has sunk into chronic disrepair but is now attracting renewed interest from international mining houses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
