<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608647" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: Mozambique plans to open stock market in 1998.</title>
<headline>Mozambique plans to open stock market in 1998.</headline>
<byline>Ben Hirschler</byline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mozambique plans to open a stock exchange in 1998 with listings likely to include key privatised companies, Prime Minister Pascoal Mocumbi said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect the exchange to start next year,&quot; he told reporters during a World Economic Forum conference in Harare.</p>
<p>No decisions had yet been taken about which companies would list on the market but Mocumbi said recently privatised enterprises were obvious candidates.</p>
<p>Mozambique has pursued an aggressive privatisation programme in recent years, selling off a total of more than 700 state enterprises to date.</p>
<p>Most have been small-scale businesses but some larger companies have also been privatised, including the state airline in which the government now holds a minority 49 percent stake.</p>
<p>Mocumbi said the government was now considering divesting that remaining stake in the flag carrier via a stock exchange listing.</p>
<p>&quot;We have not yet privatised our insurance companies or our telecommunications so there are various possibilities for other listings,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Mozambique, one of the poorest countries in the world, was devastated by 16 years of civil war which ended in 1992. But since then economic activity has started to pick up, and a structural adjustment has stabilised the currency and brought inflation under control.</p>
<p>Inflation last year was 16.6 percent and Mocumbi said he hoped to see it down below 10 percent this year.</p>
<p>Mozambique will be joining a growing band of southern African countries opting to establish their own stock markets, both to boost local access to capital and to signal support for market-orientated economic reform.</p>
<p>The 12-nation Southern African Development Community (SADC) now boasts eight regional stock exchanges in South Africa, Zimbabwe, Botswana, Namibia, Mauritius, Zambia, Malawi and Swaziland.</p>
<p>Tanzania plans to open its bourse for business later this year.</p>
<p>Emerging market analysts have reported a growing interest in sub-Saharan stock markets this year from specialist Africa fund managers.</p>
<p>Many have been enticed by the spectacular performance of the Zimbabwe Stock Exchange in 1996 when industrial shares leapt by over 90 percent in U.S. dollar terms at a time when South African shares -- traditionally investors' only window on Africa -- were taking a beating.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOZAM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
