<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608665" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.Africa gets 4 bids for Sun Air sale.</title>
<headline>S.Africa gets 4 bids for Sun Air sale.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa's Ministry for Public Enterprise and Transport said on Friday it had received four non-binding bids for the upcoming privatisation of domestic carrier Sun Air.  </p>
<p>Bids include the Malaysia Airlines Consortium, the Consortium and the Phoenix Venture Partners Consortium.  </p>
<p>A shorlist will be drawn from the four bids and will be announced on May 30, the ministry said.</p>
<p>It added that short-listed parties would commence due diligence investigations of Sun Air from June 3 and binding bids from short-listed parties are expected in early July.</p>
<p>&quot;Government is happy to announce that four non-binding bids were received by the transaction advisors BOE NatWest Ltd on behalf of the Sun Air restructuring committee,&quot; a statement from the ministry said.</p>
<p>The deadline for bids was 1400 GMT on Thursday.  </p>
<p>Analysts have speculated that the sale of Sun Air could fetch 150-200 million rand.</p>
<p>Public Enterprises Minister Stella Sigcau has said no final decision had been taken on how to use the proceeds of the full privatisation of Sun Air, the second major selloff by the government following the sale of a 30 percent stake in Telkom earlier this year.</p>
<p>Sun Air has eight aircraft which it successfully operates on routes between Johannesburg, Cape Town and Durban.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
