<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608603" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: PRESS DIGEST - Canada - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Canada - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the headlines from selected Canadian newspapers. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>THE GLOBE AND MAIL:</p>
<p>- Manning calls rivals unity threat: Reform Leader casts Chretien, Charest with separatists, and new ad echoes theme.</p>
<p>- NDP Leader supports euthanasia: Wants guidelines if consent clear.</p>
<p>- B.C. cancels military lease: Presses Ottawa, U.S. on salmon.</p>
<p>- Yeltsin fires military leaders: Defence minister, top commander blamed for blocking reform of armed forces.</p>
<p>- Science squirms under the microscope: A series of painful revelations at the Morin inquiry make it plain that forensic scientists are not infallible and their findings can be misused.</p>
<p>REPORT ON BUSINESS:</p>
<p>- Blue chips lead TSE to record: 300-share index gains on strong fundamentals, investors' comfort in quality, analysts say.</p>
<p>- GM ponders making hybrid vehicle in Oshawa: Minivan-sport utility mix expected for 2001, sources say.</p>
<p>- Hibernia oil platform sets sail today: Tow-out of structure to Grand Banks marks end of six years of construction and beginning of production setup.</p>
<p>- Bre-X's Felderhof surrenders prospector of the year award: No one to receive prize; TSE named in suit against firm.</p>
<p>- Tee-Comm pushed into receivership: Board resigns after Bank of Montreal makes move.</p>
<p>THE FINANCIAL POST:</p>
<p>- Tee-Com slides into receivership: Satellite TV firm's five-man board resigns after Bank of Montreal demands repayment of credit facility.</p>
<p>- TSE named in new Bre-X class action suit.</p>
<p>((Paul Simao, Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8104))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
