<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608623" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Kabila will not appoint PM in former Zaire - aide.</title>
<headline>Kabila will not appoint PM in former Zaire - aide.</headline>
<byline>Matthew Tostevin</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laurent Kabila, self-proclaimed president of the former Zaire, named an incomplete government and will not appoint a prime minister, one of his chief lieutenants told reporters early on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be no prime minister. It is a presidential regime,&quot; Gaetan Kakudji of the victorious Alliance which ousted ex-President Mobutu Sese Seko on May 17 told a news conference.</p>
<p>Just before midnight on Thursday, state radio broadcast Kabila's incomplete list of 13 ministers in a transitional government.</p>
<p>There was no mention of a prime minister -- the post which Kabila was under foreign and domestic pressure to hand to veteran civilian politician Etienne Tshisekedi.</p>
<p>Political analysts said Kakudji's statement showed Kabila, who proclaimed himself president last Saturday as his Alliance rebels marched into Kinshasa, had decided to exclude the powerful Tshisekedi, whose supporters demanded a role in the new administration.</p>
<p>Kabila's Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo-Zaire (ADFL) began their long trek across Zaire, since renamed by him, from Lake Kivu in the east last October and finally reached the Atlantic at Matadi, the country's only port.</p>
<p>State television said they took the port near the Angolan border &quot;without meeting any resistance&quot;, but did not say when.</p>
<p>Matadi is also a rail terminal near the country's only refinery and the huge Inga hydro-electric dam. It was the only major city not yet controlled by Kabila's guerrillas who captured Kinshasa on Saturday.</p>
<p>Thousands of Hutus were reported to have crossed into Angola and the Congolese government in Brazzaville sent barges with military escorts up the Congo River to try to assemble refugees crossing from ex-Zaire.</p>
<p>Armed men thought to be from Kabila's alliance looted the Kinshasa home of exiled former prime minister Kengo wa Dondo, taking televisions, videos, stereos, computers and 50 pairs of shoes.</p>
<p>Ousted dictator Mobutu Sese Seko's defeated soldiers looted widely for 48 hours after their defeat, but alliance forces had built up a solid reputation for discipline during their seven-month campaign.</p>
<p>Many former soldiers loyal to Mobutu were reported fleeing towards Matadi and officials in Angola said about 25,000 people, including armed men, had crossed over from Kabila's Congo.</p>
<p>In a sign of growing international acceptance of the new order, the United Nations said it had been officially told that Kinshasa's envoy now represented Kabila.</p>
<p>It also said it would comply with a letter informing it that the country was reviving the name, flag and anthem that it adopted soon after independence from Belgium in 1960.</p>
<p>The European Union said it hoped for a broad-based transitional government and would send a mission to convey its views to Kabila.</p>
<p>In Kinshasa, hundreds of militants demonstrated in solidarity outside Tshisekedi's home. Their leaders worked the crowd to a frenzy with speeches reminding Kabila that their own campaign paved the way for the overthrow of Mobutu, who is now in Togo.</p>
<p>&quot;We put Mobutu in a political ambulance and the AFDL took him to the cemetery,&quot; declared close Tshisekedi associate Joseph Olengankoy.</p>
<p>Kabila arrived in Kinshasa on Tuesday from his alliance's temporary headquarters in the southern city of Lubumbashi but has since remained out of public view as he prepares his cabinet.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
