<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608674" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CONGO: Neighbour Congo notes Kabila takeover in ex-Zaire.</title>
<headline>Neighbour Congo notes Kabila takeover in ex-Zaire.</headline>
<dateline>BRAZZAVILLE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Neighbour Congo on Friday noted the change of power across the river in former Zaire and said it was ready to support the efforts of the new authorities there to promote democracy.</p>
<p>A statement read on state radio by Foreign Minister Destin Arsene Tsaty-Mboungou said the government wanted to maintain &quot;brotherly relations&quot; with its larger neighbour but it did not mention self-proclaimed president Laurent Kabila by name.</p>
<p>In a tacit acknowledgement of Kabila's decision to rename Zaire as the Democratic Republic of Congo, its tiny neighbour referred to itself as Congo Brazzaville -- the name it used before 1971 when the two nations had the name Congo in common.</p>
<p>&quot;Congo Brazzaville takes note of the arrival of the new authorities and expresses its complete readiness to support their efforts at democratic restructuring,&quot; the minister said.</p>
<p>The statement, agreed by the government at a special cabinet meeting earlier this week, also appealed for international aid to help with an influx of refugees from former Zaire. Aid workers put the total at up to 8,000, mostly Rwandan Hutus.</p>
<p>Congo president, Pascal Lissouba, was a friend of Zaire's ousted president Mobutu Sese Seko. But the Brazzaville authorities, keen to maintain friendly ties with their neighbour, have been working to find alternative homes in exile for members of Mobutu's clan who fled there.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRAZZAVILLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
