<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608680" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Industry welcomes SAfrica state oil restructuring.</title>
<headline>Industry welcomes SAfrica state oil restructuring.</headline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa's oil industry has welcomed the government's decision to restructure its oil assets and invite private sector participation, particularly by blacks.</p>
<p>Minerals and Energy Minister Penuell Maduna said this week that he planned to establish a national oil company to be listed on the Johannesburg Stock Exchange in due course.</p>
<p>South African Petroleum Industry Association (SAPIA) director Colin McClelland told Reuters that the industry was aware of and supported the need for greater black involvement.</p>
<p>&quot;We welcome further black advancement in the industry and it is refreshing to see government looking at its assets and wanting to add vaue to them while assisting black empowerment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But the playing fields should be level for all investors other than things constitutionally done to assist blacks.&quot;</p>
<p>Maduna said the new company would be formed through the restructuring of the state-owned Central Energy Fund and its string of oil storage and production subsidiaries.</p>
<p>When appropriate, the company could be listed on the JSE with the government retaining majority control.</p>
<p>This would provide a vehicle for black involvement in the industry while adding value to state oil assets, which include an offshore oilfield, oil from gas producer Mossgas and three pipelines running from the eastern port city of Durban to the country's industrial heartland centred on Gauteng province.</p>
<p>Analysts said that state-owned oil exploration company Soekor, which has already sold 20 percent of its first oilfield to Energy Africa Ltd, might be expected to sell off some shares to black groups.</p>
<p>The pipelines could also be partially sold off to black interests.</p>
<p>One analyst said the oil majors -- Shell South Africa Ltd, BP, Total SA, Engen Ltd and Caltex -- were unlikely to be happy if the government favoured the state oil company over and above the others.</p>
<p>&quot;Another danger would be if the government made decisions about issues such as margin increases based purely on the state oil company's needs and not the best interests of the economy,&quot; the analyst said.</p>
<p>-- Cape Town newsroom +27 21 25-2238</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
