<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608630" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Move to postpone Nigerian elections cause ripples.</title>
<headline>Move to postpone Nigerian elections cause ripples.</headline>
<byline>James Jukwey</byline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nigerian pro-democracy activists fear that the transition from military rule could be jeopardised by politicians' attempts to postpone key elections until next year.</p>
<p>The country's five registered political parties met the electoral commission NECON and other agencies supervising the transition programme this week and asked them to consider delaying state assembly and governorship polls set for later this year and holding them along with federal polls in late 1998.</p>
<p>The current transition timetable is as follows:</p>
<p>1997</p>
<p>3rd quarter  -- elections of state legislators</p>
<p>4th quarter  -- election of state governors</p>
<p>1998</p>
<p>2nd quarter  -- election of national assembly</p>
<p>3rd quarter  -- election of federal president</p>
<p>    October 1    -- handover of power</p>
<p>Some political groups want the elections bunched together, saying this would save costs and make the transition less cumbersome.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody wants to transit forever,&quot; said Ibrahim Mantu, spokesman of the United Nigeria Congress Party (UNCP), the leading party in municipal council elections held in March, the only ones contested so far on a party basis.</p>
<p>&quot;The remaining elections should be held (in the space of) three weeks in the third quarter of next year so that members of the house of representatives, senate and president can be sworn in on the same day,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>According to Mantu, state assembly and governorship polls could be held on the same Saturday, those of the federal assembly and senate the next Saturday and the presidential poll on the following Saturday, as was done in 1979.</p>
<p>&quot;The suggestion that the governorship polls should be moved to next year is in the best interest of the country because it will bring order into implementing the (transition programme) activities,&quot; said Festus Okubor, spokesman for the Grassroots Democratic Movement, one of the five parties.</p>
<p>But pro-democracy activists immediately fired back that the plan was further evidence that General Sani Abacha's government was not sincere about restoring democracy because this would mean amending the transition timetable.</p>
<p>&quot;Such retrogressive recommendation has exposed all the key actors in the tripartite organs of the regime as co-conspirators with the military junta in its bid to hold the nation to ransom,&quot; said the Campaign for Democracy pressure group.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not a good omen for democracy,&quot; said Onikepo Oshodi, an aspiring governorship candidate in Lagos state.</p>
<p>Abacha's opponents already view the transition plan unveiled in 1995 at the peak of local and foreign pressure for a restoration of democracy, as a ruse for him to hang onto power.</p>
<p>Annulment of a presidential vote in 1993 that would have restored democracy plunged Nigeria into turmoil and the hanging in 1995 of nine minority rights activists, including author Ken Saro-Wiwa, caused the country's isolation by the West.</p>
<p>Calls by loyalists for Abacha to contest the presidential poll and turn himself into an elected ruler have increased the suspicion that the military does not intend to hand over power.</p>
<p>Local newspapers speculate that the military ruling council will meet next week to consider the request to shift the polls.</p>
<p>If this happens it will be the second time Abacha has juggled the timetable. The municipal council polls held in March were originally scheduled for the last quarter of 1996.</p>
<p>The political parties argue that shifting the elections will not stop Abacha handing over power on October 1, 1998.</p>
<p>What no one can say is whether he will be handing over to someone other than to an elected Abacha.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
