<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608672" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: PRESS DIGEST - Nigeria - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Nigeria - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are significant stories in the Nigerian press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAILY TIMES</p>
<p>- Police arrest 50 Nigeria Airways staff over theft of digital computer of the national carrier's A 310 aircraft.</p>
<p>- Customs department is to trim the number of its checkpoints in the country in order to speed evacuation of goods from ports, says customs boss Brigadier-General Sam Ango</p>
<p>- Detained presidential claimant Moshood Abiola is well and being held in a &quot;beautiful bungalow&quot; in capital Abuja, says his doctor Ore Falomo, who was allowed to meet Abiola recently.</p>
<p>- Work resumes on upgrading Forcados oil terminal following end of hostilities between two tribes in the area over the relocation of the municipal council headquarters.</p>
<p>THE GUARDIAN</p>
<p>- Visiting European Union official Tim Clarke says his mission is to explore channels for improving dialogue with Nigeria, assess transition to civil rule programme and determine conditions to be fulfilled to fund poverty alleviation projects.</p>
<p>- British aviation officials may arrive in Nigeria on Friday to carry out safety checks on Nigeria Airways planes. The two countries last week banned each other's aircraft in their airspace.</p>
<p>- Foreign exchange demand falls by 20 percent to $63.7 million at latest weekly auction from $80 million last week.</p>
<p>- Bankers at an industry seminar in Lagos score government low on measures taken so far to deal with distressed banks.</p>
<p>- France's Peugeot, which assembles cars in the north, does not plan to leave Nigeria despite parlous state of the nation's economy, says the company's Africa director Bernard Morot.</p>
<p>THISDAY</p>
<p>- Government officials barred from making public comments on issues outside their &quot;purview,&quot; according to an official circular issued in the capital Abuja.</p>
<p>- A member of the ruling council, Rear-Admiral Festus Porbeni slumps at a rally in support of the military government staged on Thursday in Port Harcourt in the southeast.</p>
<p>- Nestle Foods Plc share price hits 89 naira, the highest priced stock on the Nigerian stock exchange.</p>
<p>($1=85)</p>
<p>-- Lagos newsroom +234 1 2630317</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
