<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608659" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.Africa loses second top official in a week.</title>
<headline>S.Africa loses second top official in a week.</headline>
<byline>Brendan Boyle</byline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African Housing Minister Sankie Mthembi-Mahanyele has accepted the resignation of her top aide in the second high-profile clash in a week between a minister and a senior official.</p>
<p>Mthembi-Mahanyele said Director General of Housing Billy Cobbett would go because of a personality clash, but the reputable Mail and Guardian weekly newspaper said he was sacked because he blew the whistle on a possibly corrupt housing deal.</p>
<p>Last week, Finance Minister Trevor Manuel accepted the resignation of South African Revenue Services chief executive Piet Liebenberg, a respected former banker, in a row over the degree of autonomy to be granted to the tax collection agency.</p>
<p>Earlier this month most members of the statutory Independent Broadcasting Authority set up to oversee the dismantling of apartheid-based radio and television resigned amidst allegations of corruption and personal enrichment.</p>
<p>Mthembi-Mahanyele told reporters on Thursday that Cobbett would leave the ministry after three years because she and he could not work together.</p>
<p>&quot;It has been very difficult. We don't see things in the same way...It was becoming more and more difficult. The tension was rising,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Cobbett, a veteran anti-apartheid activist, was the architect of the government's programme to build a million houses in the first five years of democratic rule. He has not yet commented in public on the ruckus.</p>
<p>According to the Mail and Guardian, he was sacked because he reported his suspicions about a possibly corrupt housing contract to the Auditor General, naming a bank official involved in low-cost housing who was dismissed this week for unrelated offences.</p>
<p>&quot;The 185 million rand ($41.5 million) Mpumalanga Rural Housing Project -- the largest yet under the government's housing subsidy scheme -- was awarded in January to an unregistered company run by...a friend of the housing minister,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>Mthembi-Mahanyele acknowledged that a difference of opinion over the Mpumalanga housing project had been the issue over which she and Cobbett had split.</p>
<p>But she said it was a result of their different working styles and outlooks and the fact that Cobbett unilaterally reported the matter to the Auditor General, the state's independent watchdog on public spending.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a lot of work for people who deal with housing. I think we should look at what we are supposed to do and not create battlefields,&quot; she said at a news conference.</p>
<p>Nedcor Bank Ltd executive director Mike Leeming confirmed in a statement on Friday that Kevin Gibb, general manager of personal credit, was sacked after an internal inquiry.</p>
<p>He said Gibb was dismissed because of unrelated irregularities that arose out of an investigation into the Mpumalanga housing project.</p>
<p>&quot;We did not investigate Gibb's alleged involvement in this housing project as we were advised...that the Auditor General had been requested to investigate the awarding of the contract to a newly formed company called Motheo,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Mail and Guardian said Cobbett had raised concerns about the award of the tender to Motheo because the company did not yet exist at the time the contract was awarded.</p>
<p>President Nelson Mandela's three-year-old government, which is the first to be democratically elected, has been rocked by a series of tender and corruption scandals.</p>
<p>The Health Ministry was forced last year to cancel a multi-million rand AIDS-awareness play, Sarafina Two, because of improper tender procedures.</p>
<p>Several members of a state-owned Transnet transport company were disciplined last year or forced to repay large sums spent on corporate credit cards for purchases not related to work.</p>
<p>The Deputy Speaker of Parliament is awaiting the report on an official inquiry into allegations that she was awarded a driving licence without going through the usual procedures.</p>
<p>($=4.46 rand)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
