<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608675" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: PRESS DIGEST - Kenya - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Kenya - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Kenyan press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAILY NATION</p>
<p>- Church in Kenya gives government ultimatum to effect minimal constitutional reforms before next election.</p>
<p>- Kenya's Wildlife Service director David Western says Kenya will oppose proposal to re-introduce ivory trade banned in 1989.</p>
<p>- President Daniel arap Moi rejects calls for presidential commission to collate views of Kenyans on constitutional reforms.</p>
<p>EAST AFRICAN STANDARD</p>
<p>- The anti-narcotics police are investigating 12 policemen who allegedly took 3.5 million shillings from drug barons they caught with 24 tonnes of hashish and then resigned their posts to take up business.</p>
<p>- Eight people are feared dead while 400 may be displaced following a security operation to retrieve stolen animals in Isiolo district of eastern Kenya.</p>
<p>- An arrest warrant is issued against a Nairobi business tycoon who recently defrauded 14 local financial institutions and major companies of more than two billion shillings.</p>
<p>KENYA TIMES</p>
<p>- The City Inspectorate department says hawkers who have invaded the city's central business district are being used as a political ploy to hold the government to ransom.</p>
<p>- A professor of public law at the University of Nairobi says the calls for constitutional reforms were no longer geared at honestly restructuring Kenya's political order and says that meaningful reforms needed a minimum of three years.</p>
<p>THE PEOPLE</p>
<p>- The struggle for uncontrolled access to President Moi threatens to split a group of elite leaders from the populous Kikuyu tribe even before they make any tangible progress in leading back the opposition dominated community back to the ruling party.</p>
<p>- A fierce behind the scenes battle erupts between motor businessman Manish Shah of Kingsway Motors and the proprietors of a Nairobi based bank following the mysterious disappearance of an Asian businessman who defrauded the bank of 20 million shillings.</p>
<p>($1=54 Kenya shillings)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
