<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608644" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Oil partners say Nigeria can raise its market share.</title>
<headline>Oil partners say Nigeria can raise its market share.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nigeria's joint venture oil partners believe it can raise its share of the world energy market to five per cent by the year 2010.</p>
<p>&quot;Nigeria's share of world energy market can grow from the three percent level now to five percent by 2010, by increasing production capacity and reserves,&quot; the partners said in a joint proposal to a Vision 2010 committee planning Nigeria's future.</p>
<p>Nigeria, a member of OPEC, currently can produce about 2.14 million barrels per day (bpd) of oil with reserves put at 24 billion barrels as at the end of 1996.</p>
<p>Nigeria's joint venture partners are Royal Dutch Shell Group, Mobil Corp, Chevron Corp, Agip SpA, Elf Aquitaine and Texaco Inc.</p>
<p>The government holds an average of 57 percent equity in the local units of the multinationals.</p>
<p>Their joint proposal said Nigeria's government would need to establish and maintain a fiscal framework that would encourage investments as well as an appropriate mechanism for funding the government share of oil exploration and production activities.</p>
<p>The funding options they proposed include reducing the government's holding in its present joint ventures with multinational oil firms in phases and over a period of time to a pre-determined level.</p>
<p>This, they said would do away with the government's present inability to pay cash-calls, its share of the exploration and production costs of the joint ventures that operate Nigeria's oil industry.</p>
<p>&quot;The strategies should see Nigeria's production rising to 4.5 million barrels daily and 50 billion barrels reserve level by the year 2010,&quot; their proposal said.</p>
<p>The oil firms said the government should make funding cash-calls a priority basis and all new oil leases should be based on Production Sharing Contracts (PSCs).</p>
<p>Under the PSCs, which are already in operation with some foreign oil firms, the companies fund solely their exploration costs and recover it if oil is struck.</p>
<p>--Lagos newsroom +234 1 2630317</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
