<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608636" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Kinshasa jumpy, puzzled, after Kabila's first days.</title>
<headline>Kinshasa jumpy, puzzled, after Kabila's first days.</headline>
<byline>Nicholas Kotch</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>After his sure-footed military campaign to take over Zaire, Laurent Kabila's first steps in power have left many of his citizens puzzled and nervous.</p>
<p>&quot;I have two feelings: expectation and fear. We are waiting for the change we want so badly and yet we are frightened about the future,&quot; said Gilbert, a lay Catholic social worker.</p>
<p>Insecurity, the presence of foreign African troops and the absence of nationalist opposition leader Etienne Tshisekedi from Kabila's first and still incomplete government are all components in a mood of uncertainty in Kinshasa.</p>
<p>After the euphoria of last weekend, the great capital of the country Kabila has renamed the Democratic Republic of Congo is a jumpy and worried city.</p>
<p>That sentiment rose after Kabila's Alliance troops fired into the air on Friday to disperse a few hundred pro-Tshisekedi marchers protesting, after only six days, against what they see as a creeping dictatorship.</p>
<p>Across the city, ordinary people report criminal and high- handed behaviour by men claiming to be in the Alliance.</p>
<p>More ominously, there is growing resentment about the presence of Rwandan and probably other foreign troops in the city. The Alliance has worked hard for months to deny and conceal the involvement of such troops but in Kinshasa, now the goal has been reached, the evidence is overwhelming.</p>
<p>Many speak only English or Swahili, an impossible combination for Zairean nationals. Kinshasa's newspapers say the forces include Rwandans, Ugandans, Burundians and Angolans, recruited to the cause of toppling dictator Mobutu Sese Seko.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi voiced the opinion of many when he thanked neighbouring countries for their help.</p>
<p>&quot;But I am asking them to recall their forces...so that Zaireans can resolve their problems between Zaireans,&quot; he said, refusing to accept Kabila's right to decree the country's name change.</p>
<p>Kabila was entitled to a honeymoon period after his Alliance entered Kinshasa on May 17, ending the 32-year rule of Mobutu, modern Africa's supreme potentate.</p>
<p>&quot;The nation must be thankful to (Kabila) for ridding it of one of the most Machiavellian and cynical dictators,&quot; law professor Ntumba Luaba Lumu wrote in Friday's La Reference newspaper.</p>
<p>But the post-Mobutu era has begun and 56-year-old Kabila, a former Marxist guerrilla who has lived in exile for many years, needs to prove he has a fair hand on the tiller as well as a firm one.</p>
<p>&quot;A fracture is looming, clouds are gathering on the horizon,&quot; said Le Phare in its editorial on Friday.</p>
<p>Kabila has not said political parties will be free to operate, in a country thirsty for freedoms, and he has suspended the democratic transitional constitution which men like Tshisekedi laboriously negotiated with Mobutu before his fall.</p>
<p>He has angered some by proclaiming himself president instead of waiting for some neutral authority to do so.</p>
<p>Curiously, he has made no address to the nation of 40 million or any public appearances since he arrived in Kinshasa, unannounced, on Tuesday night.</p>
<p>Kabila has remained cloistered with senior figures in the Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo (AFDL), a coalition of opponents formed last October at the start of his rebellion in eastern Zaire.</p>
<p>The outcome of their deliberations so far was Thursday night's delayed announcement of an incomplete government list.</p>
<p>Crucially, there was no place for Tshisekedi and the Alliance said it would not appoint a prime minister -- the most obvious job for Kabila's only rival when credit is given for toppling Mobutu.</p>
<p>&quot;We put Mobutu in a political ambulance and the AFDL took him to the cemetery,&quot; Tshisekedi's close associate, Joseph Olengankoy, said on Thursday.</p>
<p>On Friday, 300 to 400 Tshisekedi supporters marched through Kinshasa, calling Kabila a dictator before Alliance troops fired into the air. The demonstration was tiny but it was also a jarring first note of discord.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi has been an infuriating and unfathomable man for the foreign diplomats in Zaire. He sleeps a lot, is inflexible and seldom does what Westerners expect.</p>
<p>But his consistency and sense of justice, standing almost alone for years against Mobutu, explain the passionate strand in relations between Tshisekedi and millions of downtrodden people in Africa's third biggest country.</p>
<p>Kabila's camp is unready to honour those qualities.</p>
<p>&quot;Tshisekedi is a spent force. He means very little today,&quot; a senior Alliance supporter said earlier this week.</p>
<p>That hard-nosed judgement is already being put to the test.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
