<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608619" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>sao tome and principe: Sao Tome confirms diplomatic ties with Taiwan.</title>
<headline>Sao Tome confirms diplomatic ties with Taiwan.</headline>
<dateline>SAOTOME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Miguel Trovoada of the African state of Sao Tome and Principe has issued a decree confirming the opening of diplomatic ties with Taiwan despite a parliamentary vote opposing the move, government officials said.</p>
<p>The decree, issued on Thursday night, establishes diplomatic relations with Taiwan effective from May 7 and cannot be challenged under the constitution, the officials said.</p>
<p>On May 14 Sao Tome's parliament voted against an agreement this month to open ties with Taipei, a move that has angered the Chinese government in Beijing.</p>
<p>A senior Chinese diplomat, identified only as Mr Wu, arrived in Sao Tome two weeks ago and was considering whether to recommend cutting China's ties with Sao Tome, Sao Tome officials said.</p>
<p>China said earlier this month that it was resolutely opposed to Sao Tome establishing diplomatic relations with Taiwan, but it stopped short of saying it would cut official ties with the twin-island state.</p>
<p>Beijing has regarded Taiwan as a rebel province since the Chinese Nationalists fled there in 1949 after losing the civil war on the mainland to the Communists.</p>
<p>Since wresting China's U.N. seat from the Nationalists in the 1970s, Beijing has won the recognition of most world governments. Taipei today has diplomatic links with only about 30 states, most of them small, poor and dependent on its financial largesse.</p>
<p>Sao Tome officials said that the African republic had received a pledge from Taiwan to provide aid totalling $30 million over the next decade after deciding to establish ties with Taipei.</p>
<p>Sao Tome Foreign Minister Homero Salvaterra visited Taiwan early this month, where he received $4.3 million as a first instalment, the officials said.</p>
<p>President Trovoada justified his decision to open ties with Taiwan by saying that Sao Tome desperately needed financial aid.</p>
<p>Sao Tome and Principe, a former Portuguese colony located 200 km (125 miles) off Gabon, is one of the world's poorest countries and is heavily dependent on foreign aid. The islands' population is 127,000.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAOTOME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SAO TOME AND PRINCIPE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
