<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608688" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: PRESS DIGEST - South Africa - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - South Africa - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the South African press on Friday.</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
<p>- he lifting of a three-year moratorium on police recruitment with immediate effect by Safety and Security Minister Sydney Mufamadi on Thursday will see 5,250 policemen and civilians appointed at a cost of 149.6 million rand, and foreign governments assisting with basic and specialised training of future police.</p>
<p>- Housing Department director general Billy Cobbett, who has played a pivotal rile in South Africa's low-cost housing policy, has had his five-year contract terminated as tensions with Housing Minister Sankie Mthembi-Mahanyele have finally spilled over.</p>
<p>- The Moldenhauer report on fraudulent licences insists that Mpumalanga premier Mathews Phosa must fire his safety and security MEC Steve Mabona and Mpumalanga traffic director Henry Brazer if he hopes to stamp out corruption in law enforcement agencies.</p>
<p>- The Mouthpiece Workers' Union which led a strike at Anglo American Platinum Corp Ltd (Amplats) last year said on Thursday it had aligned itself with Bantu Holomisa's National Consultative Forum.</p>
<p>- Defections from the National Party snowballed on Thursday as several senior members, including Free State deputy chairman Zaxa Pieterse and former Allied managing director Kevin de Villiers, quit to join former Gauteng leader Roelf Meyer's new movement.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BUSINESS REPORT</p>
<p>- PepsiCo International has applied for the voluntary liquidation of New Age Beverages (NAB), its local bottler, just three years after it made a high-profile return to South Africa and spent more than 700 million rand taking on mighty Coca Cola.</p>
<p>- The public destruction on Thursday of 100,000 counterfeit TDK audio tapes was just the beginning of a blitz against the importation and sale of counterfeit goods, said Christo Henning, spokesman for the South African Revenue Service.</p>
<p>- Penuell Maduna, the Minister of Mineral and Energy Affairs, said on Thursday he would ask international oil companies operating in South Africa to source about 20 percent of their needs from a proposed integrated energy company formed from state assets.</p>
<p>- Billy Cobbett, the director-general of housing, has been axed folloing long-standing differences with Sankie Mthembi-Mahanyele, the Housing Minister, sources close to the director-general said on Thursday.</p>
<p>- Just three consortiums are left in the race for a 100 percent stake in the soon-to-be privatised Sun Air  SNAJ.CN.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SAKE BEELD</p>
<p>- Investec Holdings' share price on Thursday rose 500c to R150 per share after the group reported outstanding results.</p>
<p>- The state will draw on a portion of the South African special risk insurance company's reserves of 8.4 billion rand to help reduce government debt of 310 billion rand.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>THE STAR</p>
<p>- The decision to recruit more police and bring more skilled staff on board has been welcomed as a blow to crime, and has already triggered action by campaigners in Gauteng.</p>
<p>- About 1,500 Wits University students and staff gathered on the campus on Thursday to protest against spiralling crime.</p>
<p>- Kevin Gibb, the man responsible for spearheading low-cost housing at Nedcor Ltd, was dismissed after walking out of a disciplinary hearing this week.</p>
<p>- &quot;Masturbape, don't rape&quot; -- The blunt call from the Gauteng Ministry of Public Safety and Security encouraging rapists to masturbate instead of committing sexual crimes has angered women's groups and evoked mixed reaction from mebers of the police force.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
