<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608660" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Data to give S.African shares direction next week.</title>
<headline>Data to give S.African shares direction next week.</headline>
<byline>Paul Harris</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African shares, which have been drifting aimlessly down for much of May, will seek direction from much-needed local economic data next week, dealers and portfolio managers said on Friday.</p>
<p>The Johannesburg Stock Exchange (JSE) has mostly ignored the fickle ups and downs of Wall Street this month, concentrating instead on a raft of poor corporate results in May.</p>
<p>The rot started on May 6 when leading retailer Edgars Ltd reported a sharp drop in year earnings to 598 cents per share from 642 cents. Since Edgars other under-performers have included packaging company Nampak, cement firm PPC Ltd and industrial holding firm Barlow Ltd</p>
<p>The bad figures have hit the industrials sector hardest of all and it has come off an intra-day high of 8,602.6 on May 6 to its current levels hovering around 8,350. During the same period the all-share index has dipped from 7,216.4 to around 7,050.</p>
<p>&quot;We have had a mixed bag of results recently and that has seen the industrials sector take a knock,&quot; said Grahame Graham-Parker, general manager of Infinity Asset Management.</p>
<p>Another reason for the market's downward drift has been a dearth of economic data recently.</p>
<p>But all this is set to change next week as Monday will see the publication of April trade balance figures and consumer price inflation (CPI) numbers for April are to be published from Tuesday onwards.</p>
<p>Analysts expect the figures to be positive and economists are forecasting the CPI index will remain flat from the March figure at 0.6 percent month-on-month or 9.6 percent year-on-year when inflation dipped for the first time in 11 months.</p>
<p>The trade figure is widely seen as unreliable, but economists brave enough to stick their necks out expect a surplus of around 900 million rand after a 1.98 billion surplus in March and from a 451.6 million deficit in February.</p>
<p>First quarter seasonally adjusted and annualised gross domestic product is also due next week, with growth seen slowing but still relatively strong. Finally, April and M3 money supply and private credit is set to be published with economists seeing the figures slightly worse on last month.</p>
<p>If all the economic data comes in as expected it should provide a much-needed boost to sentiment. &quot;It will give the market some local direction,&quot; said one portfolio manager who declined to be identified.</p>
<p>But the JSE also faces another slew of company figures next week and, with widely varied performances forecast, unpleasant surprises could hurt the market's mood.</p>
<p>Major banking group Amalgamated Banks of South Africa Ltd, reporting on Monday, is seen showing profit growth of over 26 percent in spite of continued major technology costs and shrinking market share.</p>
<p>Expectations are also high following rival Investec Bank Ltd's recent sparkling figures.</p>
<p>But on Tuesday retailer and leisure firm CNA Gallo is seen being hit by a slump in consumer spending triggered by high interest rates. Analysts expect the firm to hold profits steady or even see a small drop.</p>
<p>Other firms posting results include Crookes Brothers Ltd, CorpGro Ltd, Santam Ltd, Metro Cash and Carry Ltd, Metropolitan Life Ltd, Servgro International Ltd, Storeco Ltd, Specialty Stores Ltd and Tongaat-Hullet Group Ltd.</p>
<p>Dealers said any worse-than-expected performances would be punished hard by the market.</p>
<p>&quot;After this month the market is sensitive to any unexpected underperformance,&quot; one share dealer said.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom +27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
