<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608607" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Some Canada banks seen raising dividends in Q2.</title>
<headline>Some Canada banks seen raising dividends in Q2.</headline>
<byline>Paul Casciato</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three of Canada's six major banks may dole out higher dividends as the banks head for their fourth consecutive round of record profits when they begin reporting second-quarter earnings on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Analysts said Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce, Toronto-Dominion Bank and Bank of Nova Scotia would likely increase payouts to  shareholders over the next two weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;Chances are we are going to get half of them to give a dividend increase,&quot; said analyst James Keating at brokerage Midland Walwyn Inc.</p>
<p>The six banks are expected to mirror their first quarter by reporting higher than expected earnings for the second quarter ended April 30, reflecting improved loan losses and robust performances by their brokerage units.</p>
<p>&quot;Expectations in the marketplace are that we are probably looking at record second-quarter earnings,&quot; said Fred Ketchen, senior vice president in charge of equity trading at brokerage ScotiaMcLeod Inc.</p>
<p>Analysts said brokerage profits, which drove earnings in the first quarter and to record levels last year, would likely show strong gains in concert with relatively buoyant Canadian financial markets.</p>
<p>&quot;People were being very conservative at the beginning of the year and we've had better than expected markets in terms of holding power and staying power,&quot; Keating said.</p>
<p>Traders said that meant higher dividends and perhaps stock splits could be expected from all the banks this year.</p>
<p>&quot;I am looking for dividend increases somewhere along the way this year and I'm also looking for further stock splits,&quot; Ketchen said. Canadian Imperial announced a two-for-one stock split in March.</p>
<p>Institutional Brokerage Estimate System said its consensus forecast indicated that Royal Bank of Canada -- Canada's largest -- would lead the profit parade with a second-quarter net profit of C$1.20 (87 cents) a share versus C97 cents (71 cents) a share last year.</p>
<p>Bank of Nova Scotia, Canada's fifth biggest bank, was expected to post a C$1.17 (85 cent) a share profit, compared to C$1.01 (74 cents) in the year earlier period.</p>
<p>Earnings at Bank of Montreal, Canada's third-ranked bank, were seen rising to C$1.14 (73 cents) a share from year earlier C98 cents (71 cents) a share.</p>
<p>Fifth-ranked Toronto-Dominion was expected to earn C84 cents (61 cents) a share in the quarter, up from C69 cents (50 cents) a share.</p>
<p>Second-ranked Canadian Imperial was expected to report earnings per share of C78 cents (57 cents), compared to year earlier C76 cents (55 cents). The year earlier figure was restated to reflect the stock split.</p>
<p>Sixth-ranked National Bank of Canada was expected to earn C43 cents (31 cents) a share in the quarter, versus C39 cents (28 cents) a year earlier.</p>
<p>Some analysts said that despite the rosy predictions, the second quarter was usually weaker than the first for the banks because of strong first-quarter earnings from the Canadian retirement savings plan season.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that earnings in the second quarter will be five percent down or so from the first quarter on average,&quot; said Mark Maxwell, analyst at CIBC Wood Gundy Inc. &quot;That still makes them up about 14 percent from (Q2) a year ago.&quot;</p>
<p>Bank of Montreal and Bank of Nova Scotia kick off the earnings season on Tuesday, followed by Royal Bank on Wednesday, Toronto-Dominion and National on Thursday and Canadian Imperial on June 5.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
