<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608634" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.Africa rand/bonds closing report.</title>
<headline>S.Africa rand/bonds closing report.</headline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The South African rand ended the week on a blue note amid torpid dealings after a mini bull run was checked on Thursday by marked weakness in the local debt arena.</p>
<p>The rand was last at 4.4695/4725 to the dollar from Thursday's late level of 4.4675/4705.</p>
<p>But traders said the local unit could potentially weaken further on offshore dollar demand and residual nervousness about the bond market.</p>
<p>&quot;What we are looking at is that these bonds have gone up 20 basis points over the last couple of days and the rand has hardly moved, taking into account the carry costs,&quot; noted one dealer.</p>
<p>H% said repeated intervention by the Reserve Bank had save the rand's bacon.</p>
<p>But dealers said a sustained push at 4.5000 next week might trigger stop loss dollar buying, paticularly from offshore players.</p>
<p>&quot;One thing that they (the Reserve Bank) have got to protect is the 4.50 level. There are a lot of stop losses set up there. A lot of investment houses that have sold dollars...so if 4.50 goes I think we're going to see 4.58 pretty quickly,&quot; said one.  </p>
<p>Bonds kept to their weaker ranges for most of the day with the key R150 bond last at 15.04 percent from 15.015 percent on Thursday.</p>
<p>Bond market players mainly were eyeing next week's credit extension figures for a clue to direction.</p>
<p>&quot;Credit figures are the most important and should give the market new direction. Good credit figures and a good trade surplus should see this market to a break on the downside (for yields),&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>April credit sector growth was forecast by economists polled by Reuters to rise 16.4 percent year-on-year from 15.96 percent previously.</p>
<p>Foreigners were net sellers of 821.54 million rand's worth of South African bonds on Thursday after buying 742.38 million rand's worth on Wednesday, the Bond Exchange said.</p>
<p>Nominal turnover on the Exchange soared to 39.84 billion rand on Thursday -- a settlement date -- from 7.62 billion rand on Wednesday.</p>
<p>South Africa's money market shortage rose to 7.065 billion on Thursday from 6.453 billion Wednesday, the Reserve Bank said on Friday.</p>
<p>Three-month NCD rates remained unchanged from Thursday at 16.35 percent offered, as did 90-day BA rates which lined up at 15.85 percent.</p>
<p>-- Justin McCamish, Johannesburg newsrgom +27 11 482-1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
