<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608642" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MAURITIUS: Conglomerate pushes Mauritius bourse index down.</title>
<headline>Conglomerate pushes Mauritius bourse index down.</headline>
<dateline>PORT LOUIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Falling shares in conglomerate Rogers helped pushed down the Stock Exchange of Mauritius index SEMDEX 1.32 points to 383.52 on Friday, brokers said.</p>
<p>Turnover was posted at 6.44 million rupees on 339,358 shares from 7.04 million rupees on 226,485 shares on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Brokers said market sentiment was bearish and the market would continue that way until the 1997/98 budget speech scheduled for June 9.</p>
<p>In the commerce sector, conglomerate Rogers lost 3.00 rupees to 95.00 rupees on 8,598 shares and Ireland Blyth Ltd fell 30 cents to 15.60 rupees on 22,026 shares. Shell was stable at 20.90 rupees on 1,250 shares and Happy World Foods was 20 cents lower to 14.80 rupees on 3,954 shares.</p>
<p>Hotel-based Grand Baie Hotel was unchanged to 47.20 rupees on 5,110 shares, New Mauritius Hotels eased by 60 cents to 36.20 rupees on 1,500 shares and Sun Resorts lost 10 cents to 49.90 rupees, but was unquoted.</p>
<p>In the financial sector, Mauritius Commercial Bank was stable at 89.00 rupees on 6,793 shares and State Bank of Mauritius climbed 20 cents to 12.00 rupees on 112,076 shares.</p>
<p>Industry company Gamma Civic rose 1.10 rupee to 18.70 rupees on 8,229 shares, Mauritius Oil Refineries gained 20 cents to 11.20 rupees on 18,773 shares and United Basalt Products climbed 60 cents to 33.50 rupees on 1,000 shares.</p>
<p>In the investment sector, Fincorp slumped 1.00 rupee to 69.00 rupees on 3,125 shares and Promotion And Development was unchanged to 15.00 rupees on 58,812 shares.</p>
<p>Sugar-based stocks Mon Tresor Mon Desert fell 70 cents to 38.80 rupees on 4,450 shares and Harel Freres was stable at 57.00 rupees on 2,000 shares.</p>
<p>National carrier Air Mauritius was 60 cents lower to 41.40 rupees on 950 shares.</p>
<p>--Clifford Vellien ++230 211-9555</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MAURTS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORT LOUIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MAURITIUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
