<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608658" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAMBIA: Zambia maize output seen down 30 pct in 1997.</title>
<headline>Zambia maize output seen down 30 pct in 1997.</headline>
<dateline>LUSAKA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zambia's National Farmers Union said on Friday it expected the 1997 maize crop to fall by around 30 percent because of a lack of fertiliser.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect the maize harvest to fall by around 30 percent to 10.8 million 90-kg bags,&quot; union president Ajay Vashee told Reuters.</p>
<p>The maize yield in 1996 was around 14 million bags.</p>
<p>Fertiliser imports were delayed last year after South African suppliers witheld supplies until the Zambian government paid its outstanding debts to them.</p>
<p>The government managed to clear the arrears, totalling $10 million, only in October.</p>
<p>Vashee said the drop in maize output would result in a shortfall of up to two million bags, depending on how much was exported.</p>
<p>Under new policies to liberalise the economy, farmers are free to export maize even when the country faces a shortage.</p>
<p>According to official figures, Zambia consumes around 12 million bags of maize a year. However, Vashee said the figure could be lower.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of people are switching to cheaper and drought-resistant crops such as sweet potato, cassava and sorghum,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Vashee said the union expected fertiliser supplies to increase this year.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a co-ordinated effort between the private sector and the government to improve the fertiliser situation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Jowie Mwiinga, Lusaka office, +260 1 222689</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAMBIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUSAKA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
