<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608670" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Kinshasa residents react to Kabila cabinet.</title>
<headline>Kinshasa residents react to Kabila cabinet.</headline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The people of Kinshasa crowded around newspaper kiosks early on Friday, scouring reports about the absence of veteran politican Etienne Tshisekedi from a transitional government in the Democratic Republic of Congo.</p>
<p>Laurent Kabila, whose rebels captured the capital of the former Zaire six days ago, angered many in the city of five million by failing to appoint Tshisekedi prime minister.</p>
<p>&quot;This is Kabila's first failure. Tshisekedi should be in his government,&quot; businessman Jean-Marie Tshamala told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We are only waiting for Tshisekedi's instruction to take to the streets,&quot; student Kambala Tshala, standing at the same newstand in the Matonge district, chipped in.</p>
<p>Two days behind schedule, self-proclaimed president Kabila late on Thursday announced an incomplete list of 13 cabinet ministers and dropped the position of prime minister.</p>
<p>He has renamed Zaire the Democratic Republic of Congo.</p>
<p>Senior members of his Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo (ADFL) said six of the ministers were not Alliance members. But the pro-Tshisekedi La Reference newspaper said the Alliance had awarded itself all but four posts.</p>
<p>The Alliance said early on Friday the remaining cabinet posts would be named shortly.</p>
<p>The key jobs among the 13 awarded so far went to Alliance stalwarts. But the incomplete list also featured at least four non-Alliance opposition names, including two presented as Tshisekedi supporters -- Paul Bandoma and Justine Kasavubu.</p>
<p>Kabila's seven-month rebellion toppled the 32-year regime of President Mobutu Sese Seko, who fled Kinshasa a day before Kabila's troops marched into the capital on May 17.</p>
<p>Kabila was under foreign and domestic pressure to name a broad-based team before elections. For many, that meant a top job for the stubborn but courageous Tshisekedi, Mobutu's strongest civilian foe since 1990.</p>
<p>There was no immediate reaction on Friday from the Tshisekedi camp.</p>
<p>But Le Phare, one of the newspapers supporting him, headlined: &quot;Fears for the future&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I am always wary of those who take power by force of arms,&quot; Alain Matama, a civil servant, said in Matonge.</p>
<p>Le Phare's cartoonist ripped into the Alliance in a full, back-page drawing. It lampooned the Rwandan troops in the Alliance who are now ubiquitous in the capital, showing them guzzling beer in front of a nightclub.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not going back to Cyangugu,&quot; one soldier says, referring to a town in Rwanda.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
