<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608697" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: FEATURE-SAfricans paint &quot;war memorial&quot; for victims of crime.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-SAfricans paint &quot;war memorial&quot; for victims of crime.</headline>
<byline>Ingeborg Lichtenberg</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A glaring white wall in the centre of Johannesburg, once the canvas for anarchistic graffiti, has been declared a &quot;war memorial&quot; by artists painting on it the faces of South Africans slain by criminals.</p>
<p>&quot;This is like a war memorial, because there is a civil war going on,&quot; said Nicole Vinokur as she applied the finishing touches to the portrait in blues of a 30-year-old man killed by car hijackers.</p>
<p>&quot;People have to be made aware of the violent, sick society we're actually living in. It's an underground war,&quot; said Charles Levin, one of the 15 artists who have volunteered their time to portray some of the tens of thousands of people murdered during car hijackings and other violent crimes over the past year.</p>
<p>VICTIMS' FAMILY RECOUNT CRIME HORRORS</p>
<p>As passing motorists hooted and waved to applaud the young painters working at the busy intersection, Doreen Gittelson looked longingly at a photograph of her brother, a taxi driver, before she gave it to Levin.</p>
<p>&quot;He was hijacked and they stabbed and shot him to death and threw his body into the street like a dog,&quot; she said tearfully.</p>
<p>Her husband Cassel explained that only two months after his brother-in-law was killed, their son was shot in the stomach during an attempted hijacking.</p>
<p>&quot;He didn't die, but they had to cut away a quarter of his stomach and they can't remove the bullet which is still lodged next to his spine. Psychologically he's never been the same. He's scared of everything,&quot; said Cassel. &quot;He's nothing more than a bundle of nerves,&quot; Doreen added. &quot;He's finished.&quot;</p>
<p>CRIME PERMEATES LIVES OF SOUTH AFRICANS</p>
<p>The vast majority of South Africans are fed up with the country's spiralling crime rate, with an April poll showing 80 percent of urban residents demanding the reinstatement of the death penalty -- abolished by the Constitutional Court in 1995.</p>
<p>Crime, a word on the lips of every South African, is worst in the country's commercial centre Johannesburg, notorious as the murder capital of the world.</p>
<p>Many South Africans from other regions shudder at the thought of even visiting the brash city where anyone who can afford it puts bars, towering walls and electric fences round their homes and employs armed security services.</p>
<p>Last year one in 1,000 cars was hijacked in the Gauteng province encircling Johannesburg and a total of 5,789 of the province's seven million residents were murdered.</p>
<p>Countrywide 61 out of every 100,000 people were murdered last year, while 119 out of every 100,000 people were raped. Add to this the fact that police think they are told of only one in every 20 rapes.</p>
<p>Interpol has put South Africa at the top of the rape table for its 89 members, with a reported incidence three times that of the United States and 12 times Germany's.</p>
<p>&quot;All I want to do is cry to think that so many people are going through so much grief. It's heartbreaking,&quot; said Doreen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
