<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608649" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Temporary Congo capital sinks back into obscurity.</title>
<headline>Temporary Congo capital sinks back into obscurity.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Wright</byline>
<dateline>LUBUMBASHI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Workmen are slapping fresh white paint on the grand facade of the governor's mansion but the people of Lubumbashi realise their moment in history is probably over.</p>
<p>Laurent Kabila proclaimed himself the new president of the Democratic Republic of Congo in one of the reception rooms a week ago and some of his aides then said his ruling alliance might declare Lubumbashi provisional capital of the country.</p>
<p>The chances of that are receding fast as Kabila's new government takes office in Kinshasa, 1,600 km (1,000 miles) to the northwest, and starts to tackle the political and economic morass which undid deposed president Mobutu Sese Seko.</p>
<p>The people of Lubumbashi, a copper and cobalt mining city close to the border with Zambia, had dreamt of power, prestige and wealth if the Kabila government had set up shop among them.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel sorry for my city. Now everyone will forget us,&quot; said Francis Mweupu, whose language school would have thrived on an influx of bureaucrats and businessmen seeking contracts.</p>
<p>The swimming-pool patio of the Karavia Hotel, where the new rulers of former Zaire spent weeks before Kinshasa fell to rebel forces last Saturday, now has a subdued and languid air.</p>
<p>The alliance orderlies have abandoned their chairs in the hotel corridors where once they guarded sleeping VIPs. Even some of the prostitutes have drifted off to richer pastures.</p>
<p>Gone from Lubumbashi too are most of the other larger-than- life characters drawn into the rebellion against Mobutu.</p>
<p>&quot;Rebel Tim&quot;, the American cowboy who chartered planes to the Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo across eastern Zaire, said he was off to take a break in his native Pennsylvania and check up on his neglected businesses in South and Central America.</p>
<p>He had amused patrons of the bar with his naive belief in the normality of his profession. &quot;Why on earth are insurance companies so unhelpful?&quot; he would complain.</p>
<p>The U.S. diplomats have also pulled out, relieved that their government made the right decision when it sold its Lubumbashi consulate to the mobile phone company Telecel.</p>
<p>The Telecel office remains an island of modernity in a sea of decrepitude -- fully computerised and air-conditioned.</p>
<p>But cool young Tutsis of uncertain nationality -- with their blue jeans and cellular telephones -- have joined the exodus to Kinshasa, where the local people have already remarked on their presence.</p>
<p>One stood on the hotel front steps on the day of Kabila's departure, clutching a leather briefcase labelled &quot;Ministry of Defence, Kigali&quot; -- another piece of evidence that the Rwandan government in Kigali was more than an interested observer.</p>
<p>Portuguese-speaking troops in red berets have moved in to take their place at the Karavia. They are not saying where they come from but the border with Portuguese-speaking Angola, friendly towards Kabila, is less than 400 km (250 miles) to the west.</p>
<p>The white businessmen remain, eager for a slice of the action in the mineral-rich southeast when the copper, cobalt and zinc mines resume large-scale production after years of decline.</p>
<p>They need to know who the new government will put in charge of its mineral operations and how long it will take to lift a Zambian embargo on trains crossing the border.</p>
<p>Lebanese in dark glasses and double-breasted suits are also evident. The local people insist they are into dubious exports of cobalt, which at about $22 a lb ($50 a kg) on the international market can be a highly lucrative business.</p>
<p>In downtown Lubumbashi it's business as usual. The city's sole set of traffic lights clings to life by a slender thread, holding back a line of sickly vehicles, choking and lurching, grinding their gears and coughing black fumes.</p>
<p>At the lawcourts, a Belgian colonial pile with a Latin inscription, the bailiffs say nothing has changed. If they can find the remand prisoners who escaped from jail when the rebels arrived, they will bring them to trial. &quot;But they've probably changed their addresses,&quot; one clerk said.</p>
<p>The missionaries, intent on saving souls, seemed impervious to the war and political change around them.</p>
<p>They come in many a sect and denomination -- Roman Catholics, Baptists, Methodists or Seventh Day Adventists.</p>
<p>At the airport this week two forlorn Asians, unfamiliar with French, Swahili or English, waited patiently under a tree for that elusive plane to the eastern city of Goma.</p>
<p>They were a Korean delegation from the Unification Church, the Moonies, on a visit to their hapless Lubumbashi flock.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUBUMBASHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
