<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608684" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UGANDA: FEATURE-Kabila's Congo revolution good for Ugandan business.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Kabila's Congo revolution good for Ugandan business.</headline>
<byline>Steven Shalita</byline>
<dateline>KAMPALA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laurent Kabila and his movement in the new Democratic Republic of Congo have pumped more life into the Ugandan economy by pushing guerrillas back from Uganda's western border and restoring order there, business executives and political leaders said.</p>
<p>Businessmen said they welcomed Kabila's stated goal of restoring order in the east of the former Zaire because it should boost growth in Uganda.</p>
<p>&quot;(The revolution) is the best thing that has happened to Uganda in a long time,&quot; said Mike Mukula, chairman of the powerful Uganda Exporters and Importers Association (UEIA).</p>
<p>&quot;This is going to be a great opportunity for Ugandan goods and business in the region. I foresee Uganda's economy booming in the near future,&quot; added Mukula, a leading businessman.</p>
<p>Kabila's newly installed administration in eastern Congo has cut taxes on imports of Ugandan goods by 70 percent -- sparking an influx of Ugandan products in rebel-held areas. Congo gold, diamonds, timber and coffee have all started trickling into Uganda since the border situation stabilised.</p>
<p>BREAD AND BICYCLES</p>
<p>Bicycles, foam mattresses, grains, soft drinks and bread from Uganda were in demand in nearby areas of Congo, traders said.</p>
<p>Uganda's Planning and Economic Development Minister Richard Kaijuka said expanding trade into Congo would help non-coffee exports rise to $257 million in 1996/97 compared to $196 million in the previous year (July/June).</p>
<p>Traders said cross-border trade between Uganda and Zaire, which Kabila has renamed Congo, had always fluctuated since Congo's independence from Belgium in 1960, but the greatest determinant was security along the 800 km (500 mile) frontier.</p>
<p>Calm and peace means less risk and flourishing trade. Civil strife means a turnabout in fortunes, with heavy losses.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no problem of insecurity any more (in southwest Uganda),&quot; Ugandan President Yoweri Museveni said.</p>
<p>He was referring to Ugandan dissidents who he says ousted president Mobutu Sese Seko allowed to operate from his territory, keeping southwest Uganda in a virtual state of war which damaged business.</p>
<p>COFFEE TO MOMBASA</p>
<p>Coffee and other commodities from eastern Congo move through Uganda to the Kenyan port of Mombasa from where they are shipped to world markets. Whether smuggled from Congo or exported by the government, the trade contributes to Uganda's hard currency earnings.</p>
<p>A wide range of imports, including those from Uganda and Kenya, flow back into eastern Congo by the same route.</p>
<p>Before independence in 1960, the Belgian-controlled Congo government in the capital Kinshasa, then called Leopoldville, maintained an efficient system of border controls, and money paid in customs duties at even the most distant borders was returned to the central treasury.</p>
<p>But after independence, and as government inefficiency and official corruption thrived under Mobutu, Kinshasa -- 2,000 km (over 1,200 miles) away from the border with Uganda -- maintained no more than a nominal control of the trade across the frontiers.</p>
<p>For decades, this trade was controlled by local tycoons on both sides of the border, and by a multitude of peasants making a living by petty trading or smuggling.</p>
<p>Ugandan and Kenyan shillings, as well as U.S. dollars, circulate widely in eastern Congo. By contrast, Congo's tottering currency, which has fallen drastically in value over the years, carries no weight outside the country's borders.</p>
<p>BEER AND MARGARINE</p>
<p>Beer brewed in centres such as Bunia, west of Lake Albert, and Goma, further south, appears in small trading centres in western Uganda but is not listed in Ugandan customs records.</p>
<p>The beer is transported in small boats across Lake Albert to lakeside villages in Uganda, in canoes across the Albert Nile, or by road or bush track across the land border.</p>
<p>Congo's breweries have maintained production through a succession of political crises, and the quality and pricing of their products is greatly appreciated in border areas.</p>
<p>A wide range of products manufactured in Uganda and Kenya, from margarine to soap powder, and from cosmetics to pharmaceuticals, flows back into Congo by that same route.</p>
<p>Petrol for eastern Congo moves through a pipeline from Mombasa to western Kenya, where it is transferred to road tankers for the long journey across Uganda.</p>
<p>Uganda and Kenya benefit from transit dues paid in dollars and have no interest in what happens to goods once they cross into Congo territory.</p>
<p>Uganda's gross domestic product (GDP) growth is forecast at 6.3 percent in 1996/97, lower than a target of 7.0 percent or the 8.5 percent growth attained in the previous year.</p>
<p>Kaijuka said manufacturing production in January was 30.7 percent higher than in January 1996 while the average sector growth for the first seven months of 1996/97 compared with the same period in 1995/96 was 22.9 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically, production should go up. There is demand in eastern Zaire and southern and northern Uganda are more accessible now,&quot; a business consultant in Kampala said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UGANDA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KAMPALA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UGANDA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
