<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608616" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>zaire: Street protests flare over new Congo government.</title>
<headline>Street protests flare over new Congo government.</headline>
<byline>William Wallis</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Street protests erupted in Kinshasa on Friday against the new government formed in the Democratic Republic of Congo and troops opened fire in the air to stop demonstrators.</p>
<p>Opposition leader Etienne Tshisekedi, whose exclusion from President Laurent Kabila's administration sparked the protests, declared that he did not recognise the new government.</p>
<p>The firebrand politician also called for the withdrawal of foreign troops who helped Kabila's guerrilla alliance drive veteran dictator Mobutu Sese Seko from power in former Zaire.</p>
<p>&quot;This government doesn't exist for me. I ask all the people to resist with their last energy all attempts to impose a government without popular legitimacy,&quot; Tshisekedi told a news conference.</p>
<p>Hundreds of Tshisekedi followers chanted anti-Kabila slogans and called for the pullout of Rwandan troops from his Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo (AFDL).</p>
<p>A Reuters journalist followed the peaceful march from Tshisekedi's house in Limete into the city centre, past the U.S., French and Belgian embassies.</p>
<p>But troops firiing in the air blocked the marchers before they reached the People's Palace, the seat of parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;A group of demonstrators were heading towards the parliament building and the soldiers opened fire in the air,&quot; one witness said. There was no indication of any casualties.</p>
<p>At his news conference Tshisekedi did not directly ask his fanatical supporters in the the city of five million people to take to the streets, and also appeared to leave the door open for talks with Kabila.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi thanked African governments which had helped end the autocratic rule of Mobutu, who is ailing with cancer and fled the country as Kabila's forces took over.</p>
<p>&quot;But I am asking them to recall the elements they have lent the AFDL so that the Zaireans can solve their problems between themselves,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I must add that with the departure of Mr Mobutu peace will reign in the Great Lakes (region). He was involved in all the problems with our neighbours...Now that he has left all the reasons are there for us to agree,&quot; Tshisekedi added.</p>
<p>He took a jibe at Kabila's self-proclamation as president following the capture of Kinshasa.</p>
<p>&quot;Not only I but I think all of the radical opposition is agreed that this son of the country merits that function (the presidency). But it is not enough to self-proclaim oneself. There must be popular legitimacy,&quot; Tshisekedi said.</p>
<p>&quot;He is a candindate for the presidency, and we will do everything so that he is so effectively but legally,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Throughout the news conference, at which he spoke without notes, Tshisekedi stressed that his UDPS party had battled for 17 years for the state of law and democracy in Zaire. People were not ready to accept another dictatorship, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
