<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608640" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>COTE D'IVOIRE: African Development Bank &quot;has credibility again&quot;.</title>
<headline>African Development Bank &quot;has credibility again&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>ABIDJAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The president of the African Development Bank (AfDB) says the organisation has restored its credibility with both its shareholders and the financial markets, pointing to credit ratings and spreads as evidence.</p>
<p>Omar Kabbaj took over the top job at the AfDB after a period of fraught relations between its African and non-African shareholders, which led to the effective closure of its soft loan fund for 2-1/2 years to September 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;We have now reached the stage where I can say the Bank has become normal again, after a year and a half of intensive reforms,&quot; Kabbaj said in an interview with Ivory Coast's Fraternite Matin newspaper published on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The Bank has restored its credibility,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The AfDB's headquarters are in Ivory Coast's commercial capital, Abidjan, and its annual meeting will be held there from May 28-30.</p>
<p>The AfDB lost its AAA rating from Standard and Poor's rating agency because of the dispute between the shareholders, which centred on the bank's management practices.</p>
<p>Kabbaj pointed out that other major agencies, including Moody's, had confirmed the AAA rating and meetings would be held with all of them, including Standard and Poor's, in June.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously, I can't forecast what is going to happen, but I can tell you there will be no deterioration...Rather the contrary,&quot; Kabbaj said.</p>
<p>Under Kabbaj the Bank has carried out a series of reforms, adopting rigorous lending and recruitment policies.</p>
<p>The financial markets had taken note, he said, pointing to a narrowing of the yield spread between AfDB and World Bank bonds to between five and 13 basis points against 25 two years ago.</p>
<p>The Bank has been discussing a capital increase with its shareholders. Some two-thirds of its shares are held by African states, the other third by western countries, who are thought to want greater influence in return for finding more capital.</p>
<p>Kabbaj said there was no urgency, though the Bank was hoping to have the capital increase by 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;For the Bank's operations, we can live without a capital increase for three or four years,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Having said that, we need this increase to consolidate our credibility on the international financial markets, to improve our ratios, to protect ourselves against difficult conditions in several countries in the future, and also to allow us to develop the private sector more.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Alan Raybould, Abidjan newsroom +(225) 21 90 90.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ICST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150106">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ABIDJAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COTE D'IVOIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
