<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608687" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: PRESS DIGEST - Zimbabwe - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Zimbabwe - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in Zimbabwe's state-owned Herald newspaper on Friday.</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ZIMBABWE INDEPENDENT</p>
<p>- The state-owned Zimbabwe Broadcasting Corporation has been advised to invite tenders before it disposes of its second television channel and fourth radio station to ensure that it gets the best return.</p>
<p>- The New York based Human Rights Watch group this week alleged that Zimbabwe continued to produce lethal landmines well into the 1990s contrary to claims by the country's authorities that the technology was destroyed at independence in 1980.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>THE HERALD</p>
<p>- Zimbabwe and South Africa have reached agreement on the reinstatement of tariff preferences for agricultural and animal products under a 1964 trade agreement which had been affected by changes to South Africa's overall tariff structures in 1992.</p>
<p>-  The director of information in President Robert Mugabe's office, George Charamba, on Thursday dismissed as inaccurate and misleading a report by the privately owned Financial Gazette newspaper that the government tender board was instructed by the office and cabinet on its awarding of Zimbabwe's second cellular phone network licence.</p>
<p>-- Harare Newsroom: +263-4 72 52 28/9</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
