<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608769" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish bourse seen down as Handlowy offer starts.</title>
<headline>Polish bourse seen down as Handlowy offer starts.</headline>
<byline>Steven Silber</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Polish shares are likely to extend this week's 1.2-percent fall next week as the long-awaited public offering of Bank Handlowy, seen worth a total of $1 billion, gets underway, analysts said.</p>
<p>They said investors might also fear that the Czech currency crisis, in which a falling currency led to a falling bourse earlier this week, could happen in Poland. The zloty dropped almost 1.5 percent on Thursday before easing further on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;To some Central Europe is one unit -- if the Czechs were considered the region's leader a year or two ago and now it's bad there, they can think such a situation can happen here,&quot; said Pawel Tarnowski of Raiffeisen Capital and Investment.</p>
<p>Other analysts were not convinced the problems of Poland's southwestern neighbour would affect Polish shares for longer than mid next week.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation in the Czech Republic can't be compared with that of Poland because the Czech market is governed by different principles, it's much less transparent and liquid,&quot; said Grzegorz Cimochowski, an analyst at ING Baring Securities.</p>
<p>The bourse closed this week at 16,179.0 points.</p>
<p>Cimochowski said Polish shares were trading at 11 times 1997 forecast earnings, making them attractive compared to other regional bourses and likely to help prevent falls below 15,500 points.</p>
<p>Apart from the Czech crisis, analysts said the large Handlowy offer, for which the pricing is due late on Friday, could prevent growth in Warsaw.</p>
<p>They said the Handlowy price would help investors appraise listed banks, which have been slumping of late on poor 1997 earnings, and decide to what degree the offer would draw capital from listed stocks.</p>
<p>Analysts also said the public offering of copper giant KGHM Polska Miedz SA, which seeks a July listing in London as well as Warsaw, would draw cash, and that demand for listed stocks could stay low before September's parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>But they said Poland's good macro-economic environment, reflected by the finance minister's Wednesday statement that year-on-year inflation could fall below 13 percent in December from 15.3 percent in April, would prevent steep falls.</p>
<p>Espebepe was the main market's top gainer this week, up 8.8 percent after creditors last Friday accepted the firm's version of a debt-write-off deal.</p>
<p>Elektrim rebounded 8.9 percent after last week's fall when an investor shed its five percent of shares.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
