<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608787" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: Bosnian Serb police refuse to obey UN requests.</title>
<headline>Bosnian Serb police refuse to obey UN requests.</headline>
<byline>Dan De Luce</byline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.N. spokesman said on Friday relations between Bosnian Serb authorities and international police had deteriorated after the Serbs snubbed requests to remove unauthorised checkpoints along ethnic boundaries.</p>
<p>The interior minister for Bosnia's Serb republic, Dragan Kijac, has told international police monitors his officers would ignore demands to dismantle police checkpoints which are used to prevent free movement across ethnic boundaries, spokesman Aleksandar Ivanko said.</p>
<p>&quot;I can describe the current relationship with Republika Srpska (Serb republic) as extremely difficult,&quot; Ivanko told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;There are problems not only at the level of minister but also at the local level, in a number of areas the local police have refused to cooperate or even meet with U.N. officials...,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Danish commissioner of the International Police Task Force (IPTF), Manfred Seitner, has ordered the dismantling of all checkpoints in Serb and Moslem-Croat territories which are not approved by IPTF monitors.</p>
<p>Seitner's order is meant to force local police to allow free movement across former front lines and halt the enforcement of ethnic divisions created during the war.</p>
<p>Moslem-Croat federation officials have pledged to cooperate with the new policy, unlike their Serb counterparts.</p>
<p>IPTF officers have found federation police violating the policy in several cases this week but the checkpoints were dismantled, Ivanko said.</p>
<p>The NATO-led peace force has pledged to back up international police if Serb authorities refuse to accept the order.</p>
<p>NATO officers, who asked not to be named, said the 31,000- strong peace force stood ready to deploy combat helicopters and tanks if necessary to ensure local police obeyed the order.</p>
<p>&quot;We are hoping that sane heads will prevail but we will have to see,&quot; said the officer, who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>Ivanko said that the IPTF would stick to its policy on checkpoints. &quot;This is one country and people should be able to travel across this country unhindered.&quot;</p>
<p>Bosnian Serb authorities were also refusing to vet their police force for possible war crimes suspects, to limit the number of rifles at police stations or to punish an officer who threw stones at a bus of Moslem refugees in Brcko.</p>
<p>The Bosnian Serb cabinet issued a statement on Thursday evening backing the interior minister's stance and accusing the IPTF of exceeding its mandate under the Dayton peace agreement.</p>
<p>Another U.N. spokesman, Liam McDowall, said that Serb authorities were reluctant to make any changes to a police force which they use to keep tight control over their territory.</p>
<p>&quot;We appear to be speaking different languages. We are talking about accountability and democratic policing and (interior minister) Kijac seems happy with something closely akin to a police state, which rules according to an extremely narrow political agenda,&quot; McDowall said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
