<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608751" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Serbia seen selling telcom unit to Stet.</title>
<headline>Serbia seen selling telcom unit to Stet.</headline>
<byline>Gordana Filipovic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Serbia's post and telecommunications monopoly PTT Srbije is close to clinching a deal with the Italian telecommunications holding Stet and negotiations are entering the final stage, industry sources said.</p>
<p>Local media reported on Friday that Stet's negotiating team was in Belgrade to finalise details on a deal giving the Italians a 49 percent stake in the Serbian telecom unit.</p>
<p>&quot;Stet is still negotiating, But there is no deal yet and no agreement on the price,&quot; Stet's spokeswoman Francesca Impegra told Reuters.</p>
<p>News agency Beta said earlier Stet has offered 1.57 billion German marks ($929 million) for the stake, with one billion marks paid immediately and the rest in two tranches with the last 200 million tranche paid by January 1, 1998.</p>
<p>Some analysts said the price was lower than expected and were puzzled why the deal had not been put out to an international tender.</p>
<p>Industry experts said with the price of an installed phone line calculated at $2,400-$2,500 and with two million lines in Serbia, the price of the telecommunications unit could be as high as $5 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if reduced for years of exploitation, the price cannot fall so low simply because the sector is expanding and profitable,&quot; said an economist who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>Industry sources said a final deal on PTT Srbije. the biggest sell-off of the most lucrative segment of Serbia's nearly bankrupt economy, is expected within 10 days.</p>
<p>Newspaper Nasa Borba quoted a Nat West Markets public relations officer as saying that &quot;negotiations are constructive with a positive outcome in sight&quot;.</p>
<p>Nat West Markets was chosen by the Serbian government as a chief consultant in the privatisation of the PTT Srbije.</p>
<p>&quot;Negotiations are very intensive, but not much can happen within next week,&quot; said a PTT source who declined to be named</p>
<p>Serbia's parliament last week adopted legislation separating posts from telecommunications, establishing a new holding company and clearing the way for a telecoms sale. But analysts said time was needed for the new Serbian Telecom to be established.</p>
<p>Earlier Serbian privatisation minister Milan Beko had said the government was interested in selling between 30 and 49 percent of PTT's telecom capital.</p>
<p>By Yugoslav foreign investment law, foreigners cannot buy more than 49 percent stake in military industries, media and mass telecommunications.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't matter how much stake they get. The important thing is that they will seek firm guarantees for operational control and independent strategic management. Foreigners always seek control over key sectors, but the government will this time probably retain control over prices,&quot; the PTT source said. -- Belgrade newsroom, +381 11 222 4254 ($ = 1.69 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
