<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608745" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: Slovenia edges closer to EU ratification.</title>
<headline>Slovenia edges closer to EU ratification.</headline>
<dateline>LJUBLJANA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Slovenia's parliament agreed on Friday to bring national legislation into line with European Union standards, taking the country one step closer to final ratification of its association agreement with the EU.</p>
<p>Parliamentary parties agreed to adopt legislation that would allow a gradual liberalisation of Slovenian markets, including real estate, while protecting national interests in accordance with EU norms.</p>
<p>Last week parliament postponed a session on ratifying the accord, which was signed last June, to give political parties more time to reach a broader agreement on the issue.</p>
<p>Under the terms of the association agreement, Slovenia undertook to change its constitution to allow foreigners to own property within four years of the treaty taking effect.</p>
<p>Before voting on ratification the assembly has to wait for the Constitutional Court to say whether Slovenia can ratify the treaty without immediate changes to its constitution.</p>
<p>The court is expected to decide on the issue at the latest on June 5.</p>
<p>European Commission President Jacques Santer said in April a speedy ratification was essential if Slovenia wanted to be among the first nations to start talks on full EU membership, probably in early 1998.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LJUBLJANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
