<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608796" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian MinFins weaker on further freeze.</title>
<headline>Russian MinFins weaker on further freeze.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prices of Russian MinFin bonds eased on news of a further freeze of bonds by Russian police and dealers said on Friday prices could ease more in nervous trading but the decline was unlikely to be large.</p>
<p>			tranche   May 23		  May 22</p>
<p>    1999 maturity   (3)     87.00-87.30	   87.15-87.40</p>
<p>    2003 maturity   (4)     61.80-62.10	   62.25-62.50</p>
<p>    2008 maturity   (5)     43.75-44.05	   44.15-44.40</p>
<p>    2006 maturity   (6)     49.65-49.95	   50.00-50.25</p>
<p>    2011 maturity   (7)     38.10-38.40	   38.25-38.50</p>
<p>A senior official at Vneshtorgbank, the main depositary for the bonds, said police in Russia's Samara region had frozen $10.6 million nominal of the fourth and fifth tranches of MinFin bonds.</p>
<p>Vneshtorgbank said on Thursday Moscow police had frozen MinFin bonds with a face value of $129,000 this month. The total nominal value of all MinFin bonds outstanding is $11 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;The downward trend continued from yesterday,&quot; an ICFI Moscow Partners Bank dealer said. &quot;All these freezes are creating uncertainty but today's price fall was not abrupt.&quot;</p>
<p>Over Thursday and Friday prices of the most actively traded fourth and fifth tranches fell around 1.5 point each on new freezes, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices could ease more but the extent may depend on clients' reaction,&quot; a London dealer said.</p>
<p>The ICFI Moscow Partners Bank dealer said prices could still edge down but they seemed to be close to the bottom and investors could find current levels attractive.</p>
<p>&quot;After all, the market was firm after U.S. interest rates were not changed,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The U.S. Federal Reserve announced on Tuesday that it would not change interest rates.</p>
<p>--Artyom Danielyan, Moscow Newsroom (095) 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
