<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608783" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria lev dips at close on client dollar buying.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria lev dips at close on client dollar buying.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bulgarian lev edged down to 1,575-1,578 per dollar at the close from the mid-morning's 1,573-1,575 due to rising foreign currency demand from clients, but was firmly above opening lows, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Final clients started bidding for moderate dollar volumes in the afternoon when some banks already were out of the market and the lev eased,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>But the lev was off early morning lows of 1,595-1,605 it touched when some market makers unsucessfully attempted to pressure it from Thursday's close at 1,572-1,574, citing a cut in the central bank main interest rate.  </p>
<p>The central bank said on Thursday it will cut its main interest rate to 43.08 percent annually from 51.48 percent, effective from Monday.</p>
<p>The lev closed at 925-950 per mark.</p>
<p>Some paring of lev investments might take place at the beginning of next week as the new rate goes in force and if yields on government secruities keep falling, but the central bank was expected to counter possible pressure, traders said.  </p>
<p>Yields on one- and four week discount T-bills fell further at Friday's auctions. Yields on local floating interest T-bills are pegged to the main interest rate and fall each time the rate is cut.</p>
<p>-- Sofia Newsroom, (++359-2) 911 88</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
