<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608705" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZAIRE: Mobutu foe Tshisekedi has solid Kinshasa powerbase.</title>
<headline>Mobutu foe Tshisekedi has solid Kinshasa powerbase.</headline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Veteran opposition firebrand Etienne Tshisekedi, excluded by victorious rebel leader Laurent Kabila from his new government in the former Zaire, has an army of fanatical supporters in the overcrowded slums of Kinshasa.</p>
<p>Opinion polls conducted in the capital of what is now Kabila's Democratic Republic of Congo suggested that Tshisekedi, the leader of the internal opposition to ousted dictator Mobutu Sese Seko, would be by far the most popular politician in the city in any election.</p>
<p>That was as Kabila's forces marched across Africa's third largest country. Whether their arrival in Kinshasa and Kabila's civil war triumph has changed thinking in the capital remains to be tested.</p>
<p>Announcing an incomplete transitional government late on Thursday after five hours of closed-door talks with aides, Kabila abolished the post of prime minister and created a presidential regime, excluding Tshisekedi.</p>
<p>For his supporters, Tshisekedi was the staunchest and most incorruptible opponent of Mobutu -- spending time in jail and under house arrest.</p>
<p>They see the burly leader of the Union for Democracy and Social Progress (UDPS) as the one man who stood up to Mobutu in public, in government, and in face-to-face meetings.</p>
<p>At the height of the 1990s campaign for democracy, Tshisekedi denounced Mobutu as a &quot;human monster&quot; and called for the president to flee the country or stand trial for corruption and other crimes.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi has gone to some lengths to cultivate his image as a man of the people, avoiding the typical excesses of Zaire's ruling elite. He drives a modest Peugeot.</p>
<p>But some diplomats question his democratic credentials while rivals blame him for the fragmentation the political opposition.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi, 64, is a native of diamond-rich Kasai Province.</p>
<p>He spent his formative political years as both a diplomat and a minister of Mobutu, who ruled from 1965 until fleeing Kinshasa on May 16 -- the day before Kabila's rebels marched into the city.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi spearheaded domestic calls for multi-party politics which, coupled with pressure from abroad, forced a reluctant Mobutu to start to open the door to democracy in 1990.</p>
<p>In 1991 Mobutu appointed Tshisekedi first state commissar (prime minister). Mobutu dismissed him 12 days later when he refused to swear an oath of allegiance to him.</p>
<p>A sovereign national conference elected Tshisekedi prime minister in 1992. Mobutu sacked him again in 1993 but this time Tshisekedi refused to go -- maintaining a parallel government.</p>
<p>Later that year, he successfully led a campaign which blocked the introduction of five million zaire banknotes but soldiers went on a looting spree when paid in the notes.</p>
<p>Kabila's rebellion in eastern Zaire changed the balance of power in Zaire.</p>
<p>As the revolt gathered momentum, Tshisekedi called for talks with the rebels and a negotiated settlement.</p>
<p>In the dying days of the war, Zaire's transitional parliament nominated Tshisekedi as its candidate for prime minister.</p>
<p>Mobutu looked on the point of reappointing his veteran foe until Tshisekedi named a government from his own loyalists, leaving a handful of portfolios unfilled for the rebels.</p>
<p>Mobutu's supporters in parliament and Tshisekedi's opposition allies there, frustrated at being left out in the cold, withdrew their backing.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi and his supporters marched through tear gas towards the prime minister's office, vowing to move in. Mobutu's security forces prevented him.</p>
<p>Born on December 14, 1932, in the central city of Kananga, Tshisekedi trained as a lawyer and graduated from the Catholic Lovanium University in Kinshasa in 1961.</p>
<p>As interior minister from 1965, when Mobutu seized power, until 1968, he helped write the N'Sele Manifesto which laid the groundwork for Zaire's conversion to single-party rule.</p>
<p>He served as justice minister and planning minister before going to Morocco as ambassador in 1969. He was later deputy speaker of parliament and chairman of state airline, Air Zaire.</p>
<p>Tshisekedi started speaking out against the government in 1980 as a founding member of the Group of 13, an organisation of parliamentarians who published a letter to Mobutu condemning government corruption and calling for democratic reforms.</p>
<p>He was arrested in 1982 and sentenced to 15 years in prison for treason. He was released the following year after protests from Amnesty International and other human rights groups.</p>
<p>From time to time thereafter, Tshisekedi was placed under house arrest or imprisoned for mounting anti-Mobutu protests.</p>
<p>At one point the government announced he had been placed in a mental institution after trying to stage a demonstration against Mobutu in the capital.</p>
<p>He has been married to Marthe Kasalu since 1961. They have six sons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZAIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
