<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608789" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: Kazakhs may see giant oil deal signed this summer.</title>
<headline>Kazakhs may see giant oil deal signed this summer.</headline>
<byline>Murat Buldekbayev</byline>
<dateline>ALMATY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kazakhstan needs $150 billion to tap its huge oil reserves on the continental shelf of the Caspian Sea, and an international production-sharing deal may be signed by summer, senior officials said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;According to expert estimates, total investment to develop Kazakhstan's offshore oil fields will probably amount to $150 billion,&quot; said Kazakh President Nursulatan Nazarbayev.</p>
<p>The Central Asian leader was speaking at a government ceremony to present awards to Kazakhs and foreigners for geophysical exploration of the Caspian shelf.</p>
<p>The Kazakhstancaspiyshelf, or KCS, consortium, set up in 1993, groups Agip SpA, a BP /Statoil alliance, British Gas, Mobil Corp, Royal Dutch/Shell, Total SA and Kazakh joint-stock company Kazakhstancaspiyshelf (KCS).</p>
<p>KCS has carried out one of the largest offshore seismic studies ever and plans to tap oil from its findings in 12 blocks, or sections, in the Kazakh shelf.</p>
<p>&quot;The companies which are in the consortium are to sign an agreement on production-sharing, whose conditions have not yet been finalised,&quot; said KCS representative Kezhebek Ibrashev.</p>
<p>&quot;But we plan to sign the agreement by the middle of the summer.&quot;</p>
<p>KCS estimates Kazakh Caspian offshore reserves at 8.2 billion tonnes of crude oil and around two trillion cubic metres of natural gas.</p>
<p>The consortium has so far spent $218 million exploring an area of over 100,000 square km on the Caspian shelf, and Ibrashev said the money would be recompensed in line with the forthcoming production-sharing agreement.</p>
<p>Oil-rich Kazakhstan plans to produce 26.5 million tonnes of crude oil this year. It hopes to boost output to 100 million tonnes in 2000 and 170 million tonnes in 2010 to realise its dream of becoming the world's sixth largest oil producer.</p>
<p>--Almaty Newsroom, +7 3272 509410</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALMATY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
