<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608757" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UZBEKISTAN: Uzbekistan working on new oil, gas legislation.</title>
<headline>Uzbekistan working on new oil, gas legislation.</headline>
<dateline>TASHKENT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Uzbekistan is working on new hydrocarbons legislation and could be ready to push through the laws aimed at regulating the oil and gas sector by the end of the year, a senior energy official said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Yes, work on that legislation is going on at the moment,&quot; Ibrat Zaynutdinov, deputy chairman of state oil and gas concern Uzbekneftegaz, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very serious work that cannot just be pushed through, but I think that this year it may be adopted.&quot;</p>
<p>Uzbekistan already has a subsoil law in place and various other laws which can protect the interests of foreign partners in joint oil and gas projects with the Central Asian republic.</p>
<p>But some Western energy executives said privately they would prefer to see legislation tightened before making investments.</p>
<p>Western oil and gas firms welcomed the introduction of hydrocarbon legislation by Uzbekistan's southern neighbour Turkmenistan earlier this year. The hydrocarbons law was hailed as a &quot;quantum leap forward&quot; by one executive.</p>
<p>But Zaynutdinov said he did not believe the absence of a hydrocarbons law in Uzbekistan had hampered foreign investment much so far.</p>
<p>&quot;The absence of this legislation is not a big problem for investors, because there are already a lot of laws which legislate the work of such companies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan is keen to open its huge energy reserves to foreign companies.</p>
<p>The former Soviet republic is lying on estimated reserves of 5.429 trillion cubic metres of natural gas, 4.4 billion tonnes of oil and 629 million tonnes of gas condensate.</p>
<p>It produced 7.66 million tonnes (153,200 barrels per day) of oil and gas condensates in 1996, and aims to boost output to 8.0 million (160,000 bpd) in 1997 and 10.0 million (200,000 bpd) by 2000.</p>
<p>Natural gas output last year was around 50 billion cubic metres, up slightly from 1995.</p>
<p>-- Moscow Newsroom +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UZBK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TASHKENT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UZBEKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
