<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608760" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Yugo M1 money supply up, cash down - institute.</title>
<headline>Yugo M1 money supply up, cash down - institute.</headline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Yugoslavia's money supply is expanding slowly, indicating the National Bank of Yugoslavia (NBY) is again issuing money, the Belgrade-based Economics institute said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe money supply has continued expanding and is now probably very close to the level in late December, but its structure has changed,&quot; said Miroljub Labus, a prominent economist with the institute.</p>
<p>March M1 money supply stood at 5.289 billion dinars compared to 5.157 billion in February, an increase of 2.5 percent, the institute said in its latest monthly report.</p>
<p>But the structure has changed, with cash in circulation accounting for 45 percent in March, down from 55 percent last December, when M1 soared to a record 5.495 billion dinars.</p>
<p>M1 dropped in January to 5.234 billion dinars.</p>
<p>Monetary expansion in the last days of 1996 led to a plunge in the dinar's black market rate to 4.3 to the German mark in the first two weeks of 1997.</p>
<p>The dinar has recovered on the black market to 3.5-3.6 to the mark after the NBY started withdrawing cash to stabilize the national currency and restore financial discipline.</p>
<p>The dinar was last devalued in November 1995 to 3.3 to the German mark, after being kept at par to the mark since January 24, 1994.</p>
<p>Since retail price growth has been very slow over the past four months, money supply is recovering quickly and beginning to approach its long-term value of 1.5 billion marks in real terms in early 1994, Labus said.</p>
<p>This is the equivalent of the 1.5 billion dinars of real purchasing power in February-March 1994, when the dinar exchange rate was at par to the German mark.</p>
<p>The central bank discount rate in real terms is also approaching its early 1994 level of five percent, when implementation of the programme of economic and monetary reconstruction began, the report said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile liquidity is still high and monthly interest rates on the money market are between 10 and 11 percent. -- Amra Kevic, Belgrade newsroom +381 11 222 4305</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E121">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
