<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608741" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Yugoslav firms' optimism improves slightly.</title>
<headline>Yugoslav firms' optimism improves slightly.</headline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1996-05-26</dateline>
<text>
<p>Yugoslav firms were slightly more optimistic about economic prospects in April after relatively stable indicators in the first months of the year, the Belgrade-based Economics Institute said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;It is evident that firms have reacted to price and dinar stability with reduced pessimism in comparison to the previous months of the year,&quot; said Goran Pitic, a prominent economist with the institute.</p>
<p>The dinar's black market value has stabilized at 3.6 to the German mark compared with the official rate of 3.3.</p>
<p>According to official statistics, prices rose 0.1 percent in April after rising 1.0 percent in March.</p>
<p>Year-on-year April retail price growth was 22.7 percent while cumulative January-April prices rose 29.4 percent against the same four-month period last year.</p>
<p>Industrial output dropped 0.1 percent in April after rising 7.4 percent in March. Cumulative January-April output rose 7.3 percent against the same period last year.</p>
<p>&quot;But what remains a warning are inflationary expectations which are still too high despite easing slightly in April due to stable prices and dinar,&quot; Pitic said.</p>
<p>According to the institute's poll of 300 firms accounting for 55 percent of the industial and energy sectors, most still saw the overall economic climate as bad.</p>
<p>More firms reported improved production activity in April, with 22.9 percent saying their output rose, 16.3 percent that it dropped, while the rest said it was unchanged.</p>
<p>But as many as 65.9 percent assessed their current position as bad and 3.6 percent as good. Altogether 26.5 percent saw their position improving in the next three months while 13.5 percent said it would be worse.</p>
<p>Business risk was seen growing in the coming period by 36.3 percent of respondents and just 7.5 percent expected it would drop.</p>
<p>Use of capacity was reported by the firms to have risen slightly to nearly 58 percent.</p>
<p>Stocks of raw materials and semi-finished goods were low among 51.6 percent of the polled, compared with just 1.4 percent who said their stocks were high.</p>
<p>Lack of credit was listed by 38.7 percent as the major obstacle to raising production, low demand by 26.4 percent and shortage of imported raw materials 24.3 percent.</p>
<p>Although inflationary expectations eased, 43.7 percent still believed prices of input would increase in the next three months and only 0.5 percent said they would drop.</p>
<p>Prices of finished products are expected to go up by 20.6 percent of respondents and down by just 1.7 percent of the firms.</p>
<p>Although some 33.6 percent of the firms saw their sales on the local market improving in the next three months, as many as 40.7 percent said they did not expect to raise exports.</p>
<p>Nearly 30 percent of the firms consider the volume of installed capacity too large for their needs.</p>
<p>Although lack of capital remained the main problem for most firms, 31.7 saw real prospects of investments from domestic sources and 13.5 percent from foreign sources.</p>
<p>More than 55 percent of the firms reported levels of either their claims or debts were too high.</p>
<p>-- Amra Kevic, Belgrade newsroom +381 11 222 4305</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-26"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
