<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608768" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech crown turmoil hits investment reputation.</title>
<headline>Czech crown turmoil hits investment reputation.</headline>
<byline>Nigel Stephenson</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Czech Republic, with its government in suspended animation and the crown under attack, has suffered a blow to its investment reputation from which it could take a long time to recover, analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>The crown has been under severe selling pressure all week as investors, alarmed at an economic downturn and political uncertainty, aggressively sold the currency and forced the central bank to intervene in its support.</p>
<p>But some analysts said the crown turmoil was only a symptom of the country's deeper problems and that even a devaluation, which many economists say is inevitable, was not the answer.</p>
<p>&quot;On the one side is the deterioration of all economic fundamentals which was followed by growing distrust of the population and the outside world in the ruling coalition,&quot; said economist Jiri Krovak of Wood &amp; Co.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not the turmoil on the market and very probable devaluation which can have some negative long-term impact on the economy but the causes of this which certainly damage the picture of this country in the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Czech Republic has been held up as a shining example of relatively painless transition from a communist to a market economy. The currency has been stable and, until recently, monetarist Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus seemed to have found the formula for balanced growth.</p>
<p>Standard &amp; Poor's rates Czech sovereign debt an investment-grade A and Moody's Investors Services rates it Baa1, among the highest ratings for a post-Communist country.</p>
<p>But industrial output has turned down and the current account and trade deficits have widened. Several high-profile financial scandals have added to Prague's reputation for lax regulation of financial markets.</p>
<p>In response, the government unveiled a package of measures last month to kick-start the economy, including spending cuts, limits on wage growth and measures against economic crime.</p>
<p>&quot;It is pretty clear the government waited too long and now the question is whether the measures are too little,&quot; said Stephen Heintz of Prague's Institute of East-West Studies.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been real stability here since 1988 and that has been an asset. Now the government line-up seems to be a liability. How much change in the government do you make without doing damage in the underlying confidence that people have had in Mr Klaus in particular,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The three coalition parties agreed to a reshuffle but, despite a series of meetings this week, no decisions were taken on which ministers should go. Party leaders were holding separate meetings this week.</p>
<p>Heintz said overseas investors viewed events nervously.</p>
<p>&quot;It is having a material influence on the behaviour of investors and discouraging them from considering additional investment at the moment,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Many economists said that despite its rapid transformation in some areas, microeconomic restructuring at company level had been inadequate and capital markets had not developed.</p>
<p>&quot;Such a crisis cannot simply pass. Politicians will have to think of the roots...Definitely there will be much more focus on these problems,&quot; said Vladimir Kreidl of Patria Finance, adding that he saw the current problems as transitory.</p>
<p>&quot;There is now a gradually building consensus among the political parties that the unwillingness to regulate capital markets was a serious mistake and the government's package of measures obliges it to take some steps,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
