<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608781" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Average prices down, volume up on Bucharest bourse.</title>
<headline>Average prices down, volume up on Bucharest bourse.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bucharest bourse saw most average prices slide on Friday as investors held on to their wait-and-see mood.</p>
<p>Two unofficial indices, the VAB and the BIG, dropped by 6.5 and 3.51 percent respectively from the previous session. The BIG first-tier index was 4.66 percent down at 2,897.67 points.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors still consider prices too high, their waiting mood will stay on part of next week, too,&quot; said a trader.</p>
<p>Volumes rose to 2.3 million shares from 1.9 million and turnover went up by some 700 million lei to 7.1 billion.</p>
<p>The rise in volume and turnover levels was mainly a result of two special trades in first-tier Oltchim chemical plant and Policolor  PLCR.BX dye maker, a second-tier listing.</p>
<p>Oltchim had a special trade -- a deal struck outside the market and reported to the exchange later -- involving 200,000 shares worth a total 480 million lei. The Policolor deal was worth 280 million lei from trading in 50,000 shares.</p>
<p>The two deals helped the stocks close higher. Oltchim ended 50 lei up at 2,400 and Policolor firmed 100 lei to 5,600.</p>
<p>The first tier, which lists three more companies besides Oltchim, led the market, with around 75 percent of turnover.</p>
<p>First-tier Azomures fertiliser maker and pharmaceuticals company Antibiotice  ATBE.BX lost on their average prices and also closed 150 lei and 100 lei weaker at 2,500 and 4,800.</p>
<p>Terapia pharmaceuticals was the only first-tier stock to gain on both average and closing quotes. It ended 50 lei firmer at 6,300.</p>
<p>Policolor was the highlight of otherwise lacklustre second-tier trading with 1.2 billion lei in turnover.</p>
<p>On the second tier, eight stocks had no trade and three companies were suspended pending announcement of 1996 results.</p>
<p>		MAY 23    MAY 22  Week's change  1997 high 1997 low</p>
<p>VAB-Index  865.3     925.3    -1.7 pct	1,041.0    262.0</p>
<p>BIG-Index  852.53    883.58   -0.42 pct     1,020.44   266.43</p>
<p>($=7,088 lei)</p>
<p>-- Luli Popescu, Bucharest Newsroom 40-1 3120264</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
