<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608728" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Sergeyev takes over Russian defence ministry.</title>
<headline>Sergeyev takes over Russian defence ministry.</headline>
<byline>Gareth Jones</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin on Friday confirmed Igor Sergeyev as defence minister charged with the difficult task of turning Russia's cumbersome, cash-strapped military into a leaner, professional force.</p>
<p>A Kremlin spokesman said Yeltsin had also named General Anatoly Kvashnin as acting head of the general staff.</p>
<p>The appointments follow Yeltsin's surprise decision on Thursday to sack defence minister Igor Rodionov and general staff chief Viktor Samsonov. Yeltsin accused them of dragging their feet over urgently needed military reforms.</p>
<p>The new minister has headed the Strategic Rocket Forces since 1992, responsible for 756 inter-continental missiles with 3,535 nuclear warheads which make up Russia's strategic arsenal.</p>
<p>Sergeyev, 59, has said he views Russia's nuclear force as the backbone of its defence, and describes it as one that is especially economical at a time of spending cutbacks.</p>
<p>Russian ministers, facing lower than expected tax revenues, are struggling to find cash to fund their budget promises. They have already cut spending and promise to keep purse-strings tight regardless of likely demands from parliamentarians debating the cuts on Friday.</p>
<p>The silver-haired, bespectacled Sergeyev has spoken out in favor of a START-3 nuclear arms reduction agreement with the United States as an extension of the START-2 accord cutting Russian and American nuclear arsenals.</p>
<p>A man with good Western contacts, he has also argued for a political deal with NATO to prevent the stationing of nuclear forces on the territory of new eastern European members the Atlantic alliance is expected to invite into NATO in July.</p>
<p>Yeltsin, who is commander-in-chief of the armed forces, promised during his re-election campaign last year to end conscription by 2000 and create a modern, professional army.</p>
<p>But the plan has run into a shortage of funds and a marked lack of enthusiasm in the upper ranks.</p>
<p>Sergeyev will also have to oversee a crackdown on high-level army corruption.</p>
<p>Military prosecutors say about 20 generals and 100 colonels are being investigted for graft. Military prosecutors this week arrested Konstantin Kobets, one of the country's top generals and a deputy defence minister, on charges of corruption. He denies the charges.</p>
<p>NTV commercial television said on Friday that a loyal Yeltsin ally, Lieutenant General Viktor Chechevatov who commands the Far East military district, had been asked to head the general staff but had turned down the offer.</p>
<p>The head of the general staff is number two in Russia's armed forces. He is the third person, after the president and the defence minister, to have control over the use of nuclear weapons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
