<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608791" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Western envoys express concern to Tudjman.</title>
<headline>Western envoys express concern to Tudjman.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Smith</byline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Western ambassadors joined together on Friday to express concern to Croatian President Franjo Tudjman over the treatment of ethnic Serbs who have allegedly been abused after returning to their pre-war homes.</p>
<p>The joint demarche to the president was made by the ambassadors of the five Contact Group members -- United States, France, Germany, Russia and Britain -- as well as the envoys of Sweden, The Netherlands, Belgium, Italy and the European Union.</p>
<p>One diplomat told Reuters: &quot;It was a coordinated diplomatic approach to the government expressing our concern.&quot;</p>
<p>The note given to Tudjman was not a protest, he said, but rather a joint action by the ambassadors.</p>
<p>&quot;They were expressing the international community's joint concern over some of the things that have happened here. It's a sign that the international community supports what the United States has been saying publicly,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tudjman was quoted by Croatian news agency HINA as saying the government would consider what it called a &quot;protest note&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;There are reasons for all of us to be worried -- for both the government and the representatives of the international community -- about the return of refugees,&quot; Tudjman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are surprised to see such a one-sided approach which shows concern for the Serb minority in Croatia,&quot; he said, adding that not once had a similar concern been expressed for Croats who were expelled and whose homes destroyed in the war.</p>
<p>U.S. Ambassador Peter Galbraith made his strongest public criticism of Zagreb yet at a news conference earlier this week when he said the United States would only support Croatia's integration into Western Institutions with preconditions.</p>
<p>These conditions include Croatia permitting the return of all refugees and displaced persons to their homes.</p>
<p>U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright last week lambasted Granic over Croatia's treatment of Serbs and other Dayton peace accord violations.</p>
<p>She reiterated warnings that Croatia's keen desire to become fully integrated into the West would be jeopardised if Zagreb failed to meet its commitments under the Dayton accords.</p>
<p>A key to the Dayton peace accords which ended the Bosnian war is that all displaced people should be able to return home.</p>
<p>The United Nations refugee agency on Thursday accused Croatia of &quot;ethnic engineering&quot; following the reports of evictions and abuse of Serb families who had returned home.</p>
<p>Spokesman for the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees in Sarajevo Mans Nyberg told reporters empty houses in the former Serb region of Krajina which had formerly belonged to Serbs had been earmarked for Croatian refugees.</p>
<p>&quot;Croatian authorities and not Croatian refugees from FRY (Yugoslavia) evicted those families,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ten families who had returned to their homes during the last two months had been evicted, he added. &quot;This is, of course, nothing but ethnic engineering which should be condemned in the strongest terms.&quot;</p>
<p>Tudjman on Friday responded to the accusation saying: &quot;Claims that crimes in Croatia are organised and the government is unable to guarantee safety are unacceptable for the Croatian government and for the Croatian public,&quot; HINA said.</p>
<p>Croatia is launching a massive resettlement programme for citizens displaced during the war -- both Croats and Serbs. Before the war around half a million ethnic Serbs lived in Croatia, while now only around 100,000 remain.</p>
<p>Zagreb is adamant returns should be carried out in an organised manner and says it cannot be held responsible for what happens if people decide to go back spontaneously. Some of those who were attacked last week had arrived unannounced in their villages, provoking anger in nervous Croats.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
