<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608731" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: PRESS DIGEST - Poland - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Poland - May 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>Here are highlights from Polish newspapers this morning.</p>
<p>FRONT PAGE POLITICAL NEWS</p>
<p>RZECZPOSPOLITA - Around 26 percent of Poles are ready to vote for the rightist Solidarity Electoral Action (AWS) in the parliamentary elections this September, while 24 percent support the ex-communist Democratic Left Alliance (SLD) and 13 percent the centrist Union for Freedom (UW), a survey by the PBS polling institute said.</p>
<p>ECONOMIC AND MARKET STORIES</p>
<p>RZECZPOSPOLITA</p>
<p>- Over 300 firms from 15 countries are exhibiting road construction machinery, new technologies, raw materials and road lighting and signalling equipment at the Autostrada Polska road construction fair in Kielce, southern Poland.</p>
<p>- Telecommunications Minister Andrzej Zielinski has signed the new regulations on cooperation between state-owned telecoms monopolist Telekomunikacja Polska SA (TPSA) and mobile phone operators.</p>
<p>GSM operators will have to lease lines from TPSA linking their exchanges with TPSA's inter-city exchanges, Zielinski said.</p>
<p>- Poland's fuel distributors sold 5.989 million tonnes of diesel oil and 5.198 million tonnes of petrol in 1996, Polish Liquid Fuels Chamber president Andrzej Szczesniak said.</p>
<p>- The supervisory board of Star truck maker in Starachowice, southern Poland, has dismissed two board members, board president Witold Celebanski and deputy president Wojciech Dworzanski.</p>
<p>The dismissal was agreed between automotive group Sobieslaw Zasada Centrum (SZC), which holds a 28 percent stake in the plant, the trade unions and the treasury ministry.</p>
<p>- The PP Silikatow silicate plant in Bialystok, northeastern Poland, will be leased to employees for the next ten years as a result of its privatisation scheduled for June this year.</p>
<p>- A C-series share issue planned by the CeTO firm managing the regulated over-the-counter market will not take place as CeTO's shareholders declined to buy the shares.</p>
<p>The issue's failure may mean that the company is facing</p>
<p>Transmission was aborted</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
