<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608716" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech cen. bank battles crown speculators again.</title>
<headline>Czech cen. bank battles crown speculators again.</headline>
<byline>Alan Crosby</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Czech National Bank (CNB) battled speculators again on Friday to support the falling crown, but analysts remained pessimistic that the central bank could keep the currency at current levels.</p>
<p>The CNB, for the second consecutive day and fourth time in the past week, intervened on the market after speculators in London pushed the crown sharply lower.</p>
<p>The central bank, which is determined not to devalue what was once the most stable currency in post-communist central Europe, moved when the crown fell to more than five percent below the midpoint of its dollar/mark basket.</p>
<p>The CNB uses the basket to fix the crown's exchange rate daily.</p>
<p>&quot;We saw the intervention today, but I don't know how many other tools the central bank has left,&quot; said Breta Tichanek of ING Bank. &quot;The direct buying of crowns is expensive, it can't last for a long time,&quot;</p>
<p>The central bank intervention pulled the crown back to around 2.5 percent below the mid point.</p>
<p>The CNB has fought the wave of speculative short-selling, which has pushed the crown to record lows on several occasions, with a mix of intervention and interest rate tools.</p>
<p>It has raised its Lombard lending facility to 50 percent from 14 percent, its repurchase rate to 75 percent from 12.9 percent, and barred non-residents from Czech money markets.</p>
<p>    But dealers said the cost of the CNB's policies,   economic</p>
<p>and monetary, was too high to maintain for more than another week or two at most.</p>
<p>&quot;The immediate risk for the crown is a further weakening of the economy,&quot; said Tony Norfield, treasury economist at ABN Amro in London. &quot;That would encourage a renewed speculative attack, perhaps forcing the central bank to widen the official currency band.&quot;</p>
<p>The central bank is estimated to have spent some $2-3 billion so far in direct intervention alone.</p>
<p>Speculators attacked the currency, believing it to be vulnerable due to a soaring balance of payments deficit and a sharp slowdown in Czech economic growth.</p>
<p>Short sellers can make huge profits if they force the devaluation of a currency, notably when the British pound was forced out of the European exchange rate mechanism in 1992.</p>
<p>Analysts said the central bank, with limited reserves and few effective options at its disposal, might be running out of</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
