<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608754" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: IMF says Albania must deal with pyramids, deficit.</title>
<headline>IMF says Albania must deal with pyramids, deficit.</headline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) on Friday said Albania should deal urgently with the problems of its budget deficit and crooked pyramid investment schemes which sparked widespread rioting in March.</p>
<p>The IMF has had a mission in Albania, which spent 10 days in the country and gave detailed recommendations to Prime Minister Bashkim Fino and President Sali Berisha.</p>
<p>&quot;Albania's economic problems are very serious. We are particularly concerned about two issues, the budget deficit and the resolution of the pyramid scheme problem,&quot; the IMF said in a statement.</p>
<p>Albanians pumped huge amounts of money into get-rich-quick pyramid schemes, which swallowed an estimated $1.2 billion.</p>
<p>When several schemes collapsed, thousands of people lost their money and the country erupted in riots and looting.</p>
<p>&quot;Albania needs to resolve the problem of the pyramid schemes once and for all -- both to protect the interests of the depositors and to ensure that new schemes cannot flourish,&quot; the IMF added.</p>
<p>It said audits of the schemes should take place to find the insolvent schemes, which should then be closed and have their assets traced as a means to compensate depositors.</p>
<p>Solvent schemes should be controlled by administrators in the interests of depositors, the IMF added.</p>
<p>&quot;We agree with the Albanian authorities that the assets are the only feasible source of compensation for depositors and every effort should be made to recover,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>It also said that the country's budget deficit was of concern and would be more than was planned in a 1997 budget passed recently by parliament.</p>
<p>It said the country should keep the deficit under control by rebuilding tax collection, especially customs taxes, increasing some taxes, especially VAT and continuing a tight control of spending.</p>
<p>&quot;The IMF remains to willing to cooperate with Albania. Until the political and security situation is clearer, we cannot discuss a fully worked out economic programme,&quot; it added and said it would continue to advise the Albanian authorities.</p>
<p>-- Patrick Lannin, Tirana newsroom +355 42 298 25</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
