<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608715" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech leaders consult parties on cabinet changes.</title>
<headline>Czech leaders consult parties on cabinet changes.</headline>
<byline>Jan Lopatka</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leaders of the three parties in the Czech ruling coalition tried again on Friday to make changes in the cabinet, but had yet to complete an agreement, Deputy Prime Minister Josef Lux said.</p>
<p>The Czech news agency CTK quoted an unnamed top official of Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus's party as saying its leadership was looking at replacing Finance Minister Ivan Kocarnik.</p>
<p>It said Klaus's Civic Democratic Party (ODS) was considering replacing Kocarnik with another politician and installing an independent expert as first deputy finance minister.</p>
<p>Klaus's chief cabinet adviser Jiri Weigl, an economist who is not affiliated with a political party, was under consideration for the deputy minister's post, CTK said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we made progress,&quot; Lux told journalists, referring to the latest contacts between the parties.</p>
<p>Klaus agreed with coalition partners on Wednesday that a cabinet change was needed amid an economic downturn which has sapped confidence in the government.</p>
<p>The reshuffle has become more sensitive as the Czech crown has been battered by foreign speculators reacting to economic fundamentals and political instability.</p>
<p>The leadership of each of the coalition parties was to hold separate meetings over the weekend, after which an agreement may be concluded, Lux said.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it (an agreement) will be today because the leaderships of the parties are meeting today and tomorrow. I think there could be a final resolution after these meetings,&quot; Lux, leader of the Christian Democrats (KDU-CSL), said.</p>
<p>Speculation on which ministers might lose their cabinet seats has focused primarily on Kocarnik and Industry and Trade Minister Vladimir Dlouhy, of the third coalition member, the Civic Democratic Alliance (ODA).</p>
<p>Earlier this week, Dlouhy said he was prepared to step down, but that he had made no firm decision and would consult party leaders on Saturday.</p>
<p>ODA chairman Michael Zantovsky told a news conference on Friday an agreement on cabinet changes might require a restatement of the principles of the coalition agreement which was hammered out after inconclusive elections last June.</p>
<p>He said that the ODA, which considers itself the most pro-business of the three centre-right parties, was sensing a recent shift in the political tilt of the government.</p>
<p>&quot;There are some tendencies appearing in some government measures which do not reflect a government of the centre-right, but rather a centre-left one, therefore we want to clarify that the basic principles are still valid,&quot; Zantovsky said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
