<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608724" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: Bosnia textile maker thrives on cheap labor.</title>
<headline>Bosnia textile maker thrives on cheap labor.</headline>
<byline>Sabina Cosic</byline>
<dateline>TRAVNIK, Bosnia 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A textile company in central Bosnia is one of the few firms in this industry that earns a hard currency income using a simple recipe -- selling cheap labor to foreign clients until better times arrive.</p>
<p>A pre-war textile giant with seven factories scattered around Bosnia and many side businesses, &quot;Borac&quot; now uses only three factories in Travnik but still managed to gross 12 million German marks ($7 million) in earnings last year.</p>
<p>&quot;Critics say we are selling our muscles cheap but I'd like someone to offer us something else which would employ people and give them regular salaries,&quot; Borac's general director Mehmed Corhodzic told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Borac's 2,000 employees, mainly women, assemble clothes for foreign clients who ship the fabrics to the factory and get a finished product with the client's label on it in return.</p>
<p>The job provides a 300 marks salary, higher than the 250 marks average per month in the Moslem-Croat federation.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not much, but it's a regular salary and we haven't been late a single day in paying it out throughout the war,&quot; Corhodzic said.</p>
<p>He said the firm aimed for some 15.5 million marks in earnings this year. &quot;The same three factories made about 25 million marks before the war, so we are getting closer to the 1991 level,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Bosnia emerged shattered from a 43-month war which ended with the Dayton peace accord in November 1995. But the country remains in desperate need of large infrastructure investments and sizeable funds to restart its industry, which is operating at less than 20 percent of its pre-war capacity.</p>
<p>The international community has already committed several billion dollars to help repair Bosnia but companies like Borac will have to find their own way back to the world market.</p>
<p>In a country where many textile factories were set up under socialism to provide jobs for the rural population rather than to satisfy genuine market needs, Borac stood out as a company that appeared to understand the needs of the world market.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not much of a philosophy in this business -- (supply) high-quality products, good price and meet your deadlines,&quot; Corhodzic said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have renewed the cooperation with our pre-war clients from Italy and Germany because they were convinced they would be getting the same quality as before,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But before wooing their clients back, the factory had to spend about four million Marks to repair the damage inflicted by artillery shells during the war.</p>
<p>&quot;If someone was willing to invest five million marks we'd be back in top form,&quot; Corhodzic said, explaining that although the machines have been repaired, they needed upgrading and spare parts for maintenance.</p>
<p>The company had already received two offers for direct investment from Germany, but is taking its time to think them over, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;As much as we are interested in joint ventures and investors, we are not in a position in which our survival depends solely on foreign investments because we want to get the best price for our work,&quot; Corhodzic said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I43000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TRAVNIK, Bosnia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
