<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608771" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: FOCUS-Hungary hopes for higher credit ratings.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Hungary hopes for higher credit ratings.</headline>
<byline>Sandor Peto</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European credit rating agency IBCA on Friday signalled it could raise Hungary's credit rating and this move could be followed by other rating agencies, National Bank of Hungary (NBH) president Gyorgy Suranyi said.</p>
<p>IBCA, which currently rates Hungary's debt at BBB-, announced it had placed Hungary's long-term foreign currency rating on RatingWatch with positive implications.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that the other rating agencies will evaluate similarly what has happened in the recent period,&quot; Suranyi told Reuters.</p>
<p>One year ago, IBCA was the first international rating agency to grant Hungary an investment grade rating, without which many investors are unable to buy a country's securities. Later in 1996 all major rating agencies followed the step.</p>
<p>Moody's Investors Service rates Hungary's long-term foreign currency debt Baa3, and Standard &amp; Poor's Corp rates it BBB-.</p>
<p>IBCA said on Friday that Hungary's economic fundamentals were strong, its structural adjustment well advanced, economic recovery was underway and its external current account position was sustainable.</p>
<p>Suranyi said he was glad to hear IBCA's announcement, but added that rating agencies usually followed the improvement of Hungary's credit perception on the international debt markets only with a very long delay.</p>
<p>&quot;I also hope that the time differential between the market's evaluation and the rating agencies' devaluation will somewhat shorten,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The judgement of the market has been substantially more favourable for the past one and the half year than rating agencies',&quot; he added.</p>
<p>However, the upgradings would not be so important for Hungary this year than they were in 1996, Suranyi said.</p>
<p>&quot;The real difference is between investment and non-investment grade, and this breakthrough came last year.&quot;</p>
<p>Suranyi denied market talk that the NBH was looking to soon launch a 10-year dollar bond for up to $1.0 billion.</p>
<p>However, he confirmed that the NBH was considering tapping the international market with a benchmark bond.</p>
<p>&quot;If every condition is clearly favourable, we don't exclude that we will enter the market.&quot;</p>
<p>Suranyi confirmed reports of business daily Vilaggazdasag that the NBH had to extend its licence for issuing debt in the U.S. recently.</p>
<p>Along with the extension, the NBH also raised the limit amount by $250 million to $1.0 billion, the paper added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
