<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608762" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Devaluation fear prompts Czechs to dump crowns.</title>
<headline>Devaluation fear prompts Czechs to dump crowns.</headline>
<byline>Jan Lopatka</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Exchange offices in central Prague ran out of dollars and German marks on Friday as Czechs, fearful of a devaluation, dumped crown savings for foreign currencies.</p>
<p>Banks were crowded. Some large institutions confirmed that demand for foreign exchange had been many times normal levels in the past two days as people and companies joined foreign speculators in dumping the crown.</p>
<p>Some exchange booths in Prague's Wenceslas Square, the main shopping district, put up signs saying: &quot;No foreign currencies&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I've got just 10 marks here. Anytime we get more, people come and buy it immediately,&quot; an assistant at one of the exchange points said.</p>
<p>Demand for marks and dollars has soared despite President Vaclav Havel assuring the nation on Tursday that he would vontinue to keep his substantial savings in crowns.</p>
<p>The crown has been under strong pressure since last week when a wave of selling prompted the central bank to hike interest rates and intervene in the market to keep the crown within its fluctuation band.</p>
<p>The currency dived to an all-time low of minus 6.4 percent versus the basket on Thursday, but a round of restrictive moves and interventions propelled it up to less than two percent below the central bank's mark/dollar basket parity on Friday.</p>
<p>The government and central bank have repeatedly ruled out a devaluation of the currency, but some analysts said that sooner or later the central bank would either let the crown fall, or devalue.</p>
<p>One teller at bank IPB said demand for marks was about three times the normal level.</p>
<p>&quot;We have seen an increased interest in conversion both on accounts and in cash at our branches,&quot; said Irena Satavova, spokeswoman for the country's largest commercial bank, Komercni Banka a.s.</p>
<p>&quot;The data for the last two days show that the interest in transferring crown accounts into foreign currency accounts is about twice as large as the average,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
