<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608772" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Antenna Hungaria pays no dividend, eyes telecoms.</title>
<headline>Antenna Hungaria pays no dividend, eyes telecoms.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>State-owned broadcast infrastructure firm Antenna Hungaria Rt (AH) says it will not pay a dividend on its 1996 results as it needs the money to complete infrastructure required by the media law.</p>
<p>&quot;We will meet the legal deadlines and the (commercial) TV and radio stations will be able to go on the air,&quot; AH general manager Istvan Mate told a news conference on Friday following the company's annual general meeting.</p>
<p>Tenders are underway for concessions in two nationwide TV and radio channels.</p>
<p>In 1996, AH generated a net profit of 489 million forints on net sales of 8.37 billion forints, a results well above original expectations, as the media investment was delayed, Mate said. Antenna did not pay a dividend to the state in 1995 either, when it made a net profit of 264 million forints.</p>
<p>The TV tenders have entered their final phase while the tenders for the two radio channels are expected to be finalised and published in June.</p>
<p>AH will spend a total of four billion forints on building the broadcasting facilities which it is obliged to do under Hungary's media law, Mate said.</p>
<p>Privatisation agency APV Rt will foot 2.5 billion forints of the bill via a capital a increase of which it has already transferred 750 million forints and the remaining part will arrive by the end of June, Mate said.</p>
<p>AH Chairman Istvan Korda said the company remains interested in entering the telecommunications market on its own, or with domestic and foreign partners.</p>
<p>He added, however, that the state, which holds an over 90 percent stake in the company, should change regulations in order to enable AH to obtain a piece of the telecommunications market.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we can reasonably expect our majority owner to at least give us an equal chance,&quot; Korda said.</p>
<p>Hungary's long-distance and international telephony is under the monopoly of Matav Rt, 67 percent owned by a 50-50 consortium of Ameritech Corp and Deutsche Telekom, until the end of the year 2001.</p>
<p>AH has already started building a nationwide optical trunk network, to replace its ageing microwave communications system and plans to use part of its spare capacity to enter communications sectors which do not fall under the monopoly.</p>
<p>Korda also said they might form some sort of partnership with other Hungarian companies such as MVM, MOL or MAV, (which have their own communications networks).</p>
<p>Telecommunications ministry officials said earlier that establishing a second nationwide telecommunications company would require amendments of the current legislation.</p>
<p>Press reports said Hungary's economics cabinet had its first meeting on May 16 at which it considered the possibilities of giving the go-ahead for an alternative telecommunications company.</p>
<p>On Friday the economics cabinet discussed the issue for a second time and news agency MTI reported it gave its support for an alternative telecommunications company with a 60 percent domestic and 40 percent foreign stake.</p>
<p>One of the foreign companies that already said it would be prepared to invest as much $450 million over the next five years in such a venture is Unisource NV, a joint venture of Koninklijke PTT Nederland NV, Swiss Telecom PTT and Sweden's Telia AB. Unisource is part of AT&amp;T Corp's WorldPartners alliance.</p>
<p>-- Denes Albert, Budapest newsroom +36 1 327 4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
