<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608730" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVAKIA: PRESS DIGEST - Slovakia - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Slovakia - May 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>NARODNA OBRODA - The Slovak money market ground to a halt on Thursday as local banks stopped quoting crown deposit rates due to an acute shortage of liquidity on the market.</p>
<p>- Dealers said the Slovak crown on Thursday survived the third and the strongest downward attack from foreign speculators.</p>
<p>- Michel Bon, President of France Telecom Group, said the French telecommunication company could be interested in taking part in privatisation of the Slovak state-owned telecoms monopoly Slovenske Telekomunikacie.</p>
<p>- A private bank Dopravna Banka a.s. lost 150 million crowns in 1996. The bank said the loss resulted mainly from taking over Slovak branches of two troubled Czech banks, Coop Banka and Ekoagrobanka.</p>
<p>SME - U.S. President Bill Clinton has sent a letter to the Slovak President Michal Kovac in which he assured him that NATO enlargement process will continue after the alliance's Madrid summit in July.</p>
<p>- The Central Referendum Committee said it would not accept as legal a referendum with only three question -- all on NATO membership -- and without a question on direct presidential elections. Interior Minister Gustav Krajci has started distributing ballots with only NATO questions.</p>
<p>- The paper quotes unnamed political analysts as saying minister Krajci was thwarting the referedumon on direct presidential election.</p>
<p>PRAVDA - Mayors of several Slovak towns are confused by distribution of two types of referendum ballots - one type with three question on NATO referendum and one question on direct presidential elections and the second type with only three questions on integration in NATO.</p>
<p>HOSPODARSKE NOVINY - Ludova Banka a.s., a subsidiary of the Austrian bank Volksbank, posted a net profit of 113 million crowns in 1996, compared with 92 million in 1995. -- Bratislava Newsroom, 421-7-521-8402</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVAKIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
