<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608794" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: FOCUS-Duma not ready to dismantle Russian budget.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Duma not ready to dismantle Russian budget.</headline>
<byline>Peter Henderson</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's parliament, eager to have a say in dismantling the budget it passed three months ago, delayed approving massive spending cuts on Friday by asking the government to bring it more information next month.</p>
<p>&quot;The government must submit its measures on the revenue side of the budget,&quot; said Yuri Voronin, Deputy Chairman of the State Duma Budget Committee.</p>
<p>&quot;Only after that can we reasonably look at the question (of spending cuts),&quot; Voronin, a communist, said.</p>
<p>Deputies in the Duma lower house voted by 321 to 11 to delay discussion on the cuts until the government explained how it would raise an extra 30 trillion roubles ($5.2 billion).</p>
<p>The government wants to slash the 1997 budget by one fifth, which has astonished legislators of all political stripes.</p>
<p>Duma representatives said they did not believe such large cuts were necessary and were angry the government's spending bill, known as sequestration, reorders spending priorities.</p>
<p>&quot;The bill submitted by the government is not sequestration but a new budget,&quot; independent deputy Alexander Zhukov told reporters.</p>
<p>Zhukov had suggested that the government withdraw its sequestration proposals and cut each ministry's spending by the same percentage, excluding so-called protected items -- health care, pension fund payments and a few other social items.</p>
<p>The government sequestration plans would cut spending by 55 percent in areas like agriculture and culture, but by much less in others.</p>
<p>Communists on Friday also withdrew a non-binding bill calling for doubling the money supply and using the extra cash to pay overdue wages and pensions. Both suggestions will probably be rescheduled for debate with the sequestration.</p>
<p>Russian ministers have made clear that they would disregard any vote against their plans to cut spending from the Duma, which took months to pass the original 1997 budget bill.</p>
<p>&quot;Generally there is no will to take a decision,&quot; First Deputy Prime Minister Anatoly Chubais told reporters.</p>
<p>Technically, the government needs approval for its spending changes from the Duma, but in practice they are likely to go ahead regardless, analysts said.</p>
<p>The Duma's resolution to seek more information about government plans effectively pushes discussion of the spending cuts back until at least June, as the Duma is in recess next week and will next meet on June 4.</p>
<p>Under the current budget law the government must submit a sequestration if revenues fall below 90 percent of budgeted levels in a quarter.</p>
<p>Revenues were just 65 percent of the target in the first four months of this year, while the government has already cut spending at its own discretion to 70 percent of budgeted levels.</p>
<p>The government wants to slash spending by 108 trillion roubles and to raise budgeted revenues by 30 trillion roubles, primarily through privatisation and via securities markets.</p>
<p>Central Bank Chairman Sergei Dubinin said he expected the government to keep spending in line with actual revenues.</p>
<p>Asked what would happen if the Duma had not taken a decision by the end of June, when it breaks for a two month summer recess, Dubinin said:</p>
<p>&quot;I think the government will finance spending in accordance with the level of its receipts, and in line with budget deficit figures which have already been agreed.&quot;</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520  ($ 1 = 5,750 roubles)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
