<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608725" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Positive tone on Richter IPO pulls BUX up.</title>
<headline>Positive tone on Richter IPO pulls BUX up.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A successful IPO with a pricing close to the market price in pharmaceuticals company Richter Gedeon Rt revived the Budapest Stock Exchange on Friday, giving a strong push of the BUX index before the weekend.</p>
<p>The BUX index of the Hungarian stock market finished at a preliminary 5,873.59 points, up 78.35 points or 1.35 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Richter's pricing and its developments (its four and half times oversubscription) drove the market out of its falling trend,&quot; said Robert Forgo of MKB Securities.</p>
<p>Richter shares traded higher on Friday as a result of the strong demand for the 2.6 million shares offered by privatisation agency APV Rt and issued by the company for institutional investors.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors who did not get (enough) shares because of the oversubscriptions, are trying to buy the paper on the market,&quot; said Forgo.</p>
<p>The Richter share, priced at $78 and 14,160 forints, strengthened on both the Budapest bourse and in London's SEAQ. In Budapest it closed at 14,500 forints, up 260, but at one point it traded at 14,760.</p>
<p>In London Richter's Global Depositary Receipts were marked at $80.25, up from $79.50 at the opening.</p>
<p>Forgo said Richter's shares gave a boost to the rest of the market, including chemicals maker Tiszai Vegyi Kombinat (TVK) which rose 90 forints to 2,715 at close and oil company MOL which gained 95 forint to end at 3,350.</p>
<p>Market participants said pharmaceuticals  Egis Gyogyszergyar Rt benefited from Richter's rise and even outpaced it by a more than three percent gain to 11,200 forints.</p>
<p>However, they said Egis may have risen also due to the fact that the gap was too large between the prices of Richter and Egis, in favour of the former.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, meat processor  Pick Szeged Rt, rated by Hungarian brokerage New York Broker Budapest as short-term and long-term buy, gained more than three and half percent to end at 11,600 forints on client orders.</p>
<p>Despite the positive market sentiment before the weekend, traders said a sideways trend was likely to follow rather than a continuation of Friday's rally.</p>
<p>But Peter Postenyi, analyst at Raiffeisen Securities, said he expected the market to move higher in about one or two weeks' time, on further rises in heavy-weight stocks MOL and Richter, as a spillover effect of their strong first quarter earnings.</p>
<p>-- Emese Bartha, Budapest newsroom +36 1 327-4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
