<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608777" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Zloty braces for rough week marred by Czech crisis.</title>
<headline>Zloty braces for rough week marred by Czech crisis.</headline>
<byline>Jan Strupczewski</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Polish zloty, beaten down by foreign sales to its all-time lows against the parity rate, may face more rough trade next week if foreigners keep pulling out of the region because of the Czech crown crisis, dealers said.</p>
<p>The zloty closed at 0.64/0.50 percent above the trading band centre on Friday down from 2.44/2.27 percent on Wednesday as foreigners sold the zloty to cut central european exposure in general even though Polish fundamentals were very good.</p>
<p>The National Bank of Poland rescued the zloty from falling below the parity rate with an estimated $15 million dollar-selling intervention, which propped the zloty on Friday, but traders said the bank might need to step in again.</p>
<p>&quot;Next week there are likely to be clients who are going to be closing positions and if the central bank does not get involved again, the effects of the Friday intervention will not last long,&quot; said Malgorzata Sawicka of Bank Handlowy SA.</p>
<p>Dealers expect the NBP will set the defence line for the zloty at the parity rate, but some also said no intervention may be necessary as those who wanted to get out of the whole region at all costs had already done so.</p>
<p>&quot;It seems that the most nervous ones have already left, and the others, if they decide to leave despite the good Polish fundamentals, will do so very gently and gradually,&quot; said Krzysztof Kozuchowski, T-bill dealer at ING bank in Warsaw.</p>
<p>Delears estimated foreigners bought up to $350 million on the market during the pullout, but some dealers said they were already receiving first orders to buy zlotys which could be a start of a trend reversal.</p>
<p>&quot;I would not expect the zloty to fall any further next week, but rather to slowly rise -- to one and then 1.5 percent above the parity rate,&quot; said Andrzej Rzysko, chief dealer at Societe Generale in Warsaw.</p>
<p>Dealers said this week's zloty fall was likely to keep foreigners sidelined at the 1.2 billion zloty primary T-bill tender on Monday, especially that London is closed for bank holiday.</p>
<p>They said however, domestic demand was likely to be high enough to keep yields relatively stable.</p>
<p>&quot;After all the zloty sales, banks are likely to bid for slightly higher yields, say 21.45-50 percent for the 52-week paper, against 21.40 at the last tender, but corporate bidders might be satisfied with less,&quot; said ING's Kozuchowski.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81401">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
