<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608873" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: PRESS DIGEST - Yugoslavia - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Yugoslavia - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in Serbian and Macedonian press on Friday. Reuters has not verified them nor does it vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>		  --    SERBIA    --</p>
<p>POLITIKA</p>
<p>- No one from the outside can change the regime in this country, said Serbian President Slobodan Milosevic visiting central Serbia.</p>
<p>- Serbian President Milosevic received Greek Defence Minister Akis Tsohatzopoulos; said Yugoslavia and Greece make significant contribution to stability in the region.</p>
<p>- Meeting of Yugoslav, U.S. businessmen on May 27 in New York. This is first such gathering after lifting of the U.N. embargo last October.</p>
<p>- Talks between the Serbian government and parties represented in the parliament on further democratisation of political life will continue.</p>
<p>- Yugoslav and Greek Defence Ministers, Pavle Bulatovic and Akis Tsohatzopoulos, met; say many possibilities for various forms of military cooperation.</p>
<p>- The federal government decided to abolish special tax on imported trucks and cars from 1.500-3.000 ccm as of May 26, cutting total import duties to 53.75 percent from 77 percent.</p>
<p>- American Express Card to be used in Yugoslavia as of June.</p>
<p>- Belgrade Banking Group founded at an annual shareholders' meeting of Beogradska banka. It includes 20 banks.</p>
<p>NASA BORBA</p>
<p>- Striking Serbia's health workers do not give in.</p>
<p>- Negotiations between PTT Serbia and Italy's STET continue.</p>
<p>- Some one million German marks confiscated from foreigners by Yugoslav customs at the borders.</p>
<p>- Serbian authorities claim there are no mad cows in the country.</p>
<p>POLITIKA EKSPRES</p>
<p>- Serbian health ministry and Austrian Bloren-Handelgesellschaft firm signed a $100 million agreement on delivering medicine, raw-materials for the pharmaceutical industry and medical supplies and equipment to Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>		    --  MONTENEGRO  --</p>
<p>POBJEDA</p>
<p>- Parliament adopted decision on number of court judges in Montenegro. Parliament adjourned its session by May 27.</p>
<p>- Parliament adopted privatisation plan on 40 small and medium size companies in the republic.</p>
<p>- Trial to Nebojsa Ranisavljevic who participated in abduction and murder of 20 train passengers in Strpci in 1993 should start in Bijelo Polje (Montenegro) soon, said Vladimir Susovic, republic's state prosecutor.</p>
<p>MONITOR</p>
<p>- Situation in Podgorica Central clinic is worse than in Spuz prison. Podgorica and Niksic surgeons are on strike requesting replacement of republic's health minister Miodrag Mugosa.</p>
<p>- Montenegrin President Momir Bulatovic is playing on a very dangerous card -- division of Montenegro, said comentary.</p>
<p>- Current disagreements in the leadership of the ruling party has negative impact on privatisation, said Mihajlo Banjevac, director of the republic's pension fund.</p>
<p>- The Yugoslav Ministry for Foreign Affairs has 94 Montenegrins (every tenth) out of which 55 are diplomats. They are disappointed with the status of Montengrins in the diplomatic service and with Podgorica's attitute towards them.</p>
<p>- Some 200 Albanian trucks loaded with old iron, chrome and copper enter Montenegro every day. -- Belgrade Newsroom +381 11 222 4254</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
