<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608800" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Poles clash in referendum over new constitution.</title>
<headline>Poles clash in referendum over new constitution.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A deeply split Polish nation decides by referendum on Sunday whether to approve a new constitution, drafted by parliament to entrench the democracy won when communism fell in 1989.</p>
<p>This final version of the new constitution, resulting from almost eight years of debate, is a hard-won compromise between the ruling secular minded ex-communists and their allies, and two centre or left opposition parties in parliament.</p>
<p>For the Solidarity trade union and the church which battled alongside it against communist rule, the document undermines the historic ties many Poles perceive between their national identity and the majority Roman Catholic faith.</p>
<p>&quot;We are threatened in Poland by an atheistic constitution, which will cut Poland off from its Christian roots,&quot; Solidarity leader Marian Krzaklewski said in a radio interview.</p>
<p>The trade union has forged rightist parties -- now mostly unrepresented in parliament -- into an alliance which hopes to supplant the ex-communists at elections in September and it is furious that the constitution is being submitted just now.</p>
<p>&quot;To pass the constitution on the basis of a line-up that will change greatly in the next parliament is to place a time-bomb under Poland,&quot; thundered Krzaklewski, whose grouping proposed a constitution founded on religious ideas.</p>
<p>The bishops, who at first decided to keep neutral, have expressed deep reservations over the document, notably its failure to effectively ban abortion -- now legal in Poland.</p>
<p>But by no means all Catholics, nor all leading veterans of the pre-1989 struggle for democracy share such objections.</p>
<p>Tadeusz Mazowiecki, who headed the first post-1989 democratic government and is a leader of the opposition Union for Freedom, helped draft the compromise which stresses that Poles include Catholics and people of other faiths or none.</p>
<p>He says Poland, now making do with remnants of the discredited 1952 constitution and interim arrangments from 1992, must set out rights and freedoms and there is little hope the next parliament will be able to agree a new draft.</p>
<p>&quot;This constitution stabilises the transformation made after 1989,&quot; Mazowiecki told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said the current document's authors had tried to meet the bishops' every point -- for instance on abortion the wording leaves open the option of a tightening of the law.</p>
<p>Mazowiecki accuses the union-led Solidarity Election Alliance of falsely depicting the constitution debate as a clash of world views, to rally backers for the elections.</p>
<p>&quot;This is artificial and the whole argument basically has a political election lining, which we tried to avoid,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The constitution confirms civil rights, broadly retains the current political system but weakens the presidency, sets caps on government spending but controversially also obliges it to support employment and home-building.</p>
<p>Solidarity has clearly decided to stress religious issues in the election campaign and is counting on a boost from the May 31-June 10 visit by Polish Pope John Paul ll -- to the extent of issuing posters of him with its own party logo.</p>
<p>Whether this approach will bear fruit in votes is unclear.</p>
<p>Lena Kolarska-Bobinska, head of the Institute of Public Affairs think-tank, said that by polarising extremes when many resent church influence, it may benefit the political centre.</p>
<p>Solidarity portrays the referendum not as a clear test of strength, but of its backers' readiness -- a sensible policy after opinion polls suggesting the constitution will pass.</p>
<p>Surveys also suggest that Poles, baffled by the 243-page document and by politicians' conflicting accounts of what it all means, may stay away from the referendum in droves.</p>
<p>A simple majority will ensure it passes no matter how few take part, but low turnout will rob the charter of credibility.</p>
<p>&quot;The constitution won't really be legitimised, the right will always be against it, criticising and proposing changes. This would be a very mixed victory,&quot; Kolarska-Bobinska said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
