<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608807" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: National Bank of Macedonia governor resigns.</title>
<headline>National Bank of Macedonia governor resigns.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Governor of the National Bank of Macedonia Borko Stanoevski resigned four years before his term in office ended after several get-rich-quick schemes collapsed, an NBM official said on Friday.  </p>
<p>&quot;The governor's resignation was accepted by the prime minister,&quot; a senior NBM official who declined to be named, told Reuters by telephone from Skopje.</p>
<p>&quot;Stanoevski will be replaced by Deputy Prime Minister Ljube Trpeski, who takes office on Monday,&quot; said the official.</p>
<p>Investigations presented by Stanoevski to Prime Minister Branko Crvenkovski a week ago found that several government and parliament officials were involved in the collapse of several major pyramid investment schemes, a commercial bank official said.</p>
<p>Some 25,000 depositors in Macedonia's biggest savings house TAT held daily protests in March after being swindled some 112 million marks. Invstigations in several other savings houses also estabilished misappropriations amounting to some 20 million marks.</p>
<p>NBM Deputy governor Tome Nenovski, who also resigned, and TAT owner Sonja Nikolovska were arrested in March for investigation of the TAT affair and released later.</p>
<p>Thousands of Macedonians protested in the capital Skopje last week demanding the government's resignation over corruption and failed pyramid schemes which deprived thousands of their life-savings.</p>
<p>Macedonia shares a border with Albania, where the collapse of pyramid savings schemes has led to armed insurrection in much of the country in the past months.</p>
<p>Macedonia's fragile economy has been badly hit by the break-up of the former Yugoslav federation in 1991 and by sanctions against its northern neighbour Serbia. The economy has been slow to pick up as living standards continued to drop.</p>
<p>But authorities in Macedonia have said other savings houses were safe and they did not fear a crisis similar to the one in Albania. -- Elisaveta Konstantinova, Sofia Newsroom, 359-2-981-4145</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MCDNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
