<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608884" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech govt talks progress, no reshuffle yet - Lux.</title>
<headline>Czech govt talks progress, no reshuffle yet - Lux.</headline>
<byline>Jan Lopatka</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leaders of the three parties in the Czech ruling coalition made progress in talks to change the cabinet on Friday morning, but failed to complete an agreement, Deputy Prime Minister Josef Lux said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we made progress,&quot; Lux told journalists.</p>
<p>He said top officials from the coalition parties were scheduled to hold separate meetings over the weekend, after which an agreement may be concluded.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it (an agreement) will be today because the leaderships of the parties are meeting today and tomorrow. I think there could be a final resolution after these meetings,&quot; Lux, leader of the Christian Democrats (KDU-CSL), said.</p>
<p>The executive committee of Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus's Civic Democratic Party (ODS) begins to meet on Friday afternoon.</p>
<p>Klaus agreed with his coalition partners on Wednesday that a change was needed amid slumping approval ratings and an economic downturn which has sapped confidence in the government.</p>
<p>The cabinet shuffle has become even more sensitive as pressure mounts on the Czech crown, which has been battered by foreign speculators reacting to poor macroeconomic results and political instability.</p>
<p>The crown was holding steady in early morning trading at about 4.4 percent on the depreciation side of its dollar/mark basket midpoint, after hitting a record low of -6.4 percent on Thursday.</p>
<p>Speculation on which ministers might lose their cabinet seats has focused primarily on Finance Minister Ivan Kocarnik (ODS) and Industry and Trade Minister Vladimir Dlouhy, of the third coalition member, the Civic Democratic Alliance (ODA). But no final proposals have been revealed by the parties.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, Dlouhy said he was prepared to step down by the end of the year, but that he had made no firm decision and would consult party members on Saturday at an ODA executive meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;I am going to ask ODA on Saturday whether they think I should resign,&quot; Dlouhy told journalists on Thursday.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Josef Zieleniec (ODS) told commercial TV Nova on Thursday that a reported plan for him to replace Kocarnik as finance minister, with the former ambassador to Washington Michael Zantovsky (ODA) taking over as foreign minister was &quot;not on the table, so I won't discuss it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
