<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608827" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish KGHM says listing in first week of July.</title>
<headline>Polish KGHM says listing in first week of July.</headline>
<dateline>DUSZNIKI-ZDROJ, Poland 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Polish copper giant KGHM Polska Miedz SA expects its first listing on bourses in Warsaw and London in the first week of July, the firm's deputy president Stanislaw Krajewski said on Friday.  </p>
<p>&quot;Our first listing in Warsaw as well as in London should take place in the first week of July,&quot; Krajewski told a seminar for technical college graduates.</p>
<p>He said about 30 million KGHM shares would be sold in Warsaw in two tranches, for small and large investors and that many of them were likely to be bought by foreign investors.</p>
<p>&quot;About 30 million shares should be floated in Warsaw...with a large part of them likely bought up by foreign investors,&quot; he said. The government has said up to 15 percent of the firm's shares would be listed in Warsaw and up to 26 percent in London.  </p>
<p>The KGHM shares will be listed in London in the form of Global Depositary Receipts.</p>
<p>A 15 percent stake in KGHM, worth an estimated two to three billion dollars, would be divided among the firm's 50,000 present and former employees, who are obliged to keep the shares for at least two years.</p>
<p>The state treasury would keep the remaining 49 percent. The government plans to eventually sell part of this stake to fund the reform of the social security system.  </p>
<p>Krajewski said that the company would create a special pension fund in which workers would be encouraged to invest their shares.</p>
<p>&quot;We are in an advanced stage of forming a pension fund for employees, which would keep shares given to the workers from flowing out onto the market once the two-year period ends,&quot; he said. -- Wojciech Moskwa +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22460">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUSZNIKI-ZDROJ, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
