<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608893" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech crown calmer but threat remains - dealers.</title>
<headline>Czech crown calmer but threat remains - dealers.</headline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Czech crown was calmer on Friday morning but dealers warned that the threat of speculative selling remained and that domestic buying of hard currency may further destabilise the crown later in the day.</p>
<p>&quot;Especially some corporates and local funds are really converting large amounts (of crowns to hard currency),&quot; said Petr Korous of Ceskoslovenska Obchodni Banka.</p>
<p>&quot;Its much calmer than yesterday but still the battle is there,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>At 0750 GMT, the crown was trading at around 30.9 to the dollar and 18.4 to the mark implying a deviation from the mid-point of its mark dollar basket of minus 4.14 percent from Thursday's fixing of minus 3.0 percent.  </p>
<p>Some dealers said the mood in the country was becoming ever more pessimistic about the central bank's (CNB) ability to support the crown.</p>
<p>&quot;I think now that the whole feeling in the country is starting to turnarund and everyone is actually already expecting the devaluation of the Czech crown,&quot; said Petr Kukla of Girocredit Bank.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel that another wave of speculation and buying hard currency (will come) to day and think that we will again go to (minus 5.0 percent), it might be (minus 6.0 percent) and we even have the end of the band,&quot; he added.  </p>
<p>On Friday morning, the central bank again moved to choke off liquidity with three repo tenders. In the first, a one-week repo, the maximum limit was set at 75 percent. No limits were revealed for the other two repos.</p>
<p>-- Robin Shepherd, Prague Newsroom, 420-2-2423-0003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
