<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608877" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish parties' ranking before parliamentary polls.</title>
<headline>Polish parties' ranking before parliamentary polls.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A poll by the private PBS institute for Rzeczpospolita newspaper showed on Friday the opposition Solidarity Electoral Action (AWS) slightly ahead of the co-ruling ex-communist Democratic Left Alliance.</p>
<p>Parliamentary elections are likely on September 14 or 21.</p>
<p>Following is a ranking of Polish political parties according to the five most recent public opinion polls.</p>
<p>	 PBS	DEMOSKOP     OBOP	 PBS	DEMOSKOP</p>
<p>(May 17-18) (May 9-12) (May 8-11) (Apr 26-27) (Apr 9-14) AWS	26	    17	   24	    27	   20</p>
<p>SLD	24	    24	   24	    25	   25</p>
<p>UW	 13	    13	    9	    11	   13</p>
<p>UP	 10	     8	    5	    10	    7</p>
<p>PSL	 9	    13	   10	     9	   12</p>
<p>ROP	 7	     8	   12	     8	   10</p>
<p>KPEiR     9	     6	   10	     7	   na</p>
<p>NOTE - Party names:</p>
<p>AWS - The Solidarity Electoral Action, an opposition electoral bloc of more than 30 small right-wing parties led by the Solidarity trade union.</p>
<p>SLD - the Democratic Left Alliance, the ex-communist group and the larger partner in the ruling leftist coalition.</p>
<p>PSL - The Polish Peasant Party, the smaller partner in the government coalition.</p>
<p>UW - The Union for Freedom, a right-centrist group, the biggest opposition party in parliament.</p>
<p>ROP - The Movement for Reconstruction of Poland, a non-parliamentary group, advocating patriotic, anti-communist and often populist values.</p>
<p>UP - The Union of Labour, a leftist opposition party.</p>
<p>KPEiR - The National Pensioners' Party, a party lobbying pensioners' interests.</p>
<p>Polling agencies:</p>
<p>CBOS - public, Poland's biggest polling institution.</p>
<p>OBOP - controlled by the state-owned television.</p>
<p>DEMOSKOP - private.</p>
<p>PBS - private, preparing polls for authoritative Rzeczpospolita daily.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
