<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608857" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Croatian money rates steady, liquidity improved.</title>
<headline>Croatian money rates steady, liquidity improved.</headline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Croatian interbank rates held steady on Friday on improved liquidity due to central bank interventions earlier this week, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The central bank's (bill) repo operation is keeping the liquidity good,&quot; a dealer said, referring to an injection of 117 million kuna five-day funds.</p>
<p>The central bank on Thursday paid another 40 million kuna for Tuesday's purchase of hard currency from the banking sector.</p>
<p>&quot;The pension fund has also begun repaying money to banks (it borrowed to pay this month's pensions),&quot; the dealer added.</p>
<p>Friday's demand totalling 24.5 million kuna was met in full, leaving some 10 million on the supply side. More old loans were expected to be rolled over by the end of the day.</p>
<p>Most fresh loans were call money at a steady 10.5 percent.</p>
<p>Term rates were 13.5 percent for two-week funds and 15 percent for one-month. One foreign bank lent a 17-day loan at 11 and a Croatian bank at 12 percent.</p>
<p>Overnight trade totalled 42.8 million kuna after six banks sought funds to maintain their mandatory reserves. -- Laura Lui, Zagreb newsroom, 385-1-4557075</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
