<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608875" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia spending to continue at current rate-C.Bank.</title>
<headline>Russia spending to continue at current rate-C.Bank.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Russian government will continue spending in line with its actual revenues, even if parliament is unable to take a decision on budget cuts before it starts its summer recess next month, Central Bank Chairman Sergei Dubinin said on Friday.</p>
<p>Asked what would happen if the State Duma lower house had not taken a decision by the time the recess starts late next month, Dubinin told reporters:</p>
<p>&quot;I think the government will finance spending in accordance with the level of its receipts, and in line with budget deficit figures which have already been agreed.</p>
<p>&quot;To my mind there is not a big contradiction between deputies' demands for as many proposals (to increase revenues) as possible and the intentions of the government to increase revenues.&quot;</p>
<p>The Duma is currently considering a bill seeking further details of government plans to raise budgeted revenues this year by 30 trillion roubles.</p>
<p>Dubinin said he did not expect the Duma to pass a non-binding bill to double money supply, which it is scheduled to consider later on Friday.</p>
<p>The government has already cut planned spending sharply this year in line with a shortfall in budget revenues, even though it is supposed to seek Duma approval for any spending cuts.</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
