<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608887" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: PRESS DIGEST - Bosnia - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Bosnia - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Sarajevo press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DNEVNI AVAZ</p>
<p>- Special envoy for Croatian President Franjo Tudjman, Franjo Greguric, arrives in Sarajevo for talks with the High Representative, Carl Bildt, and members of Bosnia's collective presidency.</p>
<p>- Bosnia's Council of Ministers fails to adopt law on economic reforms and plans to meet again next week.</p>
<p>- Bildt warns that failure to adopt law on economic reforms threatens to reduce level of international economic assistance available for Bosnia over the next few years. He says the international donors' conference for reconstruction may be held by end of June.</p>
<p>- The main obstacle for reaching agreement in Moslem-Croat federation on joint police force is a demand by Croat side to dismantle two intelligence services, the Bosnian Agency for Investigation and Documentation (AID) and Croatian secret service for Protection of Public Order (SZUP), anonymous sources say.</p>
<p>- Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe closes five registration centres in Banja Luka area following incidents of fraud and threats against international supervisors, OSCE official says.</p>
<p>OSLOBODJENJE</p>
<p>- Moslem-Croat federation government and trade union association agree to improve workers' status and urgently adopt laws on labour and welfare policy.</p>
<p>- A hydro-electric power plant near Tuzla will be built in the coming year, a power plant official says. -- Sarajevo, newsroom, +387-71663-864</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
