<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608896" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: Kazakh pipeline company needs $500 mln investment.</title>
<headline>Kazakh pipeline company needs $500 mln investment.</headline>
<byline>Dmitry Solovyov</byline>
<dateline>ALMATY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kazakhstan's recently formed state pipeline company Kazakhnefteprovod is seeking investment of at least $500 million over the next three years, a senior company official said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;According to our rough estimates, the company will have to attract at least $500 million in the next three years to modernise the existing pipelines and build the new ones,&quot; deputy company chairman Kairgeldy Kabyldin told Reuters.</p>
<p>Kazakhnefteprovod was set up last month as a 100 percent state-run company to &quot;observe Kazakhstan's economic interests in transporting and exporting crude oil and oil products&quot;.</p>
<p>The company will manage 6,300 km (3,900 miles) of oil pipelines, 977 km (600 miles) of oil products pipelines and 3,400 km (2,100 miles) of water pipelines.</p>
<p>Kazakhnefteprovod inherited the assets of state-run Yuznefteprovod oil pipeline company.</p>
<p>Its pipelines runs across the Central Asian state's giant Mangistau, Uzen and Tengiz oil fields, and Shymkent-Pavlodar- Omsk network stretching from south to north and the new firm will also manage two oil products pipelines in the north.</p>
<p>Kabyldin said the annual capacity of the two oil products pipelines was around five million tonnes, while the capacity of crude oil pipelines was around 40 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Oil-rich Kazakhstan plans to produce 26.5 million tonnes of crude this year and hopes to become the world's sixth largest producer by 2010 with annual output of 170 million tonnes.</p>
<p>It has so far attracted around $2 billion of direct foreign investment to the decaying but potentially multi-billion dollar oil industry. Investment commitments total another $40 billion.</p>
<p>The government plans to complete selling majority stakes in national oil companies to strategic investors by July 1.</p>
<p>&quot;The capacity of the present-day pipeline system is larger than actual oil production but we must be ready for new promising oil fields to be discovered in other regions of the country and we will need the right infrastructure, and for this we need investment,&quot; Kabyldin said.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody in the world builds pipelines for his own money -- this is very expensive and costs $1 million per km. There will definitely be investment projects,&quot; he said but declined to say how the company management planned to attract investors.</p>
<p>Kabyldin said that before Kazakhnefteprovod would come out with a concrete scheme of privatisation its management had to assess the company's assets and establish the size of the authorised capital.</p>
<p>--Almaty Newsroom, +7 3272 509410</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALMATY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
