<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608822" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Focus-Duma steps from brink in Russia budget row.</title>
<headline>Focus-Duma steps from brink in Russia budget row.</headline>
<byline>Peter Henderson</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's parliament, stepping back from the brink of confrontation with the government, decided to delay a debate on planned government spending cuts on Friday and asked ministers for more information on its revenue forecasts.</p>
<p>Deputies in the State Duma lower house voted by 321 to 11 to delay discussion on the cuts until the government explained how it would raise 30 trillion roubles ($5.2 billion) in extra revenues.</p>
<p>They also shelved a controversial bill demanding that the government double money supply and use the extra cash to pay overdue wages and pensions.</p>
<p>Ministers, who had made clear that they would disregard any Duma vote against their plans to cut spending, have argued that the money supply bill would drive Russia back to hyperinflation at a time when price rises are at last under control.</p>
<p>Consumer prices rose 1.0 percent in April.</p>
<p>&quot;The government must submit its measures on the revenue side of the budget,&quot; said Yuri Voronin, Deputy Chairman of the Duma's Budget Committee. &quot;Only after that can we reasonably look at the question (of spending cuts),&quot; Voronin, a communist, added.</p>
<p>The Duma, elected in December 1995, is dominated by communists and their conservative allies. Some communist deputies backed the idea of doubling money supply, although others said it would never work.</p>
<p>The Duma's latest attempt to seek more information about the government's revenue plans effectively puts discussion of the spending cuts back until at least June, as the Duma is in recess next week and will next meet on June 4.</p>
<p>The Duma asked the government to submit details of new revenues by June 1.</p>
<p>Under the current budget law the government must submit proposals on sequestration -- cutting spending -- to the Duma if revenues fall below 90 percent of budgeted levels in a quarter.</p>
<p>Revenues were just 65 percent of the target in the first four months of this year, while spending was also cut back to 70 percent of budgeted levels.</p>
<p>The government wants to slash spending by 108 trillion roubles ($18.8 billion) and to raise budgeted revenues by 30 trillion roubles ($5.2 billion), primarily through privatisation and on securities markets.</p>
<p>But ministers, taking advantage of a budget law loophole which says they must submit sequestration plans to the Duma but does not say the Duma must approve them, have already started cutting spending to cope with the low tax revenues.</p>
<p>Central Bank Chairman Sergei Dubinin said on Friday he expected the government to keep spending in line with actual revenues regardless of what the Duma did about the cuts.</p>
<p>Asked what would happen if the Duma had not taken a decision by summer recess, which starts late next month, Dubinin said:</p>
<p>&quot;I think the government will finance spending in accordance with the level of its receipts, and in line with budget deficit figures which have already been agreed.</p>
<p>&quot;To my mind there is not a big contradiction between deputies' demands for as many proposals as possible and the government's intentions to increase revenues.&quot;</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520 ($ 1 = 5,750 roubles) ($ = 5753 Russian Roubles)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
