<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608878" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: PRESS DIGEST - Albania - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Albania - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Albanian press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>KOHA JONE</p>
<p>- Armed police forces have started travelling towards the south of Albania aiming to re-establish local government institutions there.</p>
<p>- The Socialist Party has decided to enter elections if there is full international monitoring.</p>
<p>- A rebel committe in the southern town of Vlore has called on people to receive President Sali Berisha with guns and bombs if he decides to visit the town.</p>
<p>- Smaller parties in the nine-party interim government are upset the Socialist Party did not ask their opinion before declaring it would enter elections.</p>
<p>- Albania's branch of the Helsinki human rights committee said Berisha should not take part in the electoral campaign.</p>
<p>GAZETA SHQIPTARE</p>
<p>- The Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe has promised to monitor Albania's general elections in June.</p>
<p>- President Sali Berisha has expressed his dissatisfaction to Prime Minister Bashkim Fino over the government's demand to the international community to intensively monitor parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>- Italian Foreign Minister Lamberto Dini said quotes attributed to his ambassador in Tirana did not correspond to Italy's position on Albania.</p>
<p>- The Democratic Party said Finance Minister Arben Malaj, a Socialist, carried out political revenge when he sacked the boards of state-owned banks and the insurance institute.</p>
<p>ALBANIA</p>
<p>- The Socialists have started their revenge on the Democratic Party administration. About 170,000 people could be sacked.</p>
<p>- If the Socialist Party cooperates with armed rebels in the south of the country it is a clear sign it will boycott elections on June 29.</p>
<p>- The Democratic Party said it never wrote documents published in the Koha Jone daily.</p>
<p>DITA NFORMACION</p>
<p>- Guri Durollari, the chairman of the Legality (Monarchy) Party risks being sacked because his alliance with the Democratic Party has caused many party branches to cut ties with the monarchists.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
