<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608828" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian minister fails to sway Duma on NATO deal.</title>
<headline>Russian minister fails to sway Duma on NATO deal.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Heritage</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov tried on Friday to defuse opposition in parliament to Russia's new security deal with NATO but failed to break down resistance.</p>
<p>Primakov made a rare visit to the State Duma lower house to outline the Founding Act to be signed by President Boris Yeltsin and leaders of the 16 NATO countries in Paris on Tuesday. He answered questions but did not hand out texts of the agreement.</p>
<p>&quot;I am satisfied by the discussion of this question. This is an important step in the process of preparing for the signing of the Founding Act,&quot; Primakov said as he swiftly left the Duma after addressing a closed session.</p>
<p>But opponents of the deal said they would press on with plans to draw up a declaration criticising the agreement, which maps out NATO-Russia relations and is intended to ease Moscow's fears over the Western defence alliance's eastward expansion.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear from officials' remarks and what has been published in the media that it contradicts the leadership's basic line that Russia will never accept the North Atlantic alliance's expansion,&quot; Duma deputy speaker Sergei Baburin said.</p>
<p>Baburin, a nationalist, said the declaration would urge Yeltsin to regard the Founding Act as only the first step in heading off the threat to Russia if the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation expands into eastern and central Europe.</p>
<p>Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic, three post-communist nations that formerly belonged to the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact, are expected to be offered NATO membership at an alliance summit in Madrid in July. Romania and Slovenia also hope to be in the first wave of new entrants.</p>
<p>The Russia-NATO accord creates a joint council between the two sides to give Moscow a say in matters directly affecting its security.</p>
<p>Moscow says it also offers binding guarantees that NATO will not build up its forces on the territory of new members and that the alliance will not base nuclear weapons there.</p>
<p>But communists and nationalists say Primakov and Yeltsin have sold out national interests by reaching an agreement which fails to prevent NATO enlargement.</p>
<p>Yeltsin does not need parliamentary approval for the agreement but he wants it to go down as a diplomatic triumph which averted a freeze in relations with the West.</p>
<p>In a campaign to justify and explain the agreement, Yeltsin met party and parliamentary leaders on Monday and appeared to ease some of their fears. Yeltsin also promised to present the pact to the Duma for approval after it is signed.</p>
<p>But concern remains among liberals as well as communists and nationalists in the Duma.</p>
<p>&quot;The main problem is the different view of this agreement on Yeltsin's part and on Washington's part, and I think it is a very bad sign,&quot; liberal leader Grigory Yavlinksy told reporters.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton has said the deal gives Russia a voice, but not a veto, in NATO affairs.</p>
<p>Ultra-nationalist Vladimir Zhirinovsky reacted more angrily.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a very weak document,&quot; he told reporters. &quot;We oppose the president's foreign policy in general.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
