<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608882" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: PRESS DIGEST - Latvia - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Latvia - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the main stories in Latvian newspapers on Friday. Prepared for Reuters by the Co-operation Fund. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy:</p>
<p>ALL NEWSPAPERS</p>
<p>- Leading party Saimnieks submitted materials to PM Andris Shkele which allege that economy minister Guntars Krasts of the Fatherland &amp; Freedom Union was involved in a conflict of interest. The documents may concern Krasts' business activities in the alcohol trading company Hercogs of which he was deputy manager until April 1, 1997.</p>
<p>Krasts said that Saimnieks' aim is not to fight corruption but to provoke a fresh political crisis.</p>
<p>- Italian president Oscar Luigi Scalfaro has concluded his first official visit to Latvia by voicing support for the country's EU bid.</p>
<p>- Parliament passed amendments to the law on state pensions, guaranteeing a minimum social benefit of 20 lats to people who have worked for at least 10 years in Latvia.</p>
<p>BIZNES &amp; BALTIYA</p>
<p>- The visit of president Ulmanis to Russia due at the end of May or early is once again postponed and is likely to take place in autumn.</p>
<p>- Parliament passed the law on regions needing special support, aimed at improving the economic situation in Latvia's most depressed regions.</p>
<p>- Talks on the delimitation of the sea border between Latvia and Lithuania will resume today in Riga.</p>
<p>- The Swedish fund, which is one of major shareholders in both the Universal bank and Zemes banka, is opposing the merger of the two banks. It's view is being shared by the second largest shareholder, the EBRD.</p>
<p>DIENAS BIZNESS</p>
<p>- Compared to 1995, in 1996 the after-tax profit of Ventspils nafta increased by 5.5 million lats to 25 million lats.</p>
<p>-- Riga Newsroom, +371 721 5240</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
