<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608897" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin urges young Russians to join army.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin urges young Russians to join army.</headline>
<byline>Oleg Shchedrov</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin, who has sacked his defence minister and chief-of-staff for dragging their feet over military reform, turned to Russia's youth on Friday for support in his efforts to modernise the army.</p>
<p>&quot;The army has lost its traditions and they should be revived,&quot; Interfax news agency quoted Yeltsin as telling graduates of a Moscow secondary school. &quot;We must revive the prestige of the armed forces and their appearence.&quot;</p>
<p>Yeltsin sacked Defence Minister Igor Rodionov and Chief-of- Staff Viktor Samsonov on Thurdsay, blaming them for sabotage of his plans to turn the huge and largely ineffective Soviet-era military machine into a compact and professional force.</p>
<p>Russia, which faces a range of economic problems and a severe budget crisis, can no longer pay the huge bills of the armed forces.</p>
<p>The military complain that such austerity has damaged the effectiveness of what was once one of the world's strongest armies.</p>
<p>The poor state of the armed forces has also made military service -- theoretically compulsory for all young men -- a very unattractive prospect for the nation's youth.</p>
<p>Massive conscription dodging has not only become a headache for the military but has also badly affected national morale.</p>
<p>&quot;You should not get scared of the men in uniform, you should rather envy them,&quot; Yeltsin told the graduates, urging them not to join dodgers.</p>
<p>Announcing the sackings on Thursday, Yeltsin appeared to be outraged by the scale of high-level army corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;The soldier is losing weight while the general is getting fatter,&quot; Yeltsin told his top generals at a meeting of the Defence Council advisory board.</p>
<p>Military prosecutors on Wednesday arrested Konstantin Kobets, one of the country's top generals and a deputy defence minister, previously acclaimed a hero for his defence of Yeltsin in a failed hardline communist coup in 1991.</p>
<p>Kobets is accused of corruption but denies the charges.</p>
<p>Land Forces Commander General Vladimir Semyonov was sacked after corruption charges last month, which he too denies.</p>
<p>Military prosecutors say about 20 generals and 100 colonels are under investigation for graft. Stories abound of army stores, from rations to rockets, being sold off for private profit and of defence contractors building lavish country homes for the top brass in exchange for lucrative army orders.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
