<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608816" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: End to transit ban boosts Moscow air cargo.</title>
<headline>End to transit ban boosts Moscow air cargo.</headline>
<byline>Viktor Anoshkin</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A cancellation of a recent customs ban on transit cargo through Moscow's airports made the market more active over the last four weeks, but air cargo rates were stable, forwarders said.</p>
<p>Boris Panchenko, senior cargo manager at forwarding firm Eruslan, Aeroflot's cargo agent, said the situation at Sheremetyevo became more stable after the customs ban was cancelled in the end of last month.</p>
<p>&quot;It was an absurd ban...and it caused many problems for Russian carriers and forwarders, with only Western airlines getting a good chance to make big profits as they operate direct flights from Western Europe to provincial Russian cities,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Under the ban, imposed on March 20, shippers could not automatically forward cargo into the Russian provinces through Moscow, as every client had to come to Moscow to clear customs.</p>
<p>&quot;Currently, transit operations via Sheremetyevo are recovering, making the market more active,&quot; Panchenko said.</p>
<p>But Sergei Mochalov, a senior cargo manager at TCT Cargo, an Aeroflot's cargo agent, said that Sheremetyevo customs were not hurrying to end the ban.</p>
<p>&quot;Only four firms have got permission to operate transit cargo at Sheremetyevo. Other forwarders are still unable to do so,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Mochalov said that his company saw the market as stable in the last four weeks. &quot;We try to offer stable rates for clients, even ignoring seasonal fluctuations,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Nikolai Belyayev, senior cargo manager of EMS Garant Post, Air France's  AIRF.CN cargo agent, said that all forwarders had suffered: &quot;millions of dollars of losses after the customs ban was imposed.&quot;</p>
<p>Igor Mordvinov, senior sales manager of Burlington Air Express Moscow had another opinion about the market.</p>
<p>&quot;We had less shipments in May compared to April due to a row of holidays earlier this month,&quot; he said, adding rates had not changed.</p>
<p>&quot;The end of the transit ban must make the market more active...but currently it is in stagnant until June when clients may order new shipments for new contracts for the second half of the year,&quot; Mordvinov said.</p>
<p>Alexey Yun, Tesis Group, the cargo manager for several forwarders, said there had been no rate changes in the last four weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;We had the same cargo turnover in May as in April, but a small declines in volumes is expected next month as South East Asia's air cargo market is usually weak in June,&quot; Yun said, adding that these destinations were very stable in May.</p>
<p>An official at Transaero cargo service said that much cargo was carried from Moscow to Siberia and Russia's Far East destinations in May. &quot;Demand is increasinig,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Belyayev of EMS Garant Post said U.S. destinations were also active in the last four weeks and there were more shipments from Moscow to both West Europe and South East Asia.</p>
<p>Panchenko at Eruslan said U.S. Delta Airlines had very stable shipments on the Moscow-New York route carrying 20 tonnes of cargo per month.</p>
<p>&quot;FinnAir also had many shipments on the Moscow-Helsinki route,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Mochalov at TCT Cargo said his company had stable cargo shipments on routes from Moscow to Miami and Istanbul. --Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
