<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608804" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: Kazakh T-bill yield uncertain, dealers mixed.</title>
<headline>Kazakh T-bill yield uncertain, dealers mixed.</headline>
<byline>Dmitry Solovyov</byline>
<dateline>ALMATY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kazakh Treasury bill dealers, puzzled by the recent sharp fall in yields, are divided as to whether yields have reached a bottom or are set to fall further.</p>
<p>Kazakhstan's finance ministry is offering 750 million tenge of six-month MKM discount T-bills on Monday and 700 million of three-month paper on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The yield on three-month T-bills fell to 14.59 percent annual on Tuesday from 17.23 percent at the previous auction on May 13. Six-month paper yielded 19.90 percent, compared to 22.97 percent on April 28.</p>
<p>Some dealers said they felt that yields -- especially those on three-month paper -- had already hit their lowest point.</p>
<p>&quot;Such yields do not satisfy (local) banks, and all dealers were terrified by the yield at the last auction,&quot; said Sergei Vasilyev, chief dealer at Kazkommertsbank.</p>
<p>&quot;Banks are likely to bid aggressively at next week's auctions, because such low yields are not in their interests,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Vasilyev said that some investors, mostly foreign ones, were happy even about low yields.</p>
<p>&quot;There are investors who would be satisfied even with 10 percent annual,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Other dealers said they expected the downward trend to continue.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a trend of a small but steady fall of yields on both maturities,&quot; said Lyudmila Pogulyayeva of ABN AMRO Bank Kazakhstan.</p>
<p>&quot;Taking into account the relatively stable tenge rate and the low risks of investing in Kazakh government securities, these securities remain attractive for foreigners,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Pogulyayeva said that T-bill yields could remain steady only if the National Bank announced a large issue of its short-term notes on Monday.</p>
<p>Notes are issued to sterilise the money supply and support the tenge rate, and Pogulyayeva did not rule out the possibility that banks could channel their resources to notes, thus slashing the usual high demand for T-bills.</p>
<p>A finance ministry official told Reuters that &quot;current yields reasonably reflect investors' outlook of lower inflation&quot;.</p>
<p>National Bank Governor Uraz Dzhandosov told a news conference on Thursday that annual inflation could fall this year below the official target of 17 percent.</p>
<p>($1 = 75.6600 tenge)</p>
<p>--Almaty Newsroom, +7 3272 509410</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALMATY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
