<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608837" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin meets Japan's Ikeda, hails improved ties.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin meets Japan's Ikeda, hails improved ties.</headline>
<byline>Gareth Jones</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin told Japan's foreign minister on Friday that long-frosty bilateral ties were improving and he thanked Tokyo for supporting Russian membership of the group of leading industrialised nations.</p>
<p>Welcoming Yukihiko Ikeda to the Kremlin, Yeltsin said he looked forward to talks with Japanese Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto in July in the U.S. city of Denver at a summit of the Group of Seven nations, now expanded to include Russia.</p>
<p>&quot;Relations between Russia and Japan have notably improved since we agreed that deeds should come before discussion of the islands issue,&quot; Interfax quoted Yeltsin as telling Ikeda.</p>
<p>Yeltsin was referring to a bitter territorial issue that has overshadowed bilateral ties for decades and blocked the signing of a formal peace treaty ending World War Two hostilities.</p>
<p>Tokyo wants Moscow to return four remote islands in the north Pacific seized by the Red Army in 1945.</p>
<p>Despite the lack of a breakthrough on the territorial question, the two sides have agreed to expand their economic cooperation and to step up dialogue on a range of issues.</p>
<p>Japanese diplomats said Ikeda's visit to Moscow was a further sign of the improvement in bilateral relations.</p>
<p>&quot;A peace treaty and full normalisation of our relations is the ultimate goal we are seeking,&quot; a senior Japanese official told reporters in Moscow on Thursday.</p>
<p>He said Tokyo welcomed Moscow's cuts in the number of troops stationed on the islands, known in Japan as the Northern Territories and in Russia as the Southern Kuriles. Japanese officials believe about 3,500 Russian troops are based there now.</p>
<p>&quot;We are trying to improve the environment (of our dialogue) to facilitate a resolution of the territorial dispute,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>After meeting Yeltsin on Friday Ikeda held talks with Russian Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov.</p>
<p>He was also due to meet First Deputy Prime Minister Boris Nemtsov, who chairs a bilateral intergovernmental commission on trade and economic relations.</p>
<p>The Japanese official said Nemtsov, a pro-market liberal regarded as a possible future president, would visit Japan next month. &quot;We want to put a strong emphasis on such high-level contacts,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The official said Japanese support for Russia joining the G7 nations showed Tokyo now regarded Moscow as an equal partner and not as an adversary, as during Soviet times.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to promote Russia's integration into the world economy,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>In addition to bilateral relations and G8 issues, Ikeda and Primakov are also expected to discuss reform of the United Nations' Security Council.</p>
<p>An economic superpower but still lacking real political clout in global affairs, Japan wants to win a permanent seat in the council, which currently comprises only World Two victors the United States, Russia, Britain, France and China.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
