<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608885" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: PRESS DIGEST - Slovenia - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Slovenia - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>LJUBLJANA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are the main stories in Slovenia's Friday morning newspapers:</p>
<p>DELO</p>
<p>- Slovenia's Constitutional Court said a decision on whether ratifying the EU association agreement was in line with Slovenia's constitution will be brought in the first week of June.</p>
<p>- Although the general manager of Slovenian Railways on Thursday pushed for strike leaders to be suspended, the industrial acton enters its fourth day on Friday. The railway union said passenger traffic will be halted for the first time on Saturday.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Janez Drnovsek starts his visit to the United States on Friday where he will meet Secretary of State Madeleine Albright to seek support for Slovenian membership of NATO in the first round of eastward expansion.</p>
<p>- Slovenian President Milan Kucan will stand in this year's presidential election, Kucan told Slovenian radio on Thursday.</p>
<p>- Representatives of 12 companies and two banks from Singapore visited Slovenia on Thursday to consider the possibilities of investing in Slovenia.</p>
<p>DNEVNIK</p>
<p>- Only 35 percent of Slovenians support the demands of railway workers for a 14 percent wage increase and 52 percent said the demands were unreasonable, a survey showed.</p>
<p>VECER</p>
<p>- The president of the Council of Europe's parliament, Leni Fisher, in a speech to Slovenia's parliament congratulated the country for its consistent respect of human rights.</p>
<p>FINANCE</p>
<p>- Slovenia's largest bank, state-owned Nova Ljubljanska banka said it had made an offer in April to six U.S. and British banks to open share trading custodian accounts, but none had yet replied.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LJUBLJANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
