<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608806" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungary trains sights on NATO with &quot;NATO Express&quot;.</title>
<headline>Hungary trains sights on NATO with &quot;NATO Express&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Duncan Shiels</byline>
<dateline>KECSKEMET, Hungary 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A &quot;NATO Express&quot; packed with 600 people rumbled into this central Hungarian city on Friday, launching a three-day campaign to boost public support for joining NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;It's all about people meeting and talking,&quot; said Tamas Wachsler, deputy chairman of Parliament's defence committee and main organiser of the event, which includes a weekend airshow expected to draw crowds of up to 100,000 people.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that the positive effect of the event will raise public awareness of Hungary's NATO future,&quot; said Wachsler, who strongly supports Hungary's admission to NATO in the first round of enlargement of the 16-nation alliance.</p>
<p>A NATO summit to be held in Madrid in July is expected to admit at least three new members from the former Warsaw Pact, the front-runners being Hungary, Poland and Czech Republic.</p>
<p>The chartered, first-class train, paid for in part by Western arms makers, got a sendoff from Budapest by a handful of members of the far-left Workers' Party who oppose NATO.</p>
<p>They carried banners saying &quot;No NATO&quot; and demanding a referendum be held before Hungary joins the alliance.</p>
<p>On board the train, Virag Kofer of the anti-NATO Alba Kor (White Circle) group, wore a slinky evening dress with a sash that said &quot;Miss No-NATO&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I am very actively campaigning against NATO,&quot; said Kofer, members of whose group chained themselves to the tracks last year to prevent a similar train from leaving the station.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the best way I can help in pushing our case,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Hungarians are being brainwashed,&quot; added Robert Fidrich, another Alba member.</p>
<p>&quot;A quarter of Hungary is against joining and almost half don't know what it's about and all they're getting is one side of the equation.&quot;</p>
<p>During the hour and a half trip from Budapest, politicians, members of Parliament and media representatives debated the pros and cons of this former East bloc country joining the Western alliance.</p>
<p>Mattias Eorsi, a Free Democrat member of Parliament, said joining NATO would increase Hungary's security.</p>
<p>&quot;What we lose in sovereignty we gain several times in the framework for our sovereignty that NATO gives us,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Tamas Katona, a former state secretary in the Foreign Ministry, said NATO must adapt to the times.</p>
<p>&quot;NATO has been left the lone boxer in the ring and this shadowboxing could become ridiculous if NATO doesn't move more quickly to become a political rather than a military organisation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The train's destination was an air show at the former Warsaw Pact air base of Kecskemet at which potential bidders for a $1 billion contract to supply Hungary's air force were gathered.</p>
<p>McDonnell Douglas's F18, Lockheed Martin's F16, Dassault's Mirage 2000 and Saab/British Aerospace's Gripen are the main contenders for Hungary's business. Wachsler said the train was paid for by contributions from the sponsoring companies.</p>
<p>On Saturday and Sunday the air base 80 km (50 miles) south of Budapest will be open to the public when up to 100,000 people are expected to watch flying displays by the four main Western contenders for the deal to sell Hungary up to 30 jets.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KECSKEMET, Hungary"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
