<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608825" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albania reassured on election, set for campaign.</title>
<headline>Albania reassured on election, set for campaign.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Lannin</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European envoy Franz Vranitzky has reassured troubled Albania it will get all the monitoring it needs for fair elections despite near-anarchy in several regions.</p>
<p>Vranitzky, in a letter late on Thursday to Prime Minister Bashkim Fino, said international bodies would give Albania the intensive monitoring it requested to make sure the June 29 election was free and fair, Fino's office said.</p>
<p>Albania, Europe's poorest nation, vitally needs the election to restore law and order. The country was torn apart by rioting and looting in February and March and remains tense with some areas beyond state control.</p>
<p>&quot;We can do intensive monitoring in the pre-electoral process and during voting and may assist with all possible means in post-electoral activity,&quot; the letter said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are ready to work with you and your government for the creation of conditions for elections which should represent the will of the Albanian people,&quot; said Vranitzky, envoy of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE).</p>
<p>Fino had requested intensive, &quot;Bosnia-style&quot; monitoring of the vote from start to finish in order to persuade political partes to end a threatened boycott of the vote.</p>
<p>Fino, a Socialist, heads a nine-party Government of National Reconciliation, installed in March as the rioting reached a peak.</p>
<p>The election finally got the go-ahead on Thursday as the Socialist Party, the country's second largest, ended months of deadlock by deciding to take part in the elections, provided that international monitors guarantee they are free and fair.</p>
<p>The campaign gets under way at a time when a million looted weapons, from Kalashnikovs to grenade launchers, are in unauthorised hands.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically we are dealing with a country where the state has collapsed,&quot; said one Western diplomat.</p>
<p>Many of the weapons looted from army barracks ended up in the hands of criminal gangs that seem to roam free in several areas of the country, particularly the south, where police control is virtually absent.</p>
<p>&quot;All together to save Albania,&quot; trumpeted the Zeri i Popullit newspaper, the voice of the Socialist Party, the main rival to President Sali Berisha and his former ruling Democratic Party.</p>
<p>Berisha has been on the campaign trail for more than a week, despite the uncertainty over the vote, accusing the Socialists of being unreformed Communists and blaming them for the unrest of February and March.</p>
<p>The Socialist Party is the reformed heir of the former Communist Party that kept the state in Stalinist isolation for more than 40 years.</p>
<p>&quot;The Socialism of the Communists, dictatorship or rebellion,&quot; the pro-Berisha Albania newspaper quoted the president as saying at an election rally on Thursday.</p>
<p>The boycott threat emerged after the Socialists and other parties accused Berisha and the Democrats of passing election laws aimed at ensuring they would emerge victorious.</p>
<p>They remain deeply mistrustful of Berisha after elections in May 1996 from which the Socialists withdrew on the last day, alleging vote-rigging by the Democratic Party. The OSCE described the 1996 election as deeply flawed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
