<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608892" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UZBEKISTAN: Uzbeks offer major oil, gas projects to investors.</title>
<headline>Uzbeks offer major oil, gas projects to investors.</headline>
<byline>Shamil Baigin</byline>
<dateline>TASHKENT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Uzbekistan has renewed offers to foreign firms to explore and develop five big oil, natural gas and gas condensate projects, said Khudaykul Zhumayev, deputy head of state energy concern Uzbekneftegaz, late on Thursday.</p>
<p>Some of the projects had already been offered to investors in a tender in 1993, but the deals did not go through because of &quot;a number of reasons&quot;, according to an official Uzbekneftegaz document. It gave no further details.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan has struggled to raise foreign investment in exploration and development of its energy reserves since independence from Moscow in 1991, but it has signed several huge deals with overseas energy firms.</p>
<p>At least one production project could take off soon. Enron Oil &amp; Gas Co of the United States and Uzbekneftegaz may create a joint venture by the end of this year to develop natural gas fields.</p>
<p>The new project proposals would not be based on a tender as in 1993, but on negotiations with individual companies which have already begun, the document said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are holding talks with Agip SpA, Mobil Corp, Unocal, Delta Oil and Enron on these projects,&quot; Zhumayev told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said estimated reserves for the five projects were around 2.0 trillion cubic metres of natural gas, 3.65 billion tonnes of oil and 302 million tonnes of gas condensate.</p>
<p>Around 10 percent of these reserves were proven, he said. The total area covered by the projects is 53,300 square km.</p>
<p>He listed the projects as Karakalpak in the west, Beshkent in the central southern region, Gissar and Surkhan-Darya in the south and Fergana in the east.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan also wants to develop with foreign investors oil deposits lying beneath gas caps and improve the rate of recovery at mature fields.</p>
<p>The former Soviet republic has said it plans to produce 8.0 million tonnes (160,000 barrels per day) of oil and gas condensate in 1997, up from 7.7 million tonnes (153,200 bpd) in 1996.</p>
<p>The Central Asian state expects to boost oil and condensate further to 10.0 million (200,000 bpd) by 2000.</p>
<p>It does not expect to boost gas output significantly in the short term from around 50 billion cubic metres it produced last year.</p>
<p>The mostly desert nation of 23 million sits on total estimated reserves of 4.4 billion tonnes of oil, 629 million tonnes of condensates and 5.4 trillion cubic metres of gas.</p>
<p>--Tashkent Newsroom +3712 361958</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UZBK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TASHKENT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UZBEKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
