<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608868" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Flat Polish bourse leads E.Europe slump this week.</title>
<headline>Flat Polish bourse leads E.Europe slump this week.</headline>
<byline>Steven Silber</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Polish shares' modest 0.3-percent gain this week, kept down by the coming public offering of Bank Handlowy, led major East European exchanges as Czech and Slovak stocks were stung by the currency crisis in those countries.</p>
<p>Hungarian shares fell slightly amid a lack of fresh signals, Slovenia gained, Croatia fell and Romanian shares were mixed.</p>
<p>The Central European Share Index (CESI), which measures price movements in 72 Hungarian, Polish, Czech, Slovak and Slovenian stocks, fell more than three and a half percent.</p>
<p>WARSAW</p>
<p>Polish shares inched up this week and analysts said the market would likely maintain its flat trend or fall slightly during the upcoming public offering of Bank Handlowy.</p>
<p>The bank, whose public offering starts next week and is seen worth a total of about $1 billion, is due to announce the price bracket for the offering's tranches by Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot will depend on the pricing of Bank Handlowy. The pricing of that issue should...allow an appraisal of currently listed banks,&quot; said Ryszard Wojnowski, an analyst at Polish Investment Bank (PBI) brokerage.</p>
<p>Analysts said Poland's good macroeconomic environment, reflected by the finance minister's Wednesday statement that year-on-year inflation could fall below 13 percent in December from 15.3 percent in April, would prevent steep falls.</p>
<p>BUDAPEST</p>
<p>Hungarian shares drifted lower this week as the market received few fresh impetuses after companies finished releasing first quarter earnings on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Oil company MOL, the market's highest capitalised stock, was the last firm to release data, which were in line with its own and market expectations.</p>
<p>MOL also finished the second phase of its privatisation in which a total of 19 percent of shares were placed.</p>
<p>Analysts said Budapest stocks should enter a calmer phase.</p>
<p>&quot;We still see it (the market) trading sideways, we still think it is really too expensive,&quot; said Frances Cloud of Nomura Equity Research in London.</p>
<p>&quot;But there's very little sign of people actively selling, so we think it is going to continue to move up a little bit one day, down a little bit the next, with no particular trend.&quot; @</p>
<p>PRAGUE</p>
<p>Czech shares fell sharply throughout the week with dealers saying trading was overshadowed by the crisis in the foreign exchange markets where the crown faced repeated attacks from speculative investors pushing for a devaluation.</p>
<p>Although major issues staged a slight recovery on Thursday, dealers said buying was almost entirely domestically driven with foreigners focusing thier attention on the crown.</p>
<p>&quot;Foreign clients are waiting to see if there will be a devaluation of the crown,&quot; said Ivan Kusacek of Zivnostenska Banka. @</p>
<p>&quot;I haven't seen foreign buyers today (Thursday)....I don't think foreign buyers will trade until the situation of the crown is stabilised,&quot; added ING Baring's Lubomir Vystavel.</p>
<p>The Czech central bank successfully fought off crown speculation on Thursday by taking a series of measures ranging from direct intervention to banning access to the last resort lending rate, the Lombard.</p>
<p>BRATISLAVA @</p>
<p>Turmoil on the Slovak money and forex market overshadowed activities on the Bratislava bourse this week and further weakened the already low liquidity on the Slovak stock market.</p>
<p>Though the official 16-share SAX index firmed 0.11 points this week to close at 195.45 on Thursday, traders said the bourse continued trading at very low volumes which hardly reflected the real market situation.</p>
<p>Traders said they did not expect equity trading to increase in coming days, saying players would be waiting for the result of money market crises in both Slovakia and the Czech Republic. @</p>
<p>&quot;The bourse continues trading low volumes because rates on the local money market are rising to such high levels, few investors are trading shares here,&quot; said Peter Krutil, chief trader at Creditanstalt's Bratislava branch.</p>
<p>LJUBLJANA</p>
<p>Slovenian shares gained 1.93 percent this week as the blue- chip SBI index rose 25.05 points to 1,323.34. Turnover fell to 324.9 million tolars ($2.18 million) from 378.6 million tolars. @</p>
<p>Traders said future movements on the market would largely depend on the ratification of the EU association accord, which was signed in June last year.</p>
<p>Last week the Slovenian parliament postponed a vote on whether to ratify the agreement to allow political parties one more week to reach a broader agreement on the issue.</p>
<p>Traders said the ratification could push the blue-chip index up 30 percent over the next two to three months as foreign investors would resume buying. @</p>
<p>&quot;If the treaty is not ratified the index could slide to its December level of about 1,150 points,&quot; one broker said.</p>
<p>ZAGREB</p>
<p>Croatian stocks suffered further losses in modest trade throughout the week, but analysts saw no further erosion.</p>
<p>&quot;Share prices have already fallen a lot. They have now probably reached resistance,&quot; said Davor Relja of Split-based brokerage Faktor.</p>
<p>Fully listed Zagrebacka Banka gained 30 kuna to 2,030 kuna, while drugs firm Pliva held its ground at 450 kuna. @</p>
<p>Chocolate maker Kras was among the gainers, ending at 409.9 kuna on Thursday but another popular stock, food processor Podravka, continued to slide to 265 kuna, its lowest in months.</p>
<p>BUCHAREST</p>
<p>Bucharest shares traded mixed this week, with most stocks taking a tumble on Thursday as investors took a wait-and-see attitude faced with prices they viewed as too high.</p>
<p>Traders said they expected investors to stay in a waiting mood on Friday and saw a rebound of the market next week. @</p>
<p>MAY 22    CLOSE	 WEEK'S   CHANGE    1997 HIGH  1997 LOW</p>
<p>			    pts	pct</p>
<p> WARSAW    16,436.6    52.3     0.3	18,339.4   14,421.6</p>
<p> BUDAPEST   5,795.24  -85.68   -1.46	5,985.17   4,291.29</p>
<p> PRAGUE	 477.1   -32.1    -6.3	   629.4	476.7</p>
<p> LJUBLJANA  1,323.34   25.05    1.93	1,655.4    1,156.02</p>
<p> BRATISLAVA   195.45    0.11    0.06	  207.75     174.05</p>
<p>ROMANIA</p>
<p> VAB-Index    925.3    22.6     2.5	 1,041.0	262.0</p>
<p> BIG-Index    883.58    0.4    -0.03	1,020.44     266.43</p>
<p>@</p>
<p> CESI	 1,414.72  -52.28   -3.57	1,751.89   1,432.13</p>
<p>All-time highs: PX50 1,002.4 (April 7, 1994), WIG 20,760.3 (March 8, 1994), CESI 1,751.89 (Feb 24, 1997), BUX 5,985.17 (April 30, 1997), SAX 405.49 (Feb 23, 1994), SBI 1,655.4 (Feb 10, 1997)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
