<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608917" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech c.bank head cites reasons for crown run.</title>
<headline>Czech c.bank head cites reasons for crown run.</headline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Czech National Bank Governor Josef Tosovsky told parliament on Thursday that political instability and a recent attack on the Thai baht were the reasons behind the current moves by speculators against the Czech crown.</p>
<p>&quot;There is not sufficient political stability here in the eyes of foreign investors, threrefore they are pulling their money out from here or they are not investing it here and are postponing their decision concerning their potential activities here,&quot; Tosovsky said in a speech to the lower house.</p>
<p>The central bank has been fighting to defend the crown, heavily buying the currency on several occasions in the past week as it fell as low as six percent below its mark/dollar peg.</p>
<p>Tosovsky told the chamber the crown drop followed pressure on the currencies of Thailand, Malaysia and Philippines.</p>
<p>&quot;When a situation like this develops, the market usually looks where are similar countries with similar problems, and in this case it concerned the Czech Republic,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;That is how the market evaluated it and an attack began aginst the Czech currency while there was not a significant change in the past weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the three parties in the centre-right Czech ruling coalition agreed earlier this week to shuffle cabinet seats after a sharp drop in the government's approval ratings, but the leaders have been unable to agree on how.</p>
<p>-- Jan Lopatka, Prague Newsroom, 420-2-2423-0003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
