<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608911" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: PRESS DIGEST - Hungary - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Hungary - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Here are highlights of stories reported by Hungary's press, based on information by Nepszabadsag's Hungary Around the Clock service. For further details on how to subscribe to Hungary Around the Clock, please contact Monica Kovacs at (361) 351 7142 or fax your request to (361) 351 7141.</p>
<p>ALL PAPERS</p>
<p>- Finance Minister Peter Medgyessy forecast 3-4% economic growth for next year 2000.</p>
<p>- Opposition parties walked out of three committee meetings on Thursday.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Gyula Horn denied that he had private meetings with opposition leaders with a view to discussing a future coalition.</p>
<p>- Young Democrat president Viktor Orban said that his party cannot see cooperation with the Christian Democrats should Gyorgy Giczy be reelected party president.</p>
<p>- Interior Minister Gabor Kuncze is expected to be promoted to party president at the Free Democrats' weekend congress.</p>
<p>- The environment will receive Ft 88 billion this yearfrom the budget and ECU 14.5 million under the PHARE scheme.</p>
<p>- European Parliament representatives have reacted with reservation to a request by Prime Minister Gyula Horn that the EU establish a pecking order of potential candidates for membership.</p>
<p>- Socialist parliamentary group leader Imre Szekeres met World Bank president James Wolfensohn in Washington Thursday, to discuss loans and the transfer of expertise to help Hungary catch up with the EU.</p>
<p>- Environmental protection committees from the parliaments of seven Central and East European countries signed a joint statement in Budapest Wednesday, with only Slovakia opting out.</p>
<p>- Privatization agency APV Rt is proposing that the state sell its 25% plus one vote in OTP Bank, holding on only to one golden share.</p>
<p>- The pharmaceuticals company Richter's official share price was set at $78, or Ft 14,160, in London on Thursday.</p>
<p>- The Northern Hungarian electricity supplier EMASZ suffered losses of Ft 3.6 billion last year, the highest in its history.</p>
<p>- Moscow mayor Jurij Luzskov proposed at a meeting with Ikarus chief Gabor Szeles in the Russian capital Thursday that Ikarus and Russian company Zil begin production of 500 Zil Bicsok models.</p>
<p>- MTM-SBS Televizio Rt. and the First Hungarian Commercial Television Rt., better known as Irisz TV, are to advance in first and second place to the second round of bidding for broadcasting rights to Commercial TV Channel 1.</p>
<p>- The German company Bayernwerk has purchased 23.7% of the North Transdanubian Power Supplier EDASZ from Electricite de France (EdF) for Ft 11.1 billion, or 121% of face value.</p>
<p>- Some 60 airplanes and helicopters, including models from companies interested in a current tender to provide fighters to the Hungarian Armed Forces, will be on display at the Kecskemet international air show starting Saturday.</p>
<p>NAPI GAZDASAG</p>
<p>- The tax authority APEH reports receipt of Ft 511 billion from personal income taxes on last year's incomes so far, well above the target of Ft 480 billion.</p>
<p>MAGYAR NEMZET</p>
<p>- Lockheed Martin, which manufactures F-16 fighters, has signed a cooperation agreement worth $750,000 with the Central Physics Research Institute (KFKI) for software development and technology transfer.</p>
<p>-- Budapest newsroom +36 1 327 4040</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
