<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608981" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil's 'micromanaging' of economy in full swing.</title>
<headline>Brazil's 'micromanaging' of economy in full swing.</headline>
<byline>John Miller</byline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Steps taken Thursday to lure foreign capital and discourage credit card use abroad suggest Brazil will continue to try to micromanage its way of the nation's external accounts woes, economists said.</p>
<p>Rather than jolt markets with a significant devaluation or interest rate hike, Central Bank officials appear committed to relying on a series of modest measures to slow a ballooning current account gap and protect foreign reserves.  </p>
<p>&quot;I don't think they are going to do anything radical. We're going to see more of the same and if none of it works then maybe they will have to raise interest rates,&quot; said Tomas Malaga, an economist at Brazilian retail bank Unibanco.</p>
<p>On Thursday, the government lifted a ban in place since 1995 on foreign investor participation in the derivatives market to hedge financial transactions. Officials said removal of the ban would make Brazilian stock markets more attractive.</p>
<p>Also on Thursday, officials said they would require Brazilians to pay for all credit card purchases abroad when the bill comes due and not in installments.  </p>
<p>The moves followed measures taken since March to control the trade balance deficit -- expected by economists to reach $11 billion this year -- and protect Brazil's $57 billion in net foreign reserves.</p>
<p>Although none of the measures alone are expected to have much impact, the government hopes that together they can improve Brazil's worrying external accounts picture.</p>
<p>For the most part, economists have accepted the government's cautious approach to the problem.  </p>
<p>&quot;In the past we have noted that we do not like micromanagement as a concept but we find Brazil's decisions logical and not very harmful,&quot; Bear Stearns said in a recent report.</p>
<p>The report added that the latest steps were not as drastic as Brazil's March 1995 credit tightenting, which was aimed at bursting a consumption bubble fueled by 10 percent economic growth in that year's first quarter.  </p>
<p>&quot;We don't think the trade deficit issue is as significant as the 1995 consumption problem, and we do not expect micromanagement to reach that level of intensity,&quot; Bear Stearns said.</p>
<p>Possible moves by the government in the not-too-distant future include a limit on the number of installments consumers can use to repay domestic credit card debt and further cuts in financial transaction taxes on foreign investors, economists say.  </p>
<p>They  warn, however, that as long as the government relies on tinkering techniques to steer macroeconomic policy, the prickly, deep-rooted and more significant problems, like the fiscal deficit, remain on the back burner.</p>
<p>They added that gross domestic product figures released Thursday highlight the need to tackle the growing shortfall in the balance of payment's current account. Brazil's National Statistics Institute said the economy actually shrank in the first quarter of the year by 0.56 percent against the fourth quarter of 1996.</p>
<p>But despite the economic contraction, the country's trade deficit soared in the period to $3.0 billion, compared to just $452 million in first quarter 1996.</p>
<p>Economists, who blame rising imports on the strong reais currency and pent-up demand for foreign goods, say the trade gap would grow even more worrisome with stronger economic activity.</p>
<p>((--Sao Paulo newsroom, 5511 248-5414))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
