<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608920" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Top Mexican officials accused of aiding drug lord.</title>
<headline>Top Mexican officials accused of aiding drug lord.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Brothers</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Disgraced drug-fighting general Jesus Gutierrez Rebollo has said it was not he but high-ups in the Defence Ministry who protected Mexico's most notorious drug baron, Amado Carrillo Fuentes.</p>
<p>Gutierrez Rebollo, in jail while twin civilian and military trials unfold, was fired as the country's chief anti-drug warrior amid allegations of corruption in February.</p>
<p>But in transcripts of his defence obtained on Friday by Reuters, Gutierrez Rebollo says the cocaine lord &quot;could count on the protection of personnel in the Ministry of Defence,&quot; adding that a leak from high up helped Carillo Fuentes evade arrest in January.</p>
<p>&quot;(It) is evident that complicity with Amado Carrillo came from the ranks of the Defence Ministry,&quot; Gutierrez Rebollo said in testimony delivered on May 15.</p>
<p>Responsibility for the failed arrest was pinned on a major in the Mexican military. But the general denied this possibility.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of his rank and place of commission, he could not have had any direct knowledge of an operation of such importance,&quot; Gutierrez Rebollo said.</p>
<p>Allegations of drug corruption at the highest level of Mexico's armed forces emerged as part of the jailed general's defence in court on charges that he himself had taken bribes from the drug lord, chief of the powerful Juarez cartel.</p>
<p>The claims came on top of testimony on Thursday from a key witness in the case accusing four Mexican generals, two of whom are now dead, and the private secretary of former president Carlos Salinas de Gortari of all having had ties to the drug lord.</p>
<p>Carrillo Fuentes, dubbed the most powerful man in the Mexican drug trade by the U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) the subject of at least 26 separate DEA investigations and has been a fugitive for the last eight years.</p>
<p>The general's dismissal in February as head of the National Institute for the Combating of Drugs (INCD) deeply embarrassed the Mexican government, under pressure from Washington to stem the flow of illegal drugs across the U.S.-Mexican border.</p>
<p>The government disbanded the agency and replaced it with a 60-person team of specially trained agents known as the Special Prosecutor's Office for Crimes Against Health.</p>
<p>In an interview with Reuters, Gutierrez Rebollo's lawyer, Edgar Herrera Navarrete, said the general denied protecting the drug baron.</p>
<p>&quot;He wants to demonstrate that it is not true that he has been defending Carillo Fuentes. He wants to demonstrate that it was an information leak that allowed (the drug lord) to escape,&quot; he said, adding that information of that importance could not have come from a major.</p>
<p>The general also said he kept Defence Minister Enrique Cervantes and the attorney general informed of his anti-drug efforts.</p>
<p>As proof of his impartial fight against drugs, he cited his handing over of Alejandro Hodoyan Palacio, an arms trafficker for the so-called Tijuana cartel, to the DEA as a protected witness.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
