<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608951" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico stocks end down, take a break from records.</title>
<headline>Mexico stocks end down, take a break from records.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexican stocks ended off on Friday in what traders and analysts said was a breather after chalking up three record closes in a row.</p>
<p>&quot;It was just profit-taking after it hit 4,000 points again. The market looks firm, although it ought to capitalize gains better at brisker volume,&quot; said Roberto Campuzano, an analyst at the Invex brokerage in Mexico City.</p>
<p>The leading IPC share index ended down 11.23 points, or 0.28 percent, at 3,988.29. The IPC had climbed as high as a new intraday record of 4,013.99 points in early trade. Trading volume was lacklustre at 59.6 million shares.  </p>
<p>Some dealers said light profit-taking was due to U.S. brokers closing their books ahead of the Memorial Day holiday, for which U.S. financial markets will close on Monday, May 26.</p>
<p>&quot;As Wall Street closes on Monday, several dealers decided to go into the long weekend either flat or with cash in hand. But locals did step in a little to buy low,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>The Dow Jones meanwhile soared 87.78 points to 7,345.91 points.</p>
<p>The IPC closely shadowed the changing fortunes of Telmex stock, which ended off two centavos at 17.42 pesos, down from a session high of 17.52 pesos.  </p>
<p>The telecomms' ADRs similarly ended off 1/8 at 44-1/4, but had traded earlier at 44-5/8.</p>
<p>Telmex was unseated form its usual first place on the most-traded stocks list by builder Consorcio Hogar, which made an initial public offering on Friday. Hogar closed the session at its issue price of 10.40 pesos.</p>
<p>On the broad market, 106 shares traded hands, of which sliders outpaced gainers by 53 to 34.</p>
<p>(( --Karina Balderas, Mexico City newsroom +525 728-9562))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
