<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608957" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Caracas stocks close up, with foreign bids strong.</title>
<headline>Caracas stocks close up, with foreign bids strong.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Caracas stocks closed up for the fourth session in a row on strong foreign bids, with the rally seen extending into next week, traders said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We've heard foreign analysts' commentaries that take a very positive view on Venezuela,&quot; said Multinvest broker Reinaldo Uribe. &quot;They're very optimistic on the labor reforms.&quot;</p>
<p>The lower house of the Venezuelan Congress this week approved a crucial labor reform measure, part of a wider package to overhaul the social security system and liberalize labor markets. The Senate is to consider the measure next week.  </p>
<p>The bolsa's 19-share index gained 0.9 percent to end at 6,746.69 points. About 50 million shares, worth 3.7 billion bolivars ($7.6 million), changed hands. Among traded issues, 23 rose, 10 fell and 10 closed unchanged.</p>
<p>Telephone company CANTV led gainers, rising 2.49 percent to 2474.00 bolivars. The rise helped firm Merinvest's composite index, which includes CANTV, 1.38 percent to 107.20.</p>
<p>((-- Silene Ramirez, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
