<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608919" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: TV shows shooting of kidnapper by Brazilian police.</title>
<headline>TV shows shooting of kidnapper by Brazilian police.</headline>
<byline>Simona de Logu</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazilian television on Friday showed a police officer in Sao Paulo state shooting in the head at point-blank range a man who had kidnapped a 2-year-old girl and was threatening her with a knife.</p>
<p>Globo Television footage showed the kidnapper holding the child in his arms with a knife to her throat while pacing nervously up and down on the side of a road. Then a police officer suddenly raises a gun to the man's head and fires.</p>
<p>The kidnapper died later at a hospital. The baby girl was immediately returned unharmed to her family.</p>
<p>The man, who had been fleeing from police for five hours, took three girls hostage at first but let two of them go before being surrounded near the town of Valinhos. Police tried to negotiate with him for several hours.</p>
<p>The man had tried to commit burglary at an isolated farmhouse on Thursday evening, but when he heard police coming, he kidnapped three sisters aged 13, 12 and 2 and ran from the house, a police spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;He tried to escape in a van, telling the 13-year-old to drive,&quot; he said. &quot;The girl doesn't know how to drive, so she crashed the van, and he had to continue on foot.&quot;</p>
<p>Police were unable to identify the man, who used the false name Diego Jose. He was between 25 and 30 years old and is believed to have been a former convict.</p>
<p>The man was known to the family because he had made sexual advances toward the oldest girl and had invited her several times to take drugs, the police spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;The girl says he raped her while he was in the house and told her that he has AIDS,&quot; he said. &quot;She is in a hospital, where she is being checked for any signs of rape.&quot;</p>
<p>The shooting of the kidnapper in the early hours of Friday caused controversy, and the police officer responsible was suspended from duty to undergo psychological examination. His commander, however, said the officer was right to shoot.</p>
<p>&quot;The officer was sure of what he was doing,&quot; Marci Elber, commander of an elite police force, told Globo. &quot;He waited for the right moment, making sure the life and well-being of the hostage could be preserved.&quot;</p>
<p>Elber said the encircling police had tried every means of opening negotiations with the kidnapper.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
