<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608928" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PUERTO RICO: Puerto Rico drops plans for AIDS name reporting.</title>
<headline>Puerto Rico drops plans for AIDS name reporting.</headline>
<dateline>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Puerto Rico Health Department has dropped several controversial AIDS proposals, including a plan to require that individuals report the names of their sex partners to the government, the American Civil Liberties Union said on Friday.</p>
<p>In a statement made public on Thursday, Health Department Secretary Carmen Feliciano said she would &quot;annual the contents of Regulation 87,&quot; and make its partner notification proposal a voluntary programme.</p>
<p>The American Civil Liberties Union said the regulations were to have taken effect on April 1, but were suspended after the ACLU and other AIDS advocates charged that they would have violated individual privacy and undermined public health goals. The ACLU also threatened to sue.</p>
<p>&quot;Their proposals were a disaster for HIV prevention efforts,&quot; said ACLU Aids Project staff attorney Michael Adams. &quot;I'm glad the health department has heeded the warnings of community advocates, and backed down from its ill-conceived and dangerous scheme.&quot;</p>
<p>The most controversial provision of the AIDS programme would have required anyone who tested positive for HIV, the virus that causes AIDS, to send a list of all their sex partners, including addresses and telephone numbers, to the health department. Failure to comply would have been punishable by fines up to $5,000.</p>
<p>Another provision would have authorised commonwealth officials to force any individual suspected of carrying HIV to submit to a blood test.</p>
<p>The health department also suspended a programme that would have required hospitals and medical laboratories to send HIV-positive test results to the government. Instead, the government said it would study the issue further, the ACLU said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PURI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PUERTO RICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
