<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608901" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish KGHM to trim non-core jobs, give guarantees.</title>
<headline>Polish KGHM to trim non-core jobs, give guarantees.</headline>
<byline>Wojciech Moskwa</byline>
<dateline>DUSZNIKI ZDROJ, Poland 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Polish KGHM copper concern, slated for flotation next month, plans to further shed non-production activities to cut costs, but will provide a safety net for employees, a KGHM official said.</p>
<p>Eugeniusz Kranc, head of the restructuring department, said KGHM would order services from firms formed as a result of its restructuring scheme and not reduce jobs there for three years. @</p>
<p>&quot;To secure the market success of these new firms, there are guarantees to keep the amount of orders for services steady and employment guarantees for a period of three years,&quot; Kranc told a seminar for technical college graduates late on Thursday.</p>
<p>He said that as a result of this programme KGHM would better concentrate on production of copper and silver and increase productivity and the company's value.</p>
<p>The Polish government plans to float between 11 and 15 percent of KGHM on the Warsaw bourse in June and between 21 and 26 percent on international markets in the form of global depositary receipts later in the year. @</p>
<p>KGHM employees will get 15 percent.</p>
<p>Kranc said that to facilitate restructuring KGHM had created two internal investment funds, the Dolnoslaska Spolka Inwestycyjna SA (DSI) and KGHM Metale SA.</p>
<p>DSI's main tasks were to allocate capital not directly connected to copper production, take over management of firms carved out of KGHM during restructuring and create alternative employment for the region's workers.</p>
<p>KGHM Metale will invest in industries involved in the processing of ferrous and non-ferrous metals. @</p>
<p>Kranc said that about 22,000 out of the copper concern's nearly 43,000 workers were directly involved in production.</p>
<p>&quot;Experience tells us that through restructuring jobs are actually created in these new firms....in administration, accounting, finances,&quot; he said, adding that at the start of restructuring KGHM had employed about 40,000 people.</p>
<p>KGHM, worth an estimated $2 billion to $3 billion, last year produced 425,000 tonnes of copper, 933 tonnes of silver and 530 kg of gold. @</p>
<p>The concern's net profits tumbled to 147 million zlotys last year from 482 million in 1995, as low coopper prices on world markets and large provisions reduced profits.</p>
<p>The scores of firms which have been hived off from KGHM include the costly road transportation system, energy firms supplying power to mines, and new companies created from the assets of closed mines.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22460">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUSZNIKI ZDROJ, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
