<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608983" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: Venezuela PdVSA dividends seen half of last year's.</title>
<headline>Venezuela PdVSA dividends seen half of last year's.</headline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Venezuelan state oil giant PdVSA expects this year's oil dividend -- paid to its only shareholder, the Venezuelan state -- will be less than half last year's one trillion bolivar ($2 billion) payment, a senior PdVSA official said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not going to have the same year as last when there was a devaluation and high oil prices,&quot; PdVSA vice president Luis Urdaneta told reporters.  Devaluations increase bolivar revenues from PdVSA's dollar denominated oil sales.  </p>
<p>PdVSA recently increased its 1996 dividend, to be paid this year, by 200 billion bolivars to one trillion -- but much of that increase will be used to pay down some of the 648 billion bolivars in tax refunds owed by the government to PdVSA.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect the increased dividend will be compensated for by deducting the amount from the taxes we are owed,&quot; said Urdaneta.</p>
<p>The dividends do not include other payments that PdVSA makes to the treasury, which totaled four trillion bolivars last year - - over 10 percent of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) and around half of total government revenues.</p>
<p>The reduced 1997 dividend comes as the government try to square its fiscal accounts for the year.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Luis Raul Matos Azocar said Thursday the year would close with a fiscal surplus equivalent to 1.6 percent of GDP.  But the assertion was immediately disputed by opposition parties due to recent additional spending requests.</p>
<p>((-- Ana Isabel Martinez, Caracas newsroom, 582 505 2600))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
