<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608997" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Colombia secret police chief in eyes of assassins.</title>
<headline>Colombia secret police chief in eyes of assassins.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Authorities have uncovered a plot to assassinate Gen. Luis Enrique Montenegro, the head of Colombia's state security police, police sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>It was the second time this week that security sources revealed the existence of murder plots involving high-profile targets. Police said on Monday that jailed Colombian drug bosses had placed President Ernesto Samper and U.S. Ambassador Myles Frechette on an apparent &quot;hit list.&quot;</p>
<p>The plot involving Montenegro -- one of the country's leading anti-drug fighters -- was linked to drug traffickers as well. But police sources, confirming a report in Friday's editions of Bogota's El Tiempo newspaper, said it was to have been carried out by leftist guerrillas working on behalf of drug barons.</p>
<p>The rebel hit men, believed to number no more than four and all sharpshooters with expertise in the handling of explosives, were to have carried out the attack on Montenegro somewhere in the Colombian capital, the police sources said.</p>
<p>Montenegro was named head of the Administrative Security Department (DAS) in January. He previously served as the deputy of National Police Chief Gen. Rosso Jose Serrano and took an active role in the dismantling of the country's powerful Cali cocaine cartel in 1995 and 1996.</p>
<p>Since taking over as head of the DAS, Montenegro has overseen the creation of an elite anti-drug squad to enforce an asset forfeiture law approved by Congress last year. The law allows authorities to track down and confiscate the wealth and properties of convicted drug traffickers and turn them over to the state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
