<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608921" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: South American port conditions - Lloyds.</title>
<headline>South American port conditions - Lloyds.</headline>
<text>
<p>Port conditions from Lloyds Shipping Intelligence Service --</p>
<p>ARGENTINA, May 20 - Santa Fe - no vessels berthed, no vessels in roads, no vessels due. Max. draft 21 ft. 7 in. at access channel.</p>
<p>Diamante - two vessels berthed of which 1 discharging fertiliser, 1 loading maize, no vessels in roads, 1 vessel due. Max. draft 21 ft. 7in. at passage km 520.</p>
<p>San Lorenzo - six vessels berthed of which 2 loading SBO, 2 loading by-products, 1 loading sun pellets, 1 loading sorghum. 9 vessels in roads. 35 vessels due at 6 terminals during the coming week. The recast indicates that the draft will fall approx. 0.15 metres during next week. Pasa berth draft - 18 ft. 3 in. Fw. max. rec. draft 31 ft. 7 in fw. at high tide.</p>
<p>Rosario - six vessels berthed of which 1 loading maize, 1 under repairs, 2 discharging fertiliser, 1 loading wheat, 1 loading sorghum. 3 vessels in roads, 15 vessels due during the week. Forecast indicates that the draft will fall approx. 0.10 metres during next week. Max. rec. draft 31 ft. 7 in. fw at high tide.</p>
<p>Villa Constucion - two vessels berthed of which 1 loading maize, 1 discharging WRC, No vessels in roads, 3 vessels due. Elevator berths - max. draft 22 ft. 0 in. fw.</p>
<p>San Nicolas - four vessels berthed of which 1 under orders, 1 loading pig iron, 1 discharging zinc, 1 discharging iron ore. 2 vessels in roads, 5 vessels due during next week. Forecast indicates that the draft will fall approx. 0.15 metres during next week. Max. rec. draft 32 ft. 9 in. fw. at high tide.</p>
<p>San Pedro - no vessels alongside, no vessels in roads, 1 vessel due. Forecast indicates that the draft will fall approx. 0.10 metres during next week. Max. rec. draft 32 ft. 9 in. fw. at high tide.</p>
<p>Buenos Aires - eighteen vessels in port, 20 vessels due. Max. draft - 31 ft. 6 in. fw. High tide Naabsa (guided by entrance channel), Dock Sud max. draft - 28/29 ft. fw. high tide Naabsa (guided by entrance channel).</p>
<p>Necochea - five vessels berthed of which 1 loading SFMP, 2 loading maize, 1 loading SFO. No vessels in roads, 8 vessels due. Max. draft at entrance channel - 40 ft. 0 in. bw.</p>
<p>Bahia Blanca - five vessels berthed of which 2 loading maize, 1 loading wheat, 1 loading SFO, 1 discharging fertiliser. 1 vessel in roads, 6 vessels due, Draft depends on each berth.</p>
<p>BRAZIL, May 20 - Vitoria - vessels berthed - 1 bulk malt discharger, 1 granite loader, 1 bulk soya loader, 1 container/general cargo discharger.</p>
<p>Tubarao - 1 iron ore loader, 1 fuel discharger.</p>
<p>Praia Mole - 3 steel products loaders, 1 coal discharger.</p>
<p>Portocel - 1 cellulose loader.</p>
<p>Ubu - 1 iron ore loader. Seventeen vessels waiting in roads.</p>
<p>Santos - vessels berthed - 1 full container loader/discharger, 1 bulk cement, 2 wheat dischargers, 2 general cargo loaders/dischargers, 1 general cargo loader, 1 general cargo discharger, 2 bulk soya loaders, 1 bulk chemical products discharger, 2 fertiliser dischargers, 1 bulk caustic soda discharger, 1 juice loader, 1 propane discharger, 2 vehicles loaders, 1 bulk sulphur discharger, 1 general cargo/container discharger/loader. 4 vessels waiting in roads, 71 vessels due during next 7 days.</p>
<p>Private terminals - Cosipa - 1 steel products loader, 1 bulk coal discharger, 1 iron ore discharger.</p>
<p>Ultrafertil - no vessels.</p>
<p>Paranagua - vessels berthed - 2 container dischargers, 2 sugar loaders, 3 pellets loaders, 2 soya loaders, 3 general cargo loaders. 25 vessels waiting in roads of which 8 sugar vessels for loading, 12 pellets for loading, 1 general cargo for ading, 3 soya vessels for loading, 1 container vessel for discharging. 37 vessels due during next 7 days.</p>
<p>Rio Grande - vessels berthed - 3 full container loaders, 3 soya loaders, 1 general cargo loader, 1 gas loader, 3 fertiliser dischargers, 1 wheat discharger. 3 vessels waiting in roads, 23 vessels due during next 10 days.</p>
<p>Rio de Janeiro - vessels berthed - 2 wheat dischargers, 1 paper discharger, 2 general cargo dischargers, 1 steel products discharger, 1 tubes discharger, general cargo/container loader, 1 steel products loader.</p>
<p>Tecon - 3 vessels, 24 vessels due during next 7 days.</p>
<p>Sao Sebastiao - vessels berthed - Tebar - 4 vessels, 4 waiting in roads, 3 vessels due during next 7 days.</p>
<p>Salvador - various operational disputes occurred during the day and night shifts on 12/5 due to problems with employees of the port administration (Codeba) who are to be absorbed by the casual labour categories because Codeba is gradually withdrawing itself from port operations. A compromise between Codeba, the workers' union and the Salvador port operators to find a solution normalised the situation the next day. Since 19/5, casual labour decided to work to rule, as so far no collective labour contract has been signed.</p>
<p>CHILE, May 19 - Arica - two vessels berthed, 4 berths vacant, 12 vessels due during the week.</p>
<p>Iquique - five vessels berthed and operating, 1 berth vacant, 14 vessels due during the week.</p>
<p>Antofagasta - three vessels berthed, 4 berths vacant, 13 vessels due this week to load/discharge concentrates, bulk copper, containers and general cargo.</p>
<p>Valparaiso - three vessels berthed and operating, 6 berths vacant, Pier 2 out of service for enlargement until April 1998, 21 vessels due during the week with 1 day's delay expected.</p>
<p>San Antonio - seven vessels in port operating, 3 berths vacant, 15 vessels due during the week, port busy but no delays expected.</p>
<p>Puerto Montt - two vessels and 1 passenger vessel in port, 1 vessel due during the week.</p>
<p>Punta Arenas - four vessels berthed, 5 vessels due during the week.</p>
<p>Conception Bay ports - Talcahuano - one vessel berthed, 3 vessels due this week, No vessels in roads.</p>
<p>San Vicente - three vessels berthed and operating, 6 due during the week, 1 day's berthing delay expected.</p>
<p>Navy Pier (Molo 500) - no vessels berthed, 3 due during the week. Steel Pier - 1 vessel berthed, 1 berth vacant, 1 vessel due during the week. Coronel Pier - no vessels berthed. Oil Terminal - 2 vessels berthed, none due during the week.</p>
<p>Lirquen - three vessels berthed, 3 berths vacant, 5 vessels due during the week.</p>
<p>Penco - no vessels berthed, 1 vessel due during the week.</p>
<p>PERU, May 19 - no strikes at any port. Callao - nine vessels anchored, 5 general cargo/container vessels berthed, No berthing delays.</p>
<p>Paita - no vessels anchored, 3 general cargo vessels berthed, No berthing delays.</p>
<p>Bayovar - no vessels anchored, 1 crude oil vessel berthed, No berthing delays.</p>
<p>Talara - no vessels anchored, 1 oil tanker berthed. No berthing delays.</p>
<p>Chimbote - three vessels anchored, 4 fish meal vessels berthed. No berthing delays.</p>
<p>Pisco, Ilo - no vessels, no berthing delays.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
