<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608989" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine stocks seen continuing sideways drift.</title>
<headline>Argentine stocks seen continuing sideways drift.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Argentina stocks were expected to stay rangebound at the opening Friday as the market continues to digest profit-taking after a long winning streak, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The market remains firm and is showing more mettle with good turnover of 30-35 million pesos, which denotes a higher volume of institutional investments,&quot; said Norman Trabucco at Zaracan traders. &quot;However, investors might be more reluctant now because of the recent strong advance in prices.&quot;</p>
<p>The blue-chip MerVal index posted its ninth consecutive gain Thursday, edging up 0.1 percent to 765.42.  </p>
<p>&quot;The MerVal might just narrowly stay on the upside again, especially because the Dow is recovering today and the U.S. long bond yield remains below the psychological level of seven percent,&quot; another analyst said.</p>
<p>Traders singled out oil company Astra, which has outperformed most blue chips this week, as an example of a stock moving selectively on long-term forecasts.</p>
<p>&quot;People are looking at what may happen with Astra years down the line -- this is the classic investment style of groups like the private pension funds (AFJPs),&quot; Trabucco said.</p>
<p>((-- Carmen Pignotti, Buenos Aires Newsroom 541 318-0657))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
