<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608923" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HAITI: Haiti's senatorial runoff is postponed until June.</title>
<headline>Haiti's senatorial runoff is postponed until June.</headline>
<byline>Nicole Volpe</byline>
<dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Election officials in Haiti announced late on Wednesday that second-round balloting in senatorial elections would be postponed until June 15, a move diplomatic sources attributed to international pressure.</p>
<p>&quot;What is important about this process is the credibility,&quot; U.S. Ambassador William Swing said on Thursday. &quot;It isn't the date that counts.&quot;</p>
<p>Haitian election officials have come under fire for the way ballots were counted in the first round of elections, on April 6.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a lot of discussions, and we decided it was best not to hold the elections on Sunday,&quot; Alexandre Lavaud, general secretary of the Provisional Electoral Council, told Reuters in an interview on Thursday. &quot;There was also a last-minute problem of organising the materials.&quot;</p>
<p>Diplomatic sources said the United Nations stopped delivering ballots throughout the country last weekend and negotiations to postpone the runoff went on all week.</p>
<p>The sources said the United Nations, the United States and other countries close to Haiti were concerned about the political direction in which the elections were moving.</p>
<p>The senatorial race is important because control of the senate and implementation of a U.S.-backed privatisation plan are at stake. The Senate narrowly approved privatisation last year.</p>
<p>Nine seats, or one-third of the Senate, were to be filled in the April 6 and runoff elections.</p>
<p>Two candidates of former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide's Fanmi Lavalas party were officially declared winners in the first round of voting. Members of the ruling Lavalas Political Organisation, called OPL after its French initials, protested what they called irregularities and election fraud.</p>
<p>Aristide, who was succeeded by President Rene Preval in February 1996, formed the Fanmi Lavalas party a year later. After leaving office, he made vague statements against privatisation, which has been championed by Preval.</p>
<p>Election officials declared the two Fanmi Lavalas candidates winners by a majority in the first round, making a runoff for those seats unecessary.</p>
<p>OPL candidates protested that blank ballots were not counted, as required by law, and said they would drop out of the race, giving most of the seats to Fanmi Lavalas candidates.</p>
<p>Lavaud said the extra time was needed to correct such irregularities.</p>
<p>Fanmi Lavalas candidates have taken Aristide's anti-privatisation stance. They have called for further dialogue about the government's plan to privatise nine state enterprises, a plan supported by international donors to the impoverished country.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORT-AU-PRINCE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HAITI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
