<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608987" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Argentine riots trigger debate on plight of poor.</title>
<headline>Argentine riots trigger debate on plight of poor.</headline>
<byline>David Haskel</byline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A spate of angry protests by displaced workers clamoring for jobs has triggered a heated debate in Argentina about what to do with the legions of poor with no access to the new riches generated by market reforms.</p>
<p>International Monetary Fund chief Michel Camdessus stepped into the polemic this week, praising Argentina's free market path but warning President Carlos Menem's Peronist government that:  </p>
<p>&quot;The promising prospects for Argentine reform could turn to failure if efforts are not intensified to reduce the inequality in income and even more importantly, to create more opportunities for the underprivileged.&quot;</p>
<p>Amadeo Vazquez, Vice President of Banco Rio, one of the five leading Argentine banks, told Clarin newspaper Friday: &quot;I share every word he said. Camdessus made a correct interpretation of the Argentine business community.&quot;  </p>
<p>The incidents included clashes between gendarmes and unemployed sugar workers in the northern province of Jujuy this week, with at least 80 people injured. Gendarmes used rubber bullets and batons against some 500 people who were blocking a highway to demand new jobs and state aid.</p>
<p>Other protests throughout the country included incidents involving street vendors and students in the city of La Plata near Buenos Aires Wednesday, and scuffles with police by laid-off oil workers in southern Patagonia.  </p>
<p>The debate triggered by the incidents is twofold -- who is to blame for poverty and unemployment, and who should be seeking a solution to the problem.</p>
<p>Argentina's swing from a centralized, state-dominated economy to a market-oriented system in the past six years has won the Menem administration widespread international praise.</p>
<p>But along with strong economic growth and unheard-of currency stability in a country long used to hyperinflation, unemployment has shot up to a troubling 17.3 percent.  </p>
<p>And poverty, which since Menem first took power in 1989 was cut by half, is now on the rise again. The latest official figures show that in Buenos Aires and its outskirts, where one-third of the country's population live, poverty rose to 28 percent in October 1996 from 25 percent a year earlier.</p>
<p>Camdessus made clear that despite his calls for action he was not blaming Argentina's reforms for the problems. But trade unions, the Catholic church and the political opposition have intensified their criticism of the government.</p>
<p>The main CGT labor federation this week declared itself &quot;on permanent alert to fight repression and unemployment.&quot;  </p>
<p>The opposition has decried the use of force to put down demonstrations and some of its leaders, including ex-President Raul Alfonsin of the Radical Party, have renewed their calls for an end to the Convertibility law pegging the peso at par to the dollar.</p>
<p>Introduced in 1991, the same year the government launched an ambitious privatization and tariff-cut drive, convertibility has helped bring about a healthy combination of virtually no inflation and strong economic growth, but critics also blame it for the rise in poverty and unemployment.  </p>
<p>Even within Peronist ranks many believe the time has come to losen up the federal purse strings and earmark more funds to tackle social problems. They include powerful Buenos Aires governor and presidential hopeful Eduardo Duhalde, whose wife Hilda leads an army of 17,000 women handing out food to 600,000 poor people every day.</p>
<p>The central government, grappling for answers, has come so far with a mix of promises and muscle flexing.</p>
<p>Promises include a pledge Thursday to devote $770 million in international lending agencies' funds to create 100,000 jobs and grant 120,000 high-school scholarships.  </p>
<p>Shows of force, apart from police action, include Menem's warning Thursday that &quot;unemployment cannot be turned into a matter for agitators and social unrest. This government has the duty to maintain order.&quot;</p>
<p>Mariano Grondona, one of the country's most prominent analysts, asked in an op-ed piece earlier this week: &quot;What are we going to do with the losers in the capitalist competition?&quot;</p>
<p>Calling Duhalde's populist approach &quot;dangerous&quot;, he suggested that private companies should play a bigger role in helping solve Argentina's social problems.</p>
<p>Other analysts agree, saying that unions, individuals, and local governments should look for solutions themselves, and warning against a return to the old days when a bloated state state owned most big firms and ran insurance, health and pension plans, plus transport and public services -- all inefficiently.</p>
<p>&quot;The rules have changed, but many people have not. They still maintain the same mentality, expecting the state to solve all their problems,&quot; pollster Manuel Mora y Araujo said.</p>
<p>(( -- Buenos Aires Newsroom +541 318-0652))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
