<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608943" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chile says it &quot;pointless&quot; to comment on U.S. delay.</title>
<headline>Chile says it &quot;pointless&quot; to comment on U.S. delay.</headline>
<byline>Roger Atwood</byline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chile, next in line to start free trade talks with the United States, said on Friday it was pointless to comment on a new delay in &quot;fast-track&quot; trade negotiating authority until the U.S. Congress passes it.</p>
<p>Sounding exasperated, Foreign Minister Jose Miguel Insulza said the United States was taking much too long to decide whether it would pass the legislation which would open the way to negotiations for Chile to join the North American Free Trade Agreement.</p>
<p>&quot;This has been going on much too long and commenting on it seems to me pointless,&quot; Insulza told reporters. &quot;I am not going to talk about fast track until someone comes and tells me that it has been passed by the American Congress.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Frankly this is an issue I stopped worrying about a long time ago,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton will wait until September to submit legislation to Congress seeking so-called fast track authority to negotiate international trade agreements, the White House said. Perennial NAFTA candidate Chile has been waiting since 1994 for Congress to pass fast track so negotiations can begin.</p>
<p>&quot;They've been telling us that they are deciding whether to do it (vote on fast track) in June or September, but that they'll do it sooner or later,&quot; said Insulza.</p>
<p>Chile's President Eduardo Frei said in a speech on Wednesday that a free trade area stretching from Canada to Chile, which Clinton has said he wants to establish, was &quot;the aspiration of the whole hemisphere.&quot;</p>
<p>Chile, almost alone in South America, has leaned publicly toward the U.S. idea of pushing for a hemispheric free trade agreement including the United States, rather than strengthening the four-nation Mercosur bloc led by Brazil and Argentina.</p>
<p>Chile has an &quot;association agreement&quot; with Mercosur but is not interested in becoming a full member, due to differences with Brazil on tariff policies and because it wants to keep its NAFTA option open.</p>
<p>Officials in Santiago reacted stoically to the new fast-track delay, which means Clinton might not have congressional approval before a trip to Latin America in October.</p>
<p>&quot;I've stopped being surprised by this. It's an issue that doesn't have anything to do with us any more,&quot; said one official, speaking on condition of anonymity.</p>
<p>White House officials had hoped to submit legislation for fast track authority in June but were forced to back away from that timetable after congressional Democrats and Republicans failed to agree on whether environmental and labour issues should be part of the agreement.</p>
<p>Under fast track, Congress gives up its right to amend trade agreements and only would be able to vote for or against the entire treaty.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
