<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608905" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian Duma may postpone sequestration debate.</title>
<headline>Russian Duma may postpone sequestration debate.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The State Duma lower house of parliament, struggling to make sense of government budget cuts and Russian economic growth prospects, is scheduled to vote on Friday on measures which could prolong the budget crisis or hand full responsibility for dealing with it to the government.</p>
<p>The Duma will debate in second and final readings at 11.15 a.m. (0715 GMT) a bill asking the government for more details of promised additional revenues and economic indicators for 1997.</p>
<p>The bill would put off debate on government spending cuts, known as sequestration, until the information is made available. Government officials say such information may not be available until late next month.</p>
<p>First Deputy Finance Minister Vladimir Petrov had been scheduled to speak on the sequestration bill at 11.30 a.m. (0730 GMT), but it was not clear whether the bill seeking additional revenue information would pass or whether Petrov would address the Duma at all on Friday.</p>
<p>The Duma is also scheduled to discuss on Friday a non-binding bill to double money supply, proposed by communist deputies, and another bill proposed by the Duma Budget Committee which would return full control over budget cuts to the government.</p>
<p>Government revenues in the first four months of this year were only 65 percent of budgeted levels. Under the 1997 budget, if revenues falls below 90 percent of budgeted levels in any one quarter the government must propose spending cuts, or sequestration, to the Duma.</p>
<p>The government has proposed cutting planned spending by 108 trillion roubles and raising planned revenues by 30 trillion roubles to deal with the crisis.</p>
<p>Senior officials say the state of public finances means that spending will be cut in any case whatever the Duma decides. Spending in the first four months had already fallen to 70 percent of budgeted levels.</p>
<p>--Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
