<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608998" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ARGENTINA: Maradona to host chat show on Argentine television.</title>
<headline>Maradona to host chat show on Argentine television.</headline>
<dateline>BUENOS AIRES 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Argentine soccer star Diego Maradona is going to fulfil a long held dream by hosting a prime-time television show, the Argentine newspaper Clarin reported on Friday.</p>
<p>Maradona, who has often expressed a wish to try his hand at journalism, will co-host with Mauro Viale, a sensationalist television presenter whose live lunchtime shows are one of Argentina's biggest audience pullers.</p>
<p>The 36-year-old soccer star, who has fallen into disgrace in the sporting world for his drug habit and failure to turn up for training for first-division side Boca Juniors, says he nurtures an ambition to interview Cuban leader Fidel Castro.</p>
<p>&quot;Maradona will have free rein to give his journalistic, sporting and social opinion,&quot; Viale was quoted as saying by Clarin. The prime-time show, to be aired at 8 p.m., will cover all issues for a broad television audience.</p>
<p>Apart from grabbing the headlines for his football skills which in recent years have lost some of their shine, Maradona is already a frequent commentator on television, appearing at least once a week on chat shows.</p>
<p>His relations with journalists have not always been sweet.</p>
<p>Hounded by the press for comments on everything from politics to Argentina's performance in the World Cup, in one 1994 episode he locked himself up at home and took potshots with an air rifle at a pack of journalists outside.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ARG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUENOS AIRES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ARGENTINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
