<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608961" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CUBA: Cuba's Communists defend one-party socialist system.</title>
<headline>Cuba's Communists defend one-party socialist system.</headline>
<byline>Frances Kerry</byline>
<dateline>HAVANA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cuba's ruling Communist Party, preparing for a congress in October that will chart the country's future, has urged citizens to unite behind the one-party socialist system as an indispensable pillar of the island's independence.</p>
<p>The stark appeal is made in an eight-page document to be debated over the coming weeks by party members and citizens and submitted for approval at the Fifth Party Congress on Oct. 8-10.</p>
<p>The paper, dwelling at length on historical reasons for the one-party system, makes plain that at least at the leadership level, President Fidel Castro's party is not planning major political changes as it prepares for the year 2000 and beyond.</p>
<p>&quot;In Cuba there will be no return of capitalism because the Revolution will never be vanquished,&quot; the document says. &quot;The nation will continue alive and will continue socialist.&quot;</p>
<p>The document, to be published in full on Saturday by the party newspaper Granma, was available to some Cubans on Friday. It is due to be discussed nationwide from June 1-July 15.</p>
<p>The document argues that patriotism and defence of the system are one and the same thing and that the United States is poised to gobble its small neighbour up.</p>
<p>&quot;For Cubans, an independent nation, genuine democracy and socialism are unbreakably unified,&quot; it says. &quot;Socialism in Cuba is an organic part of its historic process.&quot;</p>
<p>The document, which will be a focal point of a congress steering party strategy for the next five years, is strikingly lacking in references to the future.</p>
<p>It traces a line from the 30-year struggle for independence from Spain in 1898, what is viewed as the subsequent U.S. neo-colonialist era up to Castro's 1959 revolution and Washington's constant pressure since then for change.</p>
<p>The United States, which last year tightened its 35-year economic embargo on the island with the so-called Helms-Burton law, is a greater threat than ever, it says. Washington publicly seeks to &quot;liquidate the Cuban nation and enslave its people,&quot; the document says.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a terrible threat for future generations,&quot; it says, adding Cubans will have to &quot;strengthen our unity and will to resist.&quot;</p>
<p>The October congress will be the first Cuba has held since October 1991, when the island stood on the brink of economic crisis triggered by the collapse of its old economic and political ally, the former Soviet Union.</p>
<p>At the height of that crisis, from 1993 onward, Castro's government undertook modest economic reforms. Measures such as the legalisation of hard currency and authorisation of some private enterprise have led to huge social changes, including previously unseen wealth disparities among Cuba's 11 million people.</p>
<p>But, mindful of the snowball effect of 1980s Soviet reforms, the 70-year-old Castro has made increasingly clear he does not view Cuba on the road to capitalism.</p>
<p>The document accuses the country's small and illegal dissident groups of being in the pay of foreigners and wanting &quot;the return of the U.S. yoke and the return of capitalism.&quot;</p>
<p>It urges citizens to counter &quot;illegalities&quot; that have emerged as a result of economic changes and battle against corruption and crime. Socialist values are also harmed by &quot;fascination for and the frivolous cult of Yankee symbols,&quot; it says.</p>
<p>The Cuban Communist Party (PCC) is constitutionally the only legal party in Cuba. According to the document, it currently has 770,000 members, alongside some 500,000 members of the Union of Youth Communists.</p>
<p>Opposition is banned and freedom of expression and association are broadly limited to support of the system. The media is state-controlled and the island's dissident groups face arrest or jail for their activities.</p>
<p>The party document pours scorn on Western democratic models and in particular the U.S. system. It defends democracy and human rights in Cuba by listing improvements in social conditions since 1959 -- particularly in the provision of free education and health care for all, and improved conditions for women and blacks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAVANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CUBA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
