<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608907" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: Thomson BankWatch sets ratings for Latvian Parekss.</title>
<headline>Thomson BankWatch sets ratings for Latvian Parekss.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thomson BankWatch said on Friday that it had assigned short-term and long-term debt ratings to Latvia's largest bank, Parekss Bank.</p>
<p>The rating agency said in a statement that it assigned Parekss an LC-2 for its short-term local currency debt and and a senior debt rating of BB+.</p>
<p>&quot;As one of Latvia's most significant banks, Parekss continues to benefit from the flight to quality and has diversified into a more universal bank,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;The number of borrowers grew by three fold during 1996 and by end-1996 its market share of loans was the highest (in Latvia) at 27 percent,&quot; Thomson said.</p>
<p>&quot;Asset quality is satisfactory...capital is considered strong and Parekss continues to have the highest returns (in Latvia),&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;The ratings reflect Parekss' overall satisfactory financial condition and its position in the Latvian market. The long-term senior debt rating is equivalent to BankWatch's sovereign ceiling,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>Thomson has been active in the Baltic region and has assigned ratings to Lithuania's leading private commercial banks, Vilniaus Bank and Hermis Bank.</p>
<p>The banking sectors in both countries have recovered from serious crises.</p>
<p>Thomson also said recently that it planned to assign ratings to Estonia's top banks.</p>
<p>-- Ed Stoddard, Riga newsroom +371 721 52 40</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
