<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608922" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONDURAS: North and Central America port conditions - Lloyds.</title>
<headline>North and Central America port conditions - Lloyds.</headline>
<text>
<p>Port conditions from Lloyds Shipping Intelligence Service --</p>
<p>HONDURAS, May 19 - Puerto Cortes - Vessels berthed - 4 discharging/loading containers, 1 discharging fertiliser, 1 discharging fuel. Vessels awaiting berth, 4 discharging/loading containers, 1 discharging wheat, 1 discharging fuel, 2 discharging asphalt. Vessels due, 5 to discharge bananas, 6 to load/discharge containers, 1 to discharge rice, 1 to load sugar, 1 to discharge fertiliser.</p>
<p>MEXICO, May 20 - Tampico - vessels in port - 1 corn, 1 general cargo, 1 pipes, 2 mineral, 1 cement.</p>
<p>Altamira - vessels in port - 1 repairs, 1 chemicals.</p>
<p>Veracruz - vessels in port - 3 containers, 3 sugar, 1 steel coils, 3 corn, 2 grain.</p>
<p>Manzanillo - vessels in port - 3 containers, 2 general cargo, 1 urea, 2 grain.</p>
<p>Coatzacoalcos - vessels in port - 7 chemicals, 10 oil tankers, 1 repairs. All ports working normally.</p>
<p>PANAMA, May 19 - Cristobal - four vessels due to work cargo.</p>
<p>Balboa - six vessels due today to work cargo.</p>
<p>Panama Canal - waterway working at full capacity. Delays of 2-3 days for vessels over 91 ft. beam and 1-2 days for vessels under 91 ft. beam. The following locks lanes outages are confirmed - 7/7 to 19/7 and 11/8 to 21/8 - simultaneous Miraflores and Gatun with projected daily transits of 28-30 vessels. During these periods, delays could reach 5 or 6 days, depending on ship arrivals. Single lane outage Miraflores from 11/8 to 21/8 and 28-29/8. Projected daily transits of 32 to 34 vessels. Thirty-four vessels due, 61 in queue, 13 booked, 37 scheduled. Conditions 18/5 - actual arrivals 43, transits 42. Average of booked and non-booked canal waters time 46.5 hours.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONDURAS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
