<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608918" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: FEATURE-Croatia's future hangs on treatment of minority Serbs.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Croatia's future hangs on treatment of minority Serbs.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Smith</byline>
<dateline>BJELOVAC, Croatia 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four friends sat around a kitchen table in a dilapidated farmhouse in central Croatia telling their visitor how an angry Croat mob threatened to burn their children alive last week.</p>
<p>The friends, a Croat married to a Moslem and a Serb married to a Croat, cried as they told U.S. Ambassador Peter Galbraith about the attack by Bosnian Croat war refugees resettled in Croatia that happened on the day the two couples returned to the houses they own.</p>
<p>The riot was a worrying sign for the Croatian government which has agreed under international pressure to return tens of thousands of displaced Serbs to former homes in Croatia in the next few months.</p>
<p>But it is also a clear symbol of the bitterness of refugees and the inherent problems of trying to get people to live with their former enemies in areas where memories of war are fresh.</p>
<p>The long, low farmhouse with green-painted balconies and an old stone well in the garden outside has always been home to Dragan Banadinovic's parents.</p>
<p>He and his wife Fikreta, who continued to live in the region under rebel Serb rule in 1991-95, came back to their home nearby last week and their friends Milan and Ljerka Icitovic to a house just down the road.</p>
<p>Their return was legal, but unannounced, igniting the tempers of Bosnian Croats, recently resettled here but nervous about a pending repatriation of Serbs whose rebel fighters seized the Krajina region after Croatia seceded from Yugoslavia in 1991, forcing local Croats into exile.</p>
<p>Rumours were then spread about the imminent return of busloads of Serbs, provoking the rampage.</p>
<p>Up to 200,000 Serbs fled when the Croatian army recaptured the separatist Krajina enclave in the summer of 1995. Some 60,000 of them settled in the last Serb area, Eastern Slavonia, whose U.N. administrators will hand it back to Croatian state rule this summer.</p>
<p>Croatia now wants to return some 80,000 of its own refugees to Eastern Slavonia from where they were expelled in 1991 by Serbs who opposed Croatia's breakaway from federal Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>CROATIAN SAFETY GUARANTEES NOT HONOURED ON GROUND</p>
<p>Zagreb has guaranteed safety to Serbs wishing to go back home. But the reality on the ground is sometimes very different.</p>
<p>Galbraith had gone to see three villages around the town of Kostajnica, which lies on the Una river that divides Croatia from Bosnia, where the Bosnian Croat refugees ran riot.</p>
<p>He took the trip after ramming home the message at a news conference in Zagreb that Croatia would not win entry to Western institutions unless it allowed all displaced minority Serbs to return home and live in safety.</p>
<p>Dragan Banadinovic, an ethnic Croat, and his Moslem wife Fikreta fled Krajina for their lives in 1995. He had served with Serb forces in nearby Bosnia to avoid being expelled from his home by Serbs and so had to flee the advancing Croatian army.</p>
<p>The night they returned to Bjelovac, the mob paid a house call.</p>
<p>&quot;People gathered up our stuff from the van and burned all our things, our clothes, our shoes. They started beating people with iron bars,&quot; Dragan told Galbraith. Then he pointed to his neck, back and head where he was beaten.</p>
<p>He said there were more than 100 people and he had felt sure his life was in danger. &quot;The children started to cry, my wife was screaming, I don't know how it all stopped. They were putting dirt in my mouth and the women were beaten.</p>
<p>&quot;The children were in the basement and they (the mob) said they should stay there and the house would be burned. She went to get the children out, then the mob destroyed the basement.&quot;</p>
<p>Fikreta said her children watched while she was beaten and threatened.</p>
<p>Outside in the yard the family pig glanced over the fence from the neighbouring field in a deceptively idyllic valley with a carpet of buttercups.</p>
<p>&quot;They beat our mum and dad. I was scared but I didn't say anything,&quot; said 11-year-old Davor.</p>
<p>TACK 'STAR OF DAVID' TO OUR SHOULDER, ONE SERB SAYS BITTERLY</p>
<p>Milan Icitovic, a Serb married to a Croat, was bitter.</p>
<p>&quot;If those people (Bosnian Croats) stay, we can't live here. I don't now where we'd live. The only thing that remains here for us is just to put the Star of David on our shoulder,&quot; he said, referring to the emblem of opprobrium which Jews under Nazi German rule were forced to wear.</p>
<p>Galbraith told the families he had come for three reasons. &quot;To hear from you what happened, to see what the Croatian government is going to do to protect you and to find out what is being done to prosecute the sons of bitches who did this.&quot;</p>
<p>Local Croat leaders told Galbraith they would respect the right of Serbs to return but insisted it should be done with the cooperation of local police and officials and managed by the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.</p>
<p>A few hundred Serbs have been returned peacefully to the region with the help of the United Nations and remain there.</p>
<p>Djuro Brodarac, the county prefect, said the Kostajnica area was the most damaged Croatian region of the war. The Croat Roman Catholic church lies in ruins and houses on the north -- Croatian -- bank of the Una river stand witness to constant Serb bombardment.</p>
<p>Describing the people he met as a &quot;microcosm&quot; of ethnic minority problems in Croatia, Galbraith said:</p>
<p>&quot;I hope people like you will stay because you represent on a personal basis the ideal of pluralism, that people in a democratic country can live together without regard to their ethnicity.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is no place for people like you in Croatia, then it will not have a future as a democratic country or a part of the West.&quot;</p>
<p>Senior Croatian officials visited Washington last week and held intensive talks with Secretary of State Madeleine Albright, who scolded Foreign Minister Mate Granic over Croatia's treatment of Serbs and other peace accord violations.</p>
<p>Granic later challenged the U.S. State Department's description of the meeting and said the two had agreed on &quot;more than 90 percent&quot; of the issues they discussed. But Galbraith said U.S. policy towards Zagreb is &quot;unambiguous and clear&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it is clear that from the response from national and local government, that Secretary Albright's message has been heard, though it remains to be seen whether it is being implemented on the ground,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;There are certain things Croatia must do if it is to join the family of Western nations and those things include accepting the return of Croatian Serbs to all parts of Croatia and creating conditions of security.</p>
<p>&quot;You could say the right of return is the cornerstone of peace in former Yugoslavia.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BJELOVAC, Croatia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
