<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608924" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>VENEZUELA: U.S. praises Venezuela for drug lord extradition.</title>
<headline>U.S. praises Venezuela for drug lord extradition.</headline>
<byline>Maria Jose Gonzalez</byline>
<dateline>CARACAS 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States congratulated Venezuela on Thursday for its decision to extradite one of the last suspected Colombian drug lords not behind bars.</p>
<p>&quot;The decision is an important symbol of the cooperation between the United States and Venezuela against the common enemy of drug trafficking,&quot; Attorney General Janet Reno said in a statement distributed by the U.S. Embassy in Caracas.</p>
<p>Venezuela's Supreme Court ruled earlier on Thursday that suspected Colombian drug kingpin Justo Pastor Perafan should be extradited to the United States where he faces drug trafficking and possession charges in New York.</p>
<p>Venezuela's Foreign Minister, Miguel Angel Burelli Rivas, said it would probably take a couple of days to process the necessary documentation for the extradition.</p>
<p>Perafan, 50, who was using an alias and had undergone plastic surgery and hair implants to change his appearance, was captured in April by Venezuelan authorities in the western town of San Cristobal, across the border from Colombia.</p>
<p>&quot;We congratulate the Venezuelan government for the arrest and decision to extradite Perafan who is accused of being responsible for smuggling more than 30 tons of drugs to the United States,&quot; Reno said.</p>
<p>Believed to possess a personal fortune of $12 billion, Perafan was said to be the last Colombian drug lord not in jail or dead. He was to be handed over to a New York state court.</p>
<p>&quot;(The decision) underlines that the fight against (drug) traffickers is one which cuts across borders,&quot; U.S. Ambassador John Maisto told reporters.</p>
<p>Perafan, a former baker of humble origins, had asked to be sent back to Colombia, which had also lodged an extradition request with Venezuela.</p>
<p>But many legal experts and Colombia's police chief, Gen. Rosso Jose Serrano, said he would face a tougher sentence in the United States.</p>
<p>Colombian officials said they would not challenge Venezuela's decision. &quot;We respect and comply with the decision which has been taken regarding this case,&quot; Colombia's Foreign Minister Maria Emma Mejia said in Bogota.</p>
<p>Perafan's lawyer, Hugo Moreno, said he was confident that the U.S. judicial system would treat Perafan fairly.</p>
<p>&quot;I am sure that Justo Perafan will be able to prove his innocence in the United States,&quot; Moreno said.</p>
<p>Perafan faces eight charges in the New York state court but under the terms of the Venezuelan-U.S. extradition treaty cannot be sentenced to a term greater than Venezuela's maximum sentence of 30 years.</p>
<p>The decision to extradite Perafan came as Colombia's Senate approved a bill to partially restore extradition treaties with the United States for drug traffickers and other criminals.</p>
<p>Colombia suspended extraditions in 1991 under pressure from a wave of violence by drug cartels opposed to the measure.</p>
<p>The extradition bill still faces six legislative hurdles and critics said it had been watered down so much that it was ineffective.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CARACAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VENEZUELA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
