<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608979" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: In Brazil, search is on for shooting-spree victims.</title>
<headline>In Brazil, search is on for shooting-spree victims.</headline>
<byline>Simona de Logu</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police said they were searching on Friday for more victims of the former soldier who ran amok in a small town in northeastern Brazil, killing at least 17 people before dying in a shootout.</p>
<p>&quot;All we know is that he killed a lot of people, at least 17, but there could be more,&quot; a police spokesman said. &quot;Officers took up the search again this morning.&quot;</p>
<p>Genildo Ferreira de Franca, armed with two automatic weapons and a handgun, started his shooting spree on Wednesday afternoon, killing a taxi driver he suspected of being the lover of his former wife, the spokesman said.</p>
<p>The 27-year-old ex-soldier, who left the armed forces five years ago, was wearing a military camouflage uniform and a bulletproof vest.</p>
<p>He then drove the taxi of his first victim through the streets of Sao Goncalo do Amarante, in Rio Grande do Norte state, until midday on Thursday, armed with a hit list. He shot to death at least another 16 people, including his former wife, his former in-laws, his current wife and his mother-in-law. Three people were injured.</p>
<p>&quot;Ferreira heard his (former) wife was having an affair and that people were saying he was homosexual. That's when he went crazy and just started shooting,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Ferreira left a letter listing 25 people he wanted to kill and giving some indication of his motives.</p>
<p>&quot;This was a premeditated crime,&quot; the mayor of the town of 65,000 people, Francisco Potiguar Cavalcanti Jr., told Reuters. &quot;We consider this an isolated case. Our town is a town of peace. The mood here is of sadness and consternation.&quot;</p>
<p>Sao Goncalo do Amarante is 1,550 miles (2,500 km) northeast of the capital, Brasilia.</p>
<p>Ferreira took two hostages, his 5-year-old daughter and a 16-year-old girl police suspect of being an accomplice in the killings.</p>
<p>&quot;She was with him the whole time and was carrying the ammunition. They were both on drugs,&quot; the police spokesman said. &quot;We believe she may have been helping him and are still questioning her.&quot;</p>
<p>A former friend and colleague of Ferreira's, who identified himself only as Genival, told Reuters that Ferreira had been threatening to kill 25 people since his son died a year ago.</p>
<p>&quot;He used to be a calm kind of guy, but ever since his son was run over by a car, he became a bit strange,&quot; Genival said.</p>
<p>Ferreira, who was finally cornered by 200 police officers in a ceramic tile factory, where he was hiding with his hostages, died in the ensuing gunfight. The hostages were unharmed.</p>
<p>It was not clear whether Ferreira committed suicide or whether police killed him. The 16-year-old hostage said Ferreira had shot himself before police riddled his body with bullets.</p>
<p>Genival said that three months ago, Ferreira went to buy a coffin, telling the undertaker he was going to commit suicide.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
