<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608930" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chileans fly over German enclave, no sign of fugitive.</title>
<headline>Chileans fly over German enclave, no sign of fugitive.</headline>
<dateline>PARRAL, Chile 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police took their inspections of a secretive German colony in southern Chile to the air on Friday as a police helicopter overflew the community, while others on horseback looked for traces of the colony's fugitive leader Paul Schaefer.</p>
<p>A helicopter with the green-and-white colours of Chile's Carabineros police force overflew Colonia Dignidad (Dignity Colony) for several minutes, after police in convoys of trucks and vans inspected the colony three times this week.</p>
<p>Officers on horseback inspected the periphery of the German enclave, set among scenic Andean foothills among traditional Bavarian-style homes, tidy farms and electrified fences.</p>
<p>Police say they are seaching for Schaefer, the colony's founder who faces a long list of charges including sexually abusing boys at a boarding school in the colony, illegal detention of children and obstruction of justice.</p>
<p>Schaefer has refused to surrender to police, and his followers issued a letter on Wednesday saying he was not inside the sprawling settlement and would sooner commit suicide than give up.</p>
<p>Some of the colony's 300 German-speaking residents and Chilean supporters held a vigil outside the colony's barbed-wire gates on Thursday night, carrying candles and signing hymns in German and Spanish.</p>
<p>&quot;We are sure that the goal of this persecution is to close our hospital and the social good works that we have thanks to Dignidad,&quot; said Olalia Vera, one of the demonstrators.</p>
<p>The colony's modern hospital is open only to people who support Colonia Dignidad, effectively buying the support of many of local farmworkers and peasants, say Chilean journalists who have written about the colony.</p>
<p>Other supporters of the colony have been raising their voices in the last couple of days.</p>
<p>A rightist Chilean congressman, Hernan Larrain, offered on Friday to mediate between Schaefer and authorities with the aim of persuading Schaefer to surrender.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm afraid this situation has grown very dangerous for Dignidad and that if it continues, it could decide to leave the country and that would be very negative,&quot; he told reporters in the nearby town of Parral, about 320 km (200 miles) south of Santiago.</p>
<p>Schaefer issued a statement from hiding last week saying he feared for his life if he surrendered to police and alleging he could not get a fair trial in Chile.</p>
<p>Residents, who have acquiesced at the police incursions, say Schaefer has not been seen for months in the colony and that police are wasting their time looking for him.</p>
<p>Schaefer, believed to be about 80, founded the colony in about 1960 after fleeing German where he was charged with molesting boys at an orphanage he founded.</p>
<p>The parents of at least five boys in their early teens who attended a boarding school in the colony filed charges of sexual abuse and illegal detention of the children against Schaefer and other colony authorities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARRAL, Chile"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
