<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608960" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peru sees IMF reviewing economic aims by July.</title>
<headline>Peru sees IMF reviewing economic aims by July.</headline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) is likely to review by early July Peru's 1997 economic policies that forecast an improved set of indicators, Central Reserve Bank President German Suarez said Friday.</p>
<p>Peru is set to send the IMF &quot;soon&quot; the final draft of a provisional letter of intent -- published for public debate last week -- that outlines its 1997 targets, Suarez told reporters at a central bank seminar on the financial system.  </p>
<p>The IMF has to approve these goals because they form part of a three-year economic program that the government is implementing in return for multilateral loans from the IMF, World Bank and International Development Bank (IADB).</p>
<p>&quot;It is going to be sent soon.  Once the IMF receives the letter with our macroeconomic policies ... the fund will discuss it at the end of June or beginning of July,&quot; Suarez said.</p>
<p>The global IMF-approved program aims to create sustained growth, control inflation and privatize most assets in the mining, oil, fishing industries.</p>
<p>The 1997 letter of intent -- expected to recieve rubber- stamp approval from the IMF -- reiterated the government's goals to achieve five percent growth this year, up from 2.8 percent last year.</p>
<p>The letter also stated the aim to reduce inflation to between eight and 10 percent from 11.8 percent in 1996 and lower the current account deficit in 1997 to less than 5.5 percent of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) from last year's 5.8 percent.</p>
<p>((-- Marco Aquino, Lima newsroom, 511 221-2134))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
