<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608945" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil shrs end up, trade weak before U.S. holiday.</title>
<headline>Brazil shrs end up, trade weak before U.S. holiday.</headline>
<dateline>SAO PAULO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazilian stocks closed mildly higher led by rises in power shares but trade was weak amid an absence of foreign investors ahead of Monday's Memorial Day holiday in the United States, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was dead. There was no news and it seems a lot of people in New York left early for the holiday weekend,&quot; said one local broker.</p>
<p>The Sao Paulo bourse's Bovespa index of 48 most-traded shares ended up 0.17 percent at 10,764 points on volume valued at 552.7 million reais ($521 million).  </p>
<p>Brokers said volume was down from recent daily averages as many foreign investors were absent from the session, apparently having taken off early for the long holiday in the United States.</p>
<p>Markets are closed on Monday both in the U.S. and Britain.</p>
<p>The bolsa's rise was led by increases in electrical sector stocks, with the bolsa's Electrical Energy Index up 1.82 percent at 2,829 points.</p>
<p>Among rising power issues was blue-chip Eletrobras preferred B, which ended 1.38 percent higher at 513.00 reais, and Minas Gerais state's Cemig preferred, which closed up 0.63 percent at 47.80 reais.  </p>
<p>Trade was dominated by leading blue-chip Telebras, whose benchmark preferred closed 0.36 percent higher at 137.50 reais, while its common shares ended 0.39 percent down at 128.00 reais.</p>
<p>Telebras regularly accounts for 60 to 65 percent of trade on the Sao Paulo bourse.</p>
<p>Among other top blue chips, recently privatized miner Cia Vale do Rio Doce dropped 1.2 percent to end at 24.60 reais.</p>
<p>Petrobras' preferred declined after Friday's sale of one billion shares on the Rio de Janeiro bolsa for 240.99 million reais ($225.22 million), or 240.99 reais per lot of 1,000 shares.</p>
<p>&quot;The price was slightly below the price it was already trading at,&quot; a dealer said. The issue closed down 1.22 percent at 242.00 reais in Sao Paulo.</p>
<p>((--James Craig, Sao Paulo newsroom 5511 2485413))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAO PAULO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
