<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="608980" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Ex-drug warrior accuses Mexico defense officials.</title>
<headline>Ex-drug warrior accuses Mexico defense officials.</headline>
<dateline>GUADALAJARA, Mexico 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico's disgraced drug-fighting general Jesus Gutierrez Rebollo has accused top military officials of protecting the country's most notorious drug lord, newspaper Reforma said on Friday.</p>
<p>Allegations of drug corruption at the highest level of Mexico's armed forces emerged as part of the jailed general's defence in court on charges he himself had taken bribes from the cocaine baron, Amado Carrillo Fuentes.</p>
<p>&quot;(It) is evident that complicity with Amando Carillo came from the ranks of the Defence Ministry,&quot; the paper quoted Gutierrez Rebollo as saying.</p>
<p>Gutierrez Rebollo was fired as chief of Mexico's now defunct National Institute for the Combat of Drugs (INCD) in February, deeply embarrassing the Mexican government amid pressure from Washington to stem the flow of illegal drugs across the U.S.-Mexican border.</p>
<p>Carillo Fuentes, described by the U.S. Drug Enforcement Agency (DEA) as the most powerful man in the Mexican drug trade, is the subject of at least 26 separate DEA investigations and has been a fugitive for eight years.</p>
<p>He escaped arrest in January this year when police and the army bungled an attempt to capture him at a family wedding, and an army major was blamed for tipping off the drug kingpin.</p>
<p>But Gutierrez Rebollo said in his testimony, extracts of which appeared on Reforma's front page, that the major was not senior enough to have known of the operation in advance, adding that his superiors were the ones who helped Carrillo escape.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of his rank and place of commission (the major) could not have had any direct knowledge of an operation of such importance,&quot; Reforma quoted Gutierrez Rebollo as saying.</p>
<p>The INCD was scrapped in February and since replaced with a 60-strong team of specially trained agents known as the Special Prosecutor's Office for Crimes Against Health.</p>
<p>Gutierrez Rebollo also said he kept Defence Minister Enrique Cervantes and the attorney general informed of his anti-narcotics efforts, according to Reforma.</p>
<p>As proof of this cooperation, he cited his handing over of Alejandro Hodoyan Palacio, an arms trafficker for the so-called Tijuana cartel, to the DEA as a protected witness.</p>
<p>Gutierrez Rebollo said Hodoyan Palacio revealed the names of a number of high-ranking Mexican officials in the pay of the cartel, run by the Arrellano Felix brothers and based in the north of the country.</p>
<p>He said Mexican defence chief Cervantes and the attorney general had both been informed of the names. He also asked the DEA to make the report public.</p>
<p>Friday's allegations come a day after the paper cited a key witness in the Rebollo case denouncing two generals and the private secretary of former president Carlos Salinas de Gortari for having links with Carillo Fuentes.</p>
<p>But on Friday Salinas, who is living in self-imposed exile in Ireland, lept to the defence of the army, insisting in a letter to Reforma that the armed forces' record was unstained by the recent scandals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GUADALAJARA, Mexico"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
