<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609047" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asian crudes steady, two-tier market for Minas.</title>
<headline>Asian crudes steady, two-tier market for Minas.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The heavy sweet Asian crude market saw little change, but a two tier market developed amid thin demand as June sellers continued to outnumber buyers.</p>
<p>Shosha with June barrels were aggressive, selling at lower premiums to Japanese refiners to dispose of barrels. But western traders were holding out for stronger prices.</p>
<p>A trader sold June Minas to China this week at ICP +25 cents.</p>
<p>This compared with ICP +15 cents that a Japanese refiner paid for its barrels on Wednesday and the ICP +17 cts that an Indonesian affiliate achieved for its Minas trade to a shosha.  </p>
<p>Offers of Thevenard Island and North West Shelf condensate by Australian refiners for June were keeping the light Asian grades under pressure.</p>
<p>But North West Shelf demand in July could increase, due to a shortage of Indonesia's Arun condensate, traders said.</p>
<p>Indonesia did not allocate any Arun condensate to its affiliates for June exports. Traders attributed this to the start-up of a new condensate splitter in Indonesia.  </p>
<p>The tighter outlook for condensate spot supplies has supported North West Shelf condensate levels, with July cargoes expected to trade around Arun APPI +50 cts for July cargoes. In Middle East trade, A July Oman was rumoured sold by a South Korean refiner to China at MPM -10 cts. The trade could not be confirmed, but traders thought the level was a fair reflection of the July Oman market.</p>
<p>Lighter crudes from Abu Dhabi and Qatar are expected to start trading at wider discounts, as Japanese refiners have high inventory stocks of middle distillates.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
