<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609029" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>Australia: Chinese vice premier Zhu Rongji praises Australia.</title>
<headline>Chinese vice premier Zhu Rongji praises Australia.</headline>
<dateline>PERTH, Australia 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chinese vice-premier and economic tsar Zhu Rongji arrived in Australia on Friday for a landmark visit to cement improved ties and reward Canberra for an easing of its stand on human rights in China.</p>
<p>On arrival in Perth, Zhu issued a statement praising Australia as an important player in the Asia-Pacific region and said a strong Sino-Australia relationship would foster regional peace and stability.</p>
<p>&quot;It (Australia) plays an important role in international and regional affairs,&quot; said Zhu, adding the recent visit of Australian Prime Minister John Howard to Beijing had advanced bilateral relations.</p>
<p>&quot;This not only serves the fundamental interests of our two peoples but also conduces to promoting regional peace, stability and prosperity,&quot; Zhu said.</p>
<p>Australia-China relations chilled last year with a series of diplomatic and security spats and Australian officials said Zhu's week-long visit would not only focus on trade and investment, but repairing bilateral relations.</p>
<p>Zhu is the most senior Chinese official to visit Australia since National People's Congress chairman Qiao Shi in 1994.</p>
<p>He told Beijing-based Australian journalists this week his trip, which replaces a cancelled European tour, was a payback for Australia abandoning a U.N. resolution censuring China over its human rights record.</p>
<p>&quot;You can see Australia this time really acted very good on the human rights question,&quot; Zhu quoted Premier Li Peng as telling him.</p>
<p>Announcing Australia's decision not to co-sponsor the U.N. resolution, Foreign Minister Alexander Downer said last month the two countries had agreed to set up a formal human rights dialogue.</p>
<p>Australian officials said Canberra would push for an early start to the unscheduled dialogue when Zhu is in Canberra early next week. Downer said on Wednesday that he would also raise human rights issues in his meeting with Zhu.</p>
<p>Zhu's Australian tour replaces a planned visit to Austria, Ireland, Luxembourg and the Netherlands which Beijing-based Australian media quoted Zhu as saying was cancelled because of those countries' support for the U.N. motion.</p>
<p>Zhu heads a delegation which includes leading business people and 10 officials of at least vice-ministerial rank.</p>
<p>Australian officials said Zhu, credited with China's rapid economic growth and a key force in the restructuring of state businesses, will discuss a range of economic and business issues, including a proposed A$500 million (US$390 million) reduced iron project in Western Australia state and wool quotas.</p>
<p>China is Australia's fifth largest trading partner, with two-way trade worth A$8.0 billion in calendar 1996.</p>
<p>Trade is growing about 20 percent a year and China is projected to move to Australia's number two trading partner, behind Japan, by 2005.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$0.78)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PERTH, Australia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
