<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609055" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai finance merger collapse may trigger share slump.</title>
<headline>Thai finance merger collapse may trigger share slump.</headline>
<byline>Vithoon Amorn</byline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The collapse of the biggest merger ever planned in Thailand's finance sector may trigger further heavy selling on the country's battered stock market next week, brokers said on Friday. News that the planned merger between Thai Danu Bank Plc and Finance One Plc had collapsed hit the stock market just before the market close on Friday, sparing shares from bigger losses, brokers said.</p>
<p>The composite SET index barely moved on Friday, closing 0.26 point lower at 581.13 on sluggish 3.2 billion baht turnover.</p>
<p>But brokers said selling could be heavy on Monday if investors interpret the collapse as a sign that the country was sliding deeper into an economic morass.</p>
<p>Finance One and Thai Danu on Friday announced they decided to end two-month merger talks as the weak Thai economy and complicated legal and tax issues made their proposed alliance unfeasible and too time consuming.</p>
<p>Cash-strapped Finance One Plc, Thailand's largest finance company, indicated at a news conference that it had not found a new potential partner to replace Thai Danu, which ranks 11th among Thailand's 15 commercial banks.</p>
<p>Analysts said the government was concerned that the collapse of the Thai Danu-Finance One talks could shake public confidence in the stability of Thailand's 91 finance companies which are mostly heavily exposed to the troubled Thai property sector.</p>
<p>The Thai property sector is in its fourth year of severe slump with no immediate recovery in sight.</p>
<p>Stockbrokers said only two factors could avert a sharp sell off on Monday -- new monetary measures from the government and an interest rate cut soon by the Thai central bank.</p>
<p>Bank of Thailand deputy governor Chaiyawat Wibulswasdi said on Friday the central bank would call a press conference at 11.00 am (0400 GMT) on Monday to announce new monetary measures.</p>
<p>He declined to eraborate what measures the bank plans to announce but some analysts expected the new measures to be related to the abortive merger between Finance One and Danu.</p>
<p>The battered Thai bourse has been hammered to its lowest levels in nearly eight years in the past few weeks on a combination of bad news, an attack on the baht currency and a poor outlook for the once-booming economy.</p>
<p>It clawed back 3.6 percent this week partly with the help of a government announcement that commercial banks would pool a 50 billion baht ($1.9 billion) market support fund for buying blue-chip stocks.</p>
<p>Two sets of export figures were also announced by different agencies on Monday and although the numbers varied both sets showed growth over last year.</p>
<p>Investors remain disappointed, however, that the Bank of Thailand had failed to cut its discount rate, a move waited by the market as a signal for commercial banks to reduce their lending rates, currently among the highest in Asia.</p>
<p>The discount rate is the interest rate charged to commercial banks on loans from the Bank of Thailand. It currently stands at 10.50 percent and was last cut on March 1, 1995.</p>
<p>A finance ministry official was quoted by a newspaper on Tuesday as saying the central bank would announce a one percentage point reduction in its discount rate on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But the speculation proved groundless and the central bank governor later said he did not foresee an easing until early June.</p>
<p>Private bankers have said that with a lower discount rate, they could reduce lending rates, currently averaging 13.25 percent, by at least 50 basis points in the next few months to help spur cash-strapped business.</p>
<p>Analysts said the Bank of Thailand is in a policy dilemma over cutting interest rates, torn between a government push for economic recovery and a need to defend the baht.</p>
<p>Fears of a capital flight and the threat of attacks on the baht, which could remain as long as investors had doubts about Thai economic fundamentals, would force the central bank to take a cautious stance on rates despite finance ministry pressure for cuts, they said.</p>
<p>Deputy central bank governor Jaroong Nookhwun said on Friday the Bank of Thailand was prepared to contain any damage that the finance sector may face from the collapse of the Thai Danu-Finance One merger plan. He did not elaborate.</p>
<p>Broker said Finance One's troubles, including its huge 3.75 billion baht first quarter loss and plunging assets, could renew market concern about the stability of Thailand's 91 finance companies which had been weakened by a slowing economy and ailing property and capital markets in the past few years.</p>
<p>($1 = 26 baht)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
