<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609068" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila mills seen shying away from wheat market.</title>
<headline>Manila mills seen shying away from wheat market.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippine mills are expected to move out of the world wheat market next week as strong demand from Pakistan threatens to boost prices, local executives and grains traders said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody from Manila will dare compete with Pakistan next week,&quot; an official at one of the country's largest flour mills told Reuters.</p>
<p>Pakistan had said it will seek 376,000 tonnes of U.S. or Australian white wheat on May 28.</p>
<p>Traders said Philippine mills still require at least 23,000 tonnes of wheat for June shipment.</p>
<p>Last week they bought 63,000 tonnes of U.S. and Canadian wheat.</p>
<p>Only one mill shopped for wheat this week, traders said.</p>
<p>On Thursday, a mill bought 7,500 tonnes of western white wheat for August shipment.</p>
<p>Traders said importers of rice, soymeal and soybeans would also remain on the sidelines as supplies were ample.</p>
<p>Corn suppliers were waiting to see whether or not Manila would tender for at least 300,000 tonnes of yellow corn before July this year, they said.</p>
<p>Prevailing flour and corn prices in Manila in pesos-</p>
<p>						May 23	   May 16</p>
<p> Hard flour wheat per 25 kg	     290		290</p>
<p> Soft flour wheat per 25 kg	     260		260</p>
<p> Retail price of yellow corn per kg   9.59	     9.67</p>
<p> Retail price of white corn per kg    9.61	     9.85</p>
<p>--Manila Newsroom (63 2) 841-8936, Fax 817-6267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
