<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609023" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GUATEMALA: Guatemala must solve case of missing rebel - URNG.</title>
<headline>Guatemala must solve case of missing rebel - URNG.</headline>
<byline>Lorraine Orlandi</byline>
<dateline>GUATEMALA CITY 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leaders of Guatemala's former rebel army said on Thursday the case of a missing rebel commander allegedly killed by government security forces threatened the country's fledgling peace.</p>
<p>The Guatemalan National Revolutionary Unit (URNG) urged the government to solve the case of Jose Juan Cabrera Rodas, known as Commander Mincho.</p>
<p>Cabrera went missing last year just before both sides signed a peace accord ending 36 years of civil war.</p>
<p>&quot;The peace process could be damaged if the explanation of these events is left inconclusive,&quot; the URNG said in a statement.</p>
<p>URNG leaders stopped short of criticising the government directly in the case later on Thursday, blaming shadowy groups for trying to shake up the peace process and damage the image of the ex-rebels and the government.</p>
<p>&quot;The objectives of those that have done all of this is to destabilise the peace process,&quot; the URNG's Commander, Pablo Monsanto, told reporters.</p>
<p>Cabrera and another guerrilla were abducted in October by an elite army group after the two rebels allegedly led a high-profile kidnapping that forced the government to temporarily break off peace talks. They concluded successfully with a Dec. 29 accord.</p>
<p>The other rebel was released after the kidnap crisis was resolved, but Cabrera never resurfaced and was probably killed, according to a United Nations report earlier this week.</p>
<p>Cabrera was likely the last victim of the war, which claimed an estimated 140,000 lives. His fate has gripped the country's attention in the past few months.</p>
<p>The URNG high command previously denied Cabrera existed because the disappearance added tension to the final stretch of the peace talks and deeply embarrassed the group, which is now trying to become a political party.</p>
<p>Amnesty International demanded on Wednesday the government clear up the case, but President Alvaro Arzu called the U.N. Mission for the Verification of Human Rights in Guatemala report unfounded.</p>
<p>Despite the case, Monsanto said the former rebels were generally pleased with progress in implementing the peace accords.</p>
<p>The ex-combatants, however, said former paramilitary groups in rural areas were still actively trying to harrass URNG members and were urging local communities not to allow the group's former fighters to live there.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GUAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GUATEMALA CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GUATEMALA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
