<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609035" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai finance firms says weak economy killed merger.</title>
<headline>Thai finance firms says weak economy killed merger.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cash-strapped Finance One Plc, Thailand's largest finance company, on Friday said that it had ended two-month merger talks with Thai Danu Bank Plc because of the weak economy and complicated legal and tax issues.</p>
<p>The finance company said in a statement it would seek shareholders and central bank approvals of any new institutional partners in the future.</p>
<p>Finance One president Pin Chakkapak indicated at a news conference that Finance One had not found a new potential partner to replace Thai Danu, which ranks 11th among Thailand's 15 commercial banks.</p>
<p>He said: &quot;After the failure to merge with Thai Danu, Finance One has no (immediate) plan to merge with any other company. We will continue to operate our own business after raising our capital.&quot;</p>
<p>Thai Danu said in a statement of its decision to end efforts of forming alliance with Finance One: &quot;The two companies have started conducting a due diligence exercise...and devoted considerable time for determining the ratio of mutual share swaps.</p>
<p>&quot;We concluded that the merger process as agreed to under the memorandum of understanding and related legal proceeding would take considerable time and also due to unclear merger related tax issues...a merger between Thai Danu and Finance One would not create real synergy as expected by both organisations.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts said the government was concerned that the collapse of the Thai Danu-Finance One talks could shake public confidence in the stability of Thailand's 91 finance companies which are mostly heavily exposed to the troubled Thai property sector.</p>
<p>The Thai property sector is in its fourth year of severe slump with no immediate recovery in sight.</p>
<p>Deputy central bank governor Jaroong Nookhwun said earlier on Friday his bank was prepared to contain any damage that the financial sector may face if the proposed Thai Danu-Finance One alliance did not materialise.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Amnuay Viravan said the delay in wrapping up their merger talk partly stemmed from problems encountered by auditors assessing Finance One's assets.</p>
<p>Finance One had earlier said it would comply with an instruction by the Bank of Thailand for the company to raise its capital by 8.28 billion baht through a 2-to-1 rights issue at 7.50 baht.</p>
<p>Pin said Finance One's outstanding loans and accrued interest amounted to about 59.4 billion baht, of which about 5.46 billion are non-performing.</p>
<p>Finance One said the prolonged bearishness on the Thai bourse had reduced the market value of equities in its investment portfolio to 2.05 billion baht now from 6.37 billion at end-1996.</p>
<p>It said: &quot;The company was affected by the slowing economy which raised the level of troubled loans that it carried. The overall prolonged slump of the capital market also sharply reduced the market value of its investment.&quot;</p>
<p>Finance One said at the end of the first quarter, its provisions against doubtful loans stood at 3.62 billion baht and provisions for its own equity loss stood at another 4.75 billion baht.</p>
<p>Trading of Finance One and Thai Danu's shares have been suspended by the Stock Exchange of Thailand since late February pending the result of their merger talks.</p>
<p>($1 = 26 baht)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
