<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609010" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chilean economy grows 3.9 pct in first quarter.</title>
<headline>Chilean economy grows 3.9 pct in first quarter.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chilean economic activity as measured by the Imacec index rose 3.9 percent in the first quarter of 1997 over the first quarter of last year, the Central Bank reported.</p>
<p>The increase, one of the lowest quarterly figures of the past three years, reflected the effects of drought in central Chile and a general slowdown in the rate of economic growth, the Central Bank said in its twice-monthly macroeconomic report.</p>
<p>The Imacec in March rose 3.4 percent, the bank previously announced.  </p>
<p>&quot;The March figure was negatively affected, like those in January and February, by the drought which has recently affected much of the country,&quot; said the Central Bank's report. The drought has hit agricultural production, especially in the export fruit sector, and electric power generation because of sagging water levels at dams.</p>
<p>If it weren't for the drought, economic growth in the first quarter would have been 4.5 percent, said the report.</p>
<p>The figure also &quot;reflects a path of moderation in the dynamism of economic activity,&quot; said the report.  </p>
<p>Growth in the mining sector was still leading the rest of the economy, said the report.</p>
<p>&quot;The vigorously dynamic growth in mining production is worth noting, especially in copper, the sector which is leading growth in the economy,&quot; said the report.</p>
<p>((--Roger Atwood, Santiago newsroom +56-2-699-5595 x211))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
