<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609077" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Malaysia futures bourse chiefs support merger.</title>
<headline>Malaysia futures bourse chiefs support merger.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The heads of futures exchanges the Malaysia Monetary Exchange and the Kuala Lumpur Options and Financial Futures Exchange said they supported a merger between them proposed by the Securities Commission.</p>
<p>They told Reuters Financial Television on Friday that the merger of MME, KLOFFE and the Kuala Lumpur Commodities Exchange (KLCE) would greatly enhance efficiency and reduce cost of operations.</p>
<p>A merger between the three was proposed by Munir Majid, chairman of the Securities Commission, this week.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there are a number of compelling commercial issues that would mitigate in favour of some sort of merger (between) what are now three (futures) exchanges in Malaysia,&quot; said John Duggan, chief operating officer of KLOFFE.</p>
<p>KLOFFE trades futures on the Composite Index of blue chip stocks, MME trades an interest rate futures contract based on the benchmark three-month Kuala Lumpur Interbank Offered Rate (KLIBOR) and KLCE has futures contracts in palm oil, rubber, tin and cocoa futures.</p>
<p>&quot;I think if you just look at the issue of cost savings alone, there is tremendous duplication of effort,&quot; he told Reuters Financial Television's Asia Today programme.</p>
<p>He said among other areas that would benefit from a merger were development of new products, education and also market compliance and surveillance. Each exchange has its own programme in these areas.</p>
<p>Duggan said volumes on KLOFFE had risen sharply in the last two months to an average 1,300 contracts a day.</p>
<p>&quot;At these sorts of turnovers, it points to about three billion ringgit worth of underlying activity a month,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said much of the volume came from Malaysian retail investors, while institutional investors were still reluctant to enter the market in a big way.</p>
<p>MME executive chairman Syed Jabbar Shahabuddin agreed with the view that merger of the three institutions would create a more cost-efficient futures exchange, but added that institutional reluctance to participate in trading was stunting volume growth.</p>
<p>&quot;Local institutions are now gearing for participation,&quot; he told RFTV.</p>
<p>He said MME was planning to introduce new products such as a ringgit futures contract and a bond futures contract.</p>
<p>The introduction of new products and a tie-up with the New York Commodities Exchange, which allows the two to trade in each other's products, will enhance liquidity and popularity of derivatives as a price-hedging medium, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
