<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609066" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai rubber prices up as government intervenes.</title>
<headline>Thai rubber prices up as government intervenes.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thai rubber prices edged higher as the government intervened to prop up the market, traders said on Friday.</p>
<p>Enquiries came from China, but no deals emerged as buyers were deterred by high prices, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;The price ideas of buyers and sellers are so different. Buyers looked for prices of around 107.00 US cents per kg while sellers did not want to sell below 116.00 cents,&quot; said one Bangkok-based trader.</p>
<p>Traders said prices were lifted by the govenrment's intervention scheme, under which it bought rubber from domestic market at 29.00 baht ($1.11) a kg.</p>
<p>&quot;With government buying at such unrealistic prices, rubber producers won't sell below 24-25 baht a kg. That makes it difficult to be competitive,&quot; said another trader.</p>
<p>One trader said China turned to Indonesia for supplies as prices there were cheaper.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see strong buying interest emerging unless prices drop from current levels,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Thai benchmark RSS3 was quoted around 116.00 US cents a kg for July shipment and at 116.50 for August, compared with 113.00 and 115.00 respectively on Wednesday.</p>
<p>-- Anchalee Koetsawang (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
