<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609042" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>singapore: Asia Gas Oil/Jet-Diesel snaps support, set to fall.</title>
<headline>Asia Gas Oil/Jet-Diesel snaps support, set to fall.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore prompt gas oil price pierced its long-term support of $25 when it traded thrice at $24.90 a barrel on Friday, the first time since last August, and is set for a free-fall amid weak regional demand, traders said.</p>
<p>Traders said they now see support at $24.50 per barrel, which augured badly for refiners' profit margins and might force them to cut crude runs soon if the fall continued next week.</p>
<p>Three physical cargoes were traded at $24.90--a Swiss trader to a Japanese trader for June 7-11, a Mediterranean trader to a Singapore trader and a European major to a Japanese trader for June 18-22 liftings, free-on-board (fob) basis.  </p>
<p>The European major sold two other cargoes earlier to the Japanese trader at $25.00 for June 7-11 and June 18-22 liftings fob.</p>
<p>The soft undertone was also seen on the swaps market with June traded as low as $24.85.</p>
<p>Traders said in its July tender which closes on May 27, Indian Oil Corp is expected to buys about 360,000 tonnes of 1.0-percent sulphur gas oil, and 180,000 tonnes each of the 0.5 and 0.25 percent sulphur grades.  </p>
<p>India bought only 270,000 tonnes of 1.0-percent sulphur gas oil and 45,000 tonnes of the 0.25-percent sulphur grade. But traders said despite the relatively higher volumes expected for July, it was still not large enough to resuscitate the weak market.</p>
<p>Traders said Abu Dhabi National Oil Co's tender to sell 75,000 tonnes of 0.5-percent sulphur gas oil for June 22-24 lifting was awarded to Malaysia's Petco at a 30-cent-per-barrel premium, fob Ruwais. Traders had earlier said that the awarded price was a 35-cent premium.  </p>
<p>Sri Lanka has issued a tender to buy 220,000 barrels of gas oil and 80,000 barrels of jet fuel for June 10-11 delivery, which closes on May 28.</p>
<p>Singapore physical jet fuel was steady with a 130,000-barrel cargo sold by a European major to a US trader at $24.40 per barrel for June 17-21 lifting fob Singapore.</p>
<p>Taiwan bought 32,000 tonnes of jet fuel at around $201 per tonne for July delivery, c-and-f basis from a Singapore trader. This was lower than the last cargoes CPC bought for May delivery at $204 per tonne.  </p>
<p>Traders said jet fuel market was well supplied as seen in</p>
<p>the more than 15 offers made into Taiwan's tender.</p>
<p>(Prices in dollars per barrel)</p>
<p> MTH FOB SIN		     BUY/SELL     PREV BUY/SELL</p>
<p> JUN JET KEROSENE/KERO     24.20/24.60	 24.20/24.60</p>
<p> JUN GAS OIL 0.5% S	  24.90/25.00	 25.10/25.20</p>
<p> JUN JET/GAS OIL SWAPS     -0.40/-0.20	 -0.30/-0.15</p>
<p> JUN GAS OIL SWAPS	   24.85/24.95	 25.00/25.20</p>
<p> JUL GAS OIL SWAPS	   24.88/24.95	 24.90/25.10</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3084)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
