<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609065" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: China says Philippines being a bully over rocks.</title>
<headline>China says Philippines being a bully over rocks.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Thatcher</byline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>China on Friday invoked 700 year old documents to assert its claim on obscure islands and rocks in the South China Sea and accused the Philippines of being bully in trying to grab them.</p>
<p>But the Philippines took a more conciliatory tone with President Fidel Ramos saying he hoped the issue could be resolved through diplomacy.</p>
<p>The latest point of contention is the Scarborough Shoal, a dreary group of rocks in the South China Sea which almost disappear at high tide and which Philippine military officials say are little more than a resting place for smugglers.</p>
<p>&quot;Volumes of historical documents since China's Yuan Dynasty (1271-1368) kept clear records about the island. Maps and textbooks published by China since 1935 have all identified it as Chinese territory...the international community has never voiced any disagreement over this,&quot; the Chinese embassy said in a statement.</p>
<p>The tussle has followed quickly on from another dispute over the Spratly Islands, further to the south.</p>
<p>Six Asian countries claim some or all the Spratlys. Most of the islands are tiny and barely capable of supporting life, but the area is thought by some to contain rich deposits of oil and gas.</p>
<p>Diplomats and analysts have a variety of views over why the issue has been allowed to turn so rancorous.</p>
<p>Some say it is China trying to flex its muscle and picking on one of the weaker countries in southeast Asia.</p>
<p>Others contend it has as much to do with domestic politicking ahead of next year's Philippine presidential election and attempts by the navy to scare Congress into handing over more money to beef up its decrepit fleet.</p>
<p>While Beijing practised restraint, the Philippines sent warships to drive away civilian Chinese amateur radio hams in the area, and then hoisted its flag on the rocks, the Chinese embassy said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Chinese side got puzzled at and simply could not understand the position of the Philippine side. We cannot but raise the question of the real intention,'&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The two sides are due to meet in Beijing from May 25 to 28 in what Ramos said was a bid to defuse the tension over the rival claims.</p>
<p>A statement quoted him as telling businessmen in Hong Kong that he hoped the dispute would be resolved amicably.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope that the slight tensions that have arisen will be resolved diplomatically,' he said, describing relations between the two countries as very good.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, Philippines Armed Forces Chief Arnulfo Acedera warned that China risked being branded a bully because of its behaviour over the islands.</p>
<p>In a news conference on Friday, he said he had had informal talks to bring in U.S. military help if the Philippines were to find itself threatened by another country, though he did not name China.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
