<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609078" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan, HK say confident of shipping agreement.</title>
<headline>Taiwan, HK say confident of shipping agreement.</headline>
<byline>Alice Hung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan and Hong Kong officials said on Friday they were confident of resolving the thorny issue of what flags to fly when their ships sail bilateral routes after the British colony's July handover to China.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a great confidence to get things done,&quot; George Chao, head of the Hong Kong Shipowners' Association and Beijing-appointed negotiator, said on the eve of Saturday's second round of shipping talks.</p>
<p>&quot;You are welcome to attend tomorrow's news conference. I believe you will hear good news,&quot; the state-funded Central News Agency quoted Chao as saying on his arrival in Taipei.</p>
<p>Chao declined to specify how the sides would resolve the flag-flying issue, but he said: &quot;The issue will be resolved perfectly.&quot;</p>
<p>Koo Chen-fu, chairman of Taipei's semi-official Straits Exchange Foundation, was equally optimistic.</p>
<p>&quot;The outstanding obstacles are few,&quot; Koo was quoted by the state news agency as saying.</p>
<p>Talks on how to continue crucial direct shipping services after Hong Kong's handover to China ended without a deal on May 2 with the sides deadlocked on the flag issue.</p>
<p>Beijing, which regards Nationalist Taiwan as a renegade province, objects to any ship entering Hong Kong harbour flying the flag of the exiled Republic of China, which took refuge on Taiwan after its 1949 civil war defeat by the communists.</p>
<p>Taipei's United Daily News said the flag issue was expected to be resolved with a deal in which both sides could fly &quot;identification flags&quot; rather than national flags when entering each other's harbour.</p>
<p>The most likely flags, it said, would be those linked to the two harbour cities -- Hong Kong's tropical bauhinia flag and a flag representing Kaohsiung, Taiwan's main southern port.</p>
<p>This would give Hong Kong and Kaohsiung equal footing, rather than equating Hong Kong with all of Taiwan, a formula certain to be rejected by Taipei, which sees Taiwan and its exiled Republic of China as the equal of the communist mainland.</p>
<p>Beijing had proposed the sides each use their respective flower flags -- Hong Kong's bauhinia flag and Taiwan's winter plum blossom flag.</p>
<p>Taipei opposed Hong Kong's proposal for Taiwan to fly the plum blossom flag, calling this a Beijing gimmick to portray Taiwan, like Hong Kong, as a region and not a sovereign state.</p>
<p>Taipei had proposed that the sides simply lower their flags while entering each other's harbour, but this was rejected by Beijing on the grounds that only pirates sail without flags.</p>
<p>Taiwan businessmen have urged their government to secure direct shipping links with Hong Kong, which reverts to China at midnight on June 30 after 156 years as a British colony.</p>
<p>Hong Kong is an important transit point for the more than US$30 billion in investments that have poured into China from Taiwan since the easing of unofficial ties between Beijing and Taipei in the late 1980s.</p>
<p>Taiwan has banned direct links with its communist rival since 1949.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
