<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609064" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: FinOne details positions, merger fails.</title>
<headline>FinOne details positions, merger fails.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cash strapped Finance One Plc, Thailand's largest finance company, on Friday attributed its huge first quarter loss and plunging assets to the country's sluggish economy and battered stock market.</p>
<p>Finance One also said in a statement that it decided to end two-month merger talks with Thai Danu Bank Plc as the weak economy and complicated legal and tax issues made their proposed alliance unfeasible and too time consuming.  </p>
<p>Finance One said it posted a 3.75 billion baht first quarter net loss against 623.63 million baht profit a year ago.</p>
<p>It said due to sharply increased provisions for doubtful loans and loss of its investment portfolio, the company's operating capital plunged to 5.49 billion baht at end-March from 14.0 billion at end-1996.</p>
<p>Trading of Finance One and Thai Danu's shares has been suspended by the Stock Exchange of Thailand since late February pending the result of their merger talks.</p>
<p>Finance One said it would comply with an instruction by the Bank of Thailand for the company to raise its capital by 8.28 billion baht through a 2-to-1 rights issue at 7.50 baht.  </p>
<p>The statement said if Finance One's current shareholders failed to fully subscribe to the proposed rights issue, the central bank's Financial Institutions Development Fund would consider buying the offered shares.</p>
<p>Referring to the collapse of its merger talks with Thai Danu, the big finance company said it would seek shareholders and central bank approvals of any new institutional partners in the future.</p>
<p>&quot;In case of institutional investors which could boost our future business competitiveness, the company would propose to shareholders and the Bank of Thailand to approve their investment by buying the new shares,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The central bank has said it would consider allowing foreign companies to buy stakes in finance firms above the current 25 percent limit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
