<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609025" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: Colombian tribe brings its oil protest to capital.</title>
<headline>Colombian tribe brings its oil protest to capital.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>A half-dozen U'Wa Indians and hundreds of Colombian supporters marched through Bogota on Thursday to protest against a U.S. oil company's plans to explore what the tribe considers sacred ground.</p>
<p>The march, led by U'Wa chief Roberto Cobaria, tied up the Colombian capital's already chaotic downtown traffic.</p>
<p>Cobaria later repeated the determination of his 5,000-strong tribe to commit mass suicide if the exploration goes forward.</p>
<p>&quot;The suicide will happen when our traditional laws are no longer respected,&quot; he told Reuters in a phone interview. &quot;We are children of Mother Earth, and oil is the blood of Mother Earth. We cannot negotiate.&quot;</p>
<p>High-level Cabinet ministers and U'Wa representatives are scheduled to meet on May 29 in Boyaca, a jungle province northeast of Bogota, El Tiempo, Colombia's leading newspaper, said on Thursday.</p>
<p>But government officials may be hard pressed to reach an agreement before June 1, when the U'Wa begin a traditional 2 1/2-month retreat, ceasing communication with the outside world, Cobaria said.</p>
<p>The U'wa believe the sun shines directly on their homeland from June until the middle of August, he said. During this period, they eat sparingly and hold sacred ceremonies that involve ingesting a hallucinogenic plant.</p>
<p>Occidental Petroleum Corp. received a license in 1995 to explore for oil in the Samore block, a region that spreads across part of two U'Wa reservations.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, Oxy released a statement promising not to enter the reservations without the the tribe's permission.</p>
<p>The indigenous group says exploration and eventual drilling would fill the region with alien workers and destroy land that lies along an U'Wa migratory route.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
