<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609045" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Dragonair plane makes emergency landing near Manila.</title>
<headline>Dragonair plane makes emergency landing near Manila.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Hong Kong Dragon Airlines (Dragonair) Airbus 330 made an emergency landing at Subic Bay in the Philippines on Friday, airport officials said -- the latest incident involving Rolls-Royce Plc engines.</p>
<p>Flight KA-MH061 from Hong Kong landed safely at Subic Bay international airport after developing engine trouble en route to Kota Kinabalu in Malaysia, Rene Paguia, official-in-charge of the airport, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Air traffic controllers said the Dragonair pilot landed using only one engine.</p>
<p>&quot;We were told by the pilot that the plane's left engine conked out,&quot; an air traffic controller told Reuters.</p>
<p>None of the 127 passengers and crew was hurt, airport officials said.</p>
<p>A Dragonair spokeswoman in Hong Kong said the Airbus 330-300 was fitted with two Rolls-Royce Trent 700 engines and made an unscheduled stop at the Subic Bay airport &quot;because of the engine&quot;.</p>
<p>Problems with gearbox bearings in Trent 700 engines have forced Hong Kong flag carrier Cathay Pacific Airways Ltd Airbus 330-300s to make a series of unscheduled single-engine landings recently.</p>
<p>A Cathay Pacific plane with Trent 700 engines made a single-engine landing at Bangkok last week. Two weeks ago a flight to the Philippines had return to Hong Kong, a Cathay Pacific spokesman told Reuters in Hong Kong on Wednesday.</p>
<p>A Vietnam-bound Cathay airliner had to make a single-engine landing last November, he added.</p>
<p>In April, a Dragonair airliner suffered a similar gearbox problem while flying from Hong Kong to Shanghai, Hong Kong's South China Morning Post newspaper said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Cathay operates 11 A330-300s using Trent 700 engines, while its sister airline Dragonair uses four.</p>
<p>Indonesian airline Garuda operates five of the planes.</p>
<p>Rolls-Royce said on Thursday it believed it had found a design solution to the gearbox problem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
