<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609036" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: More clashes erupt as Indonesian campaign ends.</title>
<headline>More clashes erupt as Indonesian campaign ends.</headline>
<byline>Lewa Pardomuan</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rival political groups and police fought running battles in Jakarta on Friday, the last day of Indonesia's violence-marred general election campaign.</p>
<p>Witnesses said riot police fired teargas, rubber bullets and warning shots into the air to break up a minor riot involving supporters of the Moslem-oriented United Development Party (PPP) and rivals from the ruling Golkar party in the southern Ciputat district of the capital Jakarta.</p>
<p>The windows of up to 100 shops in the area were smashed by angry PPP loyalists, they said. A police officer said 12 people were detained.</p>
<p>The riot broke out after partisans of the ruling Golkar party stoned a PPP convoy, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Tens of thousands of supporters of the minority Moslem-based United Development Party (PPP) came out on the streets of cities on Java, the country's most populous island, in the last show of strength before the May 29 elections.</p>
<p>The campaign is followed by a five-day cooling off period before nearly 125 million eligible voters go to the polls next Thursday for national and local elections which GOlkar is expected to easily win.</p>
<p>Reuters Television cameraman Sarni Ocampo said plain-clothes security officers took film from his camera and from another cameraman in Ciputat. Ocampo said he was roughed up briefly but not hurt.</p>
<p>Film was also confiscated from Reuters photographer Patrick de Noirmont.</p>
<p>In the Tanah Abang area in the centre of the city, police fought a two-hour battle with stone-throwing PPP supporters, witnesses said. The crowd dispersed after repeated rounds of teargas and rubber bullets were fired, witnesses said.</p>
<p>In Tangerang, a satellite township to the west of Jakarta, witnesses said supporters of the PPP attacked commercial buildings and smashed windows after a rally.</p>
<p>Banks, shops and a government office were damaged but the violence quickly died down. Four armoured troop carriers patrolled the main commercial area of Tangerang at dusk.</p>
<p>Security forces appeared to have the situation under control as darkness fell across the city although flames from burning tyres could be seen in several areas.</p>
<p>Reuters Television producer Kenneth van Toll said tension was high in Pekalongan, a coastal city of one million in central Java which was hit by serious riots in early March before the election campaign started late last month.</p>
<p>Troops with armoured cars moved in to clear the streets after a rally of some 10,000 people at which speakers condemned corruption and collusion in government.</p>
<p>Political analysts have said the violence in the campaign has been led mostly by disadvantaged urban youth who have been left behind in Indonesia's strong economic growth under President Suharto's three decade-long rule.</p>
<p>They say these people nominally support the PPP, but are more intent on registering their protest against the country's rigid political and economic system.</p>
<p>Indonesia allows only three political parties to contest elections -- the PPP, Golkar and the divided Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI). Each party campaigns in a different area of the country on each day under previously-agreed rules.</p>
<p>However, analysts said Friday's violence was less severe than previously feared. Clashes have intensified in the last week of the campaign and many analysts had spoken of the possibility of widespread unrest throughout Java, the political nerve-centre of the country.</p>
<p>Many schools in Jakarta were closed and a number of offices shut down early. Civil service and bank officials were advised not to wear semi-official uniforms to work, like the safari suits and blue batik shirts favoured by the bureaucracy.</p>
<p>But as the day progressed with fewer reports of violence than feared, local financial markets reacted favourably.</p>
<p>The Jakarta composite stock index closed 0.68 percent up at 658.52 points while the rupiah last traded in Jakarta at 2,442.25/2.75 against the dollar versus a 2,440.00/2.00 open.</p>
<p>Currency dealers said the mild weakening in the rupiah could be ascribed to the tensions but noted that the rate was steady toward the end of the day, indicating that the market was confident for the near-term.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
