<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609061" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: New World Infra seeking rating review.</title>
<headline>New World Infra seeking rating review.</headline>
<text>
<p>HONG KONG, May 23 (Reuter) New World Infrastructure Ltd is asking for a credit rating review, managing director Douglas Chan said at a loan signing ceremony on Friday.</p>
<p>New World Infrastructure has a &quot;split rating&quot;, Chan said. It is rated BBB-minus by Standard and Poor's Corp, the lowest investment grade rating, while Moody's Investors Service has assigned the company a Ba1, a notch below investment grade.</p>
<p>Chan said he hoped the company could receive an investment grade rating from both rating agencies.</p>
<p>Since May this year, New World Infrastructure has raised an estimated HK$7 billion, with around HK$2 billion through a share placement earlier this month and US$650 million (HK$5.02 billion) via a loan syndication, chairman Henry Cheng said.</p>
<p>Cheng said the company would spend the HK$2 billion mainly on water treatment projects in China, whereas the proceeds from the loan facility would be used for general working capital.</p>
<p>Chan added the rate of return from the company's water treatment projects is around 18 percent while its road projects yield 20 percent and its power investments around 18 percent.</p>
<p>At present, the company has a gearing ratio of around 22 percent. Its gearing will rise to 90 percent if the US$650 million loan facility is fully drawn, Cheng said.</p>
<p>Cheng added that the company still has the capacity to borrow a further HK$5-6 billion, thereby pushing its gearing to a maximum of 150 percent. But he stressed that the company has no urgent funding requirements.</p>
<p>As for the company's expansion plan, Douglas Chan said the New World Infrastructure has invested close to US$1 billion in new projects in China for the past 18 months.</p>
<p>Chan said &quot;I would like to be as active as the last 18 months,&quot; when asked if the company would be more active in the coming 18 months.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2847 4039</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C174">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
