<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609072" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: New IPO rules in HK seen dampening some demand.</title>
<headline>New IPO rules in HK seen dampening some demand.</headline>
<byline>Donny Kwok</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>New rules on initial public offerings (IPO) in Hong Kong are likely to dampen the enthusiasm of large investors for the hottest shares such as the recent red-chip stocks which have sent investors into a buying frenzy.</p>
<p>Analysts said large investors might choose to scale down their subscription because of higher financing costs resulting from the new interim rules announced by the Securities and Futures Commission (SFC) and the Hong Kong Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;The measure will scale down the size of applications from big investors because their cost of financing will be raised,&quot; Manus Tam, director of corporate finance of Lippo Securities, said.</p>
<p>Analysts said the large investors would face the need to borrow more from banks because new allocation procedures would cause them to subscribe to a larger amount to get the number of shares they want.</p>
<p>The regulator and the exchange announced the interim rules on Thursday after the recent IPOs were oversubscribed by large margins, raising concern about orderly markets and straining the banking system.</p>
<p>The Beijing municipal government backed Beijing Enterprises Holdings Ltd closed its IPO on Friday and analysts expected that it would set a record for oversubscription by investors.</p>
<p>Smaller investors are expected to benefit from the interim rules, which take effect on Monday, because they will have a better chance of obtaining shares.</p>
<p>Under the new rules, underwriters would be required to divide the total number of shares available for public subscription equally into two pools.</p>
<p>Pool A would be reserved for applicants who were buying shares worth HK$5 million or less, while pool B would be reserved for those buying more than HK$5 million.</p>
<p>If one of the pools was undersubscribed, the surplus would be transferred to satisfy demand in the other pool.</p>
<p>Under the previous procedures, both big and small investors, could apply for a large amount of shares, boosting the subscription rate, but also lowering the chances for smaller investors to subscribe successfully.</p>
<p>&quot;The new interim policy is designed to achieve really one basic objective, to ensure that there is as much fairness and orderliness as possible in the security market,&quot; said SFC chairman Anthony Neoh.</p>
<p>Rafael Hui, acting financial secretary for Hong Kong, voiced support for the SFC move.</p>
<p>&quot;Our intention is not to prevent speculation...Our intention is to try to maintain an orderly market,&quot; Hui said.</p>
<p>However, some analysts warned that the measures may have negative impacts in the long run.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a kind of administrative measure, just like (government) intervention on the property market,&quot; Tam said.</p>
<p>And like other administrative measures, no one knows when it would be lifted, analysts said.</p>
<p>Analysts also question the level of HK$5 million, saying it may not always be appropriate depending on the size of the IPO.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843 6370</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
