<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609063" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: KFC says Ting quits on own free will.</title>
<headline>KFC says Ting quits on own free will.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia fast food retailer KFC Holdings Bhd said on Friday its chief executive officer and managing director George Ting had resigned on his own free will.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr George Ting Yew Tong resigned on his own free will so as to devote more time and develop his personal/private businesses after divesting his entire stake in the company,&quot; KFC said in a statement.</p>
<p>KFC earlier this week said Ting had quit his posts in the company, raising speculation that there may have been disagreements at board level.</p>
<p>It said group executive director Harris Beh has been actively managing the company with key shareholder Ishak Ismail since April 1996.</p>
<p>KFC said a new franchise agreement naming Ishak as the shareholders' representative has been presented to KFC to reflect the change in major shareholders.</p>
<p>Ting's departure had also raised speculation it would jeopardise the fast-food franchise agreement between the company and U.S.-based Pepsico Inc. The previous clause named Ting as the representative for KFC.</p>
<p>The statement said KFC performed well in the first quarter of this year, making the company &quot;confident that it will achieve another creditable performance for the coming year&quot;.</p>
<p>Without giving details, it said KFC Restaurants sales increased by 30 percent, Pizza Hut sales by 54 percent and sales of the integrated poultry business by 21 percent.</p>
<p>The feedmill division registered a 170 percent sale increase in the first quarter compared to the same period last year, while other supporting businees received sales boost of 37 percent.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-201 4813)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I66100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
