<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609031" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Chinese vice premier Zhu Rongji arrives in Australia.</title>
<headline>Chinese vice premier Zhu Rongji arrives in Australia.</headline>
<dateline>PERTH, Australia 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chinese vice-premier and economic tsar Zhu Rongji arrived in Australia on Friday for a landmark visit to cement improved ties and reward Canberra for an easing of its stand on human rights in China.</p>
<p>Australian officials said the week-long visit would focus on trade and investment and was the latest in a series of steps by Canberra and Beijing to repair relations damaged last year over a range of diplomatic and security spats.</p>
<p>Zhu is the most senior Chinese official to visit Australia since National People's Congress chairman Qiao Shi in 1994.</p>
<p>Zhu told Beijing-based Australian journalists this week that his trip, which replaces a cancelled European tour, was a payback for Australia abandoning a United Nations resolution censuring China over its human rights record.</p>
<p>Zhu said Premier Li Peng had asked him to travel to Australia as a reward for Canberra's decision not to co-sponsor the U.N. Human Rights Commission resolution this year, for the first time in seven years.</p>
<p>&quot;You can see Australia this time really acted very good on the human rights question,&quot; Zhu quoted Li as telling him.</p>
<p>Announcing Australia's decision not to co-sponsor the U.N. resolution, Foreign Minister Alexander Downer said last month the two countries had agreed to set up a formal human rights dialogue.</p>
<p>Australian officials said Canberra would push for an early start to that so-far unscheduled dialogue when Zhu is in Canberra early next week.</p>
<p>Downer said on Wednesday that he would also raise human rights concerns in his meeting with the Chinese economic leader.</p>
<p>Zhu's Australian tour replaces a planned visit to Austria, Ireland, Luxembourg and the Netherlands which Beijing-based Australian media quoted Zhu as saying was cancelled because of those countries' support for the U.N. motion.</p>
<p>Zhu arrived in Perth on Fiday night and is scheduled on Saturday to visit the Channar iron ore mine in the Western Australian outback -- a joint venture between China and mining giant RTZ Corp-CRA.</p>
<p>He also plans to visit an Australian winery in South Australia on Sunday before heading to Canberra for talks with Australian Prime Minister John Howard.</p>
<p>Zhu heads a delegation which includes leading business people and 10 officials of at least vice-ministerial rank.</p>
<p>Australian officials said Zhu, credited with China's rapid economic growth and a key force in the restructuring of state businesses, will discuss a range of economic and business issues, including a proposed A$500 million (US$390 million) reduced iron project in Western Australia state and wool quotas.</p>
<p>China is Australia's fifth largest trading partner, with two-way trade worth A$8.0 billion in calendar 1996.</p>
<p>Trade is growing about 20 percent a year and China is projected to move to Australia's number two trading partner, behind Japan, by 2005.</p>
<p>(A$1 = US$0.78)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PERTH, Australia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
