<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609056" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Hong Kong ponders future of democracy.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong ponders future of democracy.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Sprague</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's pro-democracy advocates on Friday fretted that the cards would be stacked against them after China regained control despite pledges from the territory's future leader to hold fair elections.</p>
<p>But while politicians talked, Hong Kong's punters remained wildly optimistic about the territory's business future as the stock market rocketed to new highs. The blue-chip Hang Seng index surged 119.68 points to a record 14,331.68.</p>
<p>Tung Chee-hwa, the man who will lead Hong Kong after the British colony reverts to Chinese rule at midnight on June 30, on Friday pledged fair and open elections for the territory's legislature.</p>
<p>Tung told a news conference in Beijing he would study recommendations of the China-appointed Preparatory Committee, which has been designing the framework of the future government.</p>
<p>The committee wound up a meeting in Beijing on Friday, handing Tung and the future Hong Kong government recommendations on how to fill the seats of the post-handover legislature.</p>
<p>China will scrap the territory's existing fully-elected legislature and replace it with an appointed provisional body on July 1.</p>
<p>But mindful that Hong Kong people expect a say in who rules them, it has promised fresh polls in the first half of 1998.</p>
<p>Under a formula that China has endorsed, only 20 of the legislature's 60 seats will be elected directly with the others filled by indirect vote or appointment.</p>
<p>The Preparatory Committee also made recommendations for 15 so-called &quot;functional constituencies&quot; or groups that will fill seats in indirect elections.</p>
<p>Tung will choose nine of those groups which will join 21 others.</p>
<p>One group on the recommended list, the Chinese enterprise association, has aroused controversy as it would appear to give further powers to China.</p>
<p>While the recommendations are not yet final, Hong Kong politicians and analysts said the proposals appeared to dent prospects severely of democrats winning seats in the legislature.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like the proposals are very undemocratic and unfair,&quot; independent legislator Emily Lau told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The pro-democracy camp have very little chance anyway with only 20 seats being directly elected, but on top of that China also wants to manipulate the result by changing the voting system,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The current 60-seat legislature also has just 20 seats directly returned by geographic constituencies, with 30 seats returned by profession-based &quot;functional constituencies&quot; and 10 seats by an electoral committee.</p>
<p>The fears of the pro-democracy camp are centred on the Preparatory Committee's recommendation to adopt a proportional representation or multi-candidate race in the geographic constituencies with several top vote-getters winning office.</p>
<p>&quot;The objective of having multi-seat, single-vote or proportional representation is to limit the chances of success of the pro-democracy camp and to help some unpopular parties to get more seats,&quot; political analyst Andy Ho told Reuters.</p>
<p>Under the old system, with one winner in each geographic constituency, pro-democracy candidates grabbed three quarters of the 20 seats. But with several winners in each district, pro-China candidates are more likely to win some seats.</p>
<p>In the stock market, China-related shares remained the focus of attention. The initial public offering of China-backed conglomerate Beijing Enterprises was the talk of the town, generating huge demand from retail investors who queued for hours to get in on the act.</p>
<p>And in the best tradition of this money-spinning territory, hundreds rushed to snap up the latest in a gush of souvenirs of the British colony's looming handover to China -- special Bank of England five-pound notes with a commemorative 1997 cipher.</p>
<p>&quot;The value has the potential to go up, it's a beautiful design, it's a limited edition, so I think it's a very good buy, said housewife Elaine Fong, as she scrambled to pick up one of the bills, on sale at a financial services fair.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
