<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609069" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: FOCUS - Saudi term naphtha price seen toppish.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Saudi term naphtha price seen toppish.</headline>
<byline>Marguerita Choy</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asian naphtha buyers said that soaring term prices were close to peaking in the wake of a record award by Saudi Arabia.</p>
<p>&quot;Saudi Aramco has recognised the high value placed on ethylene and that endusers are willing to pay up,&quot; a Japanese trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;But others have dropped out and the premium has reached the limit,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>The Middle East's biggest naphtha producer began negotiations in Singapore on May 12 to sell about three million tonnes of A-180 naphtha and between 1.2 and three million tonnes of full-range naphtha.</p>
<p>The sources said most buyers have agreed to pay a record premium of $17.00 per tonne over Saudi Aramco's formula for the ethylene-rich feedstock A-180, lifting from Ras Tanurah.</p>
<p>But buyers were reluctant to pay Aramco a target premium of $15 for low-paraffinic full-range material from Jubail and Rabigh ports, they said.  </p>
<p>The current term contracts, for first half 1997, A-180 is priced at $6.50 and full-range at $5.50-$5.80.Saudi Aramco traditionally sells on a one year basis, but the price is reviewed after six months.</p>
<p>The reluctance of some buyers prompted Aramco to try to sell A-180 and full range as a package.</p>
<p>&quot;Some existing Jubail lifters were said to have terminated contracts with Aramco due to the high price. As a result Aramco is still trying to sell some left-over Jubail,&quot; a trader said.  </p>
<p>However, the A-180 allocation for each existing term holder was cut &quot;substantially,&quot; from the previous year's volumes due to new buyers, such as South Korea's Hyundai Petrochemical said.</p>
<p>&quot;The price is crazy,&quot; said one of the buyers. &quot;Maybe from January 1998, the price will be lower,&quot; he said referring to the price review Aramco holds just before of the end of each year on term contracts.</p>
<p>&quot;It is possible in six month's time, the premium will come down,&quot; a Japanese trader said.  </p>
<p>Earlier this year, other Gulf exporters from Bahrain, Kuwait and Abu Dhabi capitalised on surging Asian petrochemical demand to clinch high premiums on term sales.</p>
<p>Kuwait achieved a premium of $13.50 per tonne over MidEast quotes for March 1997 to February 1998, while Bahrain National Oil Co achieved $11.00-$11.50 and Abu Dhabi National Oil Co (ADNOC) $11.50 for calendar 1997.</p>
<p>But the price spiral could have one further round to go, traders said. ADNOC has told Japan and South Korean buyers that it is seeking a premium for it high grade naphtha of $22.50 for July 1997 to June 1998, compared with $6.80 a year earlier.  </p>
<p>Kuwait is also to start term talks on June 9 in London for the sale of naphtha for one-year from August.</p>
<p>&quot;At this moment, everybody fears a tight supply situation with the start-up of new plants,&quot; said one buyer. &quot;But next year, the reality will be there are so many arbitrage cargoes that there will no need to maintain term contracts with Middle East suppliers.&quot;</p>
<p>--Singapore Newsroom (+65-870-3086)</p>
<p>With contribution from Kiyoshi Takenaka in Tokyo.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
