<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609075" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: ASIAN DEBT MARKETS-Markets shrug off rate cut.</title>
<headline>ASIAN DEBT MARKETS-Markets shrug off rate cut.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Australian rate cut failed to galvanise the Australian or Asian debt markets, although it helped erode the Australian dollar on Friday.</p>
<p>But bankers said the 50 basis points cut in the official cash rate by the Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) might inspire some fixed-rate issuance from Asian investors who believed Australian rates were near bottom.</p>
<p>The RBA rate cut was the fourth since July 1996, and took rates to their lowest level since August 1994.</p>
<p>A banker with a large Australian financial institution said spreads came in after the rate cut.</p>
<p>He said the Australian 10-year bond was trading at 85 basis points over the U.S. 10-year Treasury after the rate cut, down from 100 basis points before the cut.</p>
<p>One year ago, the spread was 200 basis points, he said.</p>
<p>There was a feeling that this might be the last RBA rate cut of the latest cycle, he said.</p>
<p>While issuers might want to lock in low rates through a fixed-rate issue, he saw more scope for an Australian dollar floating-rate note issue like a &quot;Kangaroo&quot; bond.</p>
<p>He predicted that the next entrants to the Kangaroo market would be a sovereign Asian issuer and a Hong Kong corporate.</p>
<p>The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) launched its 6.0 billion Taiwan dollar ($215 million) seven-year bond overnight Thursday in the domestic market.</p>
<p>The Taipei-listed notes carry a 6.04 percent coupon and were priced to yield 26 basis points over government bonds.</p>
<p>Despite the woes of Thai financial markets, Jasmine Submarine Telecoms said it was raising US$180 million through a 14-year bond.</p>
<p>Indian textile-maker Arvind Mills Ltd surfaced with its US$100 million floating-rate note through UBS in Hong Kong on Friday, and said to be 130 basis points over the London Interbank Offered Rate.</p>
<p>Bankers said Indian Railway Finance Corp  IRLY.BO had cleared a hurdle by gaining permission to launch its US$150 million FRN next week via ANZ.</p>
<p>It may enter the market this week with the issue, although this has not been confirmed.</p>
<p>The Hong Kong dollar market had a quiet day, bankers said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's like watching grass grow,&quot; said a local banker. &quot;It's not really that active.&quot;</p>
<p>United Chinese Bank Ltd, a unit of Bank of East Asia Ltd privately placed a HK$300 million floating-rate certificate of deposit (FRCD).</p>
<p>The one-year FRCD pays a coupon of 25 basis points over the three month Hong Kong Interbank Offered Rate.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
