<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609021" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>COLOMBIA: IMF boss urges Colombia to wipe out cancer of drugs.</title>
<headline>IMF boss urges Colombia to wipe out cancer of drugs.</headline>
<dateline>BOGOTA 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The worldwide head of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) called on Colombia on Thursday to increase spending to wipe out the &quot;cancer&quot; of drug trafficking.</p>
<p>&quot;Colombia has the obligation to put more funds toward fighting this cancer. It would be worse to allow the narco- traffickers to get away with the illusion that they're winning this battle,&quot; Michel Camdessus said at an evening press conference in Bogota.</p>
<p>&quot;When a country must combat a powerful internal enemy whose horror is a permanent threat, there is no other solution (but to spend). The government has to equip the police forces in Colombia to erradicate this cancer,&quot; Camdessus said.</p>
<p>The comments were an uncharacteristically impassioned plea from the head of an institution more used to calling for austere spending cuts and belt-tightening measures.</p>
<p>Earlier on Thursday, Camdessus met President Ernesto Samper. Among the measures he recommended were more prudent fiscal and monetary policies and for the Colombian government to press ahead with opening its economy to international trade and competition and to continue the wave of privatisations of state-owned industries.</p>
<p>This week, Finance Minister Jose Antonio Ocampo announced about a $500 million budget freeze and an efficiency drive in all government departments. He said defence spending -- which includes police and anti-drug funding -- would be carefully analysed to see if any waste could be trimmed.</p>
<p>Camdessus' call, however, seemed likely to deter the government from looking too closely at that area of the budget.</p>
<p>Despite cuts announced earlier in the year, Colombia's 1997 defence budget was estimated to be as much as the total spent in the past four years. Anti-narcotics operations and the anti-guerrilla war were two prime concerns, although army top brass has complained too much money goes to administration and personnel costs and not enough on upgrading equipment.</p>
<p>This year, the U.S. State Department has almost doubled its anti-narcotics aid to Colombia to about $44 million, and a further $37.5 million will be donated from a separate U.S. government fund. The United States was also donating a multi-million dollar equipment package, including upgraded cropduster aircraft to erradicate illegal drug plantations and 24 Huey UH-1 helicopters.</p>
<p>He declined to answer whether he thought the United States was correct to &quot;decertify&quot; Colombia as a trustworthy ally in the drug war for a second consecutive year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOGOTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COLOMBIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
