<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609067" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Jakarta hit by violence on last day of campaign.</title>
<headline>Jakarta hit by violence on last day of campaign.</headline>
<byline>Lewa Pardomuan</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Violence flared between rival political groups in south Jakarta on Friday on the final day of campaigning for Indonesia's general elections next week.</p>
<p>The campaign is followed by a five-day cooling off period before nearly 125 million eligible voters go to the polls next Thursday for national and local elections.</p>
<p>Witnesses said police fired teargas and rubber bullets at demonstrators and shots into the air to break up a fight between supporters of the Moslem-oriented United Development Party (PPP) and rivals from the ruling Golkar in Jakarta's southern Ciputat area.</p>
<p>Rioters smashed the windows of about 100 shops along three km (two miles) of the main thoroughfare from Ciputat into the city centre. Witnesses said they saw at least five people injured by flying stones and teargas canisters.</p>
<p>A police officer said 12 people were detained.</p>
<p>Reuters Television cameraman Sarni Ocampo said plain-clothes police took film from his camera and from another cameraman at the scene. Ocampo said he was roughed up briefly but not hurt.</p>
<p>Police also seized film from Reuters photographer Patrick de Noirmont. Security forces appeared to have the situation under control as darkness fell across the city.</p>
<p>Flames from burning tyres could be seen in several areas, including the central Petamburan area near the Pelni state hospital.</p>
<p>Witnesses said supporters of the PPP had smashed windows of commercial buildings in Tangerang after a rally in the town on Jakarta's western outskirts.</p>
<p>Four armoured troop carriers patrolled the main commercial area of Tangerang at dusk.</p>
<p>In central Java, Reuters Television producer Kenneth van Toll said tension was high in Pekalongan, a coastal city of one million which was hit by serious riots in early March before the election campaign started late last month.</p>
<p>She said troops with armoured cars moved in to clear the streets after a rally of some 10,000 people at which speakers condemned corruption and collusion in government.</p>
<p>The PPP, Golkar and the badly-split minority Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI) are the only three groups permitted to contest the polls for 425 seats in the House of Representatives. The other 75 seats are reserved for the military which does not vote.</p>
<p>Golkar has been in power under President Suharto for the past 30 years and is expected to win again easily next week.</p>
<p>Jakarta was tense through the day, with many schools closed and a number of offices shutting down early after violence between PPP and Golkar partisans earlier in the week.</p>
<p>The PPP campaigned on Friday on Java, home to 60 percent of the country's 200 million people, under an agreement between the three legal parties to carry their message to the voters in different areas on different days.</p>
<p>Reuters correspondent Jim Della-Giacoma reported that PPP leader Ismail Hasan Metareum played up the theme of corruption in government when he addressed about 5,000 people at Serang, 76 km (47 miles) west of Jakarta.</p>
<p>&quot;We want clean government which is not compromised by corruption or collusion...the PPP is the party of truth, honesty and justice,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Golkar is pushing to get over 70 percent of the vote compared to 68 percent in the last elections in 1992. It is widely expected to win comfortably.</p>
<p>Political and diplomatic analysts said there had been more air than substance in the campaign, in which Golkar pushed its development policies.</p>
<p>&quot;It turned out to be a contest for votes, but not a contest of substance,&quot; one analyst said.</p>
<p>The PPP won 17 percent of the vote in 1992 and the PDI 15 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
