<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609108" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: What price Taiwan's success at Europe parliament?.</title>
<headline>What price Taiwan's success at Europe parliament?.</headline>
<byline>Lawrence Chung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan on Friday hailed as a success its foreign minister's address to the European Parliament, but political analysts were deeply sceptical about its benefits in view of arch-rival China's vitriolic reaction.</p>
<p>Taiwan media trumpeted Foreign Minister John Chang's visit to the European legislature in Brussels on Thursday, calling it a breakthrough in Taiwan's drive to shake free of China's steadily tightening diplomatic embargo.</p>
<p>Chang slipped out of Taiwan on Monday for Belgium in the latest of a series of secretive overseas visits to promote Taiwan's relations with Europe.</p>
<p>Taipei would not confirm Chang's plan to address a committee of the European Parliament until just hours before he spoke, a gambit aiming to give Beijing little time to interfere.</p>
<p>State media said Chang would visit Luxembourg on Friday and unconfirmed reports said he would travel next to West Africa.</p>
<p>The foreign ministry hailed the European Parliament for &quot;defying the barbarism of the Chinese communists&quot; by offering Chang a forum despite Beijing's opposition and by condemning the intimidating war games that China mounted near Taiwan in the months before the island's March 1996 presidential election.</p>
<p>&quot;At a time of increased hardship in our international situation, it (the speech) was highly significant,&quot; the foreign ministry said in a statement.</p>
<p>China has considered Taiwan a rebel province since a civil war split them in 1949, leaving the mainland in communist hands and the island of 21 million with the defeated Nationalists.</p>
<p>Beijing has sought to isolate Taiwan in a quest to bring it under mainland rule, squeezing China's diplomatic partners to give Taiwan and its travelling officials no quarter.</p>
<p>Facing such pressure, Taiwan's diplomatic alliances have shrunk to a handful. With the recent loss of the Bahamas, only 30 states recognise Taiwan's exiled Republic of China. The number will fall to 29 when South Africa switches this year.</p>
<p>In a strongly worded protest, Beijing on Thursday condemned the European Parliament for inviting Chang to speak, calling this a serious encroachment on China's sovereignty and gross interference in China's internal affairs.</p>
<p>Analysts were unsure whether Chang's speech would help Taiwan or merely exacerbate Taiwan-China tensions.</p>
<p>They noted that President Lee Teng-hui's controversial 1995 U.S. visit infuriated Beijing, which responded by freezing what had been slowly warming semi-official contacts with Taipei.</p>
<p>&quot;The effect has yet to be seen,&quot; said Chu Hai-yuan of Academia Sinica, Taiwan's top academic institution.</p>
<p>Chu recalled that China retaliated for the U.S. trip a month after what Taiwan had billed as Lee's &quot;victorious return&quot; and ratcheted up the pressure with round after round of war games and missile tests that ended only after Taiwan's election in March 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Who would have thought the mainland would react that strongly?&quot; Chu said.</p>
<p>National Taiwan University law professor Shih Tzu-yi said Chang's European appearance was unlikely to bring change.</p>
<p>&quot;Try as he might, Chang cannot change our diplomatic condition,&quot; Shih said.</p>
<p>National Chengchi University diplomacy professor Lee Teng-ke said Chang's speech at most &quot;would increase EU understanding of Taiwan&quot; -- but could not be seen as a breakthrough.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
