<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609121" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore June gas oil breaks $25/bbl support.</title>
<headline>Singapore June gas oil breaks $25/bbl support.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore physical gas oil price broke the long-term support of $25.00 per barrel on Friday when a Swiss trader sold a 150,000-barrel cargo to a Japanese trader at $24.90, traders said.  </p>
<p>The cargo is for June 7-11 lifting, free-on-board (fob) Singapore basis.</p>
<p>This is the first time prompt gas oil has traded below $25.00 since August last year when it traded at $24.45 per barrel.</p>
<p>Following the first deal below the $25.00-mark, two more gas oil cargoes traded at $24.90 per barrel for a later date range--June 18-22. One cargo was sold by a Mediterranean trader to a Singapore trader and the other by a European major to a Japanese trader.  </p>
<p>Two other physical cargoes were traded earlier on Friday, with a Japanese trader buying the cargoes from a European major at $25.00 for June 7-11 and June 18-22 liftings fob.</p>
<p>Traders said the low levels traded underscored the bearish physical gas oil market with as many as eight offers seen on Friday.</p>
<p>They said the next support level for prompt gas oil is seen at $24.50 per barrel.  </p>
<p>Singapore is flushed with gas oil as reflected by the at least three-year high middle-distillates stocks level of 10.345 million barrels for the week ended June 21, the Trade Development Board said.</p>
<p>The market is also haunted by high stocks in China and Hong Kong as well as port congestions which are slowing China's imports.</p>
<p>Indonesia's appetite for June was also limited, with some traders estimating it at only 2.4 million barrels, after buying more than four million barrels each month in recent months.  </p>
<p>Swaps gas oil was also under pressure with the lowest traded level at $24.85 per barrel, brokers said.</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3084)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
