<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609116" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China pumps shares into markets to curb rises.</title>
<headline>China pumps shares into markets to curb rises.</headline>
<byline>Graham Earnshaw</byline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>China is pumping huge amounts of new domestic A shares into the stock markets to help cool them down, but investors' appetites show no signs so far of being sated, analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>The pace of share issues has hit a peak this past week with a dozen new A share firms issuing shares and nine others listing on the Shanghai or Shenzhen exchanges for the first time.</p>
<p>So far this year, A shares with a total face value of 4.2 billion yuan ($506 million) have been issued by 95 firms on the Shenzhen and Shanghai stock exchanges, two-thirds of them in Shenzhen.</p>
<p>&quot;There is too much 'hot money' (speculative funds) on the stock markets,&quot; said an A share trader. &quot;The central government wants to increase supply to depress excessive speculation.&quot;</p>
<p>This may not be easy.</p>
<p>Analysts said that given extremely high bank deposit levels and the large amounts of institutional funds washing around the Chinese financial system, it should not be difficult for such high levels of new issues to be absorbed in the short-term.</p>
<p>Total individual bank deposits alone currently stand at 4.15 trillion yuan, while the total capitalisation of China's stock markets currently stands at only 1.4 trillion yuan.</p>
<p>&quot;The pace of issues is incredible,&quot; said an investment analyst. &quot;But it won't bring the bubbling markets down so quickly.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Prices moved up so strongly in the first few months of this year partly due to a shortfall of stocks and the small capitalisation of the stock markets,&quot; said an executive with a major Chinese brokerage. &quot;On that basis, you can justify the move.&quot;</p>
<p>China's stock markets rose more than 50 percent in the first four months of this year despite repeated official warnings, largely on improved market fundamentals, with the economy in good shape and inflation falling.</p>
<p>The rise has also been supported by the euphuria surrounding China's takeover of the British colony of Hong Kong on July 1, analysts said.</p>
<p>Beijing last week announced a huge 1997 quota of 30 billion yuan for new domestic A share issues, compared with 15 billion for 1996. China usually announces each year's share listing quota at the end of the year.</p>
<p>Taking away the 4.2 billion yuan's worth of shares issued so far this year, the outstanding quota for share issues currently stands at around 41 billion yuan, for use either this year or beyond.</p>
<p>($1 = 8.29 yuan)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
