<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609151" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: YTL Power lists, raises 2.13 bln rgt.</title>
<headline>YTL Power lists, raises 2.13 bln rgt.</headline>
<byline>Christina Toh-Pantin</byline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia's second-largest independent power producer (IPP), YTL Power International Bhd, floated its stock in Kuala Lumpur on Friday in a listing that raised 2.13 billion ringgit for future expansions.</p>
<p>Its initial public offering (IPO), which debuted on the Kuala Lumpur Stock Exchange's main board, managed a moderate opening gain to 4.50 ringgit ($1.80), above the offer price of 3.40 ringgit before retracing to 3.82 ringgit by 0729 GMT.</p>
<p>YTL Power, a spin-off of infrastructure concern YTL Corp, had to roll out its IPO during poor stock market conditions, a point its management ruefully conceded.</p>
<p>Asked if he was satisfied with the opening price of YTL Power, managing director Francis Yeoh Sock Ping told reporters, &quot;the market is the market...sentiments affect it,&quot; adding, &quot;sentiment is not very good.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts said the stock performed within their expectations, but that its outlook will depend on new power projects, including joint ventures in Zimbabwe and China.</p>
<p>Malaysia's share market has been in a slump for almost two months amid concerns of slower growth after moves to restrict loans to the sector and to limit lending for stock purchases. The main board has shed 114.07 billion ringgit in market capitalisation from March 28 to May 16.</p>
<p>&quot;We estimated that Zimbabwe and China projects which are still under negotiation should contribute to a yearly net profit of 132.6 million ringgit and 61.2 million ringgit, respectively, upon full commissioning, or an addition of 10 cents per annum to its earnings per share,&quot; said Jupiter Securities analyst Janelle Chuah in a recent report.</p>
<p>Jupiter expects YTL Power to earn net profit of 376.4 million ringgit, or 19.7 cents a share, in the year ended December 1997 against 371.4 million ringgit, or 19.5 cents a share, in calendar 1996.</p>
<p>YTL Power has signed a letter of intent to buy a 51 percent stake in a joint venture with the Zimbabwe Electricity Supply Authority for the privatisation of the Hwange power station. A YTL Power venture is also taking up a 60 percent stake in the Nanchang Power Station to operate a coal-fired plant.</p>
<p>The outcome of both deals could weigh heavily in YTL Power's future, analysts said. &quot;I think people will watch the shares without buying them until they get hard news on Zimbabwe and China,&quot; said an equity analyst at a foreign broker.</p>
<p>But, YTL Power's Yeoh said that fair valuations of between 3.54 to 4.00 ringgit a share assessed by several brokers were conservative and did not take into account future projects.</p>
<p>&quot;That valuation (of brokerage firms) was in a bear market,&quot; Yeoh said. &quot;We have a tradition of rewarding our investors,&quot; he added, referring to YTL Corp's performance.</p>
<p>YTL Power, whose two plants have a combined capacity of 1,212 MW, ranks second in size to Malakoff Bhd It was the first IPP to be licensed in Malaysia in 1993.</p>
<p>In its IPO, YTL Power offered 235.6 million shares comprising a retail issue of 60.6 million shares priced at 3.40 ringgit each, and an institutional portion of 175 million shares priced at 4.00 ringgit.</p>
<p>YTL Power plans to use 1.16 billion ringgit of the proceeds toward financing the construction of power stations, with the balance to be used for future projects.</p>
<p>($1=2.5 ringgit)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
