<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609156" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Malaysia agrees to back Taiwan's WTO bid.</title>
<headline>Malaysia agrees to back Taiwan's WTO bid.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia has signed a pact with Taiwan to support the island's bid to join the World Trade Organisation (WTO), Taiwan's economics ministry said on Friday.</p>
<p>Malaysia also agreed to help Taiwan become a dialogue partner with the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN) and an observer in the Asia-Europe summit, the ministry said.</p>
<p>The agreement was signed at an economic cooperation forum between Taipei and Kuala Lumpur and came despite the lack of diplomatic ties between Taiwan and Malaysia, which recognises Taiwan's arch rival, communist China.</p>
<p>Taiwan has completed bilateral negotiations with 18 of the 26 WTO member nations that sought such talks, but has signed formal agreements with only 15, including Malaysia.</p>
<p>It still must complete talks with eight WTO members -- the United States, the European Union, Hong Kong, Canada, Singapore, Thailand, Switzerland and Argentina.</p>
<p>In the Kuala Lumpur forum, Taiwan agreed that after its WTO entry, it would reduce tariffs on six imported items of fruits or juice from Malaysia, a ministry statement said.  </p>
<p>Taipei agreed to consider whether to increase car imports from Malaysia if a trademark dispute between Malaysian-made Proton cars and Taiwan-made Proton electrical appliances can be solved, it said.</p>
<p>Taipei in July 1996 approved the import of 1,500 cars a year from Malaysia as part of a bid to liberalise its markets and join the WTO.</p>
<p>Taiwan applied in 1990 to join the WTO's predecessor, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, as a customs territory under the name of Chinese Taipei.</p>
<p>GATT was replaced by the WTO in January 1995.</p>
<p>Taiwan has made major concessions in recent years in its bid to join the world trade body, allowing more imports, opening up domestic markets and dismantling state monopolies.</p>
<p>Two major obstacles stand in Taiwan's path: opposition by the United States and some other WTO heavyweights that are demanding greater concessions from Taipei, and rival China's insistence that it be allowed to enter the WTO first.</p>
<p>Taiwan has revised its timetable for WTO entry to the end of 1997, though some analysts call this over-optimistic.  </p>
<p>China, which has regarded Taiwan as a renegade province since a civil war split them in 1949, faces serious hurdles in its own bid for WTO entry -- chiefly U.S., European, Canadian and Japanese pressure to ease market barriers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASEAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
