<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609148" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: S.E.Asian Cocoa - Prices mixed, Indonesia supply up.</title>
<headline>S.E.Asian Cocoa - Prices mixed, Indonesia supply up.</headline>
<byline>K.T. Arasu</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Southeast Asian cocoa prices were mixed on Friday, with Indonesian values easing in tandem with a sharp fall in New York while Malaysian levels bucked the trend on strong demand and tight supply, regional traders said.</p>
<p>Indonesian traders said supply from the current main crop harvest is increasing steadily, adding that arrivals in the first four months of this year exceeded volumes for the same 1996 period.  </p>
<p>&quot;Prices are a little weaker today following the sharp decline in New York overnight,&quot; one trader said. &quot;But prices are still generally high, and farmers are quite happy.&quot;</p>
<p>The traders said fair average quality (FAQ) cocoa beans were quoted at 3,025-3,050 rupiah/kg in Ujung Pandang, capital of the key growing region of South Sulawesi, against 3,060-3,075 rupiah on Thursday, and compared with 2,900-2,950 rupiah last week.</p>
<p>Cocoa was quoted at 3,532 rupiah/kg in the North Sumatran city of Medan, unchanged from Thursday.  </p>
<p>New York cocoa futures ended broadly lower on Thursday, with the July contract ending $23 down at $1,463 a tonne following a speculative sell-off.</p>
<p>&quot;Exporters are continuing to buy beans, but market activity is less hectic now,&quot; one trader said. &quot;The flow of beans is steady, and is readily available now.&quot;</p>
<p>The traders said bean arrivals in Sulawesi in April totalled 59,370 tonnes compared with 30,665 tonnes in March, 21,675 tonnes in February and 14,845 tonnes in January.  </p>
<p>They said arrivals in April 1996 on Sulawesi totalled 42,877 tonnes, 28,775 tonnes in March, 20,845 tonnes in February and 13,235 tonnes in January.</p>
<p>&quot;I expect May arrivals to be higher than in April,&quot; one trader said. &quot;I am now beginning to wonder if the peak of the main crop harvest that usually comes in May and stretches for two to three months will be shorter this year.&quot;</p>
<p>Another trader said demand remained strong, and that he expected prices to stay steady next week.  </p>
<p>&quot;Although the buying frenzy has quietened down, demand still remains strong,&quot; he said. &quot;Prices should be holding next week.&quot;</p>
<p>In Malaysia, prices rose despite the fall in New York futures. Traders said domestic demand for cocoa beans was strong while there was a lack of adequate supply.</p>
<p>Traders in the main growing area of Tawau in the East Malaysia state of Sabah told a Reuters survey last week that production for the April/May/June harvest could be 50 to 60 percent lower if compared the same period a year ago.</p>
<p>&quot;This is supposed to be a good harvest but it's bad, we'll be have to be importing a lot more,&quot; one trader said.  </p>
<p>On Wednesday, the Malaysian Cocoa Board quoted Standard Malaysian Cocoa (SMC) Grade 1A out of Tawau at an average of 3,488 ringgit a tonne and Grade 1B, also out of Tawau, at an average of 3,438 ringgit.</p>
<p>Compared to Tuesday, the 1A was down up 13 ringgit while the 1B was unchanged. But if compared to a week ago, both grades were up 145 ringgit and 128 ringgit, respectively.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, trading houses quoted the 1A at around 3,540 and the 1B at 3,460-3,470.</p>
<p>-- Jakarta newsroom + 6221 3846364</p>
<p>-- Baranee Krishnaan + Kuala Lumpur newsroom + 603-2307510</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
