<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609194" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: Heung Chang sees profit rising sharply.</title>
<headline>Heung Chang sees profit rising sharply.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea's Heung Chang Products Co expects its sales and net profit to rise sharply this year in line with growing demand for telecommunications equipment, a senior company official told Reuters on Friday.</p>
<p>Choi Myung-jin, manager of Heung Chang's strategic planning department, said the company saw this year's after-tax net profit rising to 8.5 billion won from 4.28 billion in 1996.  </p>
<p>&quot;Demand for our products is growing rapidly as subscribers to various telecommunications services are increasing,&quot; Choi said by telephone.</p>
<p>He said annual sales were estimated to grow to 150 billion won this year from 88.07 billion won in 1996.</p>
<p>The company specialises in making facilities for cellular phone relay systems and radio paging systems, and other electric equipment such as testing instruments.</p>
<p>Heung Chang's customers include SK Telecom Co, the nation's largest provider of cellular phone and radio paging services, and provincial radio pager operators, he said.  </p>
<p>Choi said he was confident that a consortium led by the company would be given a government licence to set up a cable television operation in the Koyang-Paju area near Seoul.</p>
<p>The area covers about 300,000 households and the cable service is expected to contribute to a sharp raising of Heung Chang's earnings, Choi said.</p>
<p>The licence is due to be handed over next week, he said.</p>
<p>Choi said the company's sales were projected to rise further to 250 billion won in 1998 and 400 billion won in 2000.</p>
<p>-- Seoul Newsroom (822) 727-5646</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I37100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
