<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609112" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Philippines looking for U.S. help if threatened.</title>
<headline>Philippines looking for U.S. help if threatened.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Thatcher</byline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of the Philippines' armed forces said on Thursday he had held informal discussions on possible U.S. military help if the country comes under threat.</p>
<p>The comments by General Arnulfo Acedera follow growing rancour in recent weeks between the Philippines and China over small islands and rocks in the South China Sea which both claim.</p>
<p>&quot;We talked about it (a contingency plan) superficially. When you are playing together among golfers, everything is possible,&quot; Acedera said, without naming his U.S. military golfing partners.</p>
<p>The commander of the U.S. Pacific Command, Admiral Jospeh Prueher, was in Manila earlier this week.</p>
<p>A U.S. embassy official said there had been no formal discussions on the issue.</p>
<p>Acedera said all he really wanted in an emergency was a show of strength rather than combat troops, pointing to the movement of the U.S. Seventh Fleet near to Taiwan last year when a dispute with China grew tense.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we should be satisfied with that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;For instance, if without being provoked, all of a sudden a superior force would subject (our territory)...to some form of harrassment, it would constitute...a contingency situation,&quot; Acedera said.</p>
<p>However, there were no concrete proposals and the matter would have to be agreed at a higher level, he said.</p>
<p>The United States ended its military presence in the Philippines nearly five years ago with the closure of the last of its two huge bases there.</p>
<p>Manila has accused Beijing of sending naval ships into the Spratly Islands, which it claims.</p>
<p>China insists the ships were research vessels and has demanded Manila stop all activity on an obscure group of rocks further north in the South China Sea, where Philippine fishermen recently hoisted their national flag.</p>
<p>The Philippines has been pressing China to stick to an earlier agreement that binds the two to do nothing in the disputed area that would be seen as threatening.</p>
<p>Acedera this week warned China that it risked being branded a bully over its behaviour in the contested Spratly islands.</p>
<p>The Philippines is also looking at allowing U.S. naval ships to use Subic Bay, the former U.S. Navy base north of Manila, for refuelling and other support needs, Acedera said.</p>
<p>U.S. naval ships stopped calling at the port last December until the two sides could sort out an agreement on the status of U.S. servicemen once they were on Philippine soil.</p>
<p>The U.S. Embassy said there were no formal discussions on the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no ongoing discussions, nor are the U.S. and the Philippines engaged in any negotiations for increased use of Subic Bay facilities,&quot; a U.S. official said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
