<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609168" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: KL shares finish firmer, gains selective.</title>
<headline>KL shares finish firmer, gains selective.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Selective buying in timber and some motor shares helped Kuala Lumpur stocks to a firmer close on Friday, although small-cap issues took a breather from a run-up earlier in the week, dealers said.</p>
<p>At the close, the Composite Index of 100 leading blue chips ended up 7.17 points or 0.67 percent to 1,078.20. The Second Board index, which surged nearly four percent on Thursday, edged up 0.73 points or 0.13 percent to 565.71.</p>
<p>Newly listed YTL Power accounted for over 42 million shares, and was the heaviest-traded stock, closing at 3.70 ringgit against an offer price of 3.40.  </p>
<p>&quot;(National carmaker) Proton has done very well,&quot; noted Jonathan Duckett, an institutional dealer at Mohaiyani Securities. &quot;It's rebounding on the back of the yen problem.&quot;</p>
<p>Proton and other motor stocks had been weaker in the last few weeks on fears a stronger yen would crimp profits because of higher import costs. On Friday, Proton rose 90 cents to 12.90 ringgit.</p>
<p>Tan Chong Motor Holdings, which distributes Nissan vehicles, said on Friday it was not too concerned about the yen's rise, as unit costs were still below last year's. Its stock added 16 cents to 4.44 ringgit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
