<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609124" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: FOCUS-China stocks end mostly up but sentiment weak.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-China stocks end mostly up but sentiment weak.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's share indices ended mostly higher on a technical rebound on Friday after a week of steep falls, but brokers said market sentiment was weak on fears of further anti-speculation measures by authorities.</p>
<p>The Shanghai B index fell 0.196 points or 0.24 percent to 82.387 points while the Shenzhen B index rose 2.33 points or 1.55 percent to 153.19.</p>
<p>Shanghai's A share index gained 20.514 points or 1.59 percent to 1,310.627 points and the Shenzhen A index rose 3.58 points or 0.85 percent to 425.72.</p>
<p>&quot;The indices rose on bargain-hunting as short-term technical indicators showed stocks looked oversold after yesterday's sharp drops,&quot; an analyst at Shenzhen J&amp;A Securities said.</p>
<p>&quot;The markets have not bottomed out and strong downward pressure looms ahead.&quot;</p>
<p>Brokers said the movement of the indices on Monday would depend on whether there were further announcements over the weekend by the government to cool down stock trading.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very clear that Beijing is determined to dampen share volatility and investors will be bearish about the markets in the near future,&quot; an analyst at Central-South Securities said.</p>
<p>Beijing on Wednesday announced it would ban state enterprises and listed firms from speculative stock trading, a move brokers said was clearly aimed at curbing the inflow of &quot;hot money&quot; into the country's overheated stock markets.</p>
<p>The announcement sent share prices in Shenzhen and Shanghai into freefall on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Institutions are not willing to build large positions under such unfavourable conditions,&quot; one broker said. &quot;More clampdown measures are seen as being possible in the short term.&quot;</p>
<p>On the Shanghai B share market, Shanghai Rubber Belt was the biggest loser, plunging $0.020 or 8.84 percent to $0.206 on volume of 50,000 shares.</p>
<p>Inner Mongolia Erdos Cashmere was the most actively traded with its 100 million new shares listed today. It slipped $0.060 or 6.55 percent to $0.856 on volume of 5.3 million shares.</p>
<p>On the Shenzhen B share market, newcomer Nanjing Posts &amp; Telecommunication was the most actively traded with a volume of 6.93 million shares. It rose HK$0.20 or 4.81 percent to HK$4.36 on institutional buying, brokers said.</p>
<p>Nanjing Posts, which issued 100 million B shares at HK$2.43 per share earlier this month, began trading on Thursday.</p>
<p>On the Shenzhen A share market, Shenzhen Development Bank rose 2.41 yuan or 6.58 percent to 39.05 yuan, the most heavily traded counter with 41 million shares changing hands, despite a continuing investigation into alleged stock trading irregularities.</p>
<p>Traders said investors happy with the bank's dividend plans, to be confirmed at a shareholders' meeting next Monday.</p>
<p>($1=8.3 yuan, $1=HK$7.8)</p>
<p>-- Shanghai newsroom (86-21) 6279-7004</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
