<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609172" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: DBS Bank reorganises Indonesia units.</title>
<headline>DBS Bank reorganises Indonesia units.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Development Bank of Singapore Ltd (DBS) said on Friday it was reorganising its holdings in the Indonesian banking sector,</p>
<p>It said in a statement it had entered a conditional agreement with the Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi Ltd, to buy an 85 pct stake in PT Mitsubishi Buana Bank (MBB) for a cash sum of 131.75 billion rupiah (about Singapore $79 million).  </p>
<p>DBS Bank also said it had agreed to sell its 42.5 percent shareholding in PT DBS Buana Tat Lee Bank (DBT) to Tat Lee Bank for 78.45 billion rupiah (about S$47 million).</p>
<p>DBS president and chief operating officer Ng Kee Choe said in a statement: &quot;With our proposed acquisition of 85 percent and control of PT Mitsubishi Buana Bank, we have decided to divest our stake in DBT to Tat Lee Bank.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We are now better positioned to further expand our banking operations in Indonesia through MBB, in which we will have controlling interest and will manage,&quot; Ng said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We will widen the scope of our activities, offer more services and expand the branch network beyond Jakarta and Surabaya to other cities in Indonesia,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>After DBS' acquisition of 85 percent of MBB, PT Bank Buana Indonesia would retain its original 15 percent equity stake.</p>
<p>The DBS statement said approvals from the Monetary Authority of Singapore, Bank Indonesia and the Ministry of Finance of Indonesia had been obtained for DBS Bank's acquisition of MBB.</p>
<p>It said the purchase of MBB would be funded by internal resources.  </p>
<p>The proposed transaction will not have a material impact on the consolidated net tangible assets or earnings per share of the DBS group for the financial year ending December 31, 1997.</p>
<p>As a result of the acquisition in DBT, Tat Lee will hold an 85 percent stake.</p>
<p>Ng said at a news briefing DBS was planning to expand the activities of MBB with the addition of four more branches across Indonesia.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't have any time frame yet and a lot will depend on how long we take to get our staff prepared for the expansion.&quot;  </p>
<p>Ng also said the opportunity to buy into MBB resulted from the merger of Bank of Tokyo and Mitsubishi Bank.</p>
<p>An official from Tat Lee Bank said the rearrangement of assets in Indonesia was of mutual benefit to both banks.</p>
<p>--Singapore newsroom (65 870 3080)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
