<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609141" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MACAU: Macau police make arrests linked to crime wave.</title>
<headline>Macau police make arrests linked to crime wave.</headline>
<dateline>MACAU 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police in Macau may have made some progress on Friday in their battle against a crime wave in the Portuguese-run enclave, saying they had arrested a man for arson and another two possibly linked to an execution-style killing.</p>
<p>In a statement, police commander Colonel Fernando Pinto Ribeiro said two illegal immigrants were arrested in the act of burgling the home of the mother of a nurse murdered last month.</p>
<p>Ribeiro said the men were possibly involved in the slaying of the nurse, which police have described as &quot;execution style&quot;.</p>
<p>Chinese media in the enclave reported the two immigrants from central China were hired to kill the nurse, who was married to the manager of a company that operates a helicopter shuttle service linking Macau and neighbouring Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Tiny Macau, a territory of 455,000 people perched on China's southern coast, has been hit by a surge in violent crime linked to a turf war over gambling-related businesses between rival mafia-style criminal gangs called &quot;triads&quot;.</p>
<p>Fifteen people have been murdered so far this year compared to 21 for the whole of last year, and there have been a series of beatings and arson attacks.</p>
<p>Ribeiro's statement also said police caught a man suspected of being behind a string of arson attacks in the enclave, including the torching of 25 motorcycles outside a police station in February.</p>
<p>The arrest of the 23-year-old man appeared to rule out theories that the motorcycles were set ablaze by triads as a challenge to police authority.</p>
<p>The suspect allegedly committed the arson attacks as a form of &quot;protest&quot; after being sacked from his job at a bank over suspected links to a fraud case, the statement said.</p>
<p>The suspect is now in custody awaiting trial in both the arson and fraud cases.</p>
<p>Police officials from China and Macau agreed on Monday to strengthen cooperation in the fight against cross-border crime.</p>
<p>The enclave shares a 240-metre land border with China and Macau police believe many crimes are committed by mainland Chinese who are able to flee back into China within minutes.</p>
<p>The enclave returns to Chinese rule on December 20, 1999.</p>
<p>The latest surge in crime has even led the United States and Australia to issue warngings to their citizens in Macau.</p>
<p>&quot;U.S. citizens visiting Macau should be aware that the problems have been localised near the casinos during early morning hours and appear to be related to organised crime,&quot; the U.S. State Department said in a statement.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MACAO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MACAU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MACAU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
