<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609199" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asian trade sees LME copper/zinc rising further.</title>
<headline>Asian trade sees LME copper/zinc rising further.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>London Metal Exchange (LME) copper and zinc prices are tipped to post further gains later on Friday, but the red metal is seen ripe for a correction in the next few days, Far East traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;The trend is up, but copper is due for a big correction,&quot; one dealer said. &quot;I think it (three month) will reach US$2,560-$2,570 (a tonne) before it comes down.&quot;</p>
<p>Three month copper was seen by regional dealers at 0330 GMT at $2,505/10 a tonne, slightly easier from the late London quote on Thursday of $2,507/10.  </p>
<p>Metal brokers Brandeis said that copper continued &quot;to look robust but a pullback is now overdue with the market needing to confirm support in the $2,470/90 area before mustering sufficient strength to attain the $2,550 target.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Copper needs to go down. It's badly over-extended,&quot; another dealer said.</p>
<p>The current price of the red metal has drawn interest from Chinese merchants &quot;who are looking at making some sales soon,&quot; a trader said.  </p>
<p>Zinc prices, on the other hand, are expected to approach the $1,400 a tonne barrier later on Friday after hitting a high of $1,370 on the LME on Thursday -- the highest level since September 1992. Zinc eventually closed at $1,364.</p>
<p>&quot;There'll be a lot of selling when zinc hits $1,385, especially from the Chinese,&quot; one dealer said, adding some of the Chinese were already unloading material in Asian trade.</p>
<p>&quot;The price may be a bit overdone. I'm very bullish on zinc, but I'm surprised it got here so soon. There's still plenty of zinc in Asia,&quot; another dealer said.  </p>
<p>Traders estimate about 15,000-20,000 tonnes of zinc remain off-warrant in warehouses in Singapore and that an additional 5,000 tonnes of zinc from China will arrive in the city-state this week.</p>
<p>Three month zinc was quoted by the trade at 0330 GMT at $1,362/66 a tonne.</p>
<p>-- Rene Pastor, Singapore Newsroom (65-8703305)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
