<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609107" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Vietnam's corporate star Huy Hoang denies problems.</title>
<headline>Vietnam's corporate star Huy Hoang denies problems.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Vietnam's Huy Hoang company, a shining example of the communist country's switch to market economics, denied on Friday that it had followed other prominent conglomerates to the brink of bankruptcy.</p>
<p>&quot;At present we have no problems with cash,&quot; said Nguyen Duc Lam, secretary to the company chairman. &quot;People are creating lots of bad rumours to pull Huy Hoang down.&quot;</p>
<p>He was explaining a report in the official daily Vietnam News that quoted Chairman Le Van Kiem as saying the company had not invested heavily in the crisis-torn property market.</p>
<p>Doubts about the textiles-to-infrastructure company had been raised by its decision to go into partnership with state-owned companies.</p>
<p>However, Lam said that Ho Chi Minh City-based Huy Hoang was not looking to bolster its capital by taking state-owned firms into his shareholding structure.</p>
<p>Instead, it was in talks with four state companies to set up a new joint venture, in which it would hold a 70-percent share.</p>
<p>Kiem said the new organisation would combine the best of private and state-run enterprise, creating what the ruling Communist Party terms a &quot;state capitalist company&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;By blending the dynamism and effectiveness of the private sector with the state's tight management, the state capitalist company will become very productive,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Kiem, a former Communist Party member, founded Huy Hoang in 1990 with initial capital of $1 million.</p>
<p>The company thrived in the country's reform-led boom -- as did Kiem, who flaunted his personal wealth with diamond-encrusted watches and a fleet of Mercedes and Rolls Royce cars.</p>
<p>News of his plans to link up with state-owned firms came amid a flurry of bad news about other prominent companies that had embarked on headlong investment drives and then run into trouble.</p>
<p>The heads of the private-sector companies Minh Phung and Epco were arrested in March for alleged fraud linked to loans for investment in the property market, which has gone from boom to bust. Thirteen more Minh Phung executives were arrested last week.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I45300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
