<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609133" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesia palm olein weaker in quiet trade.</title>
<headline>Indonesia palm olein weaker in quiet trade.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesian palm olein prices were weaker in late trading on Friday as buyers stayed sidelined amid reports of election-related violence in Jakarta, traders said.</p>
<p>They said palm olein was quoted at 1,420 rupiah/kg in Jakarta, down from 1,425-30 rupiah at the opening.</p>
<p>&quot;There was hardly any movement in the market today because of reports of violence in the city,&quot; one trader said. &quot;Many players closed early, while others did not open at all.&quot;</p>
<p>Another trader said his business had ground to a halt as his buyers showed no interest in purchasing oil because of the tense situation in the capital.  </p>
<p>The traders said demand was expected to remain weak until after the elections, adding that players were likely to stay cautious next week although the campaign ends on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices are likely to ease further next week as demand will continue to be poor,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;They did not want to take the risk of ordering oil today because of the situation in the capital,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Violence flared between supporters of the ruling Golkar party and the Moslem-oriented United Development Party (PPP) on Friday, the final day of the campaign for the May 29 election.</p>
<p>Witnesses said police fired tear gas and warning shots into the air to break up a clash between the two groups in the Ciputat area in south Jakarta.</p>
<p>&quot;There was hardly any activity in the market today because of reports of violence and, more so, because of the swirling rumours of riots and disturbances,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>-- K.T. Arasu, Jakarta newsroom + 6221 384-6364</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
