<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609142" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore to charge Tang with income tax offences.</title>
<headline>Singapore to charge Tang with income tax offences.</headline>
<byline>Raj Rajendran</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore opposition politician Tang Liang Hong, who fled the city-state after January elections and faces record libel damages, is to be charged with income tax offences.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for the Inland Revenue Authority of Singapore (IRAS) told Reuters the charges would be laid formally in court later on Friday.</p>
<p>She declined to specify the charges.</p>
<p>In late January, the IRAS seized tax documents from Tang's home and office. It also barred Tang's wife, Teo Siew Har, from leaving the country.</p>
<p>The Home (Interior) Ministry said then the IRAS suspected Teo may have been involved in the administration of Tang's tax matters.</p>
<p>Tang fled Singapore, saying he had received death threats, after losing a bid for a seat in the Singapore parliament.</p>
<p>He was sued for libel by Prime Minister Goh Chok Tong and 10 other senior members of the ruling People's Action Party (PAP), which won 81 of the 83 seats at stake in the election, after calling them liars.</p>
<p>Goh had accused Tang of being an &quot;anti-Christian Chinese chauvinist&quot; who endangered Singapore's racial harmony.</p>
<p>Tang did not return to defend himself and the cases were awarded to the PAP leaders, who demanded a record S$12.9 million (US$9 million) in libel damages at a later hearing. A judgment on the amount of damages is still awaited.</p>
<p>Tang intends to appeal against the judgment when it is announced and against other aspects of the libel cases, his lawyer told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said High Court Justice Goh Joon Seng agreed on Friday that Tang could bring senior lawyer Charles Gray from London to conduct the appeals.</p>
<p>Goh also referred to the three-judge Court of Appeals a motion by Tang to reverse an earlier court decision that told him to pay the legal costs of a hearing which agreed that former prime minister Lee Kuan Yew could have remarks deleted from an affidavit made in pursuit of his libel case against Tang.</p>
<p>Lee had referred to Johore, the south Malaysian state to which Tang fled, as &quot;notorious&quot; for crime.</p>
<p>The leak of the comment unleashed fury in Malaysia and a major diplomatic spat that rumbled on, despite two Lee apologies, until the Singapore elder statesman announced he would ask the court to delete the remark from the record.</p>
<p>Lee said Tang was responsible for the diplomatic row because he leaked the affidavit and the court agreed, awarding legal costs for the hearing against Tang.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
