<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609134" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Malaysia rubber ends steady despite Tokyo's fall.</title>
<headline>Malaysia rubber ends steady despite Tokyo's fall.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysian rubber prices ended the week steady on sheet grade covering but dealing continued listless as buyers stayed at the sidelines in anticipation of falling prices, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Consumers are not committing themselves although local prices are much lower than other producers like Thailand and Indonesia,&quot; a dealer said. &quot;Thailand raw materials have gone much dearer after the recent government intervention.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Buyers from Asia, like the Chinese and South Koreans were just making their enquiries but did not buy anything. They know prices will dip further as Tokyo was bearish.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;There is a surplus of raw materials in the local market and local suppliers are lowering prices to attract buyers,&quot; another dealer at a trading firm said.</p>
<p>Several local glove manufacturers were making enquiries for nearby latex rubber and some trades have been transacted.</p>
<p>Dealers were unable to confirm exact transactions as business was done from hand-to-mouth basis.</p>
<p>Trading houses quoted SMR CV at 328 -330 cents, SMR L at 305-307 cents, SMR 10 at 260-262 and drum latex at 226. June RSS 1 buyer was officially closed at 278.50 cents ($1.11) a kg, up a cent from Thursday, and June SMR 20 buyer was unchanged at 264</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
