<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609131" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan begins to tire of ritual resignations.</title>
<headline>Japan begins to tire of ritual resignations.</headline>
<byline>Linda Sieg</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>More top executives performed Japan's resignation ritual on Friday, but critics are questioning whether these public acts of contrition should really bring absolution for corporate scandals.</p>
<p>Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank said on Friday that its president and chairman would resign as a gesture of remorse over the bank's links to an alleged corporate extortionist, or &quot;sokaiya&quot;, who has been accused of taking illegal payoffs from Japan's top brokerage, Nomura Secutities.</p>
<p>In a pattern that has become all-too predictable, both men agreed to accept symbolic blame for the affair, bow out, and slip into lower profile posts as advisers to the bank.</p>
<p>But this time, powerful voices in government have complained that these atonement rites are mere gestures which appear to acknowledge blame but in fact avoid responsibility.</p>
<p>The move follows raids this week on DKB, a leading Japanese commercial bank, by prosecutors investigating a scandal over links between the racketeer and Japanese finance.</p>
<p>Two Nomura presidents and 15 other top executives at the giant brokerage have already stepped down since the scandal broke in March.</p>
<p>In another unrelated case, the president of Nikko Securities Investment Trust and Management Co, an affiliate of &quot;Big Four&quot; brokerage Nikko Securities, said on Thursday he and three other executives planned to resign over illegal bond deals done in 1994.</p>
<p>Last month, seasoning maker Ajinomoto Co Inc announced the resignation of its president Shunsuke Inamori over a scandal in which two company officials were arrested and indicted on suspicion of making illegal payments to sokaiya. Inamori was to become chairman but with no voting rights on the board.</p>
<p>Trading house Sumitomo Corp said in March that two board members who had been superiors of one-time rogue copper trader Yasuo Hamanaka were stepping down -- but would remain advisers to the company -- over the scandal in which Hamanaka racked up $2.6 billion in losses on unauthorised copper trades.</p>
<p>At long last, however, some critics are expressing outrage.</p>
<p>&quot;It's sneaky (for the DKB leadership) to step down to take the blame,&quot; Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto said on Thursday as media reported the DKB executives were poised to resign.</p>
<p>&quot;Their resigning does not settle the problem. They should face up to the case until investigations make headway.&quot;</p>
<p>Finance Minister Hiroshi Mitsuzuka echoed the remarks on Friday, before DKB's announcement, telling reporters: &quot;Such resignations would not mean the bank has carried out its responsibilities.&quot;</p>
<p>Sensitive to the criticism, DKB president-designate Ichiro Fujita said on Friday the bank did not see the resignations, which will take effect next month, as obviating the need to take responsibility.</p>
<p>Ironically, Hashimoto himself followed the time-honoured script by giving up his finance portfolio in 1991 to take the blame for his ministry's failure to stop top bankers and brokers including Nomura from flouting ethical guidelines.</p>
<p>Analysts agree the practice of symbolic corporate suicide does little to solve the problems at the root of such scandals.</p>
<p>&quot;You've got people falling on their swords in the old fashion, but there is no one taking responsibility,&quot; said Jesper Koll, chief economist at JP Morgan in Tokyo. &quot;It's a pro forma resignation without anyone being held accountable.&quot;</p>
<p>The fate of Japan's former ambassador to Peru Morihisa Aoki, however, shows that for many Japanese, public shows of humility remain important.</p>
<p>Aoki, hailed as a hero during the 127-day Lima hostage crisis, was fired last week after stating he wanted to stay on at least until an investigation into the incident was finished.</p>
<p>Japanese tabloids had lashed Aoki upon his return home for alleged security lapses which allowed rebel guerrillas to storm a reception at his Lima residence last December and take hundreds of guests hostage.</p>
<p>But after he was fired, other domestic media acknowledged that Aoki's outspoken personality and his refusal to show the requisite remorse made him an easy scapegoat and target for forced resignation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
