<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609135" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Many Japan big banks return to profit in 96/97.</title>
<headline>Many Japan big banks return to profit in 96/97.</headline>
<byline>Fumiko Fujisaki</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most of Japan's top 10 commercial banks survived falling stock prices and bad loan losses to emerge with reasonable profits in the last business year.</p>
<p>Only Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank Ltd (DKB), currently under fire for its role in a racketeer payoff scandal, reported a parent current loss of 350 billion yen ($3.01 billion).</p>
<p>Parent current profit at the other nine banks ranged from 95 billion yen ($818 million) by Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi Ltd to 1.04 billion yen ($8.9 million) by Hokkaido Takushoku Bank Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;We've posted our first ever loss. But since we've carried out loan write-offs actively, from 1997/98 we should be able to cope with the problem without relying on latent profits in our securities holdings,&quot; a DKB executive told reporters.</p>
<p>Current profit is pretax and includes gains or losses on non-operating activities such as investments in stocks.</p>
<p>In 1995/96, seven out of the 10 big banks -- Sakura Bank Ltd, Fuji Bank Ltd, Sakura Bank Ltd, Tokai Bank Ltd, Asahi Bank Ltd, Daiwa Bank Ltd, and Hokkaido Takushoku  -- posted parent current losses as they disposed of massive problem loans.</p>
<p>Banks continued huge loan write-offs in 1996/97 to cover expected losses from falling domestic property prices.</p>
<p>The 10 banks said that they disposed of problem loans worth about 3.35 trillion yen ($28.8 billion) in 1996/97 against about 6.3 trillion yen ($54.3 billion) in 1995/96.</p>
<p>DKB wrote off the biggest amount of problem loans in 1996/97 -- 620 billion yen ($5.34 billion). Sakura disposed of problem loans worth 503 billion yen ($4.33 billion).</p>
<p>A 16 percent decline in Tokyo's stock market in 1996/97 also hit earnings.</p>
<p>The 10 banks expect operating profits from the banking business in 1997/98 to fall to a total of 2.32 trillion yen ($20.0 billion) from 2.7 trillion yen ($23.2 billion) in 1996/97 and 3.5 trillion yen ($30.1 billion) in 1995/96.</p>
<p>An expected decline in operating profits in 1997/98 reflects prospects for higher interest rates which would increase banks' funding costs, executives said.</p>
<p>The Bank of Japan (BOJ) is coming under growing pressure to raise interest rates as the nation's economic recovery seems fairly robust.</p>
<p>The discount rate has been at a record low 0.5 percent since September 8, 1995 to help economic recovery. It contributed to  banks' good operating profits in 1995/96 and in 1996/97.</p>
<p>The 10 banks all forecast parent current profits for 1997/98.</p>
<p>However, financial sources said some may revise forecasts downward later, as they to try to clear up bad loans to meet stricter capital adequacy standards.</p>
<p>Japan is scheduled to introduce the new adequacy standards from the end of the 1997/98 business year, in order to bolster confidence in Japan's banking sector by keeping a closer watch on the quality of bank assets.</p>
<p>Faced with pressure to build up stronger capital positions, some big banks such as DKB, Asahi, Sanwa and Sumitomo Trust &amp; Banking Co Ltd are expected to issue preferred stocks in 1997/98, they said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
