<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609109" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai baht steady, interbank rate up further.</title>
<headline>Thai baht steady, interbank rate up further.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Thai baht remained in a arrow range against the dollar in offshore and local markets, with most players reluctant to take any new positions due to the central bank's persistent measures to support the currency, dealers said.</p>
<p>The baht was quoted at 25.780/25.810 to the dollar in local market late against 25.790/25.810 in early morning. In offshore market, the baht was traded at 25.480/25.580 compared with 25.530/25.580 earlier.</p>
<p>The mid-rate was fixed at 25.79 per dollar against 25.75 on Thursday.  </p>
<p>&quot;Most players will continue to stay sidelined until the central bank's measures are lifted. They are unwilling to take any positions,&quot; said one dealer at a foreign bank.</p>
<p>The Bank of Thailand has maintained its ban on short-term baht lending to foreign buyers following heavy offshore speculative attacks on the baht last week.</p>
<p>The order to Thai-based banks not to quote dollar/baht swap rates to foreign buyers has sharply tightened baht supply in the offshore market where the Thai unit is being traded higher than the midrate and the level in the local market.  </p>
<p>Bank of Thailand governor governor Rerngchai Marakanond said on Thursday the central bank would maintain its ban on baht lending by Thai financial institutions to offshore players until the situation normalised for the Thai currency.</p>
<p>The central bank's measure has created two dollar/baht rates for offshore and onshore markets since last week, dealers said.</p>
<p>The one-month baht/dollar swap premium was traded at 50/70 satangs per dollar late versus 45/85 in early morning.</p>
<p>The overnight interbank rate firmed to 14.00-14.50 percent late from 13.50-14.00 in morning trade on the bank's early borrowings of funds for the next round of liquidity reserve requirement due on June 7, dealers said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Small local banks were quite short of funds today. They are borrowing funds for next reserve requirement,&quot; said one money market dealer.</p>
<p>All commercial banks have to meet the Bank of Thailand's reserve requirement on the seventh and 22nd of each month.</p>
<p>-- Anuchit Nguyen (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
