<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609128" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Regional Japan broker applies for liquidation.</title>
<headline>Regional Japan broker applies for liquidation.</headline>
<dateline>OSAKA, Japan 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A regional Japanese broker affiliated with Yamaichi Securities Co Ltd said on Friday it had filed a bankruptcy application after huge losses in speculative margin trading.</p>
<p>Ogawa Securities, based in Osaka, said it had filed with the Finance Ministry to discontinue operations, after Yamaichi refused it financial aid.</p>
<p>If the application is accepted, Ogawa would become the first brokerage to go bankrupt in Japan in 17 years.</p>
<p>Ogawa's business has been in trouble due to a stock market slump following the bursting of Japan's asset-inflated &quot;bubble&quot; economy of the late 1980s.</p>
<p>Its condition worsened after it suffered losses from speculative margin trading earlier this year.</p>
<p>Japan's Kyodo news agency said Tokuo Namba, president of Ogawa Securities, told a news conference in Osaka that he was responsible for the decision to get involved in the speculative trades which brought about the huge losses.</p>
<p>Yamaichi, one of Japan's &quot;Big Four&quot; brokers, said that it would still provide funds to protect Ogawa customers.</p>
<p>Ogawa's clients may also get protection from the joint deposit insurance system, a fund set up in 1968 from donations from about 150 member brokerages, the fund's chairman said in a statement.</p>
<p>Yamaichi vice president Ryuji Shirai told a news conference: &quot;Considering Ogawa's huge loss, its financial condition and earning power, we cannot expect Ogawa's financial standing to improve greatly even if we provide support.&quot;</p>
<p>Shirai said continuing to give assistance to Ogawa would also be &quot;a great risk&quot; for Yamaichi.</p>
<p>Before applying for liquidation, Ogawa will write off the losses using two billion yen ($17.2 million) to be presented from the investor protection fund, Finance Ministry officials said. ($1=116 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OSAKA, Japan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
