<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609188" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Bank of Thailand ready if finance merger collapses.</title>
<headline>Bank of Thailand ready if finance merger collapses.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thailand's deputy central bank governor Jaroong Nookhwun said on Friday the authorities are prepared to contain any damage that the financial sector may face from if there is a collapse in alliance talks between Thai Danu Bank Plc and Finance One Plc.</p>
<p>Jaroong told reporters the Bank of Thailand had tried its best to facilitate the alliance between the two companies, which would be the biggest link-up in the Thai finance industry.</p>
<p>Thai Danu and Finance One were expected to give an update on their talks later on Friday.  </p>
<p>Finance Minister Amnuay Viravan said on Friday that the delay in wrapping up the Thai Danu-Finance One talks partly stemmed from problems encountered by auditors assessing the two companies' assets.</p>
<p>The two companies were due to have voted on their alliance in late April but the decision has been postponed several times.</p>
<p>Amnuay said Thai Danu may have to decide to initially acquire shares in Finance One as the first step of their eventual merger.</p>
<p>Jaroong said if the merger talks fail, the central bank may help strengthen Finance One by raising its capital. He did not elaborate.</p>
<p>Finance One, the biggest Thai finance company, has been saddled with a large amount of non-performing loans extended to the troubled Thai property sector.</p>
<p>-- Bangkok newsroom (662)-652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
