<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609290" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Big nations agree to criminalize business bribery.</title>
<headline>Big nations agree to criminalize business bribery.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Rich Miller, Economics Correspondent</p>
<p>The United States and its fellow industrial nations agreed on Friday on a plan to criminalize business bribery of foreign public officials, U.S. officials said.</p>
<p>The pact, reached at the Paris-based Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), came after several years of protracted negotiations and should be a big plus for U.S. companies competing in world markets, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;This agreement is a major step forward in curbing international bribery,&quot; Commerce Secretary William Daley said in a statement.</p>
<p>U.S. companies have been prohibited by law for two decades from paying bribes to foreign officials to win business in developing countries and elsewhere. But their competitors in other industrial nations have not been subject to such restrictions, putting U.S. firms at a disadvantage.</p>
<p>The payment of kickbacks to government officials to win business contracts is rampant throughout much of the developing world. Washington reckons that U.S. companies lost out in some 100 business deals worth about $45 billion over the last two years because of bribes by their competitors.</p>
<p>&quot;Bribery is a major distortion of international trade and has a corrosive effect on economic and political development,&quot; Daley said.</p>
<p>Under the pact reached on Friday, the 29 nations that make up the OECD agreed to introduce legislation by April 1, 1998, to make bribery of foreign public officials in international business transactions a crime, U.S. officials said.</p>
<p>They also agreed to open negotiations promptly on a treaty to accomplish that same end, the officials said. The negotatiations are supposed to be wound up by December, with the treaty ratified and in force by the end of next year.</p>
<p>The two-track approach appeared to be a compromise between the United States on the one hand and France and Germany on the other. The two European countries had balked at introducing legislation to criminalize bribery before an international treaty was in place, out of fear that their companies would be put at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
<p>In reaching the agreement, Daley said he worked closely with French Finance Minister Jean Arthuis and German Economics Minister Guenter Rexrodt.</p>
<p>U.S. Commerce Department officials, who declined to be identified, said the latest pact had more teeth than past efforts by the OECD to ban bribery. They said that Daley had been assured by Arthuis that the talks on a treaty would begin promptly and would not last more than a few months.</p>
<p>&quot;We are optimistic,&quot; one official told Reuters. &quot;This is going to make a big difference for U.S. companies.&quot;</p>
<p>The agreement to ban bribery is expected to be endorsed by ministers at next week's annual meeting of the OECD in Paris. Daley is leading the U.S. delegation to that meeting.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="OECD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
