<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609213" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: TURKISH SHARES EDGE LOWER ON POLITICAL CONCERNS.</title>
<headline>TURKISH SHARES EDGE LOWER ON POLITICAL CONCERNS.</headline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Istanbul shares eased in quiet trade on Friday amid persisting political worries, brokers said.</p>
<p>The IMKB National-100  .XU100 closed at 1,467, down four points, or 0.27 percent from Thursday. Over the week, it lost 1.7 percent. Trade volume firmed slightly to 12.03 trillion lira from Thursday's 11.01 trillion.</p>
<p>Brokers said the resignation of a second deputy from the conservative True Path Party (DYP), the junior coalition partner, sparked selling in early afternoon trade and caused the index to fall to a low of 1,447. It rebounded in late trade.</p>
<p>&quot;Such resignations prompted sales at first, but afterwards there was buying on expectations of a new government. But it is not possible to expect a healthy rise until political stability is restored,&quot; sid Erden Gokay from Taksim securities.</p>
<p>DYP deputy Hikmet Aydin gave his resignation in the afternoon after Samil Ayrim stepped down in a row over Islamist activism earlier in the day.</p>
<p>Brokers await initial support at 1,450 and firmer support at 1,400.</p>
<p>&quot;The thought that the Islamist-led coalition is unraveling negatively affects the market. On the other hand, the expectation of an alternative (secularist) alliance is vague. Therefore, I expect the index to go down towards 1,380 in coming days,&quot; said Serdar Surer from Ekinciler securities.</p>
<p>The market awaits two meetings to be attended by top military generals and Islamist Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan. A Supreme Military Council meets on May 26 and the monthly National Security Council (NSC) meeting is due May 31.</p>
<p>The NSC had urged Erbakan's government to take tough measures against rising Islamist activism in its February meeting. It is expected to repeat its demands next week.</p>
<p>The Islamist-conservative coalition, ailing since the February NSC meeting, survived a censure motion by a close vote in parliament on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Brokers said there was no immediate reaction to deputy prime minister Tansu Ciller's remarks which came towards the close.</p>
<p>&quot;We can see a road leading to elections. The solution is the people, your decision,&quot; Ciller told a meeting of businessmen. &quot;Whatever we do, we will do together. We will open the way to the ballot box,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Of the 250 shares traded, falls outdid rises by 131 to 66 and 53 finished stable. The IMKB Industrial eased 0.56 percent to 1,417, the IMKB Services leapt 2.68 percent to 1,380 and the IMKB Financial lost 0.74 percent to 1,611.</p>
<p>Actives were led by utilities Cukurova Elektrik, up 12,500 lira at 182,500, Aktas Elektrik, up 5,000 lira at 180,000 and Kepez Elektrik, up 30,000 lira 242,500. They made up 37.7 percent of the total turnover.</p>
<p>-- Aydan Eksin, Istanbul newsroom +90-212-2750875</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
