<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609297" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Britain's Mowlam seeks US support for IRA ceasefire. [CORRECTED 08:40 GMT 24/5]</title>
<headline>Britain's Mowlam seeks US support for IRA ceasefire. [CORRECTED 08:40 GMT 24/5]</headline>
<byline>Deborah Zabarenko</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's new Northern Ireland Secretary Mo Mowlam on Friday thanked the Clinton administration for past support and sought U.S. pressure for a renewed cease-fire by the Irish Republican Army.</p>
<p>&quot;The new government in Britain is determined ... to be sure that we get momentum back into the peace process,&quot; Mowlam told reporters after a White House meeting with U.S. National Security Adviser Samuel Berger.</p>
<p>Mowlam said her message in Washington was to thank President Bill Clinton, members of Congress and other Americans for their support, and to seek to add a U.S. voice to British and Irish popular resolve for a cease-fire.</p>
<p>The message that Britain is serious in seeking peace for Northern Ireland would benefit from backing by the United States, Mowlam said.</p>
<p>&quot;That message ...from ourselves, the Irish and the Americans would be very positive,&quot; she said. &quot;We've got a window (of opportunity), we must go for it, all of us together.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked about a suggestion raised by Sen. Edward Kennedy, a Massachusetts Democrat, that community parades be banned in Northern Ireland because in the past they have fostered tensions, Mowlam said she had considered this proposal but ultimately rejected it.</p>
<p>&quot;...(T)he parades are about people expressing their culture and their traditions and their identities,&quot; she said. &quot;... In that sense to try and ban them puts the problem in the cupboard, puts it away for three or four years. the problem hasn't gone away, you haven't dealt with the root causes of fear and distrust.&quot;</p>
<p>Kennedy's office said later the two had an &quot;excellent meeting&quot; for about an hour.</p>
<p>Britain's new Labour government has insisted, like its Conservative predecessor, that an unequivocal cease-fire is a precondition for Sinn Fein, the IRA's political wing, to take part in peace talks in the troubled province.</p>
<p>The Labour government has taken over the main structure of the Conservatives' policy, whose central plank is all-party talks chaired by former U.S. Senator George Mitchell to work out the province's constitutional and political future.</p>
<p>But Mowlam said there was a basic difference of philosophy of the new government that changed the climate for the talks. She noted Labour's commitment to address what it calls the &quot;democratic deficit&quot; across Britain, in particular with regional assemblies in Scotland and Wales, and its decision to join the European Commission on Human Rights, reversing Conservative policy.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a change of climate. We are determined not just to move things but to include people,&quot; she said at a breakfast with reporters.</p>
<p>Asked how Britain would react if the United States gave Sinn Fein leader Gerry Adams another visa -- Washington has not granted a visa to Adams since the IRA bombing campaign resumed last year -- she said: &quot;It is a U.S. government decision. ... if there were an IRA cease-fire I think it would help. If not, I don't think it would be a terribly helpful step.&quot; (Corrects to drop reference to visa application being denied.)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
