<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609251" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Discharged woman U.S. bomber pilot mulling options.</title>
<headline>Discharged woman U.S. bomber pilot mulling options.</headline>
<byline>Greg Frost</byline>
<dateline>MINOT, N.D. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The first woman B-52 bomber pilot was considering her options on Friday, a day after she accepted a deal allowing her to resign from the U.S. Air Force to avoid being court-martialed.</p>
<p>Lt. Kelly Flinn's father said she will now be able to get on with her life.</p>
<p>&quot;Basically, she's going to take some time out to get over this incident,&quot; Donald Flinn, Sr., told Reuters. &quot;There are a lot of options open to her.&quot;</p>
<p>Air Force Secretary Sheila Widnall announced on Thursday that Flinn was given a general discharge and will leave the service in lieu of being court-martialed on charges she committed adultery, lied during an official investigation and disobeyed a direct order.</p>
<p>The discharge would prevent Flinn from flying for the Air Force Reserve or the Air National Guard unless she obtained a waiver, which Flinn's lawyer Frank Spinner said she will seek.</p>
<p>Flinn will be able to fly civilian aircraft. Her lawyer said on Thursday Flinn had already received phone calls of interest from some commercial airlines.</p>
<p>There was speculation she had signed a book deal. A spokeswoman for the Flinn family said on Thursday, however, she was unaware of such a deal.</p>
<p>The general discharge fell short of Flinn's original request for an honourable discharge, but her parents said she was forced to accept it because she was in a &quot;no-win situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Donald Flinn and his wife Mary drove to North Dakota from their home in Georgia to be with their daughter. Donald Flinn said he had not spoken with his daughter on Friday. He said she was &quot;very tired&quot; when he saw her on Thursday.</p>
<p>When asked if he agreed with Widnall that the deal was a &quot;satisfactory&quot; one, Flinn said, &quot;Under the circumstances, it's satisfactory in that it's a discharge under honourable conditions.&quot;</p>
<p>Support for Flinn snowballed over the past week as she and her lawyers mounted a polished public relations campaign. In a CNN/USA Today/Gallup poll of 643 people taken after Widnall's decision, 53 percent said they disapproved of the Air Force's handling of the Flinn case and 33 percent said they approved.</p>
<p>The poll, which had a sampling error of plus or minus 4 percent, showed that 47 percent of respondents felt Flinn was treated worse than a male pilot, 27 percent said she was treated the same and 17 percent said she was treated better.</p>
<p>Although Flinn will receive a &quot;general discharge under honourable conditions,&quot; the definition of that document suggested that all did not go well with her in the service, a Pentagon official told reporters on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Under honourable conditions, a general discharge is separation from the Air Force with honour, but to a lesser degree than an honourable discharge,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;This (general) discharge is given when normally faithful service is marred by negative aspects of a person's duty performance or personal conduct,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Flinn, 26 and single, admitted having sex with a married civilian, but said he told her he had legally separated from his wife at the time of their affair. Flinn was also charged with having an affair with an enlisted man.</p>
<p>While Flinn's association with the Air Force was over, ramifications of the case were still reverberating on Friday throughout the U.S. military. A leading congressional critic said the military needs to review its policies on fraternisation and enforcement.</p>
<p>&quot;The entire armed services has to review their military policies, their policies on fraternisation, their policies of enforcement, and move forward,&quot; Representative Nita Lowey, Democrat of New York, said in an interview with the Cable News Network.</p>
<p>Flinn's supporters said she had to accept the deal.</p>
<p>&quot;Today, Lt. Kelly Flinn decided to place the interests of the Air Force ahead of her own desire to fight what she believes is a true injustice,&quot; Spinner said on Thursday. &quot;The Air Force has lost a pioneer -- and at what a price.&quot;</p>
<p>White House Press Secretary Mike McCurry said on Friday President Bill Clinton believed the Air Force acted appropriately, adding, &quot;the president was not involved&quot; in deciding the case and that he was &quot;not aware of any White House influence&quot; in the outcome.</p>
<p>&quot;The president feels that the Air Force has appropriately dealt with this matter,&quot; McCurry said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINOT, N.D."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
