<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609299" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Jeeps, minivans fuel U.S. carbon dioxide pollution.</title>
<headline>Jeeps, minivans fuel U.S. carbon dioxide pollution.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Paul</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Families in their jeeps and minivans can expect to burn more gasoline than ever as the summer driving season kicks off this weekend.</p>
<p>While fuel use does not affect smog-forming pollutants, gas guzzlers boost emissions of carbon dioxide, a greenhouse gas believed to cause global warming.</p>
<p>The Energy Information Administration expects to see a 2 percent to 3 percent jump in travel this summer to 7.3 billion miles per day and a 1.5 percent to 2 percent rise in gasoline demand to 8 million barrels per day.</p>
<p>Attempts to limit gasoline use through fuel economy standards are being tossed to the wind, thanks to the appeal of cheap gasoline feeding inefficient sport utility vehicles.</p>
<p>Green groups believe the Big Three U.S. carmakers this year will all fail to meet the corporate average fuel economy (CAFE) standard for light trucks, 20.7 miles per gallon.</p>
<p>&quot;All of our companies are struggling to meet that standard because of the popularity of sport utility vehicles,&quot; Max Gates, a spokesman for the American Automobile Manufacturers Association, said.</p>
<p>But Gates said all the companies thought they would satisfy federal law, which allows automakers to use credits from past and future years to offset dips below the standard in the actual fuel economy average for the fleet.</p>
<p>&quot;They all expect to be in compliance with the law,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Among popular models, the Ford Explorer, Chevrolet Blazer and Jeep Cherokee all have city fuel economy ratings of 16-19 mpg and on-highway ratings of 21-23 mpg. Standard pickups typically have city ratings of about 13-16 mpg and on-highway ratings of 15-20 mpg.</p>
<p>The light trucks spew about 1 billion metric tonnes a year of carbon dioxide, according to the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
<p>Green groups accusing the car companies of pushing the gas guzzlers, but auto makers say they are selling what the public wants.</p>
<p>&quot;Sport utilities are the Joe Camel of the auto industry,&quot; Dan Becker, energy programme director of the Sierra Club, said.</p>
<p>&quot;They're not doing their fair share to protect our kids from polluted air ... and our energy security from being too dependent on OPEC oil,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;CAFE standards have been our most effective tool for saving oil and reducing carbon dioxide emissions,&quot; Bill Magavern, a project director for consumer advocates Public Citizen, said.</p>
<p>Oil imports topped 10 million barrels per day in April, breaking a 20-year record.</p>
<p>&quot;All these trends in the buying of sport utility and other somewhat less efficient vehicles have pushed down the potential for growing efficiency,&quot; David Costello, an economist in the Energy Information Administration, said.</p>
<p>Car companies are lobbying to block the government from raising CAFE standards.</p>
<p>Lawmakers from Michigan have introduced bills in the House and Senate to freeze the light truck standard and the 27.5 mpg car standard and give Congress instead of the Transportation Department the authority to make any future changes.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe an issue of this magnitude that affects such a large industry should have a more open debate in the Congress,&quot; an aide to Representative Fred Upton, a Republican who introduced a CAFE bill in the House, said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not a decision that should be made by unelected bureaucrats,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Congress in the past few years has barred the Transportation Department from raising CAFE standards by cutting off budget money for making any changes, and Congressional aides said lawmakers were likely to try to do the same this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
