<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609291" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Senate approves refuge for Swiss bank guard.</title>
<headline>Senate approves refuge for Swiss bank guard.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Senate agreed unanimously on Friday to grant refuge to a young Swiss bank guard who said he feared for his safety and that of his family after he tried to stop Nazi-era bank records from being shredded.</p>
<p>The Senate approved legislation granting permanent residency status for Christophe Meili, 29, his wife and their two children and sent the measure to the House for consideration. They would not have qualified for residency status under normal rules. The House will have to consider the proposal when it returns on June 3.</p>
<p>His champion in Congress, Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, a New York Republican, said the guard had asked to be protected by the United States.</p>
<p>&quot;It is our duty to do so,&quot; D'Amato said. &quot;Christophe Meili should be viewed as a hero, not a criminal.&quot;</p>
<p>Meili was a student and night security guard at the Union Bank of Switzerland when he stumbled on the carts of Holocaust-era documents waiting for the shredder.</p>
<p>Testifying before the Senate Immigration subcommittee on Tuesday, Meili accused Swiss banks, police and government authorities of hoping to keep hidden the nation's past dealings with Nazis. He also accused authorities of failing to do anything with the documents he turned over in January.</p>
<p>Swiss authorities have not closed their case against him, D'Amato said, citing reports the guard was being investigated for violating Swiss bank secrecy laws because he showed copies of the documents to members of the Swiss Jewish community.</p>
<p>His family now receives hate mail, death threats and even threats to kidnap and kill his two children, Miriam, 4, and David, 2. &quot;I fear for the safety of my wife and two children. We are afraid,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are certain powers in Switzerland who do not want to see the Swiss banks and government exposed for what they did in the Holocaust,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
