<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609206" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Neck-and-neck as first Iran election results due.</title>
<headline>Neck-and-neck as first Iran election results due.</headline>
<byline>Barry May</byline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1996-05-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>First results of Iran's presidential election were due on Saturday with two middle-ranking Shi'ite Moslem clergymen, Mohammad Khatami and Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri, reckoned by Iranian analysts to be neck-and-neck in the voting.</p>
<p>But the final outcome of Friday's voting, extended by four hours because of a high turnout, is unlikely to be known before Monday.</p>
<p>The poll represents the fiercest political battle between conservative Shi'ite Moslem clerics and moderates since the Islamic 1979 revolution.</p>
<p>Analysts said it was impossible to tell who had won in the balloting at more than 33,000 polling stations around the country. A high turnout of the 33 million Iranians aged 15 and over who were qualified to vote was reported.</p>
<p>Khatami is an ex-culture minister who has attracted a rainbow coalition of women, youths and intellectuals seeking a more relaxed application of Islamic mores 18 years after the revolution that toppled the shah.</p>
<p>He was expected to carry Tehran and other big cities by large margins and remarks by people leaving polling stations in the capital seemed to bear this out.</p>
<p>Many of his supporters see him as a moderate compared with the conservatives who control parliament and some of Iran's state institutions.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri is speaker of parliament and enjoys the backing of influential groups of conservative clergy and merchants. He was considered the establishment candidate and was stronger in rural areas, which tend to be more traditional.</p>
<p>Both men and two others who were not reckoned to get more than a few percent of the votes were screened by a conservative group of senior clergy and lawyers before being allowed to run. The council rejected 234 other candidates for failing to match up to Islamic revolutionary ideals.</p>
<p>The election was to replace President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani, who must steps down in August after serving the maximum two consecutive terms of office permitted by law.</p>
<p>First voting tallies could emerge on Saturday and the final result is expected to be announced by Monday.</p>
<p>Hatred of the United States and all things American, never far from the surface of Iranian politics since the seizure of hostages at the U.S. embassy in Tehran in the early violent months of the revolution, reappeared as an election theme.</p>
<p>Iran's supreme leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, who outranks the president, urged voters to choose the &quot;best qualified&quot; candidate and said electors would vote for someone who could &quot;stand against America and those who want to impose their will on our nation&quot;.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri said shortly after casting his own vote that, if elected, he would not change Iran's policy towards the United States and European Union.</p>
<p>Tehran has had no diplomatic relations with Washington since 1980 and its ties with the 15-nation EU are severely strained over a German court verdict implicating top Iranian leaders in political killings in Berlin.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
