<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609296" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYMEX electricity settles up, rebounds with natgas.</title>
<headline>NYMEX electricity settles up, rebounds with natgas.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>NYMEX electricity futures settled higher Friday after a volatile week, erasing early losses on a late rebound due to strength of natural gas futures.</p>
<p>&quot;Gas was what people used as a pricing signal,&quot; said a Houston futures trader.</p>
<p>The power complex pressured lower early on softer cash and over-the-counter values, market sources said.</p>
<p>June California-Oregon Border (COB) futures settled up 72 cents at $19.37 a megawatt hour (MWh), erasing a 25-cent loss. June COB gyrated the week between $18.25 and $23.00, a new life-of-contract high.</p>
<p>July COB finished up $1.66 at $21.31. Other COB months ended 25 cents to $1.35 higher.</p>
<p>June Palo Verde (PV) futures settled up 81 cents at $25.15 after hitting a session low of $23.80, down $1.54. The contract traded in a $7 range this week after posting a new high at $31.00.</p>
<p>July PV finished up 98 cents at $28.34. Deferred PV contracts ended 81 to 99 cents higher.</p>
<p>NYMEX June Henry Hub natgas futures settled up 8.9 cents at $2.285 per million British thermal units after being to maintain support above $2.150.</p>
<p>Spot electricity prices for firm, peak delivery Tuesday at COB narrowed to $18.50-19.50/MWh from Thursday's $18.50-20.50, while those at PV was finished steady at $18.00-21.00.</p>
<p>Despite today's late bounce, market sources said they are doubtful that the rise could be sustained due to forecasts of more seasonal weather in the Southwest and more generation capacity coming back to service in the next couple of weeks.</p>
<p>About 7,000 megawatts (MW) of power units remained off line in the West for either planned or unplanned maintenance.</p>
<p>The 1,087 MW Diablo Canyon 1 nuclear unit was expected to begin production May 29 from a scheduled refueling and maintenance outage which began April 19.</p>
<p>Several coal-fired plants are also expected back at the end of month including the 750 MW Colstrip unit in Montana and 750 MW Four Corners unit in Arizona.</p>
<p>Restart of the 550 MW unit 2 at the Jim Bridger coal-fired generating complex in Wyoming was heard postponed to June 4 from this weekend.</p>
<p>Forecasters expect temperatures in the Northwest would average near to above normal into next week with chance of thunderstorms Sunday. Main cities like Portland and Seattle would continue to see temperatures in the 60s degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
<p>In the Southwest, temperatures were forecast to average near normal in the eastern section and above normal in the western area. The California coast is forecast to see temperatures in the 70s, while interior cities like Phoenix and Las Vegas would experience temperatures in the 90s.</p>
<p>NYMEX estimated 305 COB and 648 PV contracts were sold.</p>
<p>NYMEX will be closed Monday in observance of Memorial Day.</p>
<p>((--New York Power Desk +1 212 859 1622))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
