<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609205" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Suspicion Arab beaten to death in hospital - paper.</title>
<headline>Suspicion Arab beaten to death in hospital - paper.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Palestinian prisoner whose family said he was tortured to death by Israeli police this week may have been fatally beaten by guards at an Israeli hospital, Israel's Haaretz newspaper said on Friday.</p>
<p>The head of Jerusalem's Shaare Zedek hospital said police, not hospital guards, were &quot;dominant&quot; in the beating of Khaled Abu Daiyeh at the hospital when he became violent after refusing treatment.</p>
<p>Police were not available to comment.</p>
<p>Palestinian Authority official Ahmed Abdel-Rahman told Reuters: &quot;Killing prisoner Abu Daiyeh is but one in a chain of Israeli crimes against the Palestinian people and we hope that the U.S. administration would protest against this killing.&quot;</p>
<p>The Palestinian Authority's chief pathologist, who examined Abu Daiyeh's body before burial on Thursday, ruled he died of &quot;neurological shock caused by severe pain resulting from external violence&quot;.</p>
<p>A Reuters cameraman who filmed the body on Thursday after it was handed to the family for burial said the skull was crushed, the chest caved in, and the hands and legs appeared broken.</p>
<p>Haaretz said Abu Daiyeh was brought to Shaare Zedek and &quot;there, according to the suspicion, he was killed&quot;.</p>
<p>It said Abu Daiyeh refused treatment and first struggled with one policeman, slightly injuring him. Then, &quot;according to the suspicion, hospital guards began beating the prisoner&quot;.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Israeli police told Reuters that Abu Daiyeh, arrested last week for trying to take a policeman's gun in Jerusalem's Old City, on Tuesday felt unwell and was taken to Shaare Zedek.</p>
<p>At the hospital, Abu Daiyeh refused treatment and &quot;went crazy&quot;, attacking anyone who came near him, police said. He was brought under control and put to bed. He was found dead in his bed on Wednesday, they said, adding that the Justice Ministry was investigating the incident.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for the hospital gave a similar account on Thursday. She refused to detail Abu Daiyeh's condition on entering the hospital.</p>
<p>Asked on Friday to comment on the Haaretz report, she referred Reuters to comments by hospital head Yonatan Halevy on Israel Radio.</p>
<p>Halevy told the radio: &quot;The two policemen, in attempts to overpower him, beat him, as I said, in front of everyone. The (hospital) guards acted according to their orders to help and without any doubt they were not the dominant or meaningful element in this violence.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The violence used, justly or unjustly, to prevent danger to the public was used by police,&quot; Halevy added.</p>
<p>Shawqi Issa, executive director of the Palestinian Society for the Protection of Human Rights and the Environment, on Thursday supported the family's accusation of torture: &quot;We believe that he died as a direct result of an Israeli high court decision allowing torture.&quot;</p>
<p>Israel's High Court in November 1996 rejected a Palestinian detainee's petition to bar Israel's Shin Bet secret service from using &quot;physical force&quot; while interrogating him.</p>
<p>Two weeks ago the U.N. Committee against Torture urged Israel to stop interrogating Palestinian detainees with methods which it said constituted torture and violated international law. Israel denied it tortured detainees.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
