<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609208" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Detained Palestinian journalist on hunger strike.</title>
<headline>Detained Palestinian journalist on hunger strike.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Detained Palestinian journalist Daoud Kuttab went on a hunger strike on Friday demanding he be freed or charged by the Palestinian Authority, a Palestinian human rights group said.</p>
<p>The Palestinian Centre for Democracy and Elections (PCDE) said Kuttab, who was taken into custody on Wednesday, was being denied visitation rights.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Kuttab announced at 11.45 a.m. this morning that he had started a hunger strike that will continue until he is released from prison, or charges are brought against him,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;The PCDE strongly condemns the order made by the office of the President (Yasser Arafat) of the Palestinian Authority to deny visitation rights to...Kuttab,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>It called for Kuttab to be immediately released or charged.</p>
<p>Kuttab's brother told Reuters on Wednesday that Kuttab was summoned to Ramallah by Palestinian police. The journalist, who holds U.S. citizenship and lives in East Jerusalem, went to the Ramallah self-rule enclave in the West Bank and was detained.</p>
<p>The United States said on Thursday that Kuttab should be released and that the matter had been raised with senior members of the Palestinian Authority but not directly with Arafat.</p>
<p>Kuttab's brother said the detention was apparently related to a dispute between Kuttab, who has a private contract to carry live broadcasts of Palestinian Legislative Council session, and Palestinian state-run television.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
