<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609282" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Export Business - Grain/oilseeds complex.</title>
<headline>Export Business - Grain/oilseeds complex.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Grain and oilseed exports reported by USDA and private export sources.</p>
<p>WHEAT SALE - CCC bought 13,500 tonnes of U.S. soft white wheat, maximum moisture 13.5 percent, for donation to Pakistan, for $174.93 FOB Portland from Columbia Grain. Shipment dates are June 10-July 15.</p>
<p>WHEAT AND BARLEY SALE - U.S. exporters reported the sale of 200,000 tonnes of soft red winter wheat to Egypt and 110,000 tonnes of barley to unknown purchasers, both for 1997/98 delivery, the USDA said.  </p>
<p>WHEAT SALE - South Korea's Daehan Flour Mills bought 25,500 tonnes of U.S. No.1 wheat from Mitsui &amp; Co Ltd, a company official said. Shipment was July 20-Aug 20 to Inchon.</p>
<p>-- A Philippine flour miller bought 7,500 tonnes of U.S. western white wheat for August shipment, Manila traders said.</p>
<p>RICE AND TAPIOCA SALE - South Korea's National Livestock Cooperatives Federation bought 10,000 tonnes of Indian rice bran pellets from Nidera and 10,000 tonnes from G. Premjee, a Federation official said. The official said the federation also bought 15,000 tonnes of Thai tapioca at $88.89 a tonne, C&amp;F, from STC Tapioca Group Co Ltd.  </p>
<p>WHEAT TENDER - Egypt's Holding Company for Rice and Flour Mills said Friday it seeks 165,000 tonnes of U.S. hard red winter wheat or Australian hard red wheat for delivery in June and July. Deadline for bids is 0900 GMT May 26. It seeks 55,000 tonnes for delivery June 15-15, 55,500 tonnes for delivery July 1-10, and 55,000 tonnes for delivery July 15-25.</p>
<p>-- Pakistan seeks 376,000 tonnes of U.S. and/or Australian white wheat on May 28, according to a Pakistan embassy official. Shipment is for June 11-July 10.</p>
<p>-- CCC seeks 5,000 tonnes of U.S. HRW wheat on May 28 for donation to Benin. Shipment dates are June 15-July 10.  </p>
<p>WHEAT TENDERS (Cont) - Sri Lanka seeks 50,000 to 60,000 tonnes of PL-480 wheat for June 30-July 19 shipment. Offers are due by 1930 GMT June 5 at the Sri Lankan embassy in Washington.</p>
<p>-- South Korea's Cheiljedang Corp and Dongah Flour Mills Co Ltd passed on tenders to buy 22,000 tonnes of U.S. No.1 wheat due to high offer prices, company officials said.</p>
<p>-- Results are awaited on this week's Iraq's tender for 50,000 tonnes of U.S. hard red winter wheat for July shipment under a United Nations oil-for-food deal, traders said.  </p>
<p>CORN TENDER - CCC said Friday it will offer 8.2 million bushels of corn for sale from its feedgrain catalog, with offers due June 3 and results announced June 4.</p>
<p>RICE TENDERS - Jordan postponed a tender to buy 15,000 tonnes of optional origin medium grain camolino rice until next week, U.S. rice exporters said. One exporter said the tender was for May 27 while another said it was for May 28. Delivery was for June with U.S. origin likely preferred.</p>
<p>-- Syria's General Foreign Trade Organisation for Chemicals and Foostuffs seeks offers June 4 to buy 12,000 tonnes of white rice for July with confirmation on June 12.  </p>
<p>RICE TENDER (Cont) - State-run Rice Export Corporation of Pakistan invited bids by May 26 for the export of 5,000 tonnes of basmati Pak-7 rice containing seven percent brokens.</p>
<p>MARKET TALK - Cargill Inc declined to comment on a rumor in the U.S. grain markets Friday that it sold at least one million tonnes of optional origin wheat to China or North Korea. Many U.S. exporters scoffed at the idea, saying North Korea had neither the cash nor the infrastructure to handle such a huge quantity of wheat...Philippine mills are expected to move out of the wheat market in the coming week on prospects of firmer prices due to big demand from Pakistan, Manila traders said...</p>
<p>Japan's Food Agency said it did not buy any Australian wheat at Thursday's import tender due to higher than expected prices...Japan's edible oil makers are likely to sharply reduce buying of U.S. soybeans for nearby because of a higher than usual soybean moisture content and wide backwardation in prices, industry officials said.</p>
<p>((Doris Frankel 312 408 8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
