<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609295" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Grains ease on weather, coffee also falls.</title>
<headline>Grains ease on weather, coffee also falls.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Grain and soybean prices fell on Friday after weather forecasters predicted showers next week in the U.S. Midwest, which should benefit newly planted crops.</p>
<p>Coffee and oil prices also fell ahead of the Memorial Day holiday which will close futures markets on Monday.</p>
<p>Overall, the Commodity Research Bureau index of 17 commodity futures ended 0.62 point lower at 251.31.</p>
<p>At the Chicago Board of Trade, soybeans for July delivery closed 10-1/2 cents a bushel lower at $8.36 and corn for July delivery fell 2-3/4 cents a bushel to $2.70-1/2.</p>
<p>&quot;We're seeing some follow-through selling from yesterday in anticipation of good weather and weakening demand,&quot; said Jack Scoville, an analyst with Price Group brokerage in Chicago.</p>
<p>A weekly report issued late on Thursday by the National Oilseed Processors Association said only 22.5 million bushels of soybeans were crushed by its members in the week ended May 21, well below trade expectations of 23.5 to 24.9 million.</p>
<p>Planting progress of corn and soybeans has run far ahead of five-year averages this year in the Midwest, although cold weather has slowed the emergence of the new crops.</p>
<p>But showers forecast from Nebraska to Ohio for the next week should help jump-start the seedlings.</p>
<p>Wheat prices also closed mostly lower, with wheat for July delivery ending at $3.75 a bushel, down 2-1/4 cents.</p>
<p>Showers overnight in parts of dry Kansas and Nebraska wheat growing areas added to selling incentive.</p>
<p>Export business was routine, although Egypt said after the market close that it would buy 165,000 tons of U.S. or Australian wheat over the holiday weekend.</p>
<p>Grain giant Cargill Inc declined comment on a market rumor it had sold more wheat to North Korea, after arranging a swap of 20,000 tons of wheat for North Korean zinc in April. But traders noted Cargill as a heavy late buyer of wheat futures.</p>
<p>&quot;They were a buyer late and that triggered buy stops and short-covering,&quot; said trader Vic Lespinasse of Dean Witter.</p>
<p>At the Coffee Sugar and Cocoa Exchange in New York, coffee closed mostly lower in thin trade ahead of the long holiday weekend as speculators took profits following two days of big gains.</p>
<p>Coffee for July delivery ended 3.45 cents a pound lower at 256.85 cents.</p>
<p>Prices last week hit a 20-year high of 280 cents a pound, and despite Friday's downturn, industry sources said a continued supply crunch was likely to underpin the market in coming months.</p>
<p>&quot;It was just a small round of profit-taking today,&quot; said Allendale Inc analyst Jim Cordier. &quot;Profit-taking could get into Tuesday's trade, but the fundamentals are still supportive. I think you'll be looking at August or September until you see any help on tight supplies.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders continued to monitor weather forecasts for the fast-approaching winter in top grower Brazil. A cold front moved into Brazil's coffee belt on Friday but no damaging cold to coffee trees was expected, Weather Services Corp said.</p>
<p>Coffee stocks in producer and consumer nations continue to hover near 20-year lows. But Brazilian officials said on Friday that initial reports of this year's harvest now under way in Brazil indicate a good quality coffee crop.</p>
<p>At the New York Mercantile Exchange, oil prices closed lower in a last-minute sell-off.</p>
<p>Crude oil for July delivery fell 23 cents to close at $21.63 a barrel.</p>
<p>With crude supplies seen as more than adequate, traders have been watching the gasoline market to provide direction with the approach of the summer &quot;driving season,&quot; which traditionally begins with the Memorial Day holiday.</p>
<p>&quot;The key thing to look at is to see if demand is going to meet all these expectations we've put on the market,&quot; said Refco Inc analyst Victor Yu.</p>
<p>On Friday, however, oil products fell in line with crude oil. Unleaded gasoline for July delivery ended down 0.20 cent a gallon at 64.90 cents a gallon and heating oil for July ended down 0.37 cent a gallon at 57.48 cents.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
