<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609222" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton, Democrats rip Republicans on disaster aid.</title>
<headline>Clinton, Democrats rip Republicans on disaster aid.</headline>
<byline>Deborah Zabarenko</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The White House on Friday blasted the Republican Congress for failing to approve emergency disaster aid for 33 states before leaving for the Memorial Day holiday weekend.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton &quot;is extremely disappointed that those citizens of 33 states that need access to disaster assistance ... will see some of their assistance jeopardized,&quot; White House Press Secretary Mike McCurry said.</p>
<p>Republicans contended there was ample money in the federal pipeline to last through the weeklong recess and beyond. The Federal Emergency Management Agency, for example, has $2 billion available to spend.</p>
<p>&quot;Communities that have been depending on this funding to get back on their feet are being left short-changed by a short-sighted Congress, which does not reflect well on the Republican leaders of Congress,&quot;  Curry said.</p>
<p>House Republican leaders on Thursday allowed members to take a week's break after blocking efforts to provide disaster aid for the flooded Midwest.</p>
<p>Senate Democratic Leader Tom Daschle of South Dakota, one of the states in line to receive federal disaster relief, said Republican legislators were more concerned with getting away for the long holiday than with disaster victims.</p>
<p>&quot;Republicans wanted to leave in the worst way, and they did,&quot; Daschle said at a news conference on Friday. &quot;They put a greater priority on plane tickets than disaster payments. They set a new low for responsibility in the Congress.&quot;</p>
<p>Most crucial is aid to farmers to help with spring planting at a critical time in the Midwest growing season, McCurry said.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott said the Senate was too involved with passage of a balanced budget amendement and the so-called &quot;partial birth&quot; abortion ban to complete the disaster aid measure.</p>
<p>&quot;We just were so involved in the budget resolution --- that was true in the House, too -- we just didn't have time to focus on some areas of disagreement and they are legitimate ones,&quot; Lott, a Mississippi Republican, told reporters.</p>
<p>The Democratic National Committee used the opportunity to express &quot;astonishment&quot; that House Speaker Newt Gingrich, a Georgia Republican, was headed for a Palm Beach fund-raiser &quot;while hard working families in North Dakota are trying to bail the water out of their homes.&quot;</p>
<p>Both parties support disaster aid, but Clinton threatened to veto the $8.4 billion emergency spending bill because of unrelated spending and environmental amendments added by Republicans.</p>
<p>&quot;Let's pray there's no hurricane any time soon,&quot; McCurry told reporters, saying &quot;there's no money left&quot; to deal will many of the problems facing disaster victims.</p>
<p>McCurry said about $100 million worth of federal money earmarked to rebuild and redevelop parts of the flood-ravaged Dakotas and Minnesota will be suspended, along with two Agriculture Department programs aimed at emergency conservation and flood control.</p>
<p>Money that would have paid for emergency loans for flood victims will also be held up without the disaster aid bill, McCurry said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
