<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609283" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ralston Purina has co-CEOs,Stiritz retires.</title>
<headline>Ralston Purina has co-CEOs,Stiritz retires.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ralston Purina Co. said Friday that Chief Executive William Stiritz will retire this fall and named the heads of its pet food and Eveready units as co-chief executives, raising speculation it may split up the company.</p>
<p>The consumer products giant said the office of chief excutive will be shared by W. Patrick McGinnis, who is president and chief executive of the Pet Products Group, and J. Patrick Mulcahy, chairman and chief executive of Ralston's Eveready Battery Co.</p>
<p>Stiritz, who will turn 63 in July, will retire from the chief executive post in September 30, but remain chairman. He also will continue to serve as chairman and chief executive of Ralston's international agricultural feeds business, which the company plans to spin off in early 1998.</p>
<p>The change in command was not expected, but did not shock analysts, given Stiritz's age.</p>
<p>Some experts said the change signalled Ralston was considering transforming itself again by breaking apart the pet and battery businesses. But Ralston denied such a move was under consideration.</p>
<p>&quot;The board's action is a vote for continuity and emphasizes a long-planned transition of the chief executive officer position,&quot; Stiritz said in a statement.</p>
<p>Other analysts said Ralston may have created the office of co-chief executive to avoid having to pass up one executive over the other.</p>
<p>Stiritz has served as Ralston's chief executive since 1981. In recent years, he led a major overhaul of the company, including the spinoff of its consumer foods business, Ralcorp Holdings Inc., in 1994.</p>
<p>In 1995, Ralston sold its Continental Baking Co. to Interstate Bakeries Corp. and it plans to spinoff its international animal feed business next year.</p>
<p>&quot;He has proven to be a very smart and shareholder-oriented chief executive,&quot; said Nomi Ghez of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
<p>Ralston's shares rose $2.75 a share to $85.625 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the market ran the stock up today because people might have viewed this as a prelude to splitting up the company,&quot; said William Leach of Donaldson Lufkin &amp; Jenrette Securities Corp. &quot;The synergy between batteries and pet food has always been elusive to me.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
