<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609280" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Albright urges Kabila to broaden new cabinet.</title>
<headline>Albright urges Kabila to broaden new cabinet.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright expressed concern on Friday about events in the Democratic Republic of Congo and urged self-proclaimed president Laurent Kabila to broaden his cabinet.</p>
<p>Opposition leader Etienne Tshisekedi was excluded from the partial cabinet announced on Thursday night by Kabila, whose forces captured Kinshasa last weekend to take control of the country formerly known as Zaire.</p>
<p>&quot;We are concerned generally ... about what is going on in the Congo now,&quot; Albright told a news conference.</p>
<p>She called Kabila's cabinet formation a &quot;work-in-progress&quot; but stressed &quot;the importance of having a cabinet and a government that is inclusive of others than just his alliance&quot;.</p>
<p>Albright said Washington wanted to see &quot;that there is a rule of law, that they are moving towards democratic elections, and that there is reconciliation&quot;.</p>
<p>Kabila's troops fired in the air to break up a protest by Tshisekedi's supporters on Friday about his exclusion from the government.</p>
<p>Albright also renewed U.S. concerns over allegations that Kabila's army maltreated Rwandan refugees in eastern Congo during its push towards the capital, saying Washington was &quot;going to be looking into this very carefully&quot;.</p>
<p>The United States was anxious to see that &quot;these very bad events are in fact dealt with&quot;, she said.</p>
<p>Albright earlier this week put Kabila on notice that Western aid for Congo would depend on the way he respected human rights and democratic principles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
