<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609210" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Iranians in Malaysia choose Khatami by landslide.</title>
<headline>Iranians in Malaysia choose Khatami by landslide.</headline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>If the 206 Iranian expatriates who voted in Malaysia on Friday reflect the mood of Iran's 33 million-strong electorate, moderate Mohammad Khatami will win the Islamic republic's presidency with a landslide.</p>
<p>As voting continued in Iran, the Iranian news agency IRNA said out of 206 votes cast by Iranians living in Malyasia Khatami led the conservative candidate Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri by 152 votes to 38.</p>
<p>The other two candidates received a total of 13 votes, two ballots were cancelled and one was a blank vote, the agency added.</p>
<p>Iranians are voting for a successor to President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani in one of the sharpest political battles between conservatives and moderates since the 1979 Islamic revolution.</p>
<p>After a fiercely fought campaign and talk of fears of vote-rigging, the result looks likely to be a close contest between, Khatami and Nateq-Nouri -- both Shi'ite Moslem clerics.</p>
<p>Khatami, a moderate former culture minister popular with women, youths and intellectuals, was expected to sweep Tehran and some other major cities.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri, conservative speaker of parliament who enjoys the backing of important groups of Iran's conservative clergy and merchants, is stronger in rural areas.</p>
<p>Analysts gave the two other candidates, Mohammad Mohammadi Reyshahri and Reza Zavarei, no chance of winning.</p>
<p>State-run radio and television reported a high turnout and the Interior Ministry twice extended the time for voting by a total of four hours to 10 p.m. (1730 GMT).</p>
<p>Iranian analysts and Western diplomats said the vote was too close to call but they thought Nateq-Nouri had the edge because he was seen as an establishment figure.</p>
<p>The result is expected to be announced by Monday.</p>
<p>Thirty-three million Iranians aged 15 and over were eligible to vote at 33,180 mosques, schools and clinics turned into polling stations and guarded by 200,000 police.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
