<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609289" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Local groups oppose planned U.S. Bancorp merger.</title>
<headline>Local groups oppose planned U.S. Bancorp merger.</headline>
<byline>Miriam Widman</byline>
<dateline>PORTLAND, Ore. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>First Bank System Inc.'s proposed $8.5 billion acquisition of U.S. Bancorp has run into opposition from groups unhappy with the companies' community banking records, a Federal Reserve spokeswoman said Friday.</p>
<p>Chris Power, a spokeswoman for the Minneapolis Fed, which regulates Minneapolis-based First Bank, said several community groups have filed letters of complaint about the merger.</p>
<p>The letters, received before last week's deadline, will be forwarded to the Fed's Board of Governors in Washington, which must decide whether to approve the merger.</p>
<p>At least one of the groups, the Black United Front in Portland, accused the banks of doing a poor job of serving African-American consumers, according to the Oregonian newspaper.</p>
<p>The group is asking the Fed to delay the merger and hold public hearings on it, contending that U.S. Bank denied home loans to African-Americans at a much higher rate than whites, according to the newspaper.</p>
<p>Karen Tolvstad, a spokesperson for U.S. Bancorp, denied the charge, saying the bank has &quot;dedicated extra attention to the African-American market.&quot;</p>
<p>In 1995, she said, the company declined 12 percent of home-related loan applications from African-Americans, compared to 12.5 percent from white applicants.</p>
<p>She said the Fed &quot;needs to give due consideration&quot; to such complaints but should also consider the many letters of support for the acquisition.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Fed in Washington said the proposed merger had not yet been placed on the Board of Governors meeting schedule. Normally such mergers are approved without a public hearing, he said.</p>
<p>Banking analysts had mixed views on whether the community protests would delay the closing of the merger.</p>
<p>&quot;It could hold up the deal,&quot; said Tom Carley of Jensen Securities in Portland. But he said he had no reason to believe Portland-based U.S. Bancorp had been unfair to minorities.</p>
<p>Steven Schroll of Piper Jaffrey said the commmunity group complaints were &quot;a wasted effort.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The hostage efforts of the various consumer groups will once again be found to simply waste taxpayers money in an effort to extract a pound of flesh that's not to be extracted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Schroll said both banks have been scrutizined constantly by regulators as they have expanded. He believes the merger is on a fast track for regulatory approval by July.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTLAND, Ore."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
