<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609351" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Ag Dept begins filling high-level vacancies.</title>
<headline>U.S. Ag Dept begins filling high-level vacancies.</headline>
<byline>Charles Abbott</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman, faced for months with vacancies in a half-dozen key posts, filled one of the slots Friday and began putting his own team in place.</p>
<p>Keith Kelly, Arizona director of agriculture since 1991, will head the Farm Service Agency (FSA) beginning in mid-June, Glickman announced.</p>
<p>FSA runs the farm programme and, with offices in nearly every county, is the branch of USDA most often contacted by farmers.</p>
<p>The post of FSA administrator does not require Senate confirmation so Kelly can begin work shortly. A Democrat and Montana native, Kelly was Montana agriculture director from 1983-88.</p>
<p>When he became agriculture secretary midway through President Clinton's first term, Glickman made no major changes in the lineup of USDA policymakers. With the start of Clinton's second term, he gained the opportunity to select the officials to fill six vacant posts.</p>
<p>&quot;These nominations have taken a very long time,&quot; Glickman told reporters. &quot;In the modern era, it takes a very long time to get through the vetting process.&quot;</p>
<p>Glickman said he called a news conference to announce Kelly's appointment partly because &quot;this is a position I can announce&quot; and partly to buck up morale at FSA, which has a heavy workload and faces staff cuts and office closings.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, the White House said it would nominate Shirley Watkins for nutrition undersecretary and Catherine Woteki for food-safety undersecretary. Both require Senate approval. Hearings were expected during the summer.</p>
<p>Still vacant were undersecretary posts for ag research and for farm and foreign ag programmes. Gus Schumacher, head of the Foreign Agricultural Service, was being reviewed by the White House for the job overseeing farm and foreign ag programmes.</p>
<p>&quot;I have great confidence in Gus Schumacher,&quot; Glickman told reporters but said he could not comment further.</p>
<p>Woteki has been acting undersecretary for research. No one has emerged as the likely candidate for the post.</p>
<p>Pearlie Reed, who headed a civil rights review, recently was named acting assistant secretary for administration.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
