<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609337" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USDA shifts crop insurance to private sector.</title>
<headline>USDA shifts crop insurance to private sector.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman Friday said catastrophic crop insurance will be available only through private crop insurance agents beginning in the 1998 crop year.</p>
<p>Previously, coverage was available through both USDA Farm Service Agency offices and private agents in 36 states.</p>
<p>The 1996 Farm Bill called for USDA to transfer sales of catastrophic coverage entirely to the private sector if a sufficient number of agents were available in each state.</p>
<p>Glickman said the shift would not weaken the safety net for producers.</p>
<p>&quot;Before making this decision, private company representatives gave me their commitment to reach out to all America's farmers and to assure that the highest level of risk management service is extended to everyone,&quot; he said in a statement.</p>
<p>USDA said it will continue to subsidize all policies, establish policy terms and conditions, set rates and guarantee funds for the payment of approved claims.</p>
<p>The transfer will begin with 1998 Fall planted crops. Policyholders will receive a letter about the change in approximately a month. USDA said producers should continue to rely on the local FSA offices for service on 1997 policies.</p>
<p>The department said farmers' policies will be randomly transferred from USDA to an insurance company but that producers may select another agent if they do so before the sales closing date for the insured crop. Waiver of administrative fees for producers who qualify as limited resource farmers will be available.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
