<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609343" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Police speed warning cheers electric-car ralliers.</title>
<headline>Police speed warning cheers electric-car ralliers.</headline>
<dateline>PORTLAND, Maine 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A road rally meant to showcase electric and solar-powered vehicles appeared to come of age on Friday when police warned at least one competitor to slow down.</p>
<p>The incident reflected the American Tour de Sol's transformation from a contest to catch the public's imagination into a race for the marketplace by major automakers nine years later.</p>
<p>&quot;The marketplace (for electric cars) is coming of age,&quot; said Roy Kilar, who drove a Ford-built Ecostar across the finish line of the 350-mile (560-km) rally through the back roads of New England.</p>
<p>The annual event, organised by the Northeast Sustainable Energy Association, still features plenty of weird-looking contraptions and science projects built by college and high school students.</p>
<p>Several hundred people, many of them schoolchildren, cheered as the vehicles crossed the finish line in downtown Portland. The event began on Monday in Waterbury, Connecticut, and passed through Massachusetts, Vermont and New Hampshire.</p>
<p>Cars built by Ford, Toyota and Massachusetts-based Solectria engaged in a spirited final dash, with the Ford warned by a police officer to slow down as the pack approached Portland.</p>
<p>&quot;It was neck-and-neck,&quot; said Solectria co-founder James Worden, whose car crossed the line first. Officials will calculate factors including battery performance before declaring a winner on Saturday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTLAND, Maine"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
