<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609368" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Farmers fight to keep ethanol subsidy.</title>
<headline>Farmers fight to keep ethanol subsidy.</headline>
<byline>Leila Corcoran</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>American farmers are fighting to hang on to a tax break for ethanol that experts say is worth billions of dollars a year.</p>
<p>Representative Bill Archer, chairman of the powerful tax-writing House Ways and Means Committee, has zeroed in on the subsidy as a way to raise money to offset tax cuts called for in the balanced budget plan.</p>
<p>The Texas Republican says Uncle Sam could get upwards of $600 million a year in tax revenue if the ethanol credit is scrapped.</p>
<p>But ethanol producers say the move would pull the rug out from under a fledgling industry. Farmers fear it will send corn prices tumbling since ethanol, which is made from corn, accounts for more than 5 percent of their market.</p>
<p>&quot;If you yank the subsidy, ethanol would no longer be profitable and would cost corn growers around $5 billion a year because the price of corn would drop sharply,&quot; said Michael Evans, professor of economics at Northwestern University's Kellogg School of Management.</p>
<p>Currently, oil companies get a tax credit of 5.4 cents per gallon when they blend clean-burning ethanol with gasoline.</p>
<p>The subsidy was born out of the 1970's oil crisis when the government wanted to provide incentives to producers of alternative fuels. In 1990, Congress passed a law guaranteeing the tax credit until the year 2000, encouraging more companies to get into the ethanol market.</p>
<p>Archer has been gunning for the tax break for years. In 1995, the provision narrowly escaped the chairman's budget chopping block when House Speaker Newt Gingrich stepped in.</p>
<p>&quot;I have long considered the ethanol subsidy to be a wasteful use of tax dollars. The subsidy has failed to achieve its desired environmental or energy-related intentions, while penalising taxpayers by removing money from our nation's roads, bridges, and infastructure,&quot; Archer said recently.</p>
<p>He got ammunition in March from a General Accounting Office report that found while ethanol tax incentives had helped boost corn prices for farmers they had done little to help the environment or to achieve energy independence.</p>
<p>But an Agriculture Department report released this year predicted eliminating the tax break would boost the U.S. trade deficit by as much as $7.8 billion during fiscal years 1998-2005 due to larger oil imports. It also would reduce cash receipts by farmers by $12 billion to $20.8 billion during that period, the report said.</p>
<p>Archer's assault strikes a nerve with farmers who saw most federal farm subsidies disappear in last year's overhaul of U.S. agriculture policy. Ethanol producers also cry foul.</p>
<p>&quot;This was a deal that was made to help a fledgling ethanol industry be competitive with fossil fuels,&quot; said Dennis Stolte of the American Farm Bureau Federation. &quot;We think it's unfair and what amounts to reneging on a deal.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;This is a matter of equity,&quot; said Steve Cropper, president of Williams Energy Group, the nation's second-largest ethanol producer. &quot;We relied on the current law remaining in place when we made our decision to get into the marketing and manufacturing of ethanol.&quot;</p>
<p>The tax break has often been attacked as a give-away for agribusiness giant Archer Daniels Midland Co., which got into ethanol early and became the dominant producer. ADM now accounts for about 50 percent of the nation's ethanol output.</p>
<p>But backers say in fact it will be the &quot;new guys&quot; that will bear the brunt if the tax break is yanked.</p>
<p>&quot;If you were to take the tax credit away today, when the dust settled, ADM would be left standing,&quot; said one industry source who asked not to be identified. &quot;They've been around longest and written everything off. They'd be the likely survivor.&quot;</p>
<p>Archer has not decided whether to propose reducing the tax credit or eliminating it all together in the tax package he is expected to unveil in early June.</p>
<p>Last week, 100 House members urged congressional leaders to protect the ethanol tax incentive. Farm lobbyists are hoping Archer's effort will turn out to be a tempest in a teapot.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we will be able to prevail on the Senate side,&quot; said Farm Bureau's Stolte. &quot;We'll have a contentious debate over something that may already be dead.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25120">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
