<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609332" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME feeders close strong after setting new highs.</title>
<headline>CME feeders close strong after setting new highs.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CME feeder cattle futures held strong at the close after setting new contract highs in all months, the highest price levels since last August. Live cattle followed to close higher, traders said.</p>
<p>Feeder cattle closed 0.875 to 0.150 cent per lb higher with August up most at 79.300 cents after posting a new high of 79.375 cents. Live cattle ended 0.075 to 0.400 higher with June up the least at 65.400. December posted a new high of 71.625 cents.</p>
<p>A strong technical picture and expected stronger cash markets boosted feeder cattle to new highs.</p>
<p>Heavy feeder cattle placements onto feedlots, for much of the early part of this year, has cut feeder supplies. Reduced feeder production that started last year and the declining feed costs should keep demand for feeders up, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;We continue to place larger and larger numbers of feeder cattle relative to our feeder inventory that we supposedly had,&quot; said Tom Tippens, CEO of Professional Cattle Consultants.</p>
<p>Tippens also cited increased cow slaughter and death losses last winter which will become more of a factor later in the year.  </p>
<p>&quot;As we get into the later part of this year and the early part of 1998 that total supply of cattle should be shrinking,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Although the latest CME feeder cattle index was off $0.09 at $76.26 per cwt, the index is expected to move higher next week, traders added.</p>
<p>Fimat Futures USA and E.D.&amp;F. Man bought late after early demand from R.J. O'Brien. Refco bought August and sold October while Cargill Investor Services spread long February live cattle/short August feeders and long April cattle/short November feeders, pit sources said.</p>
<p>Deferred months of live cattle futures also benefited from the rally in feeders and expected tighter feeder supplies going into the fall.</p>
<p>&quot;At some juncture there's certainly reasonable assumption that (feedlot) placements will begin to fall or availble (feeder) numbers likewise will fall,&quot; Tippens said.</p>
<p>Current large fed cattle numbers and seasonally weak cash market trends into the summer kept a lid on the nearby. Steak sales usually decline after Memorial Day, except for Fathers Day, as hamburgers and hot dogs take over during the summer cookout season, they said.</p>
<p>However, rolling by both longs and shorts out of June into August accounted for the bulk of trade in nearbys, they added.</p>
<p>R.J. O'Brien bought June late after selling early and Cargill and ING bought August. RBH and LIT division of First Options spread long August/short June while Cargill Investor Services was on the other side early, pit sources said.</p>
<p>In live cattle options, LIT division of First Options actively bought August 66 puts and sold August 62 puts. Commission houses sold August 67 and 68 calls, pit sources added.</p>
<p>((Jerry Bieszk 312-408-8725))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
