<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609359" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CME hogs and pork bellies end sharply lower.</title>
<headline>CME hogs and pork bellies end sharply lower.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CME hog and pork belly futures ended shaprly lower despite some late short-covering interest as weak cash pressured hogs and technicals sent bellies down, traders said.</p>
<p>Hog futures closed off 1.000 to 0.0725 cent per lb with June off 0.725 at 80.650 cents. Pork bellies were down as much as the daily limit of 3.000 cents in May before ending off 2.750 to 1.150 with May off most and July off 1.650 at 92.500.</p>
<p>Expectations of weak cash hog markets again after the holiday continued to weigh on hog futures with sell stops added to the early setback, traders said.</p>
<p>Packers have adequate slaughter supplies on hand and hog runs are expected to be larger after the holiday while mostly lower cash pork product values will keep packer demand for hogs light. Some traders said the market also looked technically weak, but most of the pressure was attributed to the weak cash markets, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Your are getting more pressure from the fundamental side of things because the cash market is continuing to be so weak,&quot; said Julia Bussie, chartist and livestock analyst for AG Edwards.</p>
<p>Technically, hogs look oversold, Bussie added.  </p>
<p>Refco sold June and July late but bought July near the close along with Rosenthal Collins. ING, E.D.&amp;F. Man and locals sold June down into stops early, pit souces said.</p>
<p>In hog options, Cargill Investor Services sold June 81 puts and August 76 puts while Lind-Waldock sold October 78 and 80 calls and August 78 and 80 puts, pit sources added.</p>
<p>Pork belly futures came under technical selling pressure from the start.</p>
<p>&quot;Yesterday, when we failed to get contract high (in July), that was the signal that this (market) needed to, at a very minimum, do some more work on the down side,&quot; Bussie said.</p>
<p>Concern also grew that high cash prices would turn off domestic demand. Cash 14-16 lb cash bellies rose to $90 per cwt Thursday, the highest level since April 30. The last time they were up that high prices quickly turned down to under $80 before finding renewed interest, traders said.</p>
<p>Sell stops were hit under Thursday's low of 92.550 and again at 92.000 cents which added to the early decline before short covering developed. LFG and Refco sold early while Cargill bought late and Lind-Waldock sold. Scattered closing buy orders pared losses at the close, pit sources said.</p>
<p>((Jerry Bieszk 312-408-8725))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
