<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609334" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT corn futures close near three-month low.</title>
<headline>CBOT corn futures close near three-month low.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT corn ended near a three-month low Friday on prospects for good growing weather and technical weakness following Thursday's losses, traders and analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's mostly a little follow-through selling from yesterday,&quot; said Jack Scoville, analyst with The Price Group brokerage in Chicago. &quot;People are also blowing out of their positions before the long three-day holiday weekend.&quot;</p>
<p>CBOT markets will be closed Monday in observance of the U.S. Memorial Day holiday. Traders often exit positions before long weekends.</p>
<p>Weather outlooks for the Corn Belt show mostly favorable growing and planting conditions, which bodes well for the newly planted crop, traders and analysts said.</p>
<p>Rain is expected in some dry regions of the western Corn Belt and clear and warmer weather has enabled eastern Corn Belt farmers to plant, traders said.</p>
<p>The outlook for good weather throughout the Corn Belt for at least the near term and the prospects for a large crop in the fall have alleviated most supply concerns, traders said.</p>
<p>CBOT corn futures ended 2-3/4 to 4-1/4 cents per bushel lower, with July down 2-3/4 at $2.70-1/2.  </p>
<p>On the day, Term Commodities and Goldenberg Hehmeyer each sold five million bushels of December. Cargill sold two million July and one million December.</p>
<p>Prudential Securities bought three million bushels December and one million July, pit sources said.</p>
<p>In options trading, Cargill Investor Services sold 900 December $2.80 calls. FIMAT Futures Inc bought 3,000 July $2.90 puts and sold 1,500 July $2.80 puts, floor sources said.</p>
<p>Corn futures volume was estimated by CBOT at 53,000 contracts, compared with Thursday's actual volume of 54,247 contracts.</p>
<p>((Anna Driver 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
