<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609350" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT soybeans end sharply down on weather, crush.</title>
<headline>CBOT soybeans end sharply down on weather, crush.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soybean futures ended sharply lower Friday, under pressure from weekly crushing data and forecasts for good planting and growing weather in the U.S. Midwest, analysts and traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're seeing some follow-through selling from yesterday (Thursday) in anticipation of good weather and weakening demand,&quot; said Jack Scoville, analyst with The Price Group brokerage in Chicago.</p>
<p>The weekly crushing pace of 22.5 million bushels reported by the National Oilseed Processors Association was well below trade expectations and implied slowing demand for soybeans.</p>
<p>Trade estimates for the crush had ranged from 23.5 to 24.9 million bushels.</p>
<p>Weather forecasts for the Midwest also point to both favorable planting and growing conditions.</p>
<p>Dry and warmer weather this week has speeded the pace of the plantings, while periodic showers seen for this weekend should promote development of the crop that has already been planted, traders said.</p>
<p>CBOT soybeans ended down 11-1/4 to 16 cents per bushel lower, with July 10-1/4 at $8.36 and August down 16 at $8.00 per bushel.  </p>
<p>Factors said to be supportive in Friday trade included very tight supplies of soybeans, a firm basis in U.S. cash markets and a lower Brazilian soy production estimate, traders said.</p>
<p>On Friday, the Brazilian government cut the size of its soybean soybean crop forecast to 25.99 million tonnes from a previous estimate of 26.41 million tonnes.</p>
<p>However, some in the trade said a smaller production number from Brazil had been factored into the market.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that's (the production cut) already in the market,&quot; Scoville said. &quot;It's just reflecting the reality of the dry season in the southern half of Brazil.&quot;</p>
<p>On the day, Smith Barney sold four million bushels July and three million August and Iowa Grain sold three million July. Merrill Lynch bought 3.5 million July, pit sources said.</p>
<p>In options trading, Lind-Waldock bought 500 November $6.50 puts and sold 1,000 $8.50 calls. Lind-Waldock also sold 500 July $8.75 calls and bought 500 July $8.50 calls.</p>
<p>Soybean futures volume was estimated by CBOT at 53,000 contracts, compared with Thursday's actual volume of 47,564 contracts.</p>
<p>((Anna Driver 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
