<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609362" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: May Department Stores says sales better this month.</title>
<headline>May Department Stores says sales better this month.</headline>
<dateline>ST. LOUIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>May Department Stores Co., which reported disappointing sales for the first quarter of this year, said Friday that business has improved in May, and it expects Father's Day sales to be good as well.</p>
<p>&quot;So far, sales for the month of May have shown some improvement,&quot; David Farrell, chairman and chief executive, said during the company's annual meeting here.</p>
<p>The retailer, which is parent of Famous-Barr, Hecht's and Lord &amp; Taylor department stores, also said it plans to open 150 children's shoe departments across all of its store divisions by this time next year.</p>
<p>&quot;Our customers said they'd like to be able to buy children's shoes, and so we've responded,&quot; Farrell said.</p>
<p>During the first quarter, May's same-store sales, or sales at stores open a year, rose 1.9 percent, less than expected, the company said. The retailer's total sales rose 7.6 percent to $2.59 billion during the quarter.</p>
<p>Farrell said the company was more upbeat about sales for the rest of this year, including Father's Day on June 15 and for the holiday season.</p>
<p>&quot;A number of positives including low unemployment, solid wage growth, a strong stock market and an extra shopping day between Thanksgiving and Christmas leave us optimistic for the year,&quot; Farrell said.</p>
<p>May said a preliminary vote count showed shareholders had defeated three proposals brought by a union group to elect company directors annually instead of on staggered terms, to beef up the company's code of conduct for vendors and to eliminate its poison pill rights plan.</p>
<p>But the activist group that sponsored the proposals, which included the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE), said it planned to contest the company's tally of votes on the measure to eliminate the poison pill.</p>
<p>UNITE claimed that May denied some shareholders the opportunity to vote on the proposal because it was not included on an initial proxy mailed on April 17.</p>
<p>&quot;We think the company did this to manipulate the voting process,&quot; said Marka Peterson, a spokeswoman for UNITE.</p>
<p>But May said that while it did not include the measure on initial proxy mailing, it did notify shareholders the proposal was forthcoming.</p>
<p>&quot;It wasn't on the initial proxy card, but we notified shareholders,&quot; said May spokeswoman Rhonda West.</p>
<p>UNITE said it has filed a lawsuit in U.S. District Court in New York to have May's first proxy card declared illegal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I65600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I6560002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ST. LOUIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
