<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609335" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mass. miracle elevates Jewish-born nun to sainthood.</title>
<headline>Mass. miracle elevates Jewish-born nun to sainthood.</headline>
<byline>Michael Ellis</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The miraculous recovery of the daughter of a Massachusetts priest from a near-coma has elevated a Jewish-born nun who died in a Nazi concentration camp to sainthood, officials said on Friday.</p>
<p>Pope John Paul II on Thursday officially approved for canonisation Edith Stein, a Polish Jew who converted to Catholicism in 1922 and became a nun before she died in the Auschwitz gas chambers in 1942.</p>
<p>The process of Stein's elevation began in March 1987 when 2-year-old Teresia Benedicta McCarthy, who has the same name as the martyred nun after her baptism, swallowed a near-lethal dose of Tylenol and suffered serious internal damage.</p>
<p>Her father, the Rev. Emmanuel Charles McCarthy, a priest in the Melkite Rite of the Catholic Church, which allows clergy to marry, appealed to friends and family to pray to Edith Stein for the child's recovery.</p>
<p>&quot;Right from the very beginning, the parents placed a cross on her bed that they had gotten from the Edith Stein guild,&quot; Monsignor Robert Deeley, who headed a Boston tribunal that investigated the miracle, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Dr. Ronald Kleinman, a pediatric specialist at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, treated Benedicta and did not believe she would recover.</p>
<p>&quot;She had very severe liver damage and kidney damage,&quot; he said in a telephone interview. &quot;That's why I did not expect her to recover from the damage that was done to her organs. We listed her for a liver transplant.&quot;</p>
<p>After about four days, Benedicta made a sudden recovery and was soon back home with no long-lasting effects from the ordeal.</p>
<p>Kleinman, who is Jewish, testified before Deeley's tribunal in Boston and a second tribunal in Rome last year. &quot;The fact that she turned around after being that sick was unexpected. I was willing to say that it was miraculous,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But some Jewish groups worry that Stein's canonisation may diminish her Jewish origins, which directly led to her death at the hands of the Nazis.</p>
<p>&quot;She was in fact murdered with so many others because she was a Jew,&quot; said Elan Steinberg, executive director of the World Jewish Congress. &quot;In that sense, the notion that her suffering contributes to her beatification minimises the fact that the 90 plus percent of those murdered at Auschwitz were Jews.&quot;</p>
<p>The fact that the Catholic Church also began the process of Stein's canonisation at about the same time as the controversial building of a Catholic convent on the grounds of Auschwitz also angered some Jewish groups, Steinberg said.</p>
<p>Still, Benedicta's father said he hopes the life of Edith Stein can teach Christians a lesson.</p>
<p>&quot;She lived with, she prayed with, suffered with and ultimately died with Jewish people, which is ultimately how Christians should relate to Jewish people,&quot; McCarthy said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
