<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609338" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT wheat ends mostly lower on weather.</title>
<headline>CBOT wheat ends mostly lower on weather.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soft red winter wheat futures closed mostly lower on overall good crop weather in U.S. winter and spring wheat growing regions, traders said.</p>
<p>Showers overnight in portions of Kansas and Nebraska wheat growing areas added to the bearish mode of the market and routine export business failed to generate new buying interest, the traders said. Also, the technical slide continued as July fell into a narrow chart gap left in April.</p>
<p>The 1-1/4 cent gap from $3.73 to $3.74-1/4 was set on April 7 and was being viewed by some technical traders as an area &quot;necessary to fill&quot; and was an area of support.</p>
<p>Traders said a late recovery in the July and September contracts was tied to commercial buying and to the filling in of the chart gaps.</p>
<p>&quot;They got the gaps filled and needed to buy some on the close,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Cargill Inc was a late purchaser of 1.5 million bushels of July and also bought one million bushels of September.</p>
<p>&quot;They were a buyer late and that triggered buy stops and short covering,&quot; said Vic Lespinasse of Dean Witter.</p>
<p>CBOT wheat closed 4-3/4 cents lower to one higher, with July down 2-1/4 at $3.75 a bushel.  </p>
<p>Traders said the market shrugged off talk that circulated on the trading floor that China may have bought one million tonnes of wheat from the U.S. and U.S. exporters said there were no indications that such a sale had taken place.</p>
<p>Position squaring was noted before the three-day holiday weekend. Markets will be closed Monday, Memorial Day, and trading was slated to resume on CBOT's Project A overnight trading Monday night, traders said.</p>
<p>FIMAT Futures sold six million bushels of July and LIT America sold two million July but bought 2.5 million July in later dealings, traders said. Prudential Securities bought 2.5 million July and bought one million bushels of December, traders said.</p>
<p>Wheat futures volume was estimated by the CBOT at 15,000 contracts, below the 16,422 traded Thursday.</p>
<p>In wheat options, Goldenberg Hehmeyer sold 900 July $3.80 calls at eight to 8-1/4 cents, Refco Inc bought 400 September $3.90 puts at 24 to 24-1/2 cents and Tenco Inc bought 200 September $4.60 puts at 81-1/2 cents, traders said. Tenco also bought 200 September $4.50 puts at 73-1/2 and sold 200 September $3.80 calls at 20-1/2 cents, traders said.</p>
<p>Wheat options volume was estimated at 8,500 contracts, below the 10,925 traded Thursday.</p>
<p>((Sam Nelson 312-408-8721))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
