<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609360" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. museum gives Italy stolen art treasure.</title>
<headline>U.S. museum gives Italy stolen art treasure.</headline>
<dateline>HARTFORD, Connecticut 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 16th century Florentine painting that found its way to Hartford after being stolen by Soviet troops during the last days of World War Two will be given back to Italy, museum officials said on Friday.</p>
<p>Jacopo Zucchi's &quot;The Bath of Bathsheba,&quot; a rare Italian Mannerist painting, was stolen from the Italian embassy in Berlin but eventually surfaced on the Paris market, where in 1965 the Hartford museum purchased it for $35,000.</p>
<p>Gary Frank, public relations officer at the Wadsworth Atheneum, said the painting now valued at between $500,000 and $700,000 was the museum's most prized Italian Mannerist work.</p>
<p>The museum will give the painting to Italy in return for an exclusive exhibit of 29 Italian masterworks, including Caravaggio's &quot;Narcissus.&quot;</p>
<p>The exchange stems from an agreement between the Wadsworth Atheneum, the Italian government and the Galleria Nazionale d'Arte Anticas in Rome, where the Zucchi work will eventually be housed, Frank said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the right thing to do,&quot; Frank told Reuters. &quot;It was taken from them, and it rightfully belongs to the people of Italy.&quot;</p>
<p>Frank said the museum purchased the painting in good faith not knowing that it was part of the Italian government's permanent collection.</p>
<p>Italian officials first contacted the Wadsworth Atheneum to claim the painting in the 1970s, but no agreement could be reached until now.</p>
<p>Frank said the eventual agreement was a &quot;win-win deal&quot; for both parties.</p>
<p>The Wadsworth Atheneum, founded in 1842, is the oldest continuously operating public art museum in the U.S. It is known for its Italian baroque paintings and Hudson River collection, among others.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARTFORD, Connecticut"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
