<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609377" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Treasuries end higher ahead of holiday weekend.</title>
<headline>US Treasuries end higher ahead of holiday weekend.</headline>
<byline>John P. Hughes</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The prices of U.S. Treasury securities closed slightly higher ahead of a three-day weekend on Friday with no economic data to trade upon.</p>
<p>Bond traders headed out of work early in an abbreviated pre-holiday session. The market closed at 1400 EDT/1800 GMT ahead of the three-day Memorial Day weekend in the U.S.</p>
<p>The yield on the 30-year bond continued to hover near the 7.0 percent level and analysts said it was likely to remain there during the foreseeable future as little market-moving data was scheduled for release.  </p>
<p>Hugh Johnson, chief economist at First Albany Corp., said bond market focus would likely remain on the value of the dollar versus the yen as little market-moving economic releases were expected near-term.</p>
<p>&quot;Durable goods may move prices, but it's hard to forecast those numbers,&quot; Johnson said. &quot;The problem facing the bond market is that the dollar will re-weaken against the yen.&quot;</p>
<p>Johnson said that fear was the only factor pressuring the market following the good news that the Federal Reserve had not voted to tighten monetary policy on Tuesday.  </p>
<p>Unwinding of yen/dollar carry trade was bound to occur next week, Johnson said. &quot;Significant positions need to be unwound and that will be reflected next week,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Given that factor, it would be difficult for yields on the long bond to remain below 7.0 percent in the absence of significant economic news, he said. Participants needed some confirmation that the economy continued to slow before becoming bullish and that might not occur until the release of the May nonfarm payrolls report on June 6.</p>
<p>Retail sales slowed 0.3 percent in April, giving analysts some hope the economy was slowing from unsustainable levels.  </p>
<p>&quot;It's been a very quiet session with a little bounce overnight. There was some hedge selling in the long end in the morning,&quot; said Michael Strauss, chief economist at Sanwa Securities (USA) Co.</p>
<p>Durable goods and consumer confidence could show strength next week, but none of the data were expected to move the market strongly in either direction.</p>
<p>John Canavan, analyst at Stone &amp; McCarthy Research Associates Inc, said the market was just marking time ahead of the holiday weekend in Friday's trading session.  </p>
<p>&quot;It was mostly holding flat to slightly higher. It will continue to test the 7.0 percent level next week,&quot; Canavan said.</p>
<p>He expected the yield on the 30-year bond to rise above 7.0 percent, but also thought the dollar had begun to stabilize following recent losses in value against the Japanese yen.</p>
<p>&quot;(Treasury Secretary Robert) Rubin is saying U.S. policy to defend the dollar is appropriate and Japan is saying the correction is finished,&quot; Strauss said.  </p>
<p>The dollar could remain volatile in trading next week but neither crash nor soar, Strauss said.</p>
<p>The 30-year bond was up 1/32 at 95-15/32 to yield 6.99 percent. The 10-year note closed at 99-4/32, up 1/32 to yield 6.75 percent. Five-year notes ended at 100-6/32, up 1/32 to yield 6.58 percent. Two-year notes closed at 100-8/32, unchanged to yield 6.23 percent.</p>
<p>Three-month bill rates fell two basis points to 5.02 percent. Six-month bill rates rose one basis point to 5.24 percent. Year bill rates were uncjanged at 5.53 percent.</p>
<p>((-- North American Treasury Desk 212-859-1663))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
