<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609397" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Brady bonds rise before Brazil swap, Ecuador poll.</title>
<headline>Brady bonds rise before Brazil swap, Ecuador poll.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Emerging debt prices ambled higher Friday on continued enthusiasm for Brazil's Brady bond swap and projections for a weekend referendum in Ecuador, traders said.</p>
<p>U.S. trading closed early Friday at 1400 EDT/1800 GMT, and there will be no activity on Monday in observance of the Memorial Day holiday.</p>
<p>Brazil &quot;C&quot; bonds  BR8D14=RR continued their upward path gaining 1/2 to 79-1/2 bid, following passage of a re-election amendment and the country's plan to swap or buy back some of its Brady debt, traders said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The topic of the week was the Brazil debt exchange,&quot; said one chief Brady bond trader. &quot;We didn't see any real (investor) flow. It's only dealers.&quot;</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Brazil announced an offer to pay investors cash for their Par bonds  BR4D24=RR, and Discount Z-L bonds BRFLTD24=RR, or swap Pars, Discounts, or &quot;C&quot; bonds BR8D14=RR for 30-year uncollaterized global bonds.</p>
<p>&quot;Brazil is outperforming the other Bradies and U.S. Treasuries,&quot; said Marcelo Fleury, who runs the Brazil desk at broker Garban Corp. &quot;It's mainly Wall Street players and locals players who are speculating on the upside.&quot;  </p>
<p>Market talk pegged the Brazilian global pricing at 350-375 basis points over Treasuries. Mexico's comparable global bond due 2026  MXUMS=RR now trades around 332 basis points over.</p>
<p>Ecuador's paper performed well ahead of Sunday's national referendum on the mandate of President Fabian Alarcon.</p>
<p>Ecuador PDIs  ECPDI=RR gained 5/8 at 63-3/8 bid, and Discounts  ECDISC=RR picked up 3/8 to 68-7/8.</p>
<p>Public support for the referendum, which had been running at more than 70 percent several months ago, now stands about 55 percent, but analysts noted that polls in Ecuador had proved unreliable in the past.  </p>
<p>&quot;If Alarcon gets a yes vote and has a short honeymoon, he can put together some relatively tame reforms, that would be good,&quot; said Tulio Vera, managing director at Bear Stearns. &quot;But the polls are too close for me to take that bet.&quot;</p>
<p>-- G. Lerner, 212-859-1671</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
