<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609388" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NASD muni overseer eyes pay-to-play waivers.</title>
<headline>NASD muni overseer eyes pay-to-play waivers.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>National Association of Securities Dealers' new muni compliance chief said Friday that bond firms need clearer guidance from his group on when they may qualify for waivers under MSRB's pay-to-play rule.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there ought to be some bright lines,&quot; Malcolm Northam, director of fixed income securities regulation at NASD, said at NASD's Spring Securities Conference here.</p>
<p>He said he may be willing to grant waivers for one-time transgressions involving modest dollar amounts at firms with clear procedures in place for monitoring contributions.  </p>
<p>Currently, NASD rarely grants waivers under the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board's pay-to-play rule G-37, which bars dealers that make contributions to issuer clients from doing business for two years with those governments.</p>
<p>But Northam, who joined NASD on May 5, said firms that uncover and report violations and have diligent recordkeeping procedures in place should be treated &quot;a little bit differently&quot; than firms with no procedures and whose violations were uncovered by investigators.  </p>
<p>Northam said he did a quick review of NASD records of MSRB rule violations in the last half of 1996 and &quot;the results are not pretty.&quot;</p>
<p>He said a whopping 32 percent were violations of MSRB's failure to supervise rule G-27 and 22 percent were problems with recordkeeping rule G-8.</p>
<p>&quot;That's serious,&quot; Northam said of the G-27 violations. &quot;This isn't one of those pesky little recordkeeping rules. Rule G-27 says you will maintain written procedures, have a compliance officer, and review on a regular basis muni transactions (for) irregularities.&quot;  </p>
<p>Northam, who works for the the regulatory arm of NASD called NASD Regulation, said the recordkeeping violations probably were connected with political contributions reporting.</p>
<p>In other comments, Northam said NASDR inspectors will focus in months ahead on compliance with MSRB's transaction reporting rule G-14 and its rule G-36, which requires dealers to send copies of OSs to MSRB within certain timeframes.</p>
<p>&quot;(We get) continual verbal complaints that it's impossible to get the official statements from the issuer, therefore, it's impossible to file it in a timely fashion,&quot; Northam said.  </p>
<p>But Northam said the onus is on busy dealers to take the time to do the &quot;follow-up&quot; required to get the documents.</p>
<p>&quot;The dealmakers do the deals and then (go) on to the next deal,&quot; he said. &quot;I certainly understand the business side of the process. But, no one is following up -- either the middle or back office, or the underwriting syndicate manager -- to make sure it's done.&quot;</p>
<p>Northam said NASD also is getting &quot;continual anecdotal complaints&quot; that firms are not sending officials statements to investors at or before the date of final settlement, as required by MSRB rule G-32.  </p>
<p>He said NASD also will be looking at that issue and other complaints about bond syndicate practices.</p>
<p>NASD conducts routine compliance exams of muni shops at least once every two years. &quot;You shouldn't be surprised if we have a look at rules G-36, G-37 and G-38. So go back and fix the issues that are there before we have to find them,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said while setting up compliance procedures at firms tends to be &quot;messy,&quot; it is important. &quot;This is not inconsequential stuff,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Northam said, in general, NASD district o ffices are not going to be very &quot;patient&quot; with firms out of sync with rules G-37 and G-36.</p>
<p>&quot;These rules have been around for awhile. I don't think we ought to expect disrict offices to listen to you whine and complain,&quot; he said, stressing that those were his personal views</p>
<p>He said if firms try to &quot;bury&quot; problems with political contributions, for instance, NASD has the option of reviewing political filing records in the particular state. &quot;We can simply go down through the campaign records and find out who gave,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Northam said compliance officers at firms themselves should be &quot;proactive.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked whether he means that dealers should research local campaign disclosure filings, Northam said, &quot;I'm not suggesting they do anything of the sort.&quot; But he signaled that they could consider reviewing local records in some cases.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
