<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609392" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Banks bracing for more bad consumer loans.</title>
<headline>Banks bracing for more bad consumer loans.</headline>
<byline>Glenn Somerville</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Banks are bracing for more consumer loans to go bad and have extended a year-old trend toward restricting their lending to individuals, a Federal Reserve survey said Friday.</p>
<p>The latest findings from loan officers at 59 domestic banks and 24 U.S. branches and agencies of foreign banks showed a sharp divergence in willingness to extend credit to businesses and to individuals.</p>
<p>&quot;The responses suggest that over the past three months domestic banks have become more accommodative lenders to businesses but have tightened credit to households,&quot; the Fed said.</p>
<p>&quot;Once again, both standards and terms for consumer loans were tightened and banks reported less demand for these loans,&quot; the survey said. It updates a survey conducted during January and issued early in February.</p>
<p>Standards for home mortgages were little changed from January but demand for them weakened a little, the survey found.</p>
<p>The Fed noted that banks began toughening their rules for lending to consumers early in 1996 and were still doing so.</p>
<p>&quot;Nearly one-half the banks said they had tightened standards for new credit-card accounts over the preceding three months, and one-fifth reported having tightened standards on other consumer loans,&quot; the survey said.</p>
<p>Forty percent of the banks said they reduced their credit limits on credit-card lines since January.</p>
<p>Furthermore, about one-third of the banks foresaw charge-off rates for consumer loans climbing, primarily because more people were willing to declare bankruptcy and stop paying.</p>
<p>A smaller proportion of banks -- about one-quarter of those surveyed -- anticipating having to charge off more business or commercial and industrial loans in coming months.</p>
<p>&quot;Banks pointed to eased standards for these loans, a deterioration in business financial conditions, and a deterioration in the economy generally as the reasons for their outlook,&quot; the Fed said.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, banks appeared eager to keep lending to businesses.</p>
<p>The survey said stiff competition had caused many banks to offer easier terms for both commercial and industrial and for commercial real estate loans. It said there has been &quot;a slight strengthening&quot; in demand for both types of business credit.</p>
<p>The Fed noted some differences developing in lending patterns between domestic banks and the U.S. branches of foreign banks.</p>
<p>It said &quot;small net fractions&quot; of foreign-controlled banks had tightened some terms on commercial loans since January.</p>
<p>&quot;This represents a shift for foreign banks, which reported having eased terms on these loans for the past several surveys,&quot; the Fed said.</p>
<p>The banks that tightened their commercial lending rules said they did so because of &quot;lower tolerance for risk and a deterioration in their current or expected capital position,&quot; the survey said.</p>
<p>But the larger percentage of banks that went the other route -- making it easier for businesses to get loans -- said their motivation was more aggressive competition from other banks and from nonbank sources of credit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
