<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609384" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US CREDIT OUTLOOK-Data smothered by 2-, 5-yr sales.</title>
<headline>US CREDIT OUTLOOK-Data smothered by 2-, 5-yr sales.</headline>
<byline>Alden Bentley</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1996-05-24</dateline>
<text>
<p>The main events for the U.S. fixed-income markets next week will be the Treasury auctions of two- and five-year notes, with a handful of economic numbers likely to offer a brief diversion, analysts said.</p>
<p>Absent a big surprise, the markets are unlikely to glean much direction on the week's data, experts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're going to be focused on how the market handles twos- and five-years in the context of support from the neutral bias at the (Federal Reserve) and no change in policy on May 20,&quot; said Josh Stiles, senior bond analyst at I.D.E.A. Inc.  </p>
<p>Going into the auctions, the market will probably remain somewhat unsettled by the release of the minutes of the March 25 Federal Open Market Committee meeting, analysts said.</p>
<p>The transcripts showed that the vote to raise the federal funds rate 25 basis points on that day was unanimous, with some members disagreeing on the size of the hike.</p>
<p>But the panel also voted 10-to-one to move to a neutral policy bias -- from a tightening bias -- on the same day, leaving the market still pondering the implications as the week drew to a close.  </p>
<p>The Treasury is scheduled to sell $16.5 billion in two-year notes on Wednesday and $12 billion in five-year notes on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;If twos and fives get a good reception it will probably give the whole market a lift because they (yields) have backed up enough to where there is room to improve,&quot; Santow said. &quot;I would say the financings would probably be the key item for the market.</p>
<p>Major data wise, the Conference Board's Consumer Confidence Index for May and April existing home sales kick off the holiday-shortened week at 1000 EDT/1400 GMT Tuesday.  </p>
<p>Economists surveyed by Reuters look for a 118.1 reading on the Consumer Sentiment Index, up from 116.8 in April. Home sales were seen at a 4.09 million unit annualized rate, slower than 4.11 million in March.</p>
<p>Durable goods orders for April, due at 0830 EDT/1230 GMT on Wednesday, were forecast to have risen 1.3 percent after slumping 2.6 percent previously.</p>
<p>&quot;Durable goods orders might provide something, but I think the expectation of a rise, after a decline last month, would generally be expected and probably would not cause the market to be much ... driven by it,&quot; Santow said.  </p>
<p>Friday brings the revision to first-quarter gross domestic product growth, which is expected to edge up to 6.0 percent, from a preliminary 5.6 percent.</p>
<p>The price index and implicit price deflator are seen unrevised at 2.7 percent and 2.3 percent, respectively.</p>
<p>Also on Friday, at 1000 EDT/1400 GMT, comes new home sales for April, seen at 800,000 units, annualized, off from 813,000 units. At the same time, the Chicago purchasing managers index is forecast at 56.8 in May, down from 57.2.</p>
<p>((--212 859 1667))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-24"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
