<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609307" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. stock index futures end strongly higher.</title>
<headline>U.S. stock index futures end strongly higher.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. stock index futures finished up strongly, with some at record highs ahead of the long weekend.</p>
<p>Trading overall was quiet and pits thin as many players began the long Memorial Day weekend early. There will be no U.S. trading on Monday, and debt futures closed early today.</p>
<p>June Standard and Poor's 500 futures rallied to a fresh record high at 852.00 in light trading when buying emerged after the Treasury bond futures close. Traders said the illiquid market offered little resistance.</p>
<p>June easily surpassed the old high of 849.50.  </p>
<p>June shaved gains slightly into the close and settled up 7.50 points at 847.75 in a range from 841.60 to 852.00.</p>
<p>One broker said a firm Nasdaq urged S&amp;P 500 futures into record territory, helped by local buying.</p>
<p>June Nasdaq 100 futures ended up 12.50 points at 963.25, just shy of the 966.00 record set Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We're missing some liquidity and it's one of those days where locals can have their way with this stuff,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the push to record territory came on light volume.</p>
<p>&quot;It's really very quiet,&quot; another trader said.  </p>
<p>&quot;It was a nice little rally, but it was very quiet,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>At the close, KCBT Value Lines were up 4.60 at 749.05, NYSE Composites were up 3.40 at 440.50, Nikkeis were up 170 at 20,100, Midcap 400s rose 3.45 to 276.45, and Russell 2000s were up 4.05 to 378.50. ((Derivatives desk 312-408-8750))</p>
<p>E-mail derivatives@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
