<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609336" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NY physical coffee - Brazil diffs continue to fall.</title>
<headline>NY physical coffee - Brazil diffs continue to fall.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cash spreads on Brazilian coffees continued to sink this week, while differentials on other grades held steady against lofty futures prices, New York physical traders said.</p>
<p>Leftover stocks of coffee from last season's crop and mounting pressure from the just-started 1997/98 harvest -- as well as producers desire to cash in on sky-high futures prices -- has caused differentials from top-grower Brazil to slide.</p>
<p>&quot;Brazilians have a lot of coffee and they're saying let's sell it before this market collapses,&quot; said a trader. &quot;They've been shipping coffee like crazy.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;The physical market is slowing down,&quot; said one dealer. &quot;It's the end of this year's crop -- Colombians, Mexicans and Central Americans are cleaned out until the fall.</p>
<p>&quot;Roaster are covered,&quot; he added, &quot;it's getting toward the low consumption season and prices are too high to take any longer position.&quot;</p>
<p>Surging prices on the futures market have forced roasters to pass along higher costs to consumers. This week, largest U.S. roasters Folgers Coffee Co. and  Maxwell House Coffee Co. raised the list price on its standard 13-ounce cans of regular and decaffeinated ground coffees by 30 cents.</p>
<p>CSCE July coffee fell 2.45 cents a lb Friday to settle at 256.85. September ended 3.90 cents lower at 226.05.</p>
<p>Differentials for spot coffee in New York, ex-warehouse, were quoted as follows, all against the CSCE May contract:</p>
<p>  USc/Lb			Differentials (basis July)     Last</p>
<p>  Santos 4's		  56 cts under &quot;C&quot;	     200.85 N</p>
<p>  Colombian MAMs	    40 cts over &quot;C&quot;		296.85 N</p>
<p>  El Salvador		 25 cts over &quot;C&quot;		281.85 N</p>
<p>  Mexican		     20 cts over &quot;C&quot;		276.85 N</p>
<p>  Guatemala		   26 cts over &quot;C&quot;		282.85 N</p>
<p>  Peru			  20 cts over &quot;C&quot;		276.85 N</p>
<p>  Uganda Pmy Robs	   12 cts over London	   106.61 N</p>
<p>  Indonesia EK1		4 cts under London	   90.61 N</p>
<p>  Ecuador Ext Sup	   16 cts under &quot;C&quot;	     240.85 N</p>
<p>--New York Commodity Desk, 212-859-1640</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
