<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609460" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French rightist hurt in clash with anti-racists.</title>
<headline>French rightist hurt in clash with anti-racists.</headline>
<dateline>MARSEILLE, France 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Members of the far-right National Front clashed with anti-racist protesters in the town of Vitrolles, two days before the French vote in parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>The National Front and the protesters blamed each other for the brawl in which the Front said Claude Bourges, an aide to the southern town's Front mayor, was injured in the jaw and taken to hospital.</p>
<p>Police intervened when fighting broke out in Vitrolles' open-air market between members of the Front and militants of the group &quot;Ras le Front&quot; (Enough of the Front). Both sides had been distributing leaflets ahead of Sunday's first round of France's parliamentary election.</p>
<p>The rightists included deputy party leader Bruno Megret, whose wife Catherine was elected mayor this year to make Vitrolles the fourth town in France in the hands of Jean-Marie Le Pen's anti-immigrant party.</p>
<p>Bruno Megret said his wife had filed lawsuits against the head of the SOS Racism group, Fode Sylla, and others for inciting the violence in the town of 40,000.</p>
<p>&quot;Catherine and Bruno Megret and their militants were violently and deliberately attacked, verbally and physically,&quot; a statement said.</p>
<p>Sylla retorted that a member of the Megrets' security force &quot;took a pistol out of his jacket&quot; at the beginning of the trouble. The Megrets and their followers had started shoving people around, throwing tear gas canisters, he said.</p>
<p>The Front said two of its substitute election candidates were attacked in other towns and one of them was in hospital.</p>
<p>A left-wing senator, a member of the European Parliament and others said they had set up a Movement for the Dissolution of the National Front, calling for the Front to be outlawed under a 1936 law banning groups which incite racial hatred.</p>
<p>A police union requested an investigation into the Front's security service and called for its dissolution under the same law, which also bans paramilitary groups.</p>
<p>Opinion polls published before a legal blackout last weekend gave the Front about 15 percent of the vote and up to three seats in the 577-seat National Assembly.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARSEILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
