<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609493" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: UN optimistic Iraq oil-for-food program will go on.</title>
<headline>UN optimistic Iraq oil-for-food program will go on.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Yasushi Akashi, the U.N. humanitarian affairs coordinator, said on Friday he was optimistic the oil-for-food plan for Iraq would be renewed next month despite recent criticisms from the United States.</p>
<p>Both the United States and Iraq have raised doubts for different reasons about continuing the plan on the same terms.</p>
<p>&quot;I am optimistic by nature,&quot; he told a news conference. &quot;If everything goes well... I think an extension may not be such a big surprise.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Prima facia, one can say the (Iraqi) government is making a good effort to distribute the food on an equitable basis,&quot; he said in answer to questions.</p>
<p>At issue is a June renewal of an accord that went into effect on Dec. 10. It allows Iraq to sell up to $2 billion of oil over six months in order to purchase food, medicine and other goods. Its people are suffering under U.N. sanctions imposed when Baghdad's troops invaded Kuwait in August 1990.</p>
<p>U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan is expected to give his recommendations shortly on the plan and the 15-member Security Council has to decide to renew it and on what terms.</p>
<p>U.S. Ambassador Bill Richardson said on Thursday, &quot;We are not in a position to say Iraq and the United Nations have implemented the resolution as it was intended, adding that Washington &quot;expected the operation to be far more transparent than it has proven to be in practice.&quot;</p>
<p>He said he needed more information on Iraq's distribution methods, U.N. monitoring methods and implmentation of the programme in the Kurdish-dominated north, which receives a separate allocation.</p>
<p>Akashi said he had spoken at length with Edward Gnehm, the deputy U.S. representative and Middle East expert, mainly about the Kurdish North and believed many of the problems had been clarified.</p>
<p>He said &quot;high expectations&quot; had been created in the north with some believing that all economic, social and educational programmes could be solved through the infusion of supplies.</p>
<p>But he said the plan as a whole was working and 150 U.N. monitors in Iraq had &quot;full freedom of movement. &quot;</p>
<p>The biggest problem, he said, was the late arrival of goods -- particularly medicines -- compared to the 550,000 tons of food that had arrived to date.</p>
<p>&quot;There are a lot of emaciated children and there is a clear lack of medicine and essential medicine. Old needles are still being used for injections,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Iraq, on the other hand, has doubts about the programme because of the delay in supplies, which it has attributed to U.S. actions in the sanctions committee.</p>
<p>Richardson contended that U.S. objections to individual contracts were not politically motivated. He said the contracts it had &quot;put on hold&quot; involved improper procedures or concerned items not on the distribution list.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
