<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609466" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Soccer transfer creates legal woes for Berlusconi.</title>
<headline>Soccer transfer creates legal woes for Berlusconi.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former prime minister Silvio Berlusconi faced fresh legal woes on Friday when a magistrate asked for him to stand trial for alleged irregularities in the transfer to his AC Milan soccer club of Gianluigi Lentini.</p>
<p>Milan state prosecutor Gherardo Colombo said he had recommended that Berlusconi, in his capacity as president of the club, should be tried for falsifying accounts to conceal illegal payments alleged to have been made to secure Lentini in 1992.</p>
<p>Colombo called for Berlusconi's brother Paolo, who sits on the AC Milan board, and a lawyer, Massimo Maria Berruti, to stand trial on the same charges.</p>
<p>An examining judge must now decide whether to commit the three men to trial or drop the case. No date was immediately set for the hearing.</p>
<p>AC Milan said in a statement that the operations to buy Lentini were carried out in a completely regular way in respect of all the regulations including tax regulations.</p>
<p>&quot;No slush funds were set up, there were no payments made that were not registered correctly in the accounts,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The statement said the club did not understand on what basis the magistrate backed up the request but added it was certain the matter would be clarified.</p>
<p>Lentini was transferred from Torino, currently in Italy's second division, for an official fee of 18 billion lire ($11 million).</p>
<p>The Berlusconi brothers and Berruti are accused of concealing an additional 10 billion lire payment allegedly made to former Torino president Gian Mauro Borsano in a Swiss bank account.</p>
<p>Prosecutors called two months ago for AC Milan's managing director Adriano Galliani to stand trial for his alleged part in the affair.</p>
<p>Berlusconi, who served as prime minister for seven months in 1994, is on trial in Milan on charges of bribing tax inspectors in return for lenient audits of his companies.</p>
<p>In a separate trial he is accused of channelling bribes to disgraced former socialist prime minister Bettino Craxi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
