<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609478" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU details concerns about Boeing, McDonnell deal.</title>
<headline>EU details concerns about Boeing, McDonnell deal.</headline>
<byline>Amelia Torres</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission has serious concerns about the proposed merger between Boeing and McDonnell Douglas and the companies would be well advised to address them, EU competition sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>While Boeing's long-term exclusive supply deals with American Airlines, a unit of AMR, and Delta Air Lines were a key problem, they added, scrapping those deals alone would not solve the competition problems.</p>
<p>Noting that Boeing already has a 64 percent share of the global commercial aircraft market and enjoys a monopoly in the jumbo jet segment, they said the deal would give it even stronger bargaining power.</p>
<p>In a statement of objections of nearly 40 pages sent to the parties on Wednesday, the Commission detailed meticulously its concerns about the $14 billion deal announced in December, which would leave the world market at the mercy of only two aircraft manufacturers: Boeing and Airbus Industrie .</p>
<p>The merger would increase Boeing's share of the market for large aircraft -- with a capacity of more than 100 seats -- to 70 percent, given McDonnell's six-percent share of total aircraft orders at the end of 1996, the officials said, quoting from the statement.</p>
<p>Moreover, Boeing would increase its customer base to 84 percent from 60 percent, they said, eager to demonstrate that McDonnell was not as negligible a player as portrayed by Boeing's chairman and CEO Philip Condit.</p>
<p>Spanish airline Iberia, Scandinavian Airlines System (SAS) and Alitalia all have a substantial number of McDonnell planes in their fleet. As a result of the merger, Boeing would most likely replace them when they are retired.</p>
<p>The European Commission started an in-depth probe into the merger in March 19 after Boeing submitted it for regulatory approval in both the EU and the United States. The American Federal Trade Commission, which is pursuing its own investigation, has not yet commented.</p>
<p>The issue has rapidly caused tensions on both sides of the Atlantic, largely because of European Competition Commissioner Karel Van Miert's open oposition earlier this month to the exclusive supply pacts.</p>
<p>Slade Gorton, U.S. senator for Washington, where Boeing is based, led the offensive by writing to President Bill Clinton to ensure that the merger gets a fair review from the EU and accusing Van Miert of protecting the interests of Airbus.</p>
<p>Boeing has also argued that the FTC should be given the lead role under an EU-U.S. cooperation agreement on competition issues.</p>
<p>But the Commission has denied that the agreement covers mergers, where there is specific legislation empowering the EU to rule against a deal if it creates or strengthens a dominant position in the 15-nation Union.</p>
<p>&quot;They must reflect on what they can do or offer to meet our concerns,&quot; one of the sources said, saying it was not for the Commission to propose remedies.</p>
<p>The two partners will have the opportunity to answer the Commission's objections at a closed hearing on June 12 and 13 in Brussels. Competitors and government antitrust officials will also be invited to state their views at the meeting before the Commission reaches a final decision by a July 31 deadline.</p>
<p>The Commission is also concerned that government subsidies involved in generously calculated U.S. military contracts will spill over to Boeing's commercial airplane programmes.</p>
<p>This, the sources said, was a legitimate worry and entirely separate from recently revived transatlantic talks on aircraft subsidies, which for the EU are being dealt with by Trade Commissioner Sir Leon Brittan.</p>
<p>McDonnell Douglas derives about 70 percent of its total business from the defence and space sector.</p>
<p>Other concerns relate to Boeing's reinforced bargaining power vis-a-vis suppliers, creation of a &quot;gigantic&quot; portfolio of intellectual property rights and an increase in Boeing's production capacity due in particular to the welcome addition of McDonnell's engineers, the sources said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
