<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609486" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: U.N. suspends Canada's Skylink firm from contracts.</title>
<headline>U.N. suspends Canada's Skylink firm from contracts.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United Nations said on Friday it suspended all contracts for helicopters and other aircraft with the Skylink company following years of controversy involving the Canadian-based firm.</p>
<p>No reason was given for the suspension after an investigation by the Office of Internal Oversight Services, the U.N. equivalent of an inspector-general headed by Karl Paschke of Germany. Its report is expected to be made public at a future date.</p>
<p>&quot;The United Nations has decided not to issue any further contracts to the Skylink corporation from which it has chartered planes and other air services in the past,&quot; spokesman Fred Eckhard said.</p>
<p>&quot;The feeling was that it would be irresponsible in light of the findings to conduct further business with Skylink at this time,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>U.N officials said the report involved a broad analysis of the U.N. air charter operations, their safety records and the bidding process. Skylink was not the only company fingered.</p>
<p>In 1993, the United Nations accused four of its high-level procurement officials of allegedly showing favoritism in awarding contracts to Skylink, which supplied aircraft in numerous peacekeeping operations.</p>
<p>Three other officials were reprimanded and one was cleared of any suspicion. Then 18 months later all were cleared of the allegations in a debacle that showed confusion and incompetence in the U.N. probe.</p>
<p>Skylink was first suspended and then reinstated in 1994. In February a Skylink-chartered helicopter crashed in Macedonia after apparently hitting a power line, killing a Canadian pilot and three Finnish peacekeepers.</p>
<p>Skylink dominated the U.N. air charter business in 1993, winning 68 percent of the contracts and earning about $179 million that year.</p>
<p>But a U.S. company, Evergreen, with the help of U.S. officials, challenged its near monopoly, saying that the bidding was unfair and prompting former Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali to initiate the investigation.</p>
<p>Several U.N. and American officials disputed this at the time, contending that the small U.N. staff was under pressure to mobilize aircraft for the growing peacekeeping mission and the Canadian firm came in quickly with low bids.</p>
<p>The case became a nightmare when new companies that won contracts to replace Skylink on Bosnia in 1994 repeatedly failed to show up or had faulty safety records.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, questions had also arisen about Skylink's safety record, after a series of crashes in Cambodia in 1993 that resulted in a temporary grounding of its entire fleet.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
