<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609423" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Nassau County, N.Y., golf course to forego bonds.</title>
<headline>Nassau County, N.Y., golf course to forego bonds.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A proposed nine-hole golf course within the Cedar Park Complex in Seaford, N.Y., would be Nassau County's first county-owned course built without using municipal bonds, according to a spokesman for County Executive Thomas Gulotta.</p>
<p>&quot;Really, what this is is a privatization of the county's park facilities,&quot; spokesman Dave Vieser said.</p>
<p>The county will circulate a request for proposals to the private sector, and select the one most favorable to Nassau, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The specific terms of how that will work, how much the county will realize and how much (potential operators) are going to put out as far as building the golf course will be determined when the RFPs are returned,&quot; Vieser said.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly given golf's &quot;tremendous&quot; popularity on Long Island and the long waits at available courses, private operators have shown considerable interest in running the new course, he said. RFPs should go out &quot;in the next several months,&quot; Vieser said.</p>
<p>Under the plan, the county would continue to own the roughly 50-acre site, but would extend a long-term lease to the operator. The operator, who would set fees, would share the proceeds with the county under a formula to be set forth in the RFP.</p>
<p>As for the lease, Vieser said, &quot;Theorizing that they would be putting a fairly substantial amount of their own capital investment into it, I would think we are looking at a 10, 15, or 20-year type of agreement.&quot;</p>
<p>Financing the Cedar Creek facility via the private sector is preferable to the bond route, Vieser said.</p>
<p>&quot;The real upside is that you've got the edge of the private sector, the profit motive of the private sector,&quot; he said, a method &quot;which really fuels the project's being done as quickly as possible, and being operated as efficiently as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>While Nassau has used bonds to finance its earlier golf courses, this is not the county's first foray into the public- private arena.</p>
<p>A private contractor now runs the Carltun on the Park restaurant in the County's Eisenhower Park.</p>
<p>The County currently owns and operates six golf courses in four of its parks. The biggest facility at Eisenhower Park, which has three, 18-hole courses. The county's North Woodmere, Cantiague Park and Christopher Morley courses are nine-hole facilties.</p>
<p>&quot;Long Island is a hot bed for golf, especially when you think we've got the (U.S.) Open coming in a couple of years to Bethpage,&quot; Vieser said. &quot;You really could build many golf courses, and still have waiting times on weekends.&quot;</p>
<p>In addition to Cedar Creek, the county is looking at other locations and hopes to have a location for a second course in the next several months, he said.</p>
<p>The second course would likely be handled in similar fashion, Vieser said.</p>
<p>((--Kathie O'Donnell, 212-859-1655))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
