<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609472" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Oil consumers urge &quot;realism&quot; in climate talks.</title>
<headline>Oil consumers urge &quot;realism&quot; in climate talks.</headline>
<byline>Richard Mably</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Energy ministers from the world's leading industrial powers appealed on Friday for realism in setting targets for the reduction of noxious emissions believed to cause global warming.</p>
<p>International Energy Agency (IEA) ministers also committed themselves to finding concrete strategies for cutting pollution in the run-up to a climate change summit in Japan this year.</p>
<p>The Paris-based IEA, part of the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), called on larger developing nations to play their part in the fight to restrain output of heat-trapping greenhouse gases.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to make a difficult trade-off between ambition and realism,&quot; IEA chairman and Dutch Economic Affairs Minister Hans Wijers told a news conference.</p>
<p>IEA countries must devise and implement energy policies that were &quot;realistic, achievable and cost-effective,&quot; said an IEA statement released after a half day of ministerial talks.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to think about the large developing countries,&quot; said Wijers. &quot;They have to be involved somewhere.&quot;</p>
<p>About 150 nations are trying to negotiate legally binding cuts in greenhouse gases in a deal to be signed in Kyoto, Japan, in December.</p>
<p>The initiative follows up the 1992 Rio de Janeiro Earth Summit that committed developed countries to reducing carbon dioxide emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
<p>Most of the IEA's 24 member countries will fail to meet their Rio targets.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe we must come out of Kyoto with goals that are realistic and achievable and in which the world can have some confidence,&quot; U.S. Energy Secretary Federico Pena said.</p>
<p>So far only European Union nations have shown their hand, proposing a 15 percent cut in emissions from 1990 levels by the year 2010.</p>
<p>The United States, easily the world's largest energy consumer, has committed itself to seeking binding targets but has not yet said what the new goals beyond 2000 should be.</p>
<p>Pena said he had &quot;some concerns&quot; about the EU proposal, for which he had not seen the analysis. The United States would make its own proposals in &quot;several weeks or months&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>The IEA gave cautious backing to a U.S. idea for emissions trading -- allowing countries to barter emissions credits or implement projects that reduce emissions in developing nations -- saying it should be given careful consideration.</p>
<p>The U.S. backs emissions trading as a way of getting the private sector involved but environmentalists have condemned the scheme as a cop-out.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be very complicated to make emissions trading measurable and open to account,&quot; IEA executive director Robert Priddle said. &quot;There is a long way to go yet to see whether it is a practical option.&quot;</p>
<p>Ministers renewed their call for maintenance of sufficient strategic oil reserves to protect against the possibility of a shortage on international markets.</p>
<p>&quot;Oil security remains a concern, particularly given the prospect of increasing import dependence...and the increasing concentration of remaining oil reserves in the Middle East,&quot; they said in a statement.</p>
<p>The IEA was set up in 1974 originally to defend consumers against huge oil price rises, but has since developed into a specialist thinktank under the auspices of the OECD.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="OECD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
