<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609468" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French leaders try to sway undecided voters.</title>
<headline>French leaders try to sway undecided voters.</headline>
<byline>Francois Raitberger</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>France's ruling conservatives and their leftist rivals on Friday made last-minute bids to sway large numbers of undecided voters ahead of Sunday's first round of a closely fought parliamentary election.</p>
<p>Both Prime Minister Alain Juppe and Socialist leader Lionel Jospin voiced concern that votes would be scattered among a record number of candidates, blurring first round results.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a large mass of undecided voters...this is why we speak up to the end,&quot; Juppe said in a radio interview a few hours before a midnight (2200 GMT) ban on further campaigning.</p>
<p>Jospin, ending his campaign in the heavily leftist southwest and in the Oise region north of Paris, urged a vote for change and warned the undecided against casting protest votes for small parties or staying at home.</p>
<p>&quot;Ballots must not be scattered...Above all people must not abstain. The French people must take their destiny into their own hands,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The last opinion polls allowed to be published last weekend saw the right's lead shrinking. The stock market has been jittery, with dealers citing rumours of secret polls showing the government's lead narrowing.</p>
<p>Juppe predicted a difficult first round for his coalition without a clear result.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a difficult first round. It will be difficult even to interpret the results since it is doubtful that a strong trend will emerge,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;They are scared of losing, we have hopes of winning,&quot; an upbeat Jospin told his last big campaign rally. He received backing from Britain's Labour Party whose Secretary General Tom Sawyer called him &quot;our good friend&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;We are looking forward to the formation of a Socialist Party government in France so that we can work together to build a better Europe for the benefit of all our citizens,&quot; Sawyer said in a message.</p>
<p>A record 6,389 candidates will vie for 577 National Assembly seats. The top two candidates in each single-member constituency, plus anyone who polls at least 12.5 percent of the number of registered voters, qualify for a June 1 runoff.</p>
<p>Juppe said in newspaper and radio interviews that a leftist victory would cripple France because of &quot;cohabitation&quot;, or power-sharing, with conservative President Jacques Chirac.</p>
<p>&quot;Experience shows that cohabitation does not put France in a strong position, it does not allow it to play its role to the full, chiefly on the European or international stage, and it puts a brake on or paralyses big economic decisions,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He reiterated charges that Jospin's European policy platform was vague and shifting.</p>
<p>&quot;This platform is worrying, it would be a jump into adventure,&quot; he told France-Info radio.</p>
<p>Jospin reaffirmed backing for a single European currency on four conditions. Apart from the inclusion of Italy and Spain, he wants a European &quot;economic government&quot; as a counterweight to the planned EU central bank, a pact of solidarity and growth against unemployment and steps to avoid over-valuing the euro.</p>
<p>To Chirac and Juppe's criticism of cohabitation, he responded with a warning against unchecked power and a call to voters to punish those who had held &quot;all power&quot; in their hands over the past two years.</p>
<p>&quot;Against monopolisation of power...we need balanced powers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Poll Commission watchdog accused four newspapers and a radio station of flouting a ban on publishing voter surveys in the last week prior to the vote, and asked the Justice Ministry to prosecute them.</p>
<p>Violating the ban, denounced by pollsters as obsolete, carries a fine of up to 500,000 francs ($88,000).</p>
<p>The Commission urged action against the daily newspaper Liberation for posting several polls on the Internet on Friday, on a page called &quot;Campaign Secrets&quot;, in a test of the reach of French laws into cyberspace.</p>
<p>The watchdog also targeted the newspapers Le Parisien, La Tribune, La Republique des Pyrenees and the France Culture radio station for mentioning &quot;secret&quot; polls in print or on the airwaves on Thursday and Friday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
