<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609465" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: EU pledges to finish treaty for its citizens.</title>
<headline>EU pledges to finish treaty for its citizens.</headline>
<byline>Fredrik Dahl</byline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union leaders, due to sign far-reaching treaty reforms at an Amsterdam summit in three weeks, said on Friday they wanted a &quot;People's Europe&quot;, creating jobs, free movement and a better environment.</p>
<p>Meeting informally at a seaside hotel in the Dutch resort of Noordwijk, leaders and foreign ministers from the 15 member states said they made progress towards forging a more modern bloc, fit to embrace up to a dozen ex-communist states and to lead its citizens into the next century.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a Europe enabling people to live a full life...a People's Europe,&quot; Irish Prime Minister John Bruton said.</p>
<p>EU leaders are due to complete the gruelling inter-governmental conference (IGC) in Amsterdam on June 16-17, effectively re-writing the bloc's &quot;constitution&quot;, paving the way for a more efficient and open Union.</p>
<p>Officials said the meeting had been surprisingly free of tension and that an agreement in Amsterdam was on the cards.</p>
<p>But the mood of optimism, in part triggered by the arrival of a more pro-European British government, risked being dashed by a pending squabble over the balance of power in an expanded Union.</p>
<p>While there is broad agreement that the bloc must make itself more accessible to its 370 million citizens through moves to promote job creation, workers' and consumers' rights and the environment, there were signs of a damaging rift over how to balance power between small and large states in the bloc.</p>
<p>Some leaders want to scale back ambitions for a bold new step towards political union, arguing that a new treaty should simply ensure that the Union works over the next few years -- by increasing majority voting and streamlining EU institutons.</p>
<p>France and Germany suggested boosting the voting power of the bloc's larger countries at the expense of the smaller ones and French President Jacques Chirac initially urged his partners to halve to 10 the number of European commissioners.</p>
<p>But this was dismissed by the likes of Luxembourg and Ireland, among the bloc's most vociferous defenders of small countries' rights. A compromise was suggested in which the Commission would be limited to 20 commissioners -- what it has now.</p>
<p>The summit, however, was dominated by Tony Blair, who breezed in to his debut among Europe's elder statesmen and caught the imagination of diplomats and media alike with his message of a positive and constructive British role in the bloc.</p>
<p>German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, portrayed as Blair's puppet master in British election campaign advert by the ousted Conservatives, was warm. &quot;There is no question at all that the British government has made clear that Britain is a part of Europe and wants to help in shaping it,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;There is without doubt a noticeable change towards the building of Europe in the new British approach,&quot; Chirac said, while others waxed lyrical about &quot;a new atmosphere.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair's message of changing Europe was well received and swiftly picked up by other leaders more used to lengthy and tortured negotiation on the niceties of institutional reform.</p>
<p>&quot;If Europe is to have support amongst the people of Europe, then it has to be a Europe that is clearly focused on the things that matter to them,&quot; the Labour leader said, giving prominence to jobs, competitivity, environmental protection and consumer rights.</p>
<p>EU diplomats said the leaders were determined to settle thorny internal issues like the size of a future Commission and a re-weighting of votes in the decision-making process in the run-up to Amsterdam so that the summit could focus on the grander ideals of bringing Europe to its citizens.</p>
<p>The new treaty is designed to ready the bloc for an ambitious eastward expansion, taking in Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic within 10 years, and adding others from Estonia to Cyprus later.</p>
<p>&quot;All delegations have said they want to finish in Amsterdam and that they are prepared to compromise. I'm optimistic that we can conclude the negotiations and take a political decision,&quot; Swedish Foreign Minister Hjelm-Wallen said.</p>
<p>&quot;An Amsterdam agreement is necessary and possible,&quot; French officials quoted Chirac as telling his EU partners. &quot;Everyone can judge for themselves the consequences of failure.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
