<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609418" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Florida court will back electric chair - governor.</title>
<headline>Florida court will back electric chair - governor.</headline>
<dateline>TALLAHASSEE, Fla 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gov. Lawton Chiles said Friday he was confident the state's 74-year-old electric chair would be back in use in September after a review ordered by the Florida Supreme Court.</p>
<p>The state's highest court Thursday suspended use of the chair until September, ordering a new hearing to determine whether the device is working properly or should be retired. In March it sent flames leaping from the head of a man being executed.</p>
<p>&quot;Anytime you have a controversy, you expect the (state Supreme Court) to play its role,&quot; Chiles said. &quot;They are playing their role. So far, the lower court has said it thinks the chair is functioning properly. All of our experts say that. I trust that is what the court will come out with.&quot;</p>
<p>The state's highest court postponed the execution of Leo Alexander Jones, convicted for the 1981 killing of a Jacksonville policeman, until at least mid-September.</p>
<p>The justices ordered that additional testimony be allowed to determine if the chair is working properly or if its use constitutes cruel and unusual punishment. A hearing was scheduled for Sept. 15.</p>
<p>During the execution of Pedro Medina March 25, flames shot from the mask covering his head, filling the execution chamber with acrid white smoke and the smell of burning flesh.</p>
<p>The decision handed down Thursday was also expected to postpone the execution of George Stano, who has confessed to killing 41 people and has been condemned to death for the murder of a hitchhiker in 1973 or 1974.</p>
<p>The high court heard testimony on the electric chair two weeks ago. During those arguments, attorneys for Jones said the trial judge in the case did not give them adequate time to respond to state experts who said the chair was in perfect working order.</p>
<p>State experts brought in to investigate the chair after Medina's execution said officials had not properly saturated a sponge used in the execution helmet. The sponge, they concluded, caught fire.</p>
<p>Under the high court's directive, the trial judge must rule by Aug. 8 on Jones' contention that using the chair, which has malfunctioned twice in the past seven years, is unconstitutionally cruel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALLAHASSEE, Fla"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
