<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609464" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Chirac sees accord limiting EU Commission members.</title>
<headline>Chirac sees accord limiting EU Commission members.</headline>
<byline>Myra MacDonald</byline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac, backing down on a call to cut the size of the European Commission, said on Friday he expected an agreement limiting its number to the current 20.</p>
<p>His comments opened the way to resolving what has been one of the thorniest issues facing the European Union, pitting big countries against the small who fear being locked out of the EU's executive.</p>
<p>He said France would like to reduce the number of Commmsioners to 10 or 12, reflecting the real practical needs of the executive.</p>
<p>But the idea had run into political problems from smaller member states unwilling to give up their right to appoint a commissioner to the executive.</p>
<p>Five big countries -- Britain, France, Germany, Italy and Spain -- currently appoint two commissioners and the smaller ones have one.</p>
<p>France and Germany have insisted on setting a ceiling on the number, arguing the Commission would become unmanageable once new countries join the European Union.</p>
<p>They also want the Commission's system of dividing up work between its members to be streamlined.</p>
<p>Under the new proposal, which is being closely scrutinised by the bloc's smaller states, the ceiling would be set at 20.</p>
<p>It was unclear whether big countries would be encouraged to give up one of their commissioners with the arrival of new members early in the next decade.</p>
<p>Some of them have said they are willing to halve their representation in exchange for more voting power in the decision-making Council of Ministers.</p>
<p>Also in question was whether a review would be written into the treaty to revisit the issue when the bloc eventually reached 20 countries and started bumping up against the ceiling.</p>
<p>Small countries such as Ireland and Luxembourg have said they will never give up their commissioner.</p>
<p>EU leaders were meeting in Noordwijk to try to speed up negotiations on EU reforms so they can be incorporated in a treaty to be signed at a full summit next month in Amsterdam.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
