<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609416" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: RCSB CEO sees improvements in auto lending.</title>
<headline>RCSB CEO sees improvements in auto lending.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Credit quality in RCSB Financial Inc's auto finance unit is &quot;a little better&quot; in the last two to three months, Leonard Simon, chairman and chief executive said in Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Credit quality has gotten better and delinquencies are down, two good trends,&quot; Simon said at an investors conference where he and Charter One Financial Inc chairman and chief executive Charles John Koch discussed the pending merger of the two thrifts.  </p>
<p>RCSB has been in the auto finance business since 1984 and its lending is focused on the East coast of the U.S. It has $1.1 billion of auto loans on its books.</p>
<p>Annualized net charge-offs in the auto finance in the past six months have been 117 basis points, compared to a typical 50-60 basis point charge-off rate, Simon and Koch said at the briefing for investors.</p>
<p>Referring to the charge-off rate, Koch said, &quot;what we've been seeing is a blip in the cycle.&quot; Both Koch and Simon noted that there are ample reserves.  </p>
<p>Simon aid RCSB is experienced in all phases of the economic cycle in auto lending. He said the company works closely with 900 auto dealers and focuses on &quot;prime&quot; borrowers rather than those who are less creditworthy. He said a key to the business is making sure the buyer is purchasing a vehicle on which he can afford to make the payments.</p>
<p>Simon said part of the problem has been the record personal bankruptcy rate in the U.S. &quot;Consumer attitudes toward debt are very different than they used to be,&quot; he said. &quot;They're more lackadaisical about it.&quot;  </p>
<p>While some observers have noted that bankruptcies increased after the laws where changed in favor of consumers, Simon said he is concerned that there have been some proposal recently to liberalize the rules even further in favor of consumers.</p>
<p>In its earnings report for the first fiscal quarter ended February 28, RCSB reported volumes in its auto business rose 20 percent from a year ago, reflecting in part a new lending center which opened in Baltimore and exceeded initial expectations.  </p>
<p>Simon said the merger of Charter and RCSB is expected to result in &quot;a few hundred&quot; layoffs but he said the issue has not yet been looked at in detail. He noted there will be no branch closings and all lines of businesses will continue. He also said the impact on jobs would not fall solely on RCSB and that there could be increased opportunities for some people.</p>
<p>RCSB has 1,632 employees and Charter One has 2,582.</p>
<p>RCSB is based in Rochester, N.Y. and Charter One is headquartered in Cleveland.</p>
<p>((--Cal Mankowski/New York Newsdesk/212-859-1732))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
