<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609481" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German court convicts Bosnian Serb of war crimes.</title>
<headline>German court convicts Bosnian Serb of war crimes.</headline>
<byline>Matthias Inverardi</byline>
<dateline>MUNICH, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 34-year-old Bosnian Serb was found guilty on Friday sentenced by a German court to five years in jail for taking part in a massacre of Moslems during the 1992-95 war in Bosnia.</p>
<p>Novislav Djajic was found guilty by a Bavarian state court of 14 counts of acting as accomplice to murder and attempted murder. It was the first war crimes trial in Germany since the Nuremberg tribunal on Nazi war crimes more than 50 years ago.</p>
<p>Djajic's lawyer said he would appeal against the verdict.</p>
<p>Judge Ermin Briessmann recalled how Djajic along with other Bosnian Serb troops had lined 15 Moslem men up on a bridge over the river Drina near Foce in eastern Bosnia in April 1992 and shot 14 of them in revenge after their fellow troops were killed by a mine.</p>
<p>Briessmann said there was no doubt Djajic had been present, but it could not be proved he had also pulled the trigger: &quot;He went along with what the others did -- but he was small fry&quot;.</p>
<p>Prosecutors had charged Djajic with genocide and complicity in genocide, but the court stopped short of convicting him of these crimes saying it could not prove he had intended to help kill the men as members of an ethnic group.</p>
<p>&quot;One can accuse Djajic of carrying out a reprisal attack in which he did not know (in advance) he was supposed to shoot (the Moslems),&quot; Briessmann told the court.</p>
<p>&quot;But it was not possible to prove that Djajic had acted on an intention to destroy an (ethnic) group. It was however doubts about this that had led to the charges against him of genocide and complicity in genocide,&quot; Briessmann said.</p>
<p>German federal prosecutors, who took on the case because of an overload at the United Nations war crimes tribunal in the Hague, had also accused Djajic of taking part in a June 1992 raid in which 14 Moslem men were killed. But the court dismissed the charge citing lack of evidence.</p>
<p>Djajic's German lawyer Wolfgang Dingfelder said he would appeal against the conviction, arguing the German court had no right to try his client because the 1992-95 Bosnian conflict was &quot;an internal civil war&quot; and not an international conflict.</p>
<p>Djajic, who entered Germany in 1993, was arrested in January 1996. Much of the prosecution's case was based on the testimony of the sole survivor of the bridge massacre who jumped into the river and escaped to safety slightly injured.</p>
<p>Although the alleged offences were not committed in Germany, Djajic was tried in Germany under a section of international law which says the perpetrators of genocide should not receive shelter anywhere and can be tried abroad.</p>
<p>Djajic's lawyer Dingfelder said the trial should not have started in the first place because the conflict was not international but a civil war.</p>
<p>&quot;I will appeal against the verdict. The court failed to recognise the limitations of its knowledge. We are not dealing with an international conflict but with an internal civil war and nothing else,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>The court however accepted prosecutors' argument that neighbouring Serbia, now part of Yugoslavia along with the smaller Montenegro, was involved in the Bosnian war and this placed it in the category of an international conflict.</p>
<p>German prosecutors are investigating 48 other people suspected of war crimes in former Yugoslavia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MUNICH, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
