<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609402" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: $200mln Conn. steel plant targeted for 1999.</title>
<headline>$200mln Conn. steel plant targeted for 1999.</headline>
<dateline>NEW HAVEN, Conn. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A $200-million start-up stainless steel plant is expected to open in late 1999, officials said on Friday.</p>
<p>However, steel industry analysts were startled by the announcement and questioned whether the Williams Specialty Steel Inc plant would actually get off the ground.</p>
<p>&quot;It is much too early to become concerned with the possible impact of this plant on the global stainless industry,&quot; said Michael Gambardella, analyst at J.P. Morgan Securities Inc.  </p>
<p>He cited the proposed plant's relatively small size, uncertain demand, and unlikely location.</p>
<p>High-cost Connecticut has been losing manufacturing jobs for years, and New Haven has tried to reinvent itself as a center of high-tech and biomedical enterprise.</p>
<p>Connecticut Gov. John Rowland (R) announced the project on Thursday, and other officials gave more details on Friday.</p>
<p>When completed, the plant will be one of the most highly automated steel factories in the world, said Roy Breward, deputy director of the Connecticut Development Authority.  </p>
<p>&quot;The manufacturing will rely on efficiency and low cost,&quot; Breward told Reuters. &quot;They have recognized that in Connecticut they can get both.&quot;</p>
<p>United Illuminating Co. will build an electrical substation at the 27-acre site and provide reduced power rates to the plant, services valued at about $5 million, said Anthony Uzzo, economic development specialist at United Illuminating.</p>
<p>Williams Specialty is the first venture into stainless steel manufacturing by Niagara Falls, N.Y. businessman James Harry Williams.  </p>
<p>Williams' background is in the waste management business, and he is president of Integrated Waste Services Inc .</p>
<p>Some 3,000 workers will be hired to construct the 250,000 square foot plant, beginning in September, Breward said.</p>
<p>At full capacity, there will be 350 permanent blue-collar jobs paying $40,000 or more annually.</p>
<p>The plant will produce up to 500,000 tons annually of stainless steel, a more durable, but expensive, alternative to traditional carbon steel.  </p>
<p>Some $70 million in loans will be provided by the state, the city of New Haven and United Illuminating, said Uzzo.</p>
<p>New Haven will issue $55 million in bonds to help finance the plant's construction.</p>
<p>That debt will be repaid in five years with real estate taxes from the plant. In return, the city gets jobs and an estimated $2 million more in annual tax revenue from the company.</p>
<p>Connecticut is providing $9.75 million in loans and another $1 million in grants for worker training.  </p>
<p>Despite perceptions that nuts and bolts industries are dying, Connecticut has not given up on its manufacturing base, Uzzo said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a fallacy about manufacturing in Connecticut,&quot; he said. &quot;We're seeing an evolution. There has been a net reduction in the labor force... but high-tech manufacturing jobs have been created in Connecticut.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;One reason the Williams company liked Connecticut is the (state's) emphasis on high-tech,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But analysts still expressed surprise.</p>
<p>&quot;Stainless steel scrap is not overly abundant (in Connecticut), guidelines regarding air quality are generally strict, and the logical consumers of stainless steel slabs are not located nearby,&quot; said Gambardella of J.P. Morgan.</p>
<p>&quot;Optimality of location notwithstanding, it is uncertain that demand for stainless slabs warrants new stainless slab capacity,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>--Matthew Lewis, Hartford newsroom (860) 727-0224</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I92110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW HAVEN, Conn."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
