<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609463" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Blair tells EU summit Britain has role in Europe.</title>
<headline>Blair tells EU summit Britain has role in Europe.</headline>
<byline>Paul Mylrea</byline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Prime Minister Tony Blair told a special EU summit called to get to know him that Britain under his rule would be a positive and constructive member of the bloc.</p>
<p>But he told EU leaders that his landslide election victory gave him a mandate to speak for the people of Europe and things had to change.</p>
<p>&quot;There are good things, let us celebrate them. There are bad things, let us change them,&quot; Blair told a packed final news conference.</p>
<p>Blair, swept to power on May 1 in an electoral landslide after a slick and controlled campaign, was clearly the star of the show at the summit in the Dutch seaside town.</p>
<p>His final conference was switched to a larger room after the scheduled venue proved too small when reporters from almost every European state tried to crush inside.</p>
<p>Fellow leaders were unanimous in their compliments for Britain's new leader.</p>
<p>German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, portrayed as Blair's puppet master in one campaign advert by the ousted Conservatives, was warm. &quot;There is no question at all that the British government has made clear that Britain is a part of Europe and wants to help in shaping it,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac described the reaction of the assembled leaders to Blair's first formal speech to a EU summit as one of respectful silence.</p>
<p>&quot;There is without doubt a noticeable change towards the building of Europe in the new British approach,&quot; Chirac said. And Swedish Prime Minister Goran Persson, a fellow social democrat, said: &quot;It is a new atmosphere.&quot;</p>
<p>Blair described the summit as constructive and gave his fellow leaders a stern warning that they risked losing touch with the voters who guaranteed their jobs.</p>
<p>&quot;I want people to realise that if Europe is to have support amongst the people of Europe, then it has to be a Europe that is clearly focused on the things that matter to them,&quot; said Blair.</p>
<p>He said job creation, competitiveness, environmental protection and consumer rights ought to be the priorities as the EU prepared to sign a treaty in three weeks at an Amsterdam summit designed to pave the way for the entry into the bloc of states from the east.</p>
<p>Blair added that Britain's decision to end the isolationism of former prime minister John Major and to sign the social chapter should not be seen as an excuse for bureaucratic legislation.</p>
<p>The ousted Conservatives had warned that the social chapter -- which sets common levels of protection for workers across Europe -- would cost jobs. Blair lectured other EU leaders on the need for flexible labour markets and said his warning against using it to create job- destroying legislation was well received.</p>
<p>He also said Britain would not budge on its refusal to give up control over its borders -- as continental European states have demanded as part of the treaty to be signed in Amsterdam.</p>
<p>&quot;We have made it absolutely clear that we believe Britain's right to determine its own defence, immigration policies and taxation policies is sacrosanct and absolute and that will remain the case,&quot; Blair said.</p>
<p>But he said he hoped this would not hold up a deal. &quot;I want to get agreement at Amsterdam but it has to be the right agreement for my country,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Diplomats from other states agree that Britain's insistence on keeping control over its borders is likely to be accommodated in the final treaty.</p>
<p>Britain's opposition to the EU taking over any international defence role by incorporating the Western European Union defence grouping has also effectively dashed any hopes of progress on this issue, they said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
