<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609433" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE- Oil union talks tough as industry shrinks.</title>
<headline>FEATURE- Oil union talks tough as industry shrinks.</headline>
<byline>Oliver Ludwig</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Unions representing U.S. oil refinery workers have had a bleak two decades, with job cuts shrinking their membership and leaving the rank and file anxious about which heads will roll next.</p>
<p>The bad news is likely to get worse as the industry goes through a period of major consolidation, which inevitably will hit the unionized workforce hard in the months and years ahead, union and industry sources said.</p>
<p>Union leadership is talking tough.</p>
<p>&quot;I may shut this industry down in 1999,&quot; warned the president of the Oil and Atomic Workers Union (OCAW), Robert Wages, in an interview with Reuters. He was referring to the next scheduled contract talks.</p>
<p>But while OCAW's top brass is beating war drums, leaders at the grassroots level are often talking more cautiously, reflecting concerns of the local plant workers who are most intimately in touch with what it means to be unemployed.</p>
<p>&quot;I think they're scared,&quot; said Mark Keppler a management professor at California State University at Fresno, referring to the way refinery workers appear to be taking the bad news often without much of a fight.</p>
<p>LABOR IN THE FRONTLINE OF COST-CUTTING</p>
<p>Membership of the Oil Chemical and Atomic Workers Union (OCAW), by far the biggest, has dropped by around 17 percent to about 100,000 since the early 1980's, bringing forth heated rhetoric from its leadership about the need to stem the losses.</p>
<p>However, the union's plight is a direct consequence of the poor state of the refining industry, which Wall Street analysts like to call &quot;mature&quot; -- a polite way of saying that the industry, with too much capacity globally, has seen profit margins dwindling and shareholders getting fed up.</p>
<p>In the last 15 years, over a third of U.S. refineries have shut, with some of the 185 which remain threatened with the same fate, especially after a wave of mergers in the past year. As a result labor remains a key target of cost-cutting.</p>
<p>&quot;Labor is one of the costs you have the most control over,&quot; said Keppler, an expert on industrial relations in the oil industry.</p>
<p>ON THE WRONG SIDE OF THE LAW</p>
<p>In an age when the industry mantra is 'bigger is better,' and it is hard to find a major oil refiner which is not looking for a merger partner, unions are cursing the law that allows acquiring companies to renegotiate labor agreements.</p>
<p>&quot;Federal law does not require that an existing labor contract be assumed by a new employer,&quot; said OCAW's Wages. &quot;Essentially what you've got is the oil industry holding a gun to our head. We've had no leverage,&quot; Wages said.</p>
<p>The law, stemming from the 1972 U.S. Supreme Court ruling Burns Security Services versus National Labor Relations Board (NLRB), has become the most lethal management weapon in extracting concessions from labor in the 1990s.</p>
<p>According to Keppler, the California State Fresno professor, refinery managers wield the Burns law as corporate raiders in the 1980s used bankruptcy rules.</p>
<p>Before Congress overturned the law in the late 1980s, declaring bankruptcy effectively allowed companies to kill off unionization when facing deadlock in cost-cutting negotiations.</p>
<p>But there are no signs that Burns is anywhere near being repealed.</p>
<p>TOSCO: UNION BUSTER OR PROFITABILITY SEEKER?</p>
<p>Just as Frank Lorenzo was the &quot;Gordon Gekko&quot; of the airline industry in the 1980s, forcing the now defunct Eastern Airlines into backruptcy to crush the union, Thomas O'Malley, chief executive of Connecticut-based refiner Tosco Corp, has taken on that mantle for the refinery industry in the 1990s.</p>
<p>Tosco's use of Burns, while rising rapidly to become the number-one U.S. independent refiner, has been phenomenally successful.</p>
<p>O'Malley, a former hot shot trader on Wall Street, has trampled roughshod over unions which formerly had held the likes of BP Oil, Exxon Corp and Unocal  UCL.L to ransom. Threats by Unocal workers to strike earlier this year petered out after O'Malley handed them an ultimatum.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there's a wholesale disrespect for the American worker. What you see from Tosco is an example of that disrespect. It's unprecedented in the oil industry. And it's not like we had to worry about any of this until Tom O'Malley and his guys showed up,&quot; said OCAW's Wages.</p>
<p>Tosco officials did not return calls on the matter.</p>
<p>But oil industry executives largely defend Tosco's actions, saying the company is only doing what is necessary to achieve what others have not -- namely profitability.</p>
<p>&quot;These companies that are selling their refineries to Tosco are doing it for a reason. I submit that reason is that they're not profitable,&quot; said James Carroll, a Houston-based attorney who represents oil companies with the firm  Littler Mendelson Fastiff Tichy &amp; Mathiason PC.</p>
<p>&quot;Now is Tosco going to go in there and operate under the same terms? No. Tosco is going to do what it needs to do to make those refineries profitable,&quot; Carroll said.</p>
<p>Investors have clearly responded to Tosco's plans, pushing the company's stock up six-fold since its buying spree started gaining momentum in 1993. The company's shares are now trading just shy of $32 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>OUT WITH THE OLD, IN WITH THE TEMPS</p>
<p>The basic Tosco approach, and one followed by others with the stomach to face down the unions, is to cut workers and hire back those it still needs as non-union contracted labor.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the entire industry has started focusing on cutting numbers and hiring temps,&quot; said OCAW President Wages.</p>
<p>More ominously, union sources said companies are seeking to fire workers with the greatest seniority, even those about to retire, as they are the ones that cost the most to employ.</p>
<p>&quot;Anytime you take seniority from a contract you don't have much left. It's like pulling the heart out of the body,&quot; said Alvin Freeman, president of the OCAW local representing workers at Crown Central Petroleum refinery in Pasadena, Texas, who were locked out last February.</p>
<p>Crown, a small refiner operating in the dense and highly competitive &quot;Refinery Row&quot; region around Houston, is battling to try to stem the flow of red ink and stay afloat. It is widely considered to be a takeover target.</p>
<p>The company locked out workers and began hiring temporary replacements, claiming union workers started destroying equipment at the refinery.</p>
<p>OCAW officials said the sabotage charges are nonsense and the lockout is Crown Central's way to bust the union by keeping temporary hires on until the union caves in on issues like seniority.</p>
<p>The FBI is investigating Crown's sabotage charges, and the future of 60 employeess at the refinery hangs in the balance.</p>
<p>BETWEEN A ROCK AND A HARD PLACE</p>
<p>OCAW's president is looking ahead to January 31, 1999 when most of the union's agreements with oil companies expire. He's in favor of at least holding the threat of a major walkout over the industry in an effort to regain leverage.</p>
<p>But though union representation in the industry has remained much stronger than in America as a whole -- as much as 70 percent of all domestic refinery workers are unionized compared with 15 percent of the total U.S. workforce -- local leaders don't sound so anxious to join the picketline.</p>
<p>&quot;How do I feel as a labor leader? Not good. I feel the country's labor laws are really stacked on one side,&quot; said Kurt Greder, president of the Teamsters Union local that represents workers at a Tosco refinery in New Jersey.</p>
<p>&quot;You could do the Italian, French or German thing and shut the whole country down. But do you need to be that outrageous to get your point across? I certainly hope not,&quot; Greder said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're not out to hurt O'Malley,&quot; he said. &quot;His company puts food on our table. He seems like a businessman who's going to do whatever it takes to achieve his plan. I've got to respect him for that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>With the absence of a strike threat and the law against them, that leaves unions rather dependent on the compassion or enlightenment of their (often new) owners.</p>
<p>Alvin Freeman, president of the locked out Crown local near Houston, reflecting this plea to the plant owners' human side, says: &quot;God does not own stock in the company.&quot;</p>
<p>-- New York Energy Desk, 1 212 859 1633</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
