<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609457" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Dry Kansas wheat areas receive beneficial rain.</title>
<headline>Dry Kansas wheat areas receive beneficial rain.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dry hard red winter wheat areas in western and northwest Kansas received 0.25 to an inch of rain overnight and another 0.50 inch was likely there Sunday or Monday, meteorologists said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was much needed but they need more,&quot; said Joel Burgio, agriculture meteorologist with Weather Services Corp.</p>
<p>He said rain fell over much of the western third of Kansas and into north central Kansas since late Thursday.</p>
<p>After warming into the 80s degrees Fahrenheit Saturday, western Kansas will turn cool Sunday and Monday.  </p>
<p>Showers may linger in eastern and southern hard red winter wheat areas early next week, after which the area should turn dry and warm, said Burgio.</p>
<p>Tim Bowden, Weather Express Inc meteorologist, said Goodland in northwest Kansas overnight received 0.72 inch rain, Garden City in southwest Kansas received 0.95 inch, and Russell in central Kansas had 0.42 inch.</p>
<p>Bowden said there was a 60 percent chance for more rain from Texas north to the Dakota Monday and Tuesday, with amounts in western Kansas likely from 0.25 to 0.75 inch. After that western Kansas should turn dry, with temperatures climbing to near 90.</p>
<p>((Chicago newsdesk 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
