<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609491" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Credit Lyonnais shares jump on recovery, sale hopes.</title>
<headline>Credit Lyonnais shares jump on recovery, sale hopes.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares of state-controlled Credit Lyonnais jumped more than five percent on Friday, boosted by robust first-quarter results and investor hopes that its privatisation could be accelerated.</p>
<p>The shares, which make up around 20 percent of the bank's capital but carry no voting rights, closed up 5.24 percent at 233.10 francs.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe said on Thursday the government might &quot;perhaps&quot; privatise the bank this year instead of late 1998 or early 1999 as planned.</p>
<p>On the same day, Credit Lyonnais issued a statement saying its first quarter profit, excluding exceptionals and tax, was significantly higher than the corresponding year-earlier period but gave no precise figures.</p>
<p>The bank has staged an unexpectedly strong recovery, helped by massive amounts of state aid, after nearly collapsing in the early 1990s under the weight of an ill-fated lending spree.</p>
<p>The newspaper Le Figaro said on Friday that U.S. investment groups and British lending institutions were interested in the privatisation and might be willing to contribute to a recapitalisation, avoiding the need for another state bailout.</p>
<p>Some media reports say the bank could need a further eight to 12 billion franc ($1.4-2.1 billion) injection to boost is solvency ratios.</p>
<p>One analyst suggested the government might seek first to assemble a group of &quot;pure financial&quot; investors who would take a 20 to 30 percent stake, and then banking and insurance partners.</p>
<p>&quot;They will want to get some pure financial partners around the table, and then look for insurers and banks to take stakes,&quot; he said. &quot;The public would hold the rest.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts noted, however, the bank had a heavy asset disposal agenda to win European Commission approval for state help.</p>
<p>They said it was more likely the bank would be ready for sale in early 1998. &quot;Many investors would prefer a full year of solid operating performance than half a year,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>&quot;But I guess it's an encouraging sign of the underlying trend at Credit Lyonnais that the government is talking about privatising it now,&quot; another said.</p>
<p>The bank's shares, formally called investment certificates, have rocketed more than 70 percent since the start of the year on the bank's financial recovery and expected sale.</p>
<p>One Paris analyst, who has a buy recommendation on the certificates, said they could reach 285 francs long term.</p>
<p>Analysts expect the bank to have profits of around 1.3 billion francs ($230 million) this year and 2.4 billion in 1998. It posted a profit of 202 million francs in 1996 after limping back into the black in 1995 with a profit of 13 million francs.</p>
<p>It lost 21 billion francs between 1992 and 1994. ($ = 5.696 French Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
