<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609480" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: EU reform talks mired in internal power struggle.</title>
<headline>EU reform talks mired in internal power struggle.</headline>
<byline>Ian Geoghegan</byline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union leaders met on Friday in a bid to forge a more modern Europe, a bloc fit and ready to embrace up to a dozen ex-communist states and to lead its citizens into the next century.</p>
<p>But attempts to inject pace into EU treaty reform negotiations just three weeks before these are due to be concluded at an Amsterdam summit risked being caught up in a power struggle between the bloc's larger and smaller nations.</p>
<p>Meeting informally at a seaside hotel in the Dutch resort of Noordwijk, leaders and foreign ministers from the 15 member states appeared to be split over who would wield power within the bloc as it expanded over the next 10 years.</p>
<p>No decisions were expected to be agreed at the half-day summit which the Dutch EU presidency had called so that leaders could sound each other out and gauge the chances of a successful agreement in Amsterdam on June 16-17.</p>
<p>The new treaty is designed to ready the bloc for an ambitious eastward expansion, taking in Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic within 10 years, and adding others from Estonia to Cyprus later.</p>
<p>Some leaders want to scale back ambitions for a bold new step towards political union, arguing that a new treaty should simply ensure that the Union works over the next few years -- by increasing majority voting and streamlining EU institutons.</p>
<p>While there is broad agreement that the bloc must make itself more accessible to its 370 million citizens through moves to promote job creation, workers' and consumers' rights and the environment, talks in Noordwijk showed signs of a damaging split over how a new-look executive Commission should be formed.</p>
<p>France and Germany on Friday floated plans to boost the voting power of the bloc's larger countries at the expense of the smaller ones.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac also urged his EU colleagues to halve to 10 the number of European commissioners, whose existence is seen by many small countries as the guarantor of their voice in an expanding Union.</p>
<p>Chirac's idea was dismissed by Ireland, among the bloc's most vociferous defenders of small countries' rights.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be a commissioner for every member state. That will always be so,&quot; Irish Prime Minister John Bruton said.</p>
<p>Britain's Prime Minister Tony Blair grabbed the early limelight as he took part in his first European summit.</p>
<p>His Labour party's election victory over the Eurosceptic Conservatives has been welcomed in Europe as crucial to the inter-governmental conference (IGC) negotiations, which have slowed due to British objections to deeper EU integration.</p>
<p>Blair's government has offered its EU partners a fresh, more constructive approach to Europe, lifting Conservative threats of a veto on various parts of the new treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;We will...make sure that Europe refocuses, that Europe is looking at the things that really matter, like jobs, competitiveness, the environment, consumer rights, the basic things that matter to the person in the street,&quot; Blair said.</p>
<p>His more pro-European comments -- on playing a constructive role -- were welcomed by other leaders in Noordwijk, but the British premier was quick to point out that he was in no mood to surrender national control of Britain's island borders.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Britain is adopting a more pragmatic and less ideological approach to Europe, which is good because that is the way Europe works as a whole,&quot; Ireland's Bruton said.</p>
<p>Swedish Foreign Minister Lena Hjelm-Wallen told reporters that Blair's arrival had improved the mood of the talks. &quot;It means the negotiation atmosphere has become easier,&quot; she said. &quot;There is now more belief in a negotiation result.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;All delegations have said they want to finish in Amsterdam and that they are prepared to compromise. I'm optimistic that we can conclude the negotiations and take a political decision,&quot; Hjelm-Wallen said.</p>
<p>&quot;An Amsterdam agreement is necessary and possible,&quot; French officials quoted Chirac as telling his EU partners. &quot;Everyone can judge for themselves the consequences of failure.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
