<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609455" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Decreasing U.S. Treasury auctions worries players.</title>
<headline>Decreasing U.S. Treasury auctions worries players.</headline>
<byline>Steven Scheer</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>It would seem strange to view continued reduction in the budget deficit as a negative, but leave it to the U.S. Treasury market to find a way.</p>
<p>Helped by an inflow of strong tax receipts, the federal deficit is slated to be roughly $75 billion this year -- well below the $300 billion-a-year deficits seen five years ago and the $100-$150 billion seen the past few years. Consequently, the Treasury doesn't have to sell as much debt to finance the deficit.  </p>
<p>While that appears to be a plus for the Treasury market, given that less supply along with good demand most certainly would drive up prices, traders do not necessarily agree it is 100 percent positive.</p>
<p>Players said activity, for example, has all but dried up in the bill sector, as the dramatic fall in the deficit has resulted in the size of the weekly three- and six-month bill auctions cut sharply to about $15 billion -- half of what they were a year ago.  </p>
<p>&quot;People are begging for more liquidity,&quot; said a trader who noted that fellow bill traders are bored. Coupon traders also noted that activity has faded and the biggest moves are largely confined to the aftermath of the release of economic data and comments from Fed officials.</p>
<p>In recent weeks, bills have traded separately from the rest of the market as demand for the small pool is very strong. Three-month bill rates, for example, were trading below 5 percent since Tuesday.  </p>
<p>&quot;You can't tell me that three-month bills are worth 4.99 percent when (federal) funds are 5.50 percent,&quot; said Vincent Verterano, head trader at Nomura Securities.</p>
<p>Plus, in the repo market, instead of being two to three basis points below funds, bill financing rates are very tight, at 10 to 15 basis points below funds, leading to &quot;squeezes&quot; on a daily basis.</p>
<p>As such, traders said that activity in bills is virtually non-existent, since nobody wants to buy them at levels deemed very expensive.  </p>
<p>The issue of declining auction sizes surfaced on Wednesday, after the Treasury cut the sizes of both the two- and five-year notes -- slated to be sold next week -- by $500 million each.</p>
<p>Smith Barney said this was the first time the Treasury reduced the size of an issue above the three-year note.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think they wanted to cut more in the bill sector because of the scarcity in three and six months,&quot; said Kevin Flanagan, money market economist at Dean Witter Reynolds Inc. &quot;They had to look at another vehicle and twos and fives were another vehicle at this stage.&quot;  </p>
<p>The cut in size to $12 billion on the two-year and $16.5 billion on the five-year was a fall of about $2 billion each over the past few months.</p>
<p>In the short-run, analysts said the smaller sizes should be a positive influence for the market.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it's a significant area of support, but it will give some support,&quot; said Flanagan, adding that the economic data is still the driving force for Treasuries. &quot;It's not going to serve as a depressant on fixed income prices.&quot;  </p>
<p>But over the long run, players see smaller sizes as problematic. Verterano said that if the recent trend in bills is a guide, trading volatility will fall dramatically, which will push Treasuries into extended narrow trading ranges and business will fall off.</p>
<p>&quot;A declining supply situation doesn't bring in volatility,&quot; he said. &quot;And you just won't get the excitement in the market.&quot;  </p>
<p>Making matters worse, traders said, is that the regular auctions have been cut further since the debut of inflation linked securities earlier in the year. And there is talk within the Treasury market that two of the six yearly 10-year note sales might be cut, and that the Treasury will go back to selling 30-year bonds two times a year from its current three.</p>
<p>Treasury officials would not comment further about their financing plans other than to say they have not announced any changes at this time.</p>
<p>Despite the market's frustration, participants said there really is no good answer how to solve their problem of declining volatility and liquidity. They said the Treasury is not at fault because its job is to manage the nation's debt.</p>
<p>Eventually, players said, more firms will merge or fold because there will not be enough business and not enough volatility for everyone around to make money.</p>
<p>(( -- N.A. Treasury Desk, 212-859-1867 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
