<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609482" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: FOCUS-Quick decision likely on BA-American deal.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Quick decision likely on BA-American deal.</headline>
<byline>Amelia Torres</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prospects that the European Union will decide soon on the proposed alliance between British Airways and American Airlines grew on Friday.</p>
<p>EU competition sources said the negotiations were gaining pace although the EU still had serious concerns.</p>
<p>Noting that the alliance had already waited a year for regulatory approval in Britain, the United States and the EU, one source said the Commission wanted to rule on it &quot;as soon as possible&quot;.</p>
<p>The deal between American Airlines, a unit of AMR, and BA ran into problems at the beginning of the year when European Competition Commissioner Karel Van Miert made it known that in his view it would restrict competition between Britain and the United States.</p>
<p>This view, expressed in a letter to the former British Trade and Industry Secretary Ian Lang in January, caused an uproar in the then British government which argued that it, not the EU, had jurisdiction over the aviation deal.</p>
<p>The battle of competences seems to be over, even more so with the new Labour government and its constructive approach towards Europe.</p>
<p>But the Commission's concerns remain, the sources said, particularly regarding access to London Heathrow airport, Europe's main hub for transatlantic business flights.</p>
<p>Britain's Office of Fair Trading proposed in a preliminary ruling in December clearing the deal that the two airlines should agree to give up 168 weekly landing and take-off slots at Heathrow.</p>
<p>U.S. and British approval also hinges on the successful conclusion of an open skies agreement between the two countries.</p>
<p>Van Miert stressed in the letter to Lang that the slots could only be surrendered, not sold, and also noted that all the airlines that had expressed their views on the case thought the number was not sufficient.</p>
<p>&quot;This remains a serious problem,&quot; one competition source said, adding there were still a few weeks of negotiations ahead.</p>
<p>The sources declined to say whether any meetings were already scheduled with representatives from the two airlines.</p>
<p>The EU was expected to reach a final decision before its August break, or even more quickly depending on the parties' willingness to make concessions.</p>
<p>There is no deadline for ruling on the agreement to coordinate passenger and freight services which falls under a string of EU treaty articles and a regulation on air transport deals which only talks of acting &quot;without undue delay&quot;.</p>
<p>Van Miert met Britain's new Trade and Industry Secretary Margaret Beckett earlier this week to inform her of the Commission's concerns and to ask for full cooperation in the examination of the case.</p>
<p>But while the Commission's probe seems to be near an end, the authorisation process was likely to take longer than expected in the U.S., because the Department of Justice, which must advise the Department of Transport on the case, has decided to organise a public hearing around mid-June, the sources said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
