<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609434" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. June cash crude turns weaker against July WTI.</title>
<headline>U.S. June cash crude turns weaker against July WTI.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. cash crudes were steady late Friday morning in quiet pre-holiday trading, while domestic grade differentials strengthened on reports of a pipeline shutdown in the U.S. Gulf.</p>
<p>U.S. markets will be closed Monday for observance of the Memorial Day holiday.</p>
<p>Cash dealers said June West Texas Intermediate/Cushing continued to lose ground against a steady July WTI, with last deals on the &quot;roll&quot; pegged at minus 40 cents.</p>
<p>July WTI/Cushing was unchanged at $21.85-95 a barrel.</p>
<p>Friday marks the final day for June crude business.</p>
<p>Louisiana Offshore Oil Port (LOOP) officials said the LOCAP pipeline link to the key Capline system remained shut Friday after experiencing a leak on Thursday. Some 800,000 barrels per day (bpd) of crude throughput was idled while repairs and an investigation into the cause of the incident were conducted.</p>
<p>LOOP sources said the line should be back in operation later Friday, but traders said it was possible the offshore link may be out for more than one day.</p>
<p>LOOP said force majeure declarations were not needed, as it would be able to compensate for lost production over the course of the month.</p>
<p>Grades were quiet in the June frame, with Light Louisiana Sweet/St. James talked at vague numbers, 10-30 cents under benchmark.</p>
<p>July LLS was sold at eight cents under July WTI, slightly firmer than Thursday deals.</p>
<p>Heavy Louisiana Sweet/Empire was marked at a 30-40 cents discount for June business, and at a negative 50 cents against July WTI.</p>
<p>West Texas Sour/Midland firmed to only a $1.20-30 discount for June, but volumes were thin and prices skewed.</p>
<p>Traders said firmers CFDs, a slight narrowing in the Brent-WTI spread and the LOOP troubles backed the firming trend for grades.</p>
<p>--Patrick Connole, NY Energy Desk, ((+1 212 859 1828))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
