<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609473" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: China says to clear Shell petchem project.</title>
<headline>China says to clear Shell petchem project.</headline>
<byline>Richard Mably</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>China on Friday pledged its long awaited approval for plans to build a major petrochemical plant in its Guandong province in co-operation with Anglo-Dutch oil giant Royal Dutch/Shell.</p>
<p>China's executive vice chairman of state planning, Ye Qing, told reporters in Paris he expected Chinese authorities soon to approve the plan.</p>
<p>&quot;I saw the managing director of Shell two days ago and I told him that I personally and the state commission will approve this project very soon,&quot; Ye told a news conference after meeting Western energy ministers during a break in oil consumer talks.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Shell in London declined to comment.</p>
<p>Ye said the plant, to be built at Huizhou in the booming Guandong region of southern China, was expected to produce 850,000 tonnes a year of ethylene.</p>
<p>This had been raised from previous plans for 450,000 tonnes of annual capacity. Ethylene is used for making plastic.</p>
<p>The project is a joint venture with the China National Offshore Oil Corporation. Shell holds a 50 percent stake.</p>
<p>It is, however, a scaled-down version of a plan originally valued at $6 billion that was to have included an oil refinery as well as a petrochemical plant. China unexpectedly dropped its support for the 160,000 barrel a day refinery early this year.</p>
<p>Ye did not say how much the ethylene plant alone was worth.</p>
<p>He made clear, however, that plans for a refinery at the same site remained on hold.</p>
<p>&quot;To ensure a better return for the project we have decided not to build a refinery at the same time but to import&quot; oil products to supply the petrochemical complex, he said.</p>
<p>China's apparent backing for the petrochemical plant will be seen as a partial victory for Shell after years of complex negotiations, but leaves doubts over China's unpredictable policy towards foreign oil refinery projects, analysts said.</p>
<p>On the drawing board currently are South Korea's Yukong Ltd 120,000 bpd refinery plan in Shenzhen and Saudi Aramco's 200,000-bpd refinery in Qingdao.</p>
<p>In January, China said Beijing would look at proposals for refineries from foreign companies on a case-by-case basis and did not rule out clearing new projects.</p>
<p>But in the same month, it told senior officials from Mobil Corp of the United States that it was not encouraging moves to build joint-venture refineries and would rather expand domestic refineries on its own.</p>
<p>Chinese sources said in February that overcapacity of the country's refinery sector was a worry for state planners, with plants running at only around 70 percent. Poor profit margins for refiners were another reason for freezing out foreign firms.</p>
<p>China's only joint venture refinery with foreign interest is the Dalian West Pacific Petrochemical Corp where Total of France holds a 20 percent stake.</p>
<p>A planned 120,000 bpd refining project in Shanghai with France's Elf fell through in 1995.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
