<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609471" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Paribas to sell Belgian unit to Bacob.</title>
<headline>Paribas to sell Belgian unit to Bacob.</headline>
<byline>Brian Love</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French financial holding company Paribas said on Friday it would sell Paribas Belgique to Bacob-Arco in a deal aimed at making Banque Bacob a major player in Belgian banking.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Paribas would not give financial details but said the deal would produce a capital gain for the French group, whose strategy is to focus on investment banking and specialised financial services.</p>
<p>It said it would sell 47 percent of its Belgian unit to Bacob-Arco, adding to the latter's existing holding. Bacob-Arco would offer to buy out minority holders, which could take its stake in Paribas Belgique to 70 percent.</p>
<p>Paribas would keep the remaining 30 percent but could later sell this to Bacob-Arco.</p>
<p>Paribas also announced a deal by its 64.9-percent-held unit Cobepa and the Almanik-Kredietbank group to split Belgian holding Gevaert which has stakes in major companies.</p>
<p>Cobepa currently holds 36 percent of Gevaert . Some 25 percent is held by Flemmish families acting in concert with Cobepa and the balance is publicly held.</p>
<p>After the operation, Gevaert will cease to exist and be split into two parts, a Cobepa spokesman said. One part will be merged into Cobepa. The other half will form a new company which will take the name of Gevaert. In that new Gevaert, Almanik-Kredietbank will be become majority shareholder.</p>
<p>The accord would give Cobepa, part of Paribas Principal Investments, &quot;more direct control over its interests and greater leverage in implementation of its investment strategy in the Benelux,&quot; Paribas said.</p>
<p>The operations were part of Paribas' corporate strategy of refocusing its activities &quot;onto its core business of international investment banking and specialised financial services,&quot; Paribas said.</p>
<p>&quot;They also illustrate Paribas' determination to redeploy its resources in Belgium with a view to creating a structure better suited to the Bank's strategic core specialities.&quot;</p>
<p>Paribas shares closed 0.53 percent higher at 399.10 francs while the CAC-40 leading share index finished up 0.78 percent.</p>
<p>Paribas Belgique, which employs 1,400 staff and 50 agencies in Belgium, is mainly active in commercial banking and made a profit of four billion Belgian francs in 1996, Paribas said.</p>
<p>Banque Bacob, the most important unit of Bacob-Arco, earned net income of 3.1 billion Belgian francs in 1996. It has 3,600 staff.</p>
<p>&quot;Banque Bacob has a strong position in the Belgian retail banking market, notably in the non-profit making organisation, repo and securitisation sectors,&quot; said the statement issued on behalf of both groups. The deal would &quot;allow a new leading Belgian bank entity to be created,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;This acquisition would let Groupe Arco extend and diversify its banking activities. It would allow Banque Bacob...to consolidate its leading position in Belgium's retail banking market and to extend its activities on the international financial markets,&quot; said the statement.</p>
<p>It said the deal was subject to regulatory approvals and the successful completion of current negotiations.</p>
<p>Paribas Belgique is 63.3 percent held by Groupe Paribas, via its 100 percent owned Paribas International unit and another 14.1 percent is held by Cobepa, a 64.9 percent-owned subsidiary of Compagnie Financiere de Paribas.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
