<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609404" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ill. school funding vote moved to next week.</title>
<headline>Ill. school funding vote moved to next week.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Illinois House Speaker Michael Madigan on Friday postponed a planned vote on school financing reform and bond issuance to next week at the request of Gov. Jim Edgar, a spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;We think there really is significant support for the bill and it would have passed today (Friday), but the speaker is supportive of the governor,&quot; spokesman Steve Brown said.</p>
<p>Edgar sought to delay the vote after negotiations with the Illinois Education Association and Illinois Federation of Teachers went late into the night Thursday, slowing preparation of the package, a spokesman for the Republican governor, Thomas Hardy, said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a 300-plus page bill, it is complex and House Minority Leader (Lee) Daniels was concerned that there was insufficient time to examine the proposal,&quot; Hardy said.</p>
<p>Edgar's plan, backed by the Democratic speaker, would use a 25 percent income tax hike to provide $600 million of new revenues for schools and $900 million of property tax relief.</p>
<p>The proposal would also take $100 million of projected state revenue growth to back issuance of $2 billion of school construction bonds for a matching program with local districts.</p>
<p>The proposal would raise per-pupil spending to a minimum of $4,225 in all Illinois districts, while not reducing aid to more affluent districts which spend much more than that on each student.</p>
<p>Edgar's plan has hit stiff opposition from his own party, however, and the Chicago Tribune reported Friday that he did not have enough House Republicans behind it for passage.</p>
<p>Daniels has questioned increasing the state income tax from three percent to 3.75 percent and recommends combining other taxes to raise base funding for school districts.</p>
<p>Republican Senate President James &quot;Pate&quot; Philip has proposed raising the income tax to 3.4 percent and had pronounced as &quot;dead&quot; the Edgar proposed income tax increase, the Tribune said.</p>
<p>Hardy said Friday that they had expected a close vote on the proposal, but still had expected representatives to approve the legislation.</p>
<p>Lawmakers had hoped to finish their session Friday, but must still reach a budget agreement for fiscal 1998 beginning July 1. Proponents of an electric deregulation plan also seek to introduce a package next week.</p>
<p>((--David Bailey, 312-408-8647))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
