<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609431" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Maria Piers, expert on child psychology, dies.</title>
<headline>Maria Piers, expert on child psychology, dies.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Maria Piers, a Vienna-born authority on the psychology of children who founded a training institute for pre-school teachers and authored several books on the subject, has died, her colleagues said on Friday.</p>
<p>Piers, 86, had suffered from heart problems and died in her Chicago home on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Educated in Austria as a kindergarten teacher and earning a doctorate in anthropology and psychology, she left Austria ahead of the Nazis with the help of friends, who included fame d psychoanalysts Anna Freud and Erik Erikson.</p>
<p>Erikson later lent his name to the Chicago institute that Piers founded in Chicago in the 1960s, where she taught prevailing theories on early childhood education to generations of teachers. She retired from the Erikson Institute in 1986.</p>
<p>Her ability to make complicated theories comprehensible to parents led to Piers becoming a frequent commentator on childhood issues that she continued as a television host and author. Among the books she wrote were &quot;Growing Up With Children&quot; (1966), &quot;The Gift of Play&quot; (1980), and &quot;Infanticide&quot; (1978), in which she examined the problems of poor, single parents that sometimes lead to child abuse.</p>
<p>Her marriage to psychoanalyst Gerhart Piers produced two children, and she had four grandchildren.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
