<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609410" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CBOT soy losses pressure soyoil, soymeal futures.</title>
<headline>CBOT soy losses pressure soyoil, soymeal futures.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CBOT soy product futures were lower at midsession Friday, under pressure mostly from heavy losses in CBOT soybeans, traders said.</p>
<p>CBOT July soybeans posted losses as large as 10-1/2 cents per bushel Friday morning, under pressure from technical weakness and a drop in the pace of the weekly U.S. soybean crush, traders said.</p>
<p>Supportive factors in soyoil trade included continued talk of heavy Chinese interest in South American vegetable oil markets, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;South American oil basis is firm again,&quot; a trader said. &quot;It's up on rumors that China is looking to buy more oil.&quot;</p>
<p>The drop in CBOT soymeal prices encouraged some buying from end-users in cash markets, dealers said. However, many livestock feeders are turning to less expensive feed alternatives such as grass, traders said.</p>
<p>In early soyoil trading Produce Grain sold 900 lots July. In soymeal trade, Prudential Securities sold 300 lots July and Refco and Rosenthal each sold 100 July, sources said.</p>
<p>At 1139 CDT, soyoil was down 0.06 to 0.13 cent per lb., and soymeal was down 0.50 to $3.10 per lb.</p>
<p>((Anna Driver 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
