<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609498" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss govt says EU transport talks delayed again.</title>
<headline>Swiss govt says EU transport talks delayed again.</headline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Swiss government said Friday talks with the European Union (EU) over an agreement on truck traffic on Swiss roads hit a snag, further delaying a planned general bilateral agreement between Switzerland and the EU.</p>
<p>Switzerland had recently said it hoped to reach a transport agreement by the summer. The talks are seen as a key issue in the bilateral agreement Swiss hope, once signed, will help pull their economy out of its current slump.</p>
<p>Swiss transport and communications minister Moritz Leuenberger told Swiss media Friday evening in the Swiss capital of Bern that a meeting of European tranport ministers originally planned for next Thursday in Brussels was cancelled.</p>
<p>The meeting plans broke down due to Swiss demands for higher tariffs on heavy truck traffic than the EU was willing to accept, Leuenberger told Swiss news agency SDA.</p>
<p>His comments followed a meeting between Swiss and European officials, including Niel Kinnock, spokesman of the Commission charged with transport negotiations, on Friday.</p>
<p>Switzerland wanted an agreement, &quot;but not at any price,&quot; Leuenberger said in a newscast on Swiss radio.</p>
<p>He said the cancellation of Thursday's planned meeting made it unlikely Switzerland would reach an agreement on the transport issue during the current EU presidency, which lasts until July, when the Netherlands will give up the chair to Luxembourg. Switzerland had hoped for an agreement by summer.</p>
<p>The next opportunity where the matter may be discussed will be in a meeting of EU foreign ministers June 2 and 3, he said.</p>
<p>Switzerland had proposed tariffs of a maximum 515 Swiss francs for &quot;dirty&quot; trucks, based on an average of 460 francs for all trucks within an agreed quota.</p>
<p>Swiss have spent several months trying to establish a workable agreement to permit 40-tonne trucks on their roads, where currently a maximum weight of 28 tonnes is permitted.</p>
<p>-- Zurich Editorial, +41 1 631 7340 (c) Reuters Limited 1997</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
