<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609400" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Bond market fears grow as US Treasury auctions shrink.</title>
<headline>Bond market fears grow as US Treasury auctions shrink.</headline>
<byline>Steven Scheer</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>It seems strange to view the narrowing budget deficit as a negative, but leave it to bond traders to find a way.</p>
<p>Thanks to a strong inflow of tax receipts, the federal deficit is expected to plunge to about $75 billion this year -- well below the $300 billion-a-year gaps seen five years ago and the $100 billion to $150 billion in the past few years.</p>
<p>Consequently, the U.S. Treasury does not have to borrow as much money and go further into debt to make ends meet.</p>
<p>Bond holders should cheer, because less supply along with good demand should drive up the price of the securities in their portfolios.</p>
<p>Bond traders, on the other hand, profit when prices are volatile because people buy and sell more.</p>
<p>The shrinking supply has shrunk the market, and as a result, profits for Wall Street firms are down. Eventually, traders said, firms will merge or fold because there will not be enough business.</p>
<p>&quot;People are begging for more liquidity,&quot; said a bill trader who noted that his colleagues are bored.</p>
<p>&quot;A declining supply situation doesn't bring in volatility,&quot; said Vincent Verterano, head trader at Nomura Securities. &quot;And you just won't get the excitement in the market.&quot;</p>
<p>Coupon traders, who deal in maturities of more than one year, sigh in agreement, pointing out that the biggest market moves are largely confined to the aftermath of economic news releases and comments from Federal Reserve officials.</p>
<p>It's not the Treasury's fault because its job is to manage the nation's debt, traders said.</p>
<p>But trading activity has all but dried up in bills, or short-term securities with maturities of up to one year, as the shrinking deficit has slashed the size of the government's weekly three- and six-month bill auctions to about $15 billion -- half of what they were a year ago.</p>
<p>And regular Treasury auctions have been cut further since the government introduced securities linked to inflation earlier in the year.</p>
<p>In recent weeks, bills have traded separately from the rest of the market as demand for the small pool is very strong. Three-month bill rates, for example, were trading below 5 percent since Tuesday. Bond prices and yields move in opposite directions.</p>
<p>&quot;You can't tell me that three-month bills are worth 4.99 percent when (federal) funds are 5.50 percent,&quot; said Vincent Verterano, head trader at Nomura Securities.</p>
<p>Since nobody wants to pay too much, the market for bills is virtually dead, traders said.</p>
<p>The market got its latest scare on Wednesday, when the Treasury slashed the sizes of both the two- and five-year notes -- slated to be sold next week -- by $500 million each.</p>
<p>This was the first time the Treasury cut the size of an issue with a term of more than three years, Smith Barney said.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think they wanted to cut more in the bill sector because of the scarcity in three and six months,&quot; said Kevin Flanagan, money market economist at Dean Witter Reynolds Inc. &quot;They had to look at another vehicle.&quot;</p>
<p>The cuts in the size of the auctions -- to $12 billion on the two-year note and $16.5 billion on the five-year note -- amounted to about $2 billion for each maturity over the past few months.</p>
<p>And there is talk within the bond market that two of the six annual 10-year Treasury note sales might be cut, and that the Treasury will go back to selling 30-year bonds two times a year from its current three.</p>
<p>Treasury officials declined to comment on the rumours.</p>
<p>In the short-run, analysts said smaller auctions should have a benign influence on the market.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think it's a significant area of support, but it will give some support,&quot; said Flanagan, adding that the economic data is still the driving force for Treasuries.</p>
<p>But over the long run, traders see a problem. If the recent trend in bills is a guide, Verterano said, price fluctuations will drop dramatically, pushing Treasuries into narrow trading ranges.</p>
<p>Chances to profit from big market moves will fall, and so will business.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
