<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609409" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Cargill says no comment on N. Korea/China rumors.</title>
<headline>Cargill says no comment on N. Korea/China rumors.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cargill Inc declined to comment on a rumor swirling through U.S. grain markets Friday that it sold at least one million tonnes of optional origin wheat to China or North Korea.</p>
<p>&quot;We never discuss transactions,&quot; a Cargill spokeswoman told Reuters.</p>
<p>Talk about the rumored deal circulated in export markets as well as on the Chicago Board of Trade trading floor but most U.S. exporters scoffed at the idea, saying North Korea had neither the cash nor the infrastructure to handle such a huge quantity of wheat.  </p>
<p>&quot;The question I have is, who started this rumor. You have to wonder who put this rumor out,&quot; a major U.S. exporter said.</p>
<p>One rumor had Cargill selling 1.0 million to 1.5 million tonnes of wheat to China which in turn would channel the grain to North Korea. Another rumor had Cargill selling the wheat directly to North Korea.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd say this was unlikely. In the past, these sales have been done by barter business and ... it is a large quantity even for the North Koreans to unload,&quot; the exporter said.</p>
<p>North Korea was struggling with a food shortage brought on by two straight years of crop-devastating floods.  </p>
<p>Cargill in April worked a barter deal with North Korea where 20,000 tonnes of U.S. wheat was swapped for zinc, traders have said.</p>
<p>Cargill has been a steady buyer of cash wheat and wheat futures for the last two or three weeks but not dramatically so, the first exporter said.</p>
<p>&quot;Personally, I don't think it is possible,&quot; a second U.S. exporter said. &quot;I do not think it is a direct sale to China. I don't know if the quantity is correct either.&quot;</p>
<p>Soft red winter wheat futures on the CBOT fell early Friday despite the rumor, with July down 2-1/4 cents a bushel at $3.74-1/2 near midday, pressured by favorable growing weather in the U.S. Great Plains, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone is talking about it,&quot; a third exporter said. &quot;If they sold, we would know shortly. We do not have a clue.&quot;</p>
<p>Cargill has permission from the U.S. government to sell North Korea up to 500,000 tonnes of wheat or rice.</p>
<p>South Korean traders said in April that Cargill was apparently interested in further grain barter deals in exchange for North Korean metals or ores, which include zinc, gold, iron ore and anthracite coal.</p>
<p>((Doris Frankel 312 408 8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
