<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609422" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NYS comptroller sues Giuliani over audit impasse.</title>
<headline>NYS comptroller sues Giuliani over audit impasse.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>New York State Comptroller said Friday he was suing New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani to force him to explain why 14 of his officials failed to comply with the state monitor's subpoenas.</p>
<p>H. Carl McCall, the state comptroller, said he issued 17 subpoenas last month after the Giuliani Administration evicted state auditors from city agencies.</p>
<p>&quot;None of this would be necessary if the Administration recognized the right of the citizens of New York to have information about how their government is working,&quot; he said, in prepared remarks.</p>
<p>Later, the comptroller, a Democrat who is considering challenging Gov. George Pataki in next year's election, stressed that his audits were not politically motivated.</p>
<p>&quot;I will continue to conduct professional, fair and independent audits of New York City. This office has performed these audits for more than 25 years--audits that have provided taxpayers with a clear understanding of how their government is working,&quot; McCall said.</p>
<p>The Republican mayor has viewed the controversy very differently, specifically accusing the state comptroller of trying to sway the mayoral election in November.</p>
<p>Giuliani has built much of his reputation on his Administration's dramatic success in cutting crime, and one of the areas McCall wants to audit is the Police Department's statistics. Some of the other audits also cover sensitive areas, like workfare, and how clean the parks are.</p>
<p>&quot;If he wants to go court, we're willing to demonstrate in court that he is acting in a way that is highly partisan. That is unfair and is intended to try to affect the mayoral election,&quot; the mayor told reporters in mid-April.</p>
<p>The Giuliani Administration has never objected to fiscal audits, only ones that examine the city's services and are unveiled by the mayor in the mayor's Management Report, a spokesman for the mayor has said.</p>
<p>((--Joan Gralla, 212-859-1654))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
