<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609440" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: USDA's Glickman backs summit on FSA future.</title>
<headline>USDA's Glickman backs summit on FSA future.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said Friday he would like a summit with lawmakers and budget officials to lay out a plan for the future of the Farm Service Agency and its tasks.</p>
<p>&quot;What I would hope we would do a better job of is analyzing the long-term strategic plan for this agency and farm program functions,&quot; Glickman told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;Otherwise, the debate becomes how many offices you're going to close in a particular state...Numbers are part of the issue but strategic planning also is part,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A Senate staff worker said several possible dates for a meeting have been raised but it was difficult to schedule a date convenient for everyone. So far, no date was set.</p>
<p>The summit should include congressional leaders and White House budget officials as well as USDA, Glickman said.</p>
<p>Glickman discussed the summit during a news conference called to announced the appointment of Keith Kelly, Arizona director of agriculture, to head FSA.</p>
<p>FSA &quot;is undergoing a lot of stress right now...I hear there are morale problems out there,&quot; Glickman said. Size of the agency has been cut but additional reductions are likely.</p>
<p>&quot;My message (to FSA workers) -- take a deep breath and relax,&quot; Kelly said. He said the shape of the agency should be determined by resources needed to carry out the farm program and FSA's other duties.</p>
<p>&quot;I emphasize we are rightsizing,&quot; Kelly said.</p>
<p>USDA has closed or moved 1,300 local offices since December 1994. An additional 500 may be closed.</p>
<p>Currnetly, FSA has 2,500 local offices and 17,000 workers.</p>
<p>&quot;It's being worked on,&quot; Glickman said when asked about potential legislation to &quot;federalize&quot; the workforce in county offices and to allow appointment of members to the locally elected committees that now oversee the county offices. Glickman did not respond to questions when the legislation would be filed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
