<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609499" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Axa rejects Australian claims on China venture.</title>
<headline>Axa rejects Australian claims on China venture.</headline>
<byline>Penny MacRae</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French insurance giant Axa-UAP on Friday rejected calls by Australia's Foreign Investment Review Board that it hand ownership of its planned Chinese life insurance venture to its Australian unit.</p>
<p>An Axa-UAP spokesman said the French company, not National Mutual Holdings Ltd, had been given the green light by Chinese authorities to sell life insurance in China.</p>
<p>&quot;Axa-UAP was chosen,&quot; the company's spokesman said. &quot;This does not hurt Australian interests.&quot;</p>
<p>National Mutual, which has applied separately for a licence to operate in China, has said it is not clear what role, &quot;if any,&quot; it will play in Axa-UAP's China business.</p>
<p>Beijing authorities told President Jacques Chirac when he was on a trade mission to China last week that they would licence Axa-UAP to sell life insurance, making it one of a handful of foreign firms with the coveted authorisation.</p>
<p>The Australian Foreign Investment Review Board (FIRB) said earlier this week it would probe the French insurer's move into China. But Axa-UAP said on Friday it had received no notice from the FIRB of any investigation.</p>
<p>An FIRB spokesman said that when Axa acquired 51 percent of National Mutual in 1995, the Australian government agreed to the deal on condition Axa made National Mutual its Asian arm.</p>
<p>The FIRB approved the investment provided Axa &quot;transferred its existing life insurance interests to National Mutual&quot; and pursued &quot;its Asia Pacific life insurance business strategy through that company,&quot; the FIRB spokesman said.</p>
<p>Axa-UAP has said it appeared &quot;probable&quot; it would work with National Mutual in China but it did not know under what terms.</p>
<p>The FIRB spokesman said if the conditions of Axa's investment in National Mutual had been breached, the government could move to enforce them.</p>
<p>In an earlier case, the Australian government ruled that Canadian company CanWest Global Communication Corp had to cut its stake in the Ten Group Ltd because it was inconsistent with the government's foreign investment policy.</p>
<p>Axa-UAP, which became the world's second largest insurer last November when it took over rival UAP, has been working to break into the Chinese market since the early 1990s, when China said it would allow foreign insurance firms into the country.</p>
<p>&quot;The Axa group is very well known in China. UAP was also known in China,&quot; the Axa-UAP spokesman said.</p>
<p>Insurance analysts have suggested Axa-UAP would keep ownership of the potentially lucrative Chinese business but would pay National Mutual's 69-percent unit, Hong Kong-based National Mutual Asia, to run it.</p>
<p>Axa-UAP has said procedural hurdles mean it will take at least a year before it can sell insurance policies in China.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
