<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609485" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German FDP vows to fight against tax rises.</title>
<headline>German FDP vows to fight against tax rises.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Gray</byline>
<dateline>WIESBADEN, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leader of Germany's liberal Free Democrats (FDP), Chancellor Helmut Kohl's coalition partners, vowed on Friday his party would not agree to raise taxes to fill a shortfall in government finances.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to achieve tax cuts, not approve tax rises,&quot; Wolfgang Gerhardt told a party congress.</p>
<p>The FDP has portrayed itself as the champion of lower taxes but come under pressure to agree to tax hikes to plug a projected gap of 18 billion marks in this year's budget and possible further shortfalls in the next few years.</p>
<p>&quot;The tax shortfalls on the horizon for 1998 to 2001 do not call for tax rises, rather for comprehensive tax reductions,&quot; Gerhardt told around 660 delegates at the congress in the central spa town of Wiesbaden.</p>
<p>Some members of Kohl's Christian Democrats have suggested a rise in petrol or value added tax as a solution to the government's budget problems as Bonn battles to meet the membership criteria for a single European currency.</p>
<p>Others have demanded that the &quot;solidarity surcharge&quot; on income tax -- levied to help pay for German unification -- be cut by only one percentage point instead of two as planned at the beginning of next year.</p>
<p>Gerhardt, who was reelected party leader at the congress with more than 84 percent of delegates' votes, made clear the FDP was committed to cutting the surcharge but did not state by how much.</p>
<p>&quot;It is and will remain the aim of the FDP to achieve stable budgets without tax rises and to reduce the solidarity surcharge step by step,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Gerhardt also called for a faster and more ambitious privatisation programme to stimulate private enterprise.</p>
<p>&quot;Privatisation is urgently required. It is progressing much too hesitantly and is even being fought against in some places and sectors,&quot; said Gerhardt, whose party provides Kohl with his 12-seat parliamentary majority.</p>
<p>&quot;There would be no Chancellor Kohl without us,&quot; he noted, promising that the FDP would continue to be a fair coalition partner but would defend its independence.</p>
<p>Hermann Otto Solms, the head of the FDP's parliamentary group in Bonn, said the pressure to balance the books should provide the impetus for a new privatisation drive.</p>
<p>&quot;It is all the more incomprehensible why the government today still has stakes in more than 400 companies,&quot; Solms wrote in the Wetzlarer Zeitung newspaper, saying the sale of these stakes would yield an income of billions of marks.</p>
<p>&quot;Privatisation doesn't just bring in more money for government coffers,&quot; Solms added. &quot;It also increases dynamism -- an important precondition for more productivity and innovation.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WIESBADEN, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
