<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609510" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Eramet minority holders suggest breakup - report.</title>
<headline>Eramet minority holders suggest breakup - report.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two minority shareholders of French nickel group Eramet, unhappy with the way the state is handling a mining assets row in New Caledonia, are proposing to break the company in two, French weekly Investir said in a story due for release on Saturday.</p>
<p>The proposal put forward by large U.S. pension fund TIAA-CREF and by Societe Generale Assets Management is aimed at protecting minority shareholders from what Investir calls &quot;the New-Caledonia risk.&quot;  </p>
<p>Industry sources told Reuters that what these shareholders are suggesting is for the state to gain control over the nickel business, leaving the rapid steel and manganese business in the hands of other shareholders.</p>
<p>These shareholders also want a majority of independent personalities to sit on Eramet's board, Investir said.</p>
<p>They also would like three independent experts to be brought in to assess the terms of a planned mining titles swap between Eramet and local Kanak company Societe Miniere de Sud Pacifique (SMSP) and the exchange to be approved by two-thirds of the group's shareholders.  </p>
<p>Eramet board met earlier in the day to review a number of requests made by shareholders and staff. The board will meet again on June 24 to set a date for the annual shareholders meeting and decide which draft proposals it would submit for shareholders' approval.</p>
<p>Eramet has been caught in a long-standing mining row with the state. State-holding Erap, which controls 55 percent of Eramet has theatened to take control of Eramet's board and to replace chairman Yves Rambaud, who opposes any plans to curb the group's expansion in New Caledonia.  </p>
<p>The state backs a plan by local Kanak company SMSP to build a nickel plant in the north of the French territory with Canadian group Falconbridge, using nickel from Eramet's Koniambo mine. In exchange Eramet would gain access to SMSP's Poum mine but Eramet and minority shareholders have said they must be compensated for the exchange.</p>
<p>The state supports the plan to appease Kanak separatists ahead of a 1998 referendum on independence.</p>
<p>-- Paris newsroom +331 4221 5432  </p>
<p>They also want minority shareholders to be compensated for the exchange and the state to lower its stake in Eramet to below 50 percent, it said.</p>
<p>Industry sources said the two shareholders together control some 3.6 percent of Eramet. The Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association-College Retirement Equities Fund (TIAA-CREF) holds 200,000 Eramet shares and New-York-based Societe Generale Assets Management 360,000 shares.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NEWCAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
