<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609560" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Astra helps lift Swedish shares to record high.</title>
<headline>Astra helps lift Swedish shares to record high.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A late rally in drugs major Astra helped lift Swedish shares higher on Friday.</p>
<p>The exchange's general index rose 1.28 percent to a record high of 2,868.75 in turnover of 5.26 billion crowns.</p>
<p>Astra surged nine crowns to 351.5 in a recovery. It was the last day it traded before a bonus issue of one share for three and a split two for one.</p>
<p>&quot;The effect of the split and the bonus issue will come after they have been done,&quot; one analyst said. &quot;Today's upturn could be because Astra has had lower market capitilisation than its European rivals since its first quarter results.&quot;</p>
<p>Insurer Skandia rocketed 34 crowns to 285, lifted by rumours about a possible deal with Nordbanken and a successful initial public offering of Hartford Life Inc, a rival to its U.S. unit linked division AFS, which Skandia might list.</p>
<p>Nordbanken rose 3.5 to 246.5.</p>
<p>Telecoms group Ericsson rose 1.5 crowns to a new record close of 279, but came off an intra-day high of 282.</p>
<p>&quot;Telecoms shares keep fairly quiet at the moment but a clear trend is that international investors are upgrading Nokia in comparison to Ericsson,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Real estate group Castellum ended at 56 crowns in its first day of trade.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
