<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609527" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Energy Council to tackle climate change.</title>
<headline>Energy Council to tackle climate change.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union energy ministers meet next Tuesday to discuss ways of dealing with climate change, including encouraging greater use of renewable energy sources.</p>
<p>Climate change will be one of two main point of the aganda, along with plans partially to liberalise the EU gas market.</p>
<p>The Energy Council will attempt to agree on conclusions identifying a number of energy-related areas where action needs to be taken to cut emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.</p>
<p>This initiative, which is also being discussed by EU environment ministers, is part of EU preparations for a third United Nations conference on climate change, due to be held in Kyoto, Japan, in December.</p>
<p>In preparation for the Kyoto conference, the European Commission published a communication on May 14 which warns that the EU will need to take &quot;major energy policy decisions&quot; if it is to get anywhere near achieving its target of bringing CO2 emissions back down to pre-1990 levels by the year 2010.</p>
<p>The communication asks the Council to look at cost-effective legislative and voluntary measures for cutting emissions, which might include a specific fuel mix strategy, targets for energy efficiency and efforts to promote renewables.</p>
<p>The issues involved are &quot;difficult and sensitive&quot;, a British diplomat recently told Reuters, adding that there were &quot;tensions&quot; between member states.</p>
<p>&quot;The different (national) points of view reflect the spectrum of opinions on the environment. There are people who think the environment comes absolutely first. Others think we need to take economic viability into account,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The ministers are expected to adopt a resolution approving the Commission's proposal to raise the share of renewables in the EU fuel mix from 5.6 to 12 percent by 2010, as set out in the Commission's November 1996 Green Paper on an EU strategy for promoting renewables.</p>
<p>The proposal came under attack on May 15 from the European Parliament, which said at least 15 of all primary fuel consumption should come from renewables by 2010 and urged the Commisison to come up with a specific plan of action for achieving this target.</p>
<p>The Commission has to some extent started moving in this direction, by proposing a new five-year programme to promote renewables.</p>
<p>Called ALTENER II, it should replace the first ALTENER programme which expires on December 31.</p>
<p>The Commission has proposed a budget of 30 million ecus for the first two years of the new programme, which ministers are expected to discuss next Tuesday.</p>
<p>A final decision is not expected until later this year.</p>
<p>The Commission has not proposed a budget for the full five year programme because the EU is due to revise its overall long-term spending plans (the so-called financial perspectives) in 1999.</p>
<p>The Council is also due to debate a series of other energy-related matters without adopting any formal conclusions.</p>
<p>Ministers will examine progress towards ratifying the pan-European Energy Charter Treaty, plans for a long-term accord with industry to improve energy efficiency, and Commission suggestions for greater member state cooperation on energy policy.</p>
<p>The Commission hopes to get all 15 EU countries to ratify the Energy Charter Treaty by June. It needs the formal support of 30 of its 50 contracting parties to come into force.</p>
<p>The United States has refused even to sign the treaty and members of the Russian parliament are stalling on ratification out of fear of handing too much power to the West, a spokesman for EU Energy Commissioner Christos Papoutsis recently told Reuters.</p>
<p>The Commissioner recently visited Moscow to tell members of the Duma ratifying the treaty was in Russia's interest because it provided a binding legal framework for energy cooperation with other countries.</p>
<p>The Commission's paper on energy cooperation between the member states and Brussels has also met with some resistance.</p>
<p>A British diplomat said London thought the paper was riddled with inconsistencies, would duplicate governments' efforts to coordinate energy policies through the International Energy Agency and would cost money.</p>
<p>But Papoutsis's spokesman said energy ministers had asked the Commission for the paper and suggested EU influence in the IEA would be more effective if the member states presented a common front.</p>
<p>The Council is due to round up its work by adopting conclusions on EU energy cooperation with Asia and discussing developments in cooperation with the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>The Council's conclusions on Asia are expected to focus on:</p>
<p>- improving energy efficiency and energy savings in Asia,</p>
<p>- the sensitive issue of environmental protection,</p>
<p>- the participation of European industry in projects to improve the energy industry in 18 Asian countries, including China, India and the Association of South East Asian States (ASEAN).</p>
<p>Discussing Asia at this time is designed to underline the EU's interest in developing relations in the energy field, ahead of two important ASEAN meetings on energy cooperation in June and July, which the Commission is expected to attend.</p>
<p>The Energy Council will end with a meeting with energy representatives from the countries of East and Central Europe who are seeking EU membership.</p>
<p>The meeting is expected to concentrate on trans-Euroepan energy networks and climate change. REUITER</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G156">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
