<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609501" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Chirac says Europe's &quot;social model&quot; winning favour.</title>
<headline>Chirac says Europe's &quot;social model&quot; winning favour.</headline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac said on Friday he saw a &quot;revolution&quot; in Europe in its growing acceptance of a need for a social model to protect its citizens from unemployment and poverty.</p>
<p>Chirac, speaking two days ahead of a parliamentary election in France, also said Europe needed to look harder at ways of reviving weak economic growth, which he blamed for joblessness and exclusion of many from mainstream society.</p>
<p>France has long fought for Europe to maintain much of its system of welfare and worker protection, rather than adopting the free market policies of the United States which some believe would help bring down its record unemployment.</p>
<p>Chirac said the idea of a &quot;social model&quot; was gathering support, and noted plans to make legally binding a commitment to fighting unemployment through a revision to European Union treaties.</p>
<p>Britain's new Labour government has also agreed to sign up to the European Union's social chapter, which sets minimum standards for workers, reversing years of resistance by the outgoing conservatives.</p>
<p>&quot;If we succeed in getting the idea of a European social model taken on board, it is a revolution,&quot; he told a news conference during a summit of EU leaders in the Dutch seaside town of Noordwijk.</p>
<p>Chirac said he had stressed the need to tackle weak growth during the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe is the only region in the world where growth is weak,&quot; he said. &quot;We have to go a bit further to look for solutions to this problem of inadequate growth and its social consequences.&quot;</p>
<p>He said only one European leader had called for greater labour force flexibility to reduce joblessness -- British Prime Minister Tony Blair -- and was greeted with silence.</p>
<p>And while Europe needed to reduce the social charges which weighed too heavily on the cost of labour, it must avoid the kind of full liberalisation which would fragment society.</p>
<p>France's centre-right government, campaigning for re-election in the two-round vote on May 25 and June 1, has been fighting to fend off charges by the opposition Socialist party that its policies would exacerbate unemployment and poverty through new austerity measures.</p>
<p>Chirac's comments appeared meant to underline the commitment of the mainstream right-wing in France to work actively to boost growth and tackle unemployment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
