<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609505" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: China sees end to oil price controls in two years.</title>
<headline>China sees end to oil price controls in two years.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>China on Friday said it expected to deregulate domestic oil prices to match international market prices within two years, helping attract foreign investment to one of the world's fastest growing economies.</p>
<p>&quot;We have planned that in about two years time we will conform will international prices,&quot; executive vice-chairman of state planning Ye Qing told reporters after a meeting of International Energy Agency (IEA) ministers in Paris.</p>
<p>&quot;Now we are adjusting our prices and closing the gap with international market prices while at the same time taking into consideration growth of the economy,&quot; said Ye. &quot;This ought to create a favourable climate for international investors.&quot;</p>
<p>Ye was in Paris as a guest of the IEA.</p>
<p>China controls domestic oil prices but has gradually relaxed restrictions in recent years.</p>
<p>The China Economic Times earlier this month quoted the ministry of internal trade saying controls might be lifted as early as 1998.</p>
<p>Domestic Chinese crude prices were last raised in December to just over $100 a tonne compared with about $140 a tonne on international markets.</p>
<p>The IEA expects demand for energy in China to grow by 5-6 percent a year with electricity demand expected to more than double by 2010. The country is expected to account for 20 percent of the increase in world energy demand to 2010.</p>
<p>China, which became a net oil importer in 1993, was encouraging domestic oil exploration and diversification of energy supplies in order not to rely too heavily on imported crude, the Chinese minister said.</p>
<p>Crude oil output from China's two main onshore fields has stagnated in recent years.</p>
<p>China depends on coal for 75 percent of its energy needs with oil taking an 18 percent share.</p>
<p>Oil imports are expected to hit 30 million tonnes this year from 22.6 million in 1996, the Chinese National Petroleum Corp has estimated.</p>
<p>Nuclear power, providing less than one percent of energy Chinese needs, would remain a minor source, Ye told the IEA.</p>
<p>Ye said China was treating environmental protection as a key part of its industrial development.</p>
<p>&quot;Environmental development and construction must be coordinated with environmental protection,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>China, the world's biggest consumer of coal, was &quot;determined to speed up clean coal technology.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
