<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609521" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: EMU to create &quot;equity culture&quot; - Smurfit director.</title>
<headline>EMU to create &quot;equity culture&quot; - Smurfit director.</headline>
<byline>Carmel Linnane</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European economic and monetary union (EMU) will shift investor emphasis to equity markets as they scramble to boost portfolio returns by moving away from lower-yielding bonds, a senior official at Ireland's largest industrial company said on Friday.</p>
<p>Ray Curran, financial director at Jefferson Smurfit Group Plc, the biggest paper packaging manufacturer in Europe, said there was already a move into equity markets out of bonds by European institutions trying to generate higher returns on portfolios, creating a new &quot;equity culture&quot;.</p>
<p>Pressure on governments to control budget deficits to comply with EMU membership criteria was likely to lead to increased privatisations across Europe, he added.</p>
<p>Curran anticipated privatisations totalling an estimated $300 billion in the next few years, mainly in utilities, telecommunications and transport areas.</p>
<p>&quot;This development will increase the range and scale of equities traded and will contribute to the development of an increasingly competitive equity market in which we must trade,&quot; Curran told the Irish Association of Corporate Treasurers.</p>
<p>Curran said that as a single currency eliminated currency risks across borders it would encourage a broadening of portfolio investments across Europe.</p>
<p>In the early stages European funds were likely to buy larger European stocks but eventually they would become more discerning and focus more on sectoral, rather than national, investments, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;This will intensify the competition for capital as companies seek to 'stand out from the crowd' in their respective sectors,&quot; Curran said. &quot;We face quite a challenge in convincing potential investors that we are worthy of their time and money.&quot;</p>
<p>Curran said the key to meeting this challenge and successfully competing for equity capital was to command a premium share price.</p>
<p>He said a commitment to shareholder value principles and the clear enunciation of this to the investment community was key to successfully raising equity capital.</p>
<p>&quot;All options should be explored. The time to do it is now,&quot; he said. &quot;Act at your leisure, repent forever,&quot; he warned.</p>
<p>Curran said the best option for ensuring successful debt financing was to obtain a credit rating. He also recommended targeting the U.S. debt market.</p>
<p>&quot;Obtaining a credit rating should provide the best assurance of successfully securing efficient debt in Europe in 2000 and beyond. In the meantime the U.S. debt market could be targeted and indeed should not be discounted even when the European market is established,&quot; Curran said,</p>
<p>-- Dublin newsroom + 353 1 676 9775</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
