<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609583" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: British betting points to narrow French right win.</title>
<headline>British betting points to narrow French right win.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Betting at British bookmaker City Index points to a victory for France's ruling centre-right coalition in a May 25-June 1 parliamentary election but the opposition left is gaining ground with punters.</p>
<p>City Index said that after release of opinion polls outside France overnight most of the betting on Friday had been in favour of the opposition Socialists and Communists, prompting the bookmakers to trim the forecast centre-right margin around which their bets were based to 38 seats.</p>
<p>City Index quoted the centre-right result in the National Assembly on Friday at a bid/offer spread of 304-310 seats. The prices mean the punter can &quot;buy&quot; the centre-right, betting they will win at least 311 seats, or &quot;sell&quot; them, betting they will get no more than than 303.</p>
<p>The centre-right spread quoted on Thursday had been 313-319 seats.</p>
<p>&quot;It reflects business seen today: buyers of Socialists, sellers of the right and buyers of the Communists,&quot; a member of staff at City Index said on Friday.</p>
<p>The Socialists were quoted on Friday at 239-245 seats and the Communists at 26-28, an increase of nine for the Socialists and one for the Communists since Thursday.</p>
<p>The centre-right coalition, which holds 464 seats in the outgoing 577-seat National Assembly, needs 289 seats for an outright majority.</p>
<p>Although French law prohibits the publication of poll results in the last week before the first round and between the two rounds, two polls have been released outside France and polls have been conducted for private clients in France.</p>
<p>One regional newspaper, La Republique des Pyrenees, flouted the ban and published a poll on Friday saying it was hypocritical to withhold the results from the population when journalists, politicians, traders or those with access to the Internet could see the results.</p>
<p>City Index said betting had been steady since the snap election was called by President Jacques Chirac on April 21, mainly from French clients based in London and Paris.</p>
<p>Opinion polls released prior to the blackout suggested the centre-right would be returned with a reduced majority but the Socialists and Communists were neck-and-neck with them in the popular vote.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
