<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609552" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy San Paolo final offer price seen 10,434 lire.</title>
<headline>Italy San Paolo final offer price seen 10,434 lire.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The final price for a public offer of shares in Italian bank San Paolo di Torino is estimated at 10,434 or 10,435 lire per share, according to analysts' calculations.</p>
<p>The San Paolo offer for a total of 26.96 percent of its stock closed on Friday. The bank has said the final offer price would be the lower price of two alternatives: a maximum price of 10,850 announced last week or the official price on the closing day of the offer, with a discount of 2.5 percent.</p>
<p>The official price is 10.702 lire and with the discount becomes 10,434.45 lire, analysts said.  </p>
<p>Analysts said whether the final price became 10.434 or 10.435 depended on whether San Paolo rounded it up or down.</p>
<p>San Paolo itself declined to make any comment on the price calculation and said it would publish the final price on Saturday.</p>
<p>The bank is seeking to privatise from the foundation which controls it. The foundation has recently placed 20 percent of its San Paolo bank stock with core of stable shareholders as well placing 35 percent on the market in 1992.</p>
<p>--Milan bureau +392 66129507</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
