<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609545" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU Commission gene-policy clear-up effort stutters.</title>
<headline>EU Commission gene-policy clear-up effort stutters.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission has gone back to the drawing board in its efforts to clarify EU rules and policy on gene-modified foods such as maize and soybeans, one official told reporters on Friday.</p>
<p>A meeting of senior officials on Thursday rejected a draft text intended to bring coherence to Commission policy across a range of areas including market release approval for genetically modified organisms (GMOs) and rules for GMO-derived human food, animal feed and plant seeds.</p>
<p>&quot;The draft did not attract much sympathy... it's been withdrawn,&quot; the official said, adding that a second paper would be prepared in time for discussion by Commissioners at their regular weekly meeting on June 11.</p>
<p>Drafting takes place as the Commission ponders a range of new EU laws on GMOs and their use through the human and animal food chain from release into the environment, sale, planting, processing and through to retail sale and consumption.</p>
<p>A draft proposal governing GMO use in animal feed, drawn up by Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler's officials but in limbo until an overall policy is defined, put its finger on the central issue in the EU biotechnology debate when it suggested labelling rules for all feeds containing gene-altered varieties.</p>
<p>The proposal said mandatory labels implied a requirement to segregate GMO varieties from other strains in shipments, an idea certain to spark vigorous opposition from the United States and from seed developers such as the U.S. chemical company Monsanto.</p>
<p>Commission hesitancy on its overall policy stems from a need to balance U.S. trade demands against the sensitivities of European consumers and the European Parliament, many of whom want mandatory labelling of all GMOs, regardless of risk arguments, in order to decide for themselves whether to avoid the new technologies.</p>
<p>It is not a problem suggesting a rapid solution, the official said, adding: &quot;I would not put too much emphasis on the (June) timetable.&quot; -- Brussels Newsroom 32 2 287 6800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
