<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609587" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bavarian Re says dropped from U.S. Holocaust suit.</title>
<headline>Bavarian Re says dropped from U.S. Holocaust suit.</headline>
<text>
<p>MUNICH, Germany, May 23 - German reinsurance group Bayerische Rueckversicherung AG said on Friday it had been dropped as a target of a U.S. lawsuit alleging that seven insurers cheated Holocaust victims of billions of dollars.</p>
<p>In a brief statement, the company, known as Bavarian Re, said lawyers who launched the suit in late March had delivered a &quot;notice to dismiss&quot; to a New York court relating to the charges against it, setting it free from the case.</p>
<p>The class action suit, which lawyers say could be brought by up to 10,000 people, charges insurers with concealing or converting the cash value and proceeds of insurance policies sold before 1946 to mainly Jewish victims of Nazi persecution.</p>
<p>The news sparked some alarm among insurers, mindful of their valuable reputations, and caused German market leader Allianz AG Holding to set up Holocaust hotlines in Germany and the U.S. to field calls from potential claimants.</p>
<p>Bavarian Re said it had been surprised to have been named in the case, since as a reinsurance company it had never issued any life insurance policies, and thus was unlikely to be liable for any claims.</p>
<p>&quot;This means that Bavarian Re was released from the case by the plaintiffs and is no longer part of the accused group,&quot; the company said.</p>
<p>&quot;Irrespective of Bavarian Re's position in the case, the plaintiffs' request has our respect,&quot; the statement added.</p>
<p>The insurers named in the suit include Allianz, its Italian unit RAS and Austrian unit Wiener Allianz, along with Assicurazioni Generali S.p.A. of Trieste, Italy, Der Anker Allgemeine Versicherungs AG of Vienna, and A.G.F. Assurances Generales de France (AGF) of Paris.</p>
<p>So far, the affected parties have not speculated on what kind of damages they may face should the court decide against them, but most companies mentioned say they expect the extent of outstanding claims to be limited.</p>
<p>Allianz says it is will process any claims with as little bureaucracy as possible but also says it has already settled the bulk of claims related to the Nazi era. The response to its hotline has been limited.</p>
<p>--Catherine O'Mahony, Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
