<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609526" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: EU's Bonino demands access to refugees in ex-Zaire.</title>
<headline>EU's Bonino demands access to refugees in ex-Zaire.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European humanitarian aid commissioner Emma Bonino demanded on Friday that the new leader of the former Zaire, Laurent Kabila, allow relief workers into the country to determine the fate of 280,000 missing refugees.</p>
<p>Bonino, the top humanitarian aid official for the 15-nation European Union, said that helping the stranded refugees must be a top priority for the self-proclaimed president of the central African nation.</p>
<p>&quot;Today we are missing 280,000 people. We don't know where they are or whether they are dead or alive because humanitarian organisations and human rights monitors have not been permitted to go there,&quot; Bonino told reporters during a visit to Madrid.</p>
<p>The mostly Rwandan refugees are believed to be stranded in the east of Zaire, which Kabila has renamed the Democratic Republic of Congo.</p>
<p>&quot;He (Kabila) has to grant access as foreseen in the Geneva convention,&quot; Bonino said. &quot;He is now head of state and, according to international convention, he is responsibile for what is happening in his own country.&quot;</p>
<p>Aid agencies have accused Kabila's forces of systematically blocking access to the refugees and hindering their repatriation to Rwanda.</p>
<p>The EU emphasised its concern on Thursday over the plight of refugees and urged Kinshasa to ensure that international humanitarian organisations could operate in the country.</p>
<p>&quot;The Union attaches great importance to Mr Kabila's earlier commitments in this regard and urges him to ensure that there is full respect for international humanitarian law,&quot; the Dutch EU presidency said in a statement.</p>
<p>Bonino had previously accused Kabila's rebels of deliberately trying to wipe out Hutu refugees believed to have been responsible for the 1994 genocide in Rwanda. She also said Kabila was trying to undermine the efficiency and credibilty of aid agencies.</p>
<p>The international medical charity Doctors without Borders accused the new administration on Tuesday of planning to exterminate all Rwandan Hutu refugees in the country.</p>
<p>Kabila's rebel alliance has denied the allegations and accuses the United Nations and other agencies of deliberately failing to repatriate the refugees.</p>
<p>Bonino estimated 10 percent of EU humanitarian aid destined for war zones such as the former Zaire is lost on bribing militants. The only way to prevent such losses, she said, was to provide military protection for aid workers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
