<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609591" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: INTERVIEW-Air France aims to sign up alliances.</title>
<headline>INTERVIEW-Air France aims to sign up alliances.</headline>
<byline>Pierre Tran</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Air France said on Friday it hopes to agree at least one alliance with an Asian airline and one or two accords in Europe by the end of this year as part of plans to build a global network.</p>
<p>&quot;We seek to increase the routes available to the customer and provide a seamless service but without the proportionate rise in costs,&quot; executive vice president for international affairs, Jean-Pierre Hoss told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said talks were going on but declined to identify the airlines.</p>
<p>As passengers travel increasingly to all points of the globe, airlines need to add routes constantly. &quot;Each customer wants a tailor-made product but the airline has to provide it at ready-made cost,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A group of major airline including Lufthansa, United Airlines, Air Canada, SAS and Thai International announced on May 14 the Star Alliance brand name to formalise existing partnerships.</p>
<p>Air France's existing alliances include Alitalia and Japan Airlines, Royal Air Maroc, and has limited agreements with Czech airline CSA, Eurowings of Germany, Malev of Hungary, and Aeromexico.</p>
<p>The state-owned French company is late in building alliances as it has had to focus on its financial recovery before it could negotiate with potential partners.</p>
<p>Full alliances usually include a code-share pact which involves integrating flight schedules allowing passengers to book a through ticket using an initial airline and transferring to the partner company.</p>
<p>About 40 percent of Air France's passengers using its Paris Charles De Gaulle hub take connecting flights and the airline wants to add to its network to capture more traffic.</p>
<p>The code-share cuts both ways as both alliance partners add a whole route network to their own but without the direct operating costs. They gain economies of scale, rationalise plane fleets, ground crews and sell tickets which they might otherwise not have been able to offer.</p>
<p>Because alliances are essentially low-cost additions, the extra revenues translate into extra profit margin, Hoss said.</p>
<p>Air France expects extra revenues of $100 million a year from its alliances with U.S. carriers Delta Air Lines and Continental, once full code-sharing pacts are in place and the alliance is at &quot;cruising speed&quot;, Hoss said.</p>
<p>But for the moment those alliances are limited as the French and U.S. governments have not agreed a bilateral air treaty. Washington is pressing Paris for an &quot;open skies&quot; pact which would allow market forces instead of official approvals to determine flights between the two countries.</p>
<p>The United States also wants rights for U.S. carriers to fly beyond France. Paris wants a nine-year progessive opening of the French market, to give time for Air France to adapt.</p>
<p>Hoss thought a bilateral agreement was unlikely this year but could be reached in 1998. &quot;We are not in a hurry,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Air France recently announced an alliance agreement with Air India, which will open up the huge domestic Indian market and has the added attraction of a prospective merger between the state-owned airlines Air India and Indian Airlines.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
