<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609504" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spain's stock watchdog bares teeth at firms.</title>
<headline>Spain's stock watchdog bares teeth at firms.</headline>
<byline>Sharman Esarey</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Signalling a new tougher stance against Spanish companies, stock market regulators on Friday fined top utility Endesa and opened a probe into leading bank Banco Bilbao Vizcaya.</p>
<p>Both actions centre on 66.8 percent state-owned Endesa's controversial purchase late last year of regional utilities Sevillana de Electricidad and Fuerzas Electricas de Catalunya.</p>
<p>Stock Market Commission CNMV fined Endesa, which is preparing for a further state stake sale this year, 300 million pesetas for failing to provide key information to the watchdog on its bid for the two regional utilities last year.</p>
<p>It also opened an investigation into BBV, saying Spain's second-largest bank had profited from information on the Sevillana purchase that should have remained confined within one department. BBV denied it had made any mistep.</p>
<p>&quot;Lack of compliance with these procedures and norms (establishing information barriers among different functions and departments) prompted BBV to order the purchase, through a foreign intermediary, shares of Sevillana de Electricidad SA in supposed violation of its obligation to keep such information in reserve,&quot; the CNMV said in a statment.</p>
<p>The CNMV has rarely targeted such high-profile companies, although last year it cited nine Spanish firms for very severe market infractions and seven for severe infractions in a market still considered fairly opaque by international standards.</p>
<p>But early last month, the chairman of the CNMV said he would seek new, higher standards of transparency and responsibility at home ahead of European monetary union.</p>
<p>The CNMV said it planned to reduce transaction costs by trimming what it saw as excessive bureaucracy, while at the same time stepping up its watchdog role to encourage listed companies to be more forthright and honest with shareholders.</p>
<p>In separate statements, Endesa said it would not appeal the fine, but BBV said it had not violated any rules. &quot;BBV, the first Spanish bank to adopt employees' rule of conduct, is convinced it has not committed any infraction,&quot; the bank added.</p>
<p>The news of the investigation, which also includes bank director general Javier Echenique, overshadowed an expected announcement that BBV would raise its nominal share value and split shares in three.</p>
<p>BBV will increase its nominal share value to 780 pesetas from 550, charging the move to bank's reserves.</p>
<p>Shares in BBV closed down 80 pesetas, or 0.79 percent, at 10,010 pesetas on Friday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
