<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609555" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Gevaert splits assets between Almanij, Cobepa.</title>
<headline>Gevaert splits assets between Almanij, Cobepa.</headline>
<byline>Geert De Clercq</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A reshuffle in shares of Belgian holding companies Gevaert, Almanij and Cobepa will bring Gevaert's Flemish and German interests under control of Almanij, while Gevaert's other interests will be moved to French-owned Cobepa, the companies said on Friday.</p>
<p>In one of the most complex operations on the Brussels bourse in years, Flemish Gevaert-Almanij and French-owned Cobepa will each go their own way after decades of close cooperation.</p>
<p>&quot;We are separating on good terms. Each side has taken off with his favourite furniture,&quot; Gevaert Chief Executive Officer Andre Leysen said at a joint news conference.</p>
<p>Gevaert is currently 35-percent owned by Cobepa and affiliates and 25 percent by families who act in concert with Cobepa. The rest is owned by the public.</p>
<p>Trade in shares of Almanij, Gevaert, Imperial Invest and of Cobepa and its affiliate companies Ibel and Belvuco was suspended on the Brussels bourse on Friday.</p>
<p>At the news conference, the companies gave no detail of how Gevaert's assets would be divided, but sources close to the companies gave the following breakdown.</p>
<p>Gevaert will keep its minority stakes in German shipping and transport group Hapag Lloyd and German real estate group IVG, in Kredietbank Luxembourg, in Flemish publishing group VUM and Flemish telecommunications group Telenet.</p>
<p>Almanij (now 11.5 percent-owned by Gevaert) will acquire a majority stake in Gevaert, which will become a diversified holding company.</p>
<p>Almanij is the controlling shareholder of Kredietbank and one of the main power brokers in Flanders, the northern, Dutch-speaking half of Belgium.</p>
<p>&quot;We will become a group which not only invests in banks, insurances and financial services. We will now acquire a fourth arm, which will focus on merchant bank activities,&quot; Almanij Chairman Jan Huyghebaert said.</p>
<p>Cobepa, 60 percent-owned by French financial group Paribas, will get Gevaert's minority stakes in Swiss holding company Pargesa and Pargesa parent company CPI, Gevaert's shares in Paribas Bank Belgium (which will be sold to Belgian Bacob, as announced separately today), and a minority stake in Belgian retailer GIB.</p>
<p>Gevaert's minority stakes in German chemical group Bayer and Dutch insurer Aegon will be split more or less evenly between Cobepa and the new Gevaert, and will serve as &quot;small change&quot; to balance out the asset division.</p>
<p>The planned reshuffle will proceed via a series of capital operations between September 15 and November 15.</p>
<p>&quot;We realise this operation is very complex, but the end result will make the two groups more transparent and simple,&quot; Cobepa Financial Director Christophe Evers told Reuters.</p>
<p>The sequence is the following: Gevaert will be split in two equal halves (A and B), each worth about 1,500 francs (the share closed at 2,975 francs on Thursday) by June 30. In September, Gevaert shareholders will receive a 150 franc gross extra dividend.</p>
<p>Before September, Almanij shares (which closed at 15,425 on Thursday) will be split in 10 new shares for one old share and shareholders will receive one free share per 50 split shares.</p>
<p>Thus, the share price value of each of the three companies will be around 1,500 francs, which will facilitate the reshuffle (Cobepa closed on Thursday at 1,430 francs). All transactions will be based on average share prices and intrinsic value of holdings in the month of April.</p>
<p>After shareholders in the three companies approve the operations at extraordinary meetings in September, Gevaert shareholders will receive for each old Gevaert share one new Gevaert share which can either be immediately exchanged for one split Almanij share or which can be exchanged against an Almanij share in September/October 2000 via a put warrant which will be attached to each new Gevaert share.</p>
<p>Cobepa and the family shareholders of Gevaert will fully convert their new Gevaert shares into Almanij shares immediately.</p>
<p>For the &quot;B-part&quot; of their old Gevaert shares, Gevaert shareholders will receive one Cobepa share which can immediately be exchanged against one split Almanij share provided by Cobepa. The new Cobepa shares will be created via an equity increase.</p>
<p>As for the A part, Cobepa and the families will fully convert into Almanij.</p>
<p>If, as expected, all Gevaert shareholders take the Almanij share, Cobepa will no longer own Almanij shares when the operations are completed.</p>
<p>The final size of Almanij's stake in Gevaert once all the exchange operations are completed will depend on how the market reacts to the proposed swaps, but could in theory rise to 100 percent, in which case the Gevaert share would no longer be listed on the Brussels bourse.</p>
<p>Almanij Managing Director Ferdinand Verdonck told Reuters that Almanij does not want this to happen since it wants to rely on the capital markets to finance Gevaert's future expansion.</p>
<p>-- Brussels Newsroom +32 2 287 6813, Fax +32 2 230 7710</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I65600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I6560002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I74000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
