<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609575" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French markets may be overconfident on Sunday poll.</title>
<headline>French markets may be overconfident on Sunday poll.</headline>
<byline>Penny MacRae</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French financial markets could be overconfident in betting on a comfortable showing by the ruling centre-right in Sunday's first round election ballot, economists said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;From the current perspective, the risk of a shock is very high,&quot; said senior bond analyst Iain Lindsay of Credit Lyonnais.</p>
<p>&quot;In percentage terms, 37 percent or less for the centre- right in the first round would be dangerous territory and a real cause for concern for the markets,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Stocks were higher on Friday but late afternoon election jitters pushed bond futures from their highs.</p>
<p>The 10-year bond future was up 0.06 basis points at 128.90 by midafternoon while the blue chip CAC 40 index of 40 leading shares was up 0.67 percent or 18.28 points at 2,759.38.</p>
<p>Traders, however, said few investors seemed worried about the outcome of the two-stage May 25-June 1 parliamentary election called by President Jacques Chirac to give him a free hand in the run-up to European monetary union.</p>
<p>&quot;People want to square up their positions, they do not want much exposure,&quot; said Marie Owens-Thomsen of BIP. &quot;So far there has been not any risk premium priced into the French market.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think people are shorting the French market or thinking about a negative outcome. People would rather sit it out and get back in when it is over,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Share investors also remained optimistic about the results, but one trader said, &quot;We're advising people to protect themselves against an adverse reaction on Monday.&quot;</p>
<p>One Paris brokerage saw the CAC index gaining 10 percent if the conservatives won and a loss of the same magnitude if the left won. &quot;Our view is that the conservatives will squeak home in the second ballot,&quot; said an equities strategist.</p>
<p>Surveys in France before a ban on publishing polls went into effect last weekend showed the left winning more votes than the conservatives in the first round but ending up with fewer seats after the run-off because of the single constituency system.</p>
<p>Economists expressed concern about the reliability of the seat projections. &quot;Given the close vote, I'm not confident about the simulations,&quot; said ABN Amro economist Philippe Brossard.</p>
<p>He said the expected high number of abstentions was an extra risk factor for the centre-right coalition. Given Prime Minister Alain Juppe's unpopularity, &quot;there is a risk (centre-right) supporters may not show up in the polling booths,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Investors recalled how pollsters got it wrong in the 1995 presidential election when the Socialists' standard bearer Lionel Jospin unexpectedly topped the first round ballot.</p>
<p>&quot;This election is obviously much more difficult for pollsters than a presidential election because you have 577 seats,&quot; said an economist.</p>
<p>Economist Sonja Gibbs of Nomura said stronger than expected Socialist gains -- even if the party fell short of winning an absolute majority -- could mean a more eurosceptic National Assembly and difficulty in pushing through austerity measures.</p>
<p>&quot;The French market is not priced for this outcome and the short end, in particular, looks vulnerable,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Even though the Socialists are committed to monetary union, a win by the party at the polls would likely mean a broader union, embracing Italy, with softer criteria for joining, she said.</p>
<p>One analyst said the upside for bonds and the franc to a centre-right win was &quot;very tame&quot; as it was already priced in.</p>
<p>If Sunday's first round decisively favoured the centre right's chances, with 39 to 40 percent of voters casting ballots for the coalition, there could be strong bidding in the cash market, Lindsay said. Domestic investors have been slowing their purchases and there was a high degree of liquidity, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;On the 10-year OAT-Bund spread you might get a one to two basis point gain and you might see the franc rising to 3.3650, closer to its pivot rate&quot; of 3.3538, Brossard said.</p>
<p>The franc was at 3.3697 per mark while the 10-year OAT-Bund spread had slipped to minus 13 from minus 15 on Thursday.</p>
<p>The median forecast for the franc against the mark in a Reuter survey on Thursday was 3.400. The forecast for the 10 year spread between French and German bond yields was 10 basis points. In the event of a right victory, the franc was seen at 3.362 and the spread was seen at minus 15 basis points.</p>
<p>&quot;The risk is if it is a very bad result in the first round with the right getting 35 percent of the vote and the left 40,&quot; said Lindsay.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see why the franc could not go above 3.40 or 3.45 per mark. I think it could crash quite badly,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
