<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609506" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Ireland's Robinson campaigns for U.N. rights post.</title>
<headline>Ireland's Robinson campaigns for U.N. rights post.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Irish President Mary Robinson on Friday spoke to U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan about her bid to become the new U.N. high commissioner for human rights but revealed little about her chances.</p>
<p>&quot;I reiterated my interest in becoming human rights commissioner, nominated by the Irish government,&quot; she told reporters. &quot;We had a very broad discussion  on the issue and I'm aware that he has a number of issues to look at in that regard. It's very much in his hands.&quot;</p>
<p>Robinson, backed by the United States and Britain, and several human rights groups, is considered the frontrunner.</p>
<p>But Annan, who prefers a woman for the job, has to cope with developing nations who object to a European, diplomats said. They said he may get around this by appointing a deputy commissioner from the Third World.</p>
<p>The General Assembly, dominated by developing states, has to approve the appointment.</p>
<p>A strong contender is Sonia Picado, Costa Rica's ambassador to Washington, who is backed by Latin American states at the United Nations.</p>
<p>Her candidacy ran into a muddle when the Mexican and Chilean foreign ministers at a European Union meeting last month said they approved of Robinson. At the United Nations, however, delegations from both countries, said they were still backing Picado.</p>
<p>Robinson, 52, steps down from her presidency in December after a seven-year term and probably would have to decide whether she would leave the post earlier. Annan is expected to make a decision by July.</p>
<p>She said that she and Annan &quot;had a very broad discuission on the issue and I am aware that we have a number of issues to look at in this regard.&quot;</p>
<p>Annan has said he want a human rights component in all U.N. operations from peacekeeping to development and Robinson said she was very pleased to hear that.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very good that the secretary-general places such high significance on human rights throughout the U.N. system, and it is really a cornerstone of the United Nations,&quot; she said. &quot;I'm glad to hear him say that so openly and in a way that I greatly appreciate.&quot;</p>
<p>The post, first suggested nearly 50 years ago, became vacant after Jose Ayala Lasso resigned last month as the first U.N. high commissioner for human rights to become Ecuador's foreign minister. He was appointed in 1994 for four years.</p>
<p>His one-time deputy Ibramina Fall of Senegal is said to be campaigning for the job as well as Finland's former defence minister Elizabeth Rehn. But their chances were considered slim compared to those of Robinson and Picado.</p>
<p>Ayala Lasso had been criticised for his low-profile in not publicly condemning more rights abuses.</p>
<p>&quot;He gave up the key force he has to defend human rights -- which is the willingness to publicly condemn abusive governments,&quot; said Kenneth Roth, executive director of the New York-based Human Rights Watch. &quot;He insisted on using quiet diplomacy when he had no clout to privately deliver.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
