<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609540" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spain's BBV denies CNMV charges of insider trading.</title>
<headline>Spain's BBV denies CNMV charges of insider trading.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spanish Bank Banco Bilbao Vizcaya (BBV), responding to an announcement by the stock market commission CNV that it had targeted the company for an insider trading investigation, denied on Friday that it had violated any rules.</p>
<p>In a statement the bank said: &quot;BBV, the first Spanish bank to adopt employees' rule of conduct, is convinced of not having committed any infraction and so it will answer with the following arguments to the CNMV's probe.&quot;</p>
<p>BBV, which has been an Endesa shareholder since 40 years, bought on September 30 an option giving them the right to acquire more Sevillana shares.</p>
<p>&quot;At that time the hypothesis was that Sevillana would remain independent,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The financial broker carried out the purchase of Sevillana's shares without express intervention from BBV, according to normal practices.</p>
<p>When BBV was informed, on October 17, about the Endesa bid for Sevillana, it asked to liquidate the option.</p>
<p>&quot;BBV did not accept any money proceedings from that option contract. And these (Sevillana) shares did not form part of the Endesa bid,&quot; the statement concluded.</p>
<p>-- Madrid Newsroom, + 341 585 8340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
