<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609512" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: UN refugee chief to visit Central Asia.</title>
<headline>UN refugee chief to visit Central Asia.</headline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of the U.N. refugee agency will visit ex-Soviet Central Asia this month to discuss the fate of hundreds of thousands of people displaced by wars, ethnic tensions or ecological disasters, her office said on Friday.</p>
<p>The military situation in Afghanistan and the conflict in neighbouring Tajikistan, which have triggered fresh movements of refugees, will be among the issues on the agenda of Sadako Ogata during her 10-day trip from May 25, a statement said.</p>
<p>Ogata will meet presidents and top officials in Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Uzbekistan, Tajikistan and Turkmenistan during her tour of the vast region stretching from China's borders in the east to the Caspian Sea in the west.</p>
<p>The Geneva-based refugee agency (UNHCR), which has more than 26 million refugees under its care, estimates that more than 4.2 million Central Asians, or one in 12 of the region's inhabitants, have been displaced since 1989.</p>
<p>In addition to tens of thousands of people left homeless by Tajikistan's four-year tribal war, hundreds of thousands of ethnic Russians have left and people have fled a series of Soviet-made environmental disasters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TADZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USSR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
