<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609562" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: FOCUS-Portugal may privatise 27.5 pct of EDP.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Portugal may privatise 27.5 pct of EDP.</headline>
<dateline>LISBON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Portugal was expected to privatise a stake of some 27.5 percent in utility EDP-Electricidade de Portugal, including a &quot;green shoe&quot;, its president Antonio de Almeida said on Friday.</p>
<p>Almeida, speaking at a roadshow to promote the sale, said it was likely a 25 percent stake in the company would be sold off, as well as a 10 percent stake of the tranche to be sold in the domestic and international direct sale in a &quot;green shoe.&quot;</p>
<p>Under a &quot;green shoe&quot; option, additional shares may be allocated to institutional investors if demand is very heavy.</p>
<p>The Socialist government was expected to sell 55 percent of the 27.5 pct stake in a public offer to sell (OPV) and 45 percent in the domestic and international direct sale at a special session on Lisbon bourse on June 16, Almeida said.</p>
<p>EDP, Portugal's dominant electricity generator and distributor, has a capital of 600 billion escudos ($3.5 billion).</p>
<p>The share price in the second stage privatisation of EDP will be substantially higher than in the first stage, reflecting expectations of improved results, Almeida said.</p>
<p>&quot;With the prospect of an improvement in EDP's results, I expect that in the second stage privatisation the sale will take place at a much higher price,&quot; he said. &quot;The state will bring in a substantially larger sum (in the second stage),&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Investors in the OPV could receive some 10 percent of the shares they apply for, Almeida said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are four days into the pre-registration period. If demand continues at this pace, and if the publicity campaign draws in more Portuguese, I think a 10 percent figure is not unrealistic,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But he said it was too early to make accurate forecasts of the total level of demand. &quot;Much of the demand is driven by the fact that many people think that they will receive a small proportion of the shares that they apply for,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A banking source told Reuters on Thursday that applications had been submitted in the first three days of pre-registration for 642 million shares, representing more than four times the number of shares likely to be on offer.</p>
<p>EDP said its first quarter consolidated net profit had risen by 21 percent to 29.16 billion escudos ($171 million).</p>
<p>The utility plans to compete for a third mobile phone licence in Portugal, Almeida said.</p>
<p>&quot;We will compete for the third licence, with a national and an international partner, but I cannot give names,&quot; Almeida said at the start of a national roadshow to promote the partial privatisation of EDP next month.</p>
<p>&quot;The national partner is not from the telecommunications sector, but the international partner is,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The two present mobile phone licence holders are Telecel-Comunicacoes Pessoais and TMN, a unit of Portugal Telecom.</p>
<p>EDP had suspended talks with a view to taking a possible 20 percent stake in Telecel, Almeida said.</p>
<p>&quot;Talks with Telecel did not reach an agreement,&quot; he said. &quot;We reached the conclusion that it was preferable not to pursue the talks,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>$1=170.743 escudos</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LISBON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
