<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609502" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Suspended terms urged for French zinc plant bosses.</title>
<headline>Suspended terms urged for French zinc plant bosses.</headline>
<dateline>BETHUNE, France 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A prosecutor on Friday urged suspended jail terms and modest fines for two former managers of a French zinc plant where explosions killed 11 workers in 1993 and 1994.</p>
<p>Lawyers for the families said the recommended sentences were too lenient. &quot;What has been given here is a genuine licence to kill,&quot; said Charles Lederman, an attorney representing victims' families and a labour union participating in the trial.</p>
<p>Prosecutor Patrick Desjardins faulted safety procedures at the plant, owned by French zinc and lead producer Metaleurop, and said it seemed the safety situation at the plant was &quot;a big mess&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It is too easy to blame fate,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Jean Neret, attorney for the two managers, urged that they be acquitted of manslaughter.</p>
<p>Desjardins recommended a two-year suspended sentence plus a fine of 30,000 francs ($5,250) for Pierre Vix, who ran the Metaleurop plant in Noyelles-Godault, northeastern France, during the first explosion in July 1993, in which 10 workers died.</p>
<p>For Jean-Jacques Dailloux, who was running the plant at the time of the second blast in January 1994 in which an 11th employee died, he urged an 18-month suspended sentence and an identical 30,000-franc ($5,250) fine.</p>
<p>He noted the managers were being tried under a provision of the penal code, since rewritten, allowing a maximum sentence of two years in prison. The new version of the code allows prison terms of up to five years.</p>
<p>The court's judgment will be released on September 25.</p>
<p>A judicial probe of the deaths, conducted before the trial which began on Tuesday, had uncovered &quot;safety shortfalls&quot; at the plant.</p>
<p>Investigating magistrate Benoit Persyn said in a court submission based on legal and technical analyses that &quot;certain steps could have been taken, if not to avoid the explosions, at least to avoid the deaths of a hefty number of victims&quot;.</p>
<p>Safety at the plant &quot;had made no advances in 15 years&quot;, the magistrate said. Before both explosions, cracking, vibration and unusual noises had been noticed by plant operators.</p>
<p>Four of the 11 who died were permanent Metaleurop staff, while the others had been hired through temporary work agencies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BETHUNE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
