<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609565" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU energy ministers to tackle gas liberalisation.</title>
<headline>EU energy ministers to tackle gas liberalisation.</headline>
<byline>Gillian Handyside</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union energy ministers will attempt next Tuesday to narrow their differences over partial liberalisation of the EU gas market, with a view to reaching a definitive accord by the end of the year.</p>
<p>The Dutch EU presidency hopes to broker a compromise at the Energy Council on three major obstacles to an EU directive on gas liberalisation -- the structure of market opening, the treatment of take-or-pay contracts and exemptions from competition rules for emerging markets and regions.</p>
<p>The presidency has not ventured to propose any definitive figures, leaving ministers to make the controversial decision on how far the member states will be obliged to open their markets.</p>
<p>A spokesman for EU Energy Commissioner Christos Papoutsis said on Friday that the Commission hoped ministers could reach an accord on principles on Tuesday but did not expect a firm deal on figures until after the forthcoming French and Irish general elections, possibly in July when Luxembourg takes over the EU presidency.</p>
<p>Papoutsis was not prepared to go ahead with a special session in June or July, unless ministers committed themselves next Tuesday to a &quot;substantial opening&quot; of the market, spokesman Costas Verros told reporters.</p>
<p>But he added that at the moment neither the Commission nor the member states were prepared to say what they interpreted &quot;substantial opening&quot; to mean.</p>
<p>Next Tuesday the Dutch will propose to ministers a two-level formula for progressively liberalising national markets.</p>
<p>The formula first defines &quot;eligible customers&quot;, who will be allowed to negotiate contracts directly with the gas supplier of their chosing.</p>
<p>These include all power generators and large industrial customers who consume several million cubic metres of gas a year, though the figure has yet to be agreed.</p>
<p>As national fuel markets vary considerably -- with gas well- established in places like Britain or France but only just beginning to develop in Portugal and Greece -- there will also be wide variations in the share of the market which these eligible customers represent.</p>
<p>The Dutch are therefore suggesting that national governments should be able to modify their lists of eligible customers in order to comply with an obligatory EU-wide minimum threshold for liberalisation and an optional maximum ceiling.</p>
<p>Again it will be left to ministers to agree on the thresholds, which would both be raised in five years time.</p>
<p>Last December, EU energy ministers agreed to a formula for opening up the European electricity sector which obliges the member states to liberalise some 12 percent of their markets by 1999, rising to 33 percent by 2003.</p>
<p>While EU diplomats are predicting a possible agreement on a formula for liberalisation, they are less optimistic about ministers reaching a deal on the long term take-or-pay contracts with external suppliers in Russia, Algeria and Norway which dominate the EU's gas industry.</p>
<p>There is general agreement among member states that in cases where introducing competition into a domestic market causes a crisis for distributors locked into take-or-pay contracts, the national government should be able temporarily to limit newcomers' market access.</p>
<p>But there are deep divisions over how this will work in practice and who will be responsible for deciding whether exemptions from competition are justifiable.</p>
<p>&quot;Commissioner Papoutsis thinks only the Commission will offer credibility and objectivity (in deciding) exemptions,&quot; Verros said.</p>
<p>This view is backed by Britain but Germany and France believe the decision should be left to their national authorities, a Dutch diplomat told Reuters.</p>
<p>She said the Dutch presidency would propose a compromise whereby derogations for existing take-or-pay contracts would be decided at national level while rulings on future contracts would be left to the Commission.</p>
<p>But she was pessimistic about the chances of an early deal.</p>
<p>Connected to this issue is the question of exemptions from competition rules for emerging markets, like Portugal and Greece, and isolated regions in other member states, such as Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>A British diplomat said there was general agreement that the two southern states should be allowed protection for 10 years but energy ministers still had to decide which regions from a list proposed by the Dutch would be allowed exemptions.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
