<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609520" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Healthy looking Mother Teresa initiates new nuns.</title>
<headline>Healthy looking Mother Teresa initiates new nuns.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A healthy looking Mother Teresa accepted a group of new nuns into her renowned missionary order at a church ceremony in Rome on Friday.</p>
<p>The Nobel Peace Prize winner, who was taken ill at her arrival at Rome airport a week ago, held up well during the two-hour initiation ceremony in stifling heat in a modern church in a working class neighbourhood.</p>
<p>Their voices cracking with emotion, the 16 young women read their Roman Catholic vows of chastity, poverty and obedience to Mother Teresa. She blessed them and tucked a crucifix into a sash of their traditional blue and white saris.</p>
<p>The new nuns included Poles, Italians and Spaniards.</p>
<p>Mother Teresa, 86, sat with her head bowed and hands clasped in prayer for much of the mass and did not need a wheelchair to enter or leave the church.</p>
<p>&quot;Prayer is that beautiful contact with God,&quot; she told the congregation, many of whom tried to get past security guards to touch her.</p>
<p>&quot;We listen to God in our hearts and then we speak to God from our hearts,&quot; she said, speaking in English.</p>
<p>The service was Mother Teresa's first public appearance since she arrived in Rome last Friday amid fears for her health.</p>
<p>She needed oxygen for 20 minutes at Rome airport after a long flight from India, but doctors and aides said there was no cause for alarm and that she has been well since.</p>
<p>Known as the &quot;saint of the gutter&quot; for her work among the poorest of the poor, Mother Teresa held talks with Pope John Paul on Tuesday to introduce her successor as head of the Missionaries of Charity order.</p>
<p>Sister Nirmala, a 62-year-old Indian, took over as superior-general of the Calcutta-based order in March when Mother Teresa stepped down after a battle against heart disease.</p>
<p>Mother Teresa, an ethnic Albanian, was admitted to hospital three times last year for emergency care and heart surgery.</p>
<p>On Thursday night she visited a cardinal whom a human rights group has accused of being an accomplice to the Argentine military's &quot;dirty war&quot; on leftists in the late 1970s.</p>
<p>Cardinal Pio Laghi, head of the Vatican's Congregation for Catholic Education, this week again denied accusations that he had turned a blind eye to human rights abuses while Vatican ambassador in Buenos Aires.</p>
<p>Mother Teresa has known Laghi since the early 1960s when he was a Vatican diplomat in India.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
