<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609509" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: Greek watchdog slaps fines in bourse scandal.</title>
<headline>Greek watchdog slaps fines in bourse scandal.</headline>
<byline>Dina Kyriakidou</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greece's capital markets commision on Friday slapped heavy fines on brokerages, traders and businessmen for insider trading in the Delta Securities scandal that rocked the Athens bourse for weeks last year.</p>
<p>The penalties prompted a storm of protest from those fined, who accused the bourse watchdog of being unfair and attempting to cover up the real culprits. The commission was not available for comment.</p>
<p>After checks by three international auditing firms called in to investigate the scandal that halted trading for four days in November 1996, the commission issued a statement announcing fines ranging from 10 million drachmas ($37,000) to 150 million drachmas.</p>
<p>&quot;The commission's board decided to apply administrative penalties on individuals and legal entities involved in pre-arranged, manipulative trades...,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>It fined three brokerage houses -- Ionian Securities, a subsidiary of state-controlled Ionian Bank 90 million drachmas, Sigma Securities 50 million drachmas and Euroxx Securities 30 million drachmas for alleged &quot;violations of insider trading regulations&quot;.</p>
<p>It also sent a written reprimand to bourse members N. Devletoglou, state-controlled National Bank subsidiary National Securities and Kappa Securities for &quot;failing to exercise the required due diligence to protect the market from the consequences of pre-arranged trades.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;All the above brokerages were found to violate the present code of conduct and it was decided to place them under a three-month probation as regards the articles of the code of conduct,&quot; the commission said.</p>
<p>It also imposed fines on nine brokers, investors and businessmen for various insider trading violations.</p>
<p>The scandal broke when Delta, a relatively small brokerage, tried to settle its account at the bourse's clearing house with 2.6 billion drachmas in bad cheques.</p>
<p>It was partly blamed on some brokers taking advantage of a overburdened settlement system, which took up to 40 days to clear instead of the regulated 72 hours, by selling shares short and capitalising on the delay before actually delivering the securities.</p>
<p>The fines prompted a storm of protest from those fined, who decried it as a cover up of the role of the clearing house in the scandal.</p>
<p>&quot;They were looking for scapegoats. The responsibilities ...(for the Delta Securities scandal) rest with the Athens stock exchange and the people operating in and around it,&quot; Constantine Georgakis told Reuters.</p>
<p>Georgakis, president of construction firm Atemke was fined 150 million drachmas for alleged insider trading violations and manipulative practices in shares of Parnassos and Atemke .</p>
<p>&quot;We are surprised with the mentality of the commission which confirms that even today, despite the progress in the market, there is preferential treatment when it comes to applying the law,&quot; said managing director of Sigma Securities John Marcopoulos, who was personally fined 25 million drachmas.</p>
<p>Market analysts said the commission fined only one state brokerage, Ionian, and reprimanded another, National Securities, although more had been implicated. ($ = 269.8 Greek Drachmas)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
