<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609598" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Asian port conditions - Lloyds.</title>
<headline>Asian port conditions - Lloyds.</headline>
<text>
<p>Port conditions from Lloyds Shipping Intelligence Service --</p>
<p>INDIA, May 20 - Bombay - Delays expected for vessels due, containers, general cargo 1-2 days, bulk vessels 5-6 days. 5 vessels loading at berth, 19 discharging at berth, 1 discharging at anchorage, 3 waiting at anchorage to load, 15 waiting at anchorage to discharge. 3 vessels under repair, 3 awaiting orders. Gang shortage due to summer vacation.</p>
<p>Calcutta - 34 vessels due of which 3 coking coal, 10 product tankers, 8 containers, 1 general, 2 crude, 3 coal, 1 limestone, 1 petcoke, 1 bulk, 1 wheels and pipes, 1 lash barge, 1 met co, 1 steel. 5 Vessels loading at berth, 16 discharging at berth, 1 discharging at anchorage, 2 bunkering.</p>
<p>Cochin - Eight vessels due, 1-2 days delay expected. 2 vessels loading at berth, 7 discharging at berth, 1 waiting at anchorage to discharge. Repair/drydock, 1 general cargo vessel at CSL jetty, 1 naval vessel in drydock.</p>
<p>Chennai/Madras - 32 vessels due of which 1 coal, 1 iron ore, 1 fertiliser, 10 general, 8 containers, 2 logs, 1 palm oil, 3 others. Delays, coal/coke fertiliser 2-3 days, scrap 4-5 days, iron ore 5-6 days, others 2-3 days. 1 vessel loading at berth, 9 discharging at berth.</p>
<p>Mormugao - Six vessels due, 6-7 days delay expected. 3 vessels loading at berth, 7 loading at anchorage, 1 discharging at anchorage, 11 waiting at anchorage to load, 1 waiting at anchorage to discharge, 3 under repair/drydock, 1 awaiting orders.</p>
<p>Kandla - 10 vessels due, 6-7 days delay expected. 4 vessels discharging at berth, 13 tankers.</p>
<p>Mangalore - Six vessels due, 1-2 days delay expected, 8 vessels loading/discharging at berth, 5 awaiting berth.</p>
<p>Jawaharlal Nehru - Two foodgrain/fertiliser vessels due, 15 days berthing delay. 4 tankers/iron ore vessels due, 7 days berthing delay. 1 tanker loading at berth, 2 discharging at berth, 2 waiting at anchorage to discharge. Bulk berth no.4 will not be available for vessels from 1/6 to 30/9.</p>
<p>Paradip - 49 vessels due, 7-8 days delay expected. 3 vessels loading at berth. 4 waiting at anchorage to load, 3 waiting at anchorage to discharge.</p>
<p>Tuticorin - Five vessels due, 1-2 days delay at present. 1 vessel loading at berth, 4 discharging at berth, 1 discharging at anchorage, 1 waiting at anchorage to load, 1 waiting at anchorage to discharge.</p>
<p>Visakhapatnam - 19 vessels due, 10-12 days delay expected. 6 vessels loading at berth, 9 discharging at berth, 7 waiting at anchorage to discharge at inner harbour berth, 2 waiting at anchorage to load at inner harbour berth, 1 waiting for repair.</p>
<p>MALAYSIA, May 20 - Port Klang - North/South Port - container/ro/ro berth - 5 vessels berthed, 2 waiting with no delays. Deep draft conventional wharf - 5 vessels berthed, 2 berthing 20/5, 6 waiting with 2 days waiting time. Dry/cent bulk terminal - 2 vessels berthed, 2 waiting with 8 days waiting time. Liquid bulk terminal - 2 vessels berthed, 2 waiting with no delays. West port - container/ro/ro berth - 4 vessels berthed, 2 waiting with no delays. Deep draft conventional wharf - 3 vessels berthed, 4 waiting with 2 days waiting time. Cement bulk terminal - 1 vessels berthed, none waiting, no delays. Liquid bulk terminal - 2 vessel berthed, none waiting, no delays.</p>
<p>SINGAPORE, May 20  - Tanjong Pagar container terminal - 11 container vessels berthed.</p>
<p>Keppel - 17 container/general cargo vessels berthed.</p>
<p>Pasir Panjang - 7 container/general cargo vessels berthed.</p>
<p>Sembawang - 8 general cargo vessels berthed.</p>
<p>Jurong - 1 bulk cargo/steel/general cargo vessel berthed.</p>
<p>Oil terminal/SBM buoys - 22 tankers berthed. Minimum berthing delays at all facilities.</p>
<p>SOUTH KOREA - Inchon - 68 vessels in port (41 berthed, 27 anchored) of which berthed - 6 logs, 6 containers, 5 general cargo, 4 pig-iron, 3 steel, 3 cars, 2 corn, 2 cotton seed meal, 2 plywood, 1 steel plates, 1 wheat blending pellets, 1 pulp, 1 coils, 1 soy beans, 1 timber, 1 wheat, 1 raw sugar. Vessels anchored - 5 scrap, 4 logs, 4 containers, 3 coils, 2 cars, 2 general cargo, 1 barley, 1 corn, 1 pulp, 1 wheat, 1 salt, 1 fertiliser, 1 pig-iron, approx. 1-2 days berthing delay expected.</p>
<p>Busan - 152 vessels in port (42 berthed, 118 anchored including 55 laid up), of which berthed - 27 general cargo, 8 containers, 4 scrap, 3 coal. 55 vessels awaiting berths with approx. 1-2 days delay expected.</p>
<p>Pohang - 37 vessels in port (all berthed), of which discharging - 7 steel billets, 6 scrap, 3 steel, 1 logs, 1 ferro-silicon. Vessels loading - 9 steel, 5 plates, 4 coils, 1 pipes, no berthing delays expected.</p>
<p>Ulsan - 19 vessels in port (all berthed), of which discharging - 3 feed meal, 2 chemicals, 2 crude oil, 1 cement, 1 raw sugar, 1 caustic soda, 1 mixed xylene, 1 wood-chips, 1 corn. Vessels loading - 3 general cargo, 1 chemicals, 1 kerosene, 1 diesel oil. No berthing delays expected.</p>
<p>Masan - ten vessels in port (all berthed) of which discharging - 3 scrap, 1 logs, 1 tapioca, 1 pulp, 1 containers. Vessels loading - 1 steel plates, 1 cars, 1 coaches. No berthing delays expected.</p>
<p>TAIWAN, May 19 - Keelung - four vessels anchored, Berthing delays - grain/steel/iron ore - 3 days, coal - 6 days.</p>
<p>Kaohsiung - four vessels anchored. Berthing delays - grain/steel - 2 days, iron/coal - 2 days (CSC berth), coal/scrap - 6 days (public berth).</p>
<p>Taichung - eight vessels anchored. Berthing delays - grain - 5-6 days, iron ore/scrap - 1-2 days, coal/steel/others - 2 days.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
