<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609608" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: PRESS DIGEST - Pakistan newspapers - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Pakistan newspapers - May 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Pakistani press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAWN</p>
<p>- The Privatisation Commission has finalised strategy to privatise Karachi Electric Supply Corporation, Sui Southern Gas Company, Sui Northern Gas Company and 14 other state units in the next six months.</p>
<p>- The government has decided to confiscate all movable and immovable properties of defaulters to recover outstanding loans of 140 billion rupees.</p>
<p>- The National Assembly adopted amendments in the banking laws dissolving the Pakistan Banking Council and repealing the exclusive right of the federal government to establish a bank.</p>
<p>- Princess Diana has arrived in Lahore on a three-day visit to launch an endowment fund appeal for Imran Khan's cancer hospital and research centre.</p>
<p>- Foreign Minister Gohar Ayub Khan has said there was a possibility that Pakistani F-16 aircrafts stranded in the United States might be sold to a East European state.</p>
<p>- Pakistan will release all the Indian fishermen and their boats in its custody within five to 10 days.</p>
<p>- Pakistan's foreign exchange reserves fell to $897.76 million on May 17 from $1.094 billion on May 10 showing a big decline of $196.24 million.</p>
<p>BUSINESS RECORDER</p>
<p>- Pakistan has lost the considerable Saudi rice market to its main competitors - America, Thailand and India, a market survey conducted by the Pakistan embassy in Jeddah said.</p>
<p>- Finance Minister Sartaj Aziz has said the current financial year was the worst in the history of the country due to the policies of former prime minister Benazir Bhutto.</p>
<p>- European Commission's plan of imposing a definitive anti-dumping duty on the exports of grey fabrics from six countries including Pakistan fizzled out as majority of the member countries rejected it.</p>
<p>NEWS</p>
<p>- Flow of foreign investment in Pakistan has been dried down completely since November.</p>
<p>MUSLIM</p>
<p>- Financial irregularities to the tune of 3.1 billion rupees and $118.5 million have been detected in the budgetary allocations of defence services in the year 1994/95, said a report of Auditor General of Pakistan.</p>
<p>NATION</p>
<p>- Bhutto said the recent meeting between Nawaz Sharif and Indian Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral was the biggest disappointment of the present government.</p>
<p>- Senate passed a law prohibiting wasteful expenses at wedding ceremonies.</p>
<p>-- Islamabad newsroom 9251-274757</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
