<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609648" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: Sri Lankan rebels shell army positions in north.</title>
<headline>Sri Lankan rebels shell army positions in north.</headline>
<byline>Mohan Samarasinghe</byline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Separatist Tamil Tiger guerrillas shelled Sri Lankan army positions on Friday around two towns captured by troops during a thrust into the rebels' northern heartland, the Defence Ministry said.</p>
<p>Rebels fired mortar rounds at army positions as troops fortified their defences around Omanthai and Nedunkeni, deep in the rebels' northern Wanni stronghold, it said in a statement.</p>
<p>Troops captured Nedunkeni, 40 miles (25 km) northeast of the government-held town of Vavuniya and Omanthai, 14 km (nine miles) north of Vavuniya, last week in one of their biggest offensives against the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE).</p>
<p>Sri Lankan forces, backed by tanks, artillery and air cover, launched &quot;Operation Jaya Sikuru&quot;, or &quot;Sure of Victory&quot;, from Vavuniya more than a week ago in a bid to open a supply route to Jaffna peninsula, 100 km (60 miles) further north. Vavuniya lies 220 km (135 miles) north of the capital Colombo.</p>
<p>The LTTE, fighting for an independent homeland for minority Tamils in mainly Sinhalese Sri Lanka's north and east, control vast swathes of land in the mostly shrub-covered Wanni between Jaffna and Vavuniya.</p>
<p>Government forces rely on costly and tenuous air and sea links to supply bases and civilians in Jaffna, the LTTE's former would-be homeland the military brought under complete control one year ago.</p>
<p>The LTTE said the army was killing Tamil civilians and destroying property under the pretext of opening the route.</p>
<p>A statement issued by the LTTE's international secretariat in London accused the military of shelling Tamil villages.</p>
<p>&quot;Sri Lankan armed forces have now begun smashing Tamil settlements around Nedunkeni and Omanthai. Tamil civilians are clearly the targets,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>It said residents in affected areas were streaming towards Mullaitivu, 280 km (175 miles) northeast of Colombo, where the rebels have their main bases.</p>
<p>A military spokesman in Colombo confirmed the shelling, but said they were never directed at civilians.</p>
<p>&quot;We only engage identified terrorist targets confirmed by our intelligence sources,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>According to Defence Ministry figures, 67 soldiers have been killed and 96 wounded in the offensive. Hospital sources have said some 600 soldiers had been wounded.</p>
<p>The LTTE statement said 59 rebels had died in the fighting.</p>
<p>The Defence Ministry says LTTE radio transmissions intercepted by the army indicated 181 Tigers had been killed and 316 wounded. It said the dead included several rebel leaders.</p>
<p>Aid workers have said food was running low in the Wanni, where thousands of civilians have been displaced by the offensive. They said no food convoys had gone north since the army offensive began last Tuesday.</p>
<p>The government says more than 50,000 people have been killed in the ethnic war, now in its 14th year. The LTTE say the toll is higher.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
