<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609638" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Two-wheeler stocks brake Delhi fall. [CORRECTED 12:40 GMT]</title>
<headline>Two-wheeler stocks brake Delhi fall. [CORRECTED 12:40 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in two-wheeler makers powered ahead on Friday, braking a broader fall in stock prices on the Delhi bourse on Friday, brokers said.</p>
<p>The Delhi Stock Exchange's benchmark index ended 3.38 points lower at 766.10.</p>
<p>(Corrects title and text to make clear that shares in two-wheeler makers, not the car industry, were ahead on Friday.)</p>
<p>Brokers said most investors refrained from making fresh purchases and squared their positions on the last day of the current settlement period.</p>
<p>Traders said speculators and foreign investors mopped up shares of Hero Honda as they expected the company to declare a bonus share issue along with encouraging 1996/97 (April-March) corporate results.</p>
<p>&quot;A steep rise in Hero Honda shares on rumours that company might propose an attractive bonus issue amidt excellent working results later this month was the main feature of the day's trade,&quot; said Ashok Arya of brokers S.C. Gupta.</p>
<p>Hero Honda shot up 41.00 rupees, or 8.84 percent, to 505.00 rupees.</p>
<p>Bajaj Auto, another two-wheeler maker, rose 5.00 rupees to 850.00.</p>
<p>TELCO edged up 0.15 rupee to 393.90.</p>
<p>Reliance Industries lost 0.70 rupee to 289.90 as speculators squared positions, brokers said.</p>
<p>ACC fell 27.05 rupees to 1,120.00.</p>
<p>-- New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
