<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609623" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India quake victims share hospital with roaming animals.</title>
<headline>India quake victims share hospital with roaming animals.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>JABALPUR, India 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Anxious relatives of earthquake victims were forced to share the filthy corridors of Victoria Hospital with cats and dogs while waiting for news of their loved ones on Friday.</p>
<p>The hospital is housing more than 200 people with broken bones and spinal and pelvic injuries sustained during the powerful earthquake that rocked this central Indian city before dawn on Thursday.</p>
<p>Officials say at least 38 people were killed when their houses caved in, more than 1,000 were injured and thousands left homeless.</p>
<p>In the hospital, Ram Kali Bai, 60, from Puranabasti village on the outskirts of Jabalpur said: &quot;The earth shook like a see-saw and the roof fell on me.&quot;</p>
<p>She sat wailing, her head covered with a blood-stained saree, pleading with her relatives to take her home.</p>
<p>Her 30-year-old daughter Parvati Bai said: &quot;The sound was like a cloudburst -- it was like a steamroller going over our house.&quot;</p>
<p>Flies and mosquitoes filled the air, attracted by pools of water in the corridors. Visitors complained of the stench of putrefying waste.</p>
<p>&quot;The roof collapsed on my father and he has suffered serious head injuries,&quot; said Rajkumar Kesarwani as he rubbed an ice-pack on his 60-year-old father's head.</p>
<p>His thin, dishevelled father Khemchand lay silently on the bed clad in a blood-stained vest and lungi, his head bandaged.</p>
<p>Grief-stricken women sat dazed, huddled in groups in hospital wards where victims had been admitted.</p>
<p>Doctor Anil Dubey said: &quot;There have been 200 cases reported to the hospital. Most of these were pelvic injuries, limb fractures and spinal injuries. Most were victims of collapsing roofs or walls.&quot;</p>
<p>A frail nine-year-old girl with chest wounds and pelvic fractures lay attached to a saline drip, a dirty sheet covering her from the neck down. He mother lay in an adjacent iron cot.</p>
<p>Two nuns dressed in the blue-edged white sarees of Mother Teresa's Missionaries of Charity talked softly to patients and their relatives, offering comfort.</p>
<p>Outside, government workers used shovels and sticks to clear the debris that littered Jabalpur's streets. Heaps of rubble lined the area near the city's whitewashed clock tower, which lost one of its four minarets in the quake.</p>
<p>The earthquake was centred on the village of Kosamghat, 23 km (14 miles) south of Jabalpur. All the village's 160 houses, mostly mud huts, were flattened, leaving more than 1,000 residents homeless.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JABALPUR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
