<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609647" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Fast food joints make Indian spices a hot affair.</title>
<headline>Fast food joints make Indian spices a hot affair.</headline>
<byline>Parakulam Sundar</byline>
<dateline>COONOOR, India 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mushrooming ethnic eateries worldwide have made Indian spices a hot commodity, officials and traders said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are no longer concentrating on wholesome exports of spices. On the contrary the focus is on value added products,&quot; said G.A. Balakrishnan, a leading exporter..</p>
<p>He said value addition was in different forms including oleoresin, essential oils, pepper in brine, dehydrated pepper and vegetables, pepper powder, dried pepper and sterilised pepper.</p>
<p>India, grows 52 varieties of spice and is the world's largest exporter of the commodity. Pepper, the king of spices, fetches the largest export earnings.</p>
<p>India's spices exports in 1996/97 (April-March) were at an all-time high of 219,400 tonnes valued at 11.8 billion rupees, compared with 202,197 tonnes in the previous year worth 7.9 billion.</p>
<p>In 1996/97 India exported 47,770 tonnes of black pepper against 26,346 tonnes in the previous year.</p>
<p>Exporters said a preference for Indian spices and a relative shortage of products from other exporting nations had kept Indian prices high.</p>
<p>Balakrishnan said exports of items such as curry powder and mint oil had increased both in volume and value with the growth of fast food joints in the United States and other countries.</p>
<p>Traders said with the rapid expansion of the noodles market in Asia, Indian exports of dehydrated onion, garlic chilli and chilli powder were growing.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect to dominate in the noodles market among the restaurants in Singapore, Hong Kong, Thailand, Taiwan and Malaysia,&quot; said Anuj Patel, a spices exporter.</p>
<p>He said pickled onion with vinegar as a preservative and ready to use ginger and onion pastes were catching on in Asian households.</p>
<p>&quot;This takes out the labour of making a paste while cooking at home,&quot; Patel said.</p>
<p>M.R. Usha, deputy director of the state-run Spices Board said an instant curry powder launched in Singapore in April had become an instant hit in Asian markets.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of demand has already been created for it,&quot; said A.S. Rajagopalan, managing director of the Concert Spices and Exports Ltd, which makes the powder.</p>
<p>Indian value added spices are exported to the Middle East, Europe, United States and most Asian countries.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COONOOR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
