<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609659" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India castor prices ease, sluggish overseas buying.</title>
<headline>India castor prices ease, sluggish overseas buying.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian castorseed June delivery prices on Friday eased to 1,081/1,082 rupees per quintal from 1,084 rupees on fresh speculative offerings, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Sluggish overseas enquiries and sustained pressure of arrivals dragged prices lower,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>Daily average arrivals of castorseed in the Gujarat region were high at 30,000/32,000 bags (75 kg each).</p>
<p>In the Bombay market trading volumes for June delivery remained low while there was trading for September delivery as traders were indicating September delivery nominally at 1,170/1,175 rupees per quintal.</p>
<p>Groundnut oil rose to 358/360 rupees per 10 kg from 355 rupees as fresh seasonal buying helped prices to bounce back after recent losses. Summer crop arrivals remained low as farmers were busy at producing centres, one miller said.</p>
<p>Imported palm oil rose by a rupee at 280/281 rupees per 10 kg on fresh local buying.</p>
<p>&quot;Deals of about 700/800 tonnes for palm oil were reported in the Bombay market on Thursday and fresh enquiries continued today,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In Rajkot spot groundnut oil was steady at 560 rupees per 15 kg.</p>
<p>-- Bombay Commodities +91-22-265 9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
