<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609619" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AFGHANISTAN: Afghan Dostum digs in, seeks talks with mutineers.</title>
<headline>Afghan Dostum digs in, seeks talks with mutineers.</headline>
<byline>Alistair Lyon</byline>
<dateline>SHIBARGHAN, Afghanistan 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Northern Afghan opposition leader General Abdul Rashid Dostum is regrouping after losing a third of his territory to his mutinous second-in-command, his spokesman said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are in a worrying situation now,&quot; General Yousaf (one name) told reporters at the military barracks in Dostum's main headquarters in the north-western town of Shibarghan, capital of Jozjan province.</p>
<p>Yousaf said there had been no fighting between Dostum's forces and those of his former foreign minister and deputy General Abdul Malik, who launched a revolt on Monday.</p>
<p>Malik, apparently acting in collusion with the purist Islamic Taleban militia, which controls the capital Kabul and most of the rest of Afghanistan, seized Maimana, capital of Faryab province, about 125 km (78 miles) south-west of Shibarghan.</p>
<p>Yousaf acknowledged Malik has gained control of all but two districts of Faryab province and had allowed the Taleban to capture the north-western province of Badghis.</p>
<p>Dostum, leader of an anti-Taleban alliance that includes factions loyal to ousted president Burhanuddin Rabbani, had been battling the militant Islamic warriors inconclusively in the remote wastes of Badghis for months.</p>
<p>At the start of the mutiny, Malik captured former Herat provincial governor Ismail Khan, who has been fighting along Dostum's mainly ethnic Uzbek troops in Badghis.</p>
<p>A Taleban spokesman, quoted by a Pakistan-based Afghan news service, said on Friday the militia would prosecute Ismail Khan under Islamic law for his responsibility in the killings of Afghan people, but that there was no hurry to do it.</p>
<p>Yousaf said Malik had defected with roughly 4,000 troops under his command and had effectively neutralised another 1,500 of Dostum's troops who had been caught in the wrong place.</p>
<p>He said there had been no challenge to Dostum's grip over the rest of his territory.</p>
<p>Dostum holds the provinces of Jozjan, Samangan and Balkh and parts of Kunduz and Baghlan.</p>
<p>Yousaf said Rabbani's military chief Ahmad Shah Masood had sent 1,000 men to help Dostum against Malik, but added that the former communist general was not short of troops or weapons.</p>
<p>&quot;We are making military preparations,&quot; he said. &quot;But we don't want to fight Malik. Negotiations are going on.&quot;</p>
<p>He did not spell out the nature of the talks and confirmed that Malik had taken three of Dostum's negotiators captive, but denied reports that one of them was the Uzbek leader's father.</p>
<p>Yousaf voiced scepticism about Malik's sincerity in linking up with the Taleban, who are bent on imposing a strict interpretation of the Islamic Sharia law throughout Afghanistan.</p>
<p>&quot;Has he prayed more than once in his life? Does he know how to read the Koran?&quot; he asked. &quot;He and his brother Ghaffar were founders of (Dostum's faction) Jumbish-i-Milli.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked why Malik had turned against Dostum, Yousaf said: &quot;Only God knows, but we have our ideas.&quot;</p>
<p>Calm reigned in Shibarghan and Mazar-i-Sharif, capital of Balkh province, on Friday, although soldiers with rifles and grenade-launchers were driving around in pick-ups and Dostum's officials were clearly nervous and sometimes hostile towards foreign reporters.</p>
<p>Farmers worked in the green fields along the 130 km (80 miles) of flat road between the two towns, barely glancing up as four of Dostum's tanks rumbled slowly towards Shibarghan, their engines frequently overheating in the sizzling sunshine.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHIBARGHAN, Afghanistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AFGHANISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
