<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609662" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: Cheap imports create chilli glut in Sri Lanka.</title>
<headline>Cheap imports create chilli glut in Sri Lanka.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sri Lankan farmers were stuck with more than 50,000 tonnes of dried chillies as prices for the hot commodity slid sharply due to cheaper imports, the state-owned Daily News said on Friday.</p>
<p>The price of chillies, used extensively in spicey Sri Lankan dishes, has come down to 40 rupees ($0.68) per kg from 90 rupees per kg a few months ago, the paper said.</p>
<p>Current prices did not even cover local farmers' cost of production, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;The price of dried chillies has dropped sharply in the Colombo market due to imports from India by the private sector,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>About two weeks ago, farmers in the island's chilli-growing north-central region burnt some of their harvest in a public protest to demand a guaranteed-price scheme for their produce.</p>
<p>But government officials responsible for purchasing farmers' produce told Reuters that farmers were asking for premium prices when cheaper imports were available in the market.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't have price controls for chillies. Anyone can import chillies and sell it at whatever price they wish,&quot; one official said.</p>
<p>&quot;Naturally, when there are chillies available in the market for 40-50 rupees, the government can't buy from farmers at higer prices,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
