<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609653" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India to discuss oil price rise at Sunday meeting.</title>
<headline>India to discuss oil price rise at Sunday meeting.</headline>
<byline>Hari Ramachandran</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's ruling United Front coalition is expected at a weekend meeting to recommend raising the prices of some oil products to plug a ballooning subsidy bill, politicians and analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral's 15-party ruling alliance meets on Sunday afternoon to consider alternative plans for stemming the rising subsidy bill, they said.</p>
<p>The coalition, ranging from free traders to communists, will seek an agreement on the outlines of a package to tackle runaway subsidies, alliance officials said.</p>
<p>The proposals would then be sent to the government for consideration by Gujral's cabinet. It was not known when the cabinet would meet on the issue.</p>
<p>Both Gujral and Finance Minister P. Chidambaram have said the government must soon decide how to repay money it owes oil companies for selling subsidised petroleum products below market prices.</p>
<p>The outstanding amount, called the oil pool deficit, totalled 155 billion rupees ($4.3 billion) at the end of March.</p>
<p>Newspapers this week said the government had tentatively decided to raise the prices of diesel and kerosene with a plan that would trim about $1.5 billion from the subsidy bill but spare petrol users.</p>
<p>Under the plan, kerosene prices would be increased by 20 percent, while those of high speed diesel and liquified petroleum gas (LPG) would be raised by 15 percent. The price of petrol would remain unchanged.</p>
<p>News reports said Gujral, who is also petroleum minister, had endorsed the plan which would be presented on Sunday.</p>
<p>Left-wing coalition partners oppose any price increases and are especially reluctant to raise the cost of kerosene.</p>
<p>&quot;Oil will be the main subject at the meeting and we will reiterate our position,&quot; said A.B. Bardhan, general secretary of the Communist Party of India (CPI).</p>
<p>Bardhan said proposals focusing on price increases did not spell out ways to dampen demand for oil or limit production of luxury cars which use large amounts of petrol.</p>
<p>&quot;After all it has to be a package of measures,&quot; Bardhan said, adding: &quot;There may be a minimum increase in some items.&quot;</p>
<p>B.G. Verghese of the Centre for Policy Research said: &quot;They may well make some compromise but basically they will have to move to tackle the major problem. Some marginal concessions are possible.&quot;</p>
<p>The Congress party, which provides make-or-break support to Gujral's minority government, acknowledged prices would have to be raised.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices will have to be increased. Which areas and what segments will have to be discussed,&quot; Congress spokesman Vithal Gadgil told Reuters.</p>
<p>Gadgil said Congress had not drafted a proposal and would await the United Front's plan. &quot;Let them come out with a proposal,&quot; Gadgil said, adding that Chidambaram had promised to consult major political parties before taking a final decision.</p>
<p>&quot;They seem to have lot of contradictions among themselves. There is no unanimity,&quot; Gadgil said.</p>
<p>The Petroleum Ministry had been pressing the Finance Ministry to cut import duties on crude and oil products to help trim the subsidy bill. But the Finance Ministry has resisted on the grounds a cut in duties would hit government revenues.</p>
<p>Sanjiv Patni, an oil analyst with securities firm W. I. Carr, said a rise the prices of petroleum products was necessary since world oil prices were firming up. He said a 15 to 20 percent increase would not have a major impact on inflation. ($1 = 35.7 rupees)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
