<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609641" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Bombay exchange plans to go on-line in 100 cities.</title>
<headline>Bombay exchange plans to go on-line in 100 cities.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE) said on Friday it plans to extend its online trading system to 100 cities in June, subject to Department of Telecommunications (DoT) clearance.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect to get DoT clearance on Monday, then within 15 days we will start installing the system at different sites,&quot; BSE,&quot; M.G. Damani, president of the BSE, said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We shall cover 100 cities within the month of June,&quot; Damani said, adding that it depended on DoT approval.</p>
<p>He also said the BSE will stop charging member brokers a 250,000 rupee admission fee if they convert to corporate entities.</p>
<p>Around 440 of the 531 active BSE card holders were either sole-ownership brokerages or partnerships.</p>
<p>&quot;I expect at least 400 of these to corporatise,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Damani said this move was taken to act in line with concessions made in the 1997/98 budget passed by parliament earlier this month, and added that he would seek further concessions from The Securities and Exchange Borad of India (SEBI).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
