<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609646" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEPAL: Nepal communists set to sweep local polls.</title>
<headline>Nepal communists set to sweep local polls.</headline>
<byline>Gopal Sharma</byline>
<dateline>KATHMANDU 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ruling communists were set on Friday to sweep local elections to 4,000 village committees, the Himalayan kingdom's equivalent of local self-governments, officials said.</p>
<p>Elections in 40 districts were held last week and voters in the remaining 35 districts of the kingdom will go to the polls on Monday in the second phase of the local body elections.</p>
<p>About 190,000 representatives will be elected with complete results will be out in two weeks.</p>
<p>The kingdom's Election Commission said initial results from last Saturday's polling showed the communist Unified Marxist-Leninist (UML) party had a big lead over arch-rivals the centrist Nepali Congress party and the Rastriya Prajatantra Party (RPP) of Prime Minister Lokendra Bahadur Chand.</p>
<p>Chand appeared unperturbed by his party's electoral losses.</p>
<p>&quot;We knew that they (UML) are ahead of our party,&quot; Chand told Reuters in an interview on Friday.</p>
<p>A commission official said results for over 20,000 positions were declared with the communists winning about 10,500 places. Congress got 6,000 seats while the RPP won only 2,600 places.</p>
<p>In March, the UML formed a coalition with the RPP, a party which was once close to the monarchy, and replaced an alliance led by the Nepali Congress.</p>
<p>The local elections will not directly affect the national government but are seen as a crucial test of political strength for political parties at the grassroot level.</p>
<p>The Nepali Congress, alleging that Saturday's polls were rigged by the communists, has urged the election commission to cancel the election and hold fresh polls.</p>
<p>&quot;We have demanded that the polls be cancelled,&quot; a Congress spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>Chand said the Election Commission had a right to decide on the matter. &quot;I have tried my best to help electioneering to be free and fair,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Local press reports said rival groups clashed during polling last week and at many places no nomination was filed because of a threat from hardline Maoist communists who are boycotting the elections.</p>
<p>The Maoists are trying to replace multi-party democracy with a government of the working class.</p>
<p>About 10 people were killed in poll-related violence during campaigning or during the election.</p>
<p>About 100 people have been killed in the past 15 months in militancy-related violence since the Maoists launched an insurgency in some remote districts to press for their demand.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NEPAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KATHMANDU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEPAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
