<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609630" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India rupee ends up, tests 35.75 per dlr, RBI buys.</title>
<headline>India rupee ends up, tests 35.75 per dlr, RBI buys.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Indian rupee ended Friday sharply up against the US currency at 35.750/755 per dollar against its previous close of 35.35.790/795, dealers said.</p>
<p>They said the rupee touched 35.75 in trade just before close, its highest point since 35.7475 on May 5.</p>
<p>Dealers said the rupee traded at a high of 35.75 and a low of 35.775 on Friday with most of the day's business done around 35.77 per dollar.</p>
<p>&quot;The rupee tested the 35.75 barrier in late trade but ran into Reserve Bank of India (RBI) intervention at that level,&quot; said a dealer at a private bank.</p>
<p>&quot;RBI bought dollars at around 35.755 but the buying was in very small amounts...$25 million at the most,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dealers said they expected a more serious test of the 35.75 barrier on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the (35.75) mark will be tested in earnest on Monday,&quot; said another dealer. &quot;There was some pretty good dollar selling today and given the supply, we can expect some upward pressure on the rupee on Monday.&quot;</p>
<p>The RBI was however expected to buy dollars more aggressively in case 35.75 looked like breaking, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think today's action (by RBI) was more by way of a signal,&quot; the dealer said. &quot;The market does not really expect 35.75 to be broken, given RBI's actions in the past.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The last time this mark looked like being broken, the RBI hit the market in a big way,&quot; he added. &quot;Given that some liquidity is going out of the system through Wednesday's auction, there is sufficient leeway for the RBI to buy dollars aggressively.&quot;</p>
<p>The RBI auctions 30 billion rupees of government bonds on May 28.</p>
<p>&quot;Earlier, the RBI was worried about the effects of its dollar purchases on domestic monetary expansion,&quot; the dealer said. &quot;But with the bond outflows coming up, they have some leeway.&quot;</p>
<p>Dealers said forward premiums ended marginally up in range-bond trade.</p>
<p>November-delivery dollars ended at a premium of 88/90 paise against the previous close of 86/89, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Premiums opened up on fears of tightening liquidity due to the bond issue,&quot; said a dealer. &quot;But the movement was not much as demand and supply are well-matched at the moment.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Bombay newsroom +91-22-265 9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
