<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609631" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Bombay shares close lower in erratic trade.</title>
<headline>Bombay shares close lower in erratic trade.</headline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares finished lower on Friday as players squared-up positions on the last day of weekly account at the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE), brokers said.</p>
<p>They said a possible increase in oil prices by the government over the weekend discouraged fresh demand.</p>
<p>&quot;There was some stagnation,&quot; said Rasesh Maniar, dealer at brokerage Mukesh Babu Securities. &quot;People know the (oil price) hike is coming and they're waiting.&quot;</p>
<p>The benchmark BSE index dropped 29.92 points, or 0.80 percent, to 3,700.86 off day's high of 3,742.35.</p>
<p>The steering committee of India's 15-party coalition government is scheduled to meet on Sunday to decide on ways to tackle a huge oil pool deficit.</p>
<p>Traders expect the government to raise prices of petroleum products, which India imports but sells at below world prices to domestic customers, to offset the deficit.</p>
<p>Activity was focussed on Tata Iron and Steel Company Ltd (TISCO) ahead of earnings announcement for the year ended March 31, 1997.</p>
<p>The company's board began a meeting at 1000 GMT to finalise the results.</p>
<p>Analysts expect flat-to-lower profits due to weak steel market conditions and higher costs.</p>
<p>Credit Rating Information Services India Ltd shares fell 3.75 rupees to 291.25 after the rating agency said its net profit rose marginally to 76.42 million rupees in 1996/97 (April-March) from 75.71 million a year ago.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
