<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609622" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India TISCO seen better after poor 96/97.</title>
<headline>India TISCO seen better after poor 96/97.</headline>
<byline>Anshuman Daga</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's largest private steel maker on Friday turned in lower than expected annual results but analysts saw better times ahead in financial year 1997/98 (April-March), on hopes of an industrial recovery.</p>
<p>&quot;The sales are mostly in line with expectations, but the net profit is sharply lower,&quot; said Prabhat Awasthi, analyst at SSKI Securities Ltd.</p>
<p>After the close of market hours on Friday, TISCO announced a lower net profit of 4.69 billion rupees for fiscal 1996/97, (April-March) against 4.56 billion the previous year.</p>
<p>Shares of TISCO were traded 5.50 rupees lower at 168.0 in kerb deals after the results were announced. The stock ended at 173.50 rupees at the Bombay Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;Lower-than-expected steel and cement prices led to the poor show,&quot; Awasthi said.</p>
<p>Sales of TISCO rose to 63.51 billion rupees in 1996/97 against 58.54 billion last year.</p>
<p>Lower steel demand, depressed prices and tight margins contributed to the fall in profits, analysts said.</p>
<p>Some analysts said the results were at the bottom end of their expectations.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no major surprises,&quot; said Anurag Mathur, TISCO analyst at Peregrine Capital. &quot;The company was expected to perform badly due to a slowing economy.&quot;</p>
<p>Sluggish steel demand, cheaper imports, and tight money market conditions all coincided with additional capacity coming on line to yield an adverse effect on realisations and margins in the second half of 1996/97, TISCO said.</p>
<p>An expected industrial revival is seen aiding demand for steel, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;From these levels, the flexibity to earnings becomes much higher,&quot; said SSKI's Awasthi. &quot;The only catch is when the economy picks up.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The pressure on margins should ease off. I see profits up 17-18 percent higher in 1997/98,&quot; said Peregrine's Mathur.</p>
<p>TISCO, which has underperformed Bombay's top 30-share index 14 percent this year is expected to continue underperforming the market till the economy shows signs of revival, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The stock will be an underperformer. I don't see demand really picking up till the second half of 1997/98 (April-March), SSKI's Awasthi said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
