<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609635" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Cotton seen stable in Pakistan, firm in India.</title>
<headline>Cotton seen stable in Pakistan, firm in India.</headline>
<dateline>KARACHI, Pakistan 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cotton rates are likely to remain stable in Pakistan next week on low buying by spinners and firm in neighbouring India owing to a shortage of ready stocks, dealers in the two countries said on Friday.</p>
<p>In Pakistan, the rates remained unchanged in the last week and are likely to remain stable in the next week as spinners face a paucity of funds, dealer Nasim Usman at the private Karachi Cotton Association (KCA) said.</p>
<p>The fund shortage is due to a low physical offtake of yarn by yarn users and exporters, he said.</p>
<p>Unsold stocks of more than 826,000 bales (375 lbs each) also kept the market sentiment depressed, the dealer said.</p>
<p>Some exporters showed buying interest in low-quality cotton but their purchases did not push the rates up, he said.</p>
<p>The rates are likely to remain at the current levels as dealers expect 1997/98 (July-June) crop in the last week of June, one broker said.</p>
<p>In the kerb market, the NIAB-78 variety was quoted at 2,050/2,150 rupees per maund, the K-68 at 2,350/2,375 and the MNH-93 at 2,350/2,400.</p>
<p>The KCA said Pakistan had shipped 47,413 bales of cotton by May 12 out of 78,528 booked for export, compared to 1.815 million and 2.32 million bales respectively in the same period a year ago.</p>
<p>Delivery and ginning figures in million bales by May 15 (year-ago figures in brackets) as supplied by the state-run Cotton Export Corp (CEC):</p>
<p>		    Punjab	   Sindh	    Total</p>
<p> Delivery	 6.660 (8.175)  2.084 (1.771)  8.744 (9.947)</p>
<p> Pressed	  6.655 (8.174)  2.084 (1.771)  8.739 (9.946)</p>
<p> Mill sales     5.950 (6.951)  1.944 (1.274)  7.895 (8.225)</p>
<p> Export sales   0.008 (1.023)  0.014 (0.471)  0.022 (1.494)</p>
<p> CEC		nil   (nil)    nil   (nil)    nil   (nil)</p>
<p> Unsold	   0.701 (0.200)  0.125 (0.026)  0.826 (0.226)</p>
<p>KCA-supplied closing prices in rupees per maund (37.32 kg):</p>
<p>		    Friday	   Thursday	 May 16</p>
<p>    NIAB-78     2,146.50	 2,146.50	 2,146.50</p>
<p>    K-68	  2,366.50	 2,366.50	 2,366.50</p>
<p>    MNH-93	2,376.50	 2,376.50	 2,376.50</p>
<p>In India, cotton prices rose in the past week owing to a shortage of ready stock after slow arrivals, dealers said.</p>
<p>The market was closed on Thursday to mark Buddha's birthday.</p>
<p>&quot;Mill buying for fabric purposes remained slow during the week but spinning mills continued to buy as they are seeing higher overseas demand for cotton yarn,&quot; a broker said.</p>
<p>In spot deals, Bengal-deshi rose by 25 to 30 rupees to 925/965 rupees per maund (37.32 kg) while Punjab saw-ginned rose by 50 rupees to 1,650/1,700 rupees. F-414 lifted by 30/40 rupees to 1,940/1,965 rupees per maund.</p>
<p>Daily arrivals of cotton in India's Punjab region dropped during the week to 1,000 to 1,200 bales (170 kg each) against an earlier average of 2,000/3,000 bales a day.</p>
<p>Manubhai Amarsey, a leading dealer, said there was a shortage of good-quality cotton owing to which millers bought lower and average grades for blending.</p>
<p>Gujarat varieties also extended gains during the week amid dwindling supplies.</p>
<p>Gujarat Kalyan (medium-staple) rose by 300 rupees to 14,000/14,500 rupees per candy (355.56 kg) while long-staple Gujarat Sankar-4 lifted to 18,000/21,000 rupees per candy from 17,000/20,000 rupees.</p>
<p>-- Karachi Newsroom 9221-5685192</p>
<p>-- Bombay Commodities +91-22-265 9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARACHI, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
