<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609697" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Boeing calling for inspections of 747 fuel tanks.</title>
<headline>Boeing calling for inspections of 747 fuel tanks.</headline>
<byline>Martin Wolk</byline>
<dateline>SEATTLE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Boeing Co plans to ask airlines around the world to inspect their 747 jet aircraft for possible fuel tank problems in the latest effort to find out why TWA Flight 800 crashed last year.</p>
<p>A Boeing spokesman said Friday the aircraft manufacturer would issue a service bulletin next month asking for voluntary inspections of the center fuel tanks on all of the more than 1,000 jumbo jets in service.</p>
<p>&quot;This is one more way of gathering information that may shed some more light on the situation,&quot; Boeing spokesman Russ Young said.</p>
<p>Boeing had already inspected 10 of the jumbo jets and found no problems, but decided to broaden the inspection in an effort to detect any abnormalities that may have contributed to the July 17 crash.</p>
<p>The cause of the crash is still unknown, but after nearly 10 months of investigation FBI director Louis Freeh said this month the agency was leaning toward the conclusion that a &quot;catastrophic mechanical failure&quot; caused the jet to explode less than 12 minutes after takeoff.</p>
<p>Authorities believe the plane exploded when something ignited fuel vapors in the nearly empty center tank between the wings.</p>
<p>In a Telex sent to all 747 operators, Boeing noted that the aircraft are designed to &quot;preclude ignition sources in the fuel system.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Our experience indicates that the protective features built into the fuel system are effective for the service life of the airplane,&quot; Boeing said in the Telex.</p>
<p>The National Transportation Safety Board, which is heading the Flight 800 investigation, has called for center fuel tank improvements, but so far the Federal Aviation Administration has declined to act, saying there is no evidence of any defect.</p>
<p>Boeing said it would send out a service bulletin soon covering all the approximately 1,000 Boeing 747s in service around the world, including the current 747-400 models. The bulletin formally will ask airlines to make voluntary checks of the fuel tank wiring, pumps, fuel lines and fittings for signs of corrosion, wear or abnormality.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not anything specific that we're looking for,&quot; Young said, adding that the results of the inspections would be shared with federal authorities investigating the crash.</p>
<p>TWA Flight 800 was one of the oldest 747-100 models, having gone into service in 1971.,</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEATTLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
