<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609669" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan hopes for new IMF loan before September.</title>
<headline>Pakistan hopes for new IMF loan before September.</headline>
<byline>Tahir Ikram</byline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistan hopes to get a new medium term loan or enhanced structural adjustment facility (ESAF) from the International Monetary Fund (IMF) before September, Finance Minister Sartaj Aziz said on Friday.</p>
<p>Aziz, who was talking by telephone to Reuters Financial Television in Tokyo and was monitored in Islamabad, said under the ESAF Pakistan could get $1.2 billion to $1.5 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be somewhere between $1.2 to $1.5 billion but the exact amount will be determined once the IMF board considers the position and the arrangements that are agreed with the (IMF) staff,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Once our budget is presented the Fund will come here in July and if all goes well, we could wrap it up before September,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Pakistan budget for fiscal 1997/98 (July-June) is due to be announced on June 14.</p>
<p>Aziz said the IMF was supportive of the economic reforms undertaken by the three-month old government of Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of our structural reforms are very, very far-reaching and they are quite comprehensive also and they go beyond the expectations of even the IMF,&quot; Aziz said.</p>
<p>Pakistan's inability to meet agreed targets prompted the IMF to halt a standby loan after Sharif took power following his February election triumph.</p>
<p>&quot;Over the last two years, Pakistan has experienced a severe aggravation of its macroeconomic imbalances,&quot; an IMF official told donors at the Aid-to-Pakistan Consortium meeting in Paris last month.</p>
<p>IMF Deputy Managing Director Stanley Fischer said in Tokyo this week that Sharif's economic reforms had a good chance of working.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that if they get everything done that they would like to get done and that they've agreed to with us, there's a very good chance of it working,&quot; Fischer said.</p>
<p>An IMF mission visited Islamabad last week to set broad macroeconomic targets for 1997/98 in consultation with officials preparing the June 14 budget.</p>
<p>The IMF loan would be used for balance of payment support.</p>
<p>Aziz said Pakistan's balance of payment gap was six percent of GDP and the government was aiming to reduce it to five percent of GDP in 1997/98.</p>
<p>Last week Hafeez Pasha, deputy chairman of the Planning Commission, put this year's current account deficit at $4.0-4.5 billion, against last year's $4.244 billion, and forecast a trade gap of $3 billion, compared to last year's $3.6 billion.</p>
<p>Domestic bank borrowing may top 100 billion rupees by the end of 1996/97 (July-June), against an original 29.7 billion target, said one senior official, who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>($1 = 40.43 rupees)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
