<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609713" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: General Parcel to buy four trucking firms.</title>
<headline>General Parcel to buy four trucking firms.</headline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>General Parcel Services Inc said Friday that it has signed non-binding letters of intent to acquire four privately held trucking companies for $30 million to $35 million in cash and stock.</p>
<p>The company said the proposed acquisitions involve profitable short- and long-haul trucking companies in the southeastern United States which have combined annual revenues of about $100 million.</p>
<p>The acquisitons, said General Parcel, should close in the third quarter, subject to due diligence, arrangement of financing and other customary terms and conditions.  </p>
<p>The company said its acquisition criteria remain focused on mid-size trucking companies, mainly those with annual revenues between $10 million and $100 million.</p>
<p>The company also said that it has agreed to a debt- for-equity conversion that will virtually eliminate its long-term debt other than that for equipment, which it believes will be eliminated by the fourth quarter.  </p>
<p>The company said that T. Wayne Davis, chairman of the board and majority shareholder, and his affiliates have agreed to assume about $5 million of company debt in exchange for the issuance of about 2.86 million shares of new common stock.</p>
<p>General Parcel also said that it has agreed to divest its courier operations, which yield $1 million in annual revenues, to Davis as part of the debt-for-equity exchange.</p>
<p>Final determination of the amounts involved in the exchange are expected to be completed by June 30.</p>
<p>In the coming months the company said it intends to make further changes in its remaining parcel delivery operations, either reducing their size to a level that can achieve profitability or eliminating them through sale or discontinuation.</p>
<p>The company will also change its name to Transit Group Inc effective June 30.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
