<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609701" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Toronto stocks seen opening higher, light trade.</title>
<headline>Toronto stocks seen opening higher, light trade.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CHANGE				    CHANGE</p>
<p>TSE(CLS)  6336.02   +22.89   HI 6336.02	    LO  6309.86</p>
<p>DJI(CLS)  7258.13   -32.56   GOLD (LONDON)   US$341.65 -1.15</p>
<p>FTSE100   4657.60    +5.80   GOLD (NY-COMEX) US$342.40 -1.00</p>
<p>NIKKEI   20009.00  +131.61   LME CASH NICKEL US$7485    -5.0</p>
<p>CANDLR     1.3720		LME CASH ALUM   US$1606   -26.5</p>
<p>CAN 30-YR  111.50     0.05   BRENT CRUDE     US$20.07  -0.11</p>
<p>--------------------MARKET COMMENT----------------------------</p>
<p>* Toronto stocks were expected to continue to climb at the</p>
<p>open, breaking through the record session high of 6348.02. *</p>
<p>Trading should be thin ahead of the U.S. holiday weekend.</p>
<p>Toronto stocks were expected to continue to climb at the open on Friday and analysts said the index could break through the record session high of 6348.02 reached March 11.</p>
<p>&quot;We closed at the session high and at a record closing level, that's bullish... so we're looking for a positive day today, break above 6348, and we'll see how high we go,&quot; said MMS International technical analyst Katherine Beattie.</p>
<p>She said the market will be boosted by a seasonal bias as U.S. players secure investments ahead of the U.S. Memorial Day holiday weekend, which will also lighten session volumes.  </p>
<p>&quot;Volume is going to be light because a lot of U.S. participants are already on holiday,&quot; Beattie said.</p>
<p>The U.S. bond market will close early at 1400 EDT/1900 GMT ahead of the holiday.</p>
<p>Beattie said gold remains a market negative but bullish sentiment elsewhere should offset the sector's weakness.</p>
<p>&quot;Gold is under pressure, (prices are) down over a dollar, and that's going to be a weakness that's going to weigh on the gold sector, but it shouldn't be a heavy weight on the TSE 300,&quot; Beattie said.</p>
<p>The Toronto Stock Exchange's key 300 composite index rose 22.89 points on Thursday to close at 6336.02, erasing the last record closing high of 6332.87 set on March 10.</p>
<p>Bankruptcies in Canada rose to 8,147 in March from 7,775 a year earlier, the Department of Consumer and Corporate Affairs said on Friday. Statistics Canada said Canadian operating profits in the first quarter of 1997 increased 3.3 percent to a record C$25.5 billion.</p>
<p>--- STOCKS TO WATCH ---</p>
<p>* BC Sugar Refinery Ltd said its board has recommended shareholders reject the C$15 a share takeover offer by Balaclava Enterprises Ltd.</p>
<p>((Andrea Hopkins at Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8102 or e-mail andrea.hopkins@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
