<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609756" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US corp bond mart calm,players get set for holiday.</title>
<headline>US corp bond mart calm,players get set for holiday.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A quiet day is on tap for the corporate bond primary market as players head out early during a shortened session ahead of the U.S. Memorial Day holiday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be a real snoozer today,&quot; said one high-grade syndicate source. &quot;There are very few players around so if you don't see anything in the first hour get done you're not going to see it.&quot;</p>
<p>PSA The Bond Market Trade Association has recommended an early 1400 EDT/1800 GMT close for the U.S. Treasury and fixed-income markets. On Monday, U.S. financial markets will remain closed in observance of the Memorial Day holiday.  </p>
<p>On Thursday, about $1.0 billion in high-yield debt was sold in the primary market with still more business on tap for the coming weeks, dealers said.</p>
<p>So far on Friday, Brooks Fiber Properties BFPT.O), a full service provider of local telecommunications services, set $250 million in 10-year 144A notes at +327 over U.S. Treasuries.</p>
<p>The deal was increased from an initial size of $200 million and was jointly underwritten by Salomon Brothers and Merrill Lynch &amp; Co, dealers said.  </p>
<p>Also, Magnum Hunter Resources sold $140 million in 10-year 144A senior notes to yield 10 percent via BT Securities, sources said. The deal was increased from an original size of $125 million, they addes.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, several more high-yield issues are slated to come to market, one of which is Intercel Inc. The firm is expected to issue $300 million in 10-year 144A senior notes via Morgan Stanley, sources said.</p>
<p>Among other upcoming offerings, Lehman Brothers is expected to underwrite the following two new capital securities deals, sources said.  </p>
<p>Elsewhere, the calendar for high-grade issues is building with several offerings slated to come to market next week, syndicate sources said.</p>
<p>Among upcoming debt offerings Tandy Corp, a Fort Worth, Texas-based retailer of consumer electronics and computers, is expected to tap the market with a $200 million 10-year debt issue via Bear Stearns &amp; Co, sources said.</p>
<p>Briggs &amp; Stratton Corp, a maker of engines for lawn and garden equipment, is also expected to sell $100 million in 10-year debt and $75 million in five-year debt via Credit Suisse First Boston, sources said.</p>
<p>Another $600 million three-part debt offering from Hartford Life is expected to hit the market next week, sources said. The deal is expected to include seven-year, 10-year and 30-year maturities, they said.</p>
<p>In the government market, the 30-year U.S. Treasury bond is trading up 1/32 at 95-15/32 to yield 6.99 percent.</p>
<p>(( -- Nancy Leinfuss, 212-859-1675 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I64800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
