<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609711" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FULL TEXT -- Price Comms, Palmer Wireless.</title>
<headline>FULL TEXT -- Price Comms, Palmer Wireless.</headline>
<text>
<p>Palmer Wireless agreed to be acquired by Price Communications Corp for $17.50 per share in cash, the companies said on Friday. The agreement is expected to close in the fourth quarter of the year subject to FCC and regulatory approval.</p>
<p>A full text of the company's press release follows.</p>
<p>----------------------Press Release---------------------------</p>
<p>FT. MYERS, Fla., May 23 /PRNewswire/ -- Palmer Wireless, Inc. (Nasdaq: PWIR) today announced that it has reached a definitive agreement to be acquired by Price Communications Corporation (AMEX: PR) for $17.50 per share in cash, for an aggregate purchase price of $880 million, including repayment of debt.  The agreement, which is subject to FCC and regulatory approval, is expected to close in the fourth quarter of this year.  Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co. advised Palmer Wireless on the transaction.</p>
<p>Palmer Wireless, headquartered in Ft. Myers, Florida, owns and operates 18 non-wireline cellular telephone systems in Florida, Alabama, Georgia and South Carolina covering a total estimated population of 3.9 million pops and over 320,000 subscribers.  All of the Company's systems are part of the North American Cellular Network (NACN) and are Cellular One affiliates.</p>
<p>In commenting on the announcement, William J. Ryan, President and Chief Executive Officer of Palmer Wireless stated: &quot;We are very pleased to announce this agreement to join Price Communications.  Since our initial public offering in March 1995, we have significantly increased the size and scope of our operations, and have strived to maximize value to all our shareholders. Price Communications is an outstanding company and we are pleased that it has recognized the value of our markets, operations and employees.  We look forward to continuing to grow the Company under the Cellular One, Price Communications Cellular and Palmer Wireless banners.&quot;</p>
<p>Bob Price, President of Price Communications Corporation said, &quot;We are highly pleased to be successful in acquiring Palmer Wireless and its superior management team headed by Bill Ryan, President and CEO.  We share in the belief that we can provide everything that PCS has promised to provide.  We look forward to a closing this fall, following the necessary regulatory approvals.&quot; SOURCE  Palmer Wireless, Inc.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
