<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609702" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canadian dollar opens weaker on profit-taking.</title>
<headline>Canadian dollar opens weaker on profit-taking.</headline>
<text>
<p>FORECAST RANGE   1.3725/1.3780	    ASIAN CLOSE     1.3749</p>
<p>RESISTANCE 1.3630   SUPPORT 1.3800	HI 1.3773   LO  1.3738</p>
<p>CANADA OPEN  1.3749/54    HI 1.3773     EUROPE OPEN     1.3748</p>
<p>PREV CLOSE   1.3730/35    LO 1.3738     HI 1.3762   LO  1.3752</p>
<p>---------------------MARKET COMMENT--------------------------</p>
<p>* Canada's dollar opened weaker in light trading on Friday at C$1.3752 (US$0.7271) as overseas investors continued to take profits in last night's trading session, dealers said.</p>
<p>* They said Japanese investors unloaded Canadian assets as the yen gained considerable strength against the Canadian and Australian dollars.  </p>
<p>&quot;The market will watch the Aussie dollar and the Canada (dollar) together, so you're seeing the mid-level currencies taking a hit here,&quot; said Reid Farrill, corporate foreign exchange adviser for CIBC Wood Gundy.</p>
<p>Some analysts also speculated that renewed talk of the Quebec separation issue in Canada's general election campaign might be causing some market nervousness toward the Canadian dollar.</p>
<p>The western-based Reform Party and the Quebec separatist Bloc Quebecois party in the past week have upped their efforts to make national unity the bellwether issue of the election.  </p>
<p>&quot;It may well be this focus on the separation issue that is prompting some offshore players to cut their Canada holdings a bit, especially in light of the imminent long weekend in both the U.S. and London,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;If you don't live here, you're saying 'what the hell is going on in Canada,'&quot; the trader added.</p>
<p>Markets are closed on Monday for Memorial Day in the United States and a bank holiday in Great Britain.</p>
<p>Analysts said they expected markets to wind down early today, which could produce some &quot;erratic moves&quot; by the Canada dollar in morning trade.  </p>
<p>Farrill said the Canada dollar had probably reached the end of its &quot;unwinding&quot; following the U.S. Federal Reserve decision on Tuesday to hold interest rates steady.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we're pretty well finished (the downward trend), and corporate Canada will be a very active seller of Canadian dollars as this thing approaches C$1.3800 (US$0.7246),&quot; Farrill said.</p>
<p>On the crosses, the Canadian dollar fell to 84.20 yen from Thursday's close of 84.52 and dipped to 1.2316 marks from Thursday's 1.2342 marks.</p>
<p>((Paul Simao, Reuters Toronto Bureau (416) 941-8104))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
