<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609709" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canadian T-bills open firmer amid steady dollar.</title>
<headline>Canadian T-bills open firmer amid steady dollar.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canadian T-bills opened mostly firmer on Friday amid stronger Canadian and U.S. bond markets, steady trade in the Canadian dollar and good interest from accounts, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a little bit better tone in U.S. fixed-income markets this morning. And relative to where the Canadian dollar was trading last night it's doing slightly better here this morning,&quot; said Doug Sannuto, managing director of Canada cash markets with Bank of Montreal.</p>
<p>Canada's three-month when-issued T-bill firmed to yield 2.99 percent from 3.01 percent at Thursday's close.  </p>
<p>&quot;We're seeing some demand from customers this morning,&quot; said Sannuto.</p>
<p>Canadian T-bills firmed as the currency strengthened past Thursday's close of C$1.3730 (US$0.7283) after initially beginning the session weaker.</p>
<p>The Canadian money market also benefitted from firmer U.S. Treasuries, which began the session firmer ahead of an early close at 1400 EDT/1800 GMT.</p>
<p>In other prices, the six-month when-issued T-bill firmed to yield 3.34 percent from 3.36 percent. The one-year T-bill firmed to yield 3.71 percent from 3.74 percent.  </p>
<p>The call loan rate traded at 2.95 percent, the center of the Bank of Canada's 2.75-3.25 percent target range.</p>
<p>((Jeffrey Hodgson (416) 941-8105, e-mail: jeffrey.hodgson@reuters.com))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
