<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609769" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CSCE coffee called to open 1.00 cent higher.</title>
<headline>CSCE coffee called to open 1.00 cent higher.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>CSCE coffee futures were called to open 1.00 cent higher Friday, although some traders said the market could come under some pressure during the day as players take profits ahead of the extended holiday weekend.</p>
<p>CSCE will be closed Monday in observance of U.S. Memorial Day.</p>
<p>New York arabica futures rose sharply for the second straight session Thursday, with the two nearby months hitting new lifetime highs, as speculators continued to buy. July ended up 7.20 cents at 260.30 cents a lb after ranging from 265.00 to 254.00. Second-month September gained 4.90 to 229.95 cents, while the outer months finished 0.35 to 3.70 better.</p>
<p>The July/September switch ballooned to 30.35 cents compared with 28.05 cents at the close on Wednesday.</p>
<p>On the charts, traders pegged July near-term support at 256.60 cents, followed by 250.00 and 239.00. On the upside, July's new lifetime high of 265.00 cents was seen as resistance.</p>
<p>Traders are continuing their weather watch in top-grower Brazil. Much colder weather are moving into Brazil's coffee belt, but no damaging cold is expected, private forecaster Weather Services Corp said Friday. Low temperatures will be in the 40s to low 50s F, they said.</p>
<p>In other news, Association of Coffee Producing Countries' (ACPC) secretary general Robeiro Oliveira Silva said on Friday that world coffee supplies are likely to stay tight until September.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect a certain tightness in the market especially for the period from July to September,&quot; Silva told reporters on the margins of the International Coffee Organisation talks in London.</p>
<p>After Thursday's close, CSCE reported certified coffee stocks fell by 1,500 bags, to 49,712 bags as of May 21. There was no coffee pending grading, the exchange said.</p>
<p>London July robusta futures were mostly firmer at midday Friday, after early weakness. LIFFE July rose $7 at the break, to $2,089, after sinking to a low of $2,065.</p>
<p>The London market will also be closed Monday for a holiday.</p>
<p>((--Patricia Avidan, New York Commodity Desk 212-859-1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
