<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609784" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US Treasuries open higher on shortened trading day.</title>
<headline>US Treasuries open higher on shortened trading day.</headline>
<byline>Ellen Freilich</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Treasury prices opened higher on Friday in what will be a shortened trading session ahead of the three-day Memorial Day holiday weekend.</p>
<p>Trading is expected to be quiet, participants said.</p>
<p>&quot;This could be one of the more quiet days thus far in 1997,&quot; said Kevin Flanagan, first vice president and money market economist at Dean Witter Reynolds. &quot;There's no data of consequence. And there really aren't any looming on the horizon.  Next week you get April durables and the Chicago PMI and the (two- and five-year Treasury note) auctions.&quot;  </p>
<p>&quot;We're really a couple of weeks away from getting fresh economic statistics for May,&quot; Flanagan said. &quot;And that's what we neeed as a catalyst to move us out of this training range.</p>
<p>&quot;With the two o'clock close and the unofficial start of summer (on Memorial Day), it's going to be a very, very quiet session,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At the open, the benchmark 30-year Treasury bond was up 6/32 to 95-20/32, yielding 6.98 percent, versus 6.99 percent at Thursday's close.</p>
<p>At the shorter end of the yield curve, the two-year Treasury note was up 1/32 to 100-9/32, yielding 6.23 percent.  </p>
<p>Kim Rupert, senior economist at MMS International, said trading is likely to be &quot;fairly lackluster and quiet heading into the long weekend.</p>
<p>&quot;After this week's activity, everybody is wanting to go home, close out a position and leave,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Rupert said the market is maintaining a bit of a bid with the dollar relatively stable.  But she said she did not anticipate significant price movements and the market, if anything, would be technically driven.</p>
<p>Fed Governor Laurence Meyer is scheduled to speak in the afternoon, she noted, but is unlikely to move the market.  </p>
<p>Noting the firming trend in overseas trade earlier, Rupert cited a &quot;fairly large buyer of two-year notes in Japan and some interest in the middle of the yield curve during the European session.&quot;</p>
<p>Flanagan also saw &quot;a little bit of buying overseas, though nothing dramatic.&quot;</p>
<p>Looking ahead, Rupert said the Treasury's two- and five-year note auctions would probably highlight the Treasury market's schedule next week.</p>
<p>The Treasury will sell $16.5 billion in two-year notes on Wednesday and $12.0 billion in five-year notes on Thursday.  </p>
<p>&quot;I don't foresee a real problem with either of the auctions,&quot; Rupert said.  &quot;We will probably back up a little before then.  But I think the two-year auction will go off fairly well in the 6.25 (percent yield) area.&quot;</p>
<p>In early trade, 10-year notes traded at 99-9/32, up 6/32, to yield 6.73 percent.  Five-year notes traded at 100-8/32, up 3/32, to yield 6.56 percent.</p>
<p>Three-month bill rates were down three basis points to 5.01 percent.  Six-month rates were down one basis point to 5.22 percent.  Year bill rates were down one basis point to 5.52 percent. ((--North American Treasury Desk 212 859 1679))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
