<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609761" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Chart House says Kuntz to resign in June.</title>
<headline>Chart House says Kuntz to resign in June.</headline>
<dateline>SOLANA BEACH, Calif. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chart House Enterprises Inc said Friday Chief Financial Officer William Kuntz Jr., who has been acting as interim president and chief executive officer, plans to resign in June.</p>
<p>The company said he will be replaced as CFO by James Wendler, who is currently vice president and chief accounting officer.</p>
<p>The company said Stephen McGillin, executive vice president of operations, will become acting president.  </p>
<p>In a statement, Kuntz said that this is the &quot;right time&quot; for him to leave the company, and that he knew his role would be &quot;an interim one&quot; when he assumed responsibilities of president and chief executive in November.</p>
<p>In November, the company announced Kuntz was assuming some of the responsibilities of the resigning president and chief executive for an interim period.</p>
<p>The company also said its shareholders have approved the issuing of 3.4 million shares of common stock at $5.75 per share to Chart House Investors LLC, an affiliate of Equity Group Investments Inc.</p>
<p>Equity is a privately held investment company headed by Sam Zell.</p>
<p>The proceeds from the sale of shares will be applied to repay existing indebtedness.</p>
<p>Chart House operates 64 restaurants in the United States, the U.S. Virgin Islands and Puerto Rico.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I66100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOLANA BEACH, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
