<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609860" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: EASIER GREEK MONEY POLICY MAY SLOW DISINFLATION-BOA.</title>
<headline>EASIER GREEK MONEY POLICY MAY SLOW DISINFLATION-BOA.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greek monetary policy easing, as indicated by shrinking inflation-adjusted rates, may inhibit faster disinflation in the absence of measures to deal with the structural budget deficit, said Bank of America in its 1997 outlook.</p>
<p>&quot;While the monetary ease has not yet affected the drachma, it may become an obstacle to faster disinflation in the absence of structural fiscal consolidation,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;A de facto monetary ease is indicated by the fact that real debt yields have also plunged and are now lower than our Mediterranean counterparts as well as most of the EU.&quot;</p>
<p>Inflation-adjusted interest rates on 12-month T-bills stood at 3.4 percent compared to 4.8 percent for Italy, 3.2 percent for Spain and 1.8 percent for Germany, it said.</p>
<p>Inflation-adjusted yields on Greek three-year fixed coupon bonds were 3.3 percent versus 4.7 percent for Italian three-year paper, 3.6 percent for Spanish paper and 2.6 percent for German three-year instruments.</p>
<p>Inflation-adjusted yields on Greek five-year fixed coupon bonds stood at 3.0 percent, 5.0 percent for Italian bonds, 4.0 percent for Spanish bonds and 3.2 percent for German bonds.</p>
<p>Greece's seven-year fixed coupon bonds featured an inflation-adjusted yield of 2.8 percent against 5.1 percent for Italian bonds, 4.3 percent for Spanish bonds and 3.9 percent for Germany, it added.</p>
<p>&quot;Current inflation in respective country has been deducted from nominal rates, as of May 20, 1997,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>Consumer price inflation stood at 5.9 percent year-on-year in April. The economy is beginning to enter the post-stabilisation period and will become more susceptible to internal and external shocks and financial markets are likely to be more volatile.</p>
<p>&quot;The biggest potential domestic shock may be that financial euphoria itself misleads policy makers into inaction or incomplete action on the critically needed structural reforms of the labour market, as well as tax, regulatory and pension reform,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>The EMU timetable and the next tightening of global monetary conditions were the main sources of external shock, the report said.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly, success rests not only on the reservoir of political courage left to push through such reforms, but also on some good luck from the external environment,&quot; it said. --Dimitris Kontogiannis, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
