<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609867" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FOCUS- PARIBAS SELLS BANK PARIBAS BELGIUM TO BACOB.</title>
<headline>FOCUS- PARIBAS SELLS BANK PARIBAS BELGIUM TO BACOB.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French financial holding company Paribas said on Friday it planned to sell Banque Paribas Belgique to Belgium's Bacob-Arco group in a deal which was set to reinforce Bacob's role in Belgian banking.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Paribas declined to give financial details but said the deal would produce a capital gain for the French group, whose strategy is to focus on investment banking and specialised financial services.</p>
<p>It said it planned to sell 47 percent of its Belgian unit to Bacob-Arco, topping the latter's existing 3.6 percent holding, and said that Bacob-Arco would offer to buy out minority holders, which could take its stake in Paribas Belgique to 70 percent.</p>
<p>Paribas would keep the remaining 30 percent but could later sell this to Bacob-Arco, it said.</p>
<p>Paribas shares were trading 0.86 percent higher at 0915 GMT, at 400.4 francs each, while the CAC-40 leading French share index was up 0.18 percent. Bacob, a cooperative bank, is not listed, although ranks seventh in Belgium in terms of total assets.</p>
<p>Paribas Belgique, which employs 1,400 staff and 50 agencies in Belgium, is mainly active in commercial banking and made a profit of four billion Belgian francs ($114.6 million) in 1996, Paribas said. It is Belgium's eighth largest bank.</p>
<p>&quot;Banque Bacob has a strong position in the Belgian retail banking market, notably in the non-profit making organisation, repo and securitisation sectors,&quot; said the statement issued on behalf of both groups. The deal would &quot;allow a new leading Belgian bank entity to be created&quot;, it said .</p>
<p>Banque Bacob, the most important subsidiary of Bacob-Arco, earned net income of 3.1 billion Belgian francs in 1996 and it has 3,600 staff in 562 agencies.</p>
<p>&quot;The new group would allow the two institutions to develop synergies and to reinforce the quality of client service, while respecting each individual entity's business culture,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;This acquisition would let Groupe Arco extend and diversify its banking activities. It would allow Banque Bacob...to consolidate its leading position in Belgium's retail banking market and to extend its activities on the international financial markets,&quot; said the statement.</p>
<p>&quot;This proposed operation is in keeping with Paribas' strategy to strengthen further its focus on its core businesses, international investment banking and specialised financial services.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Paribas intends to continue, on behalf of its large clients, its international investment banking (business) in Belgium. To achieve this aim, it would create a branch in Belgium and would use the name Paribas,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>It said the deal was subject to regulatory approvals and the successful completion of current negotiations, expected to last three months.</p>
<p>Banque Paribas Belgique is 63.3 percent held by Groupe Paribas, via its 100 percent owned Paribas International unit and another 14.1 percent is held by Cobepa, a 64.9 percent-owned subsidiary of Compagnie Financiere de Paribas.</p>
<p>In February, Paribas Belgique chief executive officer Philippe Romagnoli said the Belgian banking scene was overly fragmented and needed to see the emergence of some larger players.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
