<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609834" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Oil consumers urge &quot;realism&quot; in climate talks.</title>
<headline>Oil consumers urge &quot;realism&quot; in climate talks.</headline>
<byline>Richard Mably</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Energy ministers from the world's leading industrial powers on Friday called for a balance between &quot;ambition and realism&quot; in setting targets for the reduction of noxious emissions believed to cause global warming.</p>
<p>International Energy Agency (IEA) ministers also committed themselves to finding concrete strategies for cutting pollution in the run-up to a climate change summit in Japan this year.</p>
<p>The Paris-based IEA, which draws its membership from the Organisation of Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), also called on larger developing nations to play their part in the fight to restrain output of heat-trapping greenhouse gases.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to make a difficult trade-off between ambition and realism,&quot; IEA chairman and Dutch economic affairs minister Hans Wijers told a news conference.</p>
<p>IEA ministers must devise and implement energy policies that were &quot;realistic, achievable and cost-effective,&quot; said an IEA statement released after a half day of ministerial talks.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to think about the large developing countries,&quot; said Wijers. &quot;They have to be involved somewhere.&quot;</p>
<p>About 150 nations are trying to negotiate legally binding cuts in greenhouse gases in a deal to be signed in Kyoto, Japan, in December.</p>
<p>The initiative follows up the 1992 Rio de Janeiro Earth Summit that committed developed countries to reducing carbon dioxide emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
<p>Most of the IEA's 24 member countries will fail to meet their Rio targets.</p>
<p>IEA chairman Wijers said ministers had agreed it was time to examine concrete methods for emissions cuts in harness with industry.</p>
<p>He said U.S. Energy Secretary Federico Pena wanted to hammer out guidelines on: &quot;Who is going to do what, where, when and at what expense.&quot;</p>
<p>So far only European Union nations have shown their hand, proposing a 15 percent cut in emissions from 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
<p>The United States, easily the world's largest energy consumer, has committed itself to seeking binding targets but has not yet proposed any level.</p>
<p>The IEA said its 24 ministers agreed that emissions trading, allowing countries to barter emissions credits or implement projects that reduce emissions in developing nations, should be given careful consideration.</p>
<p>The U.S. backs emissions trading as a way of getting the private sector involved but the scheme has been condemned by environmentalists as a cop-out.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be very complicated to make emissions trading measurable and open to account,&quot; said IEA executive director Robert Priddle. &quot;There is a long way to go yet to see whether it is a practical option.&quot;</p>
<p>There was agreement in principle that an end to subsidies and higher taxation on fossil fuels were one key response to climate change. But there was no commitment to concrete action on that score.</p>
<p>Ministers renewed their call for maintenance of sufficient strategic oil reserves to protect against the possibility of a shortage on international markets.</p>
<p>&quot;Oil security remains a concern, particularly given the prospect of increasing import dependence ... and the increasing concentration of remaining oil reserves in the Middle East,&quot; they said in a statement.</p>
<p>The IEA was set up in 1974 originally to defend consumers against huge oil price rises, but has since developed into a specialist thinktank under the auspices of the OECD.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="OECD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
