<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609873" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Wall Street boosts European stocks.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Wall Street boosts European stocks.</headline>
<byline>Malcolm Davidson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Major European bourses firmed on Friday, underpinned by a firm start on Wall Street, while the dollar searched for direction following a volatile week against the yen.</p>
<p>U.S. shares bounced ahead in early trade, adding more than 40 points in the first 30 minutes and reversing Thursday's weakness.</p>
<p>Traders said shares prices rallied because the long bond looked reluctant to push through a seven percent yield level, small-capitalisation stocks were strong and economic growth appeared moderate.</p>
<p>In Europe French stocks made some of the best gains, rising nearly 0.7 percent on the last trading day before Sunday's first round of national parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>Although publication of opinion polls is banned in France ahead of the elections, dealers said a Swiss newspaper survey boosted sentiment among Paris investors.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is reacting to the poll published in the Tribune de Geneve, but we're advising people to protect themselves against an adverse reaction on Monday,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>By 1400 GMT the CAC 40 index was showing gains of nearly 16 points to just under 2,757.</p>
<p>Traders said the top gainers were stocks hit hardest on Thursday, when the CAC lost 1.6 percent. Michelin recovered 4.32 percent and Renault 1.96 percent.</p>
<p>Elf was up 1.63 percent after announcing the buyback of two million Elf shares sold by UAP. It also bought back Elf shares sold by Renault.</p>
<p>German shares hurdled the important 3,600 level, ending floor trade up 22.77 points at 3,602.19 points. In later screen-based trade, the IBIS DAX index was up about 30 points at 3,605.</p>
<p>Traders said the market was boosted by two German state inflation reports that showed higher prices in May on a monthly basis but failed to ignite fears about inflation growth.</p>
<p>Firmer German debt prices and a higher dollar also helped to underpin the market.</p>
<p>Carmaker Volkswagen AG ended up 13 marks at 1,140 marks after briefly pushing through technical resistance at 1,150 marks.</p>
<p>Dresdner Bank, Germany's second largest bank, gained 1.02 marks to 62.82 marks after saying it was optimistic of higher full-year results following a 10 percent rise in first quarter profits.</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 index edged modestly higher in the afternoon after Wall Street provided a boost before a long holiday weekend.</p>
<p>The index was 11 points up at 4,663 by 1400 GMT, having touched 4,672.1 in early trade.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking good although there's not much real business about. It's really just market makers doing their business before the long weekend,&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>Firmer gilts and selected sectors led the market higher. Bank shares pushed up after city bookmakers set a grey market price of 700p a share for the Halifax Building Society when it comes to market on June 2.</p>
<p>On the currency front, the dollar idled around 1.69 marks and well shy of 116 yen as the unit struggled to find direction after a week of sharp volatility.</p>
<p>&quot;The big structural change has been the tightening in liquidity across markets after the yen's appreciation. For the dollar, the big question is whether this has been it in terms of liquidation and whether its going to try to stabilise,&quot; said Sheen Shipley, International economist at CS First Boston.</p>
<p>&quot;I still think we're in the exhaustion mode after the breathtaking move down in dollar/yen,&quot; said Bob Near, vice president on the corporate foreign exchange desk at Bank of New York. &quot;The holiday here and in London on Monday is just a prescription for a do-nothing market.&quot;</p>
<p>Remarks from key Japanese Ministry of Finance official Eisuke Sakakibara, who was interviewed in French newspaper Le Monde, did little to shake the dollar out of its overseas torpor.</p>
<p>Sakakibara, known as &quot;Mr Yen&quot; for his past influence on currency markets, said that a rise in Japan's discount rate should be expected by the end of the year.</p>
<p>STOCK PRICES AT 1400 GMT</p>
<p>LONDON - The FTSE 100 was up 11.6 points, or 0.25 percent, at 4,663.4.</p>
<p>PARIS - The CAC-40 index was up 15.55 points, or 0.57 percent, at 2,757.2</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - The DAX index closed floor trade up 22.77 points, or 0.64 percent, at 3,602.19. In later screen-based trade the IBIS DAX was up 30.08 points at 3,605.52.</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 1400 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar stood at 1.6922 marks and 115.61 yen compared with 1.6947 marks and 116.05 yen in late European trade on Thursday.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold was fixed at $342.55 versus $341.65 in the morning. Silver was off a cent at $4.68.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
