<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609852" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton delays seeking fast track trade powers.</title>
<headline>Clinton delays seeking fast track trade powers.</headline>
<byline>Laurence McQuillan</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton has decided to wait several months before asking Congress for authority to negotiate new trade agreements, including those expanding trade with Latin America, sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>Clinton earlier this month used a trip to Latin America and the Caribbean to repeat his plans to expand the North American Free Trade Agreement with Canada and Mexico to other nations in the hemisphere.</p>
<p>White House officials had hoped to submit legislation to Congress next month granting Clinton so-called fast track authority for trade negotiations.</p>
<p>Administration officials said the measure would be submitted in the autumn, instead, &quot;so we can get more support in Congress,&quot; one official said.</p>
<p>Under fast track, Congress gives up its right to amend trade agreements and only would be able to vote for or against the entire treaty.</p>
<p>The congressional battle over fast track centres on whether labour and environmental issues should be included in trade agreements.</p>
<p>Republicans generally oppose incorporating the issues in trade negotiations, while many Democrats insist they must be part of any trade agreement.</p>
<p>Waiting until autumn would mean final passage would be pushed off until next year. White House officials would like the authority in place by the time Clinton meets other hemispheric leaders in Santiago, Chile, in April to launch Free Trade Area of the Americas negotiations.</p>
<p>The idea of ending trade barriers in the Americas was first pushed by Republican President George Bush in 1990, when he called for a hemisphere-wide free trade zone.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Chilean President Eduardo Frei said in his annual speech to Congress that he hoped the Clinton administration would be able to overcome the obstacles to free trade in the region.</p>
<p>Frei said Chile, next in line to join NAFTA, was hopeful it can reach a free trade agreement with Washington.</p>
<p>Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin last week told an investment group that getting fast track authority &quot;is going to be very difficult and the odds clearly are not in our favour.&quot;</p>
<p>Opponents of NAFTA claim the agreement has spawned a rapid rise in the U.S. trade deficit with Mexico, a loss of jobs from manfacturing moving south and lower wages for workers.</p>
<p>Business groups who want to bring Chile into NAFTA, however, argue that the pact has been good for the U.S. economy and that the United States will be left behind as competitors in Japan and Europe form new trade relationships with Latin American countries, a traditional market for U.S. exporters.</p>
<p>The administration has been without fast track authority since 1994.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
