<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609876" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Stocks stage modest rise, dollar stabilises.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Stocks stage modest rise, dollar stabilises.</headline>
<byline>Malcolm Davidson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Major European bourses firmed on Friday despite Wall Street's weaker close overnight, while the dollar searched for direction against the yen following a volatile week.</p>
<p>French stocks made the best gains of the morning, rising 0.7 percent on the last trading day before the first round of national parliamentary elections on Sunday.</p>
<p>Although publication of opinion polls is banned in France ahead of the elections, dealers said the market rose following a survey published in a Swiss newspaper.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is reacting to the poll published in the Tribune de Geneve, but we're advising people to protect themselves against an adverse reaction on Monday,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>By 1145 GMT the CAC 40 index was showing gains of just over 20 points to 2,761.75.</p>
<p>Some traders said the market could turn lower later when the monthly settlement took place. Monday also risks being volatile with the U.S. and British markets closed for a holiday.</p>
<p>In Germany leading shares also moved higher through the morning. Although the 30-share DAX index pushed through 3,600 points, traders said they saw no major rally emerging due to long holiday weekends in the United States and Britain.</p>
<p>Volkswagen gained 13.0 marks to 1,140 marks, while Daimler rose 1.55 marks to 133.55 after its Mercedes unit reported a 13 percent gain in worldwide car sales over four months.</p>
<p>Dresdner Bank recovered from earlier weakness after reporting first quarter operating profit before provisions up 10 percent. It said it was cautiously optimistic for 1997 results and dividend as a whole.</p>
<p>London's FTSE 100 gave up most of the day's gains by mid-session as market-makers moved prices to square positions ahead of the long weekend break.</p>
<p>The index was trading 5.7 points up at 4,657.5 by 1145 GMT, having touched 4,672.7 during the morning.</p>
<p>&quot;It's gone up and down with very little underlying business. It's just market-makers tidying their books and it was never going to be any different today,&quot; said one dealer.</p>
<p>The market continued to garner support from firmer bonds but prices stayed mixed.</p>
<p>Financial stocks rose, led by a higher grey market price of 700p for upcoming stock market entry of the Halifax Building Society.</p>
<p>Alliance &amp; Leicester Plc rose in brisk trade, putting on 24p to 623 with more than five million traded and Barclays Plc rose 16-1/2p to 1,225p with more than 2.7 million changing hands.</p>
<p>On the currency front, the dollar reclaimed well-worn ground above 1.69 marks but hovered a little shy of 116 yen as the unit struggled to find direction after a week of sharp volatility.</p>
<p>&quot;The big structural change has been the tightening in liquidity across markets after the yen's appreciation. For the dollar, the big question is whether this has been it in terms of liquidation and whether its going to try to stabilise,&quot; said Sheen Shipley, International economist at CS First Boston.</p>
<p>The dollar tumbled to five-month lows of 111.88 yen on Tuesday as markets banked on higher rates in Japan. By 1145 GMT on Friday it was quoted at 115.79 but below its overnight peak above 116 yen.</p>
<p>&quot;The dollar is lacking a bit of interest, to be honest. We've got a long weekend coming up and some of the banks are off,&quot; said a senior dealer at a British merchant bank.</p>
<p>Traders said the dollar was relegated to the sidelines as the market eyed a stumble in sterling, punished by speculation that Bank of England Governor Eddie George might not be reappointed at the end of his five-year term next year.</p>
<p>The pound was down from late Thursday levels in early European trading but off its overnight lows against the mark and dollar at around 2.7600 marks and 1.6304 dollars.</p>
<p>STOCK PRICES AT 1145 GMT</p>
<p>LONDON - The FTSE 100 was up 5.7 points, or 0.12 percent, at 4,657.5.</p>
<p>PARIS - The CAC-40 index was up 20.10 points, or 0.73 percent, at 2,761.75.</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - The DAX index was up 22.77 points, or 0.64 percent, at 3,602.19.</p>
<p>CURRENCIES AT 1145 GMT</p>
<p>The dollar stood at 1.6921 marks and 115.79 yen compared with 1.6947 marks and 116.05 yen in late European trade on Thursday.</p>
<p>PRECIOUS METALS</p>
<p>Gold was fixed at $341.65 versus $342.75 on Thursday afternoon and a London close of $342.75. Silver was off a cent at $4.68.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
