<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609840" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Silence of the Fed may have set stage for summer rally.</title>
<headline>Silence of the Fed may have set stage for summer rally.</headline>
<byline>Pierre Belec</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>Wall Street let out an exuberant cheer after the Federal Reserve passed on raising interest rates this week, and it may have set the stage for a blowout summer rally.</p>
<p>The silence of the Fed removed a major roadblock for stock investors who have been on the edge of their seats, worrying about higher interest rates.</p>
<p>Two months earlier, the master mechanics of the economy whose policy decisions impacts corporate earnings and consumer pocketbooks, had fallen out of investors' graces when they raised the cost of borrowing for the first time in more than two years.</p>
<p>Now, the Fed is out of the doghouse, having opted to keep interest rates unchanged.</p>
<p>The inaction suggested that the Fed had joined the camp of people who believe that the economy can grow without generating bad inflation. This perfect scenario has been at the root of the greatest bull market in history.</p>
<p>The one quarter percentage point hike in March, and speculation that the Fed was planning extended monetary tightening, scared the stock market, sending the Dow Jones industrial average down a dizzying 700 points.</p>
<p>It was the biggest freefall in the six-year history of the fast rising market, which has propelled the Dow to 19 record highs so far this year. The last milestone was set on May 15, as the blue-chip index zoomed to 7,333.55.</p>
<p>In early afternoon trading Friday, the Dow was up 38.33 points at 7,296.46. For the week, it gained 101.79 points.</p>
<p>The rate hike took the concept of controlled terror to a new height, rattling investors who have been pouring billions of dollars into retirement pension plans such as 401-K plans.</p>
<p>Fed Chairman Alan Greenspan, who has never been the poster idol of the investment community, called the March rate increase &quot;a form of insurance&quot; against the inflation risk that can stem from rapid growth and low unemployment.</p>
<p>But the popular inflation gauges such as the Consumer Price Index and the Producer Price Index have shown that companies still have little pricing power and in fact, many have been unable to pass their extra costs through to consumers.</p>
<p>&quot;The Fed made the right decision in not raising and the decision was not so much that they were not raising interest rates but that they would wait until July and look at more numbers,&quot; said Hugh Johnson, chief investment officer for First Albany Corp.</p>
<p>He said that the evidence shows that the econonomy has slowed and there is no much upward pressure on prices.</p>
<p>The Fed's hands-off policy coincided with the arrival of a summer rally in stocks.</p>
<p>Wall Street, which operates on its own calendar, traditionally romps higher about one month before the summer season's official start on June 21.</p>
<p>The annual pattern has been around for the past decade, and the Dow index has climbed nearly 500 points between May and September.</p>
<p>&quot;Inflation has been muted and in fact, it appears to be an endangered species, and with the Fed putting interest rates on hold we could see a rip roaring summer as long as the economy doesn't begin to heat up,&quot; said Alan Ackerman, market strategist at Fahnestock &amp; Co.</p>
<p>The proverbial summer rally can be disappointing. Last year, the Dow jumped on cue in May and raced up in June but the rise came to an abrupt halt in July as the blue-chip index crumbled about 8 percent, falling from 5,731 on July 1 to 5,359 by July 16.</p>
<p>Johnson said Wall Street may already had its summer rally after the Dow has soared 900 points in the last four weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;The market may have already discounted too many good things that lie ahead, and it may be over-valued and set for a pause,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The experts say the Fed will still dictate stock sentiment in the short-term, but the central bank's influence may deteriorate if the government continues to report tame inflation numbers.</p>
<p>They expect that Greenspan will continue to issue a steady stream of observations about the economy, advertising the message that the Fed would strike quickly to head off any inflation pressures. The next policy-maker's two-day meeting is set for July 1 and 2.</p>
<p>By not raising rates last week, the Fed still held open the possibility of a monetary tightening in the future, which should temper the bullish enthusiasm in the stock market.</p>
<p>Greg Smith, chief investment strategist for Prudential Securities says that the Fed may eventually become a minor issue and bow out of the stock market's picture as more people realise that inflation is not a threat.</p>
<p>&quot;Having sounded the alarm of higher inflation -- putting the financial markets on edge about the economy fanning inflation problems -- the Fed may feel forced to tighten at least one more time before sitting back on its hand and becoming a relatively unimportant factor in the market once again,&quot; Smith said.</p>
<p>&quot;It does appear as though Fed action in 1997 will be fairly minor and increasingly take a backseat to the fundamental issue of earnings as midyear approaches -- it's about then that forecasters start to make serious projections for the following calendar year's earnings,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In June, Wall Street will get a better idea of how good or bad the second-quarter earnings will be as companies start to parade their earnings warnings.</p>
<p>&quot;I remain fairly optimistic on profits, particularly if the Fed does not aggressvely raise interest rates, which seems to be the most likely case in the current environment,&quot; Smith said.</p>
<p>(Questions or comments on the Stocks-Week Column can be addressed to Pierre.Belec (at)Reuters.Com)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
