<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609896" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-Zeneca firing on all cylinders.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Zeneca firing on all cylinders.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>British drugs and specialty chemicals company Zeneca Group Plc showed on Friday that it was continuing to fire on all cylinders, with pre-tax profits in the first four months of the year ahead by 15 percent.</p>
<p>The company, which doubled its pre-tax profits in the five years from 1992 to 1996, has set itself a similarly ambitious target for the next five years.</p>
<p>Chairman Sir Sidney Lipworth told shareholders at the group's annual meeting that Zeneca was &quot;well in touch with&quot; that goal, and the group's shares responded by adding 19 1/2 pence to 1890 pence in mid-afternoon trading.</p>
<p>&quot;There's reassurance there with underlying profits up 15 percent against a strong first-half last year, and they have said that new products are looking good,&quot; said one analyst. &quot;That 15 percent is among the best in the industry.&quot;</p>
<p>Zeneca, which did not provide detailed figures, said the gain excluded the impact of sterling's rise, which it acknowledged had had &quot;a dampening effect,&quot; but said its underlying improvement &quot;continues apace.&quot;</p>
<p>In a sign that it is reluctant to disturb the management chemistry which has helped Zeneca to leave its one-time parent Imperial Chemical Industries Plc in the dust, Zeneca announced that chief executive Sir David Barnes would stay at the helm for an extra 12 months, retiring at the annual meeting in 1999.</p>
<p>The delay buys time for Zeneca in the notoriously difficult job of finding top-flight pharmaceutical executives.</p>
<p>Barnes, who picked up nearly 900,000 pounds last year including pension contributions, steered Zeneca through its spin-off from ICI in 1993, since when its shares have more than trebled in value, giving it a stock market capitalisation of nearly 18 billion pounds ($29.2 billion) and dwarfing ICI's 5.7 billion pound valuation.</p>
<p>The company is the world's second biggest seller of cancer drugs after Bristol Myers Squibb Co and has its eyes on the number one slot. Other strengths include heart drugs such as the ACE-inhibitor Zestril and it has recently moved into the highly competitive asthma field with Accolate, a new type of asthma treatment.</p>
<p>It strong growth record and an impressive pipeline of new drugs and specialty chemicals have also turned it into the industry's most eligible bride in the eyes of many speculators, with a match with Switzerland's Roche Holdings AG frequently sighed over but never consummated.</p>
<p>Zeneca has been adept at picking up successful products from other companies, and has recently launched cardiovascular drug Sular, licensed from Germany's Bayer AG and Zomig, a migraine drug acquired from Glaxo Wellcome Plc.</p>
<p>Speculation about who will take Zeneca into the next century as chief executive has so far centred on internal appointments, with finance director John Mayo thought to be a contender. Forty-year old Mayo has shepherded the group's finances since demerger after joining from merchant bank SBC Warburg.</p>
<p>($ = 0.615 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
