<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609839" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French markets may be over-confident on Sunday poll.</title>
<headline>French markets may be over-confident on Sunday poll.</headline>
<byline>Penny MacRae</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Investors could be over-confident in betting on a comfortable showing by the ruling centre-right in Sunday's first-round of the French legislative elections, market watchers warned on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;From the current perspective, the risk of a shock is very high,&quot; said senior bond analyst Iain Lindsay of Credit Lyonnais.</p>
<p>&quot;In percentage terms, 37 percent or less for the centre-right in the first round would be dangerous territory and a real cause for concern for the markets,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bonds and shares gained on Friday with few investors appearing nervous about the outcome of the snap vote called by President Jacques Chirac to give &quot;a new elan&quot; to France's drive to join Europe's planned single currency in 1999. The second round of the election will be on June 1.</p>
<p>The 10-year bond future contract ended 0.16 basis points higher at 129.0 on Friday, while the blue chip CAC-40 stocks index of 40 leading shares closed up 0.78 percent at 2,762.90.</p>
<p>There was some position-squaring ahead of the election but &quot;so far there has not been any risk premium priced into the French market,&quot; said economist Marie Owens-Thomsen of BIP.</p>
<p>Share investors also remained optimistic about the results, but one trader said: &quot;We're advising people to protect themselves against an adverse reaction on Monday.&quot;</p>
<p>One Paris brokerage predicted the CAC index gaining 10 percent if the conservatives won and a loss of the same magnitude if the left won. &quot;Our view is that the conservatives will squeak home in the second ballot,&quot; said an equities strategist.</p>
<p>Surveys in France before a ban on polls went into effect last weekend showed the left winning more votes than the conservatives in the first round but ending up with fewer seats after the run-off because of the single constituency system.</p>
<p>The conservatives won an unprecedented 385 seat majority in the 577-seat National Assembly in 1993 but polls suggested their majority could be slashed to as low as 38 in this election.</p>
<p>The unusually high level of undecided voters, widespread public apathy and an expected high abstention rate were extra factors, raising the possibility of an upset victory by the Socialists, economists said.</p>
<p>With Prime Minister Alain Juppe's unpopularity, &quot;there is a risk (traditional centre-right) supporters may not show up in the polling booths,&quot; said ABN Amro economist Philippe Brossard.</p>
<p>Economists said there was concern about the reliability of seat projections in polls. &quot;Given the close vote, I'm not confident about the simulations,&quot; Brossard said.</p>
<p>Economists recalled how pollsters got it wrong in the 1995 presidential election when the Socialists' standard bearer Lionel Jospin unexpectedly topped the first-round ballot.</p>
<p>&quot;This election is obviously much harder for pollsters than a presidential election because you have 577 seats,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>Economist Sonja Gibbs of Nomura said stronger than expected Socialist gains -- even if the party fell short of winning an absolute majority -- could mean a more eurosceptic National Assembly and difficulty in pushing through austerity measures.</p>
<p>&quot;The French market is not priced for this outcome and the short end, in particular, looks vulnerable,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Even though the Socialists are committed to monetary union, a win by the party could mean a broader union, embracing Italy, with softer criteria for joining, she said.</p>
<p>One analyst said the upside for bonds and the franc from a centre-right win was &quot;very tame&quot; as it had already been priced in.</p>
<p>But if Sunday's round decisively favoured the centre-right, with the conservatives drawing 39 to 40 percent of the vote, there could be strong demand in the cash market with investors deciding not to wait for the final ballot, Lindsay said.</p>
<p>&quot;There might be a couple of basis points added on to the 10-year OAT-Bund spread,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The franc was at 3.3697 per mark on Friday while the spread, or difference between the 10-year OAT and German Bund was minus 0.15 percentage points .</p>
<p>The median forecast for the franc against the mark in the event of a Socialist election win in a Reuter survey on Thursday was 3.400. The forecast for the 10 year spread between French and German bond yields was 10 basis points.</p>
<p>In the event of a right-wingvictory, the franc was seen climbing to 3.362 and the spread was seen at minus 15 basis points.</p>
<p>&quot;The risk is if it is a very bad result in the first round with the right getting 35 percent of the vote and the left 40,&quot; said Lindsay. &quot;I don't see why the franc could not go to 3.40 or 3.45 per mark. I think it could crash quite badly.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
