<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609883" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: OPTIONS - Gilt vols steady as futures fluctuate.</title>
<headline>OPTIONS - Gilt vols steady as futures fluctuate.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Implied volatility of gilt options traded on LIFFE failed to budge on Friday, despite a drop in the underlying futures this week after a poor showing on a long-term auction, traders said.</p>
<p>Investors bought calls to get long of gilt options at out-of-the-money strikes on a view that the market would move higher.</p>
<p>But there was also strong interest in selling vol ahead of the Bank holiday weekend in Britain. Markets will be closed on Monday.</p>
<p>Thursday's fall sent gilt futures almost back to levels seen before a sharp rally at the beginning of May when the new Labour government shifted the decision on interest rates to the Bank of England (BOE).</p>
<p>That decision was seen positive for the gilt market as the more independent BOE was expected to have a firmer grip on inflation.</p>
<p>But analysts said continued evidence on the robustness of the economy was fuelling expectations of an interest rate hike soon.</p>
<p>Thursday's auction of paper due 2021 attracted cover of just 1.29 times with a lengthy yield tail, further weighing on sentiment.</p>
<p>But on Friday gilts recovered some of their losses with the June futures traded on LIFFE up 17/32 basis points at 112-13 by 1400 GMT, and compared with the lows on Thursday of 111-21.</p>
<p>In options, activity centred on July calls on September futures.</p>
<p>&quot;In the short term people view that there is more positive feeling in the market,&quot; said one trader at a UK investment house.</p>
<p>&quot;It's mainly been upside buying (in options),&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A call spread on July 113-00/114-00 strikes grabbed the biggest slice of the day's volume, traders said.</p>
<p>But volatilities of out-of-the-money calls stood around 7.5 percent, broadly unchanged from Thursday.</p>
<p>In the short sterling market, volatilities eased in line with the market's recent rangebound tone, traders said. The December out-of-the-money strikes traded at around 10 percent, down 1.15 points from Thursday.</p>
<p>March and December calls at 93.75 and 93.50 strikes on respectively on March and December futures saw moderate business.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone sold the vols before the long weekend,&quot; said one trader on the LIFFE floor.</p>
<p>&quot;The vols are not high but I think they will go even lower,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>September short sterling futures traded two basis points up at 93.19 on Friday.</p>
<p>-- Clelia Oziel, International Bonds +44-171-542 8663</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
