<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609888" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Upside LME copper options targeted in covering move.</title>
<headline>Upside LME copper options targeted in covering move.</headline>
<byline>Eric Onstad</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A scramble to cover short copper option positions by a major Korean firm pushed up volatilities this week, while granting by the same company depressed aluminium vols to historic lows, traders said.</p>
<p>Nearby upside copper options were purchased as cover by a Korean metals company which had been prominent in the market at the end of last year and early 1997 for granting large lumps of copper and aluminium options, they added.</p>
<p>The firm has been running a short book and were caught out by the run-up in LME prices, which hit a fresh one-year peak of $2,530, basis three-months, on Thursday.</p>
<p>One options source said the buying of upside options was linked to an expanded credit line granted by a major U.S. investment bank.</p>
<p>The credit was approved on condition that $2,600 and $2,700 calls were bought as protection against further price rises, he said.</p>
<p>Another source said the Korean positions were taken over by the metals trading arm of a large investment bank.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, LME data showed turnover of 2,190 lots of $2,700 calls and on Thursday 1,460 lots in June $2,600 calls.</p>
<p>In addition, some producers have been buying downside fourth quarter puts, traders said. On Thursday, LME data shows turnover of 1,170 lots of $2,150 puts for October through December.</p>
<p>Implied volatility on the $2,600s and $2,700s traded as high as 24.5 and 25.5 percent, traders said.</p>
<p>Vols drifted back a bit ahead of the long weekend, but the nearbys were still one to two points firmer on the week.</p>
<p>At-the-money (ATM) implied volatility for June was bid at 21.0-23.0 percent, July at 20.0-20.5 percent and fourth quarter at 15.5-16.5 percent.</p>
<p>Aluminium volatility sank, however, mainly under pressure from granting, said to be by the same Korean player.</p>
<p>&quot;To finance the purchase of nearby call options, they sold forward aluminium options,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>LME data showed turnover on Wednesday of 1,920 lots of $1,675 calls for January-March 1998 and 3,630 lots of $1,650 calls for the same dates.</p>
<p>The market was already saturated with aluminium options and the heavy granting hammered implied volatility to historic lows, traders said.</p>
<p>ATM volatility on Friday was bid for June at 13.5-14.5 percent and for July at 15.0-15.5 percent, down about two points.</p>
<p>One trader said nearby volatility was the lowest since October 1993, when volatility on the front month was quoted at 11.0/13.0 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;It is getting so low I am telling my customers they are a good buy at these levels. There is not much downside,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Nickel also saw weaker vols as the market saw granting of June to August material in both calls and puts.</p>
<p>&quot;There was some granting but nobody wants them,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>June was bid at 20.0-22.0 percent and July at 21.0-22.5 percent, down two to three points.</p>
<p>--London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
