<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609880" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Crude has solid base, needs gasoline lead.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Crude has solid base, needs gasoline lead.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>---------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>NEARBY MONTH CLOSE * SUPPORT * RESIST  * RSI-14 * MA-10 * MA-20</p>
<p> BRENT	  20.18 *  20.08  *  20.35  *   65   * 19.80 * 19.06</p>
<p> GAS OIL     179.00 * 177.25  * 180.00  *   67   *174.13 *170.86</p>
<p>----------------- VIEWS FROM THE MARKET - MAY 23 --------------</p>
<p>*   Brent's inability to break down has left good support in a band around the $19.95-$20.10 range and with a little help from gasoline prices could continue to track higher. *   Gas oil's $173 to $176.50 gap-up from last Friday to Monday remains supportively intact providing a solid base to move higher.</p>
<p>More consolidation looks likely on Brent crude oil futures, dealers and chartists said. This week's period of chart congestion above $20 after last Friday's rally looks likely to have set new higher levels of support giving a solid base to move up from.</p>
<p>However, futures brokers said crude will look increasingly to NYMEX gasoline for a lead higher as Memorial Day in the U.S. on Monday traditionally marks the start of the gasoline season.</p>
<p>&quot;It's gasoline season. If gas is going to lead anything, this is the time,&quot; said Tom Bentz, analyst at High Yield Analytics in New Yorks.</p>
<p>NYMEX ACCESS trade saw June unleaded gasoline 0.23 cents a gallon lower at around $66.70.</p>
<p>July Brent was quoted at $20.08/15 a barrel on SIMEX, slightly off from the London close of $20.18. NYMEX crude on ACCESS was last done at $21.78 off eight cents from the close.</p>
<p>Analysts said on Brent the bulls appeared to be winning the day with the market's inability to break down leaving good support in a band around the $19.95-$20.10 range and with a little help from gasoline prices could continue to track higher.</p>
<p>They saw the next upside target as $21.35, Thursday's high, after which the contract high of $21.90 will come into focus.</p>
<p>Fenella Graham at MeesPierson Derivatives in London said, &quot;The longer these markets fail to push decisively upward and soon, the greater the chance of a retest of the lower end of the ranges to find support, as the longs are quietly withering on the vine.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Gas oil and unleaded lead the way up so we look to them to provide this momentum (for crude) soon,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>However, on the fundamental side narrower crack margins for products after crude's recent run-up has caused BP and Texaco to cut runs in Rotterdam, and others to think of doing so, pressurising crude.</p>
<p>10 and 20-day moving averages are creeping higher and widening apart again with little sign of a directional cross but directionally 14-day RSIs continue to teeter on the edge of the 70 percent overbought line.</p>
<p>Momentum indicators for gas oil are also edging higher but there is little sign of a correction on the charts.</p>
<p>The $173 to $176.50 gap-up from last Friday to Monday remains supportively intact providing a solid base to move higher, however, MeesPierson said in their daily report that it could easily be argued that gas oil was still in an extended range, $179.50 being high and $175.25 the low.</p>
<p>NYMEX crude futures ended little changed Thursday after a quiet day leading up to the Memorial Day weekend, as the market continued to consolidate after last week's rally.</p>
<p>Crude oil for July delivery on the New York Mercantile Exchange settled unchanged at $21.86 a barrel.</p>
<p>-- Colin Wooster, London Newsroom, +44 171 542 7456</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
