<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609862" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: SANTASALO SEES '97 PROFIT UP AT ALL LEVELS.</title>
<headline>SANTASALO SEES '97 PROFIT UP AT ALL LEVELS.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Finnish engineering group Santasalo-JOT Oy expects its full-year 1997 earnings to improve at all levels, CEO Heikki Lehtonen told a briefing on the company's January-April results on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The result will improve on all levels regardless of whether we talk about profit after financial items, profit after tax or profit after extraordinary items,&quot; Lehtonen said.</p>
<p>&quot;But due to big extraordinary items, the difference won't necessarily be terribly big in the result after extras,&quot; he added. Group full-year extraordinaries charges were estimated at 30 million markka against a 6.6 million markka charge in 1996.</p>
<p>Santasalo-JOT reported an unchanged January-April profit after financial items of 14 million markka. Earnings per share rose to 1.46 markka from 1.23 markka in the year-ago period.</p>
<p>In 1996, Santasalo-JOT posted a full-year 37.9 million markka profit after financial items, a 31.4 million markka pre-tax profit after extraordinary items, a 10.8 million markka net profit after tax and EPS of 3.75 markka.</p>
<p>Santasalo said in its interim report it expected group net sales to rise to 1.3 billion markka from 846 million in 1996.</p>
<p>While the outlook for the forestry industry -- a major Santasalo-JOT client -- remained uncertain, the trend was clearly upward, Lehtonen said.</p>
<p>&quot;Big pulp industry projects in the Far East will have an effect on the intake of orders this year and next,&quot; Lehtonen said.</p>
<p>The economic outlook in Europe had improved, he said, and added: &quot;That is of great importance to us.&quot;</p>
<p>The main task for Santasalo-JOT this year would be to integrate its acquisition of vehicle components maker Asko Components, which would have a positive effect on earnings after financial items this year, Lehtonen said.</p>
<p>Another project would be to ramp up capacity at its new China gear unit factory, which Lehtonen said had been in full operation since the beginning of May but where the utilisation rate this year would be about a third of full capacity.</p>
<p>Santasalo-JOT planned to invest a total of 140 million markka this year, Lehtonen said.</p>
<p>&quot;Next year we should get back to a normal investment level, or in other words to investments about equal to depreciation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In 1996, depreciations totalled 48.3 million markka. In January-April, depreciations were 18.9 million markka, up from 15.6 million.</p>
<p>--Jon Acher, Helsinki Newsroom +358-9-680 50 235</p>
<p>					     news@reuters.fi</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
