<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609848" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Bradford &amp; Bingley buys Mortgage Express.</title>
<headline>Bradford &amp; Bingley buys Mortgage Express.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Bradford &amp; Bingley Building Society said on Friday it had bought Mortgage Express from Lloyds TSB Group for 64 million pounds ($104 million).</p>
<p>The mutually-owned building society said in a statement that Mortgage Express had 26,000 mortgage customers and a mortgage book totalling 1.5 billion pounds. Mortgage Express is based in Barnet, north London.  </p>
<p>A Bradford &amp; Bingley spokesman told Reuters that talks on buying Mortgage Express had been going on for three months and the society had beaten off stiff competition to buy the business.</p>
<p>Mortgage Express offered a means of diversification for Bradford &amp; Bingley but in no way diluted its commitment to mutuality, corporate affairs manager Chris Holland said. It will operate as a wholly-owned subsidiary and maintain its brand, head office and staff, he added.</p>
<p>Holland said the move into what are generally accepted to be riskier mortgages for self-employed and contract workers was a sensible step forward for Bradford &amp; Bingley. Problems suffered by the centralised lender in the past were behind it and it was now a profitable business.</p>
<p>Unlike Bradford &amp; Bingley, whose borrowers own the society, Mortgage Express borrowers will not be members. Mortgage Express recently re-entered the specialist lending market, offering products such as buy-to-rent loans, second home finance and negative equity loans. ($ = 0.615 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
