<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609832" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: FEATURE - Canada writer Timothy Findley returns to stage.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Canada writer Timothy Findley returns to stage.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Hodgson</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thirty-five years after he left the theater to became one of Canada's most celebrated authors, Timothy Findley has made a triumphant return to the stage.</p>
<p>The award-winning author of &quot;The Wars&quot; and &quot;Not Wanted on the Voyage&quot; is back on stage before sellout crowds in an 18-city touring production called &quot;The Pianoman's Daughter ...and others.&quot;</p>
<p>The show -- a mix of singing, dancing and storytelling -- is based on Findley's three most recent books. Findley's role in the show includes reading from his work and narrating the action onstage.</p>
<p>Findley, who was an actor for 18 years, said he thought returning to the stage was a risk. But despite the risk, or perhaps because of it, the 66-year-old author felt it was a challenge worth taking.</p>
<p>&quot;If you don't take a risk, if you're not in danger, you're not doing your job,&quot; Findley told Reuters. &quot;That's the only thing that produces the next step forward. You have to be willing to make a fool of yourself.&quot;</p>
<p>Since giving up the theater in 1962 to write full time, Findley has become one of the country's most respected and popular authors.</p>
<p>Like fellow Canadians Michael Ondaatje and Margaret Atwood, his books are best sellers and regularly earn international acclaim.</p>
<p>Last year France recognized Findley's contribution to literature by making him a Knight of the Order of Arts and Letters. The recognition from France follows a career in which Findley's work garnered almost every single major Canadian literary prize, including the Governor-General's award for fiction.</p>
<p>HOLLYWOOD LIKES HIM</p>
<p>Like &quot;The English Patient&quot; author Ondaatje, filmakers have also recently discovered Findley's work. Actress Whoopi Goldberg has bought the rights to his best-selling novel &quot;The Pianoman's Daughter.&quot; Film rights to his 1981 novel &quot;Famous Last Words&quot; were sold earlier this year.</p>
<p>It was the 1995 publication of &quot;The Pianoman's Daughter&quot; that inspired the current show. Findley's publishers suggested that he add to his usual public reading with songs, dance and actors performing the scene being read.</p>
<p>Folk singer Sylvia Tyson and former National Ballet of Canada prima ballerina Veronica Tennant -- both big Findley fans -- were recruited for the show. The resulting production was performed only once but was a critical hit.</p>
<p>&quot;It blew everybody away. It was a huge success. We all sat down at a celebratory dinner after the performance and virtually everybody said we've got to do this again and we should take it on the road,&quot; said Findley.</p>
<p>With the publication of Findley's latest collection of short stories, &quot;Dust to Dust,&quot; the cast decided to remount and add to the production.</p>
<p>MIXES RAGTIME, FOLK AND BALLET</p>
<p>The innovative mix of ragtime and folk music, storytelling and ballet dancing is touring Canada until the end of May. So far the show has traveled from Niagara Falls, Ontario, to Prince Edward Island on Canada's east coast, playing before sellout crowds and earning standing ovations.</p>
<p>&quot;People are kind of predisposed to like it because they love Timothy Findley's writing. I think they're ready to receive it on that level,&quot; singer Tyson told Reuters.</p>
<p>In addition to &quot;The Pianoman's Daughter&quot; the show includes segments inspired by Findley's wartime novella &quot;You Went Away&quot; and &quot;Dust to Dust.&quot;</p>
<p>Published this year, Findley said &quot;Dust to Dust&quot; was inspired by a trip to Europe with his companion of more than 30 years, William Whitehead. The nine stories are set mostly in Europe and focus on characters who have in some way been touched by death or darkness.</p>
<p>While the three books that make up &quot;The Pianoman's Daughter...and others&quot; vary in time and setting, Findley says the stories work well together as theater because they share a common theme.</p>
<p>&quot;They do have a kind of mutual focus on the triumphs of various people under extremely trying circumstances. I guess you could say that the unifier is the word survival, and in some instances triumph,&quot; said Findley.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
