<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609837" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: TRADE-CHINA-WTO 1STLD.</title>
<headline>TRADE-CHINA-WTO 1STLD.</headline>
<byline>Stephanie Nebehay</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chinese Assistant Foreign Trade Minister Long Yongtu pledged to return to the next round of World Trade Organisation (WTO) entry talks in July with better offers on market access, but said partners had to be realistic.</p>
<p>Long said &quot;very good progress&quot; had been made in WTO negotiations over the terms for Beijing joining the 131-member trade watchdog, adding: &quot;We are going to table new offers.</p>
<p>&quot;I am very hopeful that in the next few months we can have decisive progress in the field of market access,&quot; he told a news conference in Geneva.</p>
<p>U.S. and European Union trade officials agreed progress had been made but stressed they would be looking for fresh concessions on market access when the talks resumed.</p>
<p>Jim Wallace of the U.S. Trade Representative's Office told reporters: &quot;There was progress. Momentum was maintained.&quot;</p>
<p>EU ambassador Roderick Abbott cited &quot;modest progress&quot;, but added: &quot;Modest is signficant&quot;.</p>
<p>Pierre-Louis Girard, the Swiss diplomat who chairs the WTO talks on China's accession, warned that unless real progress was made in the coming months, there was a &quot;real danger of deadlock in the negotiations&quot;.</p>
<p>Beijing applied to the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) in 1986, but progress has been slow. WTO chief Renato Ruggiero this week urged China to make a &quot;very ambitious&quot; market-access offer, a major issue in service and farm sectors.</p>
<p>Long was upbeat in his speech to delegates but acknowledged that more steps were needed: &quot;Everything is on the right track.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;At the same time, we are also aware that there are still many difficulties in the market access negotiations,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Asked about Girard's warning, Long said: &quot;I do not a see a danger of the momentum being lost because we have a very firm political commitment from the Chinese government to continue this process. That political commitment will ensure that we will continue to make new offers.&quot;</p>
<p>Long said a &quot;major step&quot; had been made through an accord on two paragraphs in the protocol of accession which should improve the legal environment for foreign businesses in China. These were the principles of judicial review and non-discrimination.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that the agreement reached on these two provisions is of great significance and will have important commercial value for the 140,000 joint ventures and wholly-owned foreign enterprises now operating in China,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The kind of progress we made this week will enable the business community -- both investors and traders -- to have access to the judicial review system in China and to protect their interests and to subject the business activities in China to the so-called rules of law.</p>
<p>&quot;I think this is very crucial in the context of China.&quot;</p>
<p>Wallace of the USTR, referring to the agreement on the two protocol issues, said: &quot;We were quite pleased with the outcome. These are fairly fundamental WTO rules.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked what Washington would seek in July, Wallace replied: &quot;More fundamental progress on market access and a commitment from China, particularly on services.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Their offer is a basis for further discussion but much more fundamental progress is hoped for,&quot; Wallace added.</p>
<p>Girard urged China and WTO members to discuss market access as a &quot;matter of utmost priority&quot; in bilateral negotiations before the next meeting of the working party.</p>
<p>Long was to remain in Geneva next week for bilateral talks, including a meeting with Japanese officials over the weekend, to be followed by a new round of negotiations with the EU.</p>
<p>Long said that China had pledged upon entry to eliminate all remaining dual-price practices, including those for the service sector, which should encourage foreign investment.</p>
<p>&quot;The commitment to eliminate or remove the requirement of dual prices will definitely reduce the operating costs for those enterprises working in China,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
