<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609842" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UZBEKISTAN: Uzbekistan in $900 mln deals with Indonesians.</title>
<headline>Uzbekistan in $900 mln deals with Indonesians.</headline>
<byline>Mike Collett-White</byline>
<dateline>TASHKENT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Uzbekistan has signed two deals worth nearly a billion dollars with privately-owned Indonesian conglomerate Bakrie, in a major boost to the former Soviet republic's energy and fertiliser sectors.</p>
<p>Bakrie's director for Uzbekistan, Robert Sutrisno, told Reuters the company had signed two memoranda of understanding with the Central Asian state's State Property Committee.</p>
<p>The first, signed on Wednesday, was for investments of $600 million in the resource-rich republic's oil and gas fields. The second, signed on Friday, was for a further $300 million to be spent on building a fertiliser plant.</p>
<p>&quot;This is true,&quot; Sutrisno said, when asked about the first $600 million agreement. &quot;And we have also just signed another deal with the committee for $300 million.&quot;</p>
<p>In a region where deals can suddenly turn to dust, Sutrisno was quick to stress the agreements would be realised.</p>
<p>&quot;These are not just pieces of paper,&quot; he said. &quot;We are very serious about the work and the plans are already very concrete.&quot;</p>
<p>The bigger of the agreements will come as welcome news to the oil and gas sector, which this week hosted a major international oil and gas conference in the Uzbek capital of Tashkent to woo foreign investment in energy projects.</p>
<p>Representatives from major international oil and gas companies attended, expressing strong interest in the rich resources lying beneath the mostly desert nation but giving little away as to whether they may do business in Uzbekistan.</p>
<p>Estimated energy reserves in the former Soviet republic are 5.429 trillion cubic metres natural gas, 4.4 billion tonnes of oil and 629 million tonnes of gas condensate.</p>
<p>Bakrie's Sutrisno said the $600 million oil and gas deal, the firm's single biggest investment project in Uzbekistan, included a $250 million agreement with state oil and gas concern Uzbekneftegaz to work mature oil fields.</p>
<p>The second, smaller deal, was for a fertiliser plant, and a final decision for the go-ahead would be taken in two months, Sutrisno said.</p>
<p>Bakrie has already invested in a multi-million dollar telecoms joint venture in Uzbekistan and plans further co-operation in this sector.</p>
<p>A source at the State Property Committee confirmed the deals, adding that domestic enterprises would benefit.</p>
<p>&quot;These documents open the way for feasibility studies and work on concrete projects with sub-contractors, including Uzbekneftegaz and other state bodies,&quot; the source, who declined to be named, said.</p>
<p>His remarks were mirrored by Sutrisno, who said the priority for both projects was to supply oil, gas, gas condensates and fertilisers to the domestic market first and foremost, although export opportunities would be considered.</p>
<p>-- Moscow Newsroom +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UZBK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25130">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TASHKENT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UZBEKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
