<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609921" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Euro fuel oil broadly steady, low sulphur bid high.</title>
<headline>Euro fuel oil broadly steady, low sulphur bid high.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European fuel oil prices were broadly steady in thin pre-weekend trade with markets still unimpressed by crude oil's strength, traders said.</p>
<p>Poor bunker demand and aggressive selling by one refiner in Rotterdam pushed high sulpur barge prices down $1 to sit at $80/$81 fob a tonne, the bottom end of the last two months' range.</p>
<p>Solid flows of Russian cracked fuel from St.Petersburg began to weigh on the ARA barge market, traders said, while refinery run cuts were unlikely to ease the pressure of over-supply for some time.</p>
<p>Low sulphur was supported by one bid in the market at $97 fob a tonne from a trader but there was no prompt supply available to meet it.</p>
<p>&quot;Its very easy to bid high when you know the cargo is not there but I think the bidder would actually buy at that number if the material was there,&quot; said one supplier.</p>
<p>A cargo of low sulphur straight-run was heard sold quietly out of Scandinavia on Thursday for a price believed to be around $109-$110 a tonne fob. Sellers were originally hoping to achieve better than the $110 mark but buying interest softened to prevent it.  </p>
<p>Russian straight-run cargoes were scarce and commanding good premiums.</p>
<p>- London newsroom +44 171 542 8060</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
