<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609910" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: European wheat lower as old crop fades.</title>
<headline>European wheat lower as old crop fades.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European wheat prices fell this week as the old crop played itself out and many market players marked time, awaiting more indications on how the new crop market will shape up.</p>
<p>French old-crop wheat drifted lower on fading demand, with consumers mostly covered until the new harvest, dealers said.</p>
<p>On the export front there was also very little news to move wheat prices as the European Union on Thursday maintained its 15 Ecus per tonne tax on wheat exports.</p>
<p>The EU gave no signal on what its approach to new crop exports would be.</p>
<p>Intra-EU trade was quiet but dealers said a new wave of British wheat imports to Spain at competitive prices may add pressure to French wheat.</p>
<p>New-crop wheat slipped on improved prospects for the 1997 harvest as rain since the last week of April has dampened fears of a drought.</p>
<p>Old crop barley prices were easier this week. News Saudi Arabia bought 700,000 tonnes of feed barley for July delivery failed to boost French prices. The EU, near the end of its campaign, is expected to supply only 100,000 to 200,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>On Thursday an EU official signalled the barley export season was drawing to a close. He said the EU had no intention of easing a 20 Ecus per tonne penalty on barley exports in June nor opening a special round of sales of German intervention to facilitate barley sales to the Saudis.</p>
<p>He said this could be done with export licences already in the market.</p>
<p>On Thursday the EU granted only 21,540 tonnes of free-market barley with an export refund of 14.00 Ecus per tonne.</p>
<p>Maize prices rose as buyers stepped up offers in the face of sidelined sellers. On Friday French maize ignored news that the EU rejected bids for the preferential import of 500,000 tonnes of maize into Spain but added 300,000 tonnes to the initial allocation.</p>
<p>Some dealers however said they doubted Spain could absorb the new maize allocation in the face of recent outbreaks of swine fever and ahead of the arrival of the new wheat and barley crops.</p>
<p>But EU grain industry sources said Spain's wheat and barley crops were hit by a prolonged drought and may not be that much of a threat.</p>
<p>UK futures hit contract lows this week. Physical traders complained that low prices were stifling farmer selling, but some conceded that buyers were still looking for lower levels. &quot;At these levels you can't get any physical supplies,&quot; one broker said. &quot;Farmers are not selling a tonne,&quot; another said.</p>
<p>British supplies are still competitive with French into Spain and Portugal, and there is still demand for fob grain, one trader said. Consumer demand is limited.</p>
<p>He noted the big discount between July and September. &quot;It's not been like this for as long as I've been trading,&quot; he said. &quot;Somebody's bound to be prepared to hold it (the old crop).&quot;</p>
<p>While futures had been hit by the perception that there was still a big long position on July, persuading market players that now was the time to bale out and force prices lower, the physical market was still dealing with the remaining surplus. the trader was optimistic. &quot;It's slowly going,&quot; he said. &quot;We've still got all of June and July until the harvest starts to deal with it.&quot;</p>
<p>Wheat prices in Germany prove to be relatively robust amid a generally easier tone in Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a lack of aggressive sellers and that is underpinning new crop prices,&quot; one broker said.</p>
<p>&quot;Old crop prices are also resilient and their levels will depend on what becomes available from Britain and Denmark over the next few weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders said that some major grain houses were long and preferred to lock in high prices as long as possible while farmer reluctance to sell new crop wheat also helped to keep levels firm.</p>
<p>Bread wheat in the domestic market remained around 285 marks free Hamburg while feed wheat in the country's west was available at 277.50-280 and buyers were looking for 272.50.</p>
<p>Barley sellers were still offering what brokers consider a cheap 252.50-255 marks a tonne cif range on the new crop.</p>
<p>&quot;With the fob price nearing 240 for the new crop, we're approaching intervention levels,&quot; one broker said.</p>
<p>Spanish grains prices were sharply lower --with the exception of durum wheat-- due to the start of barley harvesting in some areas and increased imports from other European countries, traders said.</p>
<p>Maize prices fell sharply after Spain's import quota was raised by the EU on Thursday.</p>
<p>Barley was also significantly lower, although traders noted that farmers are still withholding some stocks from last year in the hope that the price will rise again.</p>
<p>But they predict that it could fall as low as 22,500 as the harvest advances.</p>
<p>Feed wheat was depressed by UK exports, also pressuring milling wheat lower, dealers said.</p>
<p>But durum wheat was sharply higher, still affected by a diminished harvest in Spain and also by higher prices in France pressuring upwards.</p>
<p>Italian durum wheat prices fell slightly over the past week as a result of a lack of demand with consumers looking more towards the next crop harvest.</p>
<p>Soft wheat prices sere slightly higher but within last week's already narrow range. The Italian Insitute for Agricultural Studies (Ismea) noted that demand was modest and the focus, also in this case, was on the next harvest.  </p>
<p>The following are benchmark European prices. French prices exclude carrying charges. Italian durum wheat prices refer to official closing prices on the Milan mercantile exchange.</p>
<p>						 May 23	     May 16</p>
<p>Rouen-dlvd wheat May		  830 ffr ($146) 840</p>
<p>Rouen dlvd wheat Sept-Dec     880-885 ffr ($154-155) 885-890</p>
<p>Rouen dlvd barley May		 835 ffr ($147)     860</p>
<p>Bordeaux dlvd maize June-July     850 ffr ($149)     840</p>
<p>May-June</p>
<p>German Hamburg Exch br wheat   285.00 Dm ($169)	285.00</p>
<p>	   (12.5 pct spot)</p>
<p>German Hamburg Exch feed wheat 280.00 Dm ($166)	280.00</p>
<p>UK feed wheat E. Anglia (May)   88.00 stg ($143)	91.00</p>
<p>UK feed barley E. Anglia (May)  89.00 stg ($145)	92.75</p>
<p>(Jun)</p>
<p>Spain feed wheat		   25,000 ptas ($175)     26,000</p>
<p>Spain milling wheat     26,500-27,000 ptas ($186-189) 28,000</p>
<p>Spain durum wheat		  31,000 ptas ($217)     29,000</p>
<p>Spain barley		24,100-25,000 ptas ($169-175) 26,000</p>
<p>Spain maize			  24,250 ptas ($170)</p>
<p>24,800-25,000</p>
<p>Italy wheat		   322-323,000 lire ($193-194)</p>
<p>321-323,000</p>
<p>Italy durum (North)	 377-380,000 lire ($227-228)</p>
<p>380-383,000</p>
<p>Italy durum (Centre)	379-382,000 lire ($228-230)</p>
<p>382-385,000</p>
<p>Italy maize		   264-265,000 lire ($159)</p>
<p>266-267,000</p>
<p>--Compiled by Christopher Lyddon in London, with contributions from Milan, Paris, Hamburg and Madrid.</p>
<p>One dollar equals 5.696 French Francs, 1.69 German Marks, 0.615 Pounds Sterling, 142.5 Spanish Pesetas and 1,664 Italian Lire)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
