<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609945" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Expectations of June 10 UK budget fade - analysts.</title>
<headline>Expectations of June 10 UK budget fade - analysts.</headline>
<byline>Cheryl Juckes</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Expectations of a UK budget on June 10 have all but evaporated given that, less than three weeks before the widely anticipated date, the new Labour government has not announced a date.</p>
<p>&quot;June 10 was looking very early in any case and they're quite simply running out of time,&quot; said Yamaichi chief economist John Shepperd. &quot;Budgets are inherently complex affairs and they take time.&quot;</p>
<p>Labour ousted the 18-year old Conservative administration on May 1 and has since barely paused for breath.</p>
<p>It has raised interest rates to stand at 6.25 percent, given the Bank of England the power to set rates and as well as stripping it of its regulatory role and control of the gilt market.</p>
<p>Given the drain on Treasury time of all the changes it has made, it would be surprising if it had also managed prepare a budget for June 10, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;That window has now closed,&quot; said NatWest Markets UK economist Geoff Dicks.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that Parliament has disappeared off on a week's Whitsun recess, without revealing the date, suggests it's not going to be June 10,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Parliament closed on Thursday and will not reconvene until June 2.  </p>
<p>The date of the budget is traditionally announced to the House of Commons although there is nothing to stop Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown from brushing aside this convention.</p>
<p>The Financial Times said in an article on Friday that July 3 was now the favourite date for the budget but said the Treasury was also believed to be looking at late June.</p>
<p>The UK Treasury itself said it did not yet have a date for the budget.</p>
<p>Analysts said that the longer it took to prepare the budget, the more speculation there would be that it would be a large package rather than one simply on the manifesto promises.</p>
<p>Labour pledged to hold a budget within two months of taking office to announce the so-called Windfall Tax on privatised utility firms, the welfare-to-work scheme and the cutting of the rate of value added tax on domestic fuel to 5.0 percent from 8.0 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;The term &quot;mini-budget&quot; that was doing the rounds was always going to be a misnomer even if the budget was just confirming the manifesto commitments,&quot; Yamaichi's Shepperd said.</p>
<p>&quot;But it's quite clear that Gordon Brown has hit the ground running and what we're looking at is a full blown serious budget,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The importance the market attaches to the budget is overwhelming so it's much better to have it several weeks later, than to have it earlier and look as if you're rushing.&quot;</p>
<p>--London newsroom +44 171 542 5109</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
