<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609942" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: World coffee supplies seen tight until September.</title>
<headline>World coffee supplies seen tight until September.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>World coffee supplies are likely to stay tight until September, Association of Coffee Producing Countries' secretary general Robeiro Oliveira Silva said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect a certain tightness in the market especially for the period from July to September,&quot; Silva told reporters on the margins of the International Coffee Organisation talks in London.  </p>
<p>The 14-member ACPC, anxious to defend prices after the present fever in the market abates, on Wednesday hammered out an accord to limit total exports by the members to 52.75 million 60-kg bags for the 12 months from July 1. This was about the same as the volume limit they had set under current curbs expiring June 30.</p>
<p>Silva said the agreement was meant to preserve the current supply co-ordination among the producers. &quot;We have to do it in a way that we don't disrupt supply to the market, but at the same time, keep the control over this variable, supply, on the market,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He also said nobody was confident over the medium-term market direction. &quot;The market is subject to so many wild swings. We have to try to keep it under control at least on our side.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if there was enough coffee supply in the market, he said &quot;in Europe yes...of the coffee that you want.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The only problem really is concentrated in the U.S. We have coffee that usually would go to the U.S. coming to Europe.&quot; He said the supply problems in the U.S. were due to &quot;technical problems&quot; and this was beyond producer control.</p>
<p>He also said roasters in Europe were able to cover much more than their counterparts in the U.S. &quot;When U.S. roasters realised they would have (supply) problems, coffee was simply not there.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked why the ACPC meeting on Wednesday deferred any quota allocation until after September, he said &quot;we want to keep an open mind in terms of evolution of supply demand fundamentals.&quot; Producers were not certain whether their recent stock build-up was due to consumer holdings.</p>
<p>The next ACPC council meeting was scheduled for September, he said. A technical group would meet before September to study the market and stocks situation.</p>
<p>--Jalil Hamid, London newsroom +44 171 542 4985</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100137">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
