<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609922" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS -British universites launch debut bond issue.</title>
<headline>FOCUS -British universites launch debut bond issue.</headline>
<byline>Dan Lalor</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A group of anonymous British universities banded together successfully on Friday to raise 48 million pounds ($80 million) in international capital markets, Bankers Trust said as arranger.</p>
<p>&quot;We are very pleased with the reception. There was a competing deal in the market so some of the orders were scaled back. But it has gone very well,&quot; said BT vice-president head of Eurobond syndication Vincent Keith.</p>
<p>The pre-marketed 29-year deal for Varsity Funding (Holdings), a special purpose finance vehicle, was the first to be backed by a portfolio of university properties, BT said.</p>
<p>However, the identity of the universities involved remained a closely guarded secret.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a grey box structure. People know that the underlying notes are university obligations secured by prime university properties,&quot; BT's Keith said. &quot;Beyond that it's wrapped by FSA.&quot;</p>
<p>The deal is guaranteed by Financial Security Assurance, a company which specialises in insuring bond issues, both the principal amount and coupon repayments.</p>
<p>FSA's backing meant the notes carry AAA ratings from both main credit rating agencies -- Moody's Investors Service and Standard and Poor's Corp.</p>
<p>The notes were priced to yield 65 basis points over Britain's 8.00 percent gilt due 2021. The 6.418 percent coupon will step up by 0.25 percentage point per annum until 2007. The bond then amortises until maturity, giving an average life of just over 22 years.</p>
<p>The competing deal was a 100 million stg debenture due 2022 from Edinburgh Investment Trust.</p>
<p>A British university bond has been on the back burner for some years.</p>
<p>Analysts noted that British universities and colleges have been vulnerable in the past to shifts in the pattern of higher education provision by the government of the day.</p>
<p>The new Labour Party administration, which came to power on a slogan of &quot;Education, education and education&quot; among others, has announced initiatives to increase funding at all levels.</p>
<p>Analysts drew comparisons between a university deal and those in the past from British housing associations which banded together to raise funds, and also with the PUBCO bond issued jointly and severally by a group of British breweries.</p>
<p>Like the PUBCO deal in which only smaller breweries took part, analysts said blue chip educators such as Oxford and Cambridge might not be in the university bond.</p>
<p>&quot;Oxford and Cambridge don't need the money,&quot; a banker said. &quot;As always in life it's the lesser credits that need the cash, particularly some of the newer universities.&quot;</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 8863</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
