<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609920" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FORECAST - Strong Q4 needed to spice up EMI.</title>
<headline>FORECAST - Strong Q4 needed to spice up EMI.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>EMI Group Plc, one of the world's top music companies, will have to deliver on its promise of a very strong final quarter on Tuesday, to meet analysts' forecasts of pre-tax, pre-exceptional profit of around 370-400 million stg for the year.</p>
<p>EMI finance director Simon Duffy said in February that the group was banking on a record fourth quarter to allow it to hit those targets for the year to end-March.</p>
<p>EMI, which has seen its shares underperform the UK media sector by around 13 percent since it demerged from Thorn Plc last August -- partly because an expected bid failed to emerge -- posted 1996 proforma pre-tax profit of 367 million stg.</p>
<p>Pre-tax profits before exceptional items fell six percent to 293.3 million pounds in the nine months to end-December.</p>
<p>The success of EMI's Spice Girls quintet has been a highlight and earnings should feed through in the fourth quarter -- and the first quarter of next year -- in a year in which the firm has been hit by a slowdown in growth in music sales. The U.S., in particular, has been affected.</p>
<p>Moreover, the strength of sterling is expected to wipe some 25 million stg off profits.</p>
<p>But Jason Crisp, media analyst at SogGen, said: &quot;You'll still see double digit growth in earnings this year.&quot;</p>
<p>EMI, which owns the Dillons bookstore, has also  revived in interviews old speculation that it might consider buying a book publisher. The company had modest debt of 230.8 million stg at December 31.</p>
<p>EMI, which earlier this month paid 18 million stg for worldwide distribution rights to the back catalogue of recordings by rock star David Bowie, believes releases from a number of its top artists should boost the final three months.</p>
<p>Britain's Blur, Japan's Yumi Matsutoya and Jon Secada, a big star in the U.S. and Latin America, all put out new material.</p>
<p>The Spice Girls have also continued to flourish, their debut album &quot;Spice&quot; having clocked up more than 10 million sales worldwide.</p>
<p>EMI shares have fallen some two pounds from their demerger price of 1460p last August. EMI is the only pure music company among the big players in the industry and was regarded as a natural bid target.</p>
<p>But analysts say despite the uninspired stock, which was trading up 1.0p at 1211p on Friday, the possibility of a bid is likely to underpin performance.</p>
<p>&quot;...we believe the chances of a bid for EMI in the short term are slight,&quot; said Salomon Brothers' analyst Ivor Jones. &quot;However, we believe the possibility of a bid should remain at the back of investors' minds and put a floor under the share price.&quot;</p>
<p>Jones said any successful bid would have to top 8.0 billion stg, adding that only Canadian drinks and entertainment group Seagram Co Ltd is sufficiently free of major competition concerns to contemplate such a move.</p>
<p>A newspaper report last month said EMI had had abortive merger talks with Seagram, owner of the MCA record label. But EMI declined comment.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34520">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
