<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609960" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT -T-bonds to seek refuge at 108-30.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT -T-bonds to seek refuge at 108-30.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>June T-bond futures will look for support at 108-30 on Friday, but risk a drop lower if that fails, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>The 108-30 was the low on May 8 and also on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The contract went through 109-00 yesterday, but bounced at 108-30,&quot; said Gerry Celaya, senior technical analyst at American Express Bank in London.</p>
<p>June T-bonds were trading at 109-07 at 1025 GMT, 5/32 above the Chicago settlement price. Philippe Cahen, technical analyst at Credit Lyonnais in Paris, also found support for T-bonds at 108-31.</p>
<p>Cahen said the lower boundary of Bollinger bands on an hourly basis offered the market a good prop at this level.</p>
<p>Bollinger bands are lines drawn at standard deviations around the price action, to give support and resistance.</p>
<p>On a daily basis, Cahen put support at 108-25. &quot;If we break 108-25 we must watch this level very carefully, as the market could go much lower,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the problem was there was not much support for T-bonds between that level and 106-08.</p>
<p>Celaya found further support for the contract at 108-12, the low on April 30.</p>
<p>On the upside, Cahen said Bollinger band resistance comes in at 109-09.</p>
<p>&quot;The next resistance after that is the daily moving average of Bollingers at the 109-23 level,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But I think it will be very difficult to go towards this level today.&quot;</p>
<p>Celaya found resistance for the contract at 109-13, and at the 109-18/20 area.</p>
<p>September Eurodollar futures were at 93.965 in automated trade at 1042 GMT, up 0.01.</p>
<p>-- Carolyn Cohn, International Bonds Unit +44 171 542 6320</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
