<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609970" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: U.S. stocks in London steady, investors cautious.</title>
<headline>U.S. stocks in London steady, investors cautious.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. shares were little changed in quiet trade, with many participants reluctant to take new positions ahead of the long holiday weekend.</p>
<p>Rising bond yields also kept players on edge, dealers here said.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is pretty nervy this morning. With the (U.S. 30-year) long bond yield threatening to go through the magic seven percent level again, people are a bit cautious,&quot; one market maker said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Dow might try and go a bit higher today but with the U.S. shut on Monday, I can't see it going to far.&quot;  </p>
<p>U.S. financial markets will be closed on Monday, May 26 in observance of the annual Memorial Day holiday.</p>
<p>The yield on the benchmark U.S. 30-year long bond was standing at 6.99 percent by 1030 GMT, prompting fears that the Dow Industrials Average could be on the verge of a downward correction.</p>
<p>The Dow's 700-point decline from mid-March to mid-April coincided with rising yields, which saw the long bond yield peak at around 7.20 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;The threat of higher interest rates is still hanging over this market. Wall Street managed to shrug the threat aside the last time, but it may not be so resilient in the run-up to the next FOMC meeting in July,&quot; another dealer said.</p>
<p>Anheuser-Busch Companies Inc. slipped $3/8 to $42-3/8, after credit rating agency Standard &amp; Poors lowered its corporate credit and senior unsecured debt ratings on the U.S. brewer.</p>
<p>General Motors Corp eased $1/4 to $56-1/2. after a Wall Street Journal report said the company was having a problem manufacturing one of its cars, due to a strike at one of the two plants that builds the model.</p>
<p>The U.S. June T-bond was up 5/32 to 109-8/32, while the June S&amp;P 500 futures contract rose 0.75 to 841.00.</p>
<p>-- Dale Faulken, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
