<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609955" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Laporte current yr trade in line with plans.</title>
<headline>Laporte current yr trade in line with plans.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>British speciality chemicals group Laporte Plc said on Friday that despite the strength of the sterling posing challenging conditions, its performance in the first four months of the current year was in line with its plans.  </p>
<p>The company's chairman, George Duncan, told the annual meeting of shareholders that it had reached an agreement to sell its U.S. adhesives and sealants businesses for a consideration of about 90 million stg.</p>
<p>The sale will result in an exceptional gain, before expenses and tax, of about 13 million stg after a goodwill write-off of 55 million stg.</p>
<p>The sale is expected to be completed in the third quarter, Duncan said.  </p>
<p>These businesses reported sales of 103 million stg and operating profits of 11 million stg in the year to December 31, 1996 with its net assets valued at 22 million stg as of that date.</p>
<p>&quot;These businesses are in line with the group's stated strategy of focusing on businesses which have market leadership in the growth sectors of the international speciality chemicals and performance materials markets...,&quot; Duncan said.</p>
<p>He said the company last month approved capital investments of 23 million stg, out of which 15 million will be invested to set up a silicone wafer reclaim facility in Taiwan.</p>
<p>--London Newsroom +44 171 542 4366</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
