<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609963" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Options - Coffee stays active, volatility climbs.</title>
<headline>Options - Coffee stays active, volatility climbs.</headline>
<byline>Medora Lee</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Coffee options activity stayed brisk this week, with traders mostly setting up for further gains in the underlying futures.</p>
<p>At-the-money implied September coffee volatility has soared to about 60 percent from 44 percent about a week ago. November leapt to 55 percent from about 45 percent last week.</p>
<p>But traders said 55- to 60-percent levels on September were in-line with historical volatility. They said the jump seems bigger because sales earlier this year near 40 percent were considered low.</p>
<p>This week's volatility jump has come off the heels of a surging futures market. July scored a contract high on Monday after an early burst of fund buying.</p>
<p>Options traders said a large trade house that sold 1,000 September calls last week at the $2,000 and $2,300 strikes was forced to buy large amounts of underlying futures earlier this week to stay hedged as underlying prices surged. They estimated the options-related buying added about $50 to already climbing futures prices early in the week.</p>
<p>They said the trade house is still holding its short September call position.</p>
<p>Options buying this week was seen across months but mostly in September calls as investors piled in on expectations of further gains in underlying prices.</p>
<p>Most September purchases have been in the out-of-the-money strikes between $2,100 and $2,800. He said even deep out-of-the-money calls were trading at very high volatilities because &quot;people still don't want to go short out-of-the-money calls in September, particularly if there are any signs of frost (in Brazil),&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>September $2,300 calls were seen trading as high as 73 percent volatility earlier this week, he said. Volatility is expected to rise much higher if underlying futures make another foray up into uncharted territory.</p>
<p>Call spreads were also popular in July and September. Traders sold July calls between the $1,750 and $1,850 strikes and bought September between $2,000 and $2,100. They said investors sold the nearby because people did not want to be short September calls.</p>
<p>As a result of the spreading, traders said July volatilities have gradually eased relative to forward months. At-the-money implied July volatility peaked near 55 percent and settled on Thursday near 46 percent, but traders said July activity was low.</p>
<p>While coffee options stayed busy, cocoa options remained lackluster. With little movement in the underlying futures market, options trading was at a near standstill.</p>
<p>July cocoa futures have stuck to a range of about 1,008 and 1,036 stg per tonne this week.</p>
<p>Earlier in the week, a floor trader crossed about 500 forward month options with back-month futures, but traders said that was to get out of a position established a few months ago.</p>
<p>Implied, at-the-money July cocoa options volatility was seen steady near 30 percent and September between 28.5 to 29 percent.</p>
<p>--London newsroom, +44 171 542 8072</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
