<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609924" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK shares set for nervous week,upside seen limited.</title>
<headline>UK shares set for nervous week,upside seen limited.</headline>
<byline>Dale Faulken</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The UK share market is unlikely to make much headway next week as rising bond yields and the spectre of higher interest rates weighs on investor sentiment, dealers and strategists said.</p>
<p>A wall of windfall cash from looming building society flotations may underpin the market for a few more weeks but the FTSE 100, which is trading within a whisker of its record closing peak, is destined to suffer a setback sooner rather than later, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Halifax and Norwich (mutuals) mania is helping to keep up the financial sector and the market in general,&quot; said Richard Marshall, strategist at Investment Research of Cambridge Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;But the FTSE is still on the over-bought side and I think there is going to be a sharp correction at some stage, perhaps starting next week.&quot;</p>
<p>Marshall cited a slump in UK gilts on Thursday as a clear sign that share prices were overstretched. Gilts plunged more than a full point and breached key support levels on Thursday after a disappointing gilt auction.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't believe the share market won't follow the gilts. I certainly can't see the FTSE making it back to its record highs next week.&quot;</p>
<p>Marshall thinks the FTSE will fall back to around the 4,450 level before attempting a fresh assault on its record closing high of 4,693.9, set on May 16.</p>
<p>Other market watchers, while convinced a correction is due, are not convinced the FTSE's recent rally will end as soon as next week, however.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no doubt that the FTSE is getting near the top but it still doesn't pay to sell this market just yet,&quot; the head of trading at a large brokerage said.</p>
<p>&quot;Institutions still have a lot of money and appear to be willing to spend it. They will be piling into the building societies and until those flotations are out of the way, the market should at least remain steady.&quot;</p>
<p>The Halifax Building Society, Britain's biggest home loan provider, is expected to convert into a public listed company on June 2. The Halifax float will be followed by the listing of insurer Norwich Union on June 16.</p>
<p>Both companies will qualify for inclusion in the FTSE 100 making it necessary for fund managers to take stakes.</p>
<p>A buying frenzy for these new financials would not be enough to prevent the FTSE from a setback if rising bond yields spook U.S. investors on Wall Street, another trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;Building society windfalls are all well and good but the real story next week as it has been most weeks, is Wall Street,&quot; the head of sales and trading at a large investment bank said.</p>
<p>&quot;If the Dow cracks, the Halifax will only cushion the fall -- it won't stop it.&quot;</p>
<p>With the yield on the benchmark U.S. 30-year long bond hovering just under the seven percent level, some dealers are worried that the Dow could be about to suffer another setback, similar to its 10 percent decline earlier this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The last time the bond yield was above seven percent the Dow fell 700 points,&quot; one senior dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;The closer we get to July and the next FOMC meeting, the more the market will worry about higher U.S. interest rates. Both of these factors will make it difficult for the Dow and the FTSE to do anything spectacular in the coming few weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>Economic data due next week includes UK money supply and the latest distributive trades survey from the Confederation of British Industry. U.S. personal income, leading indicators, and the May survey from the U.S. National Association of Purchasing Managers are also scheduled for release.</p>
<p>Only a handful of large companies are due to report results. Full-year numbers from EMI Plc and Thorn Plc are due on Tuesday followed by 12-month figures from United Utilities and Siebe Plc on Thursday.</p>
<p>London financial markets are close on Monday, May 26 for a Spring Bank Holiday.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
