<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609906" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK rates up, Germany on hold, Italy to cut-futures.</title>
<headline>UK rates up, Germany on hold, Italy to cut-futures.</headline>
<byline>Tara FitzGerald</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Interest rates rises in Britain, converging rates in Germany and France, and falling rates in Italy are on the way, according to European interest rate futures, analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>And for once the markets' views on rates match economists' views fairly accurately.</p>
<p>&quot;In historical terms, the markets are not far off presenting an accurate picture,&quot; said Peter Osler, head of research at GNI Ltd in London. &quot;The markets have been very wrong before but at the moment I don't think they are far out.&quot;</p>
<p>Short-term interest rate futures traded on London exchange LIFFE and France's MATIF reveal the markets' interest rate view.</p>
<p>Three-month sterling interest rate futures for December, known as short sterling, stand at 92.99, factoring in money market rates of around seven percent by the end of the year.</p>
<p>British base rates currently stand at 6.25 percent.</p>
<p>At 1000 GMT, June short sterling was trading at 93.43, indicating anything between unchanged to a 25 basis point hike is priced into the market for the near term.</p>
<p>&quot;Looking at the UK, I do think we'll get another rate hike, and the markets are also looking for that,&quot; said Gianpaolo Mosconi, bonds analyst at Sanwa International in London.</p>
<p>&quot;One reason is the Chancellor's budget is coming up. On the fiscal side they're going to make quite a bit of money and that should help the government and the Bank of England so they won't need to raise rates so much.&quot;</p>
<p>British Chancellor of the Exchequer Gordon Brown is due to announce a budget in June or July, the first of the new Labour government.</p>
<p>Analysts said rates in France and Germany were likely to move in tandem to a large extent, converging as the planned start for European Economic and monetary union (EMU), on January 1, 1999 approached.</p>
<p>&quot;In Germany I see rates staying fairly close to what they are now for a while and that is what the curve is effectively saying. I think they are telling the right story, that interest rates in Germany have levelled off,&quot; said Mosconi.</p>
<p>&quot;There's no real need to cut in Germany as I think the economy will gradually pick up momentum.&quot;</p>
<p>The interest rate picture in France looked much the same as that of Germany, with both interest rate futures markets predicting no moves in the near term and money market rates edging higher by the end of the year.</p>
<p>The German repo rate is currently at three percent, while the French intervention rate stands at 3.10 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;French monetary policy is quite similar to Germany's. Once the election is over and if the current (centre right) coalition remains in power, which seems likely, then there could be a further marginal rate change, but nothing major. We could see a small convergence towards Germany,&quot; said Audrey Childe Freeman, economist at CIBC Wood Gundy here.</p>
<p>France holds the first round of its parliamentary elections on Sunday with the final round on June 1.</p>
<p>In Italy, rate cuts already priced into the Eurolira market were also in line with analysts' predictions.</p>
<p>They said after recent soft Italian inflation data and with a strong lira, the case for a rate cut was strong.</p>
<p>Italy's discount rate currently stands at 6.75 percent. At 1011 GMT, June Eurolira was at 93.35, while December Eurolira reflected market rates around 40 basis points below there.</p>
<p>Mosconi said with the lira below 995 to the mark, this provided the perfect opportunity to cut rates.</p>
<p>&quot;Looking down the road, the market pattern is for rate cuts (in Italy) and I quite agree with that. We'll get a rate cut very soon, if not this week then once the French elections are out of the way,&quot;</p>
<p>-- International Bonds Unit, +44 171 542 4041</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
