<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609930" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FORECAST-Hot topics for water firms are tax, spend.</title>
<headline>FORECAST-Hot topics for water firms are tax, spend.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>As the flood of British water and sewerage company annual results starts next week, with four firms reporting, analysts said the hot topics will be tax and spend.</p>
<p>&quot;The profit numbers are not that important...we'll be watching everything they say on the windfall tax...and responses to the question of leakage,&quot; said Nigel Hawkins of Yamaichi.</p>
<p>The new Labour Government has vowed to introduce a one-off tax on the &quot;excess profits&quot; of privatised utilities and water firms are widely considered to be in its sights.</p>
<p>The government also announced it would set mandatory targets for cutting leakage for the companies at a special &quot;crisis summit&quot; this week to tackle the worst drought in Britain for 200 years.</p>
<p>The companies have been given three weeks to respond to the plans.</p>
<p>The four companies reporting next week are all expected to show increased profits and dividends, although analysts said the shareholder payout might be muted, while the political spotlight shines.</p>
<p>Anglian Water Plc should see pretax profits of 242-260 million stg, up from 238.6 million, when it reports on Wednesday and is expected to pay out a total dividend of 34-34.5 pence per share, compared with 30 pence a year ago.</p>
<p>On Thursday, South West Water Plc is eyed for pretax profits of 118-140 million stg, up from 109.1 million, with a dividend of around 36.6-36.7 pence per share compared with 30.5 pence.</p>
<p>United Utilities plc, a combined water and electricity firm, should turn in annual pretax profits of 458-475 million stg on Thursday, compared with 464.2 million previously, with wide ranges on the amount of exceptionals expected for restructuring and overseas operations.</p>
<p>Yorkshire Water plc completes next week's stream of results on Friday with pretax profits of 211-220 million stg expected.</p>
<p>Yorkshire's total dividend is seen in a range of 17.5-19.3 pence per share. Its payout last year was 31 pence per share but Yorkshire made a share split operation with a buyback in January.</p>
<p>&quot;On dividends, there is an expectation of 13-15 percent growth but they might play safe in view of the windfall tax,&quot; Hawkins said.</p>
<p>The government has said the one-off tax should &quot;comfortably&quot; fund a three billion stg plan to cut unemployment but further details have not been disclosed ahead of a first budget, likely in June or July.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be a helpful approach if the companies were to say we can offer x percent growth based on y tax,&quot; said Rebecca Reehan at Dresdner Kleinwort Benson.</p>
<p>&quot;The companies have so far been cagey on the figures they are using for the tax in terms of underpinning dividend growth,&quot; said one analyst who asked not to be identified.</p>
<p>At the same time, analysts will be watching for any indications from the companies on costs associated with fulfilling the government's challenges on leakage and other issues laid out at the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Some of the government's proposals could have an impact on costs ahead of the next price review. It would be interesting to have some comments on that,&quot; the analyst said.</p>
<p>Water firms, privatised by the previous Conservative government in 1989, have come under fierce criticism for making huge profits, payouts and pay packets, while over 800 million gallons of supplies leak from pipes every day.</p>
<p>Labour's windfall tax was, as a result, an unusually popular fiscal plan, while its tough line on leakage has been welcomed by consumer groups and environmentalists alike. -- Jo Winterbottom, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I17000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
