<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609974" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Zeneca says underlying profits up 15 pct.</title>
<headline>Zeneca says underlying profits up 15 pct.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>British bioscience company Zeneca Group Plc said on Friday that its underlying pre-tax profits in the first four months of 1997 were up 15 percent year-on-year at constant exchange rates.  </p>
<p>Chairman Sir Sidney Lipworth told the group's annual meeting that the gain was &quot;at a similar rate to that achieved in the first half of 1996, despite higher costs associated with the development, launch and roll-out of many new products.&quot;</p>
<p>Lipworth said the rise in the pound &quot;has had a dampening effect on this growth when reported in sterling...but it has had no effect on the real underlying performance which continues apace.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the sale of newly-launched products &quot;continue to meet fully our targets and expectations.&quot;  </p>
<p>Lipworth said group pre-tax profit before exceptional items had doubled from 442 million stg in 1992 to more than 1.0 billion stg in 1996, with operating profit rising at a compound annual rate of 15 percent.</p>
<p>Shares in Zeneca edged up 10 pence to 1884 pence in late morning trading following the announcement.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
