<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609914" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Euro oil swaps - Brent CFDs rocket on physical deal.</title>
<headline>Euro oil swaps - Brent CFDs rocket on physical deal.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European oil swaps were steady or narrowly firmer, bar storming Brent crude CFDs which rocketed on the back of a physical cargo deal and fuel oil which dropped $2.</p>
<p>May 27-30 CFDs gained sharply to 12 cents over July compared with 2.5 cents under July on Thursday. Dated Brent jumped nearly 20 cents as a cargo due to load June 9-11 attracted July Brent +17 cents.</p>
<p>Further out CFDs were also stronger, but by a lesser degree. June 2-6 was around 12.5 cents under July compared, a rise of four cents or so while June 9-13 firmed to 13 cents under compared with 14 cents under.</p>
<p>Heavy fuel swaps fell $2 a tonne to trade at $82 for June barges although that level was well bid later.</p>
<p>Further forward the market was also under pressure with the third quarter talking $86.75 a tonne and the fourth $94 after trading at $94.75 on Thursday.</p>
<p>The first quarter next year remained some $3.75 a tonne above the fourth quarter which some dealers saw as too wide.</p>
<p>&quot;If there are any time trades it probably selling that spread,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>Low sulphur was little changed after physical trade reported at $97 fob NWE on Thursday.</p>
<p>The third and fourth quarters were pegged around $98 and $102.50 respectively.</p>
<p>A June gasoline swap went at $209.75 although physical Eurograde barges had been sold earlier at $212 fob ARA. This eased back to $209-211.</p>
<p>Naphtha swaps were quiet with support from the physical market. June was fractionally stronger by 25-50 cents at $193 with July contangoed by 50 cents.</p>
<p>-- Matthew Jones, London Newsroom +44 171 542 8980</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
