<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609968" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Newspaper magnate deals blow to UK Conservatives.</title>
<headline>Newspaper magnate deals blow to UK Conservatives.</headline>
<byline>Gerrard Raven</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Newspaper magnate Lord Vere Rothermere landed a further blow to Britain's battered Conservatives on Friday by joining the Labour ranks in the House of Lords and showering Prime Minister Tony Blair with praise.</p>
<p>Rothermere, proprietor of the Daily Mail &amp; General Trust Plc, became the latest in a series of traditionally pro-Conservative newspaper owners to declare their allegiance to the party's main foes.</p>
<p>With the Conservatives embroiled in a row over how to choose a new leader after a shattering defeat at the polls, his move was another sign of the unravelling of a political coalition which had ruled Britain since 1979 until the May 1 election.</p>
<p>On election day, the Mail told its readers: &quot;There is a terrible danger that the British people, drugged by the mantra It's time for a change', are stumbling, eyes glazed, into an election that could undo 1,000 years of our nation's history.&quot;</p>
<p>But writing in London's Evening Standard, which he also owns, Rothermere said he had quit the independent crossbenches in the upper House for the Labour side &quot;as a positive act, for today I wish to support Tony Blair's administration&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Tony Blair is a true representative of his generation...He understands absolutely the temper of the times and the spirit of the age,&quot; Rothermere wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course he will make mistakes, but in him I feel Britain has got a strong and dedicated prime minister who has a vision of the wider horizons.&quot;</p>
<p>The Conservatives have generally enjoyed the backing of a majority of Britain's national newspapers, but even before the election that position started to change.</p>
<p>The best-selling Sun, once an enthusiastic supporter of former prime minister Margaret Thatcher, and its Sunday stablemate, the News of the World, both came over to Blair, who had assiduously courted their proprietor, Rupert Murdoch.</p>
<p>Even the Daily Express, which has been backing the Conservatives since the heyday of the British Empire, is now owned by a Labour-supporting peer, Lord Hollick, although this has yet to show in its political stance.</p>
<p>The Mail announced Rothermere's switch in a small article tucked away on page 12 headed &quot;Backing from Lord Rothermere&quot;.</p>
<p>In its leader columns, however, it was bashing Thursday's decision by the 164 Conservative MPs that they alone would take part in the election for a new party leader to replace John Major, despite grassroot demands for a say in the vote.</p>
<p>&quot;The party in the country is demoralised and in tatters. It needs to be inspired and rebuilt from the ground up. Instead it has been fobbed off,&quot; the Mail said.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 7717</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
