<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609958" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: London precious metals weaker ahead of long weekend.</title>
<headline>London precious metals weaker ahead of long weekend.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gloomy sentiment prevailed in the precious metals markets on Friday, with sharply lower platinum and palladium prices setting the tone.</p>
<p>The market was reluctant to do more than clear the books ahead of a long holiday weekend in Britain and the United States, traders said.</p>
<p>Still, the downside was beckoning for the complex after the platinum group metals (PGMs) took a kicking on a weaker yen and news that long-delayed Russian supplies were imminent.</p>
<p>In the absence of consumer interest, gold also followed suit, fixed at an easier $341.65 per ounce.</p>
<p>It had previously been fixed at $342.75 on Thursday afternoon and closed in London at $342.50/$343.00.</p>
<p>Dealers said it could tick still lower by the end of the day although chart-wise support was expected to emerge at the $340.00 level.</p>
<p>&quot;People don't want to do much at the end of the week. But the PGMs remain the market's focus and sentiment doesn't look great,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Dealers were also closely watching to see whether Australian producers would sell gold after the central bank cut official cash rates.</p>
<p>A resulting fall in the value of the Australian dollar against the U.S. currency means Australian gold will get a higher return in Australian dollars.</p>
<p>But the centre of attention was still palladium, which tumbled to fix dramatically lower at $168.50 an ounce, compared to $174.50 on Thursday afternoon.</p>
<p>The drop in spot palladium in Europe followed a sell-off in yen-based futures in Tokyo in which all months expect for limitless May fell by their daily limit.</p>
<p>Aggressive selling by private investors was triggered by news this week that long-delayed talks between Russian suppliers and Japanese consumers are due to start next month, dealers in Tokyo said.</p>
<p>A rise in the U.S. dollar against the yen was also discouraging Japanese importers.</p>
<p>Platinum was similarly easier, fixing at $387.00 an ounce versus $388.75 the previous afternoon. It subsequently eased further to around $385.00 in European trading.</p>
<p>Silver was easier at $4.66/$4.68, down two cents. It was seen following gold's lead, with support seen at $4.60.</p>
<p>--Lida Poletz, London newsroom +44 171 542 2936</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
