<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609992" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada's leftist leader seeks campaign attention.</title>
<headline>Canada's leftist leader seeks campaign attention.</headline>
<byline>Heather Scoffield</byline>
<dateline>OTTAWA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canada's leader of the political left is eloquent, poised, tough and media-savvy.</p>
<p>But Alexa McDonough, the leader of the New Democratic Party (NDP) and the only female party leader running in the June 2 federal election, is struggling to capture national attention.</p>
<p>Canadians seem more enchanted with McDonough's romance with a former Conservative cabinet minister than with her party's fight against unemployment.</p>
<p>At stake is the party's fragile credibility and the future of the left in Canada.</p>
<p>&quot;They're off the script, they're out of the consensus, at least with the opinion leaders,&quot; said Fred Fletcher, professor of political science at York University in Toronto.</p>
<p>Canada's right wing is shared by the traditional Conservatives and the upstart Reform Party, while the governing Liberals dominate the political center.</p>
<p>But public opinion in Canada has shifted steadily to the right during the 1990s, leaving little room for the NDP.</p>
<p>&quot;The whole left is facing this problem of how to operate in global markets,&quot; said Fletcher.</p>
<p>Even McDonough, a former leader of the Nova Scotia provincial NDP, admits her party has no hope of winning the federal election. She sells herself as a strong opposition leader who should go to Ottawa to keep in check the winning party -- likely the Liberals again.</p>
<p>&quot;What people are thinking about as they go to the polls in this election is how much better they would be served if there were more New Democrats in the House of Commons,&quot; she said in a recent speech.</p>
<p>But while McDonough, 54, has won praise for her practical and honest strategy, she has not generated widespread enthusiasm for her campaign. The latest Reuters/Zogby poll pegged her support at 9.9 percent and no poll has put the NDP above 11 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the hidden stories of this election is the fact that the New Democratic Party, with its very left-wing platform, has not been able to make a significant improvement on where they stood when the election (campaign) began,&quot;  Globe and Mail national affairs columnist Jeffrey Simpson said recently.</p>
<p>In the 1993 election, the NDP, which has never won a federal election, plunged to nine seats from a record high 43 seats. It needs 12 of the 301 seats up for grabs in this election to win official party status.</p>
<p>The party's platform promises to cut unemployment to five percent from its current stubborn 9.6 percent, while eliminating the deficit and rejuvenating social programs. The party would finance the measures by raising taxes on corporations and higher paid Canadians.</p>
<p>But although jobs are consistently listed as the top concern in public opinion polls, the NDP's competitors have made national unity and Quebec separation the focus of the election campaign.</p>
<p>McDonough has little to say on the matter.</p>
<p>&quot;This is about jobs, stupid,&quot; she sniped this week as the other party leaders harped on matters from gun control to how to keep Quebec part of Canada.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, she mentioned the unmentionable in Canadian politics. She accused right-wing Reform Party leader Preston Manning of pushing the country in the direction of &quot;civil war&quot; with his &quot;divisive&quot; proposals for national unity.</p>
<p>Canadians are giving up hope that the federal government can have any role in job creation and have little faith that the NDP could deliver on its job creation plans, analysts said.</p>
<p>The NDP also faces credibility problems because of its unpopularity in British Columbia, where it forms the provincial government, and the unsuccessful NDP provincial government in Ontario from 1990 to 1995.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OTTAWA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
