<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609901" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Rolls-Royce says to solve aero engine problem.</title>
<headline>Rolls-Royce says to solve aero engine problem.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>British aero-engine manufacturer Rolls-Royce Plc said on Friday it had identified the technical problem with its Trent 700 engines that forced a Hong Kong Dragon Airlines (Dragonair) Airbus 330 to make an emergency landing in the Phillippines on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have identified the problem and we are working closely with our customers to sort it out,&quot; a company spokeswoman in London told Reuters.</p>
<p>The Dragonair pilot was forced to land on one engine after Flight KA-MH061, carrying 127 passengers, from Hong Kong developed an engine fault en route to Kota Kinabalu in Malaysia.</p>
<p>The Dragonair landing was the latest in a series of recent forced landings involving Airbus 300s using Trent 700 engines.</p>
<p>She said the problem was in the gearbox bearings in the Trent 700 engines. &quot;We are replacing the affected parts,&quot; the spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>The pilot had to shut off the engine after it developed an oil pressure problem. &quot;The problem posed no danger to passengers or to the aircraft,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Airport officials in Manila confimed that none of the passengers or flight crew members were hurt.</p>
<p>The Rolls-Royce official said there was no reason to pull out the engines saying the problem should be rectified and the solutions tested within a month.</p>
<p>Problems with gearbox bearings in Trent 700 engines have forced Hong Kong's leading carrier Cathay Pacific Airways Ltd Airbus 330-300s to make a series of unscheduled single-engine landings recently.</p>
<p>A Cathay Pacific plane with Trent 700 engines made a single-engine landing at Bangkok last week. Two weeks ago a flight to the Philippines had to return to Hong Kong, a Cathay Pacific spokesman told Reuters in Hong Kong on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The Rolls-Royce official said it was the same problem which had forced these landings.</p>
<p>The Trent 700 engine was introduced in March 1995 and apart from Cathay Pacific and Dragonair, they are also used by Indonesian carrier Garuda Indonesia.</p>
<p>The company said orders for at least 60 such engines were in place from other leading airlines including TWA, Gulf Air and Emirates Air.</p>
<p>--Arindam Nag, London Newsroom +44 171 542 4366</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
