<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609953" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Blue Circle says UK cement business gains.</title>
<headline>Blue Circle says UK cement business gains.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's biggest cement producer, Blue Circle Industries Plc, said on Friday its UK cement business had gained during the first four months of the year.  </p>
<p>Blue Circle's chairman Lord Tugendhat told the annual meeting the UK cement business had gained from increased demand and prices in the first four months.</p>
<p>&quot;Demand prospects are strong for the remainder of this year,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>In the bathroom division, he said no improvement had yet been seen in the UK or Italian markets.</p>
<p>In the group's heating division, the full effects of last year's restructuring are expected to enhance that division's profits this year. Demand in the UK and France got off to a strong start before the milder weather set in.</p>
<p>Tugendhat said that Blue Circle America continued to advance in the first four months and a strong market is now expected for the year as a whole.</p>
<p>Elsewhere overseas, the group's Malaysian business is still performing well, while the outlook in Chile is for more cement demand growth, but at a lower rate than last year.</p>
<p>-- London newsroom +44 171 542 4365</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I24200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
