<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609997" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Quebec wants to join challenge to MMT ban.</title>
<headline>Quebec wants to join challenge to MMT ban.</headline>
<dateline>OTTAWA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The province of Quebec says it wants to join Alberta in challenging a new Canadian law that effectively bans the gasoline additive MMT, Ethyl Corp said on Friday.</p>
<p>Ethyl, Canada's only provider of methylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl (MMT), has also launched a US$250 million challenge to the legislation, passed last month.</p>
<p>The Virginia-based company said on Friday that Quebec officials made a request earlier this week to Industry Canada to join Alberta in consultations about the law.</p>
<p>&quot;The government of Quebec feels it has a substantial interest in this issue...since there are in Quebec several refineries that will be affected by the legislation,&quot; Quebec official Yves Castonguay said in a letter to Industry Canada.</p>
<p>&quot;Furthermore, Quebec feels that this act is inconsistent with the spirit and the letter of the agreement on internal trade.&quot;</p>
<p>The bill prohibits interprovincial trading and importing MMT, effectively banning the substance in Canada.</p>
<p>MMT has been used in Canada since 1977 to replace lead in boosting octane in gasoline. But the federal government moved to ban the substance for environmental reasons. Environmentalists say it was potentially a hazard and automakers said it gummed up cars' diagnostic systems and could therefore lead to more pollution.</p>
<p>Opponents of the law deny the claims, saying the substance is safe.</p>
<p>((Reuters Ottawa Bureau 613 235-6745))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OTTAWA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
