<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609943" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: IPE Brent and gas oil weaker but supports holding.</title>
<headline>IPE Brent and gas oil weaker but supports holding.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>IPE Brent crude and gas oil futures were generally weaker over the morning but supports on both markets were holding fairly well, traders said.</p>
<p>At 1135 GMT, July Brent was trading 13 cents lower at $20.05 a barrel holding stable in a narrow range over the morning after bobbing back from a low of $20.</p>
<p>However, GNI Research said in its daily report that volatility could increase later in the day. The funds could look for higher prices and the trade lower numbers.</p>
<p>&quot;On balance we would not be surprised to see a test of higher levels again, but the push may have to come from New York,&quot; GNI said.</p>
<p>The Brent market spent most of the morning bouncing off support around $20 that appeared to be holding well, although traders said there was little volume in the selling.</p>
<p>Gas oil futures showed a similar pattern of trade with support around the $177-$177.25 level holding well, apart from a brief dip to a $176.75 low.</p>
<p>The June contract last traded $1.50 down at $177.50 with July contangoed by around $1.</p>
<p>Traders said talk of run cuts due to poor crack margins was also seen providing some support.</p>
<p>-- Colin Wooster, London Newsroom +44 171 542 7456</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
