<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="609989" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Copper slips under $2,500 on LME pre-market.</title>
<headline>Copper slips under $2,500 on LME pre-market.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Copper shuffled lower in early Friday trade, testing the psychological $2,500 per tonne area ahead of a long holiday weekend.</p>
<p>The market was fundamentally strong, but was susceptible to profit-taking and book squaring ahead of the three-day weekend in Britain and the U.S., traders said.</p>
<p>Three month copper jumped to a fresh one-year peak of $2,530 on Thursday morning, and speculative buying helped it close the afternoon kerb at a buoyant $2,526.</p>
<p>But prices slipped lower in late inter-office trade and on Friday morning were indicated at $2,495/98.  </p>
<p>&quot;There's some support around $2,495...whether it will be aggressively tested I'm not sure,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Analysts said the market was over-extended, with the 14-day RSI at 80 at Thursday's kerb close. It was the highest RSI since last May when prices were climbing ahead of the Sumitomo scandal.</p>
<p>The market was still tight, with scant LME stocks in Europe, and inventories eroded by a further 1,325 tonnes on Friday to 137,675 tonnes.</p>
<p>Other analysts pegged support at $2,470/90 and then $2,462.</p>
<p>Not helping upside sentiment was news that supervisors at Chilean state copper firm Codelco's Chuquicamata pit are unlikely to strike, according to a source close to the talks.</p>
<p>Aluminium extended Thursday's decline, slipping to $1,625 from Thursday's kerb close of $1,633, despite an inventory decline of 2,575 tonnes.</p>
<p>&quot;The mood is bearish and I would expect more lower numbers today. There's some light support at $1,616/17,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>Others noted that the convergence of the 30-day and 100-day moving averages at $1,620/21 should also provide a floor.</p>
<p>Zinc stocks showed another good fall at 2,350 tonnes, but the price still struggled to retain its upward momentum, edging down $3 to $1,361.</p>
<p>The market was solid, but would find difficulty making a great deal of upside progress ahead of the long weekend. Players were already long and the charts were looking overbought with the 14-day RSI at 73.5.</p>
<p>Resistance was pegged at Thursday's high of $1,370, then at $1,380, while support was seen at the 10-day moving average of $1,348, then at $1,340 and $1,332.</p>
<p>Lead gave up Thursday's gains, dropping $9 to $635.</p>
<p>The market showed two days of strength, but would have to consolidate at higher levels before the bear trend could be shaken off, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We would want to see a close above $650 or at least above range resistance at $644 before suggesting that prices would recover to target $700,&quot; said analyst Martin Squires of broker Rudolf Wolff.</p>
<p>Tin was barely moved at $5,760, down $10, and alloy was indicated at a little changed $1,493/98.</p>
<p>--Eric Onstad, London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
