<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610055" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Flinn to leave U.S. Air Force -- no court martial.</title>
<headline>Flinn to leave U.S. Air Force -- no court martial.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Air Force has dropped plans to court-martial its first woman bomber pilot on adultery and other charges but said she must leave the service with less than the honourable discharge she sought.</p>
<p>Air Force Secretary Sheila Widnall announced the compromise on Thursday in a case that had pitted Lt. Kelly Flinn, once a celebrated standard-bearer for women in the services, against the Air Force establishment and prompted an emotional national debate.</p>
<p>Widnall told reporters she had refused to accept Flinn's offer to leave with an honourable discharge but granted her a &quot;general discharge&quot;, which does not carry the stigma and conditions of a dishonourable discharge.</p>
<p>Flinn, 26 and single, was charged with breaking the service's strict sexual code by having an affair with the husband of an enlisted woman, lying about her conduct during a subsequent investigation and disobeying a direct order.</p>
<p>Flinn has now agreed to resign rather than face a court-martial.</p>
<p>Her lawyer, Frank Spinner, told reporters at Minot Air Force base in North Dakota, where Flinn is stationed: &quot;Lt. Flinn decided to place the best intererst of the Air Force ahead of her own&quot; in her battle against &quot;a true injustice&quot;.</p>
<p>He said she realised &quot;there was no way she could win the battle&quot; and added: &quot;She has experienced significant public humiliation ... The Air Force has lost a pioneer, and at what a price.&quot; Her resignation would take effect in about 10 days.</p>
<p>Widnall rejected allegations by some groups that Flinn had been discriminated against because she was a woman and that the tough action would not have been taken against her had she been a man.</p>
<p>&quot;I absolutely reject that. That is one thing that I feel has never really been an issue in this case,&quot; Widnall told a news conference at the Pentagon.</p>
<p>Widnall added: &quot;Obviously I have to say from a personal point of view that is extremely important to me that we hold men and women to the same standards of officership in the Air Force and clearly we have done that.&quot;</p>
<p>The main reason Flinn was denied an honourable discharge, she said, was allegations of a &quot;lack of integrity and disobedience to order&quot;.</p>
<p>Flinn expressed concern earlier that, if she left with a general discharge, it would restrict her ability to fly heavy bombers in the part-time Air Force reserve.</p>
<p>She will now have to obtain a special waiver to do so, Air Force officials said. Flinn's brother, Don, speaking to reporters in Minot, said she would apply for such a waiver.</p>
<p>Formally, Flinn was given &quot;a general discharge under honourable circumstances&quot;.</p>
<p>Officials said that since she would only have completed about four years of her five-year term she will have to pay back about 20 percent of the cost of her Air Force academy education, which officials estimated at $18,000 to $19,000.</p>
<p>The officials said she would not be eligible for veterans' benefits because she had resigned.</p>
<p>In making her decision, Widnall said she considered the &quot;absolute requirement&quot; to maintain good order and discipline in the military and to protect the &quot;Air Force core values of integrity and obedience to orders&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Finally, I considered carefully the need for a firm, just and equitable disciplinary system that is administered even-handedly,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Democratic and Republican leaders in Congress as well as many women's groups accused the Air Force of bungling the case by allowing it to balloon into a national cause.</p>
<p>Democratic Representative Nita Lowey of New York and three other women who have criticised the Air Force praised Widnall's solution as fair but called for a more extensive review of the military's policies on fraternisation and sexual conduct.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
