<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610041" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NOTICE OF SALE - Santa Clara County, Calif..</title>
<headline>NOTICE OF SALE - Santa Clara County, Calif..</headline>
<text>
<p>NOTICE OF INTENTION TO SELL</p>
<p>			 Not to Exceed $6,000,000</p>
<p>			    Santa Clara County</p>
<p>			    Board of Education</p>
<p>		  1997 Certificates of Participation</p>
<p>		    (Child Care Facilities Project)</p>
<p>NOTICE IS  HEREBY GIVEN  that  the Santa  Clara  County of Board  of  Education,  State  of  California  (the  County Board''),  acting  for  the  Santa  Clara  County  Board  of Education Finance Corporation (the Corporation''), intends to offer for public sale on</p>
<p>			  Tuesday, June 10, 1997</p>
<p>at the hour of 9:30 a.m., California time, at the office  of Orrick, Herrington &amp; Sutcliffe LLP, 400 Sansome Street,  San Francisco, California 94111-3143,  not to exceed  $6,000,000 principal amount of Certificates of Participation designated Santa Clara County Board of Education 1997 Certificates of Participation  (Child   Care  Facilities   Project)</p>
<p>Certificates to be issued pursuant to a Trust Agreement dated as of  June 1,  1997 by  and among  BNY Western Trust Company, as trustee, the  County Board and the  Corporation. The total  principal  amount  of the  Certificates  and  the principal component  for  each  year  shall  be  subject  to increase or decrease in accordance with the Official  Notice of Sale,  so  long as  the  total principal  amount  of  the Certificates does not  exceed $6,000,000.  The County  Board reserves the right to postpone to a later date or dates said public sale  date by  announcing such  postponement  through Thompson Municipal News and Bloomberg Business News no later than 24 hours prior to the  hour fixed for receipt of  bids. If the date of sale is postponed, bids will be received  for the Certificates at the same place on such date and at  such time as  shall be  designated by  the County  Board  through  Thompson Municipal  News   and  Bloomberg Business  News  no</p>
<p>later than 24  hours prior to  the new time  bids are to  be received. As an accommodation to bidders, telephonic or  fax notice of the postponement of the sale date will be given to any bidder requesting  such notice from  the County  Board's Financial Advisor,  Kelling,  Northcross  &amp;  Nobriga,  Inc., Attn. Dave Olson  (510) 839-8200. Failure  of any bidder  to receive such news  service, telephonic or  fax notice  shall not affect the legality of the sale. NOTICE IS HEREBY FURTHER GIVEN  that the Certificates will be  offered  for  public  sale  subject  to  the  terms  and  conditions  of   the  Official   Notice  of   Sale  of   the</p>
<p>Certificates, dated May 21, 1997, and copies of the Official  Notice of  Sale   and of  a Preliminary  Official  Statement</p>
<p>relating to the Certificates will be furnished upon  request to Kelling, Northcross &amp; Nobriga, Inc., 1333 Broadway, Suite 1000, Oakland, California 94612, tel. no. (510) 839-8200.</p>
<p>Dated: May 21, 1997.</p>
<p>				  /s/ Cathy Grovenburg</p>
<p>			 Assistant Superintendent</p>
<p>			   of Business Services</p>
<p>		  Santa Clara County Board of Education</p>
<p>			  (From The Bond Buyer)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
