<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610056" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Woman Air Force pilot defended by family, lawyer.</title>
<headline>Woman Air Force pilot defended by family, lawyer.</headline>
<byline>Greg Frost</byline>
<dateline>MINOT, N.D. 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lawyers and relatives of the first woman B-52 bomber pilot said Thursday she was locked in a &quot;no-win situation,&quot; and that she had to accept a deal allowing her to resign from the Air Force and avoid being court-martialed.</p>
<p>&quot;Today, Lt. Kelly Flinn decided to place the interests of the Air Force ahead of her own desire to fight what she believes is a true injustice,&quot; said Frank Spinner, Flinn's civilian lawyer. &quot;The Air Force has lost a pioneer -- and at what a price.&quot;</p>
<p>Air Force Secretary Sheila Widnall announced Thursday that Flinn had been given a general discharge and will leave the service in lieu of being court-martialed on charges that she committed adultery, lied during an official investigation and disobeyed a direct order.</p>
<p>Spinner described Flinn's condition Thursday as &quot;physicaly and emotionally exhausted.&quot;</p>
<p>Saying there was &quot;a strong possibility that Kelly would end up as a convict,&quot; Flinn's mother, Mary, explained the reasoning that led the pilot to accept a general discharge instead of her earlier demand for an honourable one.</p>
<p>&quot;The family felt it was a no-win situation and the Air Force would attempt to make an example of her,&quot; Mary Flinn told reporters at Minot Air Force Base. She was accompanied by her husband Don, Sr., and her son, Don, Jr.</p>
<p>&quot;I love my daughter. I know my daughter loves the Air Force,&quot; she said. &quot;I feel a great injustice has been done to Kelly Flinn.&quot;</p>
<p>Although Flinn will receive a &quot;general discharge under honourable conditions,&quot; the definition of that document suggests that all did not go well with her in the service, a Pentagon official told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;Under honourable conditions, a general discharge  is separation from the Air Force with honour, but to a lesser degree than an honourable discharge,&quot; said the official.</p>
<p>&quot;This (general) discharge is given when normally faithful service is marred by negative aspects of a person's duty performance or personal conduct,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The discharge would prevent Flinn from flying planes for the Air Force Reserve or the Air National Guard unless she obtained a waiver, which Spinner said she would seek.</p>
<p>He also said she will have to repay $18,000 in tuition fees that the government gave her to attend the prestigious Air Force Academy.</p>
<p>Flinn's brother, Don, also blasted the military justice system, saying her superiors had shown &quot;blatant disregard&quot; for her and had sought to &quot;discredit and destroy&quot; the pilot before she could receive due process.</p>
<p>Aside from criticising the Air Force's handling of the case, Spinner blamed Flinn's ex-lover Marc Zigo for deceiving her.</p>
<p>&quot;If Marc Zigo had never come to Minot Air Force Base, none of this would have happened,&quot; Spinner said. He then distributed copies of his background check on Zigo, and said the background would have come out during the court-martial.</p>
<p>Flinn, 26 and single, has admitted having sex with Zigo, a married civilian, but said he told her he had legally separated from his wife Gayla at the time of their affair. Flinn had also been charged with having an affair with an enlisted man.</p>
<p>A clearly emotional Gayla Zigo spoke to reporters briefly Thursday night. Trembling and on the verge of tears, she said she felt victimised by the whole affair but declined to reveal many specifics about the case.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not the outcome that I was expecting but I respect (Widnall's) decision,&quot; Gayla Zigo said.</p>
<p>Earlier in the week, reporters obtained a letter Gayla wrote to Widnall accusing Flinn of being a homewrecker. When asked why she wrote the letter, Gayla said, &quot;She told her side of the story and everybody listened. But they don't know what happened. They don't know what I felt.&quot;</p>
<p>Marc Zigo spoke to reporters for about 12 minutes Thursday evening and said Gayla was the real victim in the case.</p>
<p>&quot;I lied. I lied about my life. I lied and I'm not proud,&quot; he said, but then blamed Flinn as the real culprit in the case.</p>
<p>&quot;To say 'Marc Zigo made me do this' -- at no time was I holding a gun to Lt. Flinn's head,&quot; Zigo said. Reuter</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MINOT, N.D."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
