<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610006" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: More Turk soldiers enter Iraq to hunt down rebels.</title>
<headline>More Turk soldiers enter Iraq to hunt down rebels.</headline>
<dateline>SILOPI, Turkey 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey ferried fresh forces into northern Iraq on Friday in a cross-border drive against Kurdish rebels that shows no sign of easing after 10 days despite international concern.</p>
<p>Witnesses said an armoured unit of around 1,000 men entered Iraq overnight through the Turkish border town of Silopi.</p>
<p>They said 12 U.S.-made Sikorsky carrier helicopters, empty of troops, flew across the border on Friday morning for apparent use in shifting forces inside Iraq.</p>
<p>Turkish officials and Iraqi Kurds have confirmed that the Turkish army has begun digging in after initial clashes with Kurdistan Workers Party (PKK) rebels.</p>
<p>NATO ally France voiced concern over Turkish reports of a buildup of foreign troops near the Iraqi border and urged Ankara to swiftly withdraw its troops from northern Iraq.</p>
<p>&quot;France wants to express its acute concern. It calls on Iraq's neighbours to stick to utmost restraint in order to avoid worsening a fragile regional situation,&quot; foreign ministry spokesman Jacques Rummelhardt said in Paris.</p>
<p>&quot;It calls for the earliest withdrawal of Turkish troops from northern Iraq,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Turkish press has reported that troops may defy international concerns about the length of the stay and remain in Iraq until as late as August.</p>
<p>&quot;A long stay like that would test the patience of everyone, even the Americans,&quot; said a Western diplomat in Ankara.</p>
<p>A U.S.-led allied air force that flies over northern Iraq protects the Kurdish autonomous enclave from any attack by Baghdad.</p>
<p>Washington has offered only mild criticism of Turkey's incursion and urged that it end swiftly.</p>
<p>The Iraq operation has been carried out under a strict news blackout, making independent confirmation of information from the region impossible.</p>
<p>The diplomat played down reports by Turkish officials that Iran, Syria and Iraq were building up military forces on the borders of the Iraqi Kurdish region to help the rebels escape.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not seeing that to such an extent, although there may be an increase in border guards and the likes,&quot; he said. Turkey often accuses Damascus and Tehran of aiding the PKK.</p>
<p>More than 10,000 Turkish troops, allied with an Iraqi Kurdish militia, poured into northern Iraq last week in pursuit of PKK rebels, who use northern Iraq as a base to launch raids into southeast Turkey.</p>
<p>In Geneva, some 200 Kurdish demonstrators, stormed the United Nations' European headquarters on Thursday, occupying the building for five hours and demanding international action to halt Turkey's offensive into northern Iraq.</p>
<p>The Turkish army says it has killed well over 1,000 PKK rebels during the incursion. Western diplomats say the figures are inflated.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SILOPI, Turkey"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
