<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610038" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NOTICE OF SALE - St. Louis County, Mo..</title>
<headline>NOTICE OF SALE - St. Louis County, Mo..</headline>
<text>
<p>SUMMARY NOTICE OF SALE</p>
<p>				 $16,005,000*</p>
<p>			St. Louis County, Missouri</p>
<p>	  General Obligation Refunding Bonds, Series 1997</p>
<p>Proposals  for  the  purchase  of  $16,005,000*  principal amount of General Obligation  Refunding Bonds, Series  1997, of St.  Louis  County, Missouri,  will  be received  by  the Director  of  Administration  of  the  County  at  41  South Central, 9th  Floor,  Clayton, Missouri,  until  9:30  A.M., Central Time, on</p>
<p>			  Thursday, May 29, 1997</p>
<p>or on such later date as may be established by the  Director of Administration  and  announced  via  the  MUNIFACTS  News Service at least 48 hours prior  to the time bids are to  be submitted, as  provided  in the  Notice  of Bond  Sale.  All proposals will  be publicly  opened, read  and evaluated  at said time, date and place. The Bonds will consist of fully registered  bonds in book- entry only form.  The Depository Trust  Company will act  as securities depository for the Bonds. The Bonds will be dated as of  their  date  of  issuance  and  delivery,  will  bear interest payable semiannually on February 1 and August 1  in each year, beginning  on February 1,  1998, and will  become due in principal installments on February 1 in the years  as follows:</p>
<p>	  Principal	Principal	Principal</p>
<p>    Year Amount*   Year Amount*   Year Amount*</p>
<p>1998 $335,000  2003$1,240,000 2008$1,570,000</p>
<p>    1999  30,000   20041,300,000  20091,650,000</p>
<p>    2000  30,000   20051,365,000  20101,740,000</p>
<p>    2001  30,000   20061,425,000  20111,830,000</p>
<p>    2002  35,000   20071,495,000  20121,930,000</p>
<p>Bonds maturing on February 1, 2008  and thereafter will be subject to  redemption  and  payment prior  to  maturity  on February 1, 2007 and thereafter  as described in the  Notice of Bond Sale. The Bonds will  be awarded  to the  bidder whose  bid will result in the lowest true interest  cost to the County.  The County reserves  the right  to waive  irregularities and  to reject any or all proposals. The Bonds are  being issued  for the purpose  of refunding portions of  the  County's  outstanding  General  Obligation Bonds, Series 1992. The Bonds and the interest thereon  will constitute general obligations of  the County, payable  from ad valorem taxes which may  be levied without limitation  as to rate or  amount upon all  the taxable tangible  property, real and personal, within the County. The Bonds  will be  sold  subject to  the  approving legal opinion  of  Thompson  Coburn,  St.  Louis,  Missouri,  Bond Counsel, which opinion will be furnished by the County. A Good  Faith  Deposit  in  the  form  of a  certified  or cashier's check or a Financial Surety Bond in the amount  of  $320,000,  payable  to  the  order  of  St.  Louis   County,</p>
<p>Missouri, is  required for  each bid  to be  considered provided in the Notice of Bond Sale. Bidders must refer to the complete Notice of Bond Sale for the terms  and  conditions  of  the  sale.  The  County  has prepared a Preliminary Official  Statement, copies of  which  may  be  obtained   from  the  Financial   Advisor  or   the</p>
<p>undersigned. All proposals must be  made on forms which  may be procured from the  Financial Advisor or the  undersigned. Additional information regarding the  Bonds may be  obtained from the Financial Advisor, A.G.  Edwards &amp; Sons, Inc.,  One North Jefferson,  St. Louis,  Missouri 63103,  Attn:  Amelia A.J. Bond, (314)  955-2594 or  James E.  Baker, Director  of  Administration,  41  South  Central,  9th  Floor,   Clayton,</p>
<p>Missouri 63105, (314) 889-2046.</p>
<p>DATED this 23rd day of May, 1997.</p>
<p>		     ST. LOUIS COUNTY, MISSOURI</p>
<p>		    By: /s/ James E. Baker</p>
<p>			   Director of Administration</p>
<p>*Subject to change as provided in the Notice of Bond Sale.</p>
<p>(From The Bond Buyer)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
