<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610062" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Albright unveils plan to speed peace in Bosnia.</title>
<headline>Albright unveils plan to speed peace in Bosnia.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Secretary of State Madeleine Albright on Thursday unveiled a U.S. initiative to spur progress toward peace in Bosnia that would include having NATO-led troops there take on new roles.</p>
<p>Testifying before Congress and later speaking on an aircraft carrier in New York harbour, Albright announced that President Bill Clinton, after a six-week review, had approved a series of measures to bring increased pressure on Bosnia's ethnic rivals and ensure that the difficult peace process succeeds.</p>
<p>Other parts of the package would give financial rewards to Bosnian communities that accept refugees, withhold aid from uncooperative governments and renew talk of a special unit to track down war criminals, U.S. officials said.</p>
<p>Albright said Washington would ensure that by year's end all of Bosnia had access to independent television or radio reporting and would open diplomatic offices in the towns of Mostar and Banja Luka, symbols of Bosnia's ethnic woes.</p>
<p>The NATO-led force would still focus on enforcing the military aspect of the Dayton peace agreement reached by Bosnia's combatants in 1995. But the force could also get involved in tasks like establishing telecommunications links between the rival Croat, Moslem and Serb communities, Albright said.</p>
<p>The force &quot;will build on its past accomplishments by actively supporting crucial civil implementation tasks within its mandate and capabilities,&quot; Albright said.</p>
<p>&quot;These include helping to create a secure environment for managed refugee returns ... and specific economic reconstruction projects, which could include interentity telecommunications and restoring civil aviation,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Pentagon spokesman Ken Bacon later said the troops, known as SFOR, would &quot;do everything they can to maintain a secure atmosphere in Bosnia, including building roads and other efforts, but it is not anticipated that SFOR troops will take on significant new tasks&quot; outside the military portfolio.</p>
<p>But a State Department official said, &quot;We think there are ways within the mandate to increase their involvement.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pentagon has resisted calls for the peacekeeping force to become involved in such untraditional tasks as tracking down war criminals indicted by a special tribunal in The Hague.</p>
<p>But others say the troops could be used in a broader role. Asked about the special war crimes unit, the State Department official said, &quot;We are looking for every possible way to bring war criminals to justice.&quot;</p>
<p>The official, who requested anonymity. left open the possibility that U.S. troops, which form the bulk of the NATO-led peacekeeping force, could stay in Bosnia beyond a June 1998 deadline. Defence Secretary Willam Cohen has said the deadline is firm.</p>
<p>The troop issue was not addressed in the just-finished review of Bosnian policy and &quot;the president has not yet made any commitment,&quot; the official said, adding: &quot;That is an issue that the president will be addressing at a future time. ... The future still has to be decided.&quot;</p>
<p>But State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns later contradicted those comments. &quot;SFOR ends in June 1998. There are no plans for American troops to remain beyond June 1998,&quot; Burns said. The review reaffirmed &quot;that we believe SFOR will end in June 1998, and we have no plans and no intention for any American troop presence in Bosnia beyond June 1998,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Albright said in her speech that much had been accomplished in Bosnia since a peace deal was signed in Dayton, Ohio, in November 1995, but many problems remained.</p>
<p>&quot;Full implementation of Dayton must be our goal in all sectors, and the parties cannot pick and choose those elements they prefer at the expense of others,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;If they are not complying on key implementation tasks, it will not be business as usual for their politicians or their military leaders,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Clinton and Albright are determined to make Dayton a success and &quot;we'll use whatever leverage we have,&quot; one official said. He cited as an example Washington's blocking of new aid for Bosnia -- including $90 million in cash from the International Monetary Fund and $1.4 billion to be pledged at a donors' conference -- until economic reforms are enacted.</p>
<p>Albright, who took a big interest in Bosnia when she was U.N. ambassador but had said little about it publicly since becoming secretary of state in January, plans to visit the Balkans next week. In addition to Sarajevo, a stop previously announced, she will go to Brcko and Banja Luka, two of the most troubled symbols of ethnic division.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
