<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610074" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Memorial Day market hours.</title>
<headline>U.S. Memorial Day market hours.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. financial markets will be closed Monday, May 26, for the Memorial Day holiday. It will be business as usual on Tuesday, May 27.</p>
<p>On Friday, May 23, the New York Stock Exchange, American Stock Exchange and Nasdaq will have regular trading hours, and there will be no early close on the New York Mercantile Exchange, Coffee Sugar and Cocoa Exchange, and Cotton Exchange.</p>
<p>However, the following markets will close early on Friday:</p>
<p>The Treasury and related Debt markets will close trading at 1400 EDT/1800 GMT.</p>
<p>Forex trade is expected to wind down around 1300 EST/1700 GMT.</p>
<p>In Chicago, CBOT financial and insurance products will shut early at 1210 CDT/1710 GMT but all other CBOT contracts will observe normal hours. Evening pit trading and Project A overnight sessions will be closed Sunday May 25.</p>
<p>At Chicago's CME, currency and interest rate futures and options close at 1200 CDT/1700 GMT Friday. Agricultural, equity and GSCI contracts close at their regular times.</p>
<p>Also at the CME, there will be an evening Globex Taiwan Stock Index session from 1930 CDT/0050 GMT to 2215 CDT/0315 GMT Friday.</p>
<p>CBOE interest-rate options trading will close early at 1200 CDT/1700 GMT on Friday, but equity options and index options will observe normal trading hours.</p>
<p>On Monday night the Chicago Board of Trade (CBOT), Chicago Mercantile Exchange (CME) and Chicago Board Options Exchange (CBOE) open night pit trading and overnight Project A electronic trade will be open.</p>
<p>CME's GLOBEX session Sunday, May 25, will run from 1730 CDT/2230 GMT to 2230 CDT/0330 GMT. CME's GLOBEX trading will resume Monday, May 26, at 1730 CDT/2230 GMT.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
