<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610058" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Budget deal faces delays in U.S. Congress.</title>
<headline>Budget deal faces delays in U.S. Congress.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Senate on Thursday delayed passage of a balanced budget agreement worked out with President Clinton after rejecting calls to spend more money to improve the nation's schools and roads. The vote was postponed until Friday.</p>
<p>Senate leaders had hoped to pass the budget late on Thursday with strong support from both parties and the White House, but lawmakers did not finish work on a host of amendments -- most of which would not have significantly altered the agreement.</p>
<p>Final approval by both chambers of Congress will have to wait until June 3 when both chambers return formally from a week-long Memorial Day recess. The budget is a blueprint for spending and taxes and does not go to Clinton for his signature, but it embodies agreements made on future legislation which will be sent to his desk for approval.</p>
<p>The budget deal was supposed to be sealed by Friday, but differences between the House and Senate versions could not be ironed out by the deadline. In addition, House Republican leaders sent members back to their districts when work on an unrelated disaster aid bill could not be completed Thursday.</p>
<p>Speaking earlier in West Virginia, the president praised the budget deal: &quot;We are about to conclude debate in the Senate today on a balanced budget...that will give our country the first balanced budget we've had since the 1960s and it's high time, and I'm proud of it.&quot;</p>
<p>The Senate will vote on 30 to 40 amendments Friday. Most seek to add funds for various causes and will likely fail.</p>
<p>&quot;I think ultimately, after all the dust settles and the shots have been fired, that a majority of Democrats and a majority of Republicans are going to support this agreement,&quot; Senate Minority Leader Tom Daschle of South Dakota said.</p>
<p>A virtually identical plan passed the House on Wednesday 333-99.</p>
<p>During Thursday's debate the Senate rejected 56-43 an amendment to add $5 billion for school construction after budget leaders argued that they could not change the hard-won agreement now. The Senate also rejected 51-49 an amendment seeking to increase transportation funds by $16 billion.</p>
<p>As the Senate heard pleas for more funds, Appropriations Committee chairman Ted Stevens defended those who voted against popular causes. The most difficult vote was Wednesday's rejection of $20 billion to give health insurance to poor children.</p>
<p>&quot;We're voting againt these not because we're against highways or children who need insurance. I, for one, don't want to be accused of being an old tightwad,&quot; the Alaska Republican said.</p>
<p>&quot;If you vote for one of these things, you show us where ther money is and we'll allocate it. Don't give us any more of this funny money. Show me real money.&quot;</p>
<p>But both sides agree the budget agreement is a short-term solution to the problem of exploding costs of Medicare, Social Security and other benefits in the next century.</p>
<p>&quot;A short-term solution was required first to get us out of the hottest part of the fire, which is ... Medicare insolvency,&quot; Daschle added.</p>
<p>The budget plan trims Medicare by $115 billion over five years and makes changes to the programme -- including shifting the cost of home health care to the individual health care plan and out of the hospital trust fund.</p>
<p>These changes are expected to keep it solvent for the next decade after which the large baby boom generation will start retiring and make heavy demands on the programme.</p>
<p>The plan brings the deficit to zero by 2002, slows the growth of federal spending and provides a net tax cut of $85 billion through 2002. The tax cuts would be used to give a $500 per child tax credit, add deductions and credits for post-secondary education, cut the capital gains tax rate, reduce inheritance taxes and expand retirement savings tax breaks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
