<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610061" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Subpoenas issued on Buddhist temple fundraiser.</title>
<headline>Subpoenas issued on Buddhist temple fundraiser.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Alan Elsner, Political Correspondent</p>
<p>A Senate committee investigating campaign finance on Thursday voted to issue 43 new subpoenas, including 23 connected to a Democratic fund-raising event last year at a Buddhist temple in California.</p>
<p>Vice President Al Gore attended the April 1996 event at the Hsi Lai Temple, which participants paid $2,500 each to attend, in apparent violation of the temple's tax-free status as a non-political religious group.</p>
<p>Gore at first said it was not a fund-raising event, even though memos prepared by the Democratic National Committee for his staff clearly showed that it was.</p>
<p>The Senate Governmental Affairs Committee also issued a subpoena to the AFL-CIO labour federation, which spent an estimated $35 million trying to help Democrats in last year's congressional elections.</p>
<p>The committee was investigating whether China and other foreign interests sought to influence U.S. foreign policy by helping President Bill Clinton and the Democratic Party with illegal political contributions.</p>
<p>It also was investigating whether the White House or the Democrats knowingly solicited, received or laundered foreign funds. The FBI and a House committee were conducting simultaneous but separate investigations.</p>
<p>Additionally, the Senate committee voted unanimously to issue 10 subpoenas requested by Democrats to individuals and entities connected to the U.S. subsidiary of an Asian company which illegally contributed money to a Republican think tank.</p>
<p>The Republicans returned $122,000 to the company earlier this month when it learned the money came from overseas.</p>
<p>But the committee's action was not enough to quiet Democratic complaints that the investigation had degenerated into a &quot;partisan street fight,&quot; in the words of Connecticut Democrat Joseph Lieberman.</p>
<p>Ohio Sen. John Glenn, the ranking Democrat on the committee, called a news conference to complain that the Republican majority was refusing to issue most of the subpoenas requested by the Democrats.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been stymied at most everything we have tried to do,&quot; Glenn said. &quot;I don't think it's fair when we're only going after one side.&quot;</p>
<p>Committee Chairman Fred Thompson of Tennessee rejected the criticism, saying he was trying to focus the investigation on the most serious allegations of wrongdoing first before tackling less important matters later.</p>
<p>&quot;Every day it becomes more apparent to me that we have an awful lot of heavy lifting to do on matters that affect the basic integrity of our government,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Thompson said he and Glenn had received confidential briefings which made it clear the investigation had important national security implications -- &quot;some of the most serious allegations our country has ever faced,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't mistreat my Democrat colleagues but I can't let them run the investiation either,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>After a 90-minute debate, the committee split 9-7 along partisan lines in rejecting Glenn's demand for additional subpoenas of groups linked to Republican fund-raising.</p>
<p>The Democratic Party, which is deeply in debt, has returned $1.5 million which it suspected came from foreign interests and promised to repay another $1.5 million as soon as it can afford to do so.</p>
<p>Much of that money came from Asian business interests or individuals who have since fled the country or who have refused to cooperate with the investigation.</p>
<p>While the House investigation had been sharply partisan from the outset, Thompson had promised to run a balanced probe that went after both parties.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
