<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610003" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Iran in close election battle for new president.</title>
<headline>Iran in close election battle for new president.</headline>
<byline>Barry May</byline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iranians voted on Friday for a successor to retiring President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani in a battle between conservative and moderate factions.</p>
<p>After a fiercely fought campaign in which fears of vote-rigging were raised, the result looked set to be a close contest between two senior Shi'ite Moslem clergymen.</p>
<p>The leading candidates are Mohammad Khatami, a moderate, and Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri, a conservative. Analysts gave two others, Mohammad Mohammadi Reyshahri and Reza Zavarei, no chance of winning.</p>
<p>Iranian analysts and Western diplomats said the vote was too close to call but they thought Nateq-Nouri had the edge because he was seen as an establishment figure.</p>
<p>The result is expected to be known by Monday. If no candidate wins more than 50 percent of the votes the two leading candidates will face a runoff, possibly next Friday.</p>
<p>Iranian radio and television said the turnout was high.</p>
<p>All four candidates had to pass scrutiny for their belief in Iran's Islamic system of government before they were allowed to contest the election. The Guardian Council, a powerful body of clergymen and lawyers, rejected 234 other contenders.</p>
<p>Khatami, a former culture minister popular with women, youths and intellectuals, was expected to sweep the capital and some other major cities.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri, the speaker of parliament, is backed by important groups of Iran's conservative clergy and merchant class and is stronger in rural areas.</p>
<p>Supreme spiritual leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei and Rafsanjani, who is bound by law to step down in August after eight years in office, called on all eligible voters to take an active part in the election.</p>
<p>&quot;If one candidate shows the slightest tolerance to America and the Western countries' interference and cultural onslaught the people will not vote for him,&quot; Khamenei said in remarks broadcast by Tehran radio.</p>
<p>&quot;They will vote for someone who can stand against America and those who want to impose their will on our nation.&quot;</p>
<p>Khamenei said after voting at his official residence that he expected the next president to be a servant of the people and within the framework of the Islamic rules, and to do his best for people's welfare and spiritual affairs.</p>
<p>Rafsanjani said after voting: &quot;I hope the next president continues the construction plans and provides for people's requirements. That is the aim of the rule of Islam in the country and protects the national interest.&quot;</p>
<p>Khamenei, Iran's highest authority, and Rafsanjani, its most senior elected official, warned people before voting began against tampering with ballots and promised a fair election.</p>
<p>Thirty-three million Iranians aged 15 and over were eligible to vote at more than 33,000 mosques, schools and clinics turned into polling stations and guarded by 200,000 police. They opened at 8 a.m. (0330 GMT) and were to close at 6 p.m. (1330 GMT).</p>
<p>Voting hours were likely to be extended to encourage a high turnout, analysts said.</p>
<p>Armed police guarded barricaded approaches to national election headquarters at the Interior Ministry.</p>
<p>In the previous presidential election in 1993, Rafsanjani was returned for a second four-year term with 64 percent of 16.7 million votes cast.</p>
<p>Ballot papers do not name the candidates but a notice lists the four with Nateq-Nouri first followed by Reyshahri, Khatami and Zavarei. The list does not follow the Persian alphabet.</p>
<p>Voters must write in the name of their preferred candidate. There are no photographs of the candidates and illiterate voters have to ask for help.</p>
<p>A man interviewed on the radio about the election said voting was &quot;a strong smack in the jaw of world arrogance&quot; -- a term usually taken to mean the United States and the West.</p>
<p>Television coverage included footage of Iran's &quot;bad old days&quot; before the 1979 Islamic revolution including scenes of U.S. President Richard Nixon meeting Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi and crowds burning U.S. flags and the Jewish Star of David.</p>
<p>Images of the early violent years of the revolution which toppled the shah, and its leader the late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, were shown repeatedly with graphic scenes of combat in the 1980-88 Iran-Iraq war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
