<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610018" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel hints at nuclear capability.</title>
<headline>Israel hints at nuclear capability.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of the atomic energy commission in the Israeli prime minister's office was quoted on Friday as saying years of democracy were needed in Arab states before Israel could give up its nuclear capability.</p>
<p>It was a rare instance of Israeli comment on a nuclear capability.</p>
<p>When asked about nuclear arms, Israeli officials typically refuse comment other than to say that the Jewish state will not be the first to introduce such weapons into the region.</p>
<p>The newspaper Haaretz said the views of nuclear chief Gideon Frank dated from a talk he gave in Israel on the eve of national elections a year ago. It said the comments were only recently made available.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's spokesman declined comment on the report.</p>
<p>&quot;In Frank's view, Israel would give up its nuclear capability when it reaches -- with Egypt, Syria and other states -- a 'utopia' on the order of Argentina and Brazil, between which peace and full diplomatic relations prevail. Their last war was 170 years ago,&quot; Haaretz wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;Additional conditions he set were a well-organised framework for mutual cooperation particularly in the economic area in addition to a regional framework. Frank also set 'a long and phased confidence-building process',&quot; the daily said.</p>
<p>It said Frank emphasised that to build Israel's confidence, a &quot;process of democratisation&quot; in Arab states would have to occur.</p>
<p>According to foreign news reports, Israel has a nuclear arsenal of at least 200 bombs.</p>
<p>Syrian President Hafez al-Assad, in response to Israeli accusations his country was manufacturing a more lethal nerve gas, told a news conference this month in Egypt:</p>
<p>&quot;He who has nuclear weapons has no right to criticise others for whatever weapons they have. If they (Israel) want disarmament, let's start with nuclear weapons. Arabs in general are ready to get rid of other weapons.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
