<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610079" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PSE&amp;G moves closer to restarting N.J. nuke.</title>
<headline>PSE&amp;G moves closer to restarting N.J. nuke.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Public Service Electric &amp; Gas Co (PSE&amp;G) is moving closer to restarting its Salem 2 nuclear power unit before the summer air-conditioning season.</p>
<p>&quot;We are ready to request permission to restart at the end of June,&quot; a PSE&amp;G spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Testing procedures at Salem unit 2 are nearly completed as scheduled, she added.</p>
<p>The unit, in Salem, New Jersey, and adjacent unit 1, both rated at 1,106 megawatts (MW), have been shut for two years after safety concerns were raised by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission (NRC).</p>
<p>PSE&amp;G must wait with restart until after it has NRC approval, which requires the agency sending a team to inspect and evaluate the improvements and conditions of the unit after the extended overhaul.</p>
<p>&quot;They have agreed not to restart until we approve,&quot; said a NRC spokesman.</p>
<p>After the NRC team holds a meeting next Wednesday to listen to public concerns. It will begin a two-week review on Salem 2's readiness to restart on June 9.</p>
<p>Then, it would take another week to evaluate its findings and present them at a public &quot;exit&quot; conference with PSE&amp;G.</p>
<p>If the team is satisfied with the findings, it would recommend to the agency to approve the unit's restart.</p>
<p>Senior NRC officials in Washington DC with input from regional administrators will authorize clearance for PSE&amp;G to restart Salem 2, the NRC spokesman said.</p>
<p>If Salem 2 restarts, it would operate at low power for several weeks for testing, NRC and PSE&amp;G said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, PSE&amp;G still planned to restore Salem unit 1 to service in the autumn.</p>
<p>PSE&amp;G is the operator and co-owner of both Salem units. Other owners include PECO Energy Co, Delmarva Power &amp; Light Co and Atlantic Energy Co.</p>
<p>((--New York Power Desk +1 212 859 1622))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
