<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610064" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CSCE cocoa ends sharply lower, early gains erased.</title>
<headline>CSCE cocoa ends sharply lower, early gains erased.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>CSCE cocoa futures ended broadly lower on Thursday, after the failure to fill a key chart gap on the upside sparked a speculative sell-off, traders said.</p>
<p>Weakness in the British pound against the U.S. dollar also contributed to the selling, traders said, as dealers favored sterling-denominated London cocoa.</p>
<p>&quot;The sterling was down a bunch and it didn't help matters over here,&quot; one New York trader said. &quot;It just added pressure.&quot;</p>
<p>CSCE July futures ended down $23 a tonne, at $1,463, after trading from $1,498 to $1,460. Second-month September fell $19, to $1,493, while the back months slumped $18.</p>
<p>Speculative buying this morning sent cocoa prices into positive territory, with the July contract triggering buy-stops near $1,492-$1,493 and peaking at $1,498 -- partially filling the gap between $1,494 and $1,501.</p>
<p>But scale-up selling by the trade limited further gains and the market retraced, with downward momentum accelerating after July breached chart support at $1,480.</p>
<p>&quot;It tried to make an upside move. It tried to fill the gap,&quot; one trader said. &quot;After that, it lost all the buying strength behind it. This market just doesn't have any resiliency.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders said a report released by ED&amp;F Man had little impact on today's dealings. &quot;It's already factored in the market,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>ED&amp;F Man cut its 1996/97 cocoa deficit forecast to between 125,000 and 150,000 tonnes from its previous estimate in January of between 170,000 and 230,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Technically, traders pegged near-term July support at $1,460-$1,459, followed by $1,445. On the upside, resistance was seen at $1,476 and $1,483.</p>
<p>Volume was moderate, at an estimated 8,317 lots.</p>
<p>((--Patricia Avidan, New York Commodity Desk +1 212 859 1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
