<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610012" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish Tupras plans 21 mln ton crude imports in '97.</title>
<headline>Turkish Tupras plans 21 mln ton crude imports in '97.</headline>
<byline>Servet Yildirim</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's state-run refining company Tupras plans to import 21 million tonnes of crude oil, worth $3.1 billion, this year, up from 20.8 million tonnes and $3 billion in 1996, its new general manager said.</p>
<p>&quot;In addition to this, three million tonnes of domestic crude oil will be purchased this year,&quot; Husamettin Danis said on Friday in response to written questions from Reuters.</p>
<p>Danis, who replaced Ergun Kuran on Thursday, said Tupras will refine 24 million tonnes of crude oil at its four refineries this year after 23.3 million tonnes in 1996.</p>
<p>The company aims to increase its refined oil product output to 22.2 million tonnes in 1997 from a record high of 21.6 million tonnes last year.</p>
<p>It plans to export 440,000 tonnes of its output, including 400,000 tonnes of naphta. Tupras will also export 175,000 tonnes of product to the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus.</p>
<p>The company which plans to sell 25.3 million tonnes of petroleum products in domestic markets, will import four million tonnes of products worth $763.6 million -- about 87 percent of Turkey's total 1997 petroleum product imports.</p>
<p>Danis said Tupras, which employs 4,447 people, is planning to increase its total gross turnover to 1,300 trillion lira this year from 700.3 trillion last year.</p>
<p>The company has already been slated for privatisation.</p>
<p>The Privatisation Administration holds a 96.41 percent stake in the company with a capital of 30 trillion lira.</p>
<p>Danis said Tupras planned to invest 12.6 trillion lira for 1997, almost unchanged from 12.2 trillion in 1996, as part of its $1.8 billion Investment Master Plan for the period of 1989-2003.</p>
<p>The company has already completed $840-million part of the plan. About $320 million worth of projects are still continuing.</p>
<p>Danis said Tupras aimed to shift towards lighter refined products, increase refinery productivity and save energy, boost product quality to reach European specifications, prevent environmental pollution and protect human health through the master plan.</p>
<p>Danis said a $78-million modernisation project at its refinery in the western town of Izmit was expected to be completed this year.</p>
<p>The modernisation of crude oil and vacuum units will contribute another $50 million a year to the Turkish economy, he said, adding that the internal rate of return of the project was 36 percent and payback period 1.8 years.</p>
<p>A $45 million isomerisation project at the central Anatolian Kirikkale refinery is also expected to be completed this year.</p>
<p>The project with an internal rate of return of 20 percent and payback period of 4.3 years will earn the economy $8.5 million in added value a year, Danis said.</p>
<p>Tupras completed a $380 million hydrocracker and continous catalytic reformer (CCR) at the Izmir plant in February.</p>
<p>The company reported a loss of 26.9 trillion lira in the first quarter of this year, sharply up from a loss of 1.8 trillion lira in the same 1996 period.</p>
<p>Officials blamed the state's subsidised oil pricing policy for the loss. The government is planning to set up an automated pricing mechanism to eliminate losses.</p>
<p>Tupras shares were last traded at 50,000 lira on the Istanbul stock exhange in the afternoon session, down from Thursday's closing of 54,000.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
