<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610081" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Plains fed cattle market inactive - feedlots.</title>
<headline>U.S. Plains fed cattle market inactive - feedlots.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Plains feedlot cattle markets were quiet early Friday as the industry begins to settle down for the Memorial Day holiday weekend, feedlot sources said.</p>
<p>The bulk of this week's cattle sales were done at $67.00 per cwt on Tuesday, with light sales Thursday at $66.50 for the comparable quality of cattle, they said.</p>
<p>Light sales were possible Friday, but little activity was expected, several sources said.</p>
<p>Fed cattle Tuesday were seen bid at $66.00 with owners expected to price cattle at $67.00, sources said.  </p>
<p>Fed cattle prices following the holiday could be underpinned by ideas packers would be buying cattle during the short week for a full week's slaughter the following week, some sources said.</p>
<p>Major beef plants will be closed Monday in observance of Memorial Day and Saturday slaughter was expected to be light.</p>
<p>If retail beef clearance is strong over the long holiday weekend, retailers could be in the market to replenish stocks, sources noted. Prices also could be buoyed by talk packers have been buying &quot;hand to mouth&quot; as was reflected by early pick-up of cattle this week.</p>
<p>((Bob Janis 312-408-8720))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
