<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610011" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: IMF praises Palestinian budget law passage.</title>
<headline>IMF praises Palestinian budget law passage.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) on Friday welcomed the Palestinian Legislative Council's passage of its first budget law.</p>
<p>The 88-member council approved a 13-article budget law this week, setting the framework within which annual budgets are laid out. Council members said they expected an $866 million budget for 1997 to be approved next week.</p>
<p>The budget, presented to the council for the first time since the Palestinian Authority was established in 1994, was submitted late for a year that runs from January to December.</p>
<p>&quot;The IMF is extremely happy that the budget law has been passed by the Palestinian Legislative Council...It's an extremely important step since it is the first budget to be approved,&quot; Salam Fayyad, IMF director in the West Bank and Gaza, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The next step now in 1997 is strict implementation of this law. It's key for fiscal conversions to continue as planned,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Fayyad said projected revenues for the 1997 budget were $814 million while expenditures were set at $866 million.</p>
<p>A $51.8 million deficit is forecast. Both the Palestinian Authority and the IMF say they expect donor countries to cover the deficit.</p>
<p>Fayyad said the Palestinian Authority had already secured external financing of $10 million for the budget deficit.</p>
<p>Last year's deficit was $95 million. Fayyad said the deficit reduction was because of improved revenue administration.</p>
<p>The 1997 budget encompasses only current expenditures, excluding capital expenditures which depend on funds pledged by donor countries.</p>
<p>Fayyad said the IMF was looking forward to working with the Palestinian Authority on the 1998 budget, which he said he hoped would be approved early next year.</p>
<p>&quot;We also look forward to beginning work on next year's budget so it would not be delayed. We also hope that for 1998 there would be a budget encompassing both capital and current expenditures,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>- Wafa Amr, Jerusalem newsroom, 972-2-537-0502</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
