<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610066" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: INSIGHT -- Corrective dlr/yen seen capped at 117.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT -- Corrective dlr/yen seen capped at 117.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dollar/yen could rise to 117 in the short-term, before the larger downtrend reasserts itself, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're upside corrective within the larger May downturn. So 117 (yen), it looks like that's where we're heading,&quot; said Ken Boyer, foreign exchange analyst at MMS International. &quot;Then I look for some renewed selling.&quot;</p>
<p>After a brush with the 117 level, which corresponds with the daily high on May 16, Boyer said a move back down to 114 yen was likely.  </p>
<p>But analysts said they would not rule out a rise to the 117.50 to 118 yen area, where the 38.2 percent retracement target (117.90) from the decline to 111.98 yen from 127.47 can be found.</p>
<p>&quot;For now it still needs to work off some oversold daily RSI studies,&quot; said John Moore, foreign exchange analyst at Technical Data. &quot;Daily slow stochastics, they're in buy mode. So that seems to suggest dollar/yen could correct a little bit more.&quot;  </p>
<p>Below 114 yen, the next support is placed at 113.52. The 109.30 region marks an important long-term retracement target, if Tuesday's low at 111.98 is taken out, analysts said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, dollar/mark is rangebound, with a firm short-term bias, in the congested zone between 1.6850 and 1.71, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Today we're within yesterday's range and there is just not a whole lot of momentum there,&quot; said Boyer.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's the same sort of deal (as dollar/yen),  some daily studies are suggesting it can score some gains,&quot; Moore added.  </p>
<p>At 1130 EDT/1530 GMT on Friday, dollar/mark was at 1.6906/11, off from 1.6924/27 at the open. Dollar/yen was at 115.51/56, off from 115.68/73.</p>
<p>((--Alden Bentley, 212 859 1667))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
