<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610040" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NOTICE OF SALE - Richmond, Va..</title>
<headline>NOTICE OF SALE - Richmond, Va..</headline>
<text>
<p>SUMMARY NOTICE OF SALE</p>
<p>				  $5,895,000</p>
<p>			City of Richmond, Virginia</p>
<p>	     General Obligation Serial Equipment Notes</p>
<p>				  Series 1997</p>
<p>Sealed bids will be received by the Director of Finance of the City of Richmond,  Virginia (the</p>
<p>									 ), unt</p>
<p>a.m., Richmond, Virginia, Time on</p>
<p>			  Tuesday, June 10, 1997,</p>
<p>at  the  Offices  of  Wilder  &amp;  Gregory,  Eighth  and  Main Building,  707  East  Main  Street,  10th  Floor,  Richmond, Virginia, for the purchase of $5,895,000 General  Obligation Serial Equipment Notes, Series 1997 (the Notes''). The Notes will be  issued by means of  a book-entry system with no distribution of  physical note certificates made  to the public. The  Notes will  be issued  in fully  registered form, will be  dated their  date of  issuance and  delivery, which is  scheduled  for  June 24,  1997,  and  will  mature serially on May 15 in each  of the years 1998 through  2002, inclusive. Notes maturing on or after May 15, 2000, will  be callable on  or after  May 15,  1999,  as described  in  the City's detailed Official Notice of Sale. The Notes will be general obligations of the City, secured by a  pledge of  its full  faith and  credit. The  approving opinions of Lewis, Clay, Munday, Wilder &amp; Gregory, Richmond, Virginia, and Hunton &amp; Williams, Richmond, Virginia, will be furnished to the successful bidder at the City's expense. The Notes will  be awarded  to the responsible  bidder who offers to purchase the Notes at the lowest interest cost  to the City and who complies  with the City's equal  employment  opportunity  requirements   and   submission   of   required</p>
<p>documents, all as provided  in the detailed Official  Notice of Sale. Additional information,  including  the  detailed Official Notice of Sale,  the Official Bid  Form and the  Preliminary Official Statement, may  be obtained  from the  undersigned, 10th Floor,  City  Hall,  900  E.  Broad  Street,  Richmond, Virginia 23219 (telephone 804/780-5829).</p>
<p>			 CITY OF RICHMOND, VIRGINIA</p>
<p>			    By Max R. Bohnstedt</p>
<p>			    Director of Finance</p>
<p>			  (From The Bond Buyer)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
