<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610057" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. House's break leaves disaster aid in limbo.</title>
<headline>U.S. House's break leaves disaster aid in limbo.</headline>
<byline>Sue Kirchhoff</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Republican leaders shuttered the House Thursday for a week's break after blocking efforts to provide disaster aid for the flooded Midwest, sparking a bipartisan rebellion that threw Congress into chaos.</p>
<p>Furious at the prospect of going home to voters empty-handed, lawmakers by a vote of 67-278 blocked formal efforts to adjourn. Determined leaders quickly suspended House business and will hold only perfunctory sessions until the recess ends on June 3.</p>
<p>Both parties support disaster aid. But President Clinton has threatened to veto the $8.4 billion emergency spending bill because of unrelated spending and environmental amendments added by Republicans.</p>
<p>In a statement, Clinton urged lawmakers not to leave without sending him a disaster measure. &quot;The people of 33 states are waiting. ... The Congress owes it to them to pass a clean bill,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bob Livingston, chairman of the House Appopriations Committee, tried to offer a stripped-down $1 billion measure. But he was prevented by his own party leaders, who worried that pulling must-pass funding out of the original bill would reduce their leverage in talks with the White House.</p>
<p>North Dakota Representative Earl Pomeroy, whose state is trying to recover from severe floods, seethed. &quot;If this Congress goes home without doing something to provide flood relief to those who need it, this Congress will have failed,&quot; the Democratic lawmaker said.</p>
<p>Other Democrats said the decision to close shop with aid in limbo was reminiscent of the two unpopular government shutdowns engineered by Republicans during unsuccessful talks on a fiscal 1996 budget deal.</p>
<p>Under standing rules, the House must now reconvene periodically. Livingston will try again to offer his plan if House leaders will recognise him.</p>
<p>But Ohio Republican Representative John Boehner, chairman of the Republican Conference, ruled that out. &quot;They may be thinking they have an opportunity. If we were going to have a slimmed-down version, we would have had one,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Other lawmakers said they had been told to leave town, with the understanding that the aid issue was dead until Congress returned.</p>
<p>House Speaker Newt Gingrich had been willing to support aid, but his top lieutenant, Majority Leader Dick Armey, opposed it, congressional aides said. Gingrich left town before the vote on adjournment.</p>
<p>Despite days of talks, Congress and the White House could not bridge their differences on the original disaster aid bill, which would provide $5.5 billion to more than 30 states hit by floods, mudslides and other natural disasters. The bill also included about $2 billion for U.S. overseas military operations.</p>
<p>Livingston said he had been told there was enough federal money in the pipeline to help affected states. But lawmakers from those states said that was not true and the delay only caused further uncertainty and expense.</p>
<p>Senate Democrats threatened to block any move to adjourn on their side of the Capitol as well.</p>
<p>&quot;The House Republican leadership has sent one message loud and clear. That message is 'Drop dead,'&quot; South Dakota Democratic Sen. Tim Johnson said. &quot;It is utter arrogance.&quot;</p>
<p>The biggest hurdle in the way of the disaster aid bill was a provision added by Republicans to keep the government open next year automatically if Congress and the White House failed to agree on needed spending bills.</p>
<p>Clinton threatened a veto over that plan, arguing that it would provide billions less for domestic spending than allowed under a recent balanced budget deal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
