<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610036" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NOTICE OF SALE - Ocean County, N.J..</title>
<headline>NOTICE OF SALE - Ocean County, N.J..</headline>
<text>
<p>SUMMARY NOTICE OF SALE</p>
<p>				   $672,000</p>
<p>			County of Ocean, New Jersey</p>
<p>	  College Capital Improvement Bonds, Series 1997</p>
<p>		 (BOOK-ENTRY ONLYISSUE)(NON-CALLABLE)</p>
<p>SEALED PROPOSALS  will  be received,  publicly  opened and announced by the  Comptroller of  the County  of Ocean  (the County''), at the County Administration Building, on</p>
<p>			 Wednesday, June 4, 1997,</p>
<p>until 11:00 a.m., for the  purchase of the $672,000  College  Capital  Improvement  Bonds,  Series  1997  of  the   County</p>
<p>maturing on  June  15 in  the  principal amounts  set  forth below:</p>
<p>    Year     Amount	    Year     Amount</p>
<p>    1998    $134,000	   2001    $135,000</p>
<p>    1999    134,000	    2002    135,000</p>
<p>    2000    134,000</p>
<p>All bidders  for the  Bonds  must be  participants  of The Depository Trust Company, New  York, New York  (DTC''), or affiliated with its  participants. Individual purchases  may be made in the  principal amount of  $1,000 or any  multiple thereof through book entries made  on the books and  records of DTC and its participants. The Bonds will be delivered  on or about June 19, 1997 at  the offices of the County's  bond counsel, DeCotiis, FitzPatrick &amp;  Gluck, in Toms River,  New Jersey.</p>
<p>The Bonds will be dated as of June  15, 1997 and will bear interest at  the rate  or rates  of interest  per annum,  in multiples of 1/8 or 1/20 of 1%, specified by the  successful bidder,  payable  on  December  15,  1997  and  semiannually thereafter on the fifteenth day of June and December in each year until maturity. The proposed rate or rates of  interest to be borne by  the Bonds shall not  exceed 6.5% per  annum. The Bonds are not subject  to redemption prior to  maturity. The Bonds shall be entitled to the benefits of Chapter 12 of the Laws  of New  Jersey of  1971, and  the acts  amendatory thereof and supplemental thereto. The Bonds will be  awarded to the bidder on whose bid the total loan may be made at the lowest net interest  cost, in accordance  with the terms  of the sale.</p>
<p>A complete  Notice of  Sale containing  the full  terms of sale and the Preliminary  Official Statement have each  been prepared and  may be  obtained from  the County's  financial advisor, Altman &amp;  Co., 11 Pinewood  Court, Short Hills,  NJ 07078 (201/376-8916) Attention: Vivian Altman.</p>
<p>Dated: May 23, 1997</p>
<p>			 BY: /s/ Julie N. Tarrant,</p>
<p>			    County Comptroller,</p>
<p>			County of Ocean, New Jersey</p>
<p>			  (From The Bond Buyer)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
