<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610014" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Mood bullish on Beirut Stock Exchange.</title>
<headline>Mood bullish on Beirut Stock Exchange.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Banque Audi jumped 15 percent on the Beirut Stock Exchange in the week ending on Friday and brokers said they expected increased market activity next week.</p>
<p>&quot;There is definitely a bit of a mood, especially after the comments by Mark Mobius at the Arab Capital Markets conference in Beirut this week,&quot; Ali Husseini of Middle East Capital Group (MECG) told Reuters.</p>
<p>Mobius, who heads Templeton Emerging Markets is considered an emerging markets guru. He told the 400 Arab bankers and financiers at the conference he was on his second visit to Beirut and whenever he came to the Lebanese capital the air made him feel like buying.</p>
<p>&quot;We may see higher volume on many shares next week with local buyers and buyers from the Gulf,&quot; Husseini said. &quot;We are seeing definite interest from institutional investors abroad.&quot;</p>
<p>The Beirut market had been taking a breather with reduced trading volume for the past two or three weeks after frenetic trading in March and April that saw the three listed banks -- Audi, Banque Libanaise pour le Commerce and Bank of Beirut -- soar.</p>
<p>The LIBX bank index rose 5.3 percent on the week to 143.96, the LISPI general index rose 2.31 percent to 88.54 and the BLOM Stock Index fell 1.05 percent to 930.47.</p>
<p>Market rumours attributed Audi's three-day surge this week to $23 from $20 to a big buyer on the market, brokers said. The stock has followed the climb of Audi's GDRs which are $24.25-$24.75 on the Luxembourg Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>Husseini said Audi, whose shares have jumped 53 percent since listing in January, was leading the market upwards although the share would probably level off or rise slightly next week.</p>
<p>BLC, which has traded sideways for two weeks, was likely to follow Audi upwards since its P/E ratio on projected 1997 earnings at 10.24 was now well below Audi's 13.45.</p>
<p>Bank of Beirut, which was unchanged during the week, was still in demand after consolidating following its earlier price surge.</p>
<p>&quot;It has developed a very good base at these levels. People are waiting for its second quarter results,&quot; Husseini said.</p>
<p>Solidere A was unchanged on the week at $10.5 and B fell to $10.75 from $11.375 after the shares fell back from a recent surge.</p>
<p>Total weekly volume rose to 929,740 shares from 761,420 and value was $7,571,492 from $7,275,535.</p>
<p>Beirut editorial (9611) 345723 345740 602057</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
