<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610010" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish Islamists upset by secularist pressure.</title>
<headline>Turkish Islamists upset by secularist pressure.</headline>
<byline>Daren Butler</byline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Devout Turkish Moslems vented their frustration ahead of prayers on Friday at what they see as increasing secularist pressure on their beliefs.</p>
<p>Ankara's governor asked the capital's residents on Thursday to report anyone seen wearing Islamic-style turbans and robes as part of a broad-based move by the secularist establishment to curb a perceived wave of religious activism.</p>
<p>&quot;I am 80 years old. Are they going to throw me into prison? Let them do it, this is my belief,&quot; said Veysel Demirci, dressed in a white turban and long flowing robe, when asked about the governor's orders.</p>
<p>Sitting outside a mosque ahead of Friday prayers in Ankara's Islamic Haci Bayram district, Demirci accused the secularist establishment of stoking a conflict with Islamists.</p>
<p>A prosecutor announced on Wednesday he was filing a case with the constitutional court to ban Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan's Welfare Party, modern Turkey's first ruling Islamist party, for endangering the secularist state order.</p>
<p>Prosecutor Vural Savas said Welfare was pushing the country &quot;towards a civil war atmosphere.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;People are living in peace in Turkey. It is people like this who are undermining that,&quot; Demirci said of the prosecutor.</p>
<p>Pressure on Islamists has risen since February when the military-dominated National Security Council ordered a crackdown on an alleged religious revival since Erbakan came to power.</p>
<p>The council demanded moves to limit the role of religious schools and shut unofficial Koran courses. Since then, 72 illegal Koran courses have been closed and 20 new programmes were barred from opening in Ankara.</p>
<p>The council also sought tighter enforcement of restrictions on Islamic style dress introduced by the founder of Turkey's secular state, Mustafa Kemal Ataturk. These barred the turban and flowing robe for men but only discouraged veiling of women.</p>
<p>For the most part, Turkey's Moslem population dresses in Western-style clothes and even in Islamist strongholds turbans and robes are rare. But the authorities say they have become a symbol of Islamist revivalism.</p>
<p>&quot;Great Allah ordered me to wear this,&quot; said 62-year-old Ibrahim, pointing to the dark green and white turban on his head. He pulled a copy of the Koran out of his bag, kissed it and put it to his forehead.</p>
<p>&quot;But if the state orders me to take it off, I will,&quot; he shrugged, reflecting common resignation to political authority.</p>
<p>However, Ziya Bozkurt, 62, warned of a wave of Islamist protest against secularist demands. &quot;Moslems will not accept this, they are already rising to their feet,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Police detained 12 people near a religious site in the southeastern town of Sanliurfa on Friday as they marched in protest at government education plans, Anatolian agency said.</p>
<p>In eastern Erzurum province, police said an investigation had been launched into a local Imam for making a &quot;provocative&quot; speech on religious schools at a funeral ceremony.</p>
<p>Last month a Turkish court sentenced more than 100 Islamist sect members to three years in prison for forming an illegal group, insulting Ataturk and breaking the dress laws with their flowing robes and turbans.</p>
<p>Outside shops selling Islamic paraphernalia near Haci Bayram mosque, posters proclaimed support for a campaign to stop the closure of religious schools and Koran courses. Notice boards carried the front pages of Islamist newspapers attacking state efforts to crack down on religious activism.</p>
<p>&quot;People are allowed to walk freely in Moscow with turbans, but not in Fatih,&quot; Akit newspaper said in reference to an Islamist stronghold in Istanbul.</p>
<p>Police temporarily detained 81 people in a part of Fatih earlier this month in an operation against people wearing robes and turbans.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
