<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610165" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: UK's Blair urges &quot;radical shift&quot; in Europe.</title>
<headline>UK's Blair urges &quot;radical shift&quot; in Europe.</headline>
<byline>Paul Mylrea</byline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Prime Minister Tony Blair called on Friday for a &quot;radical shift&quot; in the European Union to refocus on concerns of real interest to its citizens like jobs.</p>
<p>Bringing the same reforming zeal to Europe Blair has shown at home in his first three weeks in power, Blair told fellow EU leaders in his first summit that the bloc had to stop debating its internal workings and prepare itself for the next century.</p>
<p>&quot;People know very well Britain of course wants to be a constructive player in Europe,&quot; Blair told reporters as he arrived at the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;But we will stand up resolutely and absolutely for British interests and also make sure that Europe refocusses, that Europe is looking at the things that really matter to the people of Europe, like jobs, competitiveness, the environment, consumer rights.&quot;</p>
<p>Closes aides said Blair hammered home his message in his first formal speech to a gathering of EU leaders.</p>
<p>Blair, swept to a landslide victory on May 1 which ended 18 years of Conservative rule in Britain, told his fellow leaders his election had discredited the &quot;visceral anti-Europeanism&quot; of the Conservative Eurosceptics who dogged former prime minister John Major's last year and left the country isolated in Europe.</p>
<p>But he said voters in Britain and across the bloc still felt distant from the decisions taken by a small elite running the EU.</p>
<p>In a stern message, first in one-to-one talks with European Commission President Jacques Santer and then in the full session, Blair said Britain's Labour government had shown its new constructive approach to Europe with its pledge to sign the social chapter.</p>
<p>But he warned that Britain would not accept the chapter -- which sets down standards for worker protection across the group -- being used to impose unnecessary burdens on business.</p>
<p>Blair also warned that there was &quot;no question&quot; of Britain passing control over its borders, including immigration and asylum policy, to Europe as continental European states are pressing for in the rewrite of the EU's treaties now being discussed.</p>
<p>Blair had been angered by Santer's decision to make a speech during the British election campaign criticising those opposed to further European integration.</p>
<p>The message was clearly given to Santer, although clothed in diplomatic language. Asked how the face to face talks had gone, one aide said: &quot;Mr Santer's views are known and the prime minister did all the talking.&quot; Blair has just three weeks to shape the treaty before the Amsterdam summit where it must be passed -- but diplomats said his demand to keep control over his borders is certain to be heeded by Britain's EU partners who want to keep Britain on board.</p>
<p>Blair also won a pledge from Santer to help resolve a row over quota-hopping -- when owners of vessels from other EU states buy up the fishing rights of British fishermen -- which Major threatened to make a stand on at Amsterdam.</p>
<p>Blair's mixture of a friendly tone and a tough message confounded critics in the defeated Conservative party who warned that Blair, inexperienced in government, would be no match for EU leaders like German Chancellor Helmut Kohl or French President Jacques Chirac.</p>
<p>Aides said the size of Blair's victory, seen as a result of Blair's radical overhaul of his party and his willingness to ditch traditionally sacred centre-left dogmas like opposition to privatisation, had had a &quot;profound effect across Europe and in left of centre parties in particular&quot;.</p>
<p>They said it also gave him authority to lay down the bottom line for Britain in the crucial talks on the future of the EU.</p>
<p>Aides said Blair's other face-to-face meeting on Friday morning was with Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi, who was angered recently when he interpreted a speech by British Foreign Secretary Robin Cook laying claim to a place at the EU's top table as a snub to Rome.</p>
<p>But aides said the talks had shown considerable agreement between Blair and Prodi, adding that there was no diplomatic rift. &quot;There is no problem,&quot; said one senior British aide.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
