<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610121" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Boeing says open to talks with EU.</title>
<headline>Boeing says open to talks with EU.</headline>
<byline>Martin Wolk</byline>
<dateline>SEATTLE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Boeing Co. executive on Thursday questioned the right of the European Union to block the company's planned acquisition of McDonnell Douglas Corp. but left the door open for possible negotiations.</p>
<p>Raymond Waldmann, Boeing vice president for international business, said he remained confident the proposed $14 billion merger would be approved by both U.S. and European authorities despite a formal &quot;statement of objections&quot; received from the European Commission late Wednesday.</p>
<p>While he did not rule out possible negotiations to overcome the European objections, he questioned whether the EU has jurisdiction to block the deal, which he characterised as primarily a combination of two U.S. defence contractors.</p>
<p>&quot;That's essentially how we view this,&quot; he said. &quot;That's the rationale for this -- to combine our future programmes on the defence side with McDonnell Douglas' current programmes.&quot;</p>
<p>Several analysts said they thought the EU might be trying to extract concessions from Boeing. The EU's laws would allow it to assess a fine of up 10 percent of annual gross revenues if Boeing completed a merger in defiance of the European Commission, but analysts said they thought that was unlikely.</p>
<p>&quot;The way I expect this to play out is I would expect something to be thrown their way as a political concession,&quot; said Jon Kutler, president of Quarterdeck Investment Partners, an investment banking firm devoted to the aerospace industry.</p>
<p>He and other analysts said Boeing could agree to maintain its current market share in Europe or to stop pursuing exclusive supplier arrangements like the deals it has signed with Delta Air Lines Inc. and AMR Corp.'s American Airlines.</p>
<p>Waldmann said the exclusive deals are at the top of European Competition Commissioner Karel Van Miert's &quot;personal hit list.&quot;</p>
<p>But in a 13-page position paper, Boeing focused on the merger's impact on its defence and space business and said any EC effort to derail the merger would contradict a 1991 competition agreement between the European Union and the United States.</p>
<p>Boeing has repeatedly said it believes the U.S. Federal Trade Commission, which is conducting its own investigation of the merger, should have primary authority.</p>
<p>&quot;The merger is so clearly a United States transaction that it would be contrary to reasonable expectations for the EC to take enforcement action,&quot; Boeing said in its paper, prepared before the EU's 44-page statement of objections was delivered.</p>
<p>One veteran airline analyst discounted the strident tone in both the European and U.S. comments on the case.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think anybody wants a trade war, but everybody is posturing right now to try to get as good a deal as they can,&quot; said Darryl Jenkins, a professor at George Washington University who runs the Consultancy Aviation Foundation in Falls Church, Va.</p>
<p>Noting that Boeing is the biggest U.S. exporter and that its rival Airbus Industrie includes companies from four European countries, Jenkins said officials on both sides are taking care of their &quot;constituent interests.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the EU &quot;just wants to make sure Airbus can compete in a global market. And that's what it should be.&quot;</p>
<p>Waldmann did not rule out the possibility of negotiating with the EU.</p>
<p>&quot;We know the commission has operated in that mode before,&quot; he said. When Boeing Chairman and Chief Executive Phil Condit met with Van Miert in March, the European official repeatedly said &quot;it is up to the company to suggest remedies for issues,&quot; Waldmann said.</p>
<p>He said Boeing had not yet decided on a whether to offer any such remedies but would file a written response to the EU objections in about two weeks.</p>
<p>A formal hearing is scheduled to be held in Brussels on June 12 and 13 and the commission is expected to make its final decision in late June or early July, Waldmann said.</p>
<p>Boeing's fell $2.125 to $100.375 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEATTLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
