<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610142" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Federal agents arrest 11 New York prison guards.</title>
<headline>Federal agents arrest 11 New York prison guards.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Federal investigators Thursday arrested 11 guards assigned to the Metropolitan Detention Centre in Brooklyn on charges of smuggling and supporting jailed mobsters, according to grand jury indictments.</p>
<p>They were charged with smuggling drugs, liquor, food and other supplies into the jail and helping prisoners from the mob conduct meetings and search computer files for potential witnesses. The prisoners were also warned about searches.</p>
<p>According to the indictments, corrections officers received at least $100 a week for their efforts with some getting as much as $1,000 a week during the 18-month investigation. Guard Anthony Martinez allegedly demanded $800 a week from mobsters to bring drugs, food and liquor in and to assist them in jail.</p>
<p>Each of the 22 defendants arrested Thursday faces a maximum of 15-years in prison and a $250,000 fines.</p>
<p>Among mobsters receiving special attention was Vic Orena, the boss of the Colombo crime family, court records showed. Others included Nicholas Corazzo, said to be a ranking member in the Gambino crime family.</p>
<p>Two men with mob connections allegedly paid so at least 10 other mobsters could receive the illegal goods and help from the corrupt jailers, court papers showed.</p>
<p>Martinez, 35, a 10-year veteran of the Bureau of Prisons and the jail's chief hostage negotiator, is alleged to have turned over to mobsters the names of informants in their cases after checking through prison computers.</p>
<p>Martinez was also charged with agreeing to smuggle in 10 grams of heroin sold by an undercover agent.</p>
<p>Alberto Cruz,  28, a two-year veteran of the prison service was videotaped smuggling in expensive food. He also smuggled in marijuana, vodka and steroids for cash and two tickets to the Radio City Christmas show.</p>
<p>According to the indictments, Cruz told an informant, he needed the money to pay for a ski trip.</p>
<p>The corrections officer's union president, Raymond Cotton, 39, a six-year, veteran, was also arrested. Cotton allegedly notified mob inmates that other officers were going to be conducting a search for prison-made knife called a &quot;shank.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
