<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610176" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: N.Europe rapeseed price off, buyers lose interest.</title>
<headline>N.Europe rapeseed price off, buyers lose interest.</headline>
<dateline>HAMBURG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rapeseed prices in Northern Europe have fallen sharply in line with a weaker Chicago soybean complex and because of fading crusher interest in old crop seed, brokers said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Crushers are emptying stocks and British and French traders are also offering cheap rapeseed,&quot; one broker said.</p>
<p>&quot;There have also been reports of Czech sales to Germany. More and more sellers compete for a shrinking market.&quot;</p>
<p>Buyers free Hamburg reduced their ideas for June old crop purchases by 10 marks to 480 marks a tonne while June rapeseed of British origin was offered at 460 marks fob, where 20-25 marks have to be added for freight.</p>
<p>Virtually ideal crop weather conditions were expected to weigh on rapeseed prices over the next few weeks.</p>
<p>Seed for the 1997 harvest is receiving enough rain and has shrugged off the effects of comparatively low May temperatures, weather reports showed.</p>
<p>New crop buyers free Hamburg offered a little changed 455 marks for August delivery while Baltic and North Sea buyers paid 450 marks fob for the new crop.</p>
<p>May buyers at points other than Hamburg were at 455-480 marks, down from 480-495 last week and from 502-510 marks a fortnight ago, with June at 480-482.50 (495-500) and August at 437-450 (440-455).</p>
<p>Eastern German farmers had sold sizeable parts of the 1997 harvest in prefixed contracts at 410-440 marks ex-farm, price office ZMP said in a weekly report.</p>
<p>August rapeseed futures on the Matif exchange last traded at 446 marks, off two from last night and down nine on the week.</p>
<p>Rape meal ex Hamburg mills was offered unchanged at 31.00-31.25 marks per 100 kg fob spot, with June at 30.75, first half July at 30.50 and August-October at 26.00.</p>
<p>Rape oil sellers were little changed on the week at 91.75 marks per 100 kg for June-July and 91.00 for August-October.</p>
<p>--Vera Eckert, Hamburg newsroom, +49-40-41903275</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAMBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
