<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610180" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Catholic scholar condemns Colombia euthanasia law.</title>
<headline>Catholic scholar condemns Colombia euthanasia law.</headline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Roman Catholic theologian close to Pope John Paul criticised on Friday the Colombian Constitutional Court's decision earlier this week to legalise euthanasia for some terminally-ill patients.</p>
<p>&quot;With the decision of the court a gap has been created in the defence of the inviolability of human life,&quot; moral theologian Gino Concetti wrote in an article for the Vatican's semi-official L'Osservatore Romano newspaper.</p>
<p>Colombia's highest court ruled on Tuesday that people who helped seriously ill friends or relatives to die would no longer face maximum charges of six years imprisonment for euthanasia.</p>
<p>Concetti said the fact the ruling only applied to terminally-ill patients who made the request to die themselves did not make it any more morally acceptable.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that euthanasia would be carried out in a terminal stage and with the consent of the patient does not change the nature of the act which is intrinsically perverse,&quot; he said in the article entitled 'A Perverse Hypocrisy: killing for mercy'.</p>
<p>Concetti added that he hoped the Colombian Congress (lower house) would overturn the ruling as the Australian federal parliament had done after the world's first euthanasia law was passed by the Northern Territory government in July 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;It is to be hoped the Congress will re-establish the truth of the inviolability of the human life of seriously ill patients,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Vatican has consistently opposed any form of artificial control on human life, including both euthanasia and abortion. Roman Catholicism is the most widely practiced religion in Colombia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="COL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
