<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610168" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NetherlandS: EU leaders begin talks on bloc reforms.</title>
<headline>EU leaders begin talks on bloc reforms.</headline>
<byline>Ian Geoghegan</byline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Union leaders began informal talks on Friday aimed at forging a more modern Europe ahead of enlargement and the new millennium.</p>
<p>Meeting at a seaside hotel in the Dutch resort of Noordwijk, heads of the 15 governments, accompanied by their foreign ministers, hoped to inject pace into gruelling 15-month-long EU treaty reform negotiations.</p>
<p>The Dutch EU presidency called the half-day summit so that leaders could sound each other out and gauge the chances of a successful agreement at an Amsterdam summit on June 16-17.</p>
<p>German Chancellor Helmut Kohl told reporters on his arrival that no decisions would be taken at the meeting, which was aimed at preparing the ground for Amsterdam.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a pre-discussion, not a decision-making conference. It will bring progress. Many of you will again report that there has been no progress but, as always, a treaty will be agreed at Amsterdam,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Britain's Prime Minister Tony Blair grabbed the early limelight as he arrived for his European summit debut.</p>
<p>His Labour party's election victory over the Euro-sceptic Conservatives has been welcomed in Europe as crucial to the inter-governmental conference (IGC) negotiations, which have slowed due to British objections to deeper EU integration.</p>
<p>Blair's government has offered its EU partners a fresh, more constructive approach to Europe, lifting Conservative threats of a veto on various parts of the new treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;We will...make sure that Europe refocuses, that Europe is looking at the things that really matter, like jobs, competitiveness, the environment, consumer rights, the basic things that matter to the person in the street,&quot; Blair said as he arrived for a pre-summit meeting with socialist leaders.</p>
<p>His more pro-European comments -- on playing a constructive role -- were welcomed by other leaders in Noordwijk.</p>
<p>Danish Prime Minister Poul Nyrup Rasmussen said that Blair's election had been been &quot;enormously helpful&quot;, while his fellow social democrat, Swedish Prime Minister Goran Persson, added: &quot;We have already seen now that it is easier to negotiate.&quot;</p>
<p>But Blair was quick to point out that he was in no mood to surrender national control of Britain's island borders.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't expect movement (from Britain) on all issues,&quot; Irish Prime Minister John Bruton told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Britain is adopting a more pragmatic and less ideological approach to Europe which is good because that is the way Europe works as a whole.&quot;</p>
<p>The new treaty is designed to prepare the bloc for an ambitious eastward expansion, taking in Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic within the next decade, and adding as many as seven others from Estonia to Cyprus further down the line.</p>
<p>Negotiations among foreign ministers have been running since March 1996, but Friday's meeting marked the beginning of a new phase in which the leaders themselves would take control.</p>
<p>Luxembourg premier Jean-Claude Juncker said earlier this week that it was time for the leaders to step in because the foreign ministers' talks appeared to be running out of steam.</p>
<p>Some leaders have said that ambitions must be scaled back by those countries seeking a bold new step towards political union and that the new treaty should simply deal with what has to be done to ensure the Union works over the next few years.</p>
<p>That includes more majority voting and streamlining some EU institutons.</p>
<p>The treaty's centrepiece is expected to be the creation of a freedom and security zone from Athens to Helsinki by early in the next century, lifting internal borders and strengthening the bloc's ability to fight organised crime and illegal immigration.</p>
<p>Leaders will also be keen to show their voters that they are doing something about the bloc's double-digit unemployment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
