<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610143" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Rural school districts sue Alaska over funding.</title>
<headline>Rural school districts sue Alaska over funding.</headline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>Six rural school districts, along with a group of parents and educators, have sued the state of Alaska for what they claim is unfair funding, state officials said Thursday.</p>
<p>Plaintiffs in the lawsuit, filed Tuesday in Alaska Superior Court in Anchorage, are districts and residents of southwest and western Alaska, areas that have limited taxing and bonding capabilities and are generally poorer than the rest of the state.</p>
<p>The school districts, parents and educators said the state &quot;has failed to live up to its constitutional obligation to provide an adequate education to children of this state.&quot;</p>
<p>The lawsuit alleges discrimination by the Republican-controlled legislature against the rural, largely Alaska Native districts in favour of urban districts, which can pay for parts of their own capital projects.</p>
<p>Even though the state Department of Education has listed several rural construction and maintenance projects as high priorities -- some of them necessary to protect students' health and safety -- the legislature has failed to fund them, the lawsuit said.</p>
<p>Harry Gamble, a spokesman for the Department of Education, said state officials were reviewing the districts' complaint.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking at the lawsuit right now,&quot; he said. &quot;However, we know there  are a lot of unmet facilities needs across the state, both in new construction and major maintenance.&quot;</p>
<p>While cities and organised boroughs have the ability to issue bonds to build and repair schools, unorganized boroughs in rural Alaska do not have such power and rely solely on state allocations, Gamble said.</p>
<p>Plaintiffs in the school-funding lawsuit are the Bering Strait School District, Iditarod Area School District, Kashunamuit School District, Lower Kuskokwim School District, Lower Yukon School District and Yupiit School District.</p>
<p>Residents in the areas are Yupik Eskimos, Inupiat Eskimos and Athabaskan Indians.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
