<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610188" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Ex-Nazi Priebke was sadistic torturer, trial hears.</title>
<headline>Ex-Nazi Priebke was sadistic torturer, trial hears.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The families of men killed in Italy's worst World War Two massacre told a court on Friday that former SS captain Erich Priebke was a sadist and a torturer.</p>
<p>&quot;Priebke was the most sadistic, the most coldhearted of the SS officers in Rome,&quot; said Elvira Sabbatini, whose husband was a prisoner in a Nazi jail during Germany's occupation of Rome.</p>
<p>&quot;He beat my husband. He used a steel glove,&quot; she told the war crimes trial being held in a military court.</p>
<p>Sabbatini and other relatives of the 335 men and boys shot in the Ardeatine Caves massacre in March 1944, were testifying against Priebke, 83, and former SS Major Karl Hass, 84.</p>
<p>Both are accused of complicity in the atrocity, ordered in retaliation for a partisan bomb attack which killed 33 soldiers of the occupying forces.</p>
<p>Remo Pellegrini recounted how he watched SS officers rounding up some of the victims from the Regina Coeli prison where he was also being held prisoner.</p>
<p>&quot;I saw there were invalids and men in wheelchairs among them. I understood they were not being taken to work abroad, as the guards said, but were being led to be shot,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The victims were taken by truck to the caves outside Rome, where they were shot in the back of the head in groups of five.</p>
<p>Priebke and Hass have admitted to taking part in the massacre, and to shooting some of the victims, but have said they had to follow orders or face the firing squad themselves.</p>
<p>Priebke is being tried for the second time in the case after a controversial verdict at the end of his first trial last August, which found him guilty but not punishable because of a statute of limitations. The verdict was quashed on appeal.</p>
<p>The trial's next session is scheduled for Tuesday, but may be postponed until June 5 because of a lawyers' strike.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
