<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610146" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Cuban voodoo gains devotees in United States.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Cuban voodoo gains devotees in United States.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Boadle</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Just blocks from the White House on a busy restaurant street, a black Madonna beckons from a shop window offering to help your love life, vanquish your enemies, find you a job.</p>
<p>She is Yemaya, a goddess of Santeria, a Cuban form of voodoo that is gaining followers in the United States despite controversy over its ritual of sacrificing animals.</p>
<p>In her shop, the unlucky can purchase jinx-removing soaps or spell-breaking ointments to change their fortunes.</p>
<p>Jilted lovers can try to rekindle old flames with powders made from horse hairs and offerings of sun-dried possum. Or, they may seek revenge by sticking pins in a $5 voodoo doll.</p>
<p>Divination by reading cards or shells is also available for those wondering what the future holds in store.</p>
<p>&quot;Depending on the seriousness of the case, you may need a sacrifice,&quot; says the shop's former manager Angel Hueca. &quot;If you've lost your job, you would want to sacrifice a chicken.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I have seen people take goats to their apartments. It depends on how badly you need help,&quot; added Hueca, who is now planning to become a Santero priest.</p>
<p>Santeria, or &quot;the worship of the saints,&quot; is the religion of the Yoruba people who were brought to Cuba as slaves from West Africa. Since their Spanish masters banned their religion, the slaves outwardly pretended to worship Catholic Saints to disguise their African deities called Orishas.</p>
<p>Cuban immigrants brought the religion to the United States where it has spread in urban centres with large Latin American populations of Caribbean origin such as New York and Miami.</p>
<p>MORE AMERICANS JOINING</p>
<p>An increasing number of Americans, particularly black Americans, have turned to Santeria seeking a new religion.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a dissatisfaction with institutionalized religions,&quot; says J. Lorand Matory, a professor of anthropology and Afro-American studies at Harvard University.</p>
<p>&quot;A greater attention is being given to ethnicity, and that has led African Americans to join African-inspired religions.&quot;</p>
<p>Santeria devotees worship the Orishas through offerings of animals, plants and food, with chants and dancing to African drum rhythms. In return, the deities are said to grant them health, prosperity, children and wisdom.</p>
<p>The spread of the religion can been seen from the numerous &quot;botanicas&quot; or stores specialising in Santeria supplies that have cropped up in Latino neighbourhoods.</p>
<p>&quot;When I was a child, Santeria had to be practiced in secret. We used to meet in people's basements,&quot; said Hueca. &quot;But now Santeria is coming out.&quot;</p>
<p>While Santeria is beginning to emerge from centuries in hiding, its following is hard to gauge as believers still keep their faith to themselves to avoid controversy.</p>
<p>There are an estimated 70,000 followers in South Florida, mostly in Dade County, and up to 800,000 in the United States.</p>
<p>The sacrificial slaying of chickens, doves and goats makes this one of the most controversial religions practiced today.</p>
<p>In 1987, the Hialeah city council in Miami banned animal sacrifices, a move aimed at the Church of Lukumi Babalu Aye led by Santero priest Ernesto Pichardo.</p>
<p>COMPLAINTS ABOUT STRENCH</p>
<p>Local residents had complained about the stench of dead chickens and carcasses of goats turning up on street corners and in the sewers of Hialeah.</p>
<p>The case went to the U.S. Supreme Court, which ruled in a landmark 1993 decision that the Hialeah ordinances violated the First Amendment of the U.S. Constitution guaranteeing the free exercise of religion.</p>
<p>Despite this legal victory, the Afro-Cuban religion has run into stiff opposition from animal rights groups seeking to stop ritual slaughter.</p>
<p>Opponents have turned to public health regulations, such as the need for an abattoir permit or restrictions on the disposal of animal remains. Santeria temples are often raided and searched by police.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not criminals. We are not doing anything wrong or illegal. We are working to help and save people,&quot; says Steve Quintana, a Cuban-born Santero priest.</p>
<p>&quot;We tell them the 'santo' can help them recover their health, find a job, get ahead,&quot; said Quintana at his House of Obatala temple in Ashmont, a working class district of Boston.</p>
<p>Quintana, who says he has over 700 followers, has started a petition for a charter that will make Santeria an official religion, with a permit for ceremonies and tax benefits.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a cult, this is a religion, with traditions that go back centuries,&quot; he said. His followers are mostly Puerto Rican and Dominican, but also include Americans of Italian and Greek origin and Jews.</p>
<p>Sacrifices are not frequent, Quintana said, since food offerings to the deities usually do the trick.</p>
<p>&quot;This religion has been in hiding too long. Now we want to bring it out into the open like any other religion,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
