<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610185" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FOCUS-SGS-Thomson cuts 1997 market forecast.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-SGS-Thomson cuts 1997 market forecast.</headline>
<byline>Marcel Michelson</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European semiconductor producer SGS-Thomson Microelectronics NV on Friday said it was cutting its forecast for the growth in the world semiconductor market to six percent for 1997 from a previous 7.4 percent.</p>
<p>Jean-Philippe Dauvin, chief economist at the Franco-Italian group, told reporters that he expected an end to the general overcapacity in the semiconductor market in the third quarter of 1997, after two years of adjustment.</p>
<p>This follows a dip of 11 percent in the first quarter of 1997 while the second quarter is likely to be only &quot;a few percentage points&quot; above this first quarter.</p>
<p>But he said, &quot;we are at the foothill of at least four years of growth of more than 20 percent per year.&quot; He therefore maintained his longstanding forecast of a total semiconductor market in the year 2000 of $300 billion, rising to $364 billion in 2002.</p>
<p>His previous forecast was of October 1996. In the year 1996, the market had a total sales size of $132 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;After 14 months of brutal adjustment, bookings hit bottom in August 1996. During the fourth quarter of 1996 bookings were picking up but despite this positive trend the first quarter of 1997 was the billing low point of this cycle at minus 11 percent over the first quarter of 1996,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;1997 will see growth resuming at a low pace due to pending memory overcapacity and lack of visibility on other products,&quot; Dauvin added.</p>
<p>&quot;The next cycle should start during the second half of 1997 and will blossom all through 1998 to 2000,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dauvin is also president of the Word Semiconductor Trade Statistics (WSTS) body which met last month in Taiwan to agree on a consensus forecast. WSTS sees 1997 growth of 4.6 percent and a year 2000 figure of $246 billion.</p>
<p>He said that for Dynamic Random Access Memory (DRAM) chips, which have been a main market driver for many years, the overcapacity situation could well last until in 1998.</p>
<p>The total memory market could be down by another 19 percent over 1996, with only flash memory growing.</p>
<p>Dauvin said that there would be a profound change in the market, with former key products as DRAM and discrete memory products seeing slow growth while differentiated integrated circuits should increase.</p>
<p>This is the result of an increasing importance of the mobile telecommunications and automotive electronics market.</p>
<p>He said that microprocessors, the lifeline of companies such as Intel, should see a slowdown in their sales growth to 20 percent per year from 40 percent.</p>
<p>DRAM sales will grow by less than five percent per year between now and 2000 while the rate was 40 percent for the 1990 to 1995 period.</p>
<p>To illustrate the change in the market, Dauvin said that personal computer sales would rise by 17 percent in 1997 from 69 million units in 1996. Colour television would be up four percent from 107 million units while set-top boxes for pay television would increase by 21 percent from 18 million.</p>
<p>Cellular phones will rise by 35 percent from 66 million units and car electonics by nine percent from $42 billion.</p>
<p>Dauvin said this would boost the market position of the European chipmakers, with SGS-Thomson at number 10 in 1996 behind Philips Electroncis NV at nine and ahead of Siemens at number 12.</p>
<p>It could weaken some U.S. and Japanese companies in the ranking while there will be much growth from Asian companies, mainly Taiwanese and South Korean.</p>
<p>It will take a lot, however, to challenge Intel's revenue ranking. The company was number one in 1996 with $17.78 billion in sales, a 35 percent rise over 1995 for a 12.7 percent market share.</p>
<p>Number two, NEC Corp of Japan, made $10.3 billion in sales and had a market share of 7.3 percent.</p>
<p>-- Paris newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I34531">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
