<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610115" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Postlethwaite, Hollywood's favourite Englishman.</title>
<headline>Postlethwaite, Hollywood's favourite Englishman.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>BEVERLY HILLS, California 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pete Postlethwaite may not be a big box-office name, but he's currently Hollywood's Englishman &quot;du jour.&quot;</p>
<p>How often does an actor have not one, but two movies opening in the world movie capital on the same day?</p>
<p>In &quot;The Lost World&quot;, Steven Spielberg's sequel to &quot;Jurassic Park,&quot; he plays an anti-environmentalist hunter out to bag a Tyrannosaurus Rex.</p>
<p>In contrast, the dinosaurs of Britain's Conservative Party loom in Postlethwaite's sights in the less commercial, but delightfully biting &quot;independent&quot; film, &quot;Brassed Off&quot;.</p>
<p>At 51, he's neither a handsome Ralph Fiennes nor a cute Hugh Grant, but Postlethwaite's gaunt looks are sure to become familiar to worldwide audiences in &quot;The Lost World&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's quite extraordinary, having two films opening here, and (another) one in competition in Cannes too (&quot;The Serpent's Kiss&quot;), he told Reuters over breakfast in his Beverly Hills hotel.</p>
<p>&quot;Somebody asked me how can you do a small independent film like 'Brassed Off' and then 'The Lost World,' which is the next big blockbuster. I couldn't answer; I don't know why you do it. You just follow the script, don't you,&quot; he said with typically English self-effacement.</p>
<p>Of course, it didn't hurt to get an Oscar nomination for best supporting actor in 1993's &quot;In the Name of the Father&quot; and to give a standout performance as Friar Lawrence in last year's MTV-style &quot;William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet&quot;.</p>
<p>Director Spielberg ended up not only casting Postlethwaite in &quot;The Lost World&quot; but also in his next film &quot;Amistad&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;BRASSED OFF&quot; BEST</p>
<p>However it is in &quot;Brassed Off&quot; that his true character comes out in the portrayal of a Yorkshire miner, dying of lung disease but determined to take the brass band he leads to the national finals in the face of government mine closures.</p>
<p>It is a not very subtle tale about how the soul of a community -- symbolised by the brass band -- can be destroyed by the political whims of a seemingly uncaring government.</p>
<p>Growing up after the war in Warrington, a mill-town outside Liverpool, Postlethwaite is nostalgic for the brass bands he heard as a boy.</p>
<p>&quot;They were magical days,&quot; the actor said. &quot;The sound of that brass band is deeply embedded in my genes.&quot;</p>
<p>But if he is modest about his acting, Postlethwaite opens up when talk turns to the Conservative governments that ruled Britain for the last 18 years.</p>
<p>&quot;I just loved what it (&quot;Brassed Off&quot;) was saying. That it was not being an allegory, it was not being a veiled criticism of a government I disrespected or didn't like. It was actually fairly and squarely laying the blame for what happened in that community exactly at the door of...(former Conservative Prime Minister) Margaret Thatcher,&quot; Postlethwaite said.</p>
<p>Inhaling coffee and Marlboros, Postlethwaite can barely contain his glee at this month's British election returning a Labour government for the first time since 1979.</p>
<p>&quot;It was time for a change, if you look at the catalogue of disasters that have occurred in the last 18 years in the welfare of Britain. Just look what happened to the welfare system, education, theatres and film, anything to do with everybody's ordinary well-being was slowly, slowly dismantled,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>SAYS HE NOT POLITICAL, THEN ATTACKS THATCHER</p>
<p>Professing no political allegiance, but favouring Labour, he launches into the same kind of attack on Conservatives that his character does in the stunning climax to &quot;Brassed Off.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;She (Thatcher) was determined in her personal and vindictive way to squash that pit. When you take away their (miners') right to work in that pit, you take away their community, their history, their culture. You take away their livelihood because there's nothing else there.&quot;</p>
<p>Warming to the subject, Postlethwaite, who came to film via the British repertory circuit and the Royal Shakespeare Company, sees Britain's rich theatrical heritage going the same way as the coal mines.</p>
<p>&quot;As soon as they (Conservatives) said: 'We're pulling any kind of support for regional theatre,' then the local governments were forced to pull back on their budgets, and local theatres were forced to do the lowest common denominator,&quot; he said, citing farces and touring musicals.</p>
<p>&quot;All the young writers couldn't experiment and slowly they (theaters) died.&quot;</p>
<p>And the country is poorer for it, Postlethwaite believes.</p>
<p>&quot;Some people in Britain say: &quot;Well, no matter what you say about Maggie, she was very strong and powerful.'</p>
<p>&quot;Well you've just got to say 'So was Hitler! So was bloody Hitler!'&quot; he laughed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEVERLY HILLS, California"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
