<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610198" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French first-round vote may obscure final winner.</title>
<headline>French first-round vote may obscure final winner.</headline>
<byline>Irwin Arieff</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Caution: Hidden curves ahead.</p>
<p>The results of Sunday's first-round vote may well obscure the ultimate winner of the French parliamentary election until the June 1 second round, analysts warn.</p>
<p>They predict, based on voter surveys, that the combined left will win the highest first-round score, only to lose to the governing centre-right in the run-off, when winners of most of the National Assembly's 577 seats will be decided.</p>
<p>That is because supporters of the extreme-right National Front switch predominantly to conservative candidates in run-offs where Front candidates are absent, the analysts say.</p>
<p>But the first-round vote should provide strong hints of the final outcome, which will fix the contours of the French political landscape for the next five years.</p>
<p>Official first-round results will not be known until early on Monday, due to the record number of candidates, an average of 11 in each of France's 577 constituencies.</p>
<p>Polling firms are expected to project first-round scores as well as expected breakdown of seats in a new assembly, beginning at 8 p.m. (1800 GMT).</p>
<p>Due to the large number of contenders, &quot;It will be a difficult first round. It will be difficult even to interpret the results since it is doubtful that a strong trend will emerge,&quot; Prime Minister Alain Juppe said.</p>
<p>The governing coalition had an overwhelming majority in the outgoing assembly with 464 deputies on its side of the aisle, to 63 Socialist deputies or allies, 24 Communists, 23 independents, two unaffiliated deputies and one vacant seat.</p>
<p>Pollsters predict improved first-round scores for the combined left, which won some 31 percent of the vote in 1993, and the National Front, which won 12.7 percent that year.</p>
<p>The extent of their gains will be key to the final result.</p>
<p>Also closely watched will be majority candidates in Paris and allies of hard-right Euro-sceptic Philippe de Villiers.</p>
<p>A weak government showing in the capital or strong gains by de Villiers will set off alarms, signaling erosion in government support in areas of historical strength.</p>
<p>In the first round of this year's election, the top two candidates in each district plus anyone who polls at least 12.5 percent of the total number of registered voters, qualify for the June 1 runoff.</p>
<p>Results will be particularly confusing if the National Front, whose fiery leader Jean-Marie Le Pen won 15 percent in a 1995 presidential election, performs that well, or better, on Sunday, creating numerous three-way races in the second round.</p>
<p>Some analysts have predicted there could be more than 200 of these three-way run-offs.</p>
<p>Sunday's turnout will also be crucial to the final election outcome, as the 12.5 percent cut-off for run-off eligibility is calculated by a percentage of the total number of registered voters rather than those actually voting.</p>
<p>If turnout is high, Front candidates will find it easier to make it into run-offs, favouring a possible government upset.</p>
<p>A low turnout, on the other hand, would favour the government, which has far more incumbents standing who would enjoy a second-round advantage over lesser-known rivals.</p>
<p>&quot;Do not abstain from voting on Sunday, because abstention helps the right,&quot; Socialist Party leader Lionel Jospin urged in the southwestern city Toulouse on Thursday.</p>
<p>Political analyst Alain Duhamel has calculated that if abstentions this year ran at the same 30.8 percent rate as in the last general election in 1993, a candidate would need on average just over 18 percent of the votes cast to get into the second round.</p>
<p>The record abstention rate in a parliamentary election was 34.3 percent in 1988, in which case candidates would need on average just over 19 percent of the total votes cast to make it into the run-off.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
