<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610182" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Dutch shares end range-bound session higher on Dow.</title>
<headline>Dutch shares end range-bound session higher on Dow.</headline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dutch shares swung a touch higher in late session as a higher Wall Street opening injected some enthusiasm into a lacklustre market.</p>
<p>The AEX index of leading shares finished up 3.12 points at 803.96, back from a high of 804.98, after spending most of the day hovering around 802 points.</p>
<p>Dealers said that while underlying sentiment was firm, a lack of major corporate or macro-economic data coupled with the upcoming market holidays in New York and London had kept most players sidelined.</p>
<p>Many stocks looked to be trading on old news, dealers said.</p>
<p>Steel and aluminium concern Hoogovens continued to coast on CS First Boston's initiation of coverage on a 'buy' rating on Thursday, adding 1.70 guilders to 99.00.</p>
<p>Foods group Nutricia added five guilders to 301.00 on fresh reports it planned a 'separate life' for its dairy and drinks division after earlier abortive attempts to swap it for the babyfood activities of rival Friesland Dairy Foods.</p>
<p>Retail and services concern Vendex also gained after announcing details of the float of its Vedior temporary employment arm on Thursday, adding 1.90 guilders to 108.60.</p>
<p>&quot;The market thinks the Vedior issue will prove very lucrative, and that's why they're getting into Vendex now,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
<p>Among the smaller caps, builder BAM shrugged off news of its failed bid to merge with unlisted sector rival Wilma, adding one guilder to 125.50 after it said it was maintaining its forecast of a return to the black in full-year 1997 with profits of at least 20 million guilders.</p>
<p>Shipping and marine construction group IHC Caland rose 3.30 guilders to 104.80, after a recent heavy seller exited the market and bargain hunters stepped in.</p>
<p>Semiconductor equipment maker ASM Lithography surged strongly in brisk trade, adding 7.30 guilders to 97.30 on news broker Merrill Lynch had reiterated its buy rating.</p>
<p>&quot;ASM is a very volatile stock anyway,&quot; one dealer said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
