<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610169" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German FDP leader warns of dangers if EMU fails.</title>
<headline>German FDP leader warns of dangers if EMU fails.</headline>
<dateline>WIESBADEN, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leader of Germany's liberal Free Democrats (FDP), junior partners in Chancellor Helmut Kohl's government, warned on Friday of the dangers of failing to realise European monetary union.</p>
<p>Wolfgang Gerhardt told a party congress that a failure of the single currency project would lead to a relaxation of monetary and fiscal discipline, push up the value of the mark and harm the competitiveness of German firms.</p>
<p>&quot;The danger cannot be ruled out that the single European market would erode, governments would no longer be able to resist the temptation of competitive devaluations,&quot; Gerhardt told delegates in the central spa town of Wiesbaden.</p>
<p>Gerhardt said he was confident Germany would meet the criteria for monetary union and that the euro would be a strong and stable currency which would boost the German economy.</p>
<p>&quot;I am convinced we can't forge our future on our own as an island of stability,&quot; he said to loud applause from delegates.</p>
<p>He also offered strong support to Finance Minister Theo Waigel's plan to revalue the Bundesbank's gold reserves in the run-up to the single currency.</p>
<p>&quot;The Bundesbank will sell not one ounce of gold and no currency reserves. A burden of the capital markets is therefore ruled out and an important political goal, the borrowing convergence criterion for the currency union, will be met.&quot;</p>
<p>Like all major German political parties, the FDP is overwhelmingly pro-European but some members at the congress called for a referendum or at least a party membership survey on the single currency.</p>
<p>One delegate, noting that opinion polls showed around two thirds of German voters rejected the single currency, said a party which had the courage to support the euro must also have the courage to put the issue to a vote.</p>
<p>Former economics minister Juergen Moellemann said it was important the party debated the subject of monetary union.</p>
<p>&quot;It is strange the way the subject is a taboo for all parties,&quot; Moellemann told the Koelner Stadt-Anzeiger newspaper. &quot;The acceptance of the new currency, in the population as a whole and especially among FDP voters, is very limited.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WIESBADEN, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
