<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610134" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PRESS DIGEST - Washington Post front - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Washington Post front - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Washington Post carried the following items on its front page on May 23:</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - Lt. Kelly Flinn agreed to resign without an honorable discharge to avoid a court-martial over an adulterous affair.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>DENVER, Colorado - Attorneys for Oklahoma City bombing defendant Timothy McVeigh opened their defence with testimony suggesting that a mystery bomber may have died in the April 19, 1995 explosion.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - Police arrested an Indian immigrant and the owner of a neighbourhood bar in Arlington, Virginia, for allegedly stealing a winning lottery ticket from a customer.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - The United States has imposed economic sanctions on two Chinese companies and five Chinese citizens for selling chemicals and chemical production equipment to Iran.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>MOSCOW - President Boris Yeltsin fired his defence minister and the chief of his general staff, and issued a blistering attack on the military high command.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - A Rockville man was indicted on charges of manslaughter and driving while intoxicated, even though his teenage son was driving their car -- without a learner's permit or driver's licence -- when it swerved into the path of a world-class triathlete.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
