<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610154" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Helms, Gilman threaten to block aid to PLO.</title>
<headline>Helms, Gilman threaten to block aid to PLO.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>The chairmen of two key Congressional committees said on Thursday they would oppose any further U.S. aid to the Palestinian Authority until it withdrew a law barring the sale of private land to Jews.</p>
<p>The threat by Senate Foreign Relations Committee chairman Jesse Helms and House International Relations Committee chairman Ben Gilman came amid a furore over revival of a law imposing a death sentence on Palestinians who make such sales.</p>
<p>The State Department on Wednesday deplored a statement by Palestinian President Yasser Arafat that he backed enforcement of the law, which dates back to the period when Jordan ruled the West Bank. Israel captured the area in 1967.</p>
<p>In a letter to Secretary of State Madeleine Albright, Helms and Gilman, both Republicans, demanded assurances that the Palestinian Authority was not involved in the murders of two Palestinians recently found dead in the West Bank.</p>
<p>The two had allegedly sold land to Jews.</p>
<p>Until they received such assurances, the Congressmen said, &quot;we will oppose any assistance programme flowing to or through the Palestinian Authority or its ministries, agencies or designees.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Further, we will continue to oppose such assistance until such time as we are assured by you or by relevant authorities in the Palestinian Authority ... (that they) have withdrawn the proposed legislation barring the sale of private Arab land to Jews,&quot; they added.</p>
<p>The United States is currently mid-way through disbursing to the Palestinians a $500 million aid pledge over five years which began in 1994. U.S. officials said each annual aid payment was subject to a vote in Congress.</p>
<p>The State Department has said it has no evidence that the Palestinian Authority, which runs self-rule areas in the West Bank and Gaza under the Oslo peace accords, was involved in the killings of the two Palestinians, Farid Bashiti and Harbi Abu-Sara.</p>
<p>But spokesman Nicholas Burns said Wednesday: &quot;The United States condemns any law or any decree that would threaten death against any Palestinian for selling land to Israelis or Jews. That's wrong. It's contrary to what must prevail in the Middle East, which is peace.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
