<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610141" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Goshawk pair terrorizes Anchorage joggers.</title>
<headline>Goshawk pair terrorizes Anchorage joggers.</headline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>State biologists are advising some Anchorage joggers to alter their route, now that a pair of protective goshawks have built a nest and hatched some goslings near a popular midtown trail.</p>
<p>Alaska Department of Fish and Game biologist Rick Sinnott, himself a victim of the swooping birds, said at least four people have been pecked or slashed by the goshawks nesting by the Anchorage Pacific University campus trail.</p>
<p>The mother goshawk is the most vicious, Sinnott said Thursday. &quot;If she sees you and you're within that 100 yards or so of the nest, she's going to get you,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Sinnott said he believes several other people have been attacked, but have not yet reported their mishaps to the state.</p>
<p>As he was walking toward the area Wednesday, with a television news team in tow, another pair of joggers ventured too close to the nest, he said. &quot;One was screaming, so I suspect it got him, too,&quot; the biologist said.</p>
<p>Northern goshawks are common in Anchorage, but it is rare for the birds to set up nests so close to buildings and well-used trails, he said. &quot;They're all around town, but they don't normally cause so much trouble,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Sinnott has posted signs warning trail users of the peril. &quot;Caution!!! Aggressive goshawk in vicinity,&quot; the signs say.</p>
<p>The birds on the campus trail should settle down in a few weeks, when their hatchlings grow large enough to fly on their own, Sinnott said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
