<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610151" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Wisconsin advances tough abortion bill.</title>
<headline>Wisconsin advances tough abortion bill.</headline>
<text>
<p>MADISON, Wis., May 22, A bill banning partial birth abortions overwhelmingly passed the Republican-run Wisconsin Assembly Thursday but faces an uphill battle in the Democrat-run state Senate, lawmakers said.</p>
<p>Opponents charged the measure was so tough it would scare doctors into sacrificing the life of a mother to save a baby.</p>
<p>The bill, which lawmakers said contained tougher penalties than federal legislation, was sent to the state Senate on a 77-17 vote after a two-day debate.</p>
<p>The measure provides for a sentence of up to life in prison for anyone convicted of performing the procedure that abortion opponents have labeled partial birth. It provides an exception for saving the life of the mother.</p>
<p>The exception didn't satisfy opponents, who said the procedure was rarely used in Wisconsin.</p>
<p>&quot;We're turning back the clock,&quot; said state Representative Frank Boyle, D-Superior, suggesting doctors will be fearful of making a wrong decision and sacrifice the life of the mother.</p>
<p>State Representative Barbara Notestein, D-Milwaukee, called the measure unconstitutional, saying it does not protect the mother's health. &quot;This bill doesn't stand a chance in the world of becoming law, and I'm glad of that,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>But state Representative Lorraine Seratti, R-Spread Eagle, said she supported the bill as a mother of a severely disabled child who died at two months of age.</p>
<p>&quot;It taught us the beauty and value of life,&quot; she said of the experience 28 years ago. &quot;That little girl brought us a lot of joy in two months. Thank God I didn't have a physician who suggested that (partial birth abortion) as an alternative.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
