<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610131" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: DNC to reimburse Cherokee tribe - report.</title>
<headline>DNC to reimburse Cherokee tribe - report.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Democratic National Committee will reimburse a Cherokee tribe in Oklahoma after its chief was charged with diverting money to pay a DNC worker during last year's presidential election, the Washington Post reported Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We've been working hard to resolve this situation as quickly as we can,&quot; DNC spokesman Steven Langdon told the newspaper. &quot;We have asked for an invoice to see how much money we're going to reimburse.&quot;</p>
<p>Cherokee Nation Chief Joe Byrd has been charged in tribal court with illegally diverting tribal funds when he authorised the hiring of a Cherokee law clerk to work as part-time deputy coordinator of the American Indian Outreach Office at DNC's Washington headquarters.</p>
<p>The clerk, Kimberly Teehee, was paid $23,420 from July to December 1996, the newspaper said, quoting from court documents.</p>
<p>Langdon told the Post the DNC was trying to determine how much of the amount was for Teehee's work at the DNC. Teehee also did research for the Five Civilised Tribes, a consortium of five tribes, including the Cherokee Nation.</p>
<p>DNC officials have pledged to return $1.5 million in campaign contributions from a variety of sources unrelated to the Cherokee Nation because the donations were deemed to be illegal or from unidentified sources.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
