<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610149" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton urges quick action on disaster aid.</title>
<headline>Clinton urges quick action on disaster aid.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton on Thursday urged Congress to pass a bill providing disaster aid for the flooded Midwest before leaving town for a week-long Memorial Day recess.</p>
<p>&quot;I urge the Congress not to leavge for Memorial Day recess without sending me a clean, emergency supplemental bill that provides the disaster assistance upon which hundreds of thousands of Americans are depending,&quot; Clinton said in a statement released by the White House late on Thursday.  </p>
<p>Clinton's statement came after House Republican leaders tried to adjourn for the recess without approving the disaster aid, only to face a bipartisan rebellion by lawmakers dismayed at the prospect of going home to voters empty-handed.</p>
<p>Both parties support disaster aid, but the original $8.4 billion emergency spending bill became bogged down because of unrelated spending and environmental amendments that were added by Republicans, drawing veto threats from the president.</p>
<p>Clinton cited the devastation wrought by floods, mudslides and other natural disasters in 33 states and said people were counting on help from the federal government. &quot;Congress owes it to them to pass a clean bill and send it to me for my signature,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Despite days of talks, Congress and the White House have been unable to bridge their differences on the original bill, which would have provided $5.5 billion to more than 30 states hit by natural disasters, as well as about $2 billion for U.S. overseas military operations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
