<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610129" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: 3d Image gets investment, new executives.</title>
<headline>3d Image gets investment, new executives.</headline>
<dateline>NORCROSS, Ga. 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>3D Image Technology Inc said it has approved a restructuring plan that includes a $3.8 million investment by Olajuwon Venture Capital Inc, which under the deal will gain control of the company.</p>
<p>3D said that as part of the restructuring, Chairman and President Allen K.W. Lo, and Director and Executive Vice President Sunny L.P. Ip have resigned.</p>
<p>Olajuwon President Akinola Olajuwon has been named chairman, while Bruce Herstowski, 3D's vice president of sales and marketing, has been named director and president.  </p>
<p>The company said in a news release that operational savings, as well as further reductions in operating costs in Europe and the United States, are expected to return it to profitability &quot;in the near future.&quot;</p>
<p>As part of the plan, 3D Image said it will terminate the direct manufacturing operation in China and will contract with independent camera manufacturers in China to manufacture cameras for the company.</p>
<p>It said it intends to negotiate a fixed delivered price per camera and will no longer directly support the China operations. 3D said it expects to achieve substantial savings from the restructuring.</p>
<p>The $3.8 million investment by Olajuwon for 7.6 million shares of common stock, is to be contributed in installments as needed for operations over the remainder of the year, with the full amount to be contributed by December 31, 1997.</p>
<p>Olajuwon has also been granted an option to acquire 6.5 million shares of its common stock and has been given an irrevocable proxy to vote the option shares for two years.  </p>
<p>On May 9, 1997, Ernst &amp; Young LLP resigned as auditors of 3D Image. Ernst &amp; Young's report on the company's results for the year ended December 31, 1996, stated that the company's financial statements had been prepared assuming that the company would continue as a going concern.</p>
<p>However, it contained an uncertainty paragraph stating that there was substantial doubt about the company's ability to continue as a going concern based upon the deficiency in working capital and recurring operating losses, without any committed sources of equity capital, 3d Image said in a statement.</p>
<p>The company said that Olajuwon's investment, as well as steps taken to eliminate deficiencies noted by Ernst &amp; Young, led it to believe &quot;that there is no longer a risk regarding the company's ability to continue as a going concern.&quot;</p>
<p>((-- New York Newsdesk 212-859-1610))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I37330">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NORCROSS, Ga."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
