<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610290" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: FORECAST - Euroblues, France to weigh on Iberia bonds.</title>
<headline>FORECAST - Euroblues, France to weigh on Iberia bonds.</headline>
<byline>Tiziana Barghini</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iberian bonds, after sharp recent outperformance, are set to correct next week as the market's focus shifts from a healthy domestic situation to the French vote and the European Union summit, dealers said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is pricing in the best of all possible worlds -- a centre-right triumph in France, juicy news from the summit,&quot; said Antonio Mielgo, economist at Bank of America in Madrid.</p>
<p>While analysts believe the news from the two events will very likely be good, they add that the market is undervaluing the risk of possible surprises from Euro-politics.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is undervaluing the loss potential of a not-very-clear French election result...or of an EMU delay -- despite the low likelihood it would have a very bad effect,&quot; said Valentin Fernandez at Credit Lyonnais in Madrid.</p>
<p>The Iberian 10-year spread over Bunds hit all-time lows earlier this week, with the Spanish spread narrowing to a record 64 basis points, and the Portuguese one at around 50 bps.</p>
<p>&quot;At these levels the market is discounting a 90 percent probability Spain will entering European Economic and Monetary Union with the first wave,&quot; Fernandez said.</p>
<p>&quot;And I think that is right...at present we are facing fewer problems than core countries in France, or Germany,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A recent Morgan Stanley analysis showed the brokerage house expects the 10-year bonos spread versus Bunds to fall to around 25-to-30 basis points before the end of the year.</p>
<p>But some analysts advised a wiser approach toward European Monetary Union (EMU) convergence, at least short run.</p>
<p>&quot;We're positive toward Spain, but we think it has become too expensive recently, so we are cooling down a bit our previous optimism,&quot; said Francesco Giordano, economist at Credit Suisse First Boston in London.</p>
<p>Economists were all forecasting the spread would bounce back toward 75-80 basis points for Spain and to around 60-65 for Portugal within one week.</p>
<p>&quot;The (10-year) spread is likely to correct next week, under the impact of the French election,&quot; said Nuno Godinho at Deutsche Bank in Lisbon.</p>
<p>&quot;The Portuguese one could climb around 60 basis points and the Spanish one to around 75 bps,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>One reason is the uncertainty in the first round of the French general election on Sunday, with the final round on June 1. Polls are pointing to a centre-right victory, but analysts cautioned that such surveys can prove false.</p>
<p>&quot;You know ..election polls are just polls, we can't trust them too much,&quot; said Bank of America's Mielgo.</p>
<p>&quot;They are not going to win, but the left wing had already said fighting unemployment could be more important than the three percent target for public deficit to gross domestic product,&quot; added Fernandez.</p>
<p>The other reason for concern is the extraordinary European Union summit starting today in Noordjwik, Netherlands, that is designed to give an extra push to efforts to seal a new treaty for the Union.</p>
<p>&quot;In this EU summit the heads of state could show a new attitude, being more keen toward the entrance of European Eastern countries,&quot; said Mielgo.</p>
<p>&quot;That is important.. those entrances could end in being the bargaining chip to convince Germany to let Italy in.&quot;</p>
<p>The spread between Spain and Portugal, which widened in the last week from 10 basis points to around 15 basis points, is likely to get narrower soon, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The lower that spread becomes the more the market is discounting a full probability that both countries will be in the first wave of EMU,&quot; said Fernandez.</p>
<p>But an obstacle could be the low degree of liquidity in the Portuguese market, other analysts added.</p>
<p>Of less interest is expected to be the short-end of the yield curve for both Iberian countries next week.</p>
<p>Although at mid-June the announcement of falling May CPI data are expected to prompt other official rate cuts, boosting the three- to five-year sector, next week the yield curve should be little affected, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The only possible movement could came from the Bank of Italy, seen cutting its official rate soon, which could refresh our expectations here,&quot; said Gudinho.</p>
<p>-- Madrid Newsroom, + 341 585 8340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
