<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610220" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FRENCH ELECTION - HOW THEY VOTE.</title>
<headline>FRENCH ELECTION - HOW THEY VOTE.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>About 39 million French voters are entitled to vote in Sunday's first round of a two-stage election to choose a new National Assembly or lower house of parliament.</p>
<p>President Jacques Chirac used his constitutional power to dissolve the Assembly on April 21 and called a snap election, 10 months ahead of schedule, for May 25 and June 1.</p>
<p>The president, who appoints the prime minister and cabinet, may not dissolve parliament again in the first year of a new legislature.</p>
<p>Some 6,389 candidates are vying for the 577 seats in single-member constituencies, the Interior Ministry said. The record is 29 candidates in a single electoral district in central Paris.</p>
<p>A candidate who wins more than 50 percent of votes cast on the first ballot is elected without a runoff.</p>
<p>Otherwise, any candidate who polls 12.5 percent of the total of registered voters has the right to contest the second ballot. The person who wins the most votes on the runoff is elected, even if he or she does not poll 50 percent.</p>
<p>There are 555 constituencies in metropolitan France and 22 in overseas departments and territories.</p>
<p>In most districts, the ruling conservative RPR-UDF coalition is running a single candidate, whereas the left-wing opposition parties are contesting the poll separately but will unite behind the best-placed opposition candidate on the runoff.</p>
<p>As a result, more conservatives than left-wingers are expected to win seats outright on the first round, but that does not mean the coalition will necessarily win the election.</p>
<p>Voting in metropolitan France takes place from 8 a.m. (0600 GMT) to 6 p.m. (1600 GMT) in most areas and 8 p.m. (1800 GMT) in Paris and major provincial citites.</p>
<p>The first round of voting for the two seats in French Polynesia was held on May 17. The last overseas departments to vote are in France's Caribbean and South American territories.</p>
<p>No results, projections or exit polls may be published until the last polling stations have closed in metropolitan France. By law, no opinion polls may be published in the last week before the first round or between the two rounds.</p>
<p>On election night, television stations broadcast usually reliable projections of the outcome in votes and forecasts of the result in seats, usually in a spread, as soon as the last polls close at 8 p.m. (1800 GMT).</p>
<p>The parties were allotted time for election broadcasts on public radio and television between May 5 and 23. Campaign spending and individual donations to parties are limited by law.</p>
<p>Any party which fields 50 candidates or more receives public funds proportionate to the number of votes it polls.</p>
<p>The centre-right coalition won a landslide majority in the last parliamentary election in March 1993. The turnout was 69.2 percent. The state of the parties in the outgoing Assembly was:</p>
<p>    RPR (Gaullists)			 258</p>
<p>    UDF (centre-right)		    206</p>
<p>    Socialist party and allies	   63</p>
<p>    Communist party and allies	   24</p>
<p>    Other left				 12</p>
<p>    Other right				13</p>
<p>    Vacant seat				 1</p>
<p>The upper house, the Senate, is elected indirectly by local officials and is not affected by this election.</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +331 4221 5339</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
