<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610208" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Dutch forwarders see 12 pct rise in 1997 air cargo.</title>
<headline>Dutch forwarders see 12 pct rise in 1997 air cargo.</headline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Total Dutch airfreight shipments are expected to rise by 12 percent in 1997 from last year's 1.54 million, which were 8.5 percent above the 1995 level, the Dutch airfreight forwarders association(NVVL) said in a statement.</p>
<p>It added that this year the total weight of shipments is seen increasing by 10 percent from 1996's 630,267 tonnes, following a 30.5 percent rise over 1995.</p>
<p>Exports are forecast to be 10 percent higher in 1997 for both shipments and tonnages moved. In 1996 export shipments totalled 802,209 (plus 11 percent over 1995) with the tonnages reaching 295,358 tonnes (plus 26 percent).</p>
<p>Import shipments are expected to be 10 percent up on the 1996 figure of 741,193 although tonnages will gain 8.5 percent on last year's 335,000 tonnes, NVVL said.</p>
<p>This is the first time the total number of shipments has passed the 1.5 m mark with the growth due to both hi-tech commodities and the perishables market ,NVVl added.</p>
<p>Textiles and perishable traffic from third world countries, as well as a strong growth from electronic products was cited as the reason for the import increase.</p>
<p>Overall the average weight for export shipments rose to 368 kg in 1996 from 324 kg a year earlier, with import shipment average weight recahing 452 kg from 354 kg, NVVL added.</p>
<p>The association said that its members spent 1.5 percent more on airfreight costs in 1996 than in 1995, with 816 million guilders paid to carriers ,compared to the previous year's 802 million.</p>
<p>It added there is still considerable pressure on yields. -- Reuters Air Cargo Newsroom Tel+44 171 542 7706 Fax:5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
