<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610299" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Europe fails to arouse passion in French vote.</title>
<headline>Europe fails to arouse passion in French vote.</headline>
<byline>Myra MacDonald</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four years after a knife-edge referendum on European monetary union, French voters get their last chance on Sunday to have their say on plans for a single currency, but the outcome may make little difference.</p>
<p>The two-round parliamentary election on May 25 and June 1, called early by President Jacques Chirac to clear the way for 1999, has been presented by the ruling centre-right as a choice between launching the euro on time and &quot;shambles in Europe&quot;.</p>
<p>But despite dire warnings that a Socialist-Communist win would make Maastricht untenable and France ungovernable, the European issue has failed to stir the passions generated by the 1992 referendum when France voted by just 51 percent in favour of monetary union.</p>
<p>Many French people, wearied by austerity and unemployment, now see monetary union as a somewhat dreary inevitability, better at least than the instability and decline in European power they fear would result from abandoning the project.</p>
<p>Private economists and some politicians say there is little real difference between the main opposition Socialist party's approach to Europe and that of the ruling centre-right coalition, with both sides committed to launching the single currency.</p>
<p>&quot;I assure you that abroad the three main political parties are seen to be in agreement on applying the (Maastricht) treaty. That will be the message which is retained,&quot; former European Commission president Jacques Delors said this week.</p>
<p>Negotiated by a Socialist government and implemented by the centre-right over the last four years, Maastricht's constraints on budget deficits are what every politician in France loves to blame for unpopular austerity policies.</p>
<p>Yet most politicians now argue that introducing the euro is vital if France, which for years has clung to the coat-tails of Germany's powerful economy, is to regain a voice in the international arena as part of a strengthened Europe.</p>
<p>Both main parties share a common vision of Europe, where the future European Central Bank is balanced by a strong political dimension with a European &quot;economic government&quot;.</p>
<p>This view has put France at loggerheads in the past with Germany, which fears any threat to the independence of the central bank, but ultimately led to compromises meant to underline both countries' commitment to the euro.</p>
<p>Economists believe politicians from the right and left would make those compromises again rather than risk derailing monetary union and accept that the sacrifices of previous years were in vain.</p>
<p>Beyond that, the impact of the vote, which opinion polls have suggested the centre-right will win, will be seen in the subtleties of how EMU shapes up.</p>
<p>French Socialist leader Lionel Jospin has said he will not impose further austerity measures just to cut the budget deficit to three percent of gross domestic product.</p>
<p>That in turn could make EMU entry easier for countries such as Italy, which most believe will be unable to get its finances squeaky clean in time, but which nonetheless will get near to the three percent requirement.</p>
<p>But the Socialists are however committed to sound management and say they would not let the deficit go out of control.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe has also said he would like Italy and Spain to join as well, if they meet the Maastricht criteria.</p>
<p>And though economists reckon it might be easier for a centre-right government to make spending cuts than a Socialist one, they believe it too would balk at drastic austerity.</p>
<p>Juppe had to back down on many reforms in 1995 after a crippling public sector strike.</p>
<p>France is generally on course to meet all requirements in the Maastricht treaty, though opinions differ on how much more austerity will be needed in the home stretch.</p>
<p>While some cite spending cuts of up to 50 billion francs ($8.8 billion), others say this is alarmist, and others that good growth this year might mean France will do better than it expects.</p>
<p>Whoever wins, economists expect if any new money is needed there will be a soft mix of tax increases, spending freezes and raids on state firms' cash to ensure French people do not make their protest on the streets rather than in the ballot box. ($ = 5.696 French Francs)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
