<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610204" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Dresdner posts 10 percent rise in operating profit.</title>
<headline>Dresdner posts 10 percent rise in operating profit.</headline>
<byline>Catherine O'Mahony</byline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT, Germany</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dresdner Bank AG, Germany's second largest commercial bank, Friday posted a 10 percent advance in operating profit for the first three months of the year as it detailed first-quarter earnings for the first time.</p>
<p>The bank attributed its positive results to strong advances in interest and commission income as fund and equity sales improved.</p>
<p>Dresdner raised its 1996 dividend to 1.45 marks (86 cents) a share from 1.35 marks (80 cents) and also paid a bonus dividend of 10 pfennigs (6 cents) to mark its 125th anniversary, as its net profit surged 31 percent to 1.58 billion marks ($935 million), outstripping its main rivals.</p>
<p>Chairman Juergen Sarrazin said earnings in the first quarter had been influenced, as usual, by special factors and could not be directly extrapolated for the full year.</p>
<p>Operating profit before risk provisions advanced to 991 million marks ($586 million) in the first quarter.</p>
<p>The bank posted a particularly strong rise in commission income for the three-month period, with a 20.6 percent rise to 1.2 billion marks ($710 million) on the strength of high equity and mutual fund sales.</p>
<p>Net interest income rose rose 8.8 percent to 1.7 billion marks ($1.10 billion), but was partly boosted by elements of &quot;quasi-trading income,&quot; Sarrazin said.</p>
<p>Own-account trading income was 330 million marks ($195 million), which Sarrazin said was very satisfactory, without providing a comparative figure. The first quarter result was, however, equal to half the full trading income for 1996, he said.</p>
<p>Sarrazin took the opportunity presented by the shareholder meeting to firmly deny media reports that Dresdner was interested in taking over Postbank, the German postal bank due for privatisation this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
