<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610293" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss Life members start vote Monday.</title>
<headline>Swiss Life members start vote Monday.</headline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Around 600,000 members of Swiss Life/Rentenanstalt will from Monday May 26 until June 20 vote on management's proposal to turn the mutual insurance company into a public limited company.</p>
<p>Swiss Life said in statement that if two-thirds of the participants agree to the legal change, Swiss Life will register in the commercial register on June 30.</p>
<p>The Swiss Life titles will be listed on the Swiss Exchange on July 3, 1997.</p>
<p>The change will allow all members of Swiss Life to become shareholders free of charge. Swiss Life is also offering its former members custody of their shares free for two years.</p>
<p>&quot;In this way, Swiss Life/Rentenanstalt, with about 600,000 shareholders, shall have at its disposal the broadest shareholder base of all companies in Switzerland,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>In 1996 Swiss Life's parent profit rose 21 percent to 1.37 billion francs from 1.13 billion in 1995.</p>
<p>In February Swiss Life holders of its participation certificates voted to convert their securities into shares.</p>
<p>After a transition phase with some conditional capital locked up in convertible bonds and loans, cooperative members will in the end hold 53 percent of Swiss Life's share capital totalling 587.35 million Swiss francs or 11.7 million bearer shares with a face value of 50 Swiss francs each.</p>
<p>The holders of participation certificates will have eight percent and Union Bank of Switzerland (UBS) 25 percent of share capital.</p>
<p>The remaining 14 percent will be in the form of convertible bonds.</p>
<p>-- Zurich Editorial +41 1 631 7340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
