<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610286" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Vogel rejects Wolf's claim W.German leader was spy.</title>
<headline>Vogel rejects Wolf's claim W.German leader was spy.</headline>
<byline>Erik Kirschbaum</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Wolfgang Vogel, an East Berlin lawyer who arranged superpower spy swaps during the Cold War, dismissed on Friday claims by former East German spymaster Markus Wolf that a leading West German politician was a communist agent.</p>
<p>Vogel said allegations Wolf makes in his forthcoming book that Herbert Wehner, a powerful West German political leader during the 1960s and 1970s, was a spy for East Berlin were outrageous.</p>
<p>Vogel and Wehner worked together on hundreds of deals between the East and West German governments that enabled thousands of East Germans move to the west involving billions of marks.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to speak out against this,&quot; Vogel said. &quot;I have no idea where Wolf is getting that from. Herbert Wehner was someone who wanted to help people in need. And without exaggerating, he helped thousands of people.&quot;</p>
<p>The autobiography &quot;Markus Wolf -- Spy Chief in a Secret War&quot; will be distributed on June 2 in 11 languages in 14 countries. Excerpts of the book were published in Stern magazine on Thursday.</p>
<p>Wolf makes a number of explosive revelations in his book, saying the CIA offered him a house, a small fortune, and a new identity in California in exchange for secrets. The CIA and West Germany's BND intelligence agency both tried to recruit Wolf shortly after the Berlin Wall fell in 1989.</p>
<p>Wolf's book begins like a spy novel, with a recently retired CIA officer named Gardner Hathaway visiting Wolf's home outside Berlin in May 1990.</p>
<p>Wolf says Hathaway brought chocolates and flowers and began by heaping praise on Wolf's spectacular 30-year career leading one of the world's most successful spy agencies.</p>
<p>Hathaway told Wolf he had come on behalf of CIA director William Webster, offering to help Wolf escape from German prosecutors preparing charges against him in exchange for Wolf's help in identifying KGB agents operating in the United States.</p>
<p>According to excerpts being published in Stern magazine, the CIA offered a California house, a new identity and more than $100,000 for his help.</p>
<p>&quot;California is a nice place with great weather,&quot; Hathaway told Wolf.</p>
<p>&quot;Siberia isn't bad either,&quot; Wolf replied, adding he doubted he would be of value because he would never betray the identities of his agents. &quot;The names of my agents are taboo.&quot;</p>
<p>Wolf was long referred to by Western intelligence as the &quot;Man Without a Face&quot; because they did not know what he looked like. Thriller writers often took him as a model when depicting a sinister communist spy chief.</p>
<p>Wolf ran a network of around 4,000 foreign-based agents from his East Berlin headquarters. One of his biggest coups was planting &quot;mole&quot; Guenter Guillaume inside then chancellor Willy Brandt's office -- leading to Brandt's resignation in 1974.</p>
<p>He was convicted in 1993 of treason but that ruling was overturned by Germany's highest court in 1995.</p>
<p>A verdict in a second trial, where Wolf has been charged with masterminding three Cold War kidnappings, is due on May 27.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
