<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610280" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Highlights of Friday's Commission briefing.</title>
<headline>Highlights of Friday's Commission briefing.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are highlights of the midday briefing by the European Commission on Friday:</p>
<p>Spokesman Joao Vale de Almeida said the Commission had decided to launch an ECU 46.3 million food aid package to help beat the famine in North Korea. He said ECHO would announce a supplementary ECU 10 million support for public health in the next few days.</p>
<p>Vale de Almeida said the European Union became the first donor to North Korea above the United States and China.</p>
<p>He added that these humanitarian measures could not be isolated from a wider political framework aimed at ensuring security on the Korean peninsula.</p>
<p>Spokeswoman Sophie Petzell briefed on Monday and Tueday's Justice and Home Affairs Council. She said discussions would focus on cross-border cooperation on criminal, civil and commercial matters, unaccompagnied minors, temporary protection of displaced persons, synthetic drugs and structured dialogue with applicant countries.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>The Commission released the following documents:</p>
<p>- IP/97/431: TV and Radio Awards for humanitarian reporting: ECHO launches the 1997 edition.</p>
<p>- IP/97/432: EU takes WTO action over Indonesia's car policy.</p>
<p>- IP/97/433: Commissioner van den Broek's visit to Malta to focus on future relations with the EU.</p>
<p>- IP/97/434: Commission approves closure aid for the Bremer Vulkan Werft GmbH.</p>
<p>- IP/97/435: Commission approves aid scheme for firms in the French overseas departments.</p>
<p>- IP/97/436: State aid: Italy - Commission approves extension to 31.12.1999 for Italian areas eligible to regional aid under Article 92.3.c.</p>
<p>- IP/97/437: State aid: Spain - Commission does not object aids in favour of Opel.</p>
<p>- IP/97/438: State aid: Finland - Commission has decided to consider a guarantee scheme aimed at improving the financial structure and growth of SME's as not constituting state aid.</p>
<p>- IP/97/439: State aid: Commission opens proceedings against planned aid from Luxembourg for steel group Arbed.</p>
<p>- IP/97/440: Famine in North Korea: the Commission launches an ECU 46 million food aid package and prepares public health support.</p>
<p>- Speech/97/116: Commissioner Yves-Thibault de Silguy speech on &quot;The Euro and Switzerland&quot;.</p>
<p>- Memo/97/53: Calendar of Commissioners activities for May 25 to June 1st, 1997.</p>
<p>- Eurostat news release No 37/97: EU industrial production up 0.5%.</p>
<p>- Oil bulletin No 868.</p>
<p>- ME97/23.5: Midday Express.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
