<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610238" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy mourns judge, Mafia killers face long terms.</title>
<headline>Italy mourns judge, Mafia killers face long terms.</headline>
<byline>Jude Webber</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy on Friday mourned the judge whose ground-breaking Mafia investigations led to his murder five years ago.</p>
<p>On Thursday, prosecutors in Sicily requested life jail terms for more than 30 bosses charged with the murder.</p>
<p>Judge Giovanni Falcone, his wife Francesca Morvillo and three bodyguards were blown up on May 23, 1992, on a motorway outside the Sicilian capital Palermo.</p>
<p>&quot;Institutions and citizens have a duty not to forget,&quot; the speaker of the Chamber of Deputies (lower house), Luciano Violante, said in an anniversary message to the families of the victims.</p>
<p>He called on Italians &quot;to avoid the rhetoric of commemorations (and to) work with determination in the fight against the Mafia to defend those values of civility and legality&quot; for which Falcone worked.</p>
<p>Crimefighters including FBI director Louis Freeh, in Palermo for a memorial service, drove in convoy along the motorway. They stopped to pay tribute at the point where explosives packed under the road were detonated by remote control as Falcone's car passed.</p>
<p>Prosecutors in the central Sicilian city of Caltanissetta requested life sentences on Thursday for 32 Mafiosi, including Cosa Nostra's jailed boss of bosses Salvatore Riina and some of his key lieutenants, who are charged with masterminding the murder.</p>
<p>For Giovanni Brusca, the most senior member of the Mob to be captured in the past year, prosecutors sought a 30-year jail term. They cited mitigating circumstances since Brusca has admitted using the remote control device that triggered the blast.</p>
<p>The trial was halted for five minutes on Friday as a mark of respect. The defence is expected to sum up late next month. A verdict is expected late this year.</p>
<p>Falcone, a Sicilian, revolutionised Italy's war on the Mafia by tracking financial records that revealed the extent of the Mob's criminal activities and resources, and by persuading captured Mafioso to turn state's evidence.</p>
<p>Testimony from &quot;Men of Honour&quot;, who are sworn on pain of death to a code of silence or &quot;omerta&quot; when they are initiated into the Mafia, gave unprecedented insight into the feared society and led to the arrest of Riina in 1993 and other bosses.</p>
<p>Violante, himself a former anti-Mafia magistrate, hailed Falcone's approach, which won him few friends in the judiciary while he was alive. &quot;Before him, the state was responding to the united activities of the Mafia in a fragmented way,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The murder of Falcone, and two months later of his friend and colleague Paolo Borsellino in a car-bomb attack, horrified Italy and galvanised efforts to crack the Mafia and end the reign of terror imposed by Riina and his bloody Corleone clan.</p>
<p>Palermo's chief prosecutor Giancarlo Caselli cautioned on Friday that Italy now risked slipping into complacency.</p>
<p>&quot;The Mafia seems to have become a second division problem, or even a non-problem, because people think...that police successes in the last few years are leading to a definitive solution of the problem.</p>
<p>&quot;That is not so,&quot; Caselli said in a radio interview. &quot;The Mafia is still an extremely robust and highly dangerous beast.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
