<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610246" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spanish cabinet approves electricity tariffs cuts.</title>
<headline>Spanish cabinet approves electricity tariffs cuts.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Spanish cabinet presented on Friday a new electricity draft bill, which will implement a 15 percent fall in the domestic user tariff and a 30 percent fall in the industrial tariff in real terms by the year 2001.</p>
<p>Speaking at a press conference, Industry Minister Josep Pique said: &quot;The main aim of the new electricity sector law is making compatible the backing and the quality of electricity supply for all users with the consolidation of the fall in the electricity tariff.&quot;  </p>
<p>The tariff will fall by 35-40 percent over the next ten years, Pique said.</p>
<p>The new bill also introduces moves to deregulate the sector by the year 1999, as advanced in the electricity protocol in December.</p>
<p>&quot;We have established a scheme for electricity companies to adapt to the cost of the transition to competition&quot; over a maximum period of ten years, the minister said.</p>
<p>&quot;A regime has been established which allows the recovery of 50 percent of (the value of) net fixed assets which has yet to be amortised&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The measures establish the liberalisation of new electricity generation installations, the creation of a wholesale electricity market and allow access by third parties to the transport and distribution networks.</p>
<p>They also allow consumers to choose their supplier in 10 years' time, Pique said.</p>
<p>The government will also set up two new administrative entities within the sector. One will be responsible for managing supply of and demand for electricity, thus fixing the market price, and the other will act as technical manager of the system.</p>
<p>National coal will be maintained in electricity production, in accordance with EU legislation allowing for 15 percent of output to correspond to locally-produced fuel, Pique said.</p>
<p>This would guarantee the use of around 13 million tonnes of Spanish coal in the next eight years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
