<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610275" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: FORECAST-Italy seen issuing 11.5 trln lire paper.</title>
<headline>FORECAST-Italy seen issuing 11.5 trln lire paper.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Italian Treasury is expected to issue between 9.5 and 14.0 trillion lire of medium and long term paper at its next auction, replacing 8.6 trillion lire of paper expiring, analysts said.</p>
<p>The average of economists' forecasts is for a total 11.5 trillion lire of paper being issued. Analysts say the Treasury's requirements from the market in June will be limited due to tax payments in that month.</p>
<p>Banca Commerciale Italiana said improved cashflow at the Treasury should continue for the entire second half of the year due to a reduction in the budget deficit and the absence of large amounts expiring in medium and long term paper.</p>
<p>&quot;As a result we expect total monthly issues of medium and long term paper to fall from around 26.5 trillion lire in the last few weeks to an average of 15.0 trillion,&quot; BCI  said, adding the reduction was likely to be seen most notably in issues of floating rate certificates (Ccts).</p>
<p>The Treasury has said it intends to offer a fifth tranche of May 1 2004 Ccts on May 28, as well as the 17th tranche of February 1, 2007 fixed rate government bonds (Btps) and the ninth tranche of the November 1, 2027 Btp.</p>
<p>On May 29 it will offer the third tranche of a May 15, 2000 Btp and the first tranche of a May 15, 2002 Btp.</p>
<p>Following are analysts' forecasts (in trillion lire):</p>
<p>		  3-yr    5-yr    10-yr    30-yr    Cct    Total</p>
<p>BankAmerica   3.00    3.00    2.50     2.00     3.50   14.00</p>
<p>Caboto	  2.00    2.50    1.50     2.00     2.00   10.00</p>
<p>Banca Roma    2.50    2.50    1.50     1.50     4.00   12.00</p>
<p>BCI	     2.00    1.50    1.50     1.50     3.00    9.50</p>
<p>Chase	   2.00    2.00    2.00     2.00     3.00   11.00</p>
<p>Credito	 2.50    3.00    2.50     2.00     2.00   12.00</p>
<p>================================================================</p>
<p>CONSENSUS     2.50    2.50    2.00     2.00     3.00   11.50</p>
<p>A total of 8.6 trillion lire worth paper and coupons are expiring of which 1.5 trillion is in five-year Btps, 1.4 trillion in Ccts and 5.7 trillion in coupons.</p>
<p>-- Milan bureau 00 39 2 66129507</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
