<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610298" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: De Silguy rules out creative accounting for EMU.</title>
<headline>De Silguy rules out creative accounting for EMU.</headline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>EU Commissioner Yves-Thibault de Silguy said countries could not use creative accounting to qualify for Europe's single currency, but he declined to comment specifically on Germany's gold revaluation plan.</p>
<p>&quot;I have not received details on this project from German authorities so I cannot react precisely,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;For countries particpating in the euro, the most important thing is to achieve a sustainable level of convergence. Accounting measures must be complemented with structural measures to achieve sound finances in the long term, but creative accounting is out of the question,&quot; he added.  </p>
<p>&quot;There are precise regulations known by everyone,&quot; de Silguy said. &quot;They will be applied. There is no question of doing creative accounting. We will apply the same accountability rules to all member states without discrimination.&quot;</p>
<p>German Finance Minister Theo Waigel has proposed using a revaluation of the Bundesbank's gold reserves to plug a hole in the 1997 budget, triggering a wave of criticism across the EU that Bonn was resorting to creative accounting.</p>
<p>In Brussels, a senior EU official said the EU was unlikely to let Germany use the plan to reduce its budget deficit, but may let Bonn apply revaluation profits against outstanding debt.</p>
<p>-- Zurich newsroom +41 1 631 7340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
