<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610214" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France wants Palestinian newsman freed.</title>
<headline>France wants Palestinian newsman freed.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>France expressed deep concern on Friday about the arrest of Palestinian newsman Daoud Kuttab, winner of the International Press Freedom Award, who is detained without charge by the Palestinian Authority.</p>
<p>&quot;French authorities wish to reaffirm their attachment to freedom of the press and the right of journalists to perform their job freely in all places and circumstances,&quot; a foreign ministry spokesman told journalists about the Kuttab case.</p>
<p>&quot;We have expressed our deep concern to Palestinian authorities about the arrest of Daoud Kuttab who is an outstanding journalist,&quot; the spokesman added.</p>
<p>Kuttab, an East Jerusalem resident, was detained in the West Bank self-rule enclave of Ramallah on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The Paris-based media rights group &quot;Reporters sans Frontieres (Reporters without Borders) said on Thursday that television broadcasts of Palestinian Legislative Council sessions by Kuttab had been jammed.</p>
<p>RSF said Kuttab had accused authorities of this prior to his detention, saying they did not want the public to hear legislators criticising President Yasser Arafat.</p>
<p>The official French spokesman said broadcasts of Council sessions contributed &quot;to reinforce democratic feelings in Palestinian society.</p>
<p>&quot;The visit to Palestine last October by President Jacques Chirac and the speech he made before the same Council underlines our attachment to that institution and to Palestinian democracy,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>He recalled that France had helped to set up the first Palestinian television station.</p>
<p>The spokesman added that France was equally concerned about a report that a Palestinian prisoner might have been beaten to death in an Israeli jail. He gave no details on the case.</p>
<p>Kuttab, who is also dean of the Modern Communications Centre at Jerusalem's al-Quds University, was awarded the International Press Freedom Award last year by the New York based Committee to Protect Journalists for his work challenging censorship practices of both Israeli and Palestinian authorities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
