<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610264" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU to send North Korea massive food aid.</title>
<headline>EU to send North Korea massive food aid.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission said on Friday it was launching a massive food aid package to help victims of widespread famine in North Korea.</p>
<p>The aid, worth 46.3 million ecus ($53.2 million), consists of 155,000 tonnes of food products, notably rice, maize and vegetable oils, and will be distributed through the U.N. World Food Programme (WFP) and independent aid agencies.</p>
<p>&quot;It's humanitarian aid and non-political,&quot; a Commission spokesman said, adding that the EU's executive had had no direct contact with the North Korean authorities.</p>
<p>The aid follows a WFP appeal in April for some 200,000 tonnes of food aid for North Korea.</p>
<p>The EU's executive said in a statement that the aid should also help to avert a possible deterioration in security in the Korean peninsula.</p>
<p>&quot;The EU's approach has not changed,&quot; the spokesman added.</p>
<p>The EU supports proposed four-way peace talks between North Korea, the Republic of Korea, the United States and China.</p>
<p>&quot;Such four-party talks are the way to promote lasting peace and stability in the Korean peninsula,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>North Korea has suffered mounting food shortages due to serious flooding in 1995 and 1996, the absence of economic reforms and alienation of small farmers.</p>
<p>The U.N. Food and Agriculture Organisation has estimated North Korea's food import needs at 2.36 million tonnes, of which only 500,000 tonnes could be imported commercially.</p>
<p>The EU has already provided some 10 million ecus of food aid to North Korea. ($1 = 0.87 ecu)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
