<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610215" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Vienna shares add on, outlook friendly.</title>
<headline>Vienna shares add on, outlook friendly.</headline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian shares end the week out on a firm note on Friday thanks to continued selective interest from investors, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;It was rather quiet ahead of the weekend. Individual issues drove the market higher,&quot; said one, adding there was also selective foreign interest although &quot;not massive&quot;.</p>
<p>Traders see the market holding onto its firm tone next week as well, but that buying needs to fan out across-the-board in order to see further significant price gains.</p>
<p>The ATX index of 21 blue chips advanced 3.51 points, or 0.27 percent, to 1,290.7 points with 10 shares higher, 10 lower, and one unchanged.</p>
<p>Traders said the ATX was pushed off its high of 1,294.21 after profittaking kicked in around midday.</p>
<p>The ATX index faces a barrier on technical charts at 1,290 points, but should have no problem testing 1,320 points next week, the trader said.</p>
<p>Another trader said: &quot;Underlying sentiment continues to be bullish. Every weaker day is seen as a buy day.&quot;</p>
<p>The leading ATX gainer was engineering group VA Tech, up 2.57 percent at 2,109.95 schillings while paper maker Leykam led losers, off 2.88 percent at 310.</p>
<p>The broad-based Vienna bourse index rose 1.15 points, or 0.24 percent, to 474.8 points.</p>
<p>The June ATX future added on 6.5 points at 1,291 on turnover of 804 contracts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
