<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610259" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Santer says will work with UK on quota-hoping.</title>
<headline>Santer says will work with UK on quota-hoping.</headline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>European Commission President Jacques Santer pledged on Friday to help ease a row with Britain over fish quotas, but underlined that the EU's internal market must not be weakened.</p>
<p>Santer's spokesman, Nikolaus van der Pas, said British Prime Minister Tony Blair had raised the issue of so-called quota-hopping at a meeting on the sidelines of a European Union summit in the Dutch seaside resort of Noordwijk.</p>
<p>Britain has been frustrated by EU rules that allow the owners of fishing vessels from other bloc countries to buy up the rights to take fish that under EU quotas were assigned to British fishermen.</p>
<p>The former Conservative government had threatened to veto the EU's new treaty, due to be agreed in Amsterdam next month, if the system was not changed.</p>
<p>Van der Pas said Blair had told Santer he would not tie the two issues together but that he still needed to show progress &quot;in or around Amsterdam&quot;.</p>
<p>Santer said he hoped a compromise could be found by the June 16-17 summit, van der Pas said.</p>
<p>But he also emphasised that the issue was of equal political sensitivity in Spain, where most of the quota-hopping vessels come from.</p>
<p>The issue also must not be allowed to weaken the internal market, under which EU countries trade freely among themselves, the spokeman said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
