<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610231" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Cleansed black market debt to boost Spanish assets.</title>
<headline>Cleansed black market debt to boost Spanish assets.</headline>
<byline>Robert Hetz</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fresh money is likely to flood Spanish markets in June, when 760 billion pesetas of newly cleansed black market money instruments mature, analysts and funds managers said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;This money, which was once black market money and was penalised with a low interest rate, will now rejoin normal circulation and will go in search of higher yields,&quot; said Alfredo Urrutia, chief economist at Societe Generale in Madrid.</p>
<p>In 1991, then economy minister Carlos Solchaga offered a new instrument, so-called special public debt in order to flush out undeclared black market earnings and cleanse them.</p>
<p>In response, 80,000 accounts for the special debt were opened. The monies in this instrument, which carried minimum interest of just two percent but which rendered the investor immune from any tax evasion charges at maturity on June 28, can now be withdrawn.</p>
<p>The newly cleansed 760 billion pesetas, together with a high volume of regular maturing issues in June and July, are expected to free some 1.3 to 1.5 trillion pesetas in funds that will flood into the Spanish debt and stock markets, Urrutia said.</p>
<p>&quot;We will be present at a solid injection of liquidity. Part of the money will go to the debt market, but it will also be a good moment to invest in the bourse because it still has room to rise despite its sharp recent uptrend,&quot; Urrutia said.</p>
<p>As a result, fund managers are raising their forecasts for the bourse in 1997. The market has already risen 25 percent in the first five months of the year despite forecasts in January for a gain of just 12 to 15 percent for the entire year.</p>
<p>&quot;This new liquidity will guarantee that the party in the market continues,&quot; said a Spanish bank equity market dealer.</p>
<p>A reflection of this market optimism is the &quot;free rise&quot; that some leading shares in the bourse are experiencing.</p>
<p>Shares in Telefonica, for example, have risen 28.5 percent since the telecommunication giant's full privatisation in February, setting a new record of 4,345 pesetas without any fundamental changes at the group, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Technically, the market is overbought, but there is no indication of any lasting correction,&quot; a Spanish fund manager said.</p>
<p>Spain's bourse fever, which has also been fed by privatisations, a decline in inflation levels and interest rates, prompted spectacular growth in equity funds since the beginning of the year as debt yields have declined.</p>
<p>For Urrutia, investment funds will be the logical vehicle for the funds.</p>
<p>But precisely for this reason, Henrik Lumholdt, chief economist at the Bank of America, was somewhat cautious about the impact of the new liquidity on the market.</p>
<p>&quot;Investment funds are following a very conservative policy in Spain and we believe a large part of the new liquidity will be parked in very short-term fixed income instruments.</p>
<p>-- Madrid Newsroom + 34 1 585-2167</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
