<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610257" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>DENMARK: Crucial EU battle to open in Danish court.</title>
<headline>Crucial EU battle to open in Danish court.</headline>
<byline>Steve Weizman</byline>
<text>
<p>COPENHAGEN, May 23 Reuter) - A Danish court is to start hearing a challenge on Monday to the legality of Denmark's European Union treaties which legal experts say could end the country's EU membership under the present terms.</p>
<p>A non-partisan group of 10 Danes charges that since joining the EU in 1973 Denmark has ceded national authority to European Union institutions in breach of its own constitution.</p>
<p>They have sought to have confidential government papers, dating back to membership and beyond, introduced as evidence but have been repeatedly refused by a judicial procedural committee.</p>
<p>Starting on Monday the High Court in Copenhagen will hear the group's lawyers argue that the treaties do not sufficiently define the extent to which the European Court and other EU institutions may overide national bodies.</p>
<p>The Danish constitution's article 20 states that national powers may only be delegated to international organisations &quot;within a specified limit&quot;.</p>
<p>The centre-left coalition government believes its case is watertight and lawyers from both sides say that the state attorneys' task has been eased by rulings that the case should be limited to events since the 1992 Maastricht treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm confident that the government has a very good case,&quot; Foreign Minister Niels Helveg Petersen told Reuters on Friday at a meeting of EU leaders in the Dutch resort of Noordwijk.</p>
<p>Independent legal experts generally see a government win as the most likely outcome, but by no means certain.</p>
<p>A defeat would force Denmark into the unwieldy and potentially destabilising process of renegotiating its EU treaties or force upon it the complex and difficult task of rewriting the constitution.</p>
<p>The government wants a quick decision, as the case casts a shadow over Danish ratification of a revised European Union treaty to be signed at the next summit, in Amsterdam next month.</p>
<p>&quot;How can you ratify before you are sure of the legality of what you are supposed to be ratifying,&quot; a diplomat said.</p>
<p>The High Court hearing is scheduled to end in mid-June but, whatever its outcome, appeals by one side or the other are likely to delay a definitive outcome until the end of the year, or beyond, lawyers say.</p>
<p>Danes, traditionally cool toward European integration, rejected the Maastricht Treaty outright in a 1992 referendum.</p>
<p>Voters grudgingly approved the treaty the following year on condition that Denmark opt out of economic and monetary union and joint defence, policing and asylum policies.</p>
<p>Government lawyers have looked at writing those waivers into the revised treaty but political sources say that no firm decision has yet been taken.</p>
<p>The opt-outs on cross-border policing and asylum could also affect Denmark's position on the Schengen open-borders accord which could become a formal part of the updated EU treaty.</p>
<p>Justice Minister Frank Jensen, in what he said was a personal view, told a Copenhagen newspaper this week that he would rather see Denmark withdraw completely from the Schengen preparations than take part in some of them and be accused of gradually eroding the decisions of the binding 1993 referendum.</p>
<p>Petersen saw no chance of withdrawing from Schengen.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see such a possibility at all. We are here to find solutions, not to plan a breakdown in negotiations,&quot; he told Reuters in Noordwijk.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DENMARK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
