<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610235" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French daily flouts no-poll law citing Internet.</title>
<headline>French daily flouts no-poll law citing Internet.</headline>
<byline>Claude Canellas</byline>
<dateline>BORDEAUX, France 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A French newspaper on Friday flouted a law barring publication of opinion polls just ahead of elections, branding the rules hypocritical when such surveys are available on the Internet.</p>
<p>The Republique des Pyrenees daily in the southwestern town of Pau carried the results of a CSA poll along with an editorial entitled &quot;In the name of equality&quot;, condemning the 20-year-old law banning the appearance of polls in the week before national elections.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the electoral law that's out of date, it should be modified,&quot; Jean-Marcel Bouguereau wrote in the editorial. The paper risks a 500,000 franc fine ($88,000) for publishing a poll just ahead of Sunday's first round of National Assembly elections. A runoff vote takes place on June 1.</p>
<p>He said confidential polls taken in recent days were available on the Internet and people like politicians, stock brokers and journalists all had access to surveys denied to French citizens under a law designed to avoid swaying voters.</p>
<p>The polls, or rumours of them, are a major factor moving the Paris stock market ahead of the election. Polls taken before the blackout all gave the ruling centre-right at least a narrow lead over the left.</p>
<p>The law cannot prevent publication abroad, boosting sales of newspapers like Switzerland's Tribune de Geneve, available just over the border. Britain's Daily Telegraph has also published a poll.</p>
<p>The Internet computer network has blasted a new hole in the law for the 300,000 subscribers in France. The Tribune de Geneve's site publishing polls, &quot;www.edicom.ch/tdg/&quot;, has been swamped by French cyberspace visitors.</p>
<p>Andre Santini, spokesman for the Union for French Democracy (UDF) which is the junior partner in the ruling coalition, urged a review of French law.</p>
<p>&quot;Technologies have evolved...I wonder if we're in the process of treating the French people like infants,&quot; he told France 3 television. &quot;I think that we must reflect on the text of this law.&quot;</p>
<p>Polling institutes fired off a last burst of public surveys last Saturday, hours before the ban came into effect. It extends until the June 1 run-off.</p>
<p>Similar bans apply in countries like Belgium, Spain and Italy. But Britain, Germany and the United States have no restrictions on polls.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BORDEAUX, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
