<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610296" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: WTO to hold fresh talks next week on Saudi entry.</title>
<headline>WTO to hold fresh talks next week on Saudi entry.</headline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Saudi Arabi and its trading partners will hold two-day talks in Geneva next week on the kingdom joining the World Trade Organisation (WTO), a WTO spokesman said on Friday.</p>
<p>Commerce Minister Osamah bin Jaafar bin Ibrahim Faqih normally leads the delegation in the WTO accession working party negotiating the terms of entry to the 131-member WTO.</p>
<p>The May 29-30 round will be the third since the world's largest oil producer applied in July 1993 to join the trade watchdog's predecessor, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT). The first WTO round was held in May 1996.</p>
<p>Faqih told the last session in November that his country would make every effort to satisfy trading partners it was committed to observe the WTO's rules.</p>
<p>The Saudi minister said his government was making a major effort to adapt to the WTO's standards and norms for intellectual property protection -- a major concern among its trading partners.</p>
<p>Saudi Arabia is eager to diversify its heavily oil-dependent economy and has hinted it wants to join on favourable terms granted to developing countries, according to trade sources.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAARAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
