<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610237" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: FOCUS-Belgian Bacob says merger prepares it for EMU.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Belgian Bacob says merger prepares it for EMU.</headline>
<byline>Nick Antonovics</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian cooperative bank Bacob announced on Friday plans to buy Bank Paribas Belgium, a move it said would reinforce its domestic position and enable the group to swim, not sink once Europe adopts a single currency.</p>
<p>&quot;As we are moving from the small Belgian franc pond to the ocean of the euro we needed to have a complete range of services in order to remain credible,&quot; Bacob chief executive officer Dirk Bruneels told a news conference.</p>
<p>Under an agreement announced simultaneously in Brussels and Paris, Bacob said it would buy 47 percent of Paribas Belgium from French holding company Paribas, lifting its stake to more than 50 percent. Under the agreement, Bacob could take full control of Paribas Belgium in three years time.</p>
<p>Terms were not disclosed, but Paribas in Paris said it would book a capital gain on the transaction and Bank Paribas Belgium has own funds, including reserves, of more than 30 billion Belgian francs ($900 million).</p>
<p>A period of due diligence runs to September.</p>
<p>The merger brings together Belgium's seventh and eight largest banks in a new group which also includes insurance company DVV/LAP and -- in a deal announced by Bacob last month -- stock broking form Smeets, Verbaet.</p>
<p>&quot;What was lacking in our network was a corporate base. We were already strong with retail investors and the social profit sector,&quot; Bruneel said.</p>
<p>Both Bacob and DVV/LAP are part of the Arco Group, which is owned by organisations and individuals linked to the Christian Workers movement - a trades union type body. Arco said it would carry out a capital increase to fund the purchase, but declined to provide details.</p>
<p>Bank Paribas Belgium will bring to Bacob -- a retail bank with 562 branch offices -- new corporate clients, investment banking expertise and a dealing room with a strong niche in foreign exchange activities, such as Ecu trading. Paribas also has about 50 agencies in Belgium, as well as minority interests in Banque Paribas Luxembourg and Banque Paribas Nederland.</p>
<p>As part of the deal, Bank Paribas Belgium will be renamed.</p>
<p>&quot;This way we acquire a client segment which otherwise would not have come to Bacob spontaneously,&quot; Bruneel said.</p>
<p>Christian Manset, chairman of board of Bank Paribas Belgium and a Paribas France board member, said the Belgian bank had become an &quot;atypical component&quot; in the French group.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a generalist bank rather than a specialised one...It needed an alliance with a large retail bank,&quot; Manset said.</p>
<p>&quot;We saw a large complimentarity between our institutions and very little overlap in client base,&quot; Henri Branson, head of Arco, said.</p>
<p>The merger appears however to have been forced on Bank Paribas Belgium. The bank's chief executive officer, Philippe Romagnoli, who said in February the Belgian financial sector was too fragmented, said: &quot;We did not want this operation. But when we understood our head office wanted to focus on its main business we saw it was unavoidable.&quot;</p>
<p>Bacob's announcement comes hard on the heels of news that rival cooperative bank CERA, which vies with it for seventh place, has bought Bank Indosuez Belgium from its French parent and against the background of a wave of consolidation in the Belgian financial sector.</p>
<p>Last year the country's number two bank Credit Communal/Gemeentekrediet entered into the Dexia alliance with France's Credit Local de France.</p>
<p>Banque Bruxelles Lambert, the number three bank, has been looking for a partner for nearly two years. A planned merger with Generale Bank fell trough over opposition from BBL Dutch minority shareholder ING.</p>
<p>Kredietbank confirmed on Thursday it had held exploratory talks with Rabobank  RAB.CN of the Netherlands.</p>
<p>The Brussels bourse was also lifted on Friday by rumours that insurer Royale Belge was about to be sold, perhaps to Dutch financial group ING. Both ING and Royale Belge are significant shareholders in BBL.</p>
<p>Both ING and Royale Belge parent, France's AXA-UAP, declined to comment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81403">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
