<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610365" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Mazda motors to higher profits but problems linger.</title>
<headline>Mazda motors to higher profits but problems linger.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mazda Motor Corp. announced sharply higher profits Friday, with the weaker yen giving earnings an added push, but the firm failed to wipe all the red ink off its balance sheet.</p>
<p>Japan's fifth biggest carmaker, turning in its first set of annual results under President Henry Wallace, a former Ford executive, managed a surge in profits, including investment income, but failed to mount a recovery in its core business.</p>
<p>The automaker posted a parent current profit of 13.90 billion yen ($119 million) in the year ended March 31, compared with 1.23 billion yen ($10.6 million) a year earlier.</p>
<p>Wallace, a Briton, took the wheel at Mazda in June after Ford Motor Co. raised its stake in the Japanese carmaker to 33 percent in order to gain management control. The first foreigner to head a major Japanese company, he was charged with turning around the firm's troubled finances.</p>
<p>Mazda boosted its earnings despite a marginal fall in parent sales after selling off securities to generate 22.18 billion yen ($191 million) of income. Current profits include losses and gains on investments in stocks and other assets.</p>
<p>On an operating level, a measure of actual business, Mazda remained in the red to the tune of 5.38 billion yen ($46.3 million). It also predicted an unspecified loss in its consolidated results, which are due to be released next week.</p>
<p>By contrast, Mazda rivals Toyota Motor Corp. and Honda Motor Co. Ltd both turned in impressive earnings results for 1996/97 on both the current and operating levels, after reaping the benefit of the weaker yen, which has made exports more price-competitive.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
