<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610319" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Ericsson denies slew of new mobile phone models.</title>
<headline>Ericsson denies slew of new mobile phone models.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swedish telecoms group Ericsson said on Friday it would make new mobile phones by modifying model platforms, denying a report saying it planned to boost launches to 6-10 models a year from one.</p>
<p>&quot;We won't launch that many models a year but rather use existing model platforms to make phones with different colours, design or features,&quot; Jan Ahrenbring, vice president marketing at Ericsson mobile phones, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;They will look like different models,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Ericsson launched three phones which were based on existing platforms, the GH688, the GA628 and the GS18 designed for data communication.</p>
<p>The two first were based on the existing GH388 platform. The GS18 was based on a platform from the group Orbitel, of which Ericsson took full control in late 1996, Ahrenbring said.</p>
<p>&quot;In comparison, the GH388 and the GH788 were completely new model concepts when they were launched,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ahrenbring admitted the company had problems meeting demand for the GH788, which was introduced in March.</p>
<p>&quot;Demand exceeds supply,&quot; he said. &quot;But internally we see this as something positive.&quot;</p>
<p>He added he expected the new phones with somewhat different design and features to strengthen Ericsson's position on the global system for mobile telecommunications (GSM) market.</p>
<p>&quot;The more mature the market becomes, the more phones customers want to be able choose from,&quot; Ahrenbring said.</p>
<p>&quot;A year ago, our product portfolio was too thin. But the new products will have a positive effect by strengthening our position on the GSM market further.&quot;</p>
<p>Ahrenbring added that total market forecasts seemed to be on target.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect the market to total 100 million mobile phones this year and the forecast seems to be right,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ahrenbring did not want to disclose how large he expected Ericsson's market share to be but figures from industry research group Dataquest Inc. showed Ericsson's market share amounted to 13 percent in 1996, he said.</p>
<p>-- Birgitta Forsberg, Stockholm newsroom +46-8-700 1017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
