<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610337" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Sakakibara sees BOJ rate rise in coming yr - paper.</title>
<headline>Sakakibara sees BOJ rate rise in coming yr - paper.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 0.50 percentage point rise would still leave Japan's discount rate at a low level and such a move should be expected from the Bank of Japan in the coming year, senior Japanese Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara said in an interview in the afternoon daily Le Monde on Friday.</p>
<p>But he said he did not think the Bank of Japan would raise the discount rate before being confident of economic upturn.</p>
<p>Sakakibara, Japan's &quot;Mr Yen&quot;, also said he believed that the future euro single currency would become a pillar of the world monetary system.  </p>
<p>&quot;I do not think that the Bank of Japan will raise its discount rate before it is sure of a solid economic upturn,&quot; he was quoted as saying. &quot;But the monetary tightening should not have a major impact on the economic recovery,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The discount rate is currently very low. If it rises by 0.50 percent, it will be at 1.0 percent, which remains low. A move on such a scale should be expected in the coming year,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The only certainty is that the euro will become one of the pillars of the world monetary system,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Japan should deregulate its financial markets or risk the yen becoming a local currency, he was quoted as saying.  </p>
<p>&quot;We have to proceed with a deregulation of our financial markets. If we leave them as they are they will become a local market versus the European and American markets and the yen will become a local currency while the euro and dollar will be international currencies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not know how the creation of the euro will modify the value of the yen and the dollar,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;That remains very uncertain and will depend on the number of countries included in the (euro) monetary zone as well as the participation from the outset of countries like Italy and Spain, as well as the attitude of the United Kingdom,&quot; he said. Bank of Japan Governor Yasuo Matsushita said on Wednesday that monetary policy was for now geared to ensuring economic recovery.</p>
<p>While the Bank is seen as coming under some pressure to raise interest rates, analysts believe it will hold off for the moment.</p>
<p>Sakikibara told Le Monde that he did not see Asia creating a monetary union of its own, because of cultural, religious and historic differences in the region and because for some in the region the dollar was still the reference currency.</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
