<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610386" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: Greek shares climb 2.6pct to 1,727 -- new high.</title>
<headline>Greek shares climb 2.6pct to 1,727 -- new high.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greek shares were propelled to new all-time highs on Friday, topping the 1,700 level with remarkable ease on upbeat banks and large cap industrials.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors are very aggressive in large caps and sentiment is better than ever despite sizeable price appreciations in the course of a few months,&quot; said Pantelis Mytilinios, an analyst at Sarros brokerage.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is in good shape and I believe we are headed for the 2,000 level,&quot; the analyst added.</p>
<p>The Athens bourse benchmark index advanced 2.60 percent or 43.85 points to 1,727.70 from Thursday's 1,683.85 close.</p>
<p>It opened on a firm note at 1,691.36 in active trading in banks and other large caps and ground its way up to a historic high of 1,728.03 points, recorded a few minutes before close.</p>
<p>Banks firmed 2.65 percent, followed by industrials which posted a 1.85 percent climb. Other sectors were mixed.</p>
<p>Market watchers said concentrated buying in large caps was responsible for the rise which was seen extending towards the 2,000 level.</p>
<p>&quot;This second leg of the rally is once again led by banks, but industrials and select mid-caps follow in tandem, said Andreas Skentzos, managing director at Condor EPEY, a financial services company.</p>
<p>He said the market's fast rise could be vulnerable to a sudden correction.</p>
<p>&quot;I am somewhat concerned with the sharp rise in bellwether stocks. Currently, demand outstrips supply but a correction could be very sudden, impacting all other sectors too,&quot; Skentzos said.</p>
<p>&quot;However, I do not think we'll see a sharp correction similar to that of last February because demand is broader and there are strong support levels at lower levels,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Turnover was heavy at 32.4 billion drachmas on 7.7 million shares traded. There was a considerable amount of block trades in a wide range of stocks.</p>
<p>Advancing stocks led decliners 132 to 96 with 28 stocks unchanged on 256 traded.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
