<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610366" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japanese bankers resign in widening racketeer scandal.</title>
<headline>Japanese bankers resign in widening racketeer scandal.</headline>
<byline>Fumiko Fujisaki</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Top executives of Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank resigned Friday and Japan's third-largest bank admitted it had been unable to cut off its ties to racketeers in a widening saga of dubious deals and illegal payoffs.</p>
<p>The latest revelations, including hints that more were imminent, put the spotlight on one of Japan's biggest banks, along with the country's biggest brokerage, Nomura Securities.</p>
<p>The spreading scandal has dealt a big blow to the tattered image of the nation's financial sector as it kicks off a &quot;Big Bang&quot; reform aimed at making Tokyo's financial markets competitive as well as &quot;free and fair.&quot;</p>
<p>DKB executives revealed the bank's misdeeds and a possible earlier attempt to hide them from regulators at a news conference after the bank announced that President Katsuhiko Kondo and Chairman Tadashi Okuda would step down over the scandal.</p>
<p>Nomura's president and 15 other top Nomura executives have already resigned over alleged illegal payoffs to the corporate extortionist, or &quot;sokaiya,&quot; at the heart of the affair.</p>
<p>DKB said Kondo would be replaced by Ichiro Fujita, who is currently vice president. Another vice president, Yoshiharu Mani, will replace current chairman Okuda.</p>
<p>Both Kondo and Okuda will become advisers to DKB, with Kondo keeping a seat on the board and Okuda retained in a non-executive capacity after a shareholders meeting on June 27. DKB also said five bank advisers who had served as chairman or president would step down, including Kuniji Miyazaki, president when the bank made the questionable loans.</p>
<p>DKB's Kondo said the bank had made a total of 26 billion yen in loans to Yoshinori Koike, the younger brother of Ryuichi Koike, the racketeer at the heart of the Nomura scandal. But he added that the bank had believed it had made the loans to the younger Koike and his company.</p>
<p>DKB's Fujita told the news conference that the bank may have covered up the dubious deals ahead of finance ministry inspections in 1990 and 1994, while another bank executive said the bank may have made other improper loans to other customers.</p>
<p>Kondo said the key to the scandal was the bank's inability to cut ties to a &quot;former publishing company president,&quot; identified by domestic media as the late Rikiya Kijima -- a sokaiya who reportedly operated as a publisher of a magazine supported by advertisements from financial firms.</p>
<p>&quot;The biggest reason for the unclear deals was that we could not reject the request of the former publishing company president and even after his death (in 1993) we could not shake off his influence and couldn't cope,&quot; Kondo said. He added, though, that no politicians were involved in the affair.</p>
<p>Kijima, said to have been a mentor to Ryuichi Koike, has been reported by Japanese media to have been close to the late Yoshio Kodama, a political &quot;fixer&quot; with gangster and right-wing links who was a key figure in the early 1970s Lockheed payoff scandal centred on former Prime Minister Kakuei Tanaka.</p>
<p>Prosecutors suspect that Ryuichi Koike was given financial favours by both DKB and Nomura to prevent disruption of their shareholders' meetings by sensitive questions. Japan's Commercial Code bans such payments.</p>
<p>A Finance Ministry official, meanwhile, told a news conference that DKB's actions may have been illegal and that it would deal seriously with the bank if violations were proved.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
