<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610306" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Sakakibara pleased with yen recovery-Le monde.</title>
<headline>Sakakibara pleased with yen recovery-Le monde.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan was pleased with the recent rise in the yen and there was no disagreement between the U.S. Treasury and the Japanese Finance Ministry on exchange rate policy, Japanese Finance Ministry official Eisuke Sakakibara said in an interview in the afternoon daily Le Monde on Friday.  </p>
<p>&quot;We were pleased with the recent recovery in the yen and I don't believe the United States was unhappy about it,&quot; Sakakibara was quoted as saying in the interview.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no disagreement between the U.S. Treasury and the Japanese Finance Ministry on exchange rate policies,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Asked whether the authorities would need to support verbal intervention with actual intervention in the market to keep exchange rate parities at a desired level Sakakibara said they could not control markets.</p>
<p>He said the Finance Ministry tried to ensure exchange rate fluctuations were as weak as possible &quot;But we will never be able to fight against the markets. They decide prices. From time to time we can have some influence on markets but no more.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;From a fundamental point of view, you have to take account of the Japanese economic recovery, which should continue to accelerate. That has implications for financial markets and on exchange rates,&quot; Sakakibara said in the interview.</p>
<p>He also said he did not agree with those commentators who believe that the Japanese economy is extremely weak and will weaken the yen.</p>
<p>&quot;The economic figures, in my opinion, are not going in that direction. The Japanese economy is relatively strong in comparison with the pace of growth in the United States and Europe,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +331 4221 5542</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
