<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610367" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: CZECH PX50 RISES BUT ACTIVITY LOW - DEALERS.</title>
<headline>CZECH PX50 RISES BUT ACTIVITY LOW - DEALERS.</headline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Czech major issues surged again on Friday pushing the PX50 index up 1.45 percent to 484 but dealers said prices had been built on low volumes and expected a downturn on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Gains are partly because of domestic buying and partly just that there are not many active players in the market. I would not bet on the day's rebound continuing,&quot; said Miroslav Nosal of Patria Finance.</p>
<p>The major factor affecting foreign investors' intentions on the Czech equities market continued to be the current instability in the Czech crown and fears of a devaluation.</p>
<p>On Friday, the crown again came under assault from foreign and domestic selling pressure but strengthened markedly after heavy central bank intervention.</p>
<p>The crown fell to a Friday low of minus five percent against the mid-point of its mark/dollar basket but rebounded to -1.8 percent after the intervention.</p>
<p>Gains on the PX50 were led by SPT Telecom which rose 60 crowns to 2,970, CEZ which rose 53 crowns to 948 and Komercni Banka which was up 87 crowns to 1,801.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
