<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610336" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Belgian bonds becalmed, focus on equities.</title>
<headline>Belgian bonds becalmed, focus on equities.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian linear bonds were a touch higher in very quiet dealings on Friday, with most attention riveted on the equities market where a major reshuffle in the financial sector was underway, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is pretty quiet. There is not a lot going on. Most people are more interested in their equities portfolios,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;We had a bit of a scare on Bavarian inflation figures that caused a little dip, but it didn't last,&quot; the trader added.</p>
<p>Traders said short-term interest rates were stable and there was little change in the Belgian franc's position.  </p>
<p>Traders said that after a week in which linear bonds had lost a lot of ground, the future would now be heavily influenced by the movement of the Japanese yen.</p>
<p>They said there was little real activity on the bond market on Friday, although there had been some business in 10-year paper.</p>
<p>The yield of the benchmark 2007 OLO was 5.98 percent at 1010 GMT against Thursday's closing 5.99 percent, and the spread over German Bunds was an unchanged seven basis points.</p>
<p>The June futures contract was seven basis points higher at 120.64. -- Brussels Newsroom +32 2 287 6810, Fax +32 2 230 7710</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
