<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610391" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: IHALAINEN SAYS BROAD '98 PAY DEAL DIFFICULT - RADIO.</title>
<headline>IHALAINEN SAYS BROAD '98 PAY DEAL DIFFICULT - RADIO.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lauri Ihalainen, chairman of the Central Organisation of Finnish Trade Unions (SAK), said on Friday it would probably be more difficult to reach a new broad centralised pay deal from February 1998 than it had been two years ago, Finnish radio news reported.</p>
<p>Ihalainen told an SAK council meeting that there were now more branch-specific issues to deal with between unions and employers, and that some branches felt a need to get their share of corporate profits, the radio said.</p>
<p>Ihalainen also said the nominal pay rise element should be bigger than the tax cut element in next incomes settlement.  </p>
<p>&quot;We must be prepared also for the alternative that this time the conditions will not exist for a broad incomes settlement,&quot; Finnish news agency STT quoted Ihalainen as saying.</p>
<p>But he noted that a majority of SAK member unions have said that their targets would best be served by a centralised deal.</p>
<p>SAK's May 23-24 council meeting is scheduled to make a preliminary decision on the organisation's targets for the next incomes settlement from February 1998, STT said.</p>
<p>Ihalainen said a new two-year deal after the 1996-97 agreement would be justified from the point of view that pay talks would then not clash with the campaign for the March 1999 general election, STT said.</p>
<p>Working hours should be reduced, but unions should not set unrealistic targets in this field, STT quoted Ihalainen as saying.</p>
<p>--Helsinki newsroom +358-9-680 50 245, news@reuters.fi</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
