<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610311" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German copper recycling firm sees higher 97 output.</title>
<headline>German copper recycling firm sees higher 97 output.</headline>
<dateline>LUENEN, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>German copper producer Huettenwerke Kayser AG (HK) expects to increase output in 1977 to meet buoyant demand, a company spokesman said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We're confident we will be able to produce at full capacity...large parts of the output are already committed to customers via long-term contracts and the rest will also be easily placed,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have targeted 170,000-175,000 tonnes of cathode production now that our investment programme has been completed.&quot;</p>
<p>HK, which works solely on the basis of secondary copper, produced 166,000 tonnes of cathodes in 1996.</p>
<p>The spokesman said high copper prices would encourage scrap sellers to bring out supplies.</p>
<p>Cash London Metals Exchange (LME) prices, converted into marks on the basis of the daily Frankfurt currency fixing, were around 4,000 marks a tonne on average in the first quarter of 1997 compared with a 1996 average of 3,453 marks.</p>
<p>The HK spokesman said the market had overcome a crisis in the summer of last year when the Sumitomo copper debacle and weak demand meant prices plummeted and scrap was scarce.</p>
<p>The company in a statement issued preliminary figures for 1996, ahead of a shareholders meeting on July 1.</p>
<p>It showed sales totalling 1.035 million marks were only slightly below 1.060 million in 1995.</p>
<p>Production in 1966 was 44,000 tonnes higher than in 1995 and accounted for 25 percent of Germany's refined copper output.</p>
<p>--Vera Eckert, Hamburg newsroom +49-40-41903275</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22460">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUENEN, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
