<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610305" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Advertising experts unimpressed by French election.</title>
<headline>Advertising experts unimpressed by French election.</headline>
<byline>Denis Thomas</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Promotion of candidates in the run-up to the French parliamentary election has been short, cheap and thin on ideas, advertising specialists say.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a campaign without communication. There will be a lot of abstaining,&quot; Marc Vanghelder, chairman of Leaders and Opinions, a communication adviser that has followed over 70 election candidates, told Reuters this week.</p>
<p>France goes to the polls on May 25 and June 1 to elect a new government. French president Jacques Chirac's mandate runs for another five years.</p>
<p>&quot;The candidates don't know where they are. They shake hands, hold meetings, but they talk more about what has been done than what will be done,&quot; Vanghelder said.</p>
<p>&quot;Even though people are fed up with promises, they would have liked to hear a few,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>There has been such a lack of public interest that one tracking institute did a poll of so-called negative voting intentions by asking, &quot;Who would you not want to vote for?&quot;, one advertising source said.</p>
<p>Earlier this week a monthly television magazine, Television-Le Mensuel, published a different poll that revealed nearly two out of three French people believed French television was politically biaised.</p>
<p>&quot;In three weeks we have not had the time to do much -- a poster here, a journal and leaflets there -- even if we are not supposed to. That favours candidates seeking re-election. The others have not got time to make themselves known,&quot; said one campaign adviser at an advertising agency.</p>
<p>A law passed in January 1990 on the financing of political parties has made advertising during election periods practically non-existent.</p>
<p>Candidates' total election expenses must not exceed 320,000 to 380,000 francs, depending on the constituency.</p>
<p>&quot;How can a deputy who needs to reach 400,000 people do so with 300,000 francs? It is stupid, especially as a mayor, whose electorate is much narrower, sometimes has a budget double that,&quot; one advertising agency official said.</p>
<p>Among the best-known communication advisers, Euro RSCG Institutionnels has 60 candidates on its books, while two others, Image et Strategies and Principes, each have around 10 candidates. Claude Fitoussi Conseil is promoting only the environment minister, Corinne Lepage, while Eric Dudan is behind the national poster campaign for the RPR-UDF coalition, which formed the outgoing government.</p>
<p>The political parties have also flocked to the Internet to get their message across.</p>
<p>The RPR (Rally for the Republic) was the first to open Web site, while the Socialist Party launched its site on May 5. The UDF (Union for French Democracy) opened its site on May 9.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
