<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610360" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Westinghouse's CBS says TV chief Peter Lund resigns.</title>
<headline>Westinghouse's CBS says TV chief Peter Lund resigns.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Westinghouse Electric Corp. said Friday that Peter Lund, president of its CBS television and cable group, has resigned.</p>
<p>As part of a corporate reorganization, the company said all of its television and radio stations will be consolidated into a single organization. Mel Karmazin, head of its radio division, will be chairman and chief executive of the new CBS station group.  </p>
<p>Westinghouse Chairman and Chief Executive Michael Jordan said in a statement that the reorganization was coming in advance of the company's corporate split this fall, when the industrial businesses become Westinghouse Electric Co. and the media businesses CBS Corp. Jordan will run CBS.</p>
<p>Beginning immediately, the television and cable units will report directly to Jordan, the company said.</p>
<p>All CBS radio and and television stations will be consolidated into a single organisation led by Karmazin, who ran Infinity Broadcasting when Westinghouse acquired it last year for about $4.9 billion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
