<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610346" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: Greek bonds fall, ecu/drs ranges, depos, forwards up.</title>
<headline>Greek bonds fall, ecu/drs ranges, depos, forwards up.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greek fixed coupon bonds and zeros continued to be under selling pressure from abroad, ecu/drachma was steady above 311 and the interbank depo and forward curves were up, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Prices of fixed coupon bonds have shed 30 to 40 basis points and zeros about 10-15 basis points since this morning on sales from abroad,&quot; said a dealer at a private bank. &quot;This is not profit-taking.&quot;</p>
<p>The dealer attributed the selling pressure to more expensive interbank funding and the deputy finance minister's announcement on Thursday that Greece will issue 12-month T-bills on June 2, auction 10-year fixed coupon bonds and reopen binds for three-, five- and seven-year fixed coupon bonds on June 19.</p>
<p>Deputy Finance Minister Nikos Christodoulakis said on Thursday that the treasury will issue 12-month T-bills at 9.60 percent on June 2, down 10 basis points, and reopen bids for three-, five- and seven-year coupon bonds on June 19.</p>
<p>Greece auctioned three-year, 9.80 percent bonds, five-year, 9.20 percent bonds and seven-year, 8.9 percent bonds on March 19.</p>
<p>&quot;The market cannot absorb large amounts of debt paper and the ministry should make sure that a relatively small amount of paper is auctioned in June,&quot; the trader said. &quot;If this does not happen, we can see prices at lower levels.&quot;</p>
<p>Players rushed to lock in profits and secure funding for the debt paper to be auctioned in June after the minister's announcement on Thursday driving bond prices lower.</p>
<p>Interbank depos and forex forwards were firmer across-the-board as players sought funding for the T-bill and coupon bonds, money market dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Depos are up 10 to 15 basis points across-the-spectrum and implied drachma rates from forex forwards are up 10 to 30 basis points from tomnext to one-year,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>Funding for June debt paper and some forex outflows were responsible for the rate rise, dealers said.</p>
<p>Ecu/drachma was trading in the 311.15/50 range since this morning and dealers said they were waiting to see the central bank's stance at the fixing.</p>
<p>&quot;We can see ecu/drachma much higher if Bank of Greece does not intervene at the fixing today,&quot; said a forex dealer. &quot;It is only fear that the central bank will intervene at the fixing that keeps ecu/drachma capped at these levels.&quot;</p>
<p>The central bank has to demonstrate that it is behind its hard drachma policy.</p>
<p>The mark was quoted at 159.40/50 from Thursday's 159.450 fix, the dollar at 269.51/61 drachmas from 269.560 and the ecu at 311.08/18 from 311.080 drachmas.</p>
<p>The National Bank of Greece, the domestic money</p>
<p>market's biggest player, quoted the following early rates:</p>
<p>** Overnight at  9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** T/N at  9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** S/N at  9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** One week at 9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Two weeks at 9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Three weeks at 9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** One month at  9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Two months at  9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Three months at 9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Six months at  9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Nine months at 9.70-10.20</p>
<p>** Twelve months at 9.70-10.20</p>
<p>--Dimitris Kontogiannis, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
