<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610373" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: No avalanche of labour laws - Santer.</title>
<headline>No avalanche of labour laws - Santer.</headline>
<dateline>NOORDWIJK, Netherlands 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>There will be no new wave of labour rules imposed on European Union employers as a result of Britain's decision to adopt the EU Social Chapter, European Commission President Jacques Santer said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have absolutely no intention of launching an avalanche,&quot; Santer's spokesman, Nikolaus van der Pas, quoted him as telling new British Prime Minister Tony Blair.</p>
<p>Blair, meeting the EU executive's leader on the margins of a summit, repeated his government's decision to sign up to the Social Chapter, an agreement designed to set standards of worker protection across the bloc.</p>
<p>The former Conservative government had negotiated an opt-out from the laws, fearing that they would harm the competitiveness of British industry. Critics charged that it left Britons with fewer workplace rights than their EU colleagues.</p>
<p>But Blair warned Santer that although he would now adopt the EU labour laws there was much concern in Britain that Brussels would unleash a tide of new rules.</p>
<p>A British aide said Blair told Santer there would be &quot;serious political difficulties in the United Kingdom if the UK signing of the Social Chapter led to a flood of proposals for social regulation.&quot;</p>
<p>He also called for flexibility in the labour market.</p>
<p>Van der Pas said Santer had emphasised to Blair that the Social Chapter was designed to provide minimum protections to workers and that there would be no flood unleashed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOORDWIJK, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
