<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610378" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ANGOLA: Angolan army said to take control in diamond area.</title>
<headline>Angolan army said to take control in diamond area.</headline>
<byline>John Fleming</byline>
<dateline>LUANDA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Angolan army has moved into the country's key diamond area with tanks and armoured vehicles, clearing areas overrun by refugees from the Democratic Republic of Congo and former rebel UNITA supporters, military and expatriate sources said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The FAA (Angolan army) has entered into our areas in the Lunda Norte and has taken the towns of Muinda, Canzar, Cambulo and Buia,&quot; a senior UNITA general told Reuters. The areas are along the Cassai River on Angola's eastern border with Zaire.</p>
<p>The general said from Luanda he had received reports of casualties, but had no figures.</p>
<p>UNITA, the National Union for the Total Independence of Angola, entered a power-sharing agreement with the government on April 11 that formally ended two decades of civil war which started at independence from Portugal in 1975.</p>
<p>Expatriate mining sources backed up the UNITA report. One source working in the region said government troops were moving further west after clearing the easternmost border area.</p>
<p>&quot;These areas are now clear of refugees and other bandits that came from Zaire. The army has also taken the opportunity to take control of areas where UNITA has been mining,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>Another mining source told Reuters the FAA had battled armed UNITA supporters in the mining town of Tchitatolo, reporting:</p>
<p>&quot;Our people there say the FAA moved into the town of Tchitatolo earlier in the week...where they encountered resistance.&quot;</p>
<p>The source said the army's action was aimed at clearing out illegal diamond diggers who had entered the province from the former Zaire during a seven-month war by rebels to topple Mobutu Sese Seko's 32-year rule as president.</p>
<p>&quot;The government at the same time took the opportunity to clean out areas held by UNITA,&quot; the source said, adding that the government move was expected to continue westwards, deeper into UNITA areas.</p>
<p>The Angolan government began tightening control of its borders with Zaire in April after an estimated 17,000 Rwandan refugees, many of them ex-soldiers of the former Hutu-dominated Rwandan government and Interahamwe militia, entered Angola from the northeast.</p>
<p>UNITA still controls vast areas of the country -- some estimates are as high as 70 percent -- including most of the diamond-producing areas.</p>
<p>In a peace plan which has taken two years to implement under United Nations supervision, UNITA and government troops have been joined under a single national army or demobilised.</p>
<p>UNITA told Reuters in April it was weeks away from signing a deal on how to share the country's diamond deposits with state-owned diamond company Endiama.</p>
<p>Last year the peace process was said to be in jeopardy because of instability in the Lunda Norte area.</p>
<p>Many foreign companies have not been able to take control of their legal diamond concessions issued by Endiama, because they are still under UNITA's control.</p>
<p>Diamond production in Angola is estimated to be worth around $1 billion a year with between $300 million and $600 million of production coming from UNITA-held areas.</p>
<p>Angola's alluvial diamonds are easily dug out of riverbeds and are of high value.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I23000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUANDA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ANGOLA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
