<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610416" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Mark steadies after Bavarian CPI, off highs vs Sfr.</title>
<headline>Mark steadies after Bavarian CPI, off highs vs Sfr.</headline>
<text>
<p>LONDON, May 23 (Reuter) The mark was steady on its European crosses, below highs it ticked up to earlier after Bavarian consumer prices rose a larger-than-expected 0.5 percent in May.</p>
<p>But analysts do not expect the report to have a lasting impact as long as consumer prices in other West German states rise in line with expectations.</p>
<p>&quot;The strong CPI number had a lagged effect but it is probably a one-off blip and shouldn't make too much difference to the mark,&quot; said Ken Watrett, an economist at Paribas Capital Markets. &quot;People are still looking for a steady hand on German rates.&quot;</p>
<p>The mark was last at 84.31/34 pesetas from 84.27/29 late Thursday in Europe. Mark/escudo was at 100.91/94 from 100.79.84 Thursday.</p>
<p>Mark/Swiss franc was less successful in holding its ground. The mark slipped from highs it set against the franc yesterday after the Swiss National Bank had pumped liquidity to the money markets for the second consecutive day.</p>
<p>The Swiss franc's resilience in the face of SNB action is partly due to concern that a broad group of countries will launch the European single currency.</p>
<p>&quot;The Swiss franc is a very attractive safe haven if you think a broad sweep of countries are going to go ahead with EMU,&quot; said Watrett at Paribas.</p>
<p>The mark was last at 83.21/23 centimes from a high of 83.60 yesterday.</p>
<p>Talk of a broad EMU was reinforced after Germany's recent decision to revalue the Bundesbank's gold reserves and sell more of the stake it holds in Deutsche Telekom in a bid to improve its fiscal position.</p>
<p>These plans came under fire yesterday when Dutch finance minister Gerrit Zalm said in a television interview that any plans to cut the German deficit by revaluing the Bundesbank's gold reserves would endanger the soundness of the planned European single currency.</p>
<p>Also, a senior European Union official said today the gold plan is unlikely to be allowed for the purposes of deficit reduction, though it could be used to offset outstanding debt.</p>
<p>Revaluing its gold reserves may not be the only ace up the German government's sleeve as it strives to cut its budget deficit and debt even as the economy struggles to recover.</p>
<p>German foreign minister Klaus Kinkel said he could foresee the government selling its entire 75 percent stake in Deutsche Telekom in order to qualify for EMU, according to the Handelsblatt.</p>
<p>&quot;It is all coming back to the question of EMU,&quot; said a trader at a German bank in London. &quot;People are beginning to expect some sort of clever accounting tricks&quot; to allow Germany to qualify for EMU.</p>
<p>--Swaha Pattanaik, London Newsroom +44171 542 6284</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
