<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610449" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: GKN up on court ruling, defence stocks rally.</title>
<headline>GKN up on court ruling, defence stocks rally.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in GKN Plc rose in early trade on Friday as a U.S. court reduced damages awarded against its Meineke Discount Muffler unit, while defence stocks rose as fears eased of a tougher UK government line on military exports.  </p>
<p>GKN was up 23p or 2.3 percent at 10.07-1/2 stg by 0742 GMT, the biggest gainer in the FTSE 100 index. British Aerospace Plc rose 22-1/2p at 12.55 stg and Smiths Industries Plc firmed 14p at 765.  </p>
<p>GKN said it was appealing against a U.S. court judgement even though damages against its Meineke unit had been reduced to $390 million from $600 million.</p>
<p>The damages relate to a claim by Meineke franchisees that the group had mishandled and mis-spent millions of dollars charged for advertising.</p>
<p>News of the award sent GKN shares sharply lower when first announced last December -- and again in March when an initial $398 million award was raised to $600 million.</p>
<p>Separately, defence stocks benefitted from a newspaper report that the UK government would not block sales of military equipment to Indonesia.</p>
<p>The Independent newspaper said Foreign Office sources said export licences granted last December would not be revoked -- easing concerns of a general clampdown on military exports.  </p>
<p>The Indonesian orders included armoured cars made by GKN, while Bae plans to sell Hawk jets to the regime.  </p>
<p>Analysts said the reduction of the award was not a major surprise since it in effect took the situation back to the original award last December.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not a particularly significant development,&quot; said one analyst, who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>&quot;We all knew that the company was going to launch an appeal and this just confirms that the franchisees who waived their rights can't get back in...it is really a non-entity of a statement.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts also noted that defence stocks had come under pressure in recent sessions, partly on worries that the recently-elected Labour government may block some defence exports.</p>
<p>They said Labour would still probably take a tougher line in some instances deals but added that major export deals were unlikely to be under threat.</p>
<p>&quot;I would be very sceptical that this would make a major impact,&quot; said another analyst. &quot;Twenty thousand jobs in the UK would be at risk, is that what the government wants to happen?&quot;</p>
<p>-- David Holmes, London Newsroom +44 171 542 4367</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34430">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
