<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610453" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Dollar steady above 1.69 marks and shy of 116 yen.</title>
<headline>Dollar steady above 1.69 marks and shy of 116 yen.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The dollar stuck to familiar ranges just below 116 yen and above 1.69 marks in early Europe, finding little impetus to break either way, said traders.</p>
<p>&quot;The dollar is lacking a bit of interest, to be honest. We've got a long-weekend coming up and some of the banks are off,&quot; said a senior dealer at a UK merchant bank.</p>
<p>At 0720 GMT dollar/mark was trading at 1.6910/15 against 1.6943/53 in late Europe on Thursday, though above overnight lows around 1.6880 marks.</p>
<p>Against the yen, the dollar was unchanged at 115.80/5.90 against 115.80/85 in late Europe on Thursday.  </p>
<p>Traders said the dollar was relegated to the side-lines as the market eyed a stumble in sterling, punished by speculation Bank of England Governor Eddie George might not be reappointed at the end of his five-year term next year.</p>
<p>&quot;Most interest is on sterling and its crosses after the well-publicised dispute between (finance minister) Gordon Brown and Eddie George,&quot; said the trader.</p>
<p>At 0735 GMT, sterling/mark was trading at 2.7535/45 against 2.7845/55 in late dealings on Thursday.</p>
<p>Dollar markets, however, should find some comfort from the overnight release of the Federal Reserve's March 25 minutes.  </p>
<p>Analysts said that as the minutes showed the Fed voting unanimously at its March 25 meeting to raise the federal funds rate by a quarter percentage point, positioning toward higher rates should therefore be a catalyst for the dollar to edge higher in the weeks ahead.</p>
<p>But not all analysts are as optimistic. &quot;We haven't seen a dramatic response from interest-rate markets. Unless the economic data shows the economy is rapidly rebounding from its slight slowdown, there will be doubt in people's minds whether a tightening is inevitable at the next FOMC,&quot; said Paul Meggyesi, senior currency economist at Deutsche Morgan Grenfell.  </p>
<p>&quot;The report leaves a couple of question marks about the near-term direction of rates,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>German April month/month producer prices were a touch higher than expected as they grew 0.3 month/month and 0.9 percent year/year against forecasts for 0.1 percent month/month growth and of 0.7 percent year/year.</p>
<p>&quot;Producer prices were slightly worse than expected. But they do not alter the outlook for Bundesbank policy,&quot; Meggyesi said.</p>
<p>--Julia Meehan, London forex +4471 542 6701</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
