<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610457" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Gilts to hold onto 111-02 support.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Gilts to hold onto 111-02 support.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>June gilt futures on LIFFE will look to support at around one full point below current levels, technical analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The gilt contract is holding onto 111-02 to 110-31,&quot; said a technical analyst at Merrill Lynch International in London.</p>
<p>&quot;The key here is the spread against Bunds - Bunds have had a very strong downmove in the last couple of days in big volume, and the gilt/Bund spread is at a critical level,&quot; the analyst added.</p>
<p>June gilts were trading at 112-02 at 0718 GMT, 6/32 above Thursday's close.  </p>
<p>Retracement support for June Bunds at 100.39 has knock-on implications for the gilt market, the Merrill Lynch analyst said.</p>
<p>&quot;If we have a sustained move through the critical 150 level on the gilt/Bund spread, it will trigger a severe reaction to 142 and then to 125, in a retracement of the movement of the last three years,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The 10-year gilt/Bund cash yield spread was at 150 basis points at 0727 GMT.</p>
<p>Resistance for the contract kicks in close to current market levels, at 112-09 and then at 112-20, the analyst said.  </p>
<p>Richard Adcock, manager, technical research, at HSBC Futures in London, also sees June gilts able to rally short-term to 112-20, if they bounce off support at 111-26.</p>
<p>But &quot;we feel further selling pressure can develop over the next few days, to take the market closer to the 111-00 region,&quot; he said in a note to clients.</p>
<p>September short sterling was at 93.17 at 0738 GMT, unchanged. Adcock put longer-term resistance at 93.28.</p>
<p>-- Carolyn Cohn, International Bonds Unit +44 171 542 6320</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
