<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610481" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia debt awaits offshore rate cut judgement.</title>
<headline>Australia debt awaits offshore rate cut judgement.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>----------(Snapshot at 4.35 P.M./0635 GMT)------------------</p>
<p>FUTURES					  CASH YIELD</p>
<p>90-DAY BILLS  (JUN) 94.47  (+ 0.40)    5.53    (- 0.49)</p>
<p>3-YR T-BONDS  (JUN) 93.47  (+ 0.23)    6.50    (- 0.23)</p>
<p>10-YR T-BONDS (JUN) 92.420 (+0.115)    7.57    (- 0.11)</p>
<p>AUD/USD  0.7684 (PREV 0.7830) US 30-YR  6.99   (6.99 NY)</p>
<p>---------------------(May 23)-------------------------------</p>
<p>*Profit-taking and caution ahead of the European opening saw early substantial falls pared in Australian debt yields, after the Reserve Bank's eased policy</p>
<p>*Official rates now 5.5 percent, same as U.S.  </p>
<p>By Colin Brinsden</p>
<p>Australian debt yields finished substantially lower after the Reserve Bank caught the market on the hop by cutting official rates for a fourth time in less than a year to 5.5 percent, and down 50 basis points.</p>
<p>Bond yields tumbled to their lowest level since January on the announcement, which saw the benchmark 10-year bond briefly drop to just under 7.50 percent, before profit-taking and caution ahead of the European opening pared the rally.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot depends now on how the offshore reacts to this (rate cut),&quot; said Su-Lin Ong, fixed income economist at Hambros Bank.  </p>
<p>&quot;It does depend on how Europe reacts in the next couple of days and whether they see this as credible, that in Australia growth can really grow faster and there really is very low inflation,&quot; Ong said.</p>
<p>Ten-year yield differentials against the U.S. sunk to their lowest level in three years on the announcement, while the benchmark three-year spread briefly brushed with parity.</p>
<p>The latest rate cut takes official interest rates to parity with the U.S., and the big test for central bank and the Australian dollar is if the Federal Reserve does tighten policy later this year, analysts said.  </p>
<p>The easing followed hot-on-the-heels of Thursday's downward revision in annual wages growth to 4.3 percent, which was back below the Reserve Bank's 4.5 percent comfort zone.</p>
<p>Announcing the cut, the central bank said the wages data seemed to be consistent with satisfactory inflation, which they expected to fall below 2.0 percent in underlying terms in the coming quarters and below its 2.0-3.0 percent target.</p>
<p>It also said that employment growth was subdued and that economic growth was unlikely to put pressure on inflation.</p>
<p>Analysts said the move was in sharp contrast to impression given by recent comments by the RBA of policy.  </p>
<p>Earlier, this month when testifying to parliament RBA governor Ian Macfarlane said he saw no economic gain from a further reduction in interest rates, which was seen by many as the final word on a rate cut.</p>
<p>&quot;It's all really confusing. I don't think I'll ever read a Macfarlane speech again,&quot; quipped one analyst.</p>
<p>The timing of the move, nearly two weeks before the next board meeting, also took the market by surprise given that they normally follow the day after and that the cut in December was only held back by a week after a meeting because of the then volatility in the Australian dollar.  </p>
<p>----------------------(SPREADS)---------------------------------</p>
<p> AUD VS   3-YR	   10-YR	* AUD 3-YR/10-YR SPREAD</p>
<p> USD	+11 (- 23)    83 (- 13) * FUTURES   105   (+ 11)</p>
<p> CAD	140 (- 25)   107 (- 16) * CASH	106   (+ 11)</p>
<p> NZD	-83 (- 14)   -02 (- 08) *</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>The Australian/U.S. 10-year bond yield spread sunk to around 75 basis points on the rate cut news. U.S. Treasuries remained around the weaker New York levels with little data trade-off on Thursday and in front of the U.S. holiday weekend with markets closed there on Monday.  </p>
<p>------------------------(TECHNICALS)-------------------------</p>
<p>FUTURES	*SUP/RES     *SUP/RES 2ND *RSI    *MA-10 *MA-20</p>
<p>10-YEAR (JUN)*92.41-92.48 *92.38-92.50 *62 PCT *92.31 *92.23</p>
<p>3-YEAR  (JUN)*93.42-93.50 *93.38-93.60 *67 PCT *93.24 *93.18</p>
<p>90-DAY  (JUN)*94.45-94.50 *94.33-94.55 *79 PCT *94.08 *94.06</p>
<p>-------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>-- Colin Brinsden 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
