<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610406" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Cocoa seen inching towards 1,060 target.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Cocoa seen inching towards 1,060 target.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>-------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p> JULY    Close  * Support * Resist * RSI14 *   MA10 *   MA30</p>
<p> COCOA   1,029  *  1,000  *  1,035 * 56.3  *  1,016 *  1,019</p>
<p>---------------VIEWS FROM THE MARKET - May 23 ----------------</p>
<p>LIFFE cocoa futures may finally break out of their recent trading range in the next couple of weeks, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>Although July was called to open two stg a tonne lower, the position had broken a downward trend on the five-day relative strength index (RSI).</p>
<p>That should give it the strength to break initial resistance near 1,035 stg and re-test key resistance near 1,060, said Trevor Neil, senior technical analyst at Union Cal Futures.</p>
<p>The 1,060 level has not been seen since late April.</p>
<p>The break indicated that the slow rise since the beginning of May would extend to 1,060 without much interruption, he said.</p>
<p>July cocoa closed little changed at 1,029, and CSCE July cocoa ended sharply lower at $1,463 after failing to break $1,500 early in the session.</p>
<p>London's July contract has held a wide range between about 1,060 and the April 9 low of 980 since around March and is currently near the middle of that range.</p>
<p>July has previously tested 1,060 twice and failed. But Neil said indicators were pointing to an ultimately successful third attempt.</p>
<p>&quot;Oscillators are in good shape despite the sideways market,&quot; he said. &quot;They have created a bullish pattern, which is unusual in a sideways market.&quot;</p>
<p>But he said the move toward 1,060 would take time. &quot;It's probably more than five days away,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>And when July finally moved up to 1,060, it would be important to see how it reacted.</p>
<p>Neil added that while he was leaning toward a break of 1,060, recent low volume was a discouraging.</p>
<p>&quot;The volume has not really added to the bullish picture,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Immediate July support rested at 1,000, with key support at 980. If July slipped below 980, the market could see a swift move to between 940 and 900.</p>
<p>--Medora Lee, London newsroom +44 171 542 8072</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
