<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610465" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FUND VIEW-Gartmore eyes S.Africa, Asia potential.</title>
<headline>FUND VIEW-Gartmore eyes S.Africa, Asia potential.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-22</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa and selective Asian markets are likely to offer increased investment opportunities in coming months, Gartmore Investment Management global emerging markets head Philip Ehrmann said.</p>
<p>Ehrmann told Reuters he would be looking for opportunities in South Africa later in the year, while certain Asian markets were beginning to show potential.</p>
<p>Gartmore, which has a portfolio of about $800 million in emerging markets, was also likely to cut an overweight Brazilian position and distribute this within Latin America, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;In Asia I'll try and hold my nerve and stick to Taiwan,&quot; he said, and in China would look for sensible plays. Korea could also do well, especially if the yen continued its recent rally.</p>
<p>Ehrmann said South African equity and bond markets would offer opportunities once the latest round of foreign exchange relaxation comes through in the third quarter.</p>
<p>&quot;Until the currency and the economy have negotiated the July/August/September watershed of the easier policy I think there is little likelihood of interest rates coming down as is merited by the lack of economic activity.&quot;</p>
<p>But this would raise interesting possibilities for equity and bond investors.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe at the shorter end of the market one will make money at some point, but currently it is going to be a little bit difficult,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The planned easing of foreign exchange controls includes allowing offshore investment by individuals and local foreign exchange accounts.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone will want to have a forex account and then after three or four months you begin to realise you are only yielding two or three percent and move back to the rand and that is the time when rates will begin to fall and I think the stockmarket will do quite well.&quot;</p>
<p>He said South African equities were currently consolidating with some weaker results coming through to reflect the state of the economy.</p>
<p>He said emerging market investors were heavily underweight South Africa relative to the benchmark indices, with the average investor at five or six percent. But this was likely to change as South Africa's index weighting fell with the inclusion of other markets and as allocations rose.</p>
<p>He said it was becoming more difficult to find value in Latin America, especially Brazil, but Gartmore remained overweight in the region.</p>
<p>Asia was currently living with the consequences of over-investment, and this was being reflected in prices and earnings.</p>
<p>&quot;Just as stock prices got overblown, now everyone thinks the world is coming to an end and we are on our way down here,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the Thai economy needed to be rebalanced after suffering a meltdown in terms of bank balance sheets. But the country's rapid growth meant this was likely to occur quickly.</p>
<p>&quot;In 12 or 18 months time we will be looking at Thailand as being a country which has learnt its lesson and can go forward again. There is absolutely no reason why if we believe Mexico can learn its lesson the Thais can't learn their lesson,&quot; Ehrmann said.</p>
<p>Thai stocks are about 50 to 60 percent off their peak and selective opportunities were likely to appear, he said.</p>
<p>He said Asia will probably prove attractive in 1998.</p>
<p>A north/south divide had appeared in Asia, with China, Taiwan, Korea and Hong Kong attractive. Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia and the Philippines had more pressing issues to deal with, but these would ease off at some stage.</p>
<p>He said Gartmore had used the recent pullback in Eastern European markets to increase exposure.</p>
<p>-- Andrew Gill, London newsroom +171 542 5887</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-22"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
