<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610437" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Dawson sees year profits reaching 12 mln stg.</title>
<headline>Dawson sees year profits reaching 12 mln stg.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Information services company Dawson Holdings Plc said on Friday that annual profits are likely to meet its broker's forecast of 12 million stg.</p>
<p>&quot;There is every indication that the group is on course to meet our principal broker's forecast,&quot; said chairman Peter Brown in a statement accompanying first half results.</p>
<p>The company's principal broker UBS is forecasting pretax profits of 12.3 million stg for the year. The group made pretax profits of 9.8 million stg for the year to September 30, 1996.</p>
<p>Full year profits at Dawson are inevitably lower than the first half because of the cyclical nature of Dawson's library supply business. It has to order technical journals direct and pay up front in the second half of the year.</p>
<p>The group lifted half year pretax profits to 16.15 million stg from 14.16 million. Turnover increased to 397.37 million from 286.81 million.</p>
<p>The results include the consolidation of Surridge Dawson, which it bought in May 1996, for the full six months.</p>
<p>Dawson's shares responded positively to the results, climbing 6p to 237-1/2p by 0846 GMT.</p>
<p>The strength of the pound reduced overseas profits by almost one million stg during the first six months, noted the company.</p>
<p>But it said the impact of a strong pound would decrease in the second half of the year even if the UK currency remains at current levels.</p>
<p>The AIM-listed company plans to transfer to a full stock exchange listing in January 1998.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 4019</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I61000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
