<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610487" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: INSIGHT-Australian Gold Index sidelined in range.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT-Australian Gold Index sidelined in range.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian Gold Index is lower and moving sideways just above support. Indicators are oversold, but the index is looking very weak.  </p>
<p>The index is still within its consolidation range 1,535 to 1,610.</p>
<p>Traders remain sceptical and trade the range and the breaks.</p>
<p>Short term techncials are mixed. The averages are bearish. Leading indicators mixed. ROC and Stochastics are moving lower, with the RSI turing higher. Traders remain cautious.</p>
<p>In the medium term, the index is in its 7th week within the range 1,535 to 1,610, and testing the lows again.</p>
<p>The bears are still in control, but traders will continue to employ trailing stops on shorts, especially if the index can rally above 1,610.</p>
<p>Medium term technicals are bearish and very oversold.</p>
<p>Averages are bearish. Leading indicators continue oversold and trading sideways to slightly lower.</p>
<p>The Stochastics are extremely oversold at 6/9.</p>
<p>While support at 1,535 holds previous Fibonacci levels remain at 1,715, 1,769, and 1,823.</p>
<p>In the longer term, the index continues lower within its bear corridor.</p>
<p>Bears continue to focus on the head and shoulders formation. But with the oversold nature of the index, they too will be cautious and move trailing stops closer to current levels.</p>
<p>Longer term technicals are bearish and oversold.</p>
<p>Averages remain bearish, leading indicators are losing bearish momenteum, but lower than last week. The index will need to rally above 1,665 to concern the bears.</p>
<p>The index continues bouncing from support at 1,535. Now only five points above, traders are likely to be anxious to see if it bounces again. Initial resistance is at 1,575, but to reverse the short term falls, the index must trade out of the range.</p>
<p>Seven weeks in the range 1,535 to 1,610, and falling for some 14 months. Is this enough to suggest that some corrective movement is well overdue?</p>
<p>Seasoned traders are likely to exercise discipline. The trend is down in short/medium/long terms. They will continue to trade the range, trade with the trend, and only change strategies when there is confirmation of such a change.</p>
<p>(Daniel Fock is a member of the Australian Technical Analysts Association. Views are his own, not those of Reuters.)</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
