<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610484" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian rate cut surprises markets.</title>
<headline>Australian rate cut surprises markets.</headline>
<byline>John Mair</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) cut official interest rates by half a percent on Friday -- a move that surprised markets given the hawkish statements two weeks ago of the central bank governor.</p>
<p>Australia's official cash rate was cut by 0.5 percentage points to 5.5 percent. It was the fourth cut since last July and took rates to their lowest level since August 1994.</p>
<p>Official rates in Australia are now level with U.S. rates, the first time since September 1984, a move that immediately saw the local dollar sold off to a three-month low of US$0.7665.</p>
<p>The RBA had been under political pressure to cut rates, with the prime minister and treasurer arguing the 1997/98 budget released last week set the stage for lower rates.</p>
<p>After the announcement, Treasurer Peter Costello said domestic influences, including a good budget outcome, had allowed for the latest easing.</p>
<p>&quot;The domestic events gave us a unique window of opportunity and you've seen the reduction in interest rates as a consequence,&quot; Costello told reporters.</p>
<p>In justifying the cut, RBA Governor Ian Macfarlane said low inflation, some scope for faster economic growth and ongoing fiscal consolidation gave the bank room to ease.</p>
<p>&quot;The above considerations -- namely, inflation forecast to fall below two percent, and economic activity providing scope for further expansion -- amount to a prima facie case for an easing in policy,&quot; Macfarlane said in a statement.</p>
<p>Many in the market were surprised by the cut, while some did not agree with the RBA's reasons for easing.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a bit hard to make a case for this cut and I think the RBA's statement on the reasons was the weakest of the four so far,&quot; J.P. Morgan senior economist John Kyiakopoulos said.</p>
<p>The cut also represented a sharp turnaround from Macfarlane's comments two weeks ago to a parliamentary committee, when he said there was no economic gain to be had from another movement in official interest rates.</p>
<p>Rumours that Treasury Secretary Ted Evans, the government's representative on the RBA board, had been pushing for a rate cut had circulated financial markets in recent weeks.</p>
<p>Government ministers had also been saying the budget released last week had set the scene for lower rates.</p>
<p>&quot;I was a bit surprised because I would have thought you would have needed to see one of the big indicators fall in the hole,&quot; Axiom Funds Management senior economist Matthew Drennan.</p>
<p>&quot;At this point in the cycle a 50 point cut is a pretty big stimulus (to the economy),&quot; Drennan said.</p>
<p>But the final factor in the decision to cut rates appears to have been wages data released on Thursduay showing wages had not been rising as quickly as previously thought.</p>
<p>Annual average weekly ordinary time earnings rose 4.3 percent in the year to February, down from the preliminary figure of 4.6 percent reported earlier this month.</p>
<p>Wages growth of 4.5 percent is seen as the RBA's &quot;line in the sand&quot; above which it threatens the pursuit of low inflation.</p>
<p>&quot;Yesterday's wages data suggested that wage growth was not accelerating at an unacceptable pace,&quot; Colonial State Bank group economist Hans Kunnen said.</p>
<p>Kunnen had thought a rate cut was justified, but said given the RBA's public statements he was surprised at the decision.  </p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
