<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610488" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: RTRS-Australia stocks jump to new high on rate cut.</title>
<headline>RTRS-Australia stocks jump to new high on rate cut.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>-----------------(Snapshot 10.10 a.m./0010 GMT)----------------</p>
<p>AORD		 2565.5   +17.6   DJIA cl	7258.13   -32.56</p>
<p>SPI		  2566.0   +20.0   US 30yr cl	6.99    +0.03</p>
<p>10yrbond futs    92.415  +0.110   Gold NY 342.65 Lon fix 342.95</p>
<p>AUD     $0.7675 (Thu   $0.7830)   CRB Index cl  251.93    -0.44</p>
<p>NIKKEI	   19950.70  +73.31   FTSE cl	 4651.8    +9.8</p>
<p>S&amp;P500(Globex)   839.50   -0.75   NZSE40	 2308.21    +2.47</p>
<p>--------------------------(May 23)-----------------------------</p>
<p>*Stocks opened at a record high after the Reserve Bank moved to cut rates by 0.5 percentage points. Volume 33.5 million, value A$47.4 million, 384 stocks traded, 142 steady, 195 up, 47 down  </p>
<p>Australian stocks surged about a percent higher on Friday in celebration at surprise news of an official interest rate cut just before the market opened.</p>
<p>Banking stocks jumped over 1.5 percent in early trade, on expectations lower bond yields and the Reserve Bank's confidence about low inflation would rub off on this interest rate sensitive sector. Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd was the big winner, rising 17 cents or two percent to A$8.35, helping drive the All Ordinaries Index up 17.6 points to a record high 2,565.5, its third successive day of record highs.  </p>
<p>Brokers and analysts said the positive effect of the rate cut was compounded by the export boost from the subsequent one U.S. cent slump in the Australian dollar to US$0.7666/71.</p>
<p>&quot;It's been taken rather well by the market,&quot; said Bankers Trust Equities Strategist David Rees. &quot;The way in which the currency has reacted is a positive for the resources sector.&quot;</p>
<p>The All Resources Index jumped 10.9 points in early trade to 1,497.2, with BHP rising 16 cents early to A$19.36 and Rio Tinto Plc rising 20 cents to A$21.35.  </p>
<p>Analysts said the rate cut would reverberate across most sectors, with stocks senstive to domestic economic growth likely to be the next in line to be boosted after the banks.</p>
<p>&quot;It's clear that the objective of the rate cut is to re-stimulate the economy and that means that the growth sector like the building stocks are likely to be strongly supported,&quot; Rees said. The U.S. Federal Reserve's decision not to raise rates on Tuesday and the Dow's strength would also support the market over the next few days as the local rate cut was absorbed by investors, analysts said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The other positive in the background is that the Fed didn't raise rates which has made it easier for our market to adjust,&quot; Rees said.</p>
<p>&quot;If the Fed had raised rates on Tuesday and Wall had come off by five percent, that wouldn't have been a very strong background,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's all fallen into place rather nicely.&quot;</p>
<p>The strength in early trade was fairly widespread across the board, except for the still lanquishing gold sector, which was basically steady.  </p>
<p>-----------------------(TECHNICALS)----------------------------</p>
<p>Short-term range    Support   Restnce   RSI-14  MA-10  MA-20</p>
<p>AORD   2530/2570     2520	2575	78.78  2536   2516</p>
<p>SPI    2520/2570     2520	2575	67.64  2539   2522</p>
<p>------------------------KEY ACTIVES----------------------------</p>
<p>*NAB A$18.62 *(+0.17) 18.80/18.54 Vol: 961,336</p>
<p>*CBA A$14.18 (+0.09) 14.40/14.13 Vol: 738,036</p>
<p>*ANZ A$8.27 (+0.09) 8.42/8.22 Vol:2,011,074</p>
<p>*Westpac A$7.20 (-0.04) 7.40/7.19 Vol:3,069,290</p>
<p>Banks jump on rates cut, bond rally, low inflation outlook</p>
<p>*BHP A$19.20 (+0.05) 19.26/19.00 Vol:2,773.247  </p>
<p>*CRA A$21.33 (+0.23) 21.35/21.96 Vol:364,518</p>
<p>Resources firm as Australian dollar weakens on rate cut.</p>
<p>-- Bernard Hickey 61-2 9373-1812</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
