<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610475" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</title>
<headline>Australian Broadcasting Corp Afternoon Update.</headline>
<text>
<p>COSTELLO TAKES CREDIT FOR RATE CUT</p>
<p>The Federal Treasurer is taking credit for today's cut in interest rates saying it results from the Government's budget strategy.</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank has announced a half a percentage cut to the official cash rate, sparking reaction from at least four financial institutions.</p>
<p>The Commonwealth and ANZ Banks and Aussie Home Loans have dropped their variable home loan rates, and the Adelaide Bank has announced it's cutting its honeymoon home loan interest rate.</p>
<p>Treasurer Peter Costello says that by breaking the back of Commonwealth debt, the Government is setting up Australia for a long economic run.</p>
<p>But Federal Opposition Leader, Kim Beazley, says the Reserve Bank has come to the rescue of the Government, whose policies have stalled the economy.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>DISAGREEMENT OVER PROGRESS AT HEALTH MINISTER'S MEETING</p>
<p>There's disagreement among Federal and state health ministers about whether any progress was made at today's meeting on Medicare in Sydney.</p>
<p>A series of meetings should be held to negotiate a new Medicare agreement by next year.</p>
<p>Federal Minister, Dr Michael Wooldridge says there was some consensus on broad principles...which is also Queensland's position.</p>
<p>However New South Wales Minister, Dr Andrew Refshauge disagrees and says legal action by his state is still a possibility.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>ABORIGINAL LEADERS IN BATTLE OVER WIK PROPOSAL</p>
<p>The Deputy-Chairman of ATSIC says growing support of his proposal to exempt small family farms and pastoral holdings from native title claims shows the Aboriginal Social Justice Commissioner is out of touch.</p>
<p>ATSIC's Ray Robinson says Commissioner Mick Dodson is a fool for opposing his compromise plan on Wik.</p>
<p>Mr Robinson says his proposal now has the support of the Queensland Federation of Land Councils.</p>
<p>He says Mr Dodson's call to have him disciplined over the plan won't do any good because he's the highest elected Aboriginal in Australia and has the support of the majority of ATSIC's board of commissioners.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MINISTER PREDICTS VAST ECONOMIC IMPROVEMENT IN 1997/98</p>
<p>The Federal Industry Minister says Australians can look forward to a vastly improved economy in the next financial year. John Moore has told a Melbourne meeting that the growth forecast for the coming year had been raised to three-and-three quarter percent.</p>
<p>Mr Moore's welcomed the prospect of lower interest rates saying budget growth forcasts will be exceeded.</p>
<p>He says with the improvement of commodity prices, the advent of low interest rates and low inflation he's confident of a four per cent growth in GDP.</p>
<p>The Minister says as a flow on from that, there's be a pick up in employment.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>REPORTS OF CAR BUILDING PLAN</p>
<p>A plan which would favour South Australia's vehicle building industry, has reportedly been prepared by the head of the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet.</p>
<p>The speculation comes as the Federal government prepares to receive the Productivity Commission's final report on car tariffs.</p>
<p>The Financial Review says that, under the plan, imported car tariffs would be held at 15 per cent until 2005, and sales tax on all vehicles would be significantly reduced.</p>
<p>The South Australian Government, Opposition, unions and car makers, have all opposed a draft recommendation from the Productivity Commission to reduce tariffs to five per cent by 2004.</p>
<p>The State Opposition has welcomed the reports of the new plan.</p>
<p>But Opposition leader Mike Rann says that any plan must include the continuation of a strong export assistance scheme for car makers.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BIG CLASH IN WORLD TEAM TENNIS CUP TONIGHT</p>
<p>In tennis, at the World Team Cup in Germany tonight, Australia's Mark Philippoussis takes on Croatia's Goran Ivanisavic.</p>
<p>Set to be the biggest clash of the last round-robin matches, Philippoussis is predicting a tough game and says he won't rely solely on his serve to get him through.</p>
<p>In the single's bout, Todd Woodbridge is replacing Mark Woodforde who's had some tough matches this week, against Sasa Hirszon.</p>
<p>And the woodies will then team up for the doubles.</p>
<p>Australia will be guaranteed of a place in the final if it beats Croatia, but coach Tony Roche says it will be tough going. Last September Australia beat Croatia in the Davis Cup.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
