<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610458" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Southern Electric firms on bid speculation.</title>
<headline>Southern Electric firms on bid speculation.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares in Southern Electric Plc firmed in pre-market trading on Friday, after newspaper reports raised speculation of a bid from power generator PowerGen Plc.</p>
<p>Southern shares were quoted up 5p at 416 by 0713 GMT, though no volume was recorded in the stock, while PowerGen was up 2-1/2p at 696-1/2 in volume of 155,000 shares.  </p>
<p>PowerGen, which last year was blocked by the government from bidding for Southern's fellow regional electricity company (REC) Midlands Electricity on anti-competitive grounds, is still smarting from the surprise ruling which sent its shares plunging.</p>
<p>The group's chief executive and chairman Ed Wallis was quoted as saying that while the company would still consider buying a REC, it was too early to say whether the new Labour Government had the same view as the former Conservative government that vetoed its bid.</p>
<p>The Financial Times said Wallis indicated no urgency, although he did say the company was looking for a big acquisition.</p>
<p>PowerGen, which reported near top-of-the-range annual results on Thursday, has a robust balance sheet with negligible debt.</p>
<p>It's shares, which have risen around a third since last October, rose 4.0p to 698p in the first few minutes of trade, near it's year high of 701.</p>
<p>Southern Electric declined to comment on any bid hints, noting that it did not wish to add to market speculation.</p>
<p>Southern is the last remaining independent REC after its 11 peers were snapped up in a bidding frenzy that began in earnest in 1995 and lasted over one year.</p>
<p>-- London Newsroom +44 171 542 4366</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
