<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610409" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - British Business - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - British Business - May 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>DAILY TELEGRAPH</p>
<p>-- F1 ANALYSTS FLY TO SEE GRAND PRIX</p>
<p>Salomon Brothers, co-ordinator of the floatation of Formula One, is to fly analysts who have to assess whether investors should subscribe for shares to Barcelona to watch the Grand Prix. Only analysts from the underwriting syndicate have been invited and no financial information will be made available. Analysts include those from Morgan Stanley, Deutsche Morgan Grenfell, SBC Warburg , Merrill Lynch, NatWest Markets, BZW and Nikko.</p>
<p>-- LEGAL ACTION THREAT IN INTERFLORA DISPUTE</p>
<p>The new board of Directors of Interflora, the flower delivery service, say that after advice from the Queen's Council they shall not carry out a postal vote on their election. Chairman Geoff Hughes said he hopes members will appreciate that the board needs to act on advice given to it. The old board says they will canvass the view of members and will issue a writ demanding a ballot if enough support exists for one.</p>
<p>-- SKETCHLEY INVESTORS TARGET CHIEF EXECUTIVE</p>
<p>Institutional shareholders, led by PDFM, M&amp;G and Prudential, are putting pressure on John Jackson, chief executive of Sketchley. They argue that Jackson should take ultimate responsibility after the discovery of &quot;accounting deficiencies&quot; related to finance director Richard Mayers. Meanwhile, the audit committee is meeting to establish a precise estimate of the loss the company will report for the year to March.</p>
<p>THE TIMES</p>
<p>-- BROWN'S TREATMENT OF GOVERNOR PROMPTS ANGER IN CITY</p>
<p>Senior City bankers have admitted to being angry at the way Eddie George, governor of the Bank of England, has been treated by the government, and insist that he should not resign. George was angered by being told of changes at the bank only 24 hours in advance. Chairman of NatWest Bank group, Lord Alexander, and chief executive of Abbey National, Peter Birch, said George had been an outstanding governor.</p>
<p>-- BECKETT OVERRULES OFT ON RAILWAY FRANCHISES</p>
<p>Margaret Beckett, president of the Board of Trade, has overruled the director-general of fair trading, John Bridgeman, by referring the award of two train franchises to National Express, the largest railway operator, to the Monopolies and Mergers Commission. This is the first time for six years a deal has been referred to the MMC against the director-general's advice. A spokeswoman said he is not considering resigning.</p>
<p>-- CBI FORECASTS 3.1 PERCENT GROWTH AND SEVEN PERCENT RATES</p>
<p>The Confederation of British Industry predicts that Britain could be entering two years of economic growth. However, the newly independent Bank of England could raise interest rates to seven percent to prevent rising inflation. The outlook is backed by official data showing strong retail sales growth and above-trend GDP growth. The quarterly forecast for GDP growth has increased to 3.1 percent this year.</p>
<p>THE GUARDIAN</p>
<p>-- NATIONWIDE CLASH WORRIES SOCIETY BOSSES</p>
<p>The Nationwide has been accused by leaders of other mutuals of threatening the demise of the mutual movement with its strategy of confronting rebels who want to turn it into a bank. They are worried that the high-risk strategy could backfire and lead to the demise of the remaining 71 societies. It has also emerged that the building society watchdog may intervene to block attempts to force a flotation of the Nationwide.</p>
<p>-- VIRGIN MISSES THE BOAT</p>
<p>The Virgin Group has rejected the offer to run the QE2, the flagship of Cunard. The QE2 and four other Cunard ships have no long-term future under Kvaerner, the Anglo-Norwegian construction and ship-building group. Shares of Kvaerner rose by three percent on the news of the possible sell. Virgin doubted that the QE2 was capable of making much money, saying it had only five years of sailing ahead and was expensive to run.</p>
<p>-- POWERGEN READY TO TEST BLAIR</p>
<p>PowerGen, the electricity generator, is preparing to bid for a regional electricity company, a moved that was banned by the former Conservative Government. This comes as PowerGen announces a 16 percent fall in per-tax profits. Chairman Ed Wallis said the company is to look closely at buying a Rec, even though it is achieving its strategy by other means. He said it remains unclear if the new Labour Government would block any takeover.</p>
<p>THE INDEPENDENT</p>
<p>-- BOEING REJECTS EUROPE'S COMPLAINTS ON MERGER</p>
<p>Boeing has rejected the European Commission's objections to its 14-billion-dollar-merger with McDonnell Douglas, the rival US aircraft manufacturer, saying it remained confident the deal would be completed in the summer. This comes after Karel Van Miert, the EU commissioner for competition, issued a formal statement of objections concerned with the commercial power the merged group would have to dictate terms to airline customers and disadvantage Airbus Industrie, its European rival.</p>
<p>-- US LEGAL RULING HITS REED SHARES</p>
<p>Shares in Anglo-Dutch media group, Reed Elsevier, have fallen on fears that the company would suffer from news that rival legal publisher West Publishing lost much of its copyright protection in a federal court ruling. Reed was also affected by a downgrade of shares by analysts at Merrill Lynch. Reed's chief financial officer, Mark Armour, said the impact on the company would not be significant.</p>
<p>-- STOREHOUSE TO OPEN MORE BHS BRANCHES</p>
<p>The BhS and Mothercare retailer, Storehouse, is set to create 1,000 jobs this year as it begins a 120 million stg investment programme. It plans to open six new branches of BhS and four branches of Mothercare. This comes as Storehouse announces a 16.7 percent increase in full-year profits. The company also admitted to a series of management mistakes and having too many unmodernised stores and out-of-date systems.</p>
<p>BMC +44-171-377-1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
