<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610401" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: PRESS DIGEST - GREEK FINANCIAL NEWS- MAY 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - GREEK FINANCIAL NEWS- MAY 23.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Leading stories in the Greek financial press:</p>
<p>KATHIMERINI</p>
<p>--The government yesterday begged to differ from the recent International Monetary Fund and OECD reports on changes needed to the job markets and social security system . Senior government officials said that the reports would have no influence on social dialogue between government, unions and employers on finding common ground on changes to the labour market and pensions.</p>
<p>--Interest on annual Treasury bills available June 2 will be 9.6 percent while a three-, five- and seven-year bonds will be auctioned on June 19. </p>
<p>--The general price index closed in on the all-time record yesterday with an increase of 2.74 percent to close at 1,683.85 points.  </p>
<p>IMERISIA</p>
<p>--The government is examining two alternate proposals on how to save its revenues, given a European Court ruling against Greece on the extra charges it imposes on imported secondhand cars is almost certain.</p>
<p>--The low returns from deposits are steering ever more investors to the stock exchange for increased returns, but a significant number of orders are coming from institutional investors from Greece and abroad.</p>
<p>--OTE, Greece's telecoms organisation, expectes improved returns from the increased rate of digitalisation of the oOTE network, according to a confidential report from the administration for prospective investors.</p>
<p>KERDOS</p>
<p>--The finance ministry will soon release new details about the taxpaying public, culled from cross-checks by the new TAXIS programme being implemented at the ministry's taxation services. Sources said the ministry would reveal that some taxpayers hold up to three tax identification numbers (AFMs) and that names of people and companies would be released.</p>
<p>--The collection of taxes for the real estate tax will begin as of September 15, according the finane ministry.</p>
<p>NAFTEMBORIKI</p>
<p>--The National Bank says there is almost twice as much demand for OTE's shares in its coming second public offer than there are shares. The high demand in the domestic market may mean that a portion of the shares destined for abroad be allocated to Greece. </p>
<p>EXPRESS</p>
<p>--New pensions for public servants will not be reduced, but will have &quot;differentiated increases&quot;, according to Deputy Finance Minister Nikos Christodoulakis. --Maria Petrakis, Athens Newsroom +301 3311812-4</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
