<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610469" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - British eco-warrior Swampy burrows on in protest.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - British eco-warrior Swampy burrows on in protest.</headline>
<byline>Catherine Bremer</byline>
<dateline>MANCHESTER, England 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swampy, a scrawny environmental activist, turned into a media star in Britain when he left his comfortable middle-class home for a grimy tunnel below a planned new road in southwest England.</p>
<p>His seven-day underground stint to delay construction of the Devon bypass hiked costs by around 700,000 pounds ($1.2 million) and was hailed as a victory by protesters who say other developments have been shelved as a result.</p>
<p>This month the 23-year-old &quot;human mole&quot; burrowed underneath the site of a proposed new runway at Manchester Airport in northwest England, where the present runway is creaking under a rising demand for air travel.</p>
<p>Environmentalists say the two-mile (three-km) second runway, will destroy 1,000 acres (400 hectares) of precious woodland, kill wildlife, and worsen air pollution.</p>
<p>Police launched an operation to evict the protesters from the site this week, removing some from treehouses they had built. Others are still hiding out in tunnels beneath the proposed runway, preventing the start of construction work.</p>
<p>Swampy -- real name Daniel Hooper -- was not around  when the evictions began but Reuters managed to track him down for an interview at the runway site earlier this month.</p>
<p>SWAMPY SAYS FAME CAME BY ACCIDENT</p>
<p>With green eyes standing out from a mud-flecked face and matted hair and wearing a stripey jumper damp with earth, Swampy gave credence to his nickname.</p>
<p>A notably shy celebrity, Swampy joked that his now famous week underground had happened by accident.</p>
<p>&quot;I just got stuck in my tunnel for a week and couldn't get out, and now I'm famous,&quot; he quipped.</p>
<p>Swampy's rise to fame has spotlighted a growing number of anti-road protest camps springing up across Britain, where concern is mounting over pollution caused by emissions from cars and aeroplanes.</p>
<p>Some activists even risk their lives, chaining themselves to trees as they are about to be felled. They say extreme action is the only way to force corporates and local government to shelve environmentally harmful developments.</p>
<p>In Manchester, Swampy spent most of his time in his underground bunker, eluding a daily stream of journalists and teenage fans.</p>
<p>But Reuters caught him when he emerged to take part in a bizarre ritual at the 10-foot (three-metre)) high fence security guards had erected around the camp.</p>
<p>In a daily routine, a van brought food, water and material to build shelters, donated by local supporters.</p>
<p>A dozen protesters leapt into action, hurling insults as they charged through security guards and attempt to shove the gear over the fence into the camp.</p>
<p>Fluorescent jackets spattered with mud, the guards pushed them back and a tug of war battle began.</p>
<p>But nobody got hurt.</p>
<p>Instead, the guards chased the demonstrators into the wooded valley amid shrieks of laughter, and it became clear the animosity was a display put on for a cluster of television cameras on a nearby hilltop.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of the guards are OK, they're just doing their job,&quot; said Swampy, adding that some secretly supported the protest. &quot;But it's a waste of our time and theirs, and it's taxpayers' money that's paying for it.&quot;</p>
<p>SWAMPY'S FAME BOOSTS SUPPORT FOR PROTESTERS</p>
<p>Despite a recent television appearance on a quiz show that revealed a shaky knowledge of politics, Swampy's rise to fame has boosted national support for environmental action groups and earned much needed cash for the Manchester campaign, which relies largely on donations from the public.</p>
<p>Splashed across newspapers and magazines in recent weeks, his cherubic face has boosted the image of green activists, who put environmental concerns before their own safety and comfort.</p>
<p>&quot;Obviously we'd rather have more focus on the issue, but Swampy's become a bit of a national hero and that hasn't done us any harm,&quot; said one campaigner, whose climbing harness identified her as a tree-dweller.</p>
<p>An air of jealousy could almost be felt at &quot;Cliff Richard Camp&quot;, when Swampy proudly showed off a newly-acquired scarlet coat which covered his battered anorak and mud-spattered green boots.</p>
<p>&quot;It's Armani,&quot; he joked, a reference to when he recently modelled a selection of designer suits, earning himself enough money to pay off a 500 pound court fine.</p>
<p>However, if his fellow protesters secretly begrudge Swampy his star image, they are starting to realise that having a high-profile campaign mascot is extremely useful.</p>
<p>&quot;The whole Swampy thing has trivialised the campaign but the good thing is we're making money out of it,&quot; said a central figure at the Coalition Against Runway Two (CAR2) headquarters who called himself 'Smurf'.</p>
<p>TV AND COLUMNS MEAN CASH FOR SWAMPY</p>
<p>With a tidy sum from his television appearance and 550 pounds a week during a brief spell as a columist for a Sunday tabloid, Swampy is coining in far more cash than most protesters, reliant on state benefits or busking.</p>
<p>And his popularity has encouraged Manchester residents to support the CAR2 campaigners to the point of recharging batteries and offering hot baths.</p>
<p>CAR2 protesters moved on to the site in February, soon after construction firms Amec and Tarmac won the contract to build Britain's first major runway for 20 years.</p>
<p>Numbers swelled to well over a hundred, some lodged in a web of subterranean tunnels, some perched in treehouses connected by ropes, and the less adventurous in more conventional shelters made from plastic sheets.</p>
<p>Claiming &quot;noisy protest, silent victory&quot; they say that, while the protest may not stop the runway going ahead, it will deter to any future projects.</p>
<p>&quot;Now, when the authorities consider chopping down trees to build a motorway, they think 'Oh no, we're going to have those raggle-taggle protestors hanging around costing us money', so certain schemes won't even get off the ground,&quot; said one.</p>
<p>But Manchester Airport Chairman Graham Stringer is defiant.</p>
<p>&quot;The second runway will be built,&quot; he told Reuters in an interview, &quot;it will just cost a bit more money.&quot;</p>
<p>He would not say what the 30 or so full-time security guards cost, but admitted: &quot;It is costing a lot.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANCHESTER, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
