<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610410" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: PRESS DIGEST - Financial Times - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Financial Times - May 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>Prepared for Reuters by The Broadcast Monitoring Company</p>
<p>-- RETAIL SECTOR STEAMS AHEAD BUT EXPORTERS FACE STRUGGLE</p>
<p>The Office of National Statistics has unveiled its latest figures, which reveal the volume of UK retail sales rose 4.7 per cent in the year to April, the highest rise since 1989. In contrast, The Confederation of British Industry reported that the strength of sterling and weak demand from continental Europe was wreaking havoc on the export sector, with orders in May their lowest since November 1993.</p>
<p>-- POWERGEN CHIEF SAYS BUMPY RIDE AHEAD</p>
<p>Ed Wallis, chairman of Britain's second biggest power generator, PowerGen, has revealed that the government will go ahead with electricity sector liberalisation in 1998, despite the problems posed by the move. Electricity industry regulator Professor Stephen Littlechild has appointed industry and energy minister John Battle as his advisor on the progress of liberalisation and said though April 1998 remains the start date he is 'looking very carefully at the situation'.</p>
<p>-- VODAFONE AND QUALCOMM IN QUEST FOR 'WORLD PHONE'</p>
<p>The leading British mobile phone operator, Vodafone, and Qualcomm of the U.S. have teamed up to conduct a series of trials hoped to result in the creation of a 'world phone' which could be used in the U.S., Europe or Asia. Such a phone would combine the best qualities of Europe's GSM standard and CDMA, its U.S. rival, but it is believed that America's CDMA is the better system and would prove superior. Using software from the UK's Technology Partnership consultancy, the handsets will most likely be be modified Qualcomm phones.</p>
<p>-- ONE-2-ONE SAYS NEW TARIFF PACKAGES 'NOT PRICE WAR'</p>
<p>One-2-One, the smallest UK mobile telephone operator, has declared that its introduction of a new price package is not intended to be the beginning of a price war. The package, which offers free minutes of talk time within the monthly fee, would only include voice mail and message retrieval features and is an attempt to revive a One-2-One business still struggling after a disastrous launch offer which resulted in the loss of significant revenues.</p>
<p>-- GRANADA RULES OUT TV DEMERGER</p>
<p>Granada, the hotels, catering, rental and television group, has ruled out a demerger of its television interests following a detailed review of the company's structure. The group is now to concentrate on building up its television arm and redoubling efforts to expand internationally. Granada is also in talks which could lead to the sale of its computer services operation, which the group values at about 80 million stg.</p>
<p>-- REED ELSEVIER SHARES DROP ON US LEGAL RULING</p>
<p>Shares in Reed International fell 18p to 607.5p on Thursday as investors considered the implications of a U.S. judicial ruling on the copyright of legal texts. Analysts at Merrill Lynch downgraded the stock, while a report in the New York Times raised doubts over the future of the Lexis-Nexis database of Reed Elsevier, the Anglo-Dutch information and media subsidiary. Reed Elsevier itself insisted that the ruling, which could reduce copyright protection for Lexis-Nexis, would have a 'minimal effect' on the company.</p>
<p>-- SCOT POWER GETS GAS LICENCE</p>
<p>Glasgow-based multi-utility Scottish Power has said it has been granted a gas transporter licence by industry regulator Ofgas. The licence allows Scottish Power to install gas pipelines to new housing and industrial developments. Duncan Whyte, executive director at Scottish Power, said the licence &quot;allows us to compete for new business in an expanding market for both large and small scale gas installation&quot;.</p>
<p>-- CELSIS CONFIDENT AS SALES GROWTH POINTS TO PROFIT</p>
<p>Celsis International, a UK biotechnology-based company, has reported a doubling in turnover following the takeover last year of Dutch group Lumac. Celsis, which develops and makes hygiene monitoring equipment, saw sales rise from 5.2 million stg to 8.3 million stg. Lumac, a quality control group, contributed 2.8 million stg in the second half.</p>
<p>-- OLIVETTI SEEKS STRATEGIC INVESTORS</p>
<p>Olivetti, the troubled Italian information technology group, has said it is seeking strategic investors to help its longer-term recovery, although the company has ruled out a new capital increase. The news came at the launch of the latest stage in the recovery strategy of new chief executive Roberto Colaninno, who presented to international customers the group's new information technology systems and solutions subsidiary, renamed Olsy.</p>
<p>-- J&amp;J IN $310 MILLION BUY</p>
<p>U.S. consumer and healthcare products group Johnson &amp; Johnson has announced it has reached a definitive agreement to acquire Biopsys Medical, a developer and manufacturer of products for diagnosing and treating breast cancer. The stock swap deal has been valued at $310 million.</p>
<p>For a full range of news monitoring services, phone BMC +44-171-377-1742</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
