<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610440" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: INSIGHT - Downside bias to notionnel,prop at 128.88.</title>
<headline>INSIGHT - Downside bias to notionnel,prop at 128.88.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>June notionnel futures on the MATIF are biased to the downside on Friday, but should glean some support from 128.88, technical analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The market will be very quiet today,&quot; said Philippe Cahen, technical analyst at Credit Lyonnais in Paris. &quot;On a 30-minute basis, there's good support at 128.88 which is the lower Bollinger band.&quot;</p>
<p>Cahen put first resistance on a 30-minute basis at 129.28.</p>
<p>Bollinger bands are lines drawn at standard deviations around the price action to give support and resistance.  </p>
<p>Cahen said the market was not yet oversold on an hourly or daily basis, making it difficult to crack strong resistance at 129.46 -- the upper Bollinger band. &quot;In the longer term, the market could go towards 128.00,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Richard Adcock, technical research manager at HSBC Futures here, said the penetration of the uptrend channel opened the way for a fresh bear leg in the notionnel market.</p>
<p>&quot;We set initial targets at 128.00 but stress that it is likely further weakness will be seen over the longer term to test in due course, the early April lows down to 127.00, which we set as our longer term objective,&quot; he said in a note.  </p>
<p>Adcock said short term rallies were possible, but with these set to be capped up to 129.40, they offered selling opportunities.</p>
<p>By 0822 GMT, June Pibor was up two basis points at 96.49. Adcock said the chances were, further weakness would develop over the next few days to test the critical support offered by the May 22 low at 96.45.</p>
<p>&quot;If moves under this point materialise, a failure of the strength will be signalled suggesting retests of the lows,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
