<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610485" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: OPINION-Jim Middleton's Canberra Closeup - Taxing times.</title>
<headline>OPINION-Jim Middleton's Canberra Closeup - Taxing times.</headline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Jim Middleton (ABC TV Political Correspondent)</p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard may not look anything like Paul Keating and he hates any comparison with the man he vanquished.</p>
<p>But every now and then the prime minister uses tactics straight out of the Keating textbook.</p>
<p>Back in 1992, when the coalition was hounding John Dawkins over unauthorised loan approvals by the Kirner government, Keating devised one of the great political diversions of recent time.</p>
<p>Not only was it the occasion on which he branded the Senate &quot;unrepresentative swill&quot; but also -- taking his heart in his hands -- declared that if John Hewson won the 1993 election Labor would allow his goods and services tax (GST) through the Upper House.</p>
<p>Uproar ensued -- the coalition (with the notable exception of Howard) fell about in self-congratulation, Labor backbenchers looked like they'd seen a ghost, but any further pursuit of Dawkins was forgotten in the hubbub.</p>
<p>Later, Keating -- with his usual sense of metaphor -- described what he'd done as getting a big hunk of smelly meat, throwing it into the distance and watching the coalition hounds pursue it, having put them off the Dawkins scent.</p>
<p>It was quite a graphic demonstration -- arm movements and all.</p>
<p>Whether Howard is depicting his re-ignition of the tax debate in similar terms has yet to be revealed, but that's what it was -- a big hunk of smelly meat hurled out in the wake of a budget which has satisfied none of his key constituencies -- the battlers, big business or small business.</p>
<p>Talkback hosts -- notably Alan Jones -- were antagonistic to the savings rebate, a clear sign their battler audience didn't think much of it either.</p>
<p>Howard's extraordinary decision to declare a &quot;Do It Yourself&quot; means test didn't help either, inadvertently boosting Labor's argument that it's an unnecessary gift to the rich rather than a tax break for the needy.</p>
<p>Business condemned the budget's caution, stinging Howard who took any example of corporate criticism as a personal affront.</p>
<p>By Sunday, he'd decided enough was enough -- threw caution to the winds and clambered back on the tax cart he'd abandoned in 1995.</p>
<p>Then he'd declared the coalition would &quot;never&quot; embrace a GST. On the Seven Network's Face to Face programme, though, he was asked whether his tax reform programme would include a GST.</p>
<p>His answer: &quot;You can't have reform unless you look at all the options.&quot; Code for &quot;Yes.&quot;</p>
<p>Howard advisers insist the prime minister did have a process and a timetable in mind when he let the tax cat out of the bag. Also that he'd discussed the handling of tax with his senior colleagues.</p>
<p>At least one cabinet minister, though, suggested the whole thing was spur of the moment improvisation.</p>
<p>He also raised the traditional fears about managing the tax debate.</p>
<p>No government, he claimed, which had introduced a consumption tax had won the subsequent election.</p>
<p>(Not quite: de Gaulle was secure in France after bringing in VAT in the early 60s; Margaret Thatcher went on to win two more elections after doing the same in Britain.)</p>
<p>The prime minister's minders also say Howard was always going to have to address the tax question before the next election, and about 18 months out was the appropriate time.</p>
<p>Another political goal -- according to the sources -- is to box the ALP.</p>
<p>The government fears Labor's campaign stategy will be to spend the proceeds of the &quot;coalition's&quot; budget surplus.</p>
<p>Thus, they say, Howard's gambit was designed to force Labor to come clean on tax.</p>
<p>As it turned out, opposition treasury spokesman Gareth Evans came a bit too clean -- suggesting on Monday that Labor would be prepared to &quot;look&quot; at a GST if it could be shown to be fair and equitable.</p>
<p>Not the Beazley line, at all.</p>
<p>But the opposition leader claims to be pleased, too.</p>
<p>He thinks the contributions on a GST of Howard and Treasurer Peter Costello have liberated Labor in its handling of the tax hot potato -- that what the prime minister has done is to open up the tax options for the ALP.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there's big danger for the coaliton in failing to direct the tax debate.</p>
<p>The debate can now throw up all manner of expectatoins Howard will be incapable of satisfying.</p>
<p>The follow-up from Howard and Costello has hardly been tidy.</p>
<p>So untidy Kim Beazley believes, the coalition has opened the way for Labor to develop its own tax agenda -- without a GST, of course.</p>
<p>That's the trouble with diversions -- they can develop a life of their own, a life beyond their instigators' control.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Canberra Bureau 61-6 273-2730</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
