<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610479" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian rate cut sees local dollar sell-off.</title>
<headline>Australian rate cut sees local dollar sell-off.</headline>
<byline>John Mair</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) cut official interest rates by half a percent on Friday -- a move that surprised markets given the hawkish statements two weeks ago of the central bank governor.</p>
<p>Australia's official cash rate was cut by 0.5 percentage points to 5.5 percent. It was the fourth cut since last July and took rates to their lowest level since August 1994.</p>
<p>The Australian dollar plummeted a full U.S. cent on the cut to close at US$0.7680, as official rates in Australia are now level with U.S. rates for the first time since September 1984.</p>
<p>The surprise rate cut also saw the Australian stock market rise to a record high and bonds rally, but not as much as might have been expected as profit taking capped the market.</p>
<p>In the share market, the All Ordinaries index reached a record high of 2,572.7 in the first hour of trade after the announcement, but ended the day slightly lower at 2,563.9.</p>
<p>While the benchmark 10-year bond ended at 7.57 percent, down 11 points on the day, although at one stage traded under 7.50 percent for the first time since February.</p>
<p>The RBA had been under political pressure to cut rates, with the prime minister and treasurer arguing the 1997/98 budget released last week set the stage for lower rates.</p>
<p>After the announcement, Treasurer Peter Costello said domestic influences, including a good budget outcome, had allowed for the latest easing.</p>
<p>&quot;The domestic events gave us a unique window of opportunity and you've seen the reduction in interest rates as a consequence,&quot; Costello told reporters.</p>
<p>In justifying the cut, RBA Governor Ian Macfarlane said low inflation, some scope for faster economic growth and ongoing fiscal consolidation gave the bank room to ease.</p>
<p>&quot;The above considerations -- namely, inflation forecast to fall below two percent, and economic activity providing scope for further expansion -- amount to a prima facie case for an easing in policy,&quot; Macfarlane said in a statement.</p>
<p>But many in the market were surprised by the cut, while some did not agree with the RBA's reasons for easing.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a bit hard to make a case for this cut and I think the RBA's statement on the reasons was the weakest of the four so far,&quot; J.P. Morgan senior economist John Kyiakopoulos said.</p>
<p>The cut also represented a sharp turnaround from Macfarlane's comments two weeks ago to a parliamentary committee, when he said there was no economic gain to be had from another movement in official interest rates.</p>
<p>Macfarlane also warned the committee of the dangers posed by high wages growth, which could fuel inflation, a sign markets interpreted as meaning no rate cut was imminent.</p>
<p>However, rumours that Treasury Secretary Ted Evans, the government's representative on the RBA board, had been pushing for a rate cut had circulated financial markets in recent weeks.</p>
<p>Government ministers had also been saying the budget released last week had set the scene for lower rates.</p>
<p>Bankers Trust interest rate strategist Rory Robertson, one of the few to expect a cut, said the market failed to appreciate the bank's tendency to overstate the danger of wages.</p>
<p>&quot;Highlighting the upside risks and jaw-boning (pressuring) wage negotiators can be regarded as part of the role of central bankers. Markets need to look behind the rhetoric,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Robertson said that while Macfarlane had sounded warnings on inflation, the RBA did not change its forecast that underlying inflation would remain in the two to three percent target range through 1998, suggesting confidence wages would not blow out.</p>
<p>In fact, the final factor in the decision to cut rates appears to have been wages data released on Thursduay, which showed wages had not been rising as quickly as thought.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
