<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610562" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: ASIAN EXOTICS - Rupiah soft on last campaign day.</title>
<headline>ASIAN EXOTICS - Rupiah soft on last campaign day.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>* Indonesian rupiah slips in cautious trade on last campaign day for May 29 election.</p>
<p>* Malaysian ringgit slips back into range after easing to 2.5055 early on stop-loss dollar buying in Sydney.</p>
<p>* Thai baht subdued as restrictions on lending baht to offshore parties remain. Market awaits cue from central bank.</p>
<p>* Singapore dollar recovers on dollar/yen drop.</p>
<p>The Indonesian rupiah weakened in cautious trade on Friday, the last day of campaigning for the May 29 general election.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is biddish on the dollar. People are rather worried about possible disturbances on the final campaign day,&quot; a Japanese bank dealer in Jakarta said.</p>
<p>Dealers said the fears resulted from the minority United Development Party's (PPP) campaign schedule in Java, including Jakarta, where there is potential for violence.</p>
<p>Spot rupiah was quoted at 2,443.0/44.0 at 0405 GMT against an opening of 2,440.0/42.0.</p>
<p>&quot;Operators are a bit nervous. I think any news of violence could spark off a slew of rupiah selling,&quot; another dealer said.</p>
<p>He said longer-term swaps were on an uptrend due to uncertainty over the election campaign.</p>
<p>Dealers said operators were concerned about the possibility of tight liquidity at the open due to the central bank's neutral money market operation on Friday.</p>
<p>But an easing of overnight money to 10.0/11.0 percent from 12.0/15.0 percent prompted some dollar purchases.</p>
<p>In Malaysia, the ringgit settled into a tight range after easing to around 2.5055 against the dollar in early trade, as Sydney players went for stop-loss orders, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;There was more action in Sydney, where players were going for stops since the market was a little short of dollars,&quot; said one U.S. bank dealer in Singapore.</p>
<p>He said Kuala Lumpur corporates were still keen to sell dollars, but were only likely to do so around the 2.5050-2.5100 levels. The ringgit was at 2.5020/25 to the dollar at 0405 GMT.</p>
<p>Dealers said the ringgit was now trading in a new range of 2.4950 to 2.5100 against the dollar as swap rates and domestic interest rates in Malaysia had started falling.</p>
<p>The Singapore dollar regained some ground as the dollar/yen came off, but dealers said the U.S. unit looked well bid below the 1.4300 level on fears of intervention by the de facto central bank.</p>
<p>&quot;For the time being, 1.4300 will be supported unless the dollar/yen collapses again,&quot; the U.S. bank dealer said.</p>
<p>The Thai baht was subdued in both domestic and foreign markets as central bank restrictions on lending short-term baht to offshore players remained in place.</p>
<p>Dealers said the baht was hovering around the central bank's mid-rate of 25.79 to the dollar in domestic markets but trading well below the fixing overseas.</p>
<p>Bank of Thailand (BOT) governor Rerngchai Marakanond said late on Thursday the central bank would maintain its ban on baht lending by Thai financial institutions to offshore players until the situation normalised for the Thai currency.</p>
<p>The central bank measure has created two dollar/baht rates for offshore and onshore markets since it was imposed last week, after the baht came under severe offshore speculative attack.</p>
<p>&quot;There's not much interest in the Thai baht any more because of these restrictions. There's been no interbank market for the dollar/baht in Singapore for the last three days,&quot; the U.S. bank dealer in Singapore said.</p>
<p>&quot;Everything's going through the brokers and the volumes are quite small,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said players were waiting to see whether the BOT would give in to mounting pressure from political and business quarters to lower the discount rate.</p>
<p>&quot;If they do lower domestic interest rates, they'll probably leave these restrictions for some time because lowering the rate could invite people to attack the baht again,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Madhav Reddy in KL (603-201 4813), Mantik Kusjanto in Jakarta (6221 384-6364), Anuchit Nguyen in Bangkok (662) 652-0642 and Sonali Desai in Singapore (65-8703090)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
