<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610534" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian man pleads for return of kidnapped wife.</title>
<headline>Australian man pleads for return of kidnapped wife.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The husband of a wealthy Australian woman kidnapped 17 days ago begged for her return and told his wife not to give up hope in a videotape released by police on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I will do whatever (the kidnappers) ask and will go anywhere to ensure the safety of my wife,&quot; millionaire businessman Bernard Whelan said in the video.</p>
<p>&quot;Kerry, if you can hear what I am saying, I want you to know we all love you, we will do anything to get you back but, most of all, do not give up,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Kerry Whelan, a 39-year-old mother of three, was last seen leaving her car in an underground carpark in the western Sydney suburb of Parramatta on May 6.</p>
<p>She was wearing several gold and diamond rings and bracelets, including one bracelet boasting 20 diamonds.</p>
<p>Police and her husband said on Wednesday they held grave fears for her safety because there had been no contact with her abductors since a deadline for their unspecified ransom demands had expired.</p>
<p>Police, who had previously kept Whelan's kidnapping secret, said the abductors had made several ransom demands for &quot;a substantial sum of money&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
