<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610550" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian dlr down a cent in wake of RBA easing.</title>
<headline>Australian dlr down a cent in wake of RBA easing.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian dollar extended its losses to a full cent in the wake of a surprise cut in Reserve Bank official cash rates to 5.5 percent from 6.0 percent.</p>
<p>By 10.15 am (0015 GMT) the dollar was down at US$0.7670/75, its lowest level since mid-February, from an early US$0.7770/75.</p>
<p>It had already tumbled from US$0.7830/35 overnight on press reports the RBA was considering an easing following domestic wages data released on Thursday.</p>
<p>But much of the market had reckoned policy would stay steady this year and analysts felt offshore investors could well be discouraged by the dollar's disappearing interest differential.  </p>
<p>&quot;For the first time in 13 or 14 years Australian short term rates are down at the same level as those in the U.S. and the relative risk/reward of investing in Australia has probably diminished somewhat,&quot; said Stephen Koukoulas, chief economist at Citibank Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;Therefore the currency's falling and probably has a little bit further to go,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Support was seen in the US$0.7650/60 area and again at US$0.7635 and US$0.7620, where a 23-month old trendline rests.</p>
<p>On the crosses the dollar sank to 88.86/96 yen from 90.50/60 late here Thursday and to 1.2955/67 marks from 1.3214/26.  </p>
<p>The RBA justified the cut by pointing to final March quarter wages data released Thursday which showed annual average weekly earnings growth revised back to 4.3 percent, below the bank's danger zone of 4.5-5.0 percent.</p>
<p>The initial figures had shown a jump to 4.6 percent from 3.8 percent in Q4 and led RBA governor Ian Macfarlane to call the figures a setback to the inflation outlook and declare there was no economic benefit in another rate cut.</p>
<p>Now, just a couple of weeks later, the Bank said its assessment was the current pace of growth of labour costs had shown sufficient moderation to permit a further easing.  </p>
<p>Some analysts had problems with this argument.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a bit hard to make a case for this cut and I think the RBA's statement on the reasons was the weakest of the four so far,&quot; said John Kyriakopoulos, senior economist at J.P. Morgan Australia.</p>
<p>The Bank cut three times in the second half of last year bringing official cash rates down from 7.5 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;The risk is that with wages bottomed around four percent and the dollar -- which has helped so much in bringing inflation down -- likely to come under pressure the next policy tightening may have actually been brought forward a little,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Some of that concern seemed to have seeped through to the bond market where the curve steepened as the long end wondered if today's move was perhaps not too stimulative.</p>
<p>The short end had no worries and romped ahead with yields on one and two year bonds falling as much as 25 basis points below their U.S. counterparts.</p>
<p>The RBA's cut brought official Australian rates down to match U.S. levels for the first time since the early 1980s and, since a U.S. hike has been priced in for some time, market rates out to a year were already beneath comparable U.S. rates. That in turn saw forward A$ rates hit highs not seen in a decade.  </p>
<p>On the futures market the September 90-day bank bill contract had soared 41 basis points to 94.43, implying a rate of 5.57 percent.</p>
<p>In contrast the SIMEX three month Euro-dollar contract for September was at 93.95, implying the market expected U.S. rates to rise to around 6.05 percent in the next three months or so.</p>
<p>How offshore investors reacted to this seminal event was hard to assess, analysts said. The few die-hard Aussie bulls around pointed to the fact that Canada had cut its rates far below those in the U.S. and its dollar had escaped with only moderate losses. -- Wayne Cole 61-2 9373 1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
