<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610502" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia central bank goes from hawk to dove.</title>
<headline>Australia central bank goes from hawk to dove.</headline>
<byline>Bernard Hickey</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>If a week is a long time in politics, the Reserve Bank of Australia's (RBA) rate cut on Friday showed that two weeks can be an eternity for monetary policy-makers.</p>
<p>Just two weeks ago, Reserve Bank Governor Ian Macfarlane told a parliamentary committee hearing that there was &quot;nothing to gain&quot; by cutting official rates again and warned that wages growth was &quot;uncomfortably high&quot;.</p>
<p>Observers left the hearing convinced of Macfarlane's hawkish tendencies and expected the bank's avowed independence would ensure steady rates for the rest of the year.</p>
<p>Despite the claims of Prime Minister John Howard and Treasurer Peter Costello that last week's budget would &quot;take massive pressure off interest rates&quot;, most saw a steadfast Macfarlane holding the inflation hard line and possibly even raising rates later this year.</p>
<p>Those expectations were reinforced only last Thursday when Macfarlane said the latest wages data had been a &quot;setback&quot; to last year's pattern of improving inflation developments.</p>
<p>The hawk's feathers seemed unruffled.</p>
<p>Then came March quarter enterprise bargaining wages data on Wednesday and average weekly earnings data for the three months to the end of February on Thursday.</p>
<p>The first showed annual wages growth running at 4.7 percent, well above the 4.5 percent level described by Macfarlane as &quot;generous&quot;. The second showed private sector growth accelerating and all sectors annual growth of 4.3 percent.</p>
<p>Most thought these numbers did little to change the rates outlook.</p>
<p>So what happened between Wednesday morning and Friday morning to apparently turn the Reserve Bank's thinking around 180 degrees?</p>
<p>The Reserve Bank said in its announcement of the cut in official rates to 5.5 percent to 6.0 percent that after consideration at its May 6 board meeting and the recent wages data it had decided wages growth had moderated to about four percent from the previously-thought 4.5 percent.</p>
<p>Most economists were surprised at the turn-around, although none suggested any political interference.</p>
<p>The Liberal-National government said in a fanfare last year when it appointed Macfarlane that the bank was independent, but that has not been written into law and depends on conventions.</p>
<p>Economists generally accepted the bank's revised reasoning, but they said Macfarlane was likely to have come under pressure from other Reserve Bank board members at that May meeting.</p>
<p>&quot;Given Macfarlane's earlier statements about wage growth, the inappropriateness of cutting interest rates, he seems to have done a U-turn,&quot; said Colonial Group Economist Hans Kunnen.</p>
<p>&quot;But then again, the RBA governor is just one voice on the policy-making committee,&quot; Kunnen said.</p>
<p>The clearest signals that a change was in the wind came as late as Thursday afternoon from one of those other voices -- the government's RBA board member, Treasury Secretary Ted Evans.</p>
<p>Evans rubbished the quality of the data showing an acceleration in private sector wages, arguing wages growth was not accelerating and was in fact steady around four percent. And he said the economy could grow considerably faster than 3.5 percent.</p>
<p>Evans' comments on wages growth and unreliable wages data were repeated virtually word for word in the Reserve Bank's statement on Friday.</p>
<p>If the entrails of Evans' statements on monetary policy were not picked over minutely in the past, they will be now.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
