<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610549" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: ANZ reviews rates after RBA rate easing.</title>
<headline>ANZ reviews rates after RBA rate easing.</headline>
<dateline>MELBOURNE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (ANZ), one of Australia's big four banks, said on Friday it was reviewing its lending rates following the central bank's monetary policy easing.</p>
<p>ANZ spokesman Ian Bremner said no decisions had yet been made on new rate levels.</p>
<p>Each of Australia's big four private banks has a standard variable mortgage rate of 7.55 percent which was struck in February and led by the Commonwealth Bank of Australia</p>
<p>The ANZ's reference rate for major business customers is set at 9.35 percent.  </p>
<p>The Reserve Bank said at 9.30 a.m. (2330 GMT) that it would cut the official cash rate by 50 basis points to 5.5 percent.</p>
<p>Non-bank mortgage originator Aussie Home Loans and the Commonwealth Bank of Australia responded soon after with reductions in their variable mortgage rates. Aussie Home said it would reduce its housing rate to 6.99 percent from 7.49 percent, passing on the full central banking easing.</p>
<p>CBA said it would cut its no-frills rate to 6.7 percent from 6.9 percent and its standard variable rate to 7.20 percent from 7.55 percent. This is the same rate set by the other major banks, National Australia Bank Ltd and Westpac Banking  </p>
<p>Corp.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MELBOURNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
