<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610541" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: U.S. confirms interest in NZ free trade agreement.</title>
<headline>U.S. confirms interest in NZ free trade agreement.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States has confirmed it is interested in a free trade arrangement with New Zealand, New Zealand's Trade Minister Lockwood Smith said from Washington on Friday.</p>
<p>Smith met U.S. Trade Representative Charlene Barshefsky on Thursday to discuss the possibility of pursuing a free trade agreement similar to the Closer Economic Relations (CER) pact between New Zealand and Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;Representative Barshefsky repeated her interest and briefed me on the necessary first step, that is the administration's requirement for fast track negotiating authority from Congress,&quot; Smith said in a statement on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;We agreed to keep in close contact,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Smith said his meeting with Barshefsky underscored the trade partnership New Zealand had with the United States through the World Trade Organisation and the Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) forum.</p>
<p>&quot;The talks were substantive, yet relaxed. We covered both agriculture and services as well as other matters,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Smith, on a trade mission that also includes France, Greece, Britain, Mexico and Brazil, was due to leave Washington for Paris on Saturday for the annual Organisation of Economic Cooperation and Development ministerial council meeting.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
