<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610577" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Hong Kong's Hang Seng Index scores record close.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong's Hang Seng Index scores record close.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's Hang Seng Index scored a record closing high on Friday, as a surge of liquidity into blue chips during afternoon trade and a buoyant tone in the red chip sector propelled prices higher.</p>
<p>The Hang Seng Index closed 119.68 points, or 0.84 percent, higher at 14,331.68, the highest level of the session.</p>
<p>Turnover was HK$14.98 billion compared with HK$14.21 billion on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's index buying -- a surge of liquidity in the market,&quot; said Geoff Galbraith, institutional sales trader at NAVA SC Securities.</p>
<p>Among the blue chips, HSBC Holdings Plc jumped HK$3.00 to close at HK$223.00, Swire Pacific Ltd advanced HK$1.00 to HK$65.00 and Henderson Land Development Co Ltd rose HK$0.75 to HK$75.25.</p>
<p>&quot;The market looks fine. It is well supported,&quot; said Richard Verin, head of equity trading at CS First Boston.</p>
<p>&quot;Every time it looks like it is going to come off it doesn't. There seems to be plenty of cash around to support the market,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Verin said the red chip sector continued to draw in much of the market turnover.</p>
<p>Shares in Shanghai Industrial Holdings Ltd gained HK$0.90 to HK$44.00 and China Resources Enterprise Ltd jumped HK$0.85 to HK$26.20. CITIC Pacific Ltd gained HK$0.50 to HK$44.60.</p>
<p>Shares in China-backed Chu Kong Shipping Development made their market debut on Friday, tripling in price to close at HK$3.60 compared with an issue price of HK$1.20.</p>
<p>Beijing Enterprises initial public offering closed on Friday with a last minute dash by investors to get their applications in before the midday deadline. The red chip said it had received &quot;a significant number of applications&quot; and that it would not cash cheques for applications for 6,000 or less shares.</p>
<p>Galbraith said the money could be redirected back into the market.</p>
<p>Brokers said the market was likely to retain a firm tone next week with investors likely to buy on any dips.</p>
<p>Galbraith noted that the futures were at a slight premium to the cash market, indicating investor optimism.</p>
<p>The May Hang Seng Index future rose 83 points to close at 14,338 and the June contract ended 90 points higher at 14,390.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
