<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610531" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian rate cut enhances corp bond growth -ANZ.</title>
<headline>Australian rate cut enhances corp bond growth -ANZ.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank's cut in Australian official interest rates to 5.5 percent on Friday should encourage corporates to issue debt to take advantage of low interest rates, ANZ Investment Bank said.</p>
<p>&quot;The rate cut will encourage corporate treasurers to issue debt and lock in these rates. The first evidence of this is that we have seen a number of corporates seeking to pay fixed-rate in the interest rate swap market,&quot; Jason Carley, ANZ Investment Bank's Head of Research, said in a commentary.  </p>
<p>Carley added that investors will be looking beyond the lower yielding government debt markets in order to increase returns and increase demand in the market. &quot;The issuance will be in the fixed and floating rate sectors of the market,&quot; Carley said.</p>
<p>Floating rate issuers will be taking advantage of the rate cut through the swap market he said, adding that spreads have historically been highly correlated with nominal interest rates.</p>
<p>&quot;Consequently, the rate cut should translate into slightly tighter corporate spreads,&quot; Carley said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
