<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610551" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia's central bank announces surprise rate cut.</title>
<headline>Australia's central bank announces surprise rate cut.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Reserve Bank of Australia on Friday surprised financial markets and cut official interest rates by 0.5 percentage points to 5.5 percent -- the fourth cut in less than a year.</p>
<p>The bank had been under political pressure to cut rates after the government released its 1997/98 budget 10 days ago, arguing economic growth and low inflation had set the scene for lower rates.</p>
<p>The central bank said it had decided to cut interest rates because it believed underlying inflation, now at 2.0 percent, would fall in the coming quarter.</p>
<p>The bank said forecast strong economic growth in 1997 and fiscal tightening in the government's budget also contributed to the cut. Economic growth, currently 3.25 percent, is forecast to reach 3.75 percent in the 1997/98 fiscal year.</p>
<p>&quot;The above considerations -- namely, inflation forecast to fall below two percent, and economic activity providing scope for further expansion -- amount to a 'prima facie' case for an easing in policy,&quot; the bank said in a statement.</p>
<p>The Australian dollar slumped more than three quarters of a U.S. cent in hectic morning trade after the rate cut caught much of the market by surprise.</p>
<p>Within 10 minutes of the cut the dollar had dived to US$0.7680/85, its lowest level since mid-February, from US$0.7761/66 just ahead of the bank's announcement.</p>
<p>&quot;I am surprised that they have done this,&quot; said Chris Richardson, director of Access Economics.</p>
<p>&quot;I would have expected no change until early 1998 when I would have expected rates to go up on the basis of very rapid growth in the United States, translating into rapid growth here and adding to inflation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Rates were last cut in December last year when the official cash rate was brought down to 6.0 percent from 6.5 percent.  </p>
<p>The latest rate cut flew in the face of a recent comment by central bank governor Ian Macfarlane that there would be no economic gain in cutting rates given the bank's assessment of strong economic growth through 1997 and persistent concerns about the pace of wages growth.</p>
<p>&quot;He seems to have done a U-turn ... he has gone completely against statements he made nearly a fortnight ago,&quot; said Hans Kunnen, group economist with Colonial State Bank.</p>
<p>&quot;I agree with the rate cut, I would have done it myself, but I didn't think they would. I thought they were more hawkish. I am not sure whose views have changed,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Analysts said the decision this week by the Federal Reserve to leave U.S. official rates unchanged had given the RBA a &quot;window of opportunity&quot; to cut rates.</p>
<p>In its statement the central bank said that while wages growth was &quot;not yet optimal&quot;, it had moderated enough to permit the rate cut.</p>
<p>Wages data released on Thursday showed wages growing at 4.3 percent over the past year, revised down from an earlier 4.6 percent. The central bank's &quot;line in the sand&quot; on wages growth is considered by the market to be 4.5 percent.  </p>
<p>&quot;Well done Reserve Bank. I didn't expect they would react this quickly (after the wages data) but I think it is very appropriate,&quot; said Dennis Mahoney, economist with Predential-Bache Securities.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
