<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610501" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: AUSTRALIA GOLD-Miners use low dollar to sell gold.</title>
<headline>AUSTRALIA GOLD-Miners use low dollar to sell gold.</headline>
<byline>James Regan</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Reacting to a sharp fall in the value of the Australian dollar, some of Australia's gold mining companies took the opportunity to sell gold.</p>
<p>The activity, prompted by a surprise rise, albeit small, gain in the value of gold in Australian dollar terms, capped an otherwise routine week for gold, bullion dealers said.</p>
<p>The Australian dollar slumped more than 3/4 cent on Friday after the Reserve Bank of Australia cut official cash rates 0.5 percentage point to 5.5 percent.  </p>
<p>&quot;The fall in the Aussie dollar has led to a small amount of selling by some Australian gold producers,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>When the Australian dollar declines against the benchmark U.S. currency it means Australian gold will fetch a higher return in Australian dollars.</p>
<p>The Perth Mint on Friday was quoting spot gold at A$446.32 an ounce based on an international price of US$343.13 an ounce.</p>
<p>On the previous day, an international price only nominally higher of US$343.43 compared with an A$443.54 an ounce quote by the mint.  </p>
<p>That means that while gold in U.S. dollars actually fell 30 cents a pound, over the same one-day period Australian-dollar gold was up A$$2.78.</p>
<p>&quot;Aussie dollar gold at the present price is really in familiar territory and not much help to producers looking to sell,&quot; the dealer said. &quot;It certainly makes it more attractive on the day but I don't think it will attract a huge amount of selling.&quot;</p>
<p>However, it appears not many of the Australian producers took advantage of the potential gains, choosing instead to sit on their reserves, dealers said.  </p>
<p>One reason offered by dealers is that even at the elevated level, the price is too low to attract much interest.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a blue-sky perception that if you can hang on, the price will go up,&quot; another dealer said.</p>
<p>The average cost of producing gold in Australia is around A$370 an ounce, which doesn't leave much room for profits, taking into account associated outside costs.</p>
<p>Mine operating costs frequently hold more sway with investors than the gold price.  </p>
<p>&quot;A mining company may not be able to control the world price, but it is responsible for its own costs,&quot; said a mine analyst.</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
