<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610554" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesian capital nervous on final campaign day.</title>
<headline>Indonesian capital nervous on final campaign day.</headline>
<byline>Ian MacKenzie</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tension gripped Jakarta on Friday on the last day of the general election campaign, but there were no reports through the morning of the violence that hit the city of 10 million earlier in the week.</p>
<p>The Moslem-oriented United Development Party (PPP) cancelled its final-day campaign in the capital to avoid confrontations, primarily between its members and partisans of the ruling Golkar party.</p>
<p>A number of offices in the main financial district closed early and many schools, including international schools for expatriate children, were closed for the day.</p>
<p>&quot;We heard people have been told to leave early,&quot; a stockbroker said.</p>
<p>Civil servants and bank employees were told to wear ordinary clothing instead of semi-official uniforms such as safari suits favoured by the bureaucracy.</p>
<p>Indonesians referred to advisories issued by the U.S., British, Italian and Australian embassies suggesting their nationals stay off the streets for the day.</p>
<p>Nearly 125 million people are eligible to vote next Thursday in the national and local elections after a five-day cooling-off period. The elections are held every five years.</p>
<p>Financial markets were jittery, but the rupiah remained stable through the morning at 2,443 to the dollar. The stock market edged down marginally on cautious sentiment, with the composite index off 1.04 at 653.05 points at the lunch break.</p>
<p>The chief of the Indonesian armed forces (ABRI), General Feisal Tanjung, said stern measures would be taken against anyone disturbing the peace during the cooling-off period.</p>
<p>&quot;Whatever the form of violation and whoever the violator, we will act according to the law. The parties should obey the regulations for the cooling-off period,&quot; the official Antara news agency quoted him as saying.</p>
<p>The PPP campaigned on Friday on Java, home to 60 percent of the country's 200 million people, and in the remote Malukus and Irian Jaya.</p>
<p>Golkar, in power under President Suharto for the past 30 years and expected to win again easily next week, campaigned on Borneo island and Sulawesi, and the Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI) -- badly split by a leadership struggle last year -- hit the hustings in Sumatra, the resort island of Bali and the adjacent Nusa Tenggara islands.</p>
<p>Megawati Sukarnoputri, who was ousted as the PDI leader by a government-backed faction in June last year, told supporters on Thursday she would not vote at the elections.</p>
<p>She also told her supporters not to vote for the official PDI, which she described as illegal and unconstitutional. She avoided an illegal call for a total boycott of the poll.</p>
<p>Indonesians also show their electoral dissent by a process called &quot;golput&quot; -- meaning &quot;white group&quot; -- in which they spoil their ballots or abstain from voting.</p>
<p>Golkar officials said golput abstentions in the last elections in 1992 amounted to three or four percent of the poll, in which over 90 percent of those eligible cast ballots.</p>
<p>Golkar is seeking just over 70 percent of the vote next week compared to the 68 percent it got in 1992, and political analysts said spoiled ballots would have little effect on this.</p>
<p>The PPP received 17 percent and the PDI 15 percent in 1992.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
