<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610536" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FEATURE - Australian PM talks tough on land reform.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Australian PM talks tough on land reform.</headline>
<byline>Jane Nelson</byline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The 2,000 farmers, many wearing the distinctive Akubra hat of the Australian bush, had travelled thousands of kilometres to stand in searing heat in the outback town of Longreach to hear Prime Minister John Howard.</p>
<p>But as the Australian leader tried to sell his solution to a bitter land rights row between farmers and Aborigines, the chorus of jeers and derisive shouts showed they were not buying.</p>
<p>Midway through his maiden three-year term, Australia's first conservative prime minister since 1983 is finding no one, including some of his political allies, wants to listen to him.</p>
<p>Now, the former Sydney lawyer is trying what analysts say is a dangerous bluff to try to win support for his reforms.</p>
<p>Howard and senior ministers have begun threatening an early election in a bid to force approval of Howard's controversial land rights solution, as well as unpopular labour reforms that would make it easier for small firms to sack new workers.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a lot of bluff and talk about double dissolution, but no one really wants one,&quot; Australian National University political analyst John Warhurst told Reuters.</p>
<p>Howard can dissolve both houses of parliament and call an early poll if the upper house Senate -- where the government does not have a majority -- twice rejects his legislation.</p>
<p>ABORIGINAL LAND ROW GREATEST CHALLENGE</p>
<p>The native title land rights row is the greatest challenge facing his government, says Howard, who estimates up to 78 percent of Australia's 7.68 million square km (2.96 million square miles) could be affected by Aboriginal land claims.</p>
<p>Native title laws were introduced by the former Labor government three years ago, but became an urgent political issue when the High Court ruled last December that land leased to farmers could be liable to undefined native claims.</p>
<p>Howard's blueprint guarantees farmers' rights to land they have leased since European settlement more than 200 years ago. It also guarantees Aborigines strictly limited access for traditional purposes, but exempts some land from native claim.</p>
<p>Both groups accuse Howard of selling them out.</p>
<p>The National Party, the coalition's junior partner, has criticised Howard's failure to wipe out native title -- a failure which roused deep anger in the party's rural heartland.</p>
<p>The Nationals and farmers say Howard's plan still leaves them uncertain about their rights and threatens their business.</p>
<p>Aboriginal groups are also angry, saying Howard's plan effectively abolishes native title and is a final step towards wiping out their race.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a revisit to our waterholes to poison it yet again,&quot; Northern Land Council chairman Galarrwuy Yunupingu said after a recent outback council of Aboriginal elders.</p>
<p>&quot;This is rounding Aboriginal people into the valleys and a final shootout. This is finally killing off Aboriginal men, women and children one by one.&quot;</p>
<p>PRIME MINISTER HOWARD TALKS TOUGH</p>
<p>Despite bitter opposition from farmers, Aborigines and sections of his government, Howard says his land rights plan is not negotiable.</p>
<p>He had hoped to pave the way for the plan by winning the support of farmers, and through them rebellious members of his Liberal-National coalition, during a recent rally at the Longreach Stockman's Hall of Fame in Queensland.</p>
<p>He talked tough to the weather-beaten throng, assuring them he would protect their land even if it meant going to the polls over the issue before the next election due in early 1999.</p>
<p>The farmers, traditionally cynical towards city politicians, remained unconvinced by the plain-talking Howard even though he wore an Akubra hat and drank their tea.</p>
<p>DOUBT OVER EARLY POLL THREAT</p>
<p>Opposition parties and political analysts also doubt Howard will carry out his early election threat, citing his falling popularity, the government's internal ructions and the surging support for race row politician Pauline Hanson.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the hoary old chestnut -- we've heard this crying wolf... so many times before,&quot; Australian Democrats leader Cheryl Kernot said. &quot;I don't believe them.&quot;</p>
<p>Opinion polls show the government's popularity has fallen to its lowest since ousting Labor 14 months ago, with its gap over the opposition halving to about six percentage points.</p>
<p>The polls also show Hanson's new One Nation party could possibly win a place in the Senate for the first time in a double dissolution, further complicating the balance of power.</p>
<p>Minor parties win Senate places more easily in a double dissolution election -- when the full 76-seat Senate faces re-election instead of half the chamber in a normal election -- because of Australia's complex proportional voting system.</p>
<p>Even if an early poll does not materialise, analysts say Howard's current woes could still hurt him at the ballot box.</p>
<p>Australian National University political analyst Jim Jupp warned that Howard's political fortunes could be damaged if he doesn't end the perception of a government divided.</p>
<p>&quot;The longer it goes on, the more that appearance will start to damage the overall credibility of the government,&quot; Jupp said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
