<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610524" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian tax reforms pose problems - analysts.</title>
<headline>Australian tax reforms pose problems - analysts.</headline>
<byline>Jane Nelson</byline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's outdated and inefficient tax system urgently needs reform, but the political problems of selling a new tax meant the government was unlikely to make more than minor changes, tax experts say.</p>
<p>Economists welcomed calls for reform and debate by Prime Minister John Howard and Treasurer Peter Costello this week, saying an overhaul was long overdue.</p>
<p>They said the current system was bogged down in inconsistencies and anomalies, and was too complicated.  </p>
<p>&quot;It's unnecessarily complex, particularly the state taxes, which are so inefficient that they subtract value from the economy,&quot; Access Economics economist Chris Richardson said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are too many avenues for avoidance and evasion -- which a GST (goods and services tax) could help pick up because it's such a blanket -- and it's too biased,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>The current indirect tax system is seen as narrowly-based, biased and inefficent -- taxing some sectors more heavily for no apparent reason -- and distorting investment decisions.  </p>
<p>But desite the widespread acceptance of the need for tax reform -- even welfare groups argue for an overhaul -- analysts said the government could be using the tax issue as a smokescreen to deflect pressure over a bitter land rights row, plunging popularity and continuing high unemployment.</p>
<p>But they urged Howard to consider all issues, including giving consideration a GST.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a very creaky income tax system, parts of it belong in the 1930s, certainly not in the 1990s,&quot; Richardson said.  </p>
<p>&quot;It's one of the two things that really holds Australia back as an economy,&quot; he said, saying the other was the country's rigid labour market laws.</p>
<p>A GST is a consumption tax or value-added tax and is paid by consumers when they buy a good or service. Australia currently has a range of indirect taxes, including sales tax, that are applied patchily and at varying rates.</p>
<p>Australian Institute of Chartered Accountants' indirect taxes spokesman David Vos said the government, beset by falling popularity, was unlikely to make any radical reforms, preferring instead to tinker at the edges.  </p>
<p>&quot;How likely are they to do anything? They'll do something, but how certain do I think it is that there's going to be a value-added tax? At best, 50-50,&quot; Vos told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been, caused I suppose by the 1993 election, an impression in Australia that GST equals Liberal and non-GST equals Labor and that's disgraceful.&quot;</p>
<p>The Liberal-National coalition was widely perceived to have lost the 1993 election because of its plans to introduce a GST.</p>
<p>It ousted the 13-year-old Labor administration in 1996 after dropping the tax and pledging not to introduce a GST in its first term. But it has not ruled out such a tax in later terms.  </p>
<p>The government's popularity has dropped to record lows mid-way through its first term, and this, with the traditional voter resistance to new taxes, is seen working against a GST.</p>
<p>However, the idea of a consumption tax has gained increasing support since 1993, with welfare groups saying they could accept a consumption tax if there was some offset to lessen the disproportionate impact on low income earners.</p>
<p>Richardson of Access said the GST met all the criteria of a good tax -- it was broadly-based, with few or no exemptions, and it did not have different rates for different things.  </p>
<p>In addition, it was simple, efficient and very likely to boost national savings through a reduction in income tax.</p>
<p>The main problem with a GST was its failure to discriminate between high and low income earners, applying to both groups in the same way, which would make it difficult to sell to voters.</p>
<p>&quot;Whether you're poor or whether you're rich, you're paying the same GST on a given item, so a switch towards GST runs the risk of having a less fair system,&quot; Richardson said.</p>
<p>&quot;But against that, you'd have to say that if a GST was replacing lots of the inefficient taxes, the whole country would win.&quot;  </p>
<p>If the government stopped short of a major tax overhaul, including introduction of a GST, it could be expected to continue making minor reforms, changing the coverage and level of existing taxes, analysts said.</p>
<p>-- Canberra Bureau 61-6 273-2730</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
