<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610548" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: OPINION - From the Beehive - &quot;For sale&quot; hints in NZ.</title>
<headline>OPINION - From the Beehive - &quot;For sale&quot; hints in NZ.</headline>
<text>
<p>By Vernon Small, political correspondent</p>
<p>WELLINGTON, May 23 - The signs are coming thick and fast that privatisations are back on the agenda for the National Party, and there is little will in New Zealand First to oppose those outside the strict(ish) no-go zone of the coalition agreement.</p>
<p>Associate Health Minister Neil Kirton and Health Minister Bill English are locked in an unedifying tussle over just how to make it seem there is no private involvement in the planned Christchurch cardiothoracic unit, while subcontracting to the same surgeons who would have had shares had &quot;private&quot; involvement been sanctioned.</p>
<p>Yet Kirton seems to be fighting a single portfolio battle.</p>
<p>Elsewhere there was no coherent NZ First opposition to calls this week from arch-economic dry Commerce Minister John Luxton, who was beating the drum for a radical downscaling of government. SOE Minister Jenny Shipley and other senior figures have joined the band with more or less subtle hints.</p>
<p>Treasurer and New Zealand First leader Wisnton Peters, whose pre-election tapping of a vein of pro-public, anti-foreign investment in the New Zealand psyche had the international community on hot bricks, is still gamely defending the coalition agreement's ban on the sale of strategic assets and what he calls a tightening of the rules on foreign investment.</p>
<p>But outside those strategic assets it is a different story.</p>
<p>For instance, Bill Birch has said the property in the Government Property Services portfolio is still high on the list of privatisation candidates.</p>
<p>This week GPS chairman Colin Beyer said a float would be the best option and hinted that the right time in the market cycle was near at hand.  </p>
<p>Peters, in his speech to the Institute of Management meeting on Tuesday, took a break from his attacks on the media and National backbenchers to ask (rhetorically) why government should own Bowen House, GPS's $38 million flagship property leased to Parliament.</p>
<p>Nor does the list of strategic assets ruled out of sale -- including ECNZ and Transpower -- prevent the sale of some generating stations and, perhaps in time, the contentious &quot;non- core&quot; spur lines off ther national grid.  </p>
<p>The word around the Beehive is that thinking is well advanced on the further split of ECNZ, leaving three power- generating SOEs and inevitable questions about when the government will decide that is one too many.</p>
<p>Against that background Alliance leader Jim Anderton's release of papers showing New Zealand's stance on the OECD's Multilateral Agreement on Investment (MAI) put another skid under NZ First's long term &quot;brand&quot; position on foreign control.  </p>
<p>Again Peters defended his party's successes in tightening the rules on foreign investment. (Since the election the Overseas Investment Commission has rejected two applications -- bringing the total to three since 1990 -- so perhaps he could argue the percentage is improving.)</p>
<p>He correctly pointed out that all the existing rules limiting foreign investment would be built into the MAI as reservations if New Zealand signed up.</p>
<p>But the MAI has at its heart, as do other international agreements on liberalisation, the implication member countries will, over time, lower these barriers.  </p>
<p>This is made explicit in papers released by the government this week above International Trade Minister Lockwood Smith's signature.</p>
<p>They show the agreement would make it impossible to move to more restrictive rules -- known as the rule of &quot;standstill&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Once a party has committed its regime ... then it cannot at any time in the future move to make that regime more restrictive, or to introduce new non-conforming measures unless it is able to obtain agreement of the other Parties (countries),&quot; the paper reads.  </p>
<p>Furthermore: &quot;The objective, both in the first negotiation and over time, will be to reduce the overall level of reservations and in this way to achieve liberalisation. This is known as 'rollback'.&quot;</p>
<p>If New Zealand signs up to that, it would make it all but impossible for Peters to again campaign on tighter restrictions on foreign investment, even given the coalition agreement he now defends is a compromise and does not reflact his party's &quot;pure&quot; position.</p>
<p>The way would then be clear for the Alliance to reclaim the anti-foreign investment constituency.  </p>
<p>-- Wellington newsroom 64 4 473 4746</p>
<p>(Note: The opinions expressed here are those of the writer. They should not be seen as representing the views of Reuters.)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
