<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610568" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: PRESS DIGEST-Hong Kong newspaper headlines-May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST-Hong Kong newspaper headlines-May 23.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Hong Kong press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>-- MING PAO -- Chinese Vice-Premier Qian Qichen said the method of electing Hong Kong's first Special Administrative Region legislature should be democratic, fair and open. He also said the Preparatory Committee, which set up the mechanism for the territory's transition to Chinese rule on July 1, should leave enough room for the post-handover government.</p>
<p>-- APPLE DAILY -- Most pro-democracy activists have decided to leave the territory before the handover. Beijing maintains a blacklist of overseas pro-democracy activists who are barred from entering the mainland and at least 18 Hong Kong people's home-visit certificates have been confiscated.</p>
<p>-- SING TAO -- An increasing number of Taiwanese men are going to the mainland in search of wives but arranging the emigration of the women has become a serious problem for Taiwan authorities. According to the quota system, mainland brides have to wait 13 years to be united with their Taiwanese husbands.</p>
<p>-- TA KUNG PAO -- Beijing has repeatedly urged departments to strengthen control over mainlanders coming to Hong Kong and supervision of Chinese companies in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>-- ECONOMIC TIMES -- Second-hand properties have become the focus of a recent war among local banks over mortgage interest rates. Some banks have lowered their rate to 8.75 percent.</p>
<p>-- SOUTH CHINA MORNING POST -- Hong Kong's securities and banking regulators plan to implement new measures from Monday aimed at improving the fairness of the way shares are distributed in initial public offerings.</p>
<p>-- Mainland share prices plunged to their lowest levels in about eight weeks after Beijing banned state enterprises and listed companies from misusing funds to trade on the country's exchanges.</p>
<p>-- HONGKONG STANDARD -- Hong Kong's post-handover legal system received a double boost with the extradition of tobacco executive Jerry Lui and the expected extradition of alleged rogue banker Ewan Launder.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6441</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
