<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610540" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Corporates gear-up to change face of Aussie debt.</title>
<headline>Corporates gear-up to change face of Aussie debt.</headline>
<byline>Colin Brinsden</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian fund managers are expected to increasingly turn their attention to corporate bond issuance amid dwindling supply of government and state debt, and as the superannuation funds industry grows, analysts said.</p>
<p>Some corporates have already taken steps into the market this year, joining the growing supply of mortaged-backed securities and the budding kangaroo market, which is open to foreign borrowers.</p>
<p>Analysts also see the move to corporate debt revolutionising the local debt market's thinking on investment.  </p>
<p>&quot;The significant changes will be for people in the fund managers where you are really going to need to assess credit from a much wider prospective,&quot; Matthew Drennan, senior economist at Axiom Funds Management, told Reuters Financial Television (RFTV).</p>
<p>&quot;You are going to have to consider 'what credit ratings are we going to let our people invest in',&quot; he added.</p>
<p>This will put increasing demand for research on companies' financial status and put more reliance on credit agencies such as Standard &amp; Poor's Corp and Moody's Investors Service, who's ratings already go hand-in-hand with trading in the U.S. corporate debt market and the Eurobond market.</p>
<p>Until recently, fund managers generally only operated in the government and semi-government, or state, debt markets and usually through taking a punt on the market's next move.</p>
<p>&quot;We are seeing a move away from that to more conservative directional plays in the market, but greater emphasis on taking credit risk or business risk for best return,&quot; said Nigel Douglas, chief economist at Merrill Lynch Australia.  </p>
<p>The current economic climate is also seen ripe for corporations to re-enter the debt market since their noticeable absence since the early 1990s, when interest rates were still relatively high.</p>
<p>Australian inflation is low, and there is a growing confidence in it staying that way, yield spreads to government debt of long standing corporate issues have tightened, and the Federal and state governments have tightened their fiscal belts.</p>
<p>As well, interest rates have fallen two full points in under a year following the Reserve Bank's surprise 0.5 percentage point cut in official rates to 5.5 percent.  </p>
<p>In last week's federal budget the government said the net borrowing requirement would be negative in 1997/98, with the government expected to repay A$5.2 billion of debt.</p>
<p>Net borrowing is also expected to remain negative in out years, with projections of contractions of A$5.8 billion in 1998/99, A$4.8 billion in 1999/00 and A$10.1 billion in 2000/01.</p>
<p>&quot;As you move out towards the turn of the century you could be looking at one quarter of the current stock of central government debt on issue being repaid,&quot; Axiom's Drennan said.  </p>
<p>&quot;That is going to make it easier for the corporates and securitised mortgage-backed securities to get into the market,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>-- Sydney newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
