<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610509" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: NRG to examine New South Wales power assets.</title>
<headline>NRG to examine New South Wales power assets.</headline>
<dateline>BRISBANE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The local subsidiary of U.S. utility NRG Energy Inc said on Friday it would be interested in bidding for some of the A$22 billion in power generation and distribution assets that are likely to be sold by the state government of New South Wales.</p>
<p>&quot;We are obviously very excited about it. We are certainly interested in all privatisation acitivity in the different states,&quot; said NRG Australia executive director Craig Cooper.</p>
<p>The state government said late on Thursday it had prepared a discussion paper supporting the sale of the power facilities as a way of retiring state debt and improving infrastructure.  </p>
<p>Cooper said NRG was not surprised by the NSW government announcement but could not yet comment on the valuation of the assets contained in the document.</p>
<p>Newspaper reports on Friday said the assets may be worth up to A$25 billion, with the document revealing a conservative valuation by accountancy firm Arthur Andersen.</p>
<p>&quot;It depends on the assets,&quot; Cooper said. &quot;Once we do a due diligence we will be able to get a better idea of the revenues available and the valuations.&quot;  </p>
<p>He said NRG was open to making its own bids or finding a joint venture partner as it did with CMS Energy Corp in the state of Victoria.</p>
<p>&quot;It depends on the opportunities and the acquisitions available in New South Wales.&quot;</p>
<p>CMS, in partnership with NRG and local institutions led by Macquarie Bank Ltd, last month purchased the Loy Yang A power station and associated coal mine from the Victorian government for A$4.86 billion. CMS will have a 50 percent stake with NRG and the institutions each holding 25 percent.  </p>
<p>Newspaper reports on Friday said other likely bidders for the NSW power generation assets were Edison Mission and CMS from the United States and U.K. groups PowerGen, British Energy Plc, and National Power.</p>
<p>The discusssion paper, which was released by NSW treasurer and energy minister Michael Egan, said the government would consider selling seven power stations, six distributors, the state's high-voltage transmission lines and the remaining 58 percent it holds in the Snowy Mountains Hydroelectric Authority.  </p>
<p>The sale requires the support of unions and the state government's ruling Labor Party before it can proceed without interruption.</p>
<p>-- Ian Pemberton, Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C182">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRISBANE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
