<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610504" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian dollar faces life without rate crutch.</title>
<headline>Australian dollar faces life without rate crutch.</headline>
<byline>Wayne Cole</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Australian dollar may finally be coming of age, some 14 years after it was first freed from official control.</p>
<p>In a bold move Friday, the Reserve Bank cut interest rates to the same level as the U.S., removing a crutch once vital for stability. The dollar's first steps were faltering, but analysts felt it could stand alone given improved economic fundamentals.</p>
<p>&quot;It's hard, but sooner or later we will all have to get used to Australia as a low inflation, low interest rate country,&quot; said Bruce Freeland, chief economist at Commonwealth Bank.  </p>
<p>The surprise 0.5 point cut left official cash rates at 5.50 percent, matching the key Fed funds rate in the U.S.</p>
<p>And, since markets have long been pricing in a tightening in the U.S., Australian money rates out to two years actually moved below their U.S. counterparts.</p>
<p>With investors now paid less to hold the local currency than U.S. dollars, the immediate reaction was to sell and the currency slumped over a cent to a three month low of US$0.7665.</p>
<p>Support did emerge there and it battled back above 77 cents, but analysts said the real test would come when the all-powerful London and New York markets opened later on Friday.  </p>
<p>&quot;The A$'s fall has actually brought it down to what we consider fair value based on fundamentals, so I would not be surprised to see it stabilise around here,&quot; said CBA's Freeland.</p>
<p>&quot;But if U.S. rates rise in a few weeks, as most still expect, we'll be in uncharted territory and some sort of A$ weakness has to be likely,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Whether it lasted depended crucially on how offshore investors, who largely fund Australia's debt habit, assessed the risks and rewards of holding the dollar in this new rate regime.</p>
<p>All analysts agreed the risks had diminished in recent years due to Australia's impressive inflation performance.  </p>
<p>After topping seven percent in 1988, underlying inflation has fallen steadily to stand at an annual 2.1 percent in the March quarter and has averaged less than 2.5 percent since 1993.</p>
<p>That was a better performance than the U.S., where the latest data put core inflation at 2.7 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;For the bulk of the 1990's underlying inflation here has been below the U.S. and it's only right the market recognises that,&quot; said Tony Meer, an economist at Deutche Morgan Grenfell.</p>
<p>And the good news would keep coming with the RBA confidently expecting underlying inflation to fall below 2.0 percent in coming quarters and remains below 3.0 percent through 1988.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
