<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610514" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia rate cut likely to be last for a while.</title>
<headline>Australia rate cut likely to be last for a while.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Even before financial markets digested Australia's fourth cut in official rates in the past 10 months, their attention was focusing on whether there would be yet another reduction.</p>
<p>The 0.5 percentage point reduction to 5.50 percent in the official cash rate announced by the Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) seemed to mark a departure from recent central bank forecasts of strong growth and warnings on wages, and caught a lot in the market off guard.  </p>
<p>The general reaction amongst economists was that it was almost certainly the last cut in rates for a while, given improving growth prospects and still high wages growth.</p>
<p>And while there was unlikely to be a hike in rates in 1998, the negative impact of Friday's cut on the exchange rate had brought forward the timing of a rate hike given its unfavourable impact on inflation, analysts said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Given the near-certainty that growth will pick up, and given that inflation is likely to be on the rise, although still low, next year, driven by wages and no longer held down by an appreciating exchange rate, we think this was the last cut,&quot; Bankers Trust Australia chief economist Chris Caton said</p>
<p>Official interest rates are now at their lowest level since August 1994, and another cut would take them their lowest level since rates were at 4.75 percent between July 1993 and August 1994 when the economy was recovering from recession.</p>
<p>In contrast, the economy has now been growing for the past six years.  </p>
<p>In fact, growth is expected to pick up as 1997 progresses, something which many had thought had ruled out the need for a rate cut to stimulate the economy.</p>
<p>Announcing the rate cut, RBA Governor Ian Macfarlane said that 1997 looked like being stronger than 1996, and also said wages growth was &quot;not yet optimal&quot; for a low inflation economy.</p>
<p>&quot;The rate cut has to be the last in the current cycle and, paradoxically, increases the likelihood of a monetary policy tightening pahse commencing in early 1998, because of the added impetus to economic growth at a time when it was no means clear cut that wages growth is entirely consistent with maintaining  </p>
<p>low inflation,&quot; UBS Australia economist Stephen Roberts said.</p>
<p>The cut may also create the need for an earlier rise than otherwise would have been the case by leading to inflationary pressures from a weaker dollar.</p>
<p>Official rates are now level with those in the U.S., and given the U.S. is in a tightening cycle, the likelihood is that local rates will soon be under those in the U.S. analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;In cutting the policy rate to the same level as U.S. Fed funds, the RBA has deliberately invited currency depreciation,&quot; HSBC Markets chief economist John Edwards said.  </p>
<p>The reason it will weigh on the Australian dollar is that one of its traditional attractions to offshore investors has been its status as a high yielding currency.</p>
<p>In an immediate response to the news, the Australian dollar fell to a three month low of US$0.7665, and just as the rising dollar from mid-1995 helped deliver low inflation, a falling Australian dollar could feed through to higher inflation in 1998.  </p>
<p>&quot;Moving into 1998, the depreciation will show up in rising import prices and an upward shift in inflation, increasing the likelihood of a tightening in the first half of 1998,&quot; Edwards said.</p>
<p>But while the immediate reaction was that another cut was unlikely, economists were reluctant to rule out the prospect entirely, especially if activity data were to turn weak, or inflation continued to surpise.  </p>
<p>&quot;Never rule out another rate cut but we might need some direction from the U.S. combined with exceptional wage and inflation figures,&quot; Colonial State Bank group economist Hans Kunnen said.</p>
<p>-- John Mair, Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
