<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610519" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: HIA says Australia rate cut factored in to outlook.</title>
<headline>HIA says Australia rate cut factored in to outlook.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Housing Industry Association of Australia said on Friday it had factored a potential interest rate cut into its latest housing start figures, which it said showed housing affordability at its highest point this decade.</p>
<p>&quot;Housing affordability reached its highest point this decade in the March quarter of 1997, leading the Housing Industry Association to predict a 13 percent increase in housing starts this year, to 136,700, and a further 13 percent in 1998, to 154,100,&quot; the HIA said in a statement.  </p>
<p>The statement was prepared before the Reserve Bank of Australia announced a cut of half a percent in official interest rates to 5.5 percent. &quot;We fully expected (the RBA) to do this,&quot; HIA spokesman Kevin Randall said.</p>
<p>HIA policy director Christianna Cobbold said a big swing to multi-unit housing was another highlight of the association's latest quarterly building industry review.</p>
<p>Approvals for multi-unit dwellings rose 35 percent over the year to March 1997, compared to a rise of four percent for detached dwellings, Cobbold said in a statement.  </p>
<p>Housing approvals for the quarter to March 1997 were equal to a rate of 139,000 dwellings a year, up 14 percent on the annual rate a year earlier, she Cobbold.</p>
<p>Renovation figures were up four percent in the December quarter of 1996 to an annual rate of A$2.46 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;With interest rates down and economic growth and employment likely to pick up in the year ahead, renovation starts should continue to increase,&quot; Cobbold said.</p>
<p>Work on non-residential building was up six percent in 1996 to more than A$11.6 billion.  </p>
<p>The HIA said it expects work in this sector to rise another five percent this year to about A$12.3 billion, with strong increases in New South Wales, Western Australia and the Australian Capital Territory likely to be partly offset by declines in Victoria and Tasmania.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E61">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
