<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610863" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: China Everbright IHD soars despite denial.</title>
<headline>China Everbright IHD soars despite denial.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shares of red chip China Everbright-IHD Pacific Ltd soared to an all time high on Friday, despite a statement from the company saying it was not in negotiations to acquire a stake in Everbright Bank of China.</p>
<p>The company said it was considering a number of possible acquisitions including some investments held by China Everbright Holdings Co Ltd, one of which was a possible acquisition of equity interest in Everbright Bank of China.</p>
<p>&quot;However, no negotiations whatsoever have been conducted and no binding agreement has been reached in connection with the acquisition,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Shares of China Everbright IHD Pacific were trading HK$1.85, or 18.23 percent, higher at HK$12.00 in Friday afternoon trade, an all-time high for the share.  </p>
<p>Brokers said that in addition to rumours regarding its acquisition of a stake in Everbright Bank of China, there was speculation Everbright IHD would have a new share placement.</p>
<p>&quot;This company has a close connection with the Chinese government and it is said it will receive greater emphasis from the authorities,&quot; said Peter Lai, associate director at OCBC Securities.</p>
<p>Brokers said Everbright IHD was also rumoured to be interested in taking a stake in Theme International.</p>
<p>Shares in Theme were suspended in early afternoon. Prior to the suspension, the share put on HK$0.675 to HK$4.225 on relatively heavy turnover of HK$128.21 million.</p>
<p>Shares in China Everbright International were also trading higher. The share leaped to HK$1.96 before easing to trade HK$0.19, or 11.05 percent, higher at HK$1.92.</p>
<p>China Everbright Technology Ltd also jumped to HK$1.79 then eased to trade HK$0.13 higher at HK$1.74.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6933</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
