<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610892" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK forwarders consider bad debtor database.</title>
<headline>HK forwarders consider bad debtor database.</headline>
<byline>Jim Gilchrist</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Hong Kong Association of Freight Forwarding Agents Ltd (HAFFA) is considering setting up a database to warn members about bad debtors, chairman Anthony Lau told Reuters.</p>
<p>Lau said many members have had to increase the amount of bad debt provision from two to five per cent because of an alarming rise in the number of non-payers in the industry.</p>
<p>&quot;It is getting serious and this is a way of doing something,&quot; Lau said in an interview.</p>
<p>Under the proposed scheme, HAFFA would encourage members to file details of debtors in a centralised computer system to alert fellow freight forwarders of potential credit risks.</p>
<p>Lau said the scheme has potential pitfalls and legal advice is being sought about whether it infringes any personal data protection rules.</p>
<p>&quot;A big operating expense is bad debt provision and we need to help our members and alert them if we can. Some unscrupulous traders are setting up companies and shutting down the next day leaving our members to foot the bill for transporting cargo for a bogus company. If we can limit our members exposure we will have been successful,&quot; Lau added. --Reuters Air Cargo Newsroom Tel+44 171 542-7706 Fax+5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
