<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610837" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan seen cutting buying of Aug-Sep U.S. soybeans.</title>
<headline>Japan seen cutting buying of Aug-Sep U.S. soybeans.</headline>
<byline>Eiichiro Tokumoto</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's edible oil makers are likely to sharply reduce buying of U.S. soybeans for nearby demand because of a higher-than-usual soybean moisture content and wide backwardation in prices, industry officials say.</p>
<p>Oilseed importers are instead considering importing Brazilian soybeans to cover prompt requirements, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;The bottom line is that U.S. soybean prices are too high. It may be wise to wait for the new crop rather than buy expensive old crop soybeans,&quot; said Masahiko Ozawa, manager of Nisshin Oil Mills Ltd's oil seeds and meal department.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll reduce purchases of U.S. soybeans for the August-September period to the minimum level,&quot; Ozawa said.</p>
<p>Nisshin Oil Mills is Japan's largest edible oil maker.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Chicago soybean futures surged in early trading, partly due to the U.S. Agriculture Department's (USDA) weekly export sales figures, which were above trade expectations. The market later lost steam, with spot July closing down 3/4 at $8.46-1/2 a bushel.</p>
<p>And the November contract closed at $6.89, sharply lower compared to spot July.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not surprising that end-users are hesitating about buying old crop, given the wide backwardation,&quot; a soybean trader at a major trade house said.</p>
<p>The United States is expected to start new crop shipments from late October.</p>
<p>Traders said another reason behind their reluctance to buy U.S. soybeans was a higher-than-usual moisture content.</p>
<p>The moisture content of U.S. soybeans from the last crop is between 12 to 12.5 percent, against an upper limit of 13 percent, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's (the moisture) within the upper limit we agreed with the U.S. exporters, but end-users are becoming concerned (about the higher moisture level),&quot; a soybean trader with another trade house said.</p>
<p>Canadian canola is also seeing similar problems and some edible oil makers are considering sending an official complaint to U.S. and Canadian exporters.</p>
<p>Japanese traders are expected to look towards Brazil and Argentina for August-September shipments, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Some will consider buying soybeans from Argentina, even though the quality is worse than Brazilian soybeans,&quot; a second trader said.</p>
<p>Japanese oil crushers are taking an especially cautious stance over imports this year, having imported too much last year due to concerns about tight supplies.</p>
<p>Some local trade houses last year had to cancel contracts for U.S. corn.</p>
<p>Japan imported 1.30 million tonnes of soybean in the first three months of this year, of which 1.21 million tonnes came from the U.S., according to the latest Finance Ministry data.</p>
<p>-- Tokyo Commodities Desk (+81-3-3432-7391)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
