<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="610946" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shenzhen shares end up on technical rebound.</title>
<headline>Shenzhen shares end up on technical rebound.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shenzhen's A and B share indices ended higher due to a technical rebound on Friday after Thursday's plunges, but volatile trading is seen ahead, brokers said.</p>
<p>The foreign currency B share index rose 2.33 points or 1.55 percent to end at 153.19, but turnover fell to HK$99 million from HK$178 million in the previous session.</p>
<p>The domestic A share index rose 3.58 points or 0.85 percent to 425.72 on turnover of 7.0 billion yuan against Thursday's 8.3 billion yuan.  </p>
<p>&quot;The indices rose on bargain-hunting as short-term technical indicators showed stocks looked oversold after yesterday's sharp drops,&quot; an analyst at Shenzhen J&amp;A Securities said.</p>
<p>&quot;The markets have not bottomed out and strong downward pressure looms ahead,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Brokers said the movement of the indices on Monday will depend on whether there are further announcements over the weekend by the government to cool down stock trading.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very clear that Beijing is decisive on dampening share prices and investors will be bearish about the markets in the near future,&quot; an analyst at Central-South Securities said.  </p>
<p>Beijing on Wednesday announced it would ban state enterprises and listed firms from speculative stock trading, in a move clearly aimed at curbing the inflow of &quot;hot money&quot; into the country's overheated stock markets, brokers have said.</p>
<p>The announcement sent share prices in Shenzhen and Shanghai into free fall on Thursday.</p>
<p>On the B share market, newcomer Nanjing Posts &amp; Telecommunication  2468.SZ was the most actively traded with volume of 6.93 million shares, rising HK$0.20 or 4.81 percent to HK$4.36 due to institutional buying, brokers said.  </p>
<p>Nanjing Posts, which issued 100 million B shares at HK$2.43 per share earlier this month, began trading on Thursday.</p>
<p>On the A share market, Shenzhen Development Bank rose 2.41 yuan or 6.58 percent to 39.05 yuan, the most heavily traded counter with 41 million shares changing hands.</p>
<p>Traders said investors happy with the bank's dividend plans, to be confirmed at a shareholders' meeting next Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
