<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611044" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Hong Kong broadcaster raps West on &quot;tensions bias&quot;.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong broadcaster raps West on &quot;tensions bias&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Nick Edwards</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Hong Kong satellite broadcaster accused Western media on Friday of bias and slanted reporting that gave a distorted image of tensions in the run-up to the territory's handover to China next month.</p>
<p>&quot;Bias has distorted the truth. The Western media is very much to be blamed,&quot; said Robert Chua, chairman of China Entertainment Broadcast Ltd (CETV).</p>
<p>&quot;I urge you not to listen to the negative rumours and bad mouthing from some quarters in Hong Kong,&quot; Chua said in a speech to the Singapore Confederation of Industries.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Western concerns are not well founded,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Chua said he thought Sino-British relations had not been damaged by media coverage of the handover so far.</p>
<p>&quot;I cannot speak for the Chinese government, but I think China understands you cannot control the press. I just think they are not pleased with it,&quot; he told Reuters after his speech.</p>
<p>Chua said the duty of the media was &quot;to inform the world and give balanced reporting&quot;, but he argued this could be done without using television images.</p>
<p>&quot;You can say it, why do you have to show it? You do not change the facts of the news, but you can change the scene. What's the problem?&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Chua, who helped launch Hong Kong's TVB television channel, said criticism from the West that this amounted to news censorship was unfair.</p>
<p>&quot;In my view it's not censorship, it's restraint,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chua said in his speech there was too much freedom to display graphic images of sex and violence on Western television and was shown &quot;at the expense of society&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;People ask, will it (the media) be free after 1997? Well, you will have your freedom, but you shouldn't abuse it like they do in the West,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chua, whose CETV is a self-described &quot;no sex, no violence, no news, family-oriented channel&quot;, said his station would not cover violence or disturbances if they broke out during coverage of handover celebrations.</p>
<p>&quot;My station is about positive images,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>CETV was launched in March 1995 and broadcasts to 33 million homes in China. Chua aims to be in 45 million homes by 1998.</p>
<p>Chua said his mission was &quot;to bring good television to Asia&quot; and added Asian programming was vital to the cultural well-being of the region.</p>
<p>&quot;Too much sex and violence will pollute China and Asian values,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chua said investment opportunities in Hong Kong would remain exciting and he had &quot;every confidence in the future of Hong Kong&quot; despite concerns the city's economic vibrancy would fade after the handover at midnight on June 30.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
