<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611172" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: JGBs end weaker on recoveries in Tokyo stocks, dlr.</title>
<headline>JGBs end weaker on recoveries in Tokyo stocks, dlr.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cash and futures Japanese Government Bonds (JGBs) were weaker in late Tokyo trading on Friday due to a recovery in Tokyo share prices and the dollar's rise against the yen.</p>
<p>Key June ended at 123.67, down from Thursday's 123.88 with turnover of 37,423 contracts.</p>
<p>The dollar rose to a high of 116.23 yen from a low of 115.13 yen during Tokyo hours.</p>
<p>Market participation by the four major Japanese brokerage houses was low because of the absence of key traders and fund managers due to seasonal personnel changes.  </p>
<p>On the technical front, liquidation in long-June JGB positions for fresh long positions in the next benchmark September was detected.</p>
<p>A shift in the key contract is expected to take place in early June, which is much later than is normal.</p>
<p>The delay in the benchmark shift is seen caused by holders of short-positions who have been reluctant to close positions for fear of realising losses.</p>
<p>The delay in closing short-positions in June was also behind a wide spread between the outgoing benchmark June and the September, traders said.  </p>
<p>Theoretically, the June-September spread should be around 130 basis points, compared with the current 146 basis, traders said. This indicates that June has more scope to climb, while September's buoyancy is technically limited, they said.</p>
<p>September closed the session at 122.21 on Friday, down from Thursday's 122.59.</p>
<p>But, short-basis trading -- buying futures and selling cash -- which is getting popular among players may lend support to the September, they said.</p>
<p>Japan's main share index, Nikkei 225, ended at 20,009.00 on Friday, up from Thursday's 19,877.39.  </p>
<p>As of 0655 GMT, the yield of the benchmark 182nd 10-year JGB was at 2.580 percent, up from 2.550 percent on Thursday.</p>
<p>It moved in a narrow range of 2.560-2.580 percent, after opening at 2.570 percent.</p>
<p>The JGB market was mostly obsessed with technical factors and failed to react to remarks made by a senior policy maker on Friday.</p>
<p>Bank of Japan Deputy Governor Toshihiko Fukui was quoted by local media as saying that the outlook for Japan's economy remains unclear despite its recovery, and the BOJ's basic policy is to deal with the situation carefully.  </p>
<p>Asked about a request by Rengo, Japan's largest labour group, to raise the discount rate, Fukui said he had told Rengo that he sympathised with the group to a certain extent, but also told the group that it should give consideration to the economic situation of entrepreneurs and smaller enterprises.</p>
<p>---Yoshiko Mori, Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-3-3432-8676</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
