<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611231" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan 3rd qtr aluminium premiums rise five dlrs.</title>
<headline>Japan 3rd qtr aluminium premiums rise five dlrs.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japanese aluminium premiums are being set at $86 to $87 dollars per tonne for deliveries in the July-September quarter, five dollars above the prior quarter's levels, traders said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Some contracts have already settled with a premium of $86/$87 (per tonne),&quot; said one trader at a major trading house.</p>
<p>&quot;Others are still negotiating between $85 and $88.&quot;</p>
<p>Several traders said the first deals struck with Australian aluminium suppliers were with a premium of $86 to $87 per tonne, reflecting bullish sentiment among suppliers against a backdrop of strong global demand.  </p>
<p>This compares with about $82 per tonne in term contracts for deliveries in the April-June quarter. Most contracts are expected to be finalised by the middle of next week.</p>
<p>Japanese spot aluminium premiums over London Metal Exchange cash prices, a benchmark for northeast Asia, rose over the last several months, lifted by strong domestic demand ahead of Japan's sales tax increase on April 1.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, Japanese traders said spot premiums were about $85/$90, reflecting a strong worldwide appetite for the metal that is evident in low warehouse stocks in London and firm U.S. Midwest premiums.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
