<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611340" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK investors make last dash for red hot red chip.</title>
<headline>HK investors make last dash for red hot red chip.</headline>
<byline>Jennifer Genevieve</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Investors made a frantic last minute dash on Friday to cash in on Hong Kong's hottest new stock listing ever, scrambling to beat a noon deadline to hand in applications for red hot &quot;red chip&quot; Beijing Enterprises.</p>
<p>The China-backed conglomerate's initial public offering (IPO) is the talk of the town, generating unprecedented demand from retail investors who queued for hours to get in on the act.</p>
<p>Beijing Enterprises Holdings Ltd launched its initial public offering amid a craze for red chip shares on the stock market ahead of the territory's return to Chinese rule on July 1.</p>
<p>Red chips are Hong Kong-incorporated companies with financial backing from China.</p>
<p>&quot;People were lining up outside the bank before we opened for business (today),&quot; said a spokesman at the Bank of China.</p>
<p>&quot;We set up a special team to handle the applications.&quot;</p>
<p>Bank of China mobilised 200 to 300 employees on Friday to handle the flood of application forms. It normally sets up a team of about 100 to handle popular IPOs.</p>
<p>&quot;This is one of the rare IPOs which has attracted such huge interest,&quot; the Bank of China spokesman said.</p>
<p>At the Standard Chartered Bank in the bustling Mongkok commercial district policemen gathered up the forms from a crowd of several hundred anxious punters who arrived before noon but were still jostling on the doorsteps as the deadline expired.</p>
<p>Police handed their forms into the bank, and the crowds dispersed peacefully. But several groups of elderly investors who ambled up to the bank late were disappointed.</p>
<p>Beijing Enterprises is controlled by the Beijing municipal government, which is expected to inject valuable assets into the company at attractive prices.</p>
<p>The conglomerate owns a stake in Beijing McDonalds, the company that operates the fast-food chain in the city. It also has interests in brewing, toll roads, hotel and retailing.</p>
<p>The subscription level for the Hong Kong offering is expected to top 1,000 times, the highest ever in the territory.</p>
<p>The stock is expected to soar with the grey market price quoted at HK$37-HK$38 compared with an issue price of HK$12.48.</p>
<p>Beijing Enterprises offered 150 million shares in a global initial public offering. Ten percent was offered in Hong Kong and 90 percent to international investors.</p>
<p>Peregrine Capital Ltd, one of the global coordinators of the issue, said it had printed 1.2 million application forms for the Hong Kong offering. A total 400,000 were initially distributed when the offering began on Tuesday but banks ran out twice during the week, forcing underwriters to print more.</p>
<p>Even major Hong Kong companies snapped up shares.</p>
<p>Cheung Kong (Holdings) Ltd, New World Development Co Ltd HK, Kerry Holdings Ltd, Shanghai Industrial Investment (Holdings) Co Ltd, Peregrine Investments Holdings Ltd and Morgan Stanley Group Inc have each subscribed for 5.4 million shares.</p>
<p>Joseph Ng, associate director of corporate finance at Citicorp International, said the frenzy generated by the offering was just an illustration of how Hong Kong people love to speculate and gamble.</p>
<p>&quot;They speculate on everything, from stamps to soccer matches,&quot; he said. &quot;People are taking a chance in the draw. They have nothing to lose -- they just need to spend a couple of hours queuing up for forms.&quot;</p>
<p>The subscription result will be announced on May 28 and the stock will make its market debut on May 29.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong newsroom (852) 2843 6345</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
