<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611328" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Scandal-hit Japanese drug firm posts net loss.</title>
<headline>Scandal-hit Japanese drug firm posts net loss.</headline>
<byline>Yuzo Saeki</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scandal-hit drug firm Green Cross Corp on Friday announced a net loss for last business year and forecast another for next year, adding to concerns about a delayed merger with Yoshitomi Pharmaceutical Industries Ltd.</p>
<p>Green Cross said it posted a parent net loss of 9.1 billion yen ($79.1 million) in the year ended March 31 and forecast a 200 million yen ($1.73 million) net loss for this year.</p>
<p>It said the forecasts were mainly due to the need to make compensation payments to people infected by Green Cross blood products with HIV, the virus that causes AIDS. Former Green Cross executives were indicted last October on charges of professional negligence.</p>
<p>The firm's sales fell sharply after public outrage at the scandal prompted boycotts of its products by many medical institutions.</p>
<p>In February, Green Cross and Yoshitomi, a medium-sized Japanese drug firm, said they would merge on October 1 this year in a bid to salvage Green Cross's operations, but on Wednesday the firms said they would postpone the merger until next April 1.</p>
<p>The firms said the merger was postponed as it would take more time than previously expected to reach an agreement on how the merged company would operate.</p>
<p>Under a plan announced in February, five shares of Green Cross were to be exchanged for three Yoshitomi shares.</p>
<p>The firms said at the time that the merged company would take over responsibility for paying compensation to victims of the scandal, but analysts questioned how Yoshitomi would benefit from such a merger.</p>
<p>Green Cross faces compensation payments totalling about 24 billion yen ($208 million) for supplying blood products that were not heat-treated even though company documents show officials knew there was a risk such products could be infected with HIV.</p>
<p>Green Cross posted parent sales of 71.5 billion yen ($621 million) and a parent current profit of 1.2 billion yen ($10.4 million) in 1996/97.</p>
<p>Current profit is pre-tax and includes gains and losses from investments, though it does not take into account extraordinary losses such as that of 11.1 billion yen ($96.5 million) posted by Green Cross last year in order to make compensation payments.</p>
<p>Green Cross forecast its parent sales would rise to 77.0 billion yen ($669 million) this business year and its parent current profit to three billion yen ($26.0 million), but it said it would still post a net loss due to the compensations payments.</p>
<p>Yoshitomi said on Friday that its parent current profit rose 3.6 percent to 13.4 billion yen ($116 million) in 1996/97, while its parent sales increased 6.2 percent to 107.9 billion yen ($938 million).</p>
<p>It forecast parent sales of 114.0 billion yen ($991 million) and a parent current profit of 14.5 billion yen ($126 million) in the year to March 1998.</p>
<p>($1=115 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C1511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
