<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611331" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: New HK poll rules seen denting democrats' chances.</title>
<headline>New HK poll rules seen denting democrats' chances.</headline>
<byline>Dominic Lau</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Hong Kong election rules proposed in Beijing will severely dent prospects of democrats winning seats in the legislature after China takes over, politicians and analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like the proposals are very undemocratic and unfair,&quot; pro-democracy politican Emily Lau told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The pro-democracy camp have very little chance anyway with only 20 seats being directly elected, but on top of that China also wants to manipulate the result by changing the voting system,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Meeting in the Chinese capital, the 150-strong Preparatory Committee, setting up Hong Kong's post-colonial political structures, unveiled proposals on Thursday for rules on 1998 elections and was set to finalise arrangements later on Friday.</p>
<p>Western countries are anxious to see that Hong Kong has assured civil liberty, an independent judiciary and free elections in the new era under communist-ruled China.</p>
<p>The proposals call for a change in the current electoral laws for the 60-seat legislature after Britain hands Hong Kong back to China at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>Under the plan, 20 directly elected seats will be filled from geographical constituencies in either multi-seat single-vote polls or proportional representation, instead of the current first-pass-the-post voting system.</p>
<p>Thirty seats are allocated to business and professional bodies in what are known as &quot;functional constitutencies&quot;.</p>
<p>The remaining 10, another major bone of contention with the pro-democracy camp in Hong Kong, will be chosen by an 800-strong selection committee with a highly complicated makeup if the proposals are implemented.</p>
<p>&quot;The objective of having multi-seat single-vote or proportional representation is to limit the chances of success of the pro-democracy camp and to help some unpopular parties to get more seats,&quot; political analyst Andy Ho told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;No matter what changes they make for the 1998 election, it will not be as democratic as the one held in 1995,&quot; Ho said.</p>
<p>The 1995 polls for the Legislative Council held under an enlarged franchise ushered in by Governor Chris Patten's electoral reforms was the first time all 60-seats were elected through direct and indirect polls.</p>
<p>The present legislature comprises 20 directly elected geographical seats based on first-past-the-post voting, 30 functional constituency seats, and 10 election committee seats. The election committee was chosen by elected local councillors.</p>
<p>Beijing has said the first polls to be held under Chinese rule will probably be in the first half of 1998.</p>
<p>But meanwhile it is installing an appointed &quot;provisional legislature&quot; on July 1 to replace the elected Legco.</p>
<p>Patten said in London on Thursday it was &quot;very important that free and democratic elections should be held as soon as possible after the handover&quot;.</p>
<p>Another analyst said the process of choosing the 800-strong selection committee was confusing and lacked transparency.</p>
<p>It was likely the popular Democratic Party would be sidelined in the 800-strong caucus, as it was by the 400-strong selection committee that chose the territory's future post-colonial leader Tung Chee-hwa and the provisional legislature members last December, the analyst said.</p>
<p>The new selection committee, if the proposal goes ahead, will be drawn from four social sectors: business and finance; professionals; labour, grassroots and religious groups; and politicans. Each sector would provide 200 committee members.</p>
<p>The Democratic Party, which dominated the popular vote in the 1995 poll, will see its 19 legislators thrown out of office after July 1 when China installs the provisional legislature, along with a number of independent pro-democracy members.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
