<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611478" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore noon shares soft on lack of incentives.</title>
<headline>Singapore noon shares soft on lack of incentives.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Singapore shares languished at noon on Friday hamstrung by a lack of incentives with funds wary about a potential rise in interest rates, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The interest rate market seems to be trending upwards and if that is the case, investors will refrain from buying,&quot; a dealer with a foreign brokerage said.</p>
<p>At the midday break, the Straits Times Industrials Index (STII) was down 2.74 points at 2,058.97. Advancing issues beat decliners by 145 against 122 on a volume of 115 million shares.</p>
<p>Nibbling of property counters was fuelled by optimism after high prices were seen for the latest government sale of land.  </p>
<p>Developers were willing to pay high prices for land to build executive condominiums, boosting construction-related issues.</p>
<p>The SES Property Index gained 5.24 points at 688.68.</p>
<p>City Developments rose Singapore 20 cents to S$12.80, and hotel and property group Orchard Parade was up 10 cents to S$3.38. Malaysian construction company Lien Hoe rose nine cents to S$1.70 and Keppel Land was up eight cents to S$4.06.</p>
<p>Profit taking continued to dampen Singapore blue chips with bank counters DBS, UOB and OUB foreign shedding 10 cents to S$8.65, S$15.00, and S$9.85 respectively.</p>
<p>--Jacqueline Wong (65 8703080)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
