<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611534" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Top bankers to resign in Japan 'sokaiya' scandal.</title>
<headline>Top bankers to resign in Japan 'sokaiya' scandal.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank Ltd (DKB) said on Friday that its president and chairman would resign to take responsibility for a racketeer scandal which has already brought down top executives of Japan's biggest brokerage.</p>
<p>DKB, one of Japan's leading commercial banks, said president Katsuhiko Kondo would be replaced by Ichiro Fujita, who is currently vice president. Another vice president, Yoshiharu Mani, will replace current chairman Tadashi Okuda.</p>
<p>The executives are stepping down in a gesture of remorse over the bank's links to an alleged corporate extortionist, or &quot;sokaiya&quot;, who has been accused of taking illegal payoffs from top brokerage Nomura Securities Co Ltd.</p>
<p>The scandal has broken in the middle of a campaign by Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto's government to clean up the country's business ethics ahead of &quot;Big Bang&quot; deregulation of its financial markets to make them globally competitive.</p>
<p>Hashimoto had said on Thursday that the bank executives' reported plans to resign over the affair would be &quot;sneaky&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's sneaky (for the DKB leadership) to step down to take the blame,&quot; Hashimoto said. &quot;Their resigning does not settle the problem. They should face up to the case until investigations make headway.&quot;</p>
<p>Finance Minister Hiroshi Mitsuzuka reiterated the remarks on Friday, before DKB's announcement, telling reporters: &quot;Such resignations would not mean the bank has carried out its responsibilities.&quot;</p>
<p>The executives' resignations will take effect after a shareholders' meeting on June 27. Both Kondo and Okuda will become advisers to DKB, with Kondo keeping a seat on the board and Okuda retained in a non-executive capacity.</p>
<p>DKB also said five advisers to the bank who had served in the posts of chairman or president in the past would also step down. They include Kuniji Miyazaki, who was president when the bank made loans to the &quot;sokaiya&quot; racketeer at the centre of the Nomura investigation, Ryuichi Koike.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, the bank's premises were raided by prosecutors investigating a web of links between the racketeer and Japan's financial world, in the latest of a series of scandals to besmirch the reputation of Japanese business.</p>
<p>DKB has not commented in detail about its relationship with Koike but has said it regrets bringing the raids upon itself. The bank was due to hold a news conference later on Friday at which it was likely to be quizzed over its racketeer ties.</p>
<p>Prosecutors suspect the &quot;sokaiya&quot; was given financial favours by both DKB and Nomura to stop him disrupting their shareholders' meetings by asking sensitive business questions.</p>
<p>Japan's Commercial Code bans companies from making such payments.</p>
<p>Nomura's president and several other top executives have already resigned over the scandal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
