<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611530" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK activists set off for disputed isles - again.</title>
<headline>HK activists set off for disputed isles - again.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A group of 20 Hong Kong activists set off by ship on a protest voyage to disputed islands in the East China Sea on Friday after rough seas and seasickness forced them back to port on Thursday night.</p>
<p>The group had sailed off originally in high spirits, chanting they would &quot;fight to the death&quot;, but the weather forced them to stop and seek refuge in a bay in Hong Kong's New Territories, where they spent the night.</p>
<p>The members of the Action Committee for Defending the Diaoyu Islands plan to land on the small, uninhabited islands -- known as the Diaoyus in China and Senkakus in Japan -- as a show of support for China's claims of sovereignty.</p>
<p>Taiwan and Japan also claim the islands.</p>
<p>The activists plan first to go to Taiwan's southern Kaohsiung port where they will be joined by a group of Taiwanese supporters. The protesters will then sail to the isles and camp there overnight.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for the Hong Kong group said the timing of their arrival at the islands depended on weather conditions.</p>
<p>Earlier in May, a Japanese rightist group led by legislator Shingo Nishimura landed on the islands and raised a Japanese flag, triggering the latest round of protests.</p>
<p>Last year, there were angry anti-Japanese protests in Taiwan, China, Hong Kong and a number of Chinese communities around the world after another ultra-rightwing Japanese group erected a makeshift lighthouse on one of the islands.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
