<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611580" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Asia Metals - Aluminium premiums for Q3 seen higher.</title>
<headline>Asia Metals - Aluminium premiums for Q3 seen higher.</headline>
<byline>Rene Pastor</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asian third quarter aluminium supply contract premiums are seen rising on the back of robust market demand, dealers said on Friday.</p>
<p>Benchmark premiums in Japan will probably range between $88-$90 a tonne CIF from $82-$85 a tonne in the second quarter. Talks are expected to be completed next week when Australian producers present their offer to Japanese end-users, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;What I understand is that premiums in Japan will be at $88 to $90. I don't think the Australians will offer the Japanese premiums below $88,&quot; an aluminium dealer told Reuters.  </p>
<p>&quot;The contracts should be done at around that level,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>Brisk demand in the can, automobile and construction sectors has fuelled aluminium consumption across the region, industry officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;Once one Japanese company signs up, its easier for the others to join up,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>Premiums in the rest of the region are also set to rise in line with the higher charges being levied on Japanese firms.</p>
<p>Taiwanese premiums are seen rising to $90 a tonne CIF Kaoshiung and Keelung from $85 previously.  </p>
<p>&quot;It would certainly not go below $90 in Taiwan,&quot; one dealer added.</p>
<p>In South Korea, premiums could reach about $90-$95 a tonne CIF Pusan from $88 in the second quarter.</p>
<p>Indonesian premiums are pegged to increase to between $95-$100 a tonne CIF Jakarta against $85 previously.</p>
<p>Dealers said more companies in Indonesia may sign up for supply contracts after getting badly burned in the second quarter when they were forced to pay steep premiums for spot purchases.  </p>
<p>&quot;The high premiums in the second quarter broke like a wave over the Indonesians. We should see some of them sign up for the third quarter,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>Premiums in the Philippines, where aluminium consumption is also rising strongly, are seen increasing to $90-$95 a tonne CIF Manila from $85-$90, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Demand in the Far East is very healthy. If you look at the economic outlook of the countries here, the demand is there. It's not a very bad business,&quot; an aluminium trader said.</p>
<p>Traders said the brisk demand in aluminium can be seen in the sharp drawdown of stocks on the London Metal Exchange (LME).  </p>
<p>LME aluminium stocks reached 758,525 tonnes on Thursday, down 81,325 tonnes from the level around the middle of April.</p>
<p>&quot;The negotiations on the premiums are very important. Some of the physical traders are waiting for that to conclude before making their next move,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>Base metal business in the rest of the region remained active, fuelled by the sharp fluctuations of the yen against the U.S. dollar and the recent rally on the LME.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen some good activity in copper although the market is concerned at the volatility in the market,&quot; a dealer said.  </p>
<p>Dealers said the current high level of zinc prices on the LME has also triggered renewed interest from Chinese sellers.</p>
<p>They estimate about 5,000 tonnes of zinc will arrive this week in Singapore from China, although one dealer claimed 6,000 tonnes will be unloaded here later on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The problem is that most of the stuff will probably not be placed on warrant at the LME (warehouse),&quot; one said.</p>
<p>An estimated 15,000-20,000 tonnes of zinc remains off-warrant in Singapore.</p>
<p>-- Singapore Newsroom (65-8703305)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
