<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611659" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan stocks end mixed in slipping turnover.</title>
<headline>Taiwan stocks end mixed in slipping turnover.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan stocks closed mixed in narrow Friday trading as some investors took quick profits against the market's two-day rebound. Brokers said they expected the index slowly to test strong resistance at 8,250 points .</p>
<p>The index finished a scant 6.28 points or 0.08 percent lower at 8,144.38, back from an intra-day 8,192.91 high. Turnover was a slack T$77.7 billion, compared with Thursday's T$90 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;Profit-taking pressure gets heavier as the index approaches 8,200 points,&quot; said National Securities fund manager Allen Huang. &quot;Investors' confidence has improved but people are not bullish.&quot;  </p>
<p>Brokers said 8,250 points stood as strong technical and psychological resistance in the near term.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like the market needs a longer consolidation period,&quot; Huang said.</p>
<p>The late morning announcement of an unexpectedly low 2.59 percent unemployment rate in April had no immediate impact on the market, brokers said.</p>
<p>Financial shares were weak, falling 0.81 percent.</p>
<p>Two bank shares that transferred directly to Taiwan's main stock exchange from the fledgling over-the-counter market fell sharply as profit-taking soured their debut, brokers said.  </p>
<p>Newcomer Dah Ah Bank  2829.TW plunged T$1.9 or 5.09 percent to T$35.4, while Grand Commercial Bank was down T$1.7 or 4.57 percent to T$35.5.</p>
<p>Banking stocks likely would attract less interest from investors compared with strong but volatile electronic shares.</p>
<p>&quot;Unlike banking and other sectors, electronics' upside potential is unlimited,&quot; Huang said.</p>
<p>Albert Lin, research head of Golden Securities, said: &quot;Only electronics can lead the market's uptrend.&quot;</p>
<p>The whole electronic index rose 0.73 percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
