<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611743" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesian election campaign enters final day.</title>
<headline>Indonesian election campaign enters final day.</headline>
<byline>Ian MacKenzie</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia entered the final day of its general election campaign on Friday, to be followed by a five-day cooling-off period before national and local polls next Thursday in the world's fourth most populous nation.</p>
<p>The Moslem-oriented United Development Party (PPP) was campaiging on Java, but its leaders called a halt to rallies in Jakarta after violence involving PPP supporters and backers of the ruling Golkar party in the capital earlier in the week.</p>
<p>PPP leader Asmail Hasan Metareum was addressing a final rally at Serang, 75 km (47 miles) west of Jakarta.</p>
<p>Golkar was on the hustings on Borneo island and remote Sulawesi, and the badly split Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI) in Sumatra, the holiday resort of Bali and the adjacent Nusa Tenggara islands.</p>
<p>The three parties are the only ones legally permitted to contest the poll held every five years for 425 elected seats in the House of Representatives. The other 75 seats are reserved for the military, whose members do not vote.</p>
<p>The official Antara news agency said local authorities in Serang were concerned about a possible influx of PPP supporters from Jakarta.</p>
<p>&quot;We are taking measures to anticipate such a possibility and are ready, among other things, to intercept the crowds...,&quot; it quoted police Lieutenant-Colonel Sudarsono as saying.</p>
<p>Security was also tight in central Java, another area where the campaign has been marred by violence primarily between PPP and Golkar partisans.</p>
<p>Former PDI leader Megawati Sukarnoputri, ousted as party chief by a government-backed faction in June last year, told supporters on Thursday she would not vote in the election.</p>
<p>She also told them not to vote for the government-recognised wing of the PDI which she said was illegal and unconstitutional. But she stopped short of making an illegal call for a complete election boycott.</p>
<p>The secretary-general of the General Elections Institute, Suryatna Subrata, has called on the country's 125 million eligible voters to exercise their political right and cast their ballots.</p>
<p>He was speaking hours after Megawati made her statement wearing a white dress -- the recogised colour of &quot;golput&quot; or &quot;white group&quot;, who register dissent by spoiling their ballots or abstaining.</p>
<p>Golkar officials in a briefing before the campaign put the size of &quot;golput&quot; in the last elections in 1992 at about three or four percent. The overall turnout in 1992 was around 90 percent.</p>
<p>Political analysts said &quot;golput&quot; would have no effect on the outcome of the current election in which Golkar -- in power under President Suharto for 30 years -- is looking to push its share of the vote over 70 percent from 68 percent in 1992.</p>
<p>The PPP got 17 percent and the PDI 15 percent in the last polls, but the PPP is also hoping to pick up extra votes as a result of the split in the PDI.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
