<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611741" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Shanghai B shares down at noon on weak sentiment.</title>
<headline>Shanghai B shares down at noon on weak sentiment.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Shanghai B share index was down slightly at midday on Friday on weak sentiment, pulled down by some big stocks including Lujiazui Finance and Trade Zone Development and Inner Mongolia Erdos Cashmere Products, brokers said.</p>
<p>The B index fell 0.583 points or 0.71 percent to 82.000 points on volume of 8.5 million shares worth $6.73 million.</p>
<p>Profit-taking in Lujiazui and the poor performance of Erdos's new 100 million B shares which debuted today dragged the index down, brokers said.  </p>
<p>Market sentiment has been hurt by the latest government crackdown, and most investors have no interest buying, rather looking for opportunities to liquidate their positions, brokers said.</p>
<p>On Thursday, Beijing imposed new curbs on the trading of shares by state-owned companies, barring them from making &quot;speculative&quot; deals.</p>
<p>&quot;Capital is seen retreating from the market on the new clampdown measures and listed firms are seen still speculating in stocks in which they have built large positions during the long bull run,&quot; one broker said.  </p>
<p>&quot;After the index falls, the market will bottom out in the short term if there is no further negative news,&quot; another broker said.</p>
<p>Of 43 B shares, 37 traded with 21 down, two flat and 14 up.</p>
<p>Shanghai Jinjiang Tower was the biggest loser on one speculative selling shot, plunging $0.034 or 10.00 percent to $0.306 on volume of 100 shares.</p>
<p>Inner Mongolia Erdos Cashmere, the most actively traded counter in the morning, followed on the weak performance of its 100 million new B shares which debuted today, slipping $0.078 or 8.51 percent to $0.838 on volume of 1.9 million shares.  </p>
<p>Lujiazui was the second most actively traded on heavy profit-taking, as its price had been pushed too high on speculative buying over the past few weeks, shedding $0.006 or 0.43 percent to $1.364 on volume of 1.8 million shares, brokers said.</p>
<p>Shanghai's A share index staged a technical rebound thanks to institutional support for stocks with a heavy index weighting, but market sentiment was still weak, brokers said.</p>
<p>The index put on 19.098 points or 1.48 percent to 1,309.211 points on volume of 239.9 million shares worth 3.6 billion yuan.  </p>
<p>The SSE30 blue chip index rose 110.186 points or 2.92 percent to 3,884.168 points.</p>
<p>Beijing Double Crane Pharmaceutical  600062.SS was the biggest winner on bargain-hunting, soaring 1.30 yuan or 9.38 percent to 15.15 yuan on volume of 7.6 million shares.</p>
<p>--Shanghai newsroom (86-21) 6279-7004</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
