<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611771" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: JGBs little changed after paring earlier losses.</title>
<headline>JGBs little changed after paring earlier losses.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The key June 10-year Japanese government bond futures contract was easier by midday Friday, but had pared a large portion of early morning losses due to buy backs, traders said.</p>
<p>Rolling over of short positions from the June to the September contract may have helped lift the key futures contract off the morning's low, a trader for a city bank's securities unit said.</p>
<p>&quot;The September is weak today, and this may be an indication that traders are continuing to roll over short positions from the June to the September,&quot; the trader said.  </p>
<p>The June stood at 123.86, down slightly from the previous day's close of 123.88. Turnover was 24,237 contracts.</p>
<p>The September stood at 122.39 by midday, down from Thursday's close of 122.59. Turnover was 8,651 contracts.</p>
<p>A shift in the benchmark status from the June to the September is likely to take place around the middle of next week, a trader for a trust bank's securities unit said.</p>
<p>There was some scattered buying of cash bonds by investors this morning, the first trader said.</p>
<p>But sentiment in the cash bond market is still weak after a massive round of selling on Wednesday, the trader said.  </p>
<p>There was vague market talk that investors such as city banks and life insurers had sold cash JGBs in large amounts on Wednesday, and such rumours weighed on cash bonds, the first trader said.</p>
<p>The benchmark 182nd JGB yield stood at 2.560 percent as of 0244 GMT, up slightly from Thursday's close of 2.550 percent.</p>
<p>The June was weak earlier in the morning due to the firmness of Tokyo share prices.</p>
<p>In the Tokyo stock market, the key Nikkei 225 average stood at 20,020.40 by midday, up 143.01 points or 0.72 percent from the previous day's close.  </p>
<p>JGBs edged upwards after falling as low as 123.65 in early trade, as they received some support from an outright bond buying operation by the Bank of Japan this morning, said a trader for an agricultural financial institution.</p>
<p>The BOJ earlier offered to buy 100 billion yen in bonds outright in an agreement starting on May 28.</p>
<p>The Finance Ministry offered 120 billion yen worth of one percent two-year government notes this morning.</p>
<p>Since two-year notes are mostly sold to retail investors, the offer is unlikely to have much impact on the market, the trader for an agricultural financial institution said.  </p>
<p>Retail investors are likely to take a favourable view of the rise in the coupon rate to one percent from 0.7 percent at the previous auction, a regional bank trader said.</p>
<p>The auction results for the two-year notes are due at 2:30 p.m. (0530 GMT) today.</p>
<p>Bank of Japan Governor Yasuo Matsushita and Finance Minister Hiroshi Mitsuzuka are scheduled to deliver speeches at a meeting of national credit associations which is due to start at 3:00 p.m. (0600 GMT).</p>
<p>-- Masayuki Kitano, Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-3-5473-3748</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
