<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611758" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Yamaichi Sec refuses support for Ogawa Sec.</title>
<headline>Yamaichi Sec refuses support for Ogawa Sec.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Yamaichi Securities Co Ltd said on Friday that it had rejected a request from its troubled affiliate Ogawa Securities Co Ltd for financial support because of Ogawa's financial condition.</p>
<p>However, Yamaichi, one of Japan's &quot;Big Four&quot; brokerages, said that it would provide funds to protect Ogawa Securities' customers.  </p>
<p>Earlier on Friday, Ogawa Securities filed an application with the Finance Ministry's regional office to close down its operations on May 26 because it was unable to obtain financial aid from Yamaichi.</p>
<p>Osaka-based Ogawa Securities had been ordered by the Finance Ministry to make management changes after it fell into financial difficulties.  </p>
<p>An official of Yamaichi Securities said it would have required more than 2.5 billion yen to buy Ogawa shares through a third-party allotment in order to boost Ogawa's capital-safety ratio to 200 percent.</p>
<p>The official said Ogawa's capital-safety ratio was expected to decline sharply from the 140 percent as of the end of March.</p>
<p>The capital-safety ratio is that of net capital and latent profit on securities holdings against risk assets and possible losses from the securities business.</p>
<p>A ratio 150 percent is considered an early warning level and if it falls below 120 percent, financial authorities can order brokerages to improve their operations under the Securities and Exchange Law.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
