<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611753" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: PRESS DIGEST - Vietnam - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Vietnam - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the official Vietnamese press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>VIETNAM NEWS</p>
<p>-- Vietnam has said it hopes Britain and the Hongkong authorities will accelerate the repatriation of Vietnamese boatpeople so that the last of them can be brought home before the handover to China on July 1.</p>
<p>-- Nguyen Van Kiem, head of Vietnam's private-sector flagship Huy Hoang Company, has denied rumours of a cashflow crisis, saying the company is not in danger of going bankrupt and has entered into joint-venture projects with several state-owned companies.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SAIGON TIMES DAILY</p>
<p>-- Saigon Postel Corporation has been authorized to set up a telecom network and services including mobile phones, wireless phones and paging services.</p>
<p>--  Consulting firm AIC Maunsell Vietnam has presented three alternative plans for linking the centre of Ho Chi Minh City with the Thu Thiem peninsula by bridge or tunnel.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>NHAN DAN</p>
<p>-- Communist Party Secretary General Do Muoi and his delegation were welcomed with a 21-gun salute after arriving in Rangoon on Thursday for an official visit to Myanmar.</p>
<p>-- Vietnam and Poland have agreed to expand cooperation in various fields, including shipbuilding, mining and aquatic and fruit processing.</p>
<p>-- Australia's Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering has been endorsed by Vietnamese and Australian governments to build the My Thuan bridge over the Mekong River.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HANOI MOI</p>
<p>-- Deputy Prime minister Nguyen Khanh has called for stronger measures to crack down on the trafficking of women and children, who are sometimes duped into the sex trade.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SAIGON GIAI PHONG</p>
<p>-- Ho Chi Minh City has been authorized by the government to expand its administrative reform for &quot;one door, one-stamp&quot; procedures.</p>
<p>-- Prime Minister Vo Van Kiet arrived in the Czech Republic for an official visit on Thursday.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
