<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611742" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shenzhen shares up at noon, investors wary.</title>
<headline>Shenzhen shares up at noon, investors wary.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shenzhen's A and B share indices staged a modest technical rebound at midday on Friday, but investors were cautious after Thursday's plunges, brokers said.</p>
<p>The foreign currency B share index rose 0.95 points or 0.63 percent to 151.80 on thin turnover of HK$37 million.</p>
<p>The domestic A share index gained 0.85 points or 0.20 percent to 422.99, on low turnover of 3.1 billion yuan.  </p>
<p>&quot;The rebound will not be much stronger later today given the thin turnover,&quot; an analyst at Central-South Securities said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very clear that Beijing wants to dampen share prices and investors will be bearish about the markets in the near future,&quot; the analyst said.</p>
<p>Beijing on Wednesday announced it would ban state enterprises and listed firms from speculative stock trading, in a move aimed at curbing the inflow of &quot;hot money&quot; into the country's overheated stock markets, according to brokers.</p>
<p>The fresh crackdown sent share prices in Shenzhen and Shanghai into a free fall on Thursday.  </p>
<p>&quot;Thursday's sharp falls presaged a bearish trend, and the Shenzhen B share index is seeking support at the 150-point level,&quot; an analyst at China Guotai Securities said.</p>
<p>&quot;But it is still too early to judge whether a long-term downward correction has begun as China's economy has been faring well,&quot; the Central-South analyst said.</p>
<p>A wait-and-see mood will continue to dominate trading in the afternoon, analysts said.  </p>
<p>On the B share market, newcomer Nanjing Posts &amp; Telecommunication  2468.SZ was the most actively traded with volume of 2.8 million shares, rising HK$0.14 or 3.37 percent to HK$4.30. Its issue price on Thursday was HK$2.43 per share.</p>
<p>Nanjing Posts began trading in Shenzhen on Thursday.</p>
<p>On the A share market, Shenzhen Development Bank rebounded 1.66 yuan to 38.30 yuan on volume of 17.8 million shares.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
