<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611768" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK's Tung prefers own flat to governor's mansion.</title>
<headline>HK's Tung prefers own flat to governor's mansion.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's future leader Tung Chee-hwa, who refuses to move into the colonial governor's mansion because of bad &quot;fung shui&quot;, has decided to stay in his own flat, newspapers reported on Friday.</p>
<p>Chinese househunters pay crucial attention to principles of fung shui --literally wind and water -- in choosing the design and location of a building.</p>
<p>The Hong Kong press said Tung plans to take over the apartment next door to the one he owns in a district overlooking Hong Kong's harbour and knock down the walls to create a single large residence from two.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman at his office declined comment beyond saying: &quot;An announcement will be made soon on Mr Tung's official residence.&quot;</p>
<p>Tung last year said he would not move into Government House, now occupied by Chris Patten, the 28th and last British governor of Hong Kong, because it was crowded and because Chinese fung shui practioners, or geomancers, had ruled it inauspicious.</p>
<p>Fung shui is an age-old Chinese belief that harmony with the elements brings good fortune and wards off bad luck.</p>
<p>Hong Kong reverts to China on July 1.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
