<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611729" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Burmese opposition carries on despite arrests.</title>
<headline>Burmese opposition carries on despite arrests.</headline>
<byline>Deborah Charles</byline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Aung San Suu Kyi's democracy party has started to hold meetings despite Burmese government attempts to block them by arresting 60 members and confining dozens more to their homes, a party official said on Friday.</p>
<p>A top National League for Democracy (NLD) official told Reuters by telephone from Rangoon that so far about 60 senior members from the provinces had been arrested by the military government as they headed to the capital to attend the meeting.</p>
<p>Several dozen others were under virtual house arrest after being told by authorities not to leave their homes.</p>
<p>But the official said some senior NLD members and party organisers had arrived in Rangoon, and the party had already begun holding meetings to plan and discuss policy.</p>
<p>The official party gathering was scheduled for May 27-28, to coincide with the seventh anniversary of the NLD's landslide 1990 electoral victory. About 300 top NLD members and party organisers have been invited to attend the function.</p>
<p>The NLD has had few opportunities to gather in a large group since it won the 1990 election. The ruling State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) never recognised the result of the poll and has cracked down on the elected members of parliament (MPs) and party members ever since.</p>
<p>&quot;We hurriedly decided to take advantage of the fact that some members had arrived, and yesterday we held a preliminary seminar to discuss political business,&quot; the NLD official said.</p>
<p>&quot;Today we will do our best to gather again at party headquarters at Daw Suu's house,&quot; he said. &quot;But some people who have arrived in Rangoon have been followed by police and told if they do not return to their respective homes they are liable to be arrested.&quot;</p>
<p>He said many opted to stay in Rangoon at undisclosed places. Some are staying in Suu Kyi's compound. She could not be reached for comment as her telephone line appears to have been cut.</p>
<p>The recent arrests has drawn widespread global condemnation, with many governments calling on the SLORC to immediately and unconditionally free the NLD members.</p>
<p>The NLD official said those who had been arrested or detained in their homes were mainly from the provinces, and so far the senior NLD members in Rangoon had not been affected.</p>
<p>&quot;The members, MPs and organising committee members in Rangoon have not been touched by the SLORC for the time being,&quot; he said. &quot;But I don't know if they will let us go in to her house on the 27th.&quot;</p>
<p>He also said he expected there would be more arrests.</p>
<p>Last year, 261 NLD members, mostly MPs, were arrested ahead of a similar party gathering. But the meeting took place anyway and Suu Kyi announced the NLD planned to continue its efforts to bring democracy to Burma despite the crackdowns.</p>
<p>The SLORC has not confirmed or denied the arrests and detentions, but on Thursday said it was taking tough measures in order to ensure peace and stability. It said the NLD was trying to &quot;rock the boat&quot; and create problems in the country.</p>
<p>The SLORC made similar comments last year. Although it released most of the NLD members it arrested last May, some were charged and given long jail terms. Others, mainly MPs, were forced to sign papers saying they would resign from the party.</p>
<p>Burma's military government arrested at least 2,000 democracy activists in 1996, but later released many of them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BURMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
