<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611754" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Top DKB executives to quit over racketeer scandal.</title>
<headline>Top DKB executives to quit over racketeer scandal.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank Ltd (DKB) said on Friday that its president and chairman would resign to take managerial responsibility for its involvement in a racketeer scandal.</p>
<p>DKB, one of Japan's top commercial banks, said president Katsuhiko Kondo would be replaced by Ichiro Fujita, who is currently vice president. Another vice president, Yoshiharu Mani, will replace current chairman Tadashi Okuda.  </p>
<p>The executives are stepping down in a gesture of remorse over the bank's links to an alleged corporate extortionist, or &quot;sokaiya&quot;, who has been accused of taking illegal payoffs from Japan's top brokerage, Nomura Securities Co Ltd.</p>
<p>Their resignations will take effect after a shareholders' meeting on June 27. Both Kondo and Okuda will become advisers to DKB, with Kondo retaining a seat on the board and Okuda retained in a non-executive capacity.</p>
<p>DKB also said five advisers to the bank who had served in the posts of chairman or president in the past would also step down. They include Kuniji Miyazaki, who was president when the bank made questionable loans to the &quot;sokaiya&quot; racketeer at the centre of the Nomura investigation, Ryuichi Koike.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, Dai-Ichi Kangyo was raided by prosecutors investigating a web of links between the racketeer and Japan's financial world, in the latest of a series of scandals to besmirch the reputation of Japanese business.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
