<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611769" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Thirdliners liven up sluggish Philippine bourse.</title>
<headline>Thirdliners liven up sluggish Philippine bourse.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thirdliners took charge in early trading at the Philippine Stock Exchange as local investors snapped them up in lieu of the slow-moving blue chips and major secondliners, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;They're alive again. They've been resurrected,&quot; Julie Ann Villena, an analyst at Magnum International Securities Inc, said.</p>
<p>She said local investors, for lack of impetus to take a long-term position in a very tentative market, decided to play the penny stocks for short-term gains.</p>
<p>&quot;People are trying to recoup their losses in recent weeks,&quot; Villena added.</p>
<p>Leading the thirdliners were newly-converted holding firms Atok Big Wedge A which jumped 65 centavos or 24.53 percent to 3.3 pesos and Acoje Holdings which gained two centavos or 13.89 percent to 21 centavos.</p>
<p>Other big movers includeed oil explorer Pacifica Inc A which went up 13.04 percent or 0.75 centavos to 6.50 centavos and mining firm Itogon Suyoc Mines Inc which gained 2.25 centavos to 25.71 percent to 11 centavos.</p>
<p>Michelle Bautista, an investment analyst at Asian Capital Equities, said the trend is typical of a short-term technical rally.</p>
<p>&quot;In a technical rally like this, it's usually the thirdliners which are the first to go off,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Bautista said the even if blue chips have already reached their oversold levels, earning potentials were still in doubt following the release of unimpressive first quarter financial results.</p>
<p>-- Manila Newsroom (63 2) 841-8938 Fax 817-6267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
