<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611861" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Dollar slips vs yen partly on remarks by EPA.</title>
<headline>Dollar slips vs yen partly on remarks by EPA.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>ASIAN FOREX ACTIVITY:</p>
<p>0142 GMT --*Dollar fell against yen in mid-morning Tokyo due to profit-taking by overseas operators and stop-loss sales at 115.50 yen, dealers said.</p>
<p>*Dealers said dollar's dips below support of 115.60 yen might be triggered by remarks by Economic Planning Agency (EPA) Minister Taro Aso that there are some companies which can cope with exchange rate of 105 yen to dollar.</p>
<p>*Aso said other companies may not be able to cope with rate of 105 yen.  </p>
<p>*Sell orders by Japanese exporters at 116.25 yen, ahead of strong resistance at 116.50 yen, put downward pressure on dollar in early trade, said a U.S. bank dealer.</p>
<p>*Traders still mixed about direction of dollar after recent volatile movements, with dealers focusing on where dollar will finish ahead of weekend.</p>
<p>*&quot;If the dollar is below 115 yen later in the day, there is a greater risk that it will fall back next week,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>*Some said trading likely to be relatively stable ahead of long weekend in U.K. and U.S., while others said price movements may be exaggerated by thin market conditions.  </p>
<p>0003 GMT</p>
<p>*Dollar down vs yen on interbank dealer selling partly due to fall in Aussie/yen in Tokyo after Reserve Bank of Australia (RBA) cut official cash interest rate by 0.5 percentage point to 5.5 percent. Aussie/yen around 88.96/06 yen at 0011 GMT.</p>
<p>*Australian dollar slumped against U.S. dollar to 3-month low on rate cut in Sydney.</p>
<p>*A trust bank dealer said interbank dealers and possibly some securites houses were keen to sell Aussie against yen, which indirectly weighed on dollar versus yen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
