<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611883" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: MOF says DKB should clear up suspicions on scandal.</title>
<headline>MOF says DKB should clear up suspicions on scandal.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank Ltd (DKB) should clear up suspicions that it may have been involved in questionable loans to a &quot;sokaiya&quot; racketeer, Finance Minister Hiroshi Mitsuzuka told reporters on Friday.</p>
<p>Asked about reports that the bank's top executives had decided to resign over the issue, Mitsuzuka said: &quot;Such resignations would not mean the bank has carried out its responsibilities.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the bank should clear up the suspicions by itself, on its own responsibility, and not leave the matter to investigations by the authorities.  </p>
<p>Asked whether MOF also had some responsibility for failing to notice the matter through its regular inspections of the bank, Mitsuzuka said ministry officials had done their best in their inspections but were just unable to find anything that violated any laws.</p>
<p>DKB executives also came under fire from Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto on Thursday, when he said their reported plans to resign over the affair would be &quot;sneaky&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's sneaky (for the DKB leadership) to step down to take the blame,&quot; Hashimoto said. &quot;Their resigning does not settle the problem. They should face up to the case until investigations make headway.&quot;</p>
<p>Hashimoto, angered by a string of business scandals, also lashed out at the Finance Ministry for not knowing that DKB might be involved in questionable loans to a racketeer.</p>
<p>Media reports have said DKB chairman Tadashi Okuda, president Katsuhiko Kondo and other top executives are expected to quit over links to a scandal also involving the country's largest brokerage, Nomura Securities Co.</p>
<p>At the heart of the affair are the activities of a &quot;sokaiya&quot; or racketeer who prosecutors suspect was given financial favours by both companies to stop him from disrupting their shareholders' meetings by asking sensitive business questions.</p>
<p>Japan's Commercial Code bans companies from making payments to sokaiya.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
