<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611806" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Shenzhen to extend loans to seven listed firms.</title>
<headline>Shenzhen to extend loans to seven listed firms.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Shenzhen city government has pledged to extend a total of 570 million yuan in loans to seven locally-listed companies to help fund eight key industrial projects, a Shenzhen-based newspaper said on Friday.</p>
<p>Shenzhen Energy Investment Co Ltd will receive 300 million yuan, the largest of the loans, the Securities Times said.</p>
<p>Other beneficiaries include conglomerate Shenzhen Lionda Holdings Co, building materials maker Shenzhen Fangda Industrial Co and China Southern Glass Holdings Co, it said.  </p>
<p>Shenzhen Energy will inject 300 million yuan into the construction of a power plant in Shenzhen, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>Lionda will use 60 million yuan to expand its brewery and 40 million yuan to fund bicycle manufacturing operations, it said.</p>
<p>Fangda, Southern Glass and Shenzhen Petrochemical (Holdings) Ltd will each use 20 million yuan for their core business operations, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>Shenzhen Kondarl Co will channel 100 million yuan into its 90 percent-owned Shenzhen Qianwan Electric Power Development Co Ltd to help fund a new power project, it said.</p>
<p>Shenzhen Qianwan and Guangdong Electric Power Holdings Co will have a combined 36 percent interest in a Shenzhen-based 1,050 megawatt natural gas-fired power plant.</p>
<p>Exxon Corp last month said Exxon Energy Ltd had signed a joint venture agreement with China Energy Investment Co Ltd for the development of the plant. China Energy is a subsidiary of Hong Kong's China Light &amp; Power Co Ltd.</p>
<p>Under the agreement, Exxon Energy and China Energy will each have a 17.5 percent interest in the project, while Kanematsu Power (South China) Co Ltd will have a 29 percent interest, Exxon Corp said.  </p>
<p>Shenzhen Huayuan Industrial Co Ltd, a floppy disk maker, will use 30 million yuan for technology upgrades, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>The loans will be arranged through China's domestic banks, it said, without giving the terms or interest rates. The paper did not explain the source of the additional funds, beyond the Shenzhen government's 570 million yuan.</p>
<p>($1=8.3 yuan)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I24300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I24700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25120">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
