<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611973" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Egypt to ask Israel at summit to halt settlements.</title>
<headline>Egypt to ask Israel at summit to halt settlements.</headline>
<byline>Howard Goller</byline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Israeli-Egyptian summit next week will succeed if Israel agrees to stop building settlements for Jews on lands it captured in 1967, Egyptian Foreign Minister Amr Moussa said in remarks broadcast on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I would foresee a success if an agreement on a freeze on the question of settlements (would) be reached,&quot; Moussa told Israel's army radio.</p>
<p>Israel's Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will meet Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak on Tuesday at the Egyptian Red Sea resort town of Sharm el-Sheikh. Egypt, partner to a 1979 treaty with Israel, hopes to break an Israel-PLO peacemaking deadlock.</p>
<p>&quot;Saving the peace process is our duty, all of us. Saving the peace process is for the good of Israel, of the Arabs, of the Palestinians, of everybody,&quot; Moussa said.</p>
<p>Mubarak has previously suggested a six-month Israeli freeze of settlement expansion would boost peace efforts. But Netanyahu has said his 11-month-old government will press ahead with Jewish construction in the areas captured in a 1967 war.</p>
<p>Palestinians say stalled talks can resume only when Israel halts work on an East Jerusalem settlement. Netanyahu plunged negotiations with the PLO into crisis two months ago when he broke ground on the settlement.</p>
<p>The PLO views the project -- on a hill Israelis know as Har Homa and Palestinians as Jabal Abu Ghneim -- as an attempt to pre-empt future &quot;final status&quot; peace talks on the fate of the city where it hopes to found a capital.</p>
<p>Israel says it can build where it likes in the city it calls its eternal capital and says an interim peace accord with the PLO enables it to do so.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no ban in the agreement to building in Jerusalem. It's clear to all,&quot; Israeli Foreign Minister David Levy insisted on Israel Radio on Friday.</p>
<p>Israel conditions a resumption of talks on a PLO crackdown against militants.</p>
<p>The last time Netanyahu met Mubarak was in early March. It was their third meeting since Netanyahu took office last June. Mubarak held talks in Cairo with Palestinian President Yasser Arafat on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Both Moussa and Levy, his Israeli counterpart, sounded a hopeful note ahead of the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps there will be an opening. Mr Netanyahu will be bringing a new attitude, a new position which would ameliorate the situation,&quot; Moussa said.</p>
<p>Levy voiced optimism, adding: &quot;I hope that we are doing our best in order to get the process back on a constructive track.&quot;</p>
<p>Netanyahu set a meeting with Mubarak only after news leaked on Thursday that Israeli President Ezer Weizman, whose job is largely ceremonial, had an invitation from the Egyptian leader, underscoring the peacemaking crisis facing Netanyahu's right-wing government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
