<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611982" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Frankfurt seeks to lead German airport alliance.</title>
<headline>Frankfurt seeks to lead German airport alliance.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Flughafen Frankfurt Main AG (FAG) said it was seeking to set up and lead a German airports alliance.</p>
<p>Such an alliance could lead to the formation of a &quot;Deutsche Flughaefen AG&quot; which could part-own or operate several major German airports in competition to European rivals, officials said.</p>
<p>The move has been sparked off by the decision of the North Rhine Westphalia government to sell its 50 percent holding in Duesseldorf airport, they noted.</p>
<p>Speaking at a news conference late Thursday, FAG chairman Wilhelm Bender said the airport company was interested in taking stakes in Berlin, Hamburg, Hanover, Duesseldorf and Cologne airports where federal or state governments were planning to sell shareholdings.</p>
<p>&quot;Frankfurt does not want to buy airports. But a network of airport co-operations in Germany would not be enough. If FAG transfers its know-how, then it wants to profit from that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Frankfurt, as the major German hub, was clearly losing traffic to Amsterdam, Paris and London as airlines built up direct flights from German regions to their national hubs, he pointed out.</p>
<p>A network of key German airports could plan jointly, co-ordinate capacity and schedules and offer common services to improve the competitiveness of each participant, he said.</p>
<p>Bender declined to name the sum which might be required to buy the stakes but said private capital could be required since the public sector was unlikely to finance new shareholdings.</p>
<p>The German government has a 25.9 percent holding in FAG, the state of Hesse holds 45.2 percent and the city of Frankfurt has a 28.9 percent holding.</p>
<p>Karl Starzacher, Hesse finance minister, said the German transport ministry and state governments would discuss the Frankfurt proposal in mid-June.</p>
<p>The FAG supervisory board, which he chaired, had an open mind on how to finance investment in other airports but it was too early to talk about a public placement of FAG shares, he added. --Reuters Air Cargo Newsroom. Tel +44 171 542 7706; Fax: 5017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I76400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
