<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611975" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: F.O.Licht - Daily coffee report.</title>
<headline>F.O.Licht - Daily coffee report.</headline>
<text>
<p>The following is a direct contribution from commodity statistician F.O. Licht in Ratzeburg, Germany. Please address any queries to Helmut Ahlfeld on +00 49 4541 88920.</p>
<p>COFFEE - World market for May 22, 1997</p>
<p>Robusta futures in London ended mostly lower in spite of further gains in New York. Players are already sufficiently long in robustas and have become more careful as the market seems to be overbought. July lost $8 to close at $2,082 per tonne, while September lost $15 to close at $2,100 per tonne.</p>
<p>Arabica futures in New York closed higher across the board reaching new contract highs once more. July added 7.20 cents/lb to close at 260.30 cents/lb, while September closed 4.90 cents/lb higher at 229.95 cents/lb. There is ongoing concern about tight supplies until new mild coffee becomes available this autumn.</p>
<p>Continued forecasts for a small Brazilian 1997/98 crop and reports of cold weather in Brazil in July also underpinned the market. In a monthly bulletin, Brazilian independent forecaster Somar said two of Brazil's key coffee regions - the north of Sao Paulo State and southern Minas Gerais - may see below average temperatures in May through to July.</p>
<p>The ACPC decision to extend quotas was no longer a factor, as players have realized that the practical value of this decision is limited.</p>
<p>FUNDAMENTALS</p>
<p>BRAZIL - Brazil's 1997/98 crop should total 22.10 million 60- kg bags, said Santos brokers Wolthers and Associates in its second crop estimate. Previously the company had estimated the crop at 22 million bags. The new total comprises arabica output of 17.8 million bags and robusta production of 4.3 million bags. Trade sources said that the estimate may be on the low side as the higher prices will prompt growers to pick every last bean off the trees and ground. It was added that the steep discount for Brazilian coffee also suggests this.</p>
<p>UNITED STATES - The increase in US certified coffee stocks seems to have come to a halt. Certified stocks fell by 1,500 bags on May 21 to 49,712 bags from 51,212 bags the previous day. There were no bags pending grading, the exchange said.</p>
<p>CANADA - Canada imported 255,200 bags of coffee in February 1997, nearly 11 per cent more than was imported the same month the previous year. That brought total imports since the beginning of 1997 up to 503,200 bags, 19 per cent more than was imported the same period in 1996. Total imports in calendar year 1996 rose by 9 per cent to 2.739 million bags. Main suppliers of green coffee in January/February 1997 were Guatemala (53,100 vs 46,200 bags), Brazil (53,600 vs 22,500 bags), Colombia (78,400 vs 90,000 bags) and Vietnam (48,200 vs 32,100 bags).</p>
<p>TANZANIA - Coffee production in 1996/97 (July/June) is estimated at 678,000 bags of which 512,000 arabicas and 166,000 robustas. This is down on the 818,000 bags produced in 1995/96 and the 743,000 bags produced in 1994/95.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TANZA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
