<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611925" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: JGBs lower, sentiment weakened by rise in stocks.</title>
<headline>JGBs lower, sentiment weakened by rise in stocks.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The key June 10-year Japanese government bond futures contract was slightly lower in early morning trade on Friday, due to firmness in Tokyo share prices, traders said.</p>
<p>The upside for JGBs is likely to be limited due to selling pressure from brokers who are still holding the new 196th 10-year JGBs offered by the Ministry of Finance (MOF) through an auction on Wednesday, a regional bank trader said.</p>
<p>Traders said the coupon rate of the two-year notes to be offered through a MOF auction this morning is likely to be set at one percent.  </p>
<p>June JGBs stood at 123.73 as of 0053 GMT, down from the previous day's close of 123.88.</p>
<p>The benchmark 182nd JGB yield stood at 2.575 percent, up from the previous day's close of 2.550 percent.</p>
<p>Brokers who have not been able to sell off their holdings of the new 196th 10-year JGB are likely to want to sell on the upside and this may drag down JGBs, the regional bank trader said.</p>
<p>Investors have been generally reluctant to buy the new 10-year issue after a sharp fall in JGBs after the auction on Wednesday, traders said.  </p>
<p>If the coupon rate for the new two-year government notes is set at one percent, there should be healthy demand from investors, traders said.</p>
<p>Traders said the Finance Ministry is likely to offer 120 billion yen worth of one percent two-year government notes at its auction later today.</p>
<p>MOF's offer for the two-year notes is due at 10.30 a.m. (0130 GMT) and the results are due at 2.30 p.m. (0530 GMT).</p>
<p>-- Tokyo Treasury Desk +81-3-5473-3748</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
