<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611905" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: FEATURE - I shall return, says Hong Kong democrat.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - I shall return, says Hong Kong democrat.</headline>
<byline>Diane Stormont</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Feisty Hong Kong legislator Christine Loh represents a tough-minded new breed of democrat in Hong Kong -- but in just over six weeks she faces an uncertain period in the political wilderness.</p>
<p>Loh, among Hong Kong's first generation of Western-educated Asian democracy activists, vows to regain an influential voice after China takes over the British colony.</p>
<p>Determined to battle on for civil liberties, Loh, 41, is undeterred by Hong Kong's shadowy future as a Special Administrative Region under the overall control of Beijing.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to build a political culture in Hong Kong -- competitive but not adversial,&quot; she says of life under the Chinese communist flag.</p>
<p>She will be swept out of political office, one of 33 lawmakers to lose their jobs when the British hand over their colony to China at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>Angered by mild democratic reforms introduced as more than 150 years of British colonial rule drew to a close, China will dismantle the Legislative Council and replace it with a selected interim chamber, expected to serve for about a year.</p>
<p>Loh, who has spared neither Britain nor China during her political career, refused to cooperate with Beijing's selection process.</p>
<p>Along with little more than half the members of the 60-seat existing chamber, she faces a post-handover future out in the cold -- at first anyway.</p>
<p>The opponent she defeated in elections in 1995 accepted a seat. If it rankles, Loh does not let it show.</p>
<p>Instead, she has focused her energies on founding a new political party, the Citizens' Party, and is looking ahead to contesting elections expected in 1998.</p>
<p>She is an ardent advocate of democracy, of universal adult suffrage and environmental responsibility.</p>
<p>&quot;For those of us who are relatively young, to be able to say we've gone through the process of getting the people's mandate, it's a big deal,&quot; she said in a recent interview.</p>
<p>&quot;It might not be a big deal in the West, but for us it's a big deal,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>China has promised Hong Kong people they will run Hong Kong and pledged to permit full democracy within 10 years -- although the details remain hazy.</p>
<p>A single woman, Loh, with her crisp British accent and mastery of Chinese dialects, is a representative of the first generation of Hong Kong people to feel they truly belong to Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Most are the sons and daughters of refugees who fled turmoil in China and landed in the colony, a tiny corner of stability on the mainland's southern flank.</p>
<p>Few share their parents' view that the territory is merely a waiting room en route to the West or, one day, back to China.</p>
<p>They want to run their own lives in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Loh, educated both in Hong Kong and in Britain where she earned a law degree, spent her early career working as a commodities trader for Philipp Brothers and Phibro in Hong Kong and China and for a trader CIM Co Ltd in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>She opened Philipp's representative office in Beijing in 1980, one of the first wave of U.S. companies to establish a toehold in China when the once reclusive country began opening its doors to the West.</p>
<p>Loh became a full time legislator in 1994, but cut her teeth in politics a decade earlier.</p>
<p>She chaired the Hong Kong Observers -- a grouping of mostly young, professional Hong Kong people who pushed for more open and representative government.</p>
<p>This alarmed some members of the colonial establishment and the older generation disturbed at seeing people in their thirties rocking the boat.</p>
<p>A generation clash is not surprising, Loh said, but she insists she has no time for the concept of &quot;Asian values&quot; as espoused by elderly leaders such as Singapore leader Lee Kuan Yew.</p>
<p>&quot;We are the fulfilment of our parents' dreams. They wanted us to be able to compete with the West -- that's why they educated us in the Western manner,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;We're comfortable with Western ways, but it doesn't make us any less Asian.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that Asians have a distinctive culture and history but I get very upset when Asian governments use bits of history and culture to say Asian values mean Asians naturally accept authoritarianism. It's a distorted argument.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
