<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611977" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Germany's gold plan seen unlikely to gain approval.</title>
<headline>Germany's gold plan seen unlikely to gain approval.</headline>
<byline>Henry Engler</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's plan to revalue the Bundesbank's gold reserves is unlikely to be allowed to be used to reduce the country's budget deficit, but there is a chance it could be applied to Bonn's outstanding debt, a senior European Union official said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I have difficulties to believe you could use (the revaluation) to reduce the deficit,&quot; the official told Reuters.</p>
<p>Faced with a gaping hole in its 1997 revenue projections, German Finance Minister Theo Waigel has proposed using a revaluation of the Bundesbank's gold reserves.</p>
<p>The controversial plan has prompted a wave of criticism across the EU, with many analysts and officials calling the strategy a clear example of &quot;creative accounting&quot; in order to meet the preconditions of a single European currency.</p>
<p>The official underlined the fact that no formal decision had been made on the issue and that talks between Bonn and the relevant EU statistical bodies were likely in the coming weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;It might be possible to apply it to the debt level, but on the deficit, I just don't see how,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Germany's specific intentions with respect to the plan were also unclear, and the hope was that talks with German officials would help clarify matters, the official added.</p>
<p>The Bundesbank, one of the few European central banks which does not revalue its gold reserves on a regular basis, currently books it assets at their all-time lowest price.</p>
<p>Experts estimate that a gold revaluation could result in a windfall profit of close to 40 billion marks ($23.6 billion).</p>
<p>Although EU accounting rules permit the sale of gold reserves to be applied to a country's debt level, no such provision exists for deficit reduction.</p>
<p>Some EU finance ministers have voiced scepticism over how a revaluation could applied at all.</p>
<p>Belgian Finance Minister Philippe Maystadt told reporters on Thursday that he did not believe Bonn's plan could be used under EU accounting practices.</p>
<p>The Dutch presidency of the EU, meanwhile, expressed alarm on Thursday to the German proposal.</p>
<p>In an interview with a Dutch newspaper on Thursday, Finance Minister Gerrit Zalm said: &quot;I cannot imagine that Germany wants to take this route to qualify for EMU as regards the budget deficit.&quot;</p>
<p>Analysts say should the revaluation strategy be allowed for debt reduction, Bonn could benefit indirectly via reduced interest payments.</p>
<p>Countries wishing to qualify for a single currency must bring their 1997 budget deficits down to three percent of Gross Domestic Product.</p>
<p>In light of Germany's revenue shortfall, economists reckon the country's budget gap could climb to as high as 3.5 percent of output without additional measures.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E513">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
