<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611953" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Iran votes for new president, U.S. demonised again.</title>
<headline>Iran votes for new president, U.S. demonised again.</headline>
<byline>Barry May</byline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iranians voted on Friday for a successor to President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani, who is bound by law to step down in August after eight years in office.</p>
<p>After a fiercely fought campaign, the result looked set to be a close contest between two Shi'ite Moslem clergymen, moderate Mohammad Khatami and conservative Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri. Two other candidates, Mohammad Mohammadi Reyshahri and Reza Zavarei, were believed unlikely to make much impact.</p>
<p>Iranian analysts and Western diplomats said the election was too close to call.</p>
<p>Supreme spiritual leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei and Rafsanjani, in remarks broadcast by Tehran radio, called on all eligible voters to take an active part in the election.</p>
<p>&quot;If one candidate shows the slightest tolerance to America and the Western countries' interference and cultural onslaught, the people will not vote for him,&quot; Khamenei said.</p>
<p>&quot;They will vote for someone who can stand against America and those who want to impose their will on our nation.&quot;</p>
<p>Khamenei said after casting his vote in a special ballot box at his official residence that he expected the next president to be a servant of the people and within the framework of the Islamic rules, and to do his best for people's welfare and spiritual affairs.</p>
<p>Rafsanjani, described by Iran's official news agency IRNA as &quot;the warrior of construction&quot;, said after voting: &quot;I hope the next president continues the construction plans and provides for people's requirements. That is the aim of the rule of Islam in the country and protects the national interest.&quot;</p>
<p>Thirty-three million Iranians aged 15 and over were eligible to vote at more than 33,000 mosques, schools and clinics turned into polling stations and guarded by 200,000 police. They opened at 8 a.m. (0330 GMT) and were due to close 10 hours later at 6 p.m. (1330 GMT).</p>
<p>Approaches to national election headquarters at the Interior Ministry were barricaded and guarded by armed police.</p>
<p>The moderate Khatami, a former culture minister popular with women, youths and intellectuals, was expected to sweep the capital and some other major cities.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri, the speaker of parliament who is backed by Iran's conservative clergy and merchant class, is seen as an establishment figure and is stronger in rural areas.</p>
<p>All four candidates had to pass scrutiny for their belief in Iran's Islamic system of government before they were allowed to stand. A senior body of clergymen and lawyers rejected 234 other contenders.</p>
<p>In the previous presidential election in 1993, Rafsanjani was returned for a second four-year term with 64 percent of 16.7 million votes cast.</p>
<p>In the courtyard of a mosque near Ibn-Sina Square in Tehran where men and women queued separately to vote, a 16-year-old youth taking part in an election for the first time turned to the man behind him and said: &quot;I'm voting for Khatami, who are you voting for?&quot;</p>
<p>Told the vote was confidential, the youth replied: &quot;Vote for Khatami, he is better.&quot;</p>
<p>Ballot papers do not name the candidates but a notice lists the four with Nateq-Nouri first followed by Reyshahri, Khatami and Zavarei. The list does not follow the Persian alphabet.</p>
<p>Voters must write in the name of their preferred candidate. There are no photographs of the candidates and illiterate voters have to ask for help.</p>
<p>Tehran radio played songs especially composed for the election and epic poems on people's duty to go to the polls.</p>
<p>A man interviewed on the radio about the election said voting was &quot;a strong smack in the jaw of world arrogance&quot; -- a term usually taken to mean the United States and the West.</p>
<p>Television coverage included footage of Iran's &quot;bad old days&quot; before the 1979 Islamic revolution including scenes of U.S. President Richard Nixon meeting Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, as well as scenes of crowds burning U.S. flags and the Jewish Star of David.</p>
<p>Images of the early violent days of the revolution which toppled the Shah, and of revolutionary leader the late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, were shown repeatedly with graphic scenes of combat in the 1980-88 Iran-Iraq war.</p>
<p>Fears of vote-rigging marked the campaign, which ended 24 hours before polling began. Both Khamenei, Iran's highest authority, and Rafsanjani, its most senior elected official, warned people against any attempt to tamper with ballots and promised the election would be fair.</p>
<p>The result is expected to be known by Monday. If no candidate wins more than 50 percent of the votes, the two leading candidates will face a runoff, possibly next Friday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
