<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611976" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: F.O.Licht - Daily sugar report.</title>
<headline>F.O.Licht - Daily sugar report.</headline>
<text>
<p>The following is a direct contribution from commodity statistician F.O. Licht in Ratzeburg, Germany. Please address any queries to Helmut Ahlfeld on +00 49 4541 88920.</p>
<p>SUGAR - World market for May 22, 1997</p>
<p>White sugar futures in London finished easier after selling in New York pressured an already weak market. August shed $1.20 to close at $320.20 per tonne, while October closed $1.10 easier at $310.20 per tonne.</p>
<p>Raw sugar futures in New York ended a volatile session weaker, but local short covering and light trade buying during the second half of the session lifted the market off the lows. July lost 9 points to close at 11.06 cents/lb, while October gave up 5 points to close at 10.87 cents/lb. There was no fresh news to influence prices.</p>
<p>FUNDAMENTALS</p>
<p>THAILAND - Thai sugar millers completed the 1996/97 crushing season with a total of 56.192 million tonnes of cane crushed which compares to 57.265 million tonnes last season. As of May 14 total sugar production was 6.040 million tonnes, raw value, down from 6.226 million tonnes last year. The share of white sugar production in 1996/97 rose to 50.14 per cent, up from 46.5 per cent last year due to strong demand for Thai white sugar from countries such as Indonesia.</p>
<p>CHINA - Chinese sugar production in April 1997 reached 381,200 tonnes, raw value, down from 413,200 tonnes produced the same month last year. This brought total production since the beginning of 1996/97 (September/August) up to 7.230 million tonnes, up from 6.585 million tonnes produced the same period in 1995/96. This points to a seasonally adjusted total for the whole of 1996/97 of 7.3 million tonnes, somewhat above earlier expectations and up from last year's production of 6.770 million tonnes.</p>
<p>CHINA - According to preliminary figures, sugar imports have started to pick up in April although the overall level is still considerably below last year's. Total imports in April reached 71,204 tonnes, raw value, up from 20,146 tonnes in March, but down on the 110,644 tonnes imported in April 1996.</p>
<p>This brought cumulative imports in the first eight months of 1996/97 (September/April) up to 549,963 tonnes, down from 1.344 million tonnes in the like period the previous year. Total imports in 1995/96 reached 1.944 million tonnes against 2.907 million tonnes in 1994/95.</p>
<p>Sugar exports in April 1997 reached 28,549 tonnes, up from 15,104 tonnes in March but down on the 50,023 tonnes exported in April 1996. This brought cumulative exports in September/April 1996/97 up to 223,805 tonnes against 627,886 tonnes in 1995/96. Total exports in 1995/96 amounted to 830,203 tonnes against 540,004 tonnes in 1994/95.</p>
<p>HONG KONG - Sugar imports in March 1997 amounted to 23,040 tonnes, raw value, up from 19,326 tonnes in March 1996. This brought cumulative imports in the fist quarter of 1997 (January/March) up to 71,599 tonnes against 67,524 tonnes in the first quarter of 1996. Total imports in 1996 amounted to 285,492 tonnes against 237,332 tonnes in 1995. Major countries of origin in January/March 1997 were South Korea with 46,903 tonnes whites against 26,808 tonnes and the United Kingdom with 7,984 tonnes compared to 6,628 tonnes.</p>
<p>Sugar exports in March 1997 amounted to 8,772 tonnes against 7,805 tonnes in March 1996. This brought cumulative exports in January/March 1997 up to 27,938 tonnes against 22,317 tonnes in the like period the previous year. Total exports in 1996 hit the record high of 80,533 tonnes against 67,970 tonnes in 1995. The major country of destination in 1997 was China with 23,362 tonnes against 18,104 tonnes in 1996.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
