<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611981" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Key constituencies to watch in French election.</title>
<headline>Key constituencies to watch in French election.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Half a dozen centre-right cabinet ministers face tough fights for a seat in France's two-round parliamentary election on Sunday and June 1, while several senior left-wing and extreme-right opposition figures are bidding to enter the National Assembly.</p>
<p>Reuters will provide highlight results from 34 key constituencies involving national political leaders.</p>
<p>Among government members who could be forced into a runoff are Prime Minister Alain Juppe, Justice Minister Jacques Toubon, Interior Minister Jean-Louis Debre, Environment Minister Corinne Lepage, Urban Affairs Minister Eric Raoult and Employment Minister Anne-Marie Couderc.</p>
<p>On the left, Socialist party leader Lionel Jospin and Communist party leader Robert Hue are both bidding to enter the Assembly, as are three Socialist women politicians likely to figure in any left-wing government -- Strasbourg mayor Catherine Trautman, ex-labour minister Martine Aubry and former European affairs minister Elisabeth Guigou.</p>
<p>We will also carry the results of former Socialist prime minister Laurent Fabius, Communist parliamentary floor leader Alain Bocquet and anti-Maastricht maverick Socialist Jean-Pierre Chevenement.</p>
<p>Four senior figures in the extreme-right National Front, which had no members in the outgoing Assembly, are hoping to win seats: the party's number two, Bruno Megret, general-secretary Bruno Gollnisch, Toulon mayor Jean-Marie Le Chevallier and the mayor of Orange, Jacques Bompard.</p>
<p>We will also be watching the two leading ecologists bidding to enter parliament for the first time, Dominique Voynet of the Greens and Noel Mamer of Convergence Ecologie-Solidarite. Both are supported by the Socialist party.</p>
<p>We will track several constituencies in Paris where the ruling Gaullist party is expected to suffer a setback because of a serious of sleaze scandals. The capital's mayor, Jean Tiberi, facing a record 28 contenders, could be forced into a runoff for the first time since he entered parliament in 1968.</p>
<p>In another Paris district, two rival Gaullists, President Jacques Chirac's former diplomatic adviser Pierre Lellouche and veteran Resistance fighter Gabriel Kaspereit, the sitting member, are fighting for the same seat.</p>
<p>We will also follow the results of two possible Gaullist contenders for the premiership if the right wins, National Assembly president Philippe Seguin and ex-premier Edouard Balladur.</p>
<p>We will report on Socialist party spokesman Francois Hollande's bid to capture a Gaullist seat in Chirac's home bastion of Correze in central France, and on potential Socialist finance minister Dominique Strauss-Kahn's attempt to win Sarcelles, in the northern Paris suburbs.</p>
<p>We will also carry the results of ex-president Valery Giscard d'Estaing, centre-right UDF leaders Francois Leotard, Francois Bayrou. Alain Madelin and Claude Goasguen, Gaullist RPR party general secretary Jean-Francois Mancel, right-wing anti-Maastricht campaigner Philippe de Villiers and of extreme-left Lutte Ouvriere leader Arlette Laguiller.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
