<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611930" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: PRESS DIGEST - Philippine newspapers - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Philippine newspapers - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in Manila newspapers on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>- China accused yesterday the Philippines of breaking international law by laying claim to Huangyan Island (Scarborough Shoal), adding that Manila's stand is &quot;absolutely unacceptable to the Chinese government and people.&quot; (STANDARD/INQUIRER)</p>
<p>- The Philippines has rejected the proposal by the United States to use their former facilities in Clark and Subic for military exercises, a ranking diplomatic official said yesterday (STANDARD/TODAY)</p>
<p>- President Ramos called yesterday on the taipans of Hong Kong and China to consider the Philippines as their gateway to business and investments in southeast Asia. (ALL NEWSPAPERS)</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>				 +++++++++</p>
<p>BUSINESS STORIES</p>
<p>- The Philippine Central Bank reduced yesterday its overnight borrowing by two percentage points to 18 percent as the financial markets returned to normal. (ALL NEWSPAPERS)</p>
<p>- The influential Bankers Association of the Philippines is strongly opposing the proposed amendments to the Bank Secrecy Law allowing certain government agencies to look into bank deposits. (CHRONICLE/STAR/BUSINESS DAILY)</p>
<p>- The scheduled bidding for the 7.5 percent shareholdings of state-owned National Development Corp in National Steel Corp faces another bleak prospect as few investors appeared interested in acquiring minority stake in the country's biggest steel firm. (BUSINESS DAILY/BUSINESSWORLD)</p>
<p>- Manila Newsroom (632) 841 8937</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
