<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611935" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: FEATURE-Turf battle lurks behind Japan reform.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Turf battle lurks behind Japan reform.</headline>
<byline>Linda Sieg</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's trade mandarins, once dubbed key architects of the nation's postwar growth miracle, are now championing reform as a new economic elixir.</p>
<p>But whether the Trade Ministry's crusade means more radical change -- or less -- is tough to predict, since many sceptics see an old-style bureaucratic turf battle as the main motive.</p>
<p>&quot;Are they serious about reform? I just don't know. They seem to talk a lot about things that are outside their jurisdiction,&quot; said Jeff Young, an economist at Salomon Brothers Asia. &quot;I think there is room for scepticism.&quot;</p>
<p>MITI OFFERS UNSOLICITED ADVICE</p>
<p>Japan's Ministry of International Trade and Industry (MITI) has long had a penchant for airing views on matters seen by rival ministries as none of its concern, but recently it has grown even more outspoken with its unsolicited advice.</p>
<p>Among the targets on which MITI has lately set its sights is the Fiscal Investment and Loan Programme (FILP), the so-called &quot;second budget,&quot; managed by the Finance Ministry and funded by the postal savings system.</p>
<p>In March, a MITI advisory panel said Japan's &quot;Big Bang&quot; financial reforms would be hamstrung without changes in FILP, already the focus of an intense and highly politicised debate.</p>
<p>That advice followed another call by the same panel for removal of barriers to entering the financial industry, already the Big Bang's ostensible goal. Details of the five-year plan are being worked out by the Finance Ministry.</p>
<p>The Trade Ministry is also trying to make sure it has a say, for example, in the future of electronic money in Japan -- an effort which brings it into conflict with both the Finance Ministry and the Posts and Telecommunications Ministry.</p>
<p>MITI CREDITED WITH HASHIMOTO PLATFORM</p>
<p>MITI officials have been credited with authoring Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto's own political platform, including his campaign to redraw the bureaucratic map by merging ministries or altering areas of jurisdiction.</p>
<p>Ironically, rival officials from the ministry were said by insiders to have crafted much of the reformist vision outlined in a 1993 book by Ichiro Ozawa, a Hashimoto rival who now heads Japan's largest, but currently enfeebled, opposition party.</p>
<p>At the request of Hashimoto, whose stint as trade minister preceded his ascent to the premiership, MITI also drafted a plan for structural economic reform across some 15 industry sectors including energy and telecommunications and finance.</p>
<p>The plan, however, drew a muted response from economists, who noted that in many cases MITI's drive for more drastic reforms stumbled on opposition from other ministries. &quot;It didn't seem to be specific enough or timely enough to draw much attention,&quot; one foreign economist said.</p>
<p>TRADE OFFICIALS' INITIATIVE DRAWS FIRE</p>
<p>The ministry's forays outside its bailiwick have drawn fire from rival ministries, where some see an ill-disguised effort to cloak bureaucratic expansionism in a reformist mantle.</p>
<p>&quot;MITI's imperialism is famous among Japanese officials. They want to expand their areas of interest in whatever way they can,&quot; said a senior official in another powerful ministry.</p>
<p>&quot;The idea of restructuring the ministries was certainly thought of by some MITI officials, partly because the ministry sees its grip on industry having declined substantially and it finds its role in society as less important than before,&quot; the senior official said. &quot;MITI wants to be key to policies for all industries,including telecommunications and finance.&quot;</p>
<p>Some analysts see similar motives behind MITI's reform policy prescriptions, which perpetuate a shift in stance begun in the late 1980s, when corporate Japan's success made big companies keen to escape their bureaucratic shackles.</p>
<p>&quot;In the late 80s there was a kind of erosion of MITI's role, not only of industrial policy but internationally...so they tried to disseminate the view that they were a kind of reform-minded think-tank,&quot; Young said.</p>
<p>MITI insiders admit the ministry feels threatened by a changing economic landscape which is reducing the relevance of industry sectors under its control to Japan's future growth.</p>
<p>&quot;MITI is trying to protect itself by going on the offensive,&quot;said one former trade bureaucrat.</p>
<p>But the Trade Ministry is hardly alone in its manoeuvring.</p>
<p>Other agencies are also jockeying to keep or carve out new powers amid calls for changes which, if enacted, would reduce the scope for their interference in markets and industries.</p>
<p>&quot;All the ministries are trying to figure out how they can play a new controlling role,&quot; one political analyst said. &quot;It's not just MITI.&quot;</p>
<p>MARGINAL CHANGE SEEN BY SOME</p>
<p>Sceptics say MITI's reformist campaign will likely yield mostly marginal and incremental changes, but some predict newly emerging growth sectors may end up relatively unfettered.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the reforms they have pushed are in most cases to try to keep ahead of the curve, to use rhetoric more vigorously than the politicians,&quot; said one American expert on Japan.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think we are going to see huge changes, because I don't think that they see much change is needed,&quot; he said. &quot;But they are allowing new business areas to go unregulated, because there they don't have to take on embedded interests.&quot;</p>
<p>LESS POWER FOR MITI, NOT MORE?</p>
<p>Other experts argue that MITI's reform efforts mirror ongoing economic changes, but suggest the ultimate result may be less power, not more, for the ministry.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a continuation of what they see as a mandate to build a strong Japanese economy, which increasingly means structural reforms and blurring the boundaries,&quot; said Keith Henry, head of the Japan office of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
<p>&quot;Increasingly to deal with macroeconomic problems, there has to be compromise and consensus (among ministries), but the question is, does that mean more power for MITI?&quot; Henry said. &quot;My feeling is they haven't thought it through.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
