<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611972" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>CYPRUS: PRESS DIGEST - Cyprus - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Cyprus - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>NICOSIA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are some of the leading stories in the Greek Cypriot press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these reports and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>ALITHIA</p>
<p>- Political instability and the rioting on Monday is harming the economy, says a government advisory commission.</p>
<p>- Direct talks between President Glafcos Clerides and Turkish Cypriot leader Rauf Denktash are due to start in July.</p>
<p>CYPRUS MAIL</p>
<p>- Classroom chaos. A UNESCO report reveals the education system in Cyprus is geared more towards satisfying the working conditions of teachers than the needs of pupils.</p>
<p>- Briton testifies against fisherman. &quot;Lover gave me AIDS,&quot; she says.</p>
<p>HARAVGHI</p>
<p>- Only 60 percent of projects planned in the development budget for 1996 were implemented.</p>
<p>- The state-run electricity authority gives assurances it will not hike its rates for at least the next two years.</p>
<p>PHILELEPHTHEROS</p>
<p>- In the days running up to the direct talks the different sides, and especially the Turkish Cypriots, have toughened their stand. Sir David Hannay takes the helm now the U.N. proximity talks in preparation for the direct negotiations are over.</p>
<p>- Imported potatoes with high chemical content were discovered at Limassol port just before they were put on the local market.</p>
<p>SIMERINI</p>
<p>- Greek Cypriot teacher Eleni Foka has been condemned to a slow death in the Turkish occupied areas. She is seriously ill but Denktash will not let her come for medical treatment unless she signs a document recognising his pseudostate.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NICOSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CYPRUS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
