<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611931" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: PHILIPPINE STOCKS - factors to watch - May 23.</title>
<headline>PHILIPPINE STOCKS - factors to watch - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are views on the direction of Philippine stocks on Friday and main factors likely to affect trading.</p>
<p>* Philippine stocks are likely to move in a range with a slightly upward bias as sentiment has improved on the Central Bank's lowering of overnight rates, Dharmala Securities Phils analyst Elline Salvatierra said.</p>
<p>* Resistance of 2,600 points may be tested, Noel Reyes, research head at Anscor-Hagedorn Securities said.  </p>
<p>* Abacus Securities research head Dennis Rayala said that media hype on an investment forum in HongKong where President Fidel Ramos was a speaker could improve market sentiment.</p>
<p>* On Thursday, the Philippine Stock Exchange composite index rose 47.72 points, or 1.88 percent, to 2,586.69.</p>
<p>* The Dow Jones on Thursday fell 32.56 points to 7,258.13. PLDT's ADR rose by $0 1/8 to $55 1/8.</p>
<p>* Philippine Central Bank Governor Gabriel Singson said in Hong Kong that he saw no sharp devaluation of the peso. He added that overnight rates could return to normal next week after having fallen to 18 percent from 20 percent last Friday.</p>
<p>* The Central Bank said it cut its overnight rates by two percentage points each. It also lowered its five-day reverse repo rate to 11.0 percent from 13.0 percent.</p>
<p>* Governor Singson said that he projected a $13-14 billion trade deficit in 1997 following a widening of the trade deficit to $11.2 billion in 1996.  He also projected a 1997 current account deficit of $4.1 billion, equivalent to 4.2 percent of gross national product.</p>
<p>* The Philippines was targetting an average inflation rate of between six and seven percent in 1997 compared with an actual performance of 8.4 percent last year, Singson said.</p>
<p>* The peso closed lower at 26.374 to the dollar vs 26.373</p>
<p>* The Philippine interbank call loan average fell to an average of 18.03125 percent from 20.03125.</p>
<p>* Phlippine private sector credit grew by 37 percent in the first three months of 1997 compared with 57 percent real growth in all of 1996.</p>
<p>* Philippine Communications Secretary Arturo Enrile said he was reviewing the possibility of extending the roll-out programme of new telephone firms for fixed telephone lines beyond the three-year deadline.</p>
<p>* The PDCP Bank said its shareholders have approved a resolution increasing its authorised capital stock to 10 billion pesos from three billion. New shares to be issued will be used for the pending merger with AsianBank Corp.</p>
<p>* The provincial government of Guimaras said it was negotiating with First Philippine Holdings Corp and A Soriano Corp to jointly develop a 216.49 hectare site into a special economic zone.</p>
<p>* Port operator Asian Terminals Inc said it had signed an underwriting agreement with a group of local investment houses for the offering of 1.5 billion pesos worth of long-term commercial papers.</p>
<p>* The Philippine Stock Exchange (PSE) said it had started investigations into four member firms following complaints by a newspaper columnist that a broker made unauthorised use of her account.</p>
<p>* The PSE said Equitable Banking Corp has set a 30 centavo cash dividend to be given to shareholders as of June 16.</p>
<p>* Industrial estate developer MRC Allied Industries Inc said it posted a net income of 37.4 million pesos in the first quarter of the year compared with 6.8 million pesos in the same period a year earlier.</p>
<p>* Newspaper BusinessWorld reported that the National Economic and Development Authority (Neda) in a position paper said that Congress has no choice but to raise indirect and corporate taxes if individual tax exemptions proposed by the House of Representatives in a comprehensive tax bill are to be adopted.</p>
<p>* Manila Bulletin said that President Ramos in a speech in Hong Kong called on taipans to consider the Philippines as their gateway to business and investments in Southeast Asia.</p>
<p>* The Philippine Star said the Bankers' Association of the Philippines remains steadfast against amending the Bank Secrecy Law that will allow certain government agencies to look into bank deposits.</p>
<p>- KATHERINE ESPINA  63 2 841-8939 Fax 8176267</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I76300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
