<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611959" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Shi'ite Moslem vows civil disobedience in Lebanon.</title>
<headline>Shi'ite Moslem vows civil disobedience in Lebanon.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A radical Shi'ite Moslem cleric who once headed the pro-Iranian Hizbollah (Party of God) threatened on Friday to lead a civil disobedience movement of the Shi'ite poor against the Lebanese government.</p>
<p>Sheikh Sobhi Tufaili, a former secretary-general of Hizbollah, said he would lead a march on Beirut by Shi'ites from the eastern Bekaa Valley if the government ignored his demands to improve their living conditions.</p>
<p>&quot;We shall stop paying taxes and electricity and water bills in (the Bekaa towns) Baalbek and Hermel in the first stage,&quot; Tufaili told the Beirut daily an-Nahar in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Hunger is widespread and men are unable to feed their children,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;If no results are achieved we shall march on Beirut as the second stage and lay siege to the palaces of the three leaders.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if that meant the residences of Maronite Christian President Elias Hrawi, billionaire Sunni Moslem Prime Minister Rafik al-Hariri and Shi'ite parliament speaker Nabih Berri, he said: &quot;Yes, that's right....We shall bury the state.&quot;</p>
<p>Tufaili, who led Hizbollah in the 1980s, no longer holds any post in the movement but he has long been linked in the Arab media with Iranian hardliners.</p>
<p>Hizbollah was founded in the Bekaa Valley in 1982 with the help of Iranian Revolutionary Guards to fight the Israeli invasion of Lebanon that year.</p>
<p>The mainly Shi'ite Bekaa, now controlled by Syrian troops, has suffered economically from a crackdown on illegal drug crops that flourished during the 1975-90 civil war.</p>
<p>Residents complain that the government has failed to support profitable alternative crops. They say cold weather this year has intensified the crisis by ruining citrus crops.</p>
<p>Both the conservative An-Nahar and the leftist Beirut daily as-Safir said Tufaili's threatened &quot;hunger revolt&quot; against the Beirut government signalled a split in Hizbollah.</p>
<p>Tufaili criticised the movement's leadership under Sheikh Hassan Nasrallah in the interview for its &quot;negative position&quot; and accused it of &quot;a wavering, incoherent policy of appeasement.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I am disenchanted with its performance,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Signs that Hizbollah was under strain emerged last week during Ashura, the main event of the Shi'ite religious year, when the leadership under Nasrallah failed to attend commemorations in Baalbek, the main city of the Shi'ite-dominated Bekaa.</p>
<p>About 4,000 Tufaili supporters attended while Nasrallah organised a rival event in a Bekaa village.</p>
<p>Tufaili said in the interview the government should grant the Bekaa poor free schooling and hospital treatment, reduction of income tax and exemption from electricity and water bills.</p>
<p>&quot;People in Baalbek and Hermel, in the eastern and northern regions of the Bekaa, are desperately hungry. Children often sleep without eating and no medical treatment is available for the sick in hospitals or elsewhere,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>If the government failed to meet his demands: &quot;We shall then descend on Beirut and declare civil disobedience there. We shall do everything to bring about a total paralysis.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
