<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611956" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: PRESS DIGEST - Turkey - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Turkey - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Turkish press on Friday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>SABAH</p>
<p>- Deputy Prime Minister Tansu Ciller bargains with Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan on taking over his office in June.</p>
<p>- The Islamist-led government appoints the general manager of state-owned petroluem refinery Tupras in what is seen as a step to put their supporters in key posts.</p>
<p>MILLIYET</p>
<p>- Erbakan's Welfare Party is angered by a prosecutor's legal challenge to close down the party. Islamist State Minister Abdullah Gul says they will take legal action against the prosecutor.</p>
<p>HURRIYET</p>
<p>- Deputies who made a U-turn ahead of a parliamentary vote to topple the government say they regret taking the government's side.</p>
<p>- The Finance Ministry stops the monthly announcement of data after reports that the government's balanced budget plans were hit by a deficit in March.</p>
<p>YENI YUZYIL</p>
<p>- Turkish armed forces move to Mosul -- near Saddam Hussein's Iraqi forces -- in a cross-border operation against Kurdistan Workers Party (PKK) rebels.</p>
<p>- McDonnell Douglas proposes the manufacture of MD-90 passenger planes in Turkey.</p>
<p>RADIKAL</p>
<p>- The cabinet meeting is postponed once again. The cabinet has not met for seven weeks.</p>
<p>DUNYA</p>
<p>- The leather sector hopes to sell out their stock in summer sales to holidaymakers.</p>
<p>- The Foreign Ministry says a regulation on the sharing of international water produced by the United Nation does not bind Turkey.</p>
<p>ZAMAN</p>
<p>- A Turkish delegation of businessmen, lecturers and journalists visit Turkish enterprises in Turkmenistan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
