<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611983" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: Eucalyptus stocks seen falling - Portucel.</title>
<headline>Eucalyptus stocks seen falling - Portucel.</headline>
<byline>Jose Barata</byline>
<dateline>LISBON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stocks of eucalyptus pulp have fallen since February and are expected to drop further in the coming months, a spokesman for Portuguese pulp group Portucel Industrial said.</p>
<p>Vitor Coelho, head of investor relations, told Reuters that Portucel, Portugal's main pulp group, was presently operating without stocks and expected firm support for prices during the rest of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;We are practically without stocks and sales continue at a significant rhythm, with a well-supported price of 450 ecus per tonne,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Expectations for the sector, both in the first half and for the whole year, are extremely positive, in line with Scandinavian companies which have published quarterly results,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Market conditions in production and sales are optimal for Portucel Industrial,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Stocks of eucalyptus pulp producers fell 21 percent in April to 307,000 tonnes and 16 percent in March to 391,000 tonnes, Coelho said. In January this year stocks were 480,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>&quot;The main Portuguese, Spanish, and some Brazilian producers are now working with minimum stocks,&quot; Coelho said.</p>
<p>&quot;The 16 percent drop in stocks in March and the 21 percent drop in April -- after a fall in February - show that there is plenty of demand for eucalyptus pulp,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>NorScan pulp stocks are also falling, having dropped by 220,000 tonnes in April, he said. He did not give a percentage figure.</p>
<p>&quot;NorScan stocks have fallen, but eucalyptus stocks have dropped even more,&quot; Coelho said.</p>
<p>&quot;The present forecast is that there will be another drop in eucalyptus pulp stocks at the end of this month,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The U.S. magazine Forecaster has said that by mid-1997 NorScan stocks would stand at 1.5 million tonnes, which analysts say is a healthy level.</p>
<p>Portucel shares closed on Lisbon bourse yesterday at 1,171 escudos, down 16, in volume of 142,192 shares.</p>
<p>-- Lisbon newsroom +(351-1) 3538254</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I47200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LISBON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
