<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611980" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss current account surplus widens in Q1.</title>
<headline>Swiss current account surplus widens in Q1.</headline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Switzerland's current account surplus widened by 500 million Swiss francs in the first quarter of 1997 from the year-earlier quarter to stand at 7.6 billion francs, the Swiss National Bank said.</p>
<p>The trade deficit rose by 600 million to 700 million francs as imports rose faster in nominal terms (7.5 percent) than exports (5.4 percent), it said in an advance summary of its monthy report for May.</p>
<p>&quot;The strong rise in imports can be traced to a special factor, the recording of duty-free oil imports that were in compulsory storage at the end of 1996,&quot; it said.  </p>
<p>Exports of services rose by 200 million to 8.6 billion. Tourism income rose slightly, ending four consecutive quarters of decline. Banks' commissions rose strongly due to higher turnover in securities deal with foreign partners.</p>
<p>Services imports were steady at year-earlier levels, so the services surplus rose by 200 million to 5.8 billion.</p>
<p>Higher revenue from foreign exchange and portfolio investment boosted the surplus on investment income by 800 million to 5.6 billion. Wages paid to foreign workers declined. The current transfers deficit was steady at 1.2 billion.</p>
<p>-- Zurich newsroom +41 1 631 7340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
