<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="611952" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish coalition MP quits in Islamist row.</title>
<headline>Turkish coalition MP quits in Islamist row.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Turkish MP from the secularist wing of Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan's Islamist-led coalition resigned on Friday in a fresh blow to the government.</p>
<p>Anatolian news agency said deputy Samil Ayrim quit the conservative True Path Party, after he had been quoted in the Turkish press as saying he would step down as part of a row over the government's Islamist leanings.</p>
<p>The agency also said one of the True Path's deputy chairmen, Necmettin Cevheri, resigned his post. Cevheri was formerly close to True Path leader Tansu Ciller, who was Turkey's first woman prime minister and is now the foreign minister.</p>
<p>&quot;I have forwarded my resignation to the chairwoman this morning,&quot; Anatolian quoted him as saying.</p>
<p>The MP's resignation leaves the coalition with 279 MPs, a slim majority in the 550-member parliament.</p>
<p>Intense pressure from the army for Erbakan to crack down on Islamist activists has opened up serious cracks in the 11-month-old coalition.</p>
<p>Erbakan won an opposition censure motion this week by only half a dozen votes. He was helped by six MPs from a small right-wing party who backed the government.</p>
<p>The Hurriyet daily quoted Ayrim as saying he wished he had withdrawn support for Erbakan at the censure motion. &quot;I have realised how wrong I was,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The cabinet failed to hold a scheduled meeting on Thursday for the eighth week running amid reports that Ciller had asked Erbakan to hand her the reins of power.</p>
<p>Erbakan's Islam-based Welfare Party is facing a case in the constitutional court that could lead to its closure on grounds that it threatens Turkey's official secularism.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
