<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612038" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Ericsson to launch 6-10 new phones a year - paper.</title>
<headline>Ericsson to launch 6-10 new phones a year - paper.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swedish telecoms group Ericsson will launch between six and 10 new mobile telephones annually instead of one per year as previously, daily Finanstidningen reported on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The sharply higher rate of product launches is a response to more differentiated customer needs,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>Ericsson has divided its mobile phone customers into five segments, each needing its own phone functionality and design, Finanstidningen said.</p>
<p>Ericsson launched three new phones on Thursday, GH688 with many features, GA628 for young people and GS18 for data communication, the daily said.</p>
<p>But the company still has problems meeting demand for the GF788 which it started selling in March.</p>
<p>&quot;We have enormous amounts of orders on GF788 and it is like a black hole,&quot; Par Sveen, head of Ericsson's Swedish mobile phones operations, was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;Production runs around the clock but all we manufacture immediately disappears. In the month of June we hope to have caught up with deliveries.&quot;</p>
<p>The delivery problems are just as big in other countries, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>If Ericsson failed to meet demand for the new models for a couple of months it would be hard to compensate for that later as the telephones' lifespan has become shorter, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;Previously, a mobile phone could have a lifespan of maybe one to one and a half years,&quot; Sveen was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;Now the lifespan is shorter and it keeps falling.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Birgitta Forsberg, Stockholm newsroom +46-8-700 1017</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
