<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612049" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German prod. prices post 4th annual rise in April.</title>
<headline>German prod. prices post 4th annual rise in April.</headline>
<dateline>WIESBADEN, Germany 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>German producer prices rose in April after remaining flat in March, nudging up the year-on-year rate of producer inflation to a 16-month high, the Federal Statistics Office said on Friday.</p>
<p>Producer prices rose by 0.3 percent in April compared to the previous month, and were up by 0.9 percent compared to the same month a year earlier.</p>
<p>The year-on-year figure was the fourth successive rise after an 11-month run of falls that ended last December, and the biggest gain since December 1995, the data showed.</p>
<p>In western Germany, producer prices were up by 0.4 percent on a monthly basis, compared to a fall of 0.1 percent in March. The year-on-year rise was in line with the national figure at 0.9 percent, up from 0.6 percent in March.</p>
<p>In the formerly communist east, prices were up by 0.3 percent after a monthly fall of 0.1 percent in March. Compared to a year earlier, producer prices were up by 1.6 percent, just up from 1.5 percent in the previous month.</p>
<p>The Statistics Office said that the main price changes in April were a jump in the cost of mined products by 3.1 percent, and in iron and steel of 1.0 percent. Petroleum products, however, fell by 1.4 percent in price.</p>
<p>In the economically dominant west, corrugated cardboard prices rose by 8.0 percent, natural gas by 5.1 percent, roast coffee by 3.2 percent and fresh pork by 2.8 percent.</p>
<p>Prices fell for bitumen by 12 percent, liquefied gas by 10 percent and heavy heating oil by 3.2 percent.</p>
<p>-- Douglas Busvine, Bonn newsroom, 49-228-26097150</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WIESBADEN, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
