<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612005" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Dresdner Q1 oper profit before provs rises.</title>
<headline>Dresdner Q1 oper profit before provs rises.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three months to March 31</p>
<p>(in millions of marks unless otherwise stated)</p>
<p>    Group oper profit before provisions   991    up 10 pct</p>
<p>    Group own account trading income	330    vs n/a</p>
<p>    Group net interest income		 1,700  up 8.8 pct</p>
<p>    Group net commission income	     1,200  up 20.6 pct</p>
<p>    Group administrative expenses	   2,300  up 10.4 pct</p>
<p>    Group balance sheet total		625,000 up 11.5 pct</p>
<p>NOTE - Full name of the German bank is Dresdner Bank AG</p>
<p>.</p>
<p>The results were released ahead of the bank's annual general meeting. Chairman Juergen Sarrazin said in the text of a speech that special factors had influenced earnings positively in the first few months of 1997 and that the results could not be extrapolated for the year.</p>
<p>The rise in operating income understated the earnings development because of the extremely good first quarter in 1996 and a pro-rata comparison would give a rise of 25 percent, he said.</p>
<p>The trading income result was equivalent to half the trading income for 1996 as a whole. Net interest income was boosted by quasi-trading income elements not necessarily sustainable over the full year.</p>
<p>Commission income rose on the back of high turnover in equities and mutual funds, and a rise in asset management fees.</p>
<p>Administrative expenses would have risen 7.3 percent excluding costs related to the first time consolidation of RCM Capital Management.</p>
<p>It was too early to detect significant new trends in loan loss provisioning, but Sarrazin said he did not expect a major increase or decrease in provisioning for the full year.</p>
<p>In the result from the liquidity portfolio, realised gains were posted in particular on bonds, which provided a good basis for further earnings development through the year.</p>
<p>The increase in the balance sheet total resulted from growth in money market business mainly, with lending contributing only 3.5 percentage points to the growth.</p>
<p>-- Frankfurt Newsroom, +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
