<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612032" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: PRESS DIGEST - Finland - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Finland - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are some of the leading stories in Finnish papers this morning.</p>
<p>HELSINGIN SANOMAT</p>
<p>- Plans to include the idea of EMU &quot;buffer funds&quot; directly in trade unions' joint EMU resolution was rejected at the last minute by heads of Enso and UPM Kymmene.</p>
<p>- Government does not want to set any conditions ahead of its EMU discussion with opposition, says Prime Minister Paavo Lipponen.</p>
<p>- Finance Minister Sauli Niinisto's comments backing nuclear power were at my request, Pekka Kuosmanen, Conservative MP says. @</p>
<p>- Unemployment statistics are unrealistic rubbish and should be changed very soon, says Heikki Ropponen, head of retail federation.</p>
<p>- Only one-tenth of party members are politically active, study shows.</p>
<p>- Digital mobile phones may disturb pacemakers, U.S. study shows.</p>
<p>- Lipponen receives honorary doctorate from Dartmouth College in New Hampshire, where he studied in early 1960s. @</p>
<p>KAUPPALEHTI</p>
<p>- Finnish banks are concentrating their statutory reporting to regulatory and statistical authorities via central data warehouse.</p>
<p>- Microsoft seeks Finnish partners to provide content for its country-specific Internet browsers.</p>
<p>- UPM's marketing chief Bengt Sjoblom sees prices of light-weight coated (LWC) magazine paper rising to about 1,350 German marks per tonne, from the current 1,220 marks, in early summer, says prices should be raised further towards year-end. @</p>
<p>- Insurer Pohjola, which controls almost one fourth of Finnish market, lost half a percentage point of its market share to other insurers in 1996. Rival Sampo is gaining market share in non-life business.</p>
<p>- Power producer IVO's CEO Heikki Marttinen says IVO will keep Swedish Gullspang on the Stockholm bourse.</p>
<p>AAMULEHTI</p>
<p>- Age of solidarity on pay is over: paper industry workers will require their share of the profits from sectors' employers, Jarmo Lahteenmaki, chairman of the Finnish Paper Workers' Union.</p>
<p>- New top Finnish state prosecutor will take office in June, if Justice Ministry's plans holds. @</p>
<p>- Profitability in retail in the first months of this year was dimmer than expected, but now sales are increasing, says Guy Wires, managing director of the Federation of Finnish Commerce and Trade.</p>
<p>DEMARI</p>
<p>- Retail sector needs long transition period from markka to euro, should be organised in phases, says Marnus Bargum, chairman of the Federation of Finnish Commerce and Trade.</p>
<p>-- Nora Hallberg, Helsinki Newsroom +358-9-680 50 292</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
