<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612081" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian stocks forge to record close on rate cut.</title>
<headline>Australian stocks forge to record close on rate cut.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian stocks raced on Friday to their third successive record close as interest rate sensitive sectors like banking, insurance and retail celebrated a surprise cut in official interest rates.</p>
<p>Brokers said the cut in the official cash rate to 5.5 percent to 6.0 percent released an already bullish market from its previous shackles around 2,550 on the All Ordinaries index, allowing it to bolt into new blue skies around 2,570.</p>
<p>&quot;The reality is, the bears have done their selling and now there's no real incentive to do any more selling,&quot; BNP Equities head of sales John Bowie Wilson.</p>
<p>The All Ordinaries Index raced to a new intra-day record high of 2,572.7 in the first hour of trade after the cut, which the Reserve Bank argued was possible because wages growth had moderated.</p>
<p>The All Ordinaries eventually closed up 16 points at 2,563.9, after a midsession consolidation was discarded in a late session bout of enthusiasm.</p>
<p>Brokers said profit-taking evident in late morning appeared to have set new resistance around 2,570.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be hard to break through that,&quot; said Macquarie Equities broker Simon Jones.</p>
<p>Interest rate sensitive stocks like the banks, insurers and retailers blazed the way for the market overall, with National Australia Bank jumping 34 cents to A$18.79 (US$14.47) and ANZ Banking Group rising 13 cents to A$8.31.</p>
<p>News that home lending market leader Commonwealth Bank had boosted its margins by passing on only 30 points of the 50 basis point cut heartened investors who began the week selling the banks down on concerns about a margin squeeze.</p>
<p>The other major banks followed suit. The banking index closed up 41.4 points or about one percent at 4,519.4, having earlier risen over 80 points to 4,564.7.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
