<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612034" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Paribas to transfer Belgian unit to Bacob.</title>
<headline>Paribas to transfer Belgian unit to Bacob.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>French financial holding company Paribas said on Friday it and Groupe Bacob-Arco had signed a memorandum laying out plans to transfer Paribas Belgique to Groupe Bacob-Arco.</p>
<p>&quot;The memorandum envisages the sale by Groupe Paribas of 47 percent of Paribas Belgique to Groupe Bacob-Arco to add to its existing shareholding,&quot; Paribas said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;At the same time, Groupe Bacob-Arco would launch a tender offer to minority shareholders which could increase its shareholding to 70 percent,&quot; it said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The remaining 30 percent of the shares would be kept by Paribas and could be sold to Bacob-Arco thereafter,&quot; says the statement.</p>
<p>The French group said its Belgian unit, mainly involved in commercial banking, held a &quot;significant share of the domestic market&quot;, employing 1,400 staff with around 50 agencies and that it made a profit of four billion Belgian francs in 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Banque Bacob has a strong position in the Belgian retail banking market, notably in the non-profit making organisation, repo and securitisation sectors,&quot; said the statement.</p>
<p>Paribas said the deal would &quot;allow a new leading Belgian bank entity to be created&quot;.</p>
<p>The statement did not give financial details of the transaction.</p>
<p>Banque Bacob, the most important subsidiary of the Bacob-Arco group, earned net income of 3.1 billion Belgian francs in 1996, the statement said, and it has 3,600 staff in 562 agencies.</p>
<p>-- Paris Newsroom +33 1 4221 5452</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
