<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612070" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: REUTERS GERMAN ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA DIGEST - MAY 23.</title>
<headline>REUTERS GERMAN ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA DIGEST - MAY 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>--------------GAM-----------------------</p>
<p>REUTERS GERMAN ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA DIGEST</p>
<p>-----------May 23, 1997-----------------</p>
<p>News from Reuters and the German press on Advertising, Marketing, Media, the Internet, Brand-name Products and Consumer Trends</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>ADVERTISING &amp; MARKETING:</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Advertising agency Ammirati Puris Lintas of Hamburg has lost the account for cinema advertising for Langnese food products. Ogilvy &amp; Mather in Duesseldorf will take over the account. (Horizont)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Siegel &amp; Gale, the sixth largest design agency in the world, is closing its office in Hamburg. (Horizont)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>DUESSELDORF - Advertising group TBWA says it names Torsten Heinson managing director of its German unit in Frankfurt. Heinson will join Ulf Schierke, Rainer Bollmann and Manfred Schneider in leading operations. (Reuter)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>MEDIA &amp; THE INTERNET:</p>
<p>UNTERFOEHRING - Television group ProSieben Media AG, which plans to float on the Frankfurt stock exchange in July, says sales and profits grew both in 1996 and the first quarter of this year. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Teenagers watch far less television than adults in Germany, media marketing company IP Deutschland says. Germans aged 14 to 19 spend an average of 100 minutes a day in front of their television sets, while those over 20 watch almost twice as much TV, IP Deutschland says, based on data from media research body GfK. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Sports like tennis, ice hockey and handball are dipping in popularity on German television and need to improve their image, market research institute Sport &amp; Markt says. Only soccer has maintained its popularity with teenagers and adults among German television sports spectators, holding onto the number one spot, says Hartmut Zastrow, director of Sport &amp; Markt. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>STUTTGART - Media officials from the southwestern state of Baden-Wuerttemberg say the state plans to launch a trial programme for digital broadcasting on the region's cable network. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>BONN - Deutsche Telekom says it plans to restructure the prices for its online service with the release of the new T-Online-Software 2.0. (Reuter)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>BRAND-NAME PRODUCTS &amp; MARKETS:</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Dell Computer Corp expects a smooth transition in leadership after naming a successor to the chief who turned around its European units. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>STUTTGART - Sportscar maker Dr.Ing.h.c. Porsche AG says demand for its products within Germany so far this year is stronger than it had expected. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>HAMBURG - Fashion group Jil Sander AG says it expects operating profit for 1997 to remain at about the same level as in 1996. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>BRAUNSCHWEIG - Authorities investigating allegations that workers at carmaker Volkswagen AG demanded and received bribes in return for contracts say they have collected &quot;wide-ranging documents.&quot; (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>ERLANGEN - Industrial group Siemens AG says its automotive systems unit will acquire 80 percent of Hydraulik-Ring Beteiligungs GmbH, a maker of hydraulic systems. (Reuter)</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MUNICH - Luxury carmaker BMW has denied it will take part in Formula 1 auto racing. (Reuter)</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>Deborah Cole, Berlin Newsroom, 49-30-203-98114</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>For further information and news, see Reuters Advertising &amp; Media Briefing. And visit us on the Internet:</p>
<p>http://www.bizinfo.reuters.com</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
