<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612041" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss M0 grew annualised 6.1 pct in April vs Q4 96.</title>
<headline>Swiss M0 grew annualised 6.1 pct in April vs Q4 96.</headline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Switzerland's seasonally adjusted central bank money supply (M0) sank by 155 million Swiss francs in April from March to stand at 32,559 million, the Swiss National Bank said in an advance summary of its monthly report.</p>
<p>&quot;This represents an increase of 2.5 percent compared with the fourth quarter of 1996. The annualised growth rate was 6.1 percent,&quot; the central bank said.  </p>
<p>M0 had grown at an annualised rate of 9.2 percent in the first quarter compared with the fourth quarter of 1996. but the SNB said last month it expected M0 growth to slow in the second quarter.</p>
<p>It forecast at that time that M0 -- which consists of notes in circulation and sight deposits at the central bank -- would average 32.9 billion francs in the second quarter.</p>
<p>But the SNB said this week it had increased liquidity significantly to counter the Swiss franc's recent rise, which it said did not reflect economic fundamentals.</p>
<p>-- Zurich newsroom +41 1 631 7340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E121">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
