<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612018" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: PRESS DIGEST - Portugal -- May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Portugal -- May 23.</headline>
<dateline>LISBON 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are leading domestic stories in Portuguese newspapers.</p>
<p>PUBLICO</p>
<p>- Prince Saidi of Saudi Arabia bought the bottled water company Frize, based in Tras-os-Montes in northern Portugal, for 1.2 billion escudos. The prince plans to invest 10 to 20 billion escudos in Portugal in the financial, real estate and water sectors.</p>
<p>- State television network RTP reduced its costs by 3.5 percent in 1996 and focused its investments on upgrading communications equipment.</p>
<p>DIARIO DE NOTICIAS</p>
<p>- The European Commission has opened an investigation against the Portuguese state following a complaint from pharmaceutical company Astra accusing the national medicines institute of failing to suspend the sale of medicines suspected of having entered Portugal bearing documents of other products.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Antonio Guterres has backed Agriculture Minister Fernando Gomes da Silva after the minister angered farmers with remarks about the competitiveness of Portuguese agriculture.</p>
<p>DIARIO ECONOMICO</p>
<p>- State electricity company EDP-Electricidade de Portugal and the U.S. company AirTouch have suspended talks on the possible purchase by EDP of a 20 percent stake in mobile phone company Telecel, the newspaper learned. One reason for the suspension of the talks is that the price of the Telecel shares was considered too high.</p>
<p>SEMANARIO ECONOMICO</p>
<p>- Alianca/UAP will sell from next year insurance products in branches of retail chain Pao de Acucar, which belongs to French retailer Auchan.</p>
<p>-- Lisbon bureau 3511-3538254</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LISBON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
