<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612017" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German DAX moves ahead, Daimler and VW lead.</title>
<headline>German DAX moves ahead, Daimler and VW lead.</headline>
<dateline>FRANKFURT 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>German shares edged up in early trade on Friday but were not seen staging any major rally with holidays due in the U.S. and Britain on Monday dampening trade and making significant dollar movements unlikely.</p>
<p>The IBIS-DAX index of electronic trade gained nearly half a percent early on before slipping back to 3,583.35, 7.91 points up on the day. June DAX futures were just higher at 3,586.0.</p>
<p>Volkswagen gained 18.0 marks to 1,155 marks, pushing through a technical resistance point of 1,150, and Daimler was up 75 pfennigs at 132.40. Dealers said there had been buy recommendations in the sector.  </p>
<p>Dresdner Bank stood 39 pfennigs lower at 61.70 after reporting first quarter operating profit before provisions up 10 percent to 991 million marks. It said it was cautiously optimistic for 1997 results and dividend as a whole.</p>
<p>Earlier, it denied media reports it was interested in taking a stake in Postbank, the state-owned bank currently tied to the postal system.</p>
<p>SAP was a little weaker at 316.10 marks, down 1.60 on the day, on what dealers said was continued concern over allegations of insider trading, despite a statement from state prosecutors Thursday clearing 71 SAP staff of any suspicion.</p>
<p>--Frankfurt Newsroom +49 69 756525</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FRANKFURT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
