<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612064" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Future of million dairy farmers on EU agenda.</title>
<headline>Future of million dairy farmers on EU agenda.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The future of more than a million dairy farmers will be aqt the heart of three days of talks between European Union farm ministers beginning in the southern Dutch town of Middelburg on Sunday .</p>
<p>The Dutch, as one of the world's leading exporters of cheese and other dairy products, want to revamp the way the EU controls its milk production to be able to compete on expanding world markets.</p>
<p>&quot;We must start the debate. It's a major issue and something has to be done,&quot; said a Dutch official, whose country holds the EU Presidency until end-June.</p>
<p>The Dutch want to review the system of national production quotas and subsidised prices in preparation for the next round of World Trade Organisation (WTO) negotiations starting in 1999 and the EU's expansion eastwards.</p>
<p>&quot;It's bad tactics to wait until the WTO forces changes,&quot; said another official.</p>
<p>But there is strong resistance from most of the EU's main dairy producers to abolishing quotas as this would result in a flood of milk and a collapse in prices, driving thousands of smaller farmers out of business.</p>
<p>Germany, the biggest producer, wants to extend quotas and maintain remunerative prices to help keep small farmers in business.</p>
<p>Angry French farmers this week blocked deliveries to hypermarkets in various parts of the country to protest against falling milk prices.</p>
<p>But in Middelburg, Farm Commissioner Franz Fischler will present an analysis of EU dairy market prospects showing that its declining 45 percent share of the world market is likely to fall further as high prices make it uncompetitive.</p>
<p>Although the report makes no proposals, it signals that prices will have to be cut if the EU is to continue to export its annual surplus of around nine million tonnes of milk.</p>
<p>The EU is by far the world's largest dairy producer, with an annual output of 120 million tonnes, or just over 20 percent of world production.</p>
<p>But with around 20 dairy cows per farm, the average size of EU holdings is much smaller than those of competitors in New Zealand and Australia which have an average of 200 and 118 animals respectively.</p>
<p>Fischler, while suggesting that quotas could become more flexible, has defended the system, saying it has curbed surpluses and allowed farmers to survive in mountain and other poor regions.</p>
<p>Italy, where milk producers earlier this year brought large parts of the country to a standstill, and Britain are pressing for increased quotas to satisfy national needs but this is likely to be strongly resisted.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
