<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612080" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Corporates gear up to change face of Aussie debt.</title>
<headline>Corporates gear up to change face of Aussie debt.</headline>
<byline>Colin Brinsden</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The time is ripe for Australian corporations to raise funds in local capital markets as a dwindling supply of government bonds leaves a growing pension funds industry short of investment opportunities.</p>
<p>And analysts say Friday's official interest rate cut to 5.5 percent from 6.0 percent, the fourth cut in under a year, will only encourage them to take the plunge.</p>
<p>&quot;The rate cut will encourage corporate treasurers to issue debt and lock in these rates. Investors will be looking beyond the lower-yielding government debt markets in order to increase returns,&quot; said Jason Carley, ANZ Investment Bank's head of research in Sydney.</p>
<p>Analysts see the move to corporate debt revolutionising the local debt market's thinking on investment.</p>
<p>&quot;The significant changes will be for people in the fund managers where you are really going to need to assess credit from a much wider perspective,&quot; Matthew Drennan, senior economist at Axiom Funds Management.</p>
<p>&quot;You are going to have to consider 'what credit ratings are we going to let our people invest in',&quot; he added.</p>
<p>This will put increasing demand for research on companies' financial status and put more reliance on credit agencies such as Standard &amp; Poor's Corp and Moody's Investors Service, whose ratings already go hand-in-hand with trading in the U.S. corporate debt market and the Eurobond market.</p>
<p>Until recently, investment fund managers generally only operated in Australian government and state debt markets and usually through taking a punt on the market's next move.</p>
<p>&quot;We are seeing a move away from that to more conservative directional plays in the market, but greater emphasis on taking credit risk or business risk for best return,&quot; said Nigel Douglas, chief economist at Merrill Lynch Australia.</p>
<p>The economic climate has also changed markedly from when corporates where last noticeably seen issuing bonds in the early 1990's, when interest rates were still relatively high.</p>
<p>Australian inflation is low -- announcing Friday's rate cut, the RBA said it expected underlying inflation below 2.0 percent in the coming quarters -- yield spreads to government debt of long standing corporate issues have tightened, and the federal and state governments have tightened their fiscal belts.</p>
<p>In last week's federal budget the government said the net borrowing requirement would be negative through to 2000/01, reducing total outstanding debt over that time to some A$84 billion from over A$100 billion.</p>
<p>ANZ Investment Bank, which is a unit of the Melbourne-based big four bank Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd, has alredy put in place a research team in Sydney to analyse credit.</p>
<p>The bank's London-based global head of finanical markets, Mark Coombs, was in Sydney on Thursday as part of its commitment to building up interest in the corporate debt market.</p>
<p>Coombs told Reuters Australian investors have been fairly conservative in their approach to credit risk, tending to stick to investments that are in the A-category rated debt.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a new departure for Australian investors. But they are doing the right thing, they are taking their time, they are beginning to understand it professionally,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are doing analysis and saying -- look don't mess around in double-A, have a look at triple-B. Start thinking about BBB and the value, and how basically you are getting paid far too much for what is not really that lower credit.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
