<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612061" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: FEATURE - Marshall Plan launched German economic miracle.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Marshall Plan launched German economic miracle.</headline>
<byline>Kevin Liffey</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The American-funded Marshall Plan, 50 years old next month, is widely credited with hauling Europe out of post-war misery with an injection of food, raw materials and dollars.</p>
<p>But to defeated, ostracised Germany it was more like a firm but friendly influence which steered the nation's western half back into the international community and down the road to a world-beating economic system -- the social market economy.</p>
<p>So impressive was Germany's recovery that the plan was invoked by politicians to inspire the post-communist rebuilding of east Germany after the fall of the Berlin Wall, and continues to be invoked wherever economic reconstruction is called for.</p>
<p>&quot;The Americans were paying and they called the shots in setting up a strongly capitalist system,&quot; said Hanno Sowade, organiser of an exhibition on Germany's post-war economy in Bonn's modern history museum.</p>
<p>&quot;Without the Marshall Plan, the young economic system would have been much slower to develop.&quot;</p>
<p>Four years after World War Two, Volkswagen cars and BMW motorcycles were being shown at the New York trade fair. By 1951, Germany's exports were back to their pre-war level.</p>
<p>By the mid-1950s, it was the world's third biggest trading nation and the pariahs of a decade earlier were proclaiming, &quot;We are somebody again&quot;.</p>
<p>The power stations and housing estates built with Marshall Plan money can still be seen, but they tell only half the story.</p>
<p>Despite the famous newsreel footage of whole cities bombed to rubble after the war, Germany's industrial base, pumped up by the Nazi war machine, remained largely intact.</p>
<p>What had gone was the effective distribution network and an economic system that people could have confidence in.</p>
<p>The American and British occupiers provided food aid that saw off the worst of the hunger.</p>
<p>But Washington, which had originally planned to revive Germany as a weakened, agricultural state, saw the European economy was not picking up and therefore needed its main motor -- Germany.</p>
<p>MARSHALL PLAN HAD CONDITIONS ATTACHED</p>
<p>The plan which Secretary of State George Marshall launched in his Harvard speech on June 5, 1947 was to offer about $13 billion to help economic revival -- but with strings attached.</p>
<p>With the Cold War brewing and communism at western Europe's door, the United States wanted to establish free-market capitalism firmly in as much of the continent as possible, among victors and vanquished.</p>
<p>Germany, meanwhile, had to replace a wartime command economy.</p>
<p>To many, socialism, promoted especially by the British occupiers in the north, seemed attractive after the far-right Nazi dictatorship which had brought ruin on the country. But the British were nearly bankrupt and had to yield to American wishes.</p>
<p>&quot;The Marshall Plan settled that question,&quot; said Hans-Juergen Schroeder of Giessen University, editor of a book on the plan.</p>
<p>&quot;The Americans didn't want socialism and essentially showed that the capitalist system worked.&quot;</p>
<p>Germany got about 10 percent of the European Recovery Plan funds but, unlike other countries, as credit, not grants.</p>
<p>Most came as food and industrial raw materials, allowing it, like the other countries, to save the scarce dollars which were virtually the only currency of international trade.</p>
<p>The German customers paid marks into a &quot;counterpart fund&quot; which went to ease production and supply bottlenecks.</p>
<p>But above all, the United States pushed a reluctant Britain and France, both still suspicious of Germany, into trading with their former enemy using a payments union which meant commerce could take place without dollars.</p>
<p>&quot;The Marshall Plan was clearly about European integration, tied to the U.S. policy of containing communism,&quot; Sowade said.</p>
<p>That policy led a substantial portion of Marshall money to be channelled to Allied-occupied West Berlin, which rapidly became an outpost of capitalism in Soviet-occupied East Germany.</p>
<p>The Kraftwerk West power station still bears testimony to the 1948-49 Allied airlift which not only flew in food to break a Soviet blockade of West Berlin, but also parts to ensure the city's electricity supply.</p>
<p>Most of the station's machinery had been dismantled by the Soviets -- a fate shared by much of eastern Germany.</p>
<p>LACK OF MARSHALL AID, SOVIET REPARATIONS CRIPPLED EAST</p>
<p>Ironically, the eastern part of the country had suffered much less from Allied bombers, which had further to travel there.</p>
<p>But Soviet reparations squads were much more diligent than their Western equivalents after the war, dismantling around 1,000 factories almost in their entirety and reducing eastern Germany's steel production capacity by 80 percent.</p>
<p>Deprived of Marshall Plan funds and a capitalist system, East Germany's standard of living fell behind, even as its leader Walter Ulbricht was railing that &quot;every German should make a stand against the colonisation of West Germany&quot;.</p>
<p>But the Americans were in fact shepherding the new post-war West Germany back towards economic independence.</p>
<p>Determined that ordinary citizens should support the plan, they launched one of the most sophisticated and successful public relations exercises of the time.</p>
<p>The highlight was the Europe Train, a rolling exhibition on the &quot;Cooperation of Free Peoples&quot; that toured 18 countries in 1951-53 and drew 780,000 visitors in West Berlin alone.</p>
<p>They found the perfect ally in economics professor Ludwig Erhard.</p>
<p>Made West German economic director with U.S. backing, Erhard fathered the &quot;social market economy&quot;, a corporatist, consensus-oriented brand of capitalism which was the framework for West Germany's famed &quot;Wirtschaftswunder&quot; (Economic Miracle) and which has only just begun to look outdated.</p>
<p>Erhard's currency reform of 1948, trigger of the Berlin blockade, eliminated the black market and put goods in shops overnight.</p>
<p>While rationing was abolished in West Germany in 1948, it lasted 10 years longer in East Germany. In 1961, 52 percent of West Germans had their own refrigerator and 34 percent a television. In the east in 1960, it was six percent and 19 percent respectively.</p>
<p>The east did belatedly get its Marshall Plan money, however.</p>
<p>West Germany amassed a fund with European Recovery Programme money that was not paid back, recycling the credits over and over again to help small and medium-sized businesses.</p>
<p>Since unification in 1990, 260,000 credits amounting to over 52 billion marks ($30.7 billion) have gone to establish the market economy in the eastern part of the country. ($ = 1.695 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
