<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612002" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Juppe predicts difficult first electoral round.</title>
<headline>Juppe predicts difficult first electoral round.</headline>
<byline>Bernard Edinger</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe predicted on Friday a difficult first round for his centre-right coalition in France's parliamentary election on Sunday because of a record number of candidates.</p>
<p>&quot;It's obvious there will be a dispersal of votes. One can see that from the high number of candidates in most constituencies,&quot; Juppe told Radio France-Inter.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of that, it will be a difficult first round. It will be difficult even to interpret the results since it is doubtful that a strong trend will emerge,&quot; Juppe said.</p>
<p>An upbeat, opposition Socialist leader Lionel Jospin told his last big campaign rally before the first round: &quot;They (the right) are scared of losing, we have hopes of winning.&quot;</p>
<p>More than 6,200 candidates will vie for 577 National Assembly seats in the single-member constituencies with a record of 29 candidates in one Paris district.</p>
<p>The top two candidates in each district plus anyone who polls at least 12.5 percent of the number of registered voters, qualify for a June 1 runoff.</p>
<p>In a separate interview published in the newspaper Le Figaro, Juppe warned that a left-wing victory would cripple France because of unavoidable &quot;cohabitation&quot; or power-sharing.</p>
<p>He said the centre-right's priorities if it stayed in power after the May 25-June 1 poll would include limiting the number of offices politicians may hold and giving women a bigger say.</p>
<p>&quot;Experience shows that cohabitation does not put France in a strong position, it does not allow it to play its role to the full, chiefly on the European or international stage, and it puts a brake on or paralyses big economic decisions,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The interviews came after the holding of the last major political rallies including one where extreme rightist leader Jean-Marie Le Pen accused President Jacques Chirac of turning France into a &quot;Chirassic Park.</p>
<p>Opinion polls released before last weekend's blackout suggested the centre-right would retain power but the stock market has been jittery, with dealers citing rumours of secret polls showing the government's lead narrowing.</p>
<p>The premier said he would overhaul voting procedures at regional and European Parliament level, limit the number of offices which parliamentarians can hold to one other post, and change the constitution to give women better access to politics.</p>
<p>&quot;I am personally in favour of a constitutional measure which would facilitate (women's presence) on a temporaray basis,&quot; Juppe said.</p>
<p>In his last campaign rally, Juppe urged voters on Thursday to put France back on its feet while Socialist challenger Lionel Jospin battled to defuse charges that he might derail a single European currency.</p>
<p>Jospin, campaigning in Toulouse in the strongly left-wing southwest, reiterated backing for a single European currency on four conditions, including the inclusion of Spain and Italy from the start.</p>
<p>Apart from the inclusion of Italy and Spain, Jospin wants a European &quot;economic government&quot; as a counterweight to the planned EU central bank, a pact of solidarity and growth to combat unemployment and measures to avoid over-valuation of the euro currency.</p>
<p>Jospin urged voters to punish those who had been in power for the past four years and who held &quot;all power&quot; in their hands.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
