<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612042" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: PRESS DIGEST - Germany - May 23.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Germany - May 23.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following are the main stories from Friday morning's German newspapers:</p>
<p>FRANKFURTER ALLGEMEINE ZEITUNG</p>
<p>- Government, union and employers launch programme to create 100,000 jobs in the next year in eastern Germany. Chancellor Helmut Kohl says the agreement is an important step for the recovery of eastern Germany.</p>
<p>- Germany's association of skilled labourers expects 50,000 jobs to be eliminated in the sector this year.</p>
<p>- Free Democrats (FDP) want to stand up to their coalition partners, the Christian Democrats, firmly but not challenge them openly. The FDP begins weekend party congress in Wiesbaden feeling pressure from the Christian Democrats to raise taxes to fill budget gaps.</p>
<p>- Pension contributions could be raised to record levels of 20.5 percent in 1998 because of costs of high unemployment, chairman of German pension insurers (VDR) Erich Standfaest says.</p>
<p>HANDELSBLATT</p>
<p>- FDP fights for its credibility at party congress in Wiesbaden. Party leaders do not want to commit themselves to negotiate with Finance Minister Theo Waigel over 1998 budget that has to pass through the cabinet in July.</p>
<p>- Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel says that he could foresee the government selling its entire stake in Deutsche Telekom in order to qualify for the EMU criteria. He says he has nothing against selling the government's 75 percent stake in Telekom.</p>
<p>- Money supply growth in April hardly changed, rising 2.7 percent from fourth quarter of 1996.</p>
<p>SUEDDEUTSCHE ZEITUNG</p>
<p>- Dresdner Bank wants to take majority stake in Postbank, according to a working paper from the London investment bank J. Henry Schroders obtained by the newspaper. The plan drawn up at the request of the postal authority is known as the &quot;Dresdner Bank Model&quot; and stands in contrast to a plan to quickly float the Postbank on the bourse. The sale to Dresdner would raise billions of marks for Finance Minister Theo Waigel.</p>
<p>- Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel plans to defend army conscripion at FDP party congress in Wiesbaden.</p>
<p>- Social Democrats (SPD) want special &quot;extra tax&quot; for millionaires. Tax would be leveled on individuals having assets of more than one million marks. Those with assets between one and 10 million marks would pay one percent tax, those with 10 to 50 million would pay two percent and those with assets over 50 million marks would pay three percent.</p>
<p>DIE WELT</p>
<p>- Kohl says the East Alliance to create 100,000 jobs represents a chance for eastern recovery.</p>
<p>- Foreign Minister Kinkel rejects criticism from U.S. government about Germany's plans to deport Bosnian war refugees.</p>
<p>- Parliamentary president Rita Suessmuth says government's plans to move to Berlin in the summer of 1999 are on track. She says the remodelling of the Reichstag building should be completed by then.</p>
<p>-- Bonn Newsroom +49 228 26097160</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
