<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612065" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Worldwide Advertising &amp; Media Digest - May 23.</title>
<headline>Worldwide Advertising &amp; Media Digest - May 23.</headline>
<text>
<p>------------------------- WAM ------------------------</p>
<p>....REUTERS WORLDWIDE ADVERTISING &amp; MEDIA DIGEST.....</p>
<p>------------------- May 23, 1997 ------------------</p>
<p>Reuters news from around the world on Advertising, Marketing, Media, the Internet, Brand-name Products and Consumer Trends ***********************************************</p>
<p>ADVERTISING &amp; MARKETING:</p>
<p>CHICAGO - UAL Corp's United Airlines says it launches its new $125 million advertising called &quot;Rising&quot;, based on a commitment to improve customer service. &quot;It tells our customers that we are working hard to improve our products and services to meet their needs,&quot; United chief executive Gerald Greenwald says. The campaign was developed by United and its two advertising agencies, Fallon-McElligott of Minneapolis and Young &amp; Rubicam of New York.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - French media company Havas reports first-quarter sales rose to 14.74 billion francs ($2.6 billion), 34 percent above year-earlier levels. &quot;Revenues reflect first full consolidation of Canal Plus and Havas Image, formerly Generale d'Images,&quot; Havas says.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>BATTLE CREEK, Michigan - Breakfast cereal giant Kellogg Co says it will team up with &quot;Batman &amp; Robin,&quot; the Warner Bros motion picture that is expected to be released across the U.S. on June 20. Kellogg said 13 of its ready-to-eat cereals, plus Kellogg's Pop-Tarts and Kellogg's Eggo Waffles, feature a variety of movie tie-ins including new movie-themed food products, special movie character package designs and promotional offers.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - Unilever AS/Plc brings a CD-Rom promoting detergents to France, where households with multimedia equipment are scarce. The CD-Rom promoting Skip detergent, already launched in Britain, Norway, Sweden and Denmark, cost much less than conventional advertising, says Loic Tardy, head of Unilever's Lever France.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>DUESSELDORF - Advertising group TBWA names Torsten Heinson managing director of its German unit in Frankfurt.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>MEDIA &amp; THE INTERNET:</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Teenagers in Germany watch far less television than adults, media marketing company IP Deutschland says. Germans between the ages of 14 and 19 spend an average of 100 minutes a day in front of their television sets, while those over 20 watch almost twice as much TV, IP Deutschland says, based on data from media research body GfK.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>WASHINGTON - The Clinton administration throws its support behind legislation to prevent state and local governments from slapping new taxes on the Internet, giving a boost to a bill opposed by state and local officials. The bill would impose an indefinite moratorium during which state and local governments could not tax the Internet, companies providng Internet access, and electronic commerce conducted in cyberspace.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>NEW YORK - Peter Lund, the president of the CBS television network has resigned, the New York Times reports. The Times quotes unnamed high-level executives as saying Lund resigned after he was informed he would no longer oversee the network's television-stations division.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>PARIS - Lyonnaise Cable, the cable television unit of Lyonnaise des Eaux, says it will launch a digital television service on all its cable television networks in France from June 2. The move will allow it to offer three times as many film channels with various subscription possibilities. It will run a national advertising campaign on the launch from next Monday until June 2.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>FRANKFURT - Sports like tennis, ice hockey and handball are declining in popularity on German television and need to improve their image, market research institute Sport &amp; Markt says. Only soccer has maintained its popularity with teenagers and adults among German television spectator sports in recent years, and remains the number one sport, says Hartmut Zastrow, director of Sport &amp; Markt.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MELBOURNE - Australian media baron Kerry Packer has again topped his country's rich list, boosting his personal fortune to a peerless A$3.9 ($2.99) billion. Packer, whose media empire owns Australia's biggest commercial television network and a stable of magazines, is now worth more than twice his nearest rival in the seriously rich stakes, Business Review Weekly magazine says in its annual &quot;Rich 200&quot; edition.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>BRAND-NAME PRODUCTS &amp; MARKETS:</p>
<p>CHICAGO - Entertainment giant Viacom Inc unveils a theme store in Chicago, the first of several retail outlets that the company hopes will bolster revenue by exploiting its Nickelodeon, Star Trek and MTV brands names. The Viacom Entertainment Store, a playhouse of products designed after Viacom's cable TV characters and Hollywood studio hits, is as much an effort to heighten recognition of its obscure corporate name as to build revenue.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MOSCOW - Foreign and Russian investors gave a green light to two major car-manufacturing projects in Russia this month, promising to build multi-million dollar factories, but planned output and foreign investment are still in low gear. Foreign car makers have announced plans to produce tens of thousands of new cars in Russia for the domestic million-car market over the next couple of years, taking a cautious approach to working in Russia with Russians.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>OAK BROOK, Illinois - McDonald's Corp says it will raise its standards on food taste and service and hints that it might add a new chicken product to the menu. &quot;Taste, service and value are the three big hitters,&quot; says Chairman Michael Quinlan. &quot;We just might have some real hot new chicken stuff.&quot;</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>MEXICO CITY - Reebok de Mexico SA, a division of Reebok International Ltd, says it plans to build a $6 million factory in Mexico's Guanajuato state this year.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>OAK BROOK, Illinois - McDonalds' Corp says it will open one of its restaurants in Ukraine, making the former Soviet republic the 102nd country to have as McDonald's location.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>CONSUMER TRENDS:</p>
<p>TEHRAN - Wealthy Iranians can still, at a price, buy at least one American luxury in the shops of downtown Tehran -- toothpaste all the way from Cincinnati. A tube of Procter and Gamble's Crest-brand toothpaste is sold at 15,000 rials ($5 at the official exchange rate) compared to Iran's home-made Darougar brand which retails at just 220 rials.</p>
<p>*********</p>
<p>ISLAMABAD - Lawmakers vote to ban lavish wedding feasts, a Pakistani custom which the government says causes hardship for the poor and middle classes. Families will be allowed to celebrate with a &quot;valima&quot; or wedding meal at home for relatives and house guests. But larger gatherings at hotels, clubs and other places outside the home will be limited to serving hot and cold soft drinks -- without food.</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>-- London Advertising Newsdesk +44 171 542 2792</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>See full stories on Reuters Advertising &amp; Media Briefing. And why not visit our Internet site at http://www.bizinfo.reuters.com?</p>
<p>***********************************************</p>
<p>($ = 5.696 French Francs)</p>
<p>($ = 1.302 Australian Dollars)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83800">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
