<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612024" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: UPM sees LWC prices up in summer - paper.</title>
<headline>UPM sees LWC prices up in summer - paper.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Finnish forest industry group UPM-Kymmene Oy sees prices of light-weight coated (LWC) magazine paper rising at the beginning of summer, business newspaper Kauppalehti reported on Friday.</p>
<p>It quoted UPM's marketing chief Bengt Sjoblom as saying that he expected LWC prices to rise to 1,350 German marks per tonne from the current 1,220 marks at the beginning of summer and that it should be possible to raise prices further towards year-end.</p>
<p>UPM-Kymmene said in its first quarter earnings report that the decline in magazine prices, which had continued for about a year, ended during the first three months of this year.</p>
<p>It also said it planned to introduce previously announced LWC price rises of five to eight percent during the second quarter.</p>
<p>UPM-Kymmene's expansion of its Rauma paper mill was progressing on schedule, and a 400,000-tonne LWC machine being installed there was expected to be completed by February, in time to benefit from the upswing in prices, Kauppalehti said.</p>
<p>The new machine would raise UPM's LWC production to 2.2 million tonnes per year, the newspaper said.</p>
<p>The paper also quoted forestry group Metsa-Serla's marketing chief Thomas Nysten as saying that -- given current pulp prices -- a tonne of LWC should be priced at 1,450 German marks, Kauppalehti said.</p>
<p>LWC prices are lagging 25 percent behind the price level of last May, Kauppalehti said, adding that the average limit for profitability is believed to be 1,670 German marks per tonne.</p>
<p>Metsa-Serla's Nysten said UPM's new 400,000-tonne capacity addition would force other manufacturers to cut their mill utilisation rates to below 90 percent for the next two or three years and spark fierce price competition.</p>
<p>UPM's Sjoblom said the 400,000-tonne addition would not upset the world market for 13 to 14 million tonnes of LWC per year.</p>
<p>-- Helsinki Newsroom +358-9-680 50 235, news@reuters.fi</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
