<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612040" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Van Miert raises stakes in Boeing/McDonnell Douglas deal.</title>
<headline>Van Miert raises stakes in Boeing/McDonnell Douglas deal.</headline>
<byline>Amelia Torres</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>The challenge by European Competition chief Karel Van Miert to the proposed merger between Boeing Co and McDonnell Douglas is a risky gamble which could spark a transatlantic dispute.</p>
<p>Ignoring claims that the U.S. is better placed to deal with the case and accusations that he is catering for the interests of Europe's Airbus, Boeing's only serious competitor, Van Miert warned the two companies of his concerns in a statement late Thursday.</p>
<p>Seattle-based Boeing immediately reacted, again denying that the deal would restrict competition and reiterating that the U.S. Federal Trade Commission should be given the prime responsibility for vetting it.</p>
<p>The EU Commission has repeatedly said it has the power to probe and, if need be, set conditions on the $14 billion deal, arguing that it is strictly applying EU rules aimed at preventing creation or strengthening of dominant positions in the Union.</p>
<p>The Boeing/McDonnell Douglas deal is one of two major proposed alliances being investigated by the Commission, the other being the linkup between British Airways and AMR's American Airlines.</p>
<p>Newspapers on both sides of the Atlantic have speculated about prospects for a nasty trade dispute. A group of U.S. senators have asked President Bill Clinton to ensure that the EU's review of the Boeing/McDonnell Douglas deal was fair and not driven by political considerations.</p>
<p>While saying it is difficult to imagine a way out of the corner which both parties have put themselves in with their strong statements, most analysts and antitrust lawyers believe a compromise will be found.</p>
<p>They stressed that both the U.S. authorities and Boeing accept that the EU has jurisdiction over the merger and, therefore, must also accept that the EU may have reservations.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's unlikely that this would result in a trade war. I would think that it would be in both parties' interests to reach an amicable resolution given the large stakes involved,&quot; Randolph Tritell, a partner with law firm Weil Gotshall &amp; Manges told Reuters.</p>
<p>Tritell noted that the United States also often asserts jurisdiction over extraterritorial transactions which have an effect on its soil. Last year the FTC approved the merger between Swiss drug companies Sandoz and Ciba Geigy only after ordering a $780 million divestiture.</p>
<p>Speculating about a war before knowing what the FTC thinks, whether or not it shares the EU's concerns, was putting the cart before the horse, another lawyer said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's idle to speculate at this point whether there will be a war before we see whether there is a jurisdictional conflict. We don't know what the FTC thinks,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Van Miert shrugged off the trade war suggestions last week as &quot;totally nonsensical&quot;.</p>
<p>Brussels-based U.S. government officials also said on Thursday they thought politicians were likely to keep out of the issue until the Commission and the U.S. completed their review.</p>
<p>They said President Clinton was not expected to discuss the merger at a regular meeting next Wednesday in the Hague with Commission President Jacques Santer and Dutch Prime Minister Wim Kok, whose country currently holds the EU presidency.</p>
<p>&quot;The president will be hard put to comment because we are still looking at it,&quot; one official said.</p>
<p>While nobody really contests the EU's competence to probe the merger, there has been some frowning at Van Miert's public aggressive stance even before Boeing formally submitted the deal for clearance last December.</p>
<p>McDonnell Douglas CEO Harry Stonecipher said recently Van Miert's public statements were &quot;totally inappropriate&quot;. &quot;It's obvious he wants a war, but I don't want a war,&quot; he told reporters in Washington.</p>
<p>Sources close to Van Miert said he was unlikely to be taken aback by such criticism, but were anxious to bring a more serene tone to the debate and to insist that negotiation, not confrontation, was the key word.</p>
<p>They also said that Van Miert's briefing of his colleagues on Wednesday about the Boeing and British Airways alliances went quite rapidly and smoothly without any discordant voices.</p>
<p>Since he took over the competition portfolio in 1993, Van Miert has become increasingly confident of ensuring a level playing ground for businesses in the 15-nation bloc.</p>
<p>He has repeatedly shown he is not frightened of upsetting large companies or powerful governments.</p>
<p>So far he has been followed by his 19 colleagues on all important cases almost without exception despite some teeth gnashing when some big national interests were at stake, a factor which will not be present in this all-American deal.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G157">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
