<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="612096" id="root" date="1997-05-23" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: FEATURE - Russia to produce foreign cars but investment scarce.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Russia to produce foreign cars but investment scarce.</headline>
<byline>Peter Henderson</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-23</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign and Russian investors gave a green light to two major car-manufacturing projects in Russia this month, promising to build multi-million dollar factories, but planned output and foreign investment are still in low gear.</p>
<p>Foreign car makers have announced plans to produce tens of thousands of new cars in Russia for the domestic million-car market over the next couple of years, taking a cautious approach to working in Russia with Russians.</p>
<p>&quot;These are two different cultures,&quot; said Juhani Riutta, president of Finland's Valmet Automotive, which plans to open a plant with General Motors and Russia's AvtoVAZ, aiming for full scale production of an Opel model adapted for the Russian market.</p>
<p>&quot;Considering the plan we have ahead of us, this will not be simple,&quot; Riutta said.</p>
<p>Foreign automobile makers are aiming at cars that cost upwards of $15,000 while domestic base models cost about half that. The average Russian wage is about $200 per month.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to grow production volumes as the economy grows,&quot; said GM manager for Sales and Marketing in Russia, Gregg Henton.</p>
<p>SHORT TERM PLANS BASED ON ASSEMBLING KITS</p>
<p>Short-term plans for foreign car production are based exclusively on assembling kits of cars with some local welding and paint shop operations beginning in 1998 or 1999 and local manufacture of parts beginning thereafter.</p>
<p>General Motors had already opened a plant last year assembling $22-$25,000 two-wheel drive Chevrolet Blazers in Tatarstan, and these have now appeared in the showrooms.</p>
<p>It will produce 10,000 in semi-knock-down kits in 1998, and aims to make about 15,000 to 20,000 complete knock-down kits in 1999.</p>
<p>GM plants may produce only about 55,000 cars before the turn of the century. Russia produced almost 900,000 cars last year.</p>
<p>A Russian company has begun kit-based production of South Korea's Kia Motors cars in western Russia and expects to produce 30,000 cars this year, while Ford has said it is doing feasibility studies on a Russian joint venture.</p>
<p>DOMESTIC PRODUCERS ALSO BOOSTING OUTPUT</p>
<p>Domestic car makers are also busy, though their vehicles are aimed at a much lower market segment.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear that this car is of the next class up from ours, so it is not a competitor,&quot; AvtoVAZ chairman Vladimir Kadannikov said at the announcement of the GM-Avtovaz plans.</p>
<p>AvtoVAZ produced 680,000 cars last year.</p>
<p>Heavy truck builder Kamaz forecasts production of its Oka micro-car would rise to 18,000 this year, double the levels of a year ago.</p>
<p>GAZ  GAZA.RTS, a stock market favourite, has begun production of a newly designed model of its Volga sedan, which like its GAZelle light truck and minibuses is based on the chassis of its older Volga.</p>
<p>Investment -- especially by well-heeled foreigners -- is less than it might appear as backers shun Russian financial risks.</p>
<p>&quot;I am sure the Kia-Baltika factory will bring large investment into the Russian auto industy,&quot; Kia Group chairman Sum Hong Kim said at the opening last week in Kaliningrad of the project, in which his company has no equity stake.</p>
<p>Kia Motors Europe President Tae Seung Chung told Reuters his company felt it was already investing substantially through credits in the form of car parts to be assembled.</p>
<p>&quot;There is still a risk because this is the very beginning stage,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Russian car makers, such as AvtoVAZ, which is the biggest single tax debtor in the country, need cash.</p>
<p>Vladimir Shcherbakov, whose Interprivatizatsia controls the Kia plant, said his company had secured financing of the main $300 million factory which will produce cars from complete knock-down kits requiring on-site welding and painting.</p>
<p>But another top official said only $54 million had been invested so far and that the rest had yet to be found.</p>
<p>&quot;Kaliningrad -- I'll believe it when I see it,&quot; Valmet president Riutta said when asked about competition from Kia.</p>
<p>MOST INVESTORS LOOKING AT LONG TERM</p>
<p>General Motors has a 25 percent equity stake and management control of its factory in Yelabuga, Tatarstan, but has limited its investment in the plant, financed by oil sales, to technology transfers and parts.</p>
<p>Most investors are still looking at the horizon when they talk about major investment, saying the economy is not growing enough to support widescale production of expensive cars.</p>
<p>&quot;We still are not going to see enough wherewithall in the economy to accomodate that much domestic consumption,&quot; GM's Henton said of the Blazer plant's capacity.</p>
<p>Dealer networks are slowly expanding, given the financial and training problems to be surmounted, he said.</p>
<p>But if foreign investors are careful with their investment, Russia is sweeping away its own trade barriers and giving up lucrative import duties and taxes to accomodate foreigners.</p>
<p>Neither Blazers nor KIA cars will pay customs duties, which can almost double the price of imports, and the Blazers avoid a 20 percent value added tax as well.</p>
<p>Valmet's Riutta said he expected tax breaks but that without investment in domestic parts manufacturing, such breaks might be taken away. &quot;They are not for free,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32754">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-23"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-23"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
