<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="619706" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish Tribunal rejects law easing abortion.</title>
<headline>Polish Tribunal rejects law easing abortion.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's Constitutional Tribunal appalled many feminists but gave hope to the Roman Catholic Church on Wednesday by ordering changes in a law which effectively allowed abortion on demand.</p>
<p>In a decision likely to delight Pope John Paul ll on the eve of his May 31 to June 10 pilgrimage to his homeland, the court ruled that the liberalised abortion law passed last year clashed with constitutional guarantees to the right to life.</p>
<p>&quot;The Tribunal's decision is one of the happiest and most important pieces of news I have heard in recent months,&quot; Radio Zet quoted Gdansk Archbishop Tadeusz Goclowski as saying.</p>
<p>But Danuta Waniek, an ex-communist senior parliamentary deputy said the decision went against the dignity of women and the rights and freedoms of those who were pregnant.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that the Tribunal took an important step today in the direction of a clerical state,&quot; said Waniek, who championed the easing of the Church-inspired anti-abortion law of 1993.</p>
<p>The ruling by the court, which exists to test whether laws conform with the constitution, obliges parliament to revise the new law on abortion within six months, during which time the current more liberal rules continue to apply.</p>
<p>To overturn the court decision would require a two-thirds majority in parliament and gaining this in the present legislature looks unlikely on the basis of last year's vote.</p>
<p>Elections are due in September and a powerful rightist alliance around the pro-Catholic Solidarity union is rivalling the secular-minded ex-communists for the lead in opinion polls.</p>
<p>Restricting abortion, an issue over which Poles are split almost exactly 50-50, is a key platform of Solidarity Election Action which hopes to win power.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz said Poland's new constitution, approved in a May 25 referendum, may provide a way to avoid implementing the Tribunal's ruling.</p>
<p>The head of the ruling ex-communists, Jozef Oleksy, told public television the answer might be a referendum on abortion.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear this issue remains constantly divisive... and we consider it could be settled by referendum,&quot; said Oleksy, had of the main party in the Democratic Left Alliance.</p>
<p>Bishop Tadeusz Pieronek, general secretary of Poland's Episcopate, condemned the idea, saying: &quot;Moral issues cannot be put to a referendum.&quot;</p>
<p>Among the court's objections to last year's legislation was a lack of clear criteria applying to a clause which allows women to terminate a pregnancy, until the 12th week, if they have difficult living conditions or other personal problems.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a lack of precise, justified criteria allowing for a distinction according to developmental phases of human life. From the moment it arises, human life becomes a value which is protected under the constitution,&quot; Tribunal president Andrzej Zoll said, announcing the ruling.</p>
<p>Under the previous 1993 law, which could return if the Tribunal's ruling takes force, abortion was allowed only when a pregancy posed a threat to a woman's life, resulted from incest or rape, or the foetus was irreparably damaged.</p>
<p>Due to that law, the number of officially registered abortions each year dropped to less than 1,000 from tens of thousands in the early 1990s when communist-era rules allowed easy abortion.</p>
<p>But critics said it encouraged illegal abortion, led many women to go abroad for the procedure and prompted tragic cases of bungled operations or abandoned infants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
