<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="619897" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: FEATURE - Russian cartoonist still working after 96 years.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Russian cartoonist still working after 96 years.</headline>
<byline>Adam Tanner</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Boris Yefimov remembers that when Josef Stalin suddenly rang to check up on a political cartoon he was drawing, he leapt up and stood at attention by the phone as the Soviet leader dictated his vision.</p>
<p>&quot;You must draw this personality armed to the teeth, with planes, tanks, all sorts of cannons, you understand?&quot; Stalin said, referring to U.S. General Dwight Eisenhower, who was to embody the West's threat to Moscow. &quot;They're coming by at 6 p.m. to pick it up.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I looked at the clock and saw it was 4:30 p.m. and I had two day's worth of work ahead. Had I failed to fulfil the order, I would have perished, but miraculously I finished it,&quot; Yefimov said in an interview.</p>
<p>Stalin personally added some text to the drawing, and the 1947 image of an aggressive Eisenhower threatening a Soviet Eskimo family became one of the first anti-American cartoons of the Cold War.</p>
<p>Today at the age of 96, Yefimov has a memory as sharp as the images of the greedy fat capitalist, the evil Uncle Sam or the crazed Adolf Hilter he drew for decades in official newspapers such as Pravda and Izvestia and other leading Soviet publications.</p>
<p>When the Soviet state wanted to sum up its position in one iconic image, it was often a Yefimov cartoon that spoke louder than an entire report from the Politburo.</p>
<p>YEFIMOV LAUNCHED CAREER DURING RUSSIAN CIVIL WAR</p>
<p>He began his career during the Russian Civil War after the Bolsheviks came to power in 1917, and already by 1924 had published his first in a series of books of political cartoons.</p>
<p>&quot;Boris Yefimov is the most political of our graphic artists,&quot; Leon Trotsky, a Bolshevik leader and once a friend of Yefimov, wrote in the introduction. &quot;He knows politics, likes it and penetrates all the details. This is his strongest trait.&quot;</p>
<p>Looking back on a career that produced tens of thousands of published political caricatures, Yefimov says, ideology and a desire to participate in events motivated his work.</p>
<p>&quot;My generation believed,&quot; he said in his book-lined appartment overlooking the Moskva River. &quot;My caricatures were directed against imperialism, against fascism, the Holocaust, the threat of war, and I believed in this.&quot;</p>
<p>But looking back today, Yefimov does regret some of his drawings, especially during the brutal Stalin era when the state killed millions of innocent citizens.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm sorry about those drawings directed against oppositionists, against Trotsky, against (leading Bolshevik Nikolai) Bukharin, who were victims of repression,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I could not refuse to do them...but today I remember this with disappointment,&quot; said Yefimov, whose bushy white eyebrows flow over his thick glasses. &quot;To say 'No, I don't want to do this, shoot me!' That would be naive.&quot;</p>
<p>YEFIMOV ESCAPED TERROR THAT KILLED BROTHER</p>
<p>Stalin's terror did claim his brother, Mikhail Koltsov, an editor at Pravda and a Supreme Soviet parliamentarian, who was shot in 1940. Many of Koltsov's associates were also arrested.</p>
<p>&quot;I was ready to be arrested the next day after the arrest of my brother Koltsov. I had packed my warm clothes, but no one came that day, or the next or the third,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I understood it was not coincidence. A case had already been prepared against me that my brother was a spy and I was a spy,&quot; he said. &quot;But I was not touched on Stalin's personal order.&quot;</p>
<p>Unlike many of older fellow Russians who, looking back, recall a golden era under the tsars, Stalin or even Leonid Brezhnev, Yefimov said all periods in this century had their shortcomings.</p>
<p>&quot;There just wasn't a time when everything was dandy,&quot; he said. &quot;Even under the tsar there were pogroms.&quot;</p>
<p>ENDURING MEMORIES OF THE 20TH CENTURY</p>
<p>Yefimov is able to speak with authority about the past because his memory for detail is remarkable. He has an ability to give exact addresses, dates, and names that date back to the beginning of the century.</p>
<p>He remembers reading the newspaper in 1914 when World War One began, watching Lenin speak in Moscow -- on November 20, 1922 he says decisively -- and seeing Hitler in Berlin.</p>
<p>&quot;I did once see Hitler in 1933. I saw him walking on Wilhemstrasse where the presidential palace was, as he was leaving a reception for President Hindenburg,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Past excitement comes back to life as he recalls the first times he saw a car, an electric lamp and the telephone.</p>
<p>&quot;I remember it as if it was today the first time I saw an automobile,&quot; he said with a laugh. &quot;I was shocked to see a carriage move without a horse. It was an incredible spectacle. Your eyes are used to seeing a horse in front and then all of sudden there was no horse! How did it move?&quot;</p>
<p>Yefimov cannot explain the secret of his longevity, but he takes a certain pride in the achievement.</p>
<p>&quot;It comes from nature probably. I don't do anything special. I don't refuse myself anything. I eat and drink a lot of whatever I want,&quot; he said. &quot;I frequently meet friends at the table and drink vodka and cognac and beer, and eat everything. I don't follow any diet.</p>
<p>&quot;As far as women, well there's nothing you can do about it, nature has blocked that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>His wife of 65 years died in 1985.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course, it's already too long. As you know the average age of death for men in our country is 58,&quot; he said. &quot;I'm already nearly 40 years above the statistical norm.&quot;</p>
<p>He devotes 40 minutes every morning to exercise, including 250 sit-ups, and walks about freely but slowly on his own.</p>
<p>As he explained his daily routine, the phone rang. &quot;That's my great grandchild,&quot; he said, adding that she has a 10-year old daughter -- one of his two great-great grandchildren.</p>
<p>Worsening vision has made it hard for Yefimov to draw political cartoons anymore, but he still paints. He is also writing his memoirs and contributing to a book celebrating Moscow's 850 anniversary, batting away on a old manual typewriter, itself a relic from an earlier era.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
