<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="619898" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: FEATURE - Pope visits Poland torn by rows over religion.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Pope visits Poland torn by rows over religion.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul II, who begins an 11-day pilgrimage to his native Poland on Saturday, lands in the midst of a domestic political battle centred in large part on the role of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
<p>The trip falls during campaigning for a general election due later this year when rightist opposition parties led by the pro-Catholic Solidarity trade union hope to supplant the secular-minded ex-communists now in government.</p>
<p>The Polish Episcopate's General Secretary, Bishop Tadeusz Pieronek, said last month: &quot;The Holy Father will not involve himself in our political debate.&quot;</p>
<p>That is more easily said than done. For Solidarity Election Action (AWS) -- an alliance of some 30 small right-wing parties clustered around the Solidarity union -- the Pope's May 31-June 10 visit is a gift from heaven which may translate into votes at the ballot box.</p>
<p>RIGHT EXPECTS BOOST FROM PAPAL VISIT</p>
<p>The rightist alliance has already printed large numbers of posters of the Pope, prominently stamped with its own logo.</p>
<p>The Pontiff, formerly Cardinal Karol Wojtyla, supported Solidarity during its struggle which led to the 1989 fall of communism and does not hide his sympathy for its traditions.</p>
<p>Solidarity identifies with Church interests. AWS demands that parliament ratify a concordat treaty with the Vatican, signed by a former government in 1993 to regulate the Church's status in Poland, but since delayed by leftists in parliament.</p>
<p>It also campaigns on a pledge to ban abortion, reversing a liberalisation of the law passed last year in a debate which divided Poles into roughly equal camps.</p>
<p>On this issue the Pope, who views abortion as killing, cannot keep silent even if his words help the political right.</p>
<p>&quot;A nation which kills its own children is a nation without a future,&quot; he said last year after learning with distress that Poland was easing abortion on social grounds such as poverty.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not the Pope's fault that in touching on such matters -- and I think he will refer to it -- he touches on politics. It is the fault of politicians who have politicised such ethical subjects,&quot; Pieronek said.</p>
<p>POLES SPLIT OVER ROLE OF CHURCH, RELIGION</p>
<p>The Church enjoyed great prestige before 1989 among Poles, 90 percent of whom are at least formally Catholics, because of its defence of human rights under communist rule.</p>
<p>But when pro-Catholic parties won power in democratic Poland, their moves to restore property and grant privileges to the Church aroused resentment, which was skillfully nurtured by the ex-communists to help their election victory in 1993.</p>
<p>Controversy on religious issues is intense now due to heated campaigning over a new constitution which Poles approved by about 53 percent to 47 percent in a referendum last Sunday.</p>
<p>The constitution, backed by the ruling coalition and two parliamentary opposition parties, leaves open the abortion issue and aims to include believers and non-believers alike.</p>
<p>Solidarity sought a &quot;no&quot; vote, proposing an alternative version clearly invoking God and effectively banning abortion.</p>
<p>Some Solidarity leaders asked bishops to seek God's help in defeating the constitution with a rare religious ceremony last performed when Bolshevik troops invaded Poland in 1920.</p>
<p>The bishops refused, saying God should not be asked to make political choices, but then strayed from neutrality and said the Church had clear moral reservations over the constitution.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the latest defeat of the Catholic bishops who still cannot find a place for the Church in a democratic State,&quot; commented an ex-communist leader, Jerzy Szmajdzinski.</p>
<p>At the same time, progress towards clinching the concordat was again stalled this month by leftist deputies disputing details of bills that would pave the way for its ratification -- notably one allowing religious education in kindergartens.</p>
<p>These delays have undermined hopes the concordat would be approved by parliament during the Pope's visit.</p>
<p>POPE COULD HELP HEAL RIFTS</p>
<p>Leading centrist opposition figure Tadeusz Mazowiecki, a Catholic who helped to draft the new constitution and was pained by the Church's intervention, said the Pope's visit may serve to soothe divisions stirred up over religious issues.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the Pope's visit will calm this atmosphere and pour oil on these troubled waters,&quot; Mazowiecki told Reuters.</p>
<p>Certainly, various key figures in Polish public life say they want an end to the use of religion in political rows.</p>
<p>Bishop Pieronek has argued that the Church should be apolitical and seek some co-existence with the ex-communists, who are now social democrats and may be in power for some time.</p>
<p>Ex-communist leaders including President Aleksander Kwasniewski say they wish to end feuds over the Church.</p>
<p>Kwasniewski, who visited the Pope in the Vatican earlier this year, said this month he hoped the Pontiff would bring the the same message he recently brought to Lebanon and Sarajevo.</p>
<p>&quot;We need help in eliminating what could still be an obstacle or threat to us...the problem of understanding and unity between Poles on the most important matters,&quot; Kwasniewski told Wprost weekly in an interview.</p>
<p>On the right, in and outside Solidarity, there are voices calling for stress to be laid on other issues in campaigning.</p>
<p>RADICALS KEEP DIVISIONS ALIVE</p>
<p>But all sides include radicals eager to keep the pot boiling for ideological or tactical reasons.</p>
<p>The ex-communist Democratic Left Alliance (SLD) has an anti-clericalist faction including several deputies linked with Poland's best-selling weekly magazine NIE (No), which carries vitriolic attacks on the Church and priests in each issue.</p>
<p>The Polish Church is hostage to Radio Maryja, a station run by an independent-minded priest whose audience of millions allows him to keep broadcasting a mixture of comforting prayer and strident ultra-nationalist, left-bashing commentary.</p>
<p>Numbers of individual bishops and prominent priests eagerly pronounce on political matters from the pulpit.</p>
<p>Despite concern over Radio Maryja's content, Pieronek says the Church cannot control it. The bishop himself has been attacked by rightist theologians for his liberalism.</p>
<p>For Poles, the Pope is perceived as above political rows, says Lena Kolarska-Bobinska, a sociologist and head of the Public Affairs Institute think-tank.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pope is seen as an authority, not involved in political machinations, unlike the Polish Church,&quot; she said, adding that what he said might affect the political climate.</p>
<p>&quot;If he speaks a lot on abortion he might strengthen these divisions, unless he speaks above the differences,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
