<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="619851" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Albanian couple on trial engage to marry.</title>
<headline>Albanian couple on trial engage to marry.</headline>
<byline>Jovan Kovacic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>An ethnic Albanian couple, on trial together with 20 others for alleged terrorism, announced their engagement on Wednesday in a courtroom in Pristina, capital of Serbia's troubled province of Kosovo, witnesses said.</p>
<p>&quot;I want to use this opportunity, since I have no other, to inform relatives and friends that Avni Klinaku and I are engaged to be married,&quot; Shurkiya Rexha said from the dock to an applause from the packed courtroom.</p>
<p>They, like all the others, have been indicted for alleged involvement in hostile activities and affiliation with a clandestine organisation, the National Movement for the Liberation of Kosovo. Klinaku is the prime defendent.</p>
<p>The indictments allege the defendants wanted to use force to make Kosovo secede from Serbia. The defence denies the charges.</p>
<p>Defence lawyers argued there was no real evidence against the defendants except for confessions during the investigation process which it claims were obtained under duress and torture.</p>
<p>The verdict is expected on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;You have the power to take the first step to reconcile our people,&quot; the defence told the judge on Tuesday, referring to the deep animosity between the Serbs and ethnic Albanians in the volatile province.</p>
<p>Kosovo, where ethnic Albanians outnumber Serbs nine to one, is widely regarded as a political powder keg which, if ignited, could wreck international peace efforts in the Balkans.</p>
<p>Some 30 people, both Serbs and Albanians, have been killed over the past year in guerrilla violence.</p>
<p>Serbian police cracked down on the province in January arresting some 70 people in a widely-pubicised sweep following the guerrilla attacks.</p>
<p>The Democratic League of Kosovo (LDK), the biggest ethnic Albanian party in Kosovo which advocates peaceful resistance to Serb rule, says up to 55 people are still in Serb custody and alleges some have been tortured.</p>
<p>In March, Serbian authorities indicted 15 ethnic Albanians on charges of terrorism, killing three policemen and one Serb civilian, and attempting to murder 16 other people. That group has yet to go on trial.</p>
<p>Serbia revoked Kosovo's autonomy in 1989, claiming its Albanian population wanted to secede and join neighbouring Albania.</p>
<p>Serbia's President Slobodan Milosevic is under pressure to restore human rights in the province if he wants a Washington-imposed outer wall of sanctions lifted.</p>
<p>The Albanians, led by Ibrahim Rugova, head of the LDK, have boycotted Serbian institutions since but they have also been warned by the United States that secession was not an option.</p>
<p>Albanian parties deny the existence of guerrilla groups and say those arrested are victims of Serb persecution.</p>
<p>But American intelligence officials believe an ethnic Albanian group -- the Kosovo Liberation Army, a shadowy group about which little is known -- has staged at least five armed attacks in the last year.</p>
<p>It has threatened severe reprisals against the Serbs and Albanians who cooperated with the Serbs and those financing the LDK, demanding money for its own cause.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
