<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620115" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Sound of ancient chime will ring HK historic change.</title>
<headline>Sound of ancient chime will ring HK historic change.</headline>
<byline>Dominic Lau</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sixty-five bronze bells will ring out an historic change here with chimes heard in China 2,400 years ago -- and the world will have a chance to buy the CD record.</p>
<p>Their unique sound, from gentle shimmer to solemn boom, will signal China's July 1 recovery of Hong Kong colony from Britain.</p>
<p>The bells, weighing a total of five tonnes, are an exact replica in appearance and tone of priceless musicaL relics recovered from a nobleman's tomb of the Warring States dynastic era.</p>
<p>They are part of a new symphony, with acclaimed cellist Yo Yo Ma as soloist, and a local children's choir, to mark the first day of Chinese rule.</p>
<p>Commissioned for the event, the work will be played for the first time during a multi-million dollar extravaganza of fireworks, lasers, an illuminated barge flotilla and giant balloons after the transfer of power.</p>
<p>Hong Kong, a British colony for 156 years, reverts to Chinese rule at midnight on June 30, just 34 days away.</p>
<p>The score, titled &quot;Symphony 1997 -- Heaven, Earth, Mankind&quot;, is by Chinese composer Tan Dun, a New York resident.</p>
<p>&quot;We want a symphony that can leave a memory to our future generations of the day of July 1,&quot; said a spokesman for a pro-China committee organising the handover ceremony.</p>
<p>Raymond Wu, of the Association for Celebration of Reunification of Hong Kong with China, told a news conference on Wednesday that he would like the symphony to be recognised by everyone around the world.</p>
<p>The last of three movements incorporates a &quot;lullaby&quot; theme in which a parent's song to a child symbolises China's love for Hong Kong which Britain seized from the old Manchu empire.</p>
<p>Sony Classical, a unit of Japan's Sony Corp, will release a recording worldwide on July 5, the same day the 55-minute work will be performed in Beijing, the record company general manager Sonya Ho-Asjoe said.</p>
<p>It will also be played in a concert in Hong Kong on July 4.</p>
<p>A replica of the bianzhang-chime bells, unearthed from an aristocrat's tomb in central China in 1978, will be flown in from China.</p>
<p>Wu said the original 65 bells, which require five people to play, were too precious to &quot;move around and play around with&quot;.</p>
<p>Tan, 40, who was born in China, was the youngest composer ever to win the prestige Suntory Prize Commission in 1993, while Ma, 42, is a ten-time Grammy award winner.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
