<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620161" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Singapore schools expel virtual pets - sources say.</title>
<headline>Singapore schools expel virtual pets - sources say.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Most Singapore schools have banned Tamagotch computer pets from classrooms to keep students focused on their studies rather than the virtual reality toys, education sources said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Schools do ban them and I think all schools have,&quot; a source close the the Ministry of Education told Reuters.</p>
<p>The ministry declined immediate comment, but the sources said it had not issued an edict that the Tamagotch -- &quot;loveable egg&quot; in Japanese -- be officially excluded from school.</p>
<p>&quot;As a general rule, principals have the power to decide,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>The craze for the egg-shaped virtual reality toy has swept the world since its launch in Japan in early 1996 and has led Taiwan and Hong Kong to ban them in schools.</p>
<p>The Tamagotch demands too much attention, the Singapore sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;Students spend more time on them than their studies,&quot; said one educationalist who declined to be identified.</p>
<p>The Tamagotch requires constant care as it is a toy which &quot;evolves&quot;. Owners must entertain, educate and feed the Tamagotch as frequently as every hour or risk the toy throwing a tantrum, developing mood swings, or dying in extreme cases of neglect.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
