<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620229" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Wake-up call to Iran clergy - &quot;We want change&quot;.</title>
<headline>Wake-up call to Iran clergy - &quot;We want change&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Barry May</byline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iran's Islamic revolution crossed a watershed with the election of an intellectual Shi'ite Moslem clergyman as its next president after years on the political sidelines, analysts said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>They said Mohammad Khatami's surprise victory by a landslide was a seismic shift unparalleled since the overthrow of the U.S.-backed shah in 1979.</p>
<p>He now has a huge mandate to make the clergy-dominated government more tolerant and improve an economy that is ailing in spite of Iran's vast petrodollar income as the world's third largest oil exporter after Saudi Arabia and Norway.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a loud wake-up call to the ruling clergy,&quot; one Tehran-based analyst said.</p>
<p>&quot;The message from the people is: we want change and we want it now. Voters are saying we want more freedom, though still within the Islamic system which was not challenged in the election, and a less rigid stance in relations with the West. These things are perfectly in tune with Khatami's own ideas.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Khatami needs to mobilise all the resources he can to improve the lives of the people,&quot; another analyst said. &quot;They have been hit hard by inflation, lack of job opportunities and ever-increasing corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;Foreign debt is under control but he will have to muster the courage to divert some of the funds spent on activities abroad to boost economic development at home.&quot;</p>
<p>Khatami was backed by a coalition that included a broad spectrum ranging from Islamist leftists opposed to privatisation and deregulation to the centrists behind outgoing President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani who want a free-market economy.</p>
<p>Reformist technocrats seeking better ties with the West, women wanting more opporunities and rights and large numbers of young people also rallied to his flag.</p>
<p>Strangest of all, his supporters included former leaders of the militant students who organised the seizure of the U.S. embassy in 1979 and held 52 Americans hostage for 444 days.</p>
<p>Relations between Tehran and Washington have been hostile ever since, with the United States frequently accusing Iran of being behind acts of international &quot;terrorism&quot; and seeking to acquire weapons of mass destruction. Iran denies both charges.</p>
<p>Khatami has a sound revolutionary past, having been close to the leader of the movement against the shah, the late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini.</p>
<p>But he fell foul of Majlis right-wingers and bazaar merchants who considered him too liberal when he was culture minister for most of the 1980s and he was forced to resign.</p>
<p>Although public celebrations of Khatami's victory have been subdued, voters' expectations of him are high and he is likely to face enormous difficulties in meeting them, analysts say.</p>
<p>&quot;I expect a head-on clash with ultra-conservatives,&quot; said one veteran Iranian analyst.</p>
<p>The powers of the president are limited and subordinate to supreme leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei who makes policy. There are no mechanisms for his word to be questioned.</p>
<p>Governance in Iran has two parallel structures: the executive, legislature and judiciary, and an unofficial one controlled by Khamenei who tacitly supported Khatami's main rival for the presidency, Majlis Speaker Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri. Khamenei has since the polls urged all Iranians to back Khatami.</p>
<p>The unofficial structure includes the Revolutionary Guards and paramilitary Basij volunteers, revolutionary courts, the supreme leader's provincial representatives, Friday prayer leaders and boniyad religious foundations that are reckoned to control up to 40 percent of the economy.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri was the establishment's candidate but he was comprehensively defeated by a challenger who had lingered out of the political limelight for the last five years and whose name was known to few beyond the intelligentsia and government officials as little as a month ago.</p>
<p>&quot;With Nateq-Nouri I thought I could sleep more easily,&quot; the Iranian analyst told Reuters. &quot;But then gradually I came to understand that this was a very special occasion in our history, and I voted for Khatami.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody thought this is a rare, historic opportunity. He doesn't seem to be a despot at all, which is what we're accustomed to. He doesn't seem to owe anything to anybody.&quot;</p>
<p>The future of key players like Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati under the new regime is uncertain.</p>
<p>International diplomats in Tehran expect Velayati, the acceptable face of the revolution in foreign capitals over the last 17 years, to fall. Tipped to become vice-president had Nateq-Nouri won, he endorsed the speaker a mere five days before the ballot, a misjudgment which could cost him his job.</p>
<p>If Velayati goes, diplomats expect his replacement to be Mohammad Hashemi, a brother of Rafsanjani.</p>
<p>Revolutionary Iran could also see its first woman in the cabinet, possibly Rafsanjani's daughter Faezeh Hashemi, a Majlis deputy and the most prominent woman in Iranian politics.</p>
<p>Nateq-Nouri himself is wounded. Just how badly will be determined on Sunday when he faces the annual election by all 270 members of the Majlis for the speakership.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
