<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620261" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Music videos face glut, record companies cut back.</title>
<headline>Music videos face glut, record companies cut back.</headline>
<byline>Sue Zeidler</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
<text>
<p>Video killed the radio star in the 1980s, but it seems the reverse is true in the 1990s.</p>
<p>The $40 billion record industry is cutting back on videos, which are in oversupply, as sales and radio airplay determine the few select videos that get broadcast.</p>
<p>&quot;There was a gold rush for videos, but then record labels tried to outsmart each other by spending more money and going after certain directors,&quot; said Billy Poveda, president of the Music Video Production Association.</p>
<p>&quot;Now, a lot of the videos don't get seen on the scale that record companies want them to be seen,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Music videos have evolved into something akin to short films. They can cost from $50,000 to several million, representing a huge chunk of marketing budgets for an album. While over half the videos never air, more videos than ever are being made because they are seen as a barometer of a label's belief in an act.</p>
<p>&quot;When a new act is signed, pressure is applied to make a video even if there's no audience for it. But with such a low rate of success, videos are an area where labels will have to start assessing costs,&quot; said one record executive. &quot;I think the answer will be to make fewer but better videos.&quot;</p>
<p>Several analysts note the music video woes mirror a slump in the overall record industry, which faces slowing sales growth.</p>
<p>&quot;We're very cacluated about it and there are times we decide not to make a video, particularly with new bands,&quot; said Emily Wittman, vice president of video promotion for A&amp;M records, a label owned by Polygram NV.</p>
<p>But that strategy has pros and cons, too. For instance, Wittman said A&amp;M is now rushing a video for a pop band called &quot;3rd Party&quot;, which debuted this month with a single &quot;Can U Feel It?&quot; that is already climbing the charts.</p>
<p>&quot;We're rushing to get a video shot because the song is moving faster than anticipated,&quot; she said. &quot;It's a good problem to have.&quot;</p>
<p>Employees at the big six labels, including Time Warner Inc., EMI Group, Seagram Co Ltd's Universal, Bertelsmann AG, Sony Corp. and Polygram, say the current video glut is due, in part, to a shift at Viacom Inc.'s MTV channel away from all-music programming.</p>
<p>While a video depicting a hit single or a new song by a big star makes its way to MTV, labels wind up sending many videos on new artists to retail stores, radio stations and regional cable channels in hopes of exposing these acts.</p>
<p>But nothing has had the same broad national impact as MTV when it was a 24-hour music channel, causing an explosion in the video business, industry sources said.</p>
<p>Yet a survey in March by the Recording Industry Association of America and the National Association of Recording Merchandisers found MTV no longer influences music consumers.</p>
<p>Shortly after the survey was released, MTV said it would boost its music videos by 10 to 20 hours a week. But industry sources say MTV just raised airtime for a select few.</p>
<p>&quot;MTV is playing fewer and fewer acts and only increasing hours for the big hits,&quot; said one executive. &quot;The odds of getting a video on MTV has steadily decreased. To count on MTV to expose a new artist is dopey.&quot;</p>
<p>MTV denies the charges. &quot;Out of nowhere, MTV can push the button to ignite sales and sell records,&quot; said Andy Schuon, vice president of programming for MTV.</p>
<p>&quot;That being said, there are more record companies now than when we started in 1981. More videos are being made and there are more people to say 'no' to,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The increased frustration is from the increased amount of supply, not the fact that MTV has cut back,&quot; Schoen said.</p>
<p>Schoen said music represents up to 80 percent of MTV's daily programming but also noted, &quot;the current MTV audience doesn't know an MTV that is not a combination of music and shows, like the 'Real World' and 'Beavis and Butthead.'&quot;</p>
<p>He said these shows have helped the industry by exposing viewers who are not passionate about music to the latest bands.</p>
<p>Poveda, of the video production association, cited cable channels like M2, MTV's all-music sister channel, The Box, an interactive video jukebox, and VH1 as vehicles for exposure.</p>
<p>&quot;These niche markets are valuable to lots of bands,&quot; he said. Digital video discs, a new video format on discs the size and shape of compact discs, will boost the industry.</p>
<p>&quot;The advent of DVD will keep the industry viable and spark a resurgence because consumers will expect to have visuals everytime they hear music,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Live concerts are also staging a comeback. &quot;MTV, in its success, killed the longform concert video industry, but people are trying to resurrect it again,&quot; Poveda said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34520">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
