<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620284" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Texas woman completes Earhart's global flight.</title>
<headline>Texas woman completes Earhart's global flight.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Croft</byline>
<dateline>OAKLAND, Calif. 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Texas woman touched down in California in her 1930s vintage plane on Wednesday, completing the around-the-world flight that legendary aviator Amelia Earhart attempted 60 years ago but never finished.</p>
<p>Linda Finch was greeted by hundreds of cheering wellwishers as her glistening 1935 Lockheed Electra 10E landed at Oakland airport, from where she set out on March 17.</p>
<p>Finch, a 46-year-old businesswoman from San Antonio, took about 15 hours to fly the 2,400 mile (3,840 km) last leg from Honolulu, the longest and most challenging of the entire 28,500 mile (45,600 km) journey because of the heavy fuel load the plane carried.</p>
<p>She smiled and waved to the crowd as she got out of the cockpit of the silver and orange plane and hugged her 2-year-old adopted daughter Katie and 2-year-old grandson Ryan. Her mother and grandmother were also there to greet her.</p>
<p>&quot;It's wonderful to have made it,&quot; Finch told reporters after being welcomed by dignitaries and being presented with bouquets and garlands. &quot;It was just great to be here and to know that it was done.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody keeps looking for a scary part and some drama. It just wasn't. It was a very delightful flight, the airplane was great,&quot; she said. &quot;The lowest point probably was just missing home and missing the kids. That was very hard, especially around the half-way point.&quot;</p>
<p>Soon after landing, Finch received a congratulatory telephone call from U.S. Vice President Al Gore, who told her; &quot;Your achievement is an inspiration to children across America... The whole country is proud of you.&quot;</p>
<p>Earhart set out from Oakland airport in 1937, attempting to fly around the world near the equator, but the flight ended in tragedy when Earhart and navigator Fred Noonan disappeared on July 2, 1937, near Howland Island in the Pacific Ocean. No trace of the plane was found despite a long search.</p>
<p>Finch set out to recreate and complete Earhart's flight, taking a similar route with a few detours. She flew a carefully restored Electra 10E, the same model Earhart used and one of only two in existence. But she did have the benefits of modern navigation equipment.</p>
<p>Finch's journey, called &quot;World Flight 1997,&quot; took her to five continents and included more than 30 stops in 18 countries including Brazil, Senegal, Greece, Egypt, Pakistan, India, Thailand, Indonesia, Australia and New Guinea.</p>
<p>The $4.5 million project marked the centenary of the birth of Earhart, who became a household name with her daring aviation feats, including becoming the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean in 1932.</p>
<p>Finch said one aim of her trip was to remind people of Earhart's life and values and to show that people could overcome the limitations they set on themselves. Finch flew over Howland Island to drop three wreaths in Earhart's memory.</p>
<p>Finch is not the first to recreate Earhart's flight. American pilot Ann Pellegreno flew around the world in 1967 using a slightly different model aircraft, an Electra 10A, said Ronald Reuther, executive director of the Western Aerospace Museum in Oakland.</p>
<p>Reuther said he admired all three women -- Earhart, Pellegreno and Finch. &quot;It was just as difficult for all three of them from the flying standpoint,&quot; he said, although he said Finch enjoyed the advantage of modern telecommunications.</p>
<p>&quot;Finch's achievement is spectacular. She's done it in style,&quot; he said, adding that what distinguished Finch's flight was the strong educational component.</p>
<p>Sponsors Pratt &amp; Whitney, the engine maker and a subsidiary of United Technologies Corp., distributed a free multi-media educational programme to schools throughout the United States. It was designed to teach students about Earhart and to use the journey to spur their interest in science, mathematics, languages and geography.</p>
<p>Students were encouraged to follow Finch's progress on the Internet (http://www.worldflight.org), where they could read Finch's pilot log messages and send her e-mail. In the log, Finch told of her delight in meeting with children along the way, in finding out about local customs and in visiting famous sites such as the temples of Egypt.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OAKLAND, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
