<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620233" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MOROCCO: Moroccan Islamists to take part in elections.</title>
<headline>Moroccan Islamists to take part in elections.</headline>
<dateline>RABAT 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Moroccan Islamist leader said in remarks published on Wednesday that members of his group, which is tolerated but not legally registered, would stand as candidates in elections this year.</p>
<p>Abdelilah Benkiran, 44, one of the leading figures in the fundamentalist Tawhid Wal Islah (Unity and Reform) movement, said members would stand as independents in local council elections due in June and in later general elections.</p>
<p>His movement had adhered to the Mouvement Populaire Democratique et Constitutionnel (MPDC) party last year but the MPDC decided to withdraw from elections, preventing Benkiran's group from taking part under its banner.</p>
<p>The movement, previously called al-Asliah Wa Tajdid (Reform and Renewal), has been tolerated by authorities since 1980 when Benkiran's group broke with the radical outlawed Ashabiba al-Islamya (lslamic Youth) led by Abdelkrim Mouti, who lives in exile.</p>
<p>Sheikh Abdsalam Yassine, 69, leader of another Islamist group al-Adl-wal-Ihsane (Justice and Charity), has been under house arrest since 1989.</p>
<p>&quot;We differ with al-Adl-wal-Ihsane because we think that we all share responsibility for the country, the state, the society as well as parties without rejecting those responsible for the current situation,&quot; Benkiran said in an interview with the Casablanca-based La Gazette du Maroc weekly paper.</p>
<p>Answering a question on Algeria, he blamed the situation there on the military government that came to power after independence in 1962 which he said prevented civilians from expressing themselves.</p>
<p>Morocco has an estimated 30 legal Moslem groups, including charity and culture associations. Benkiran's movement is one of the most active, mainly in universities and trade unions. Political parties along religious lines are banned in Morocco.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RABAT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MOROCCO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
