<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620517" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Leona Helmsley makes $1 million donation.</title>
<headline>Leona Helmsley makes $1 million donation.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Real estate heiress Leona Helmsley, once dubbed the &quot;Queen of Mean,&quot; announced Wednesday she was contributing $1 million to the Burned Churches Fund.</p>
<p>In her first public appearance since the January funeral of her husband, renowned dealmaker Harry Helmsley, she pledged her gift at Manhattan's Cathedral of St. John the Divine.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a good cause, it's a good cause,&quot; she said of the group, which was set up in response to a series of church burnings around the country. &quot;People that have had their house burned down, it's a terrible thing. But this (church burning) is even deeper than their own, personal place.&quot;</p>
<p>Helmsley served 18 months in prison in the late 1980's after she was convicted of mail fraud and tax evasion, charges that elicited her most famous quote: &quot;Only the little people pay taxes.&quot; New York's tabloid newspapers quickly christened her &quot;the Queen of Mean.&quot;</p>
<p>The 77-year-old Helmsley has inherited her late husband's real estate empire including commercial space, 100,000 apartments and 5,000 hotel rooms nationwide. Forbes magazine estimated the net worth of Helmsley's holdings, which include New York's fabled Empire State Building, at $1.7 billion.</p>
<p>The Burned Churches Fund was established last May by the National Council of Churches (NCC), an umbrella group of 33 Protestant and Orthodox denominations, after a wave of suspected arsons gutted about 40 churches.</p>
<p>There have been almost 300 suspicious fires to date, said the Rev. Joan Brown Campbell, NCC's general secretary, mostly targeting black churches in the South. She said there have already been 15 burnings in 1997.</p>
<p>Helmsley's gift of $1 million, along with her pledge of an additional $500,000 to match the fund-raising efforts of the charity, constitutes the largest cash donation to the fund, which has raised $7.5 million to date.</p>
<p>The money will be used to organise a conference in Washington for the pastors of burned churches as well as to directly fund the rebuilding of 30 churches.</p>
<p>Helmsley got involved in the cause after meeting Luther Gatling, president of New York's 100 Black Men organisation, at a memorial service for her husband, who died of pneumonia at the age of 87.</p>
<p>&quot;She speaks of him as if he's still alive,&quot; Gatling said, &quot;and he is because now he's breathing hope into these churches.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
