<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620530" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Susan Molinari quits politics to join CBS News.</title>
<headline>Susan Molinari quits politics to join CBS News.</headline>
<byline>Arthur Spiegelman</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Susan Molinari, the leading Republican woman in the House of Representatives, announced on Wednesday she was quitting politics to have her own TV show.</p>
<p>Molinari, once one of the fastest-rising stars in the Republican Party, told a packed news conference the offer to be co-anchor on a new two-hour CBS Saturday morning news show was just too good to pass up, although she added she would &quot;never say never&quot; about a possible return to politics.</p>
<p>With her father, former Republican Rep. Guy Molinari, in the wings saying his daughter always wanted to be on TV, she told reporters, &quot;This is where I want to be for my future.&quot;</p>
<p>She said she saw the two-hour &quot;CBS News Saturday Morning&quot; show as &quot;60 Minutes meets Rosie O'Donnell,&quot; a reference to two of television's top shows, one a hard-hitting investigative program and the other a variety and celebrity interview show.</p>
<p>Both are hits and CBS News president Andrew Heyward was clearly hoping his reaching out for a popular political figure would translate into instant success when the shows airs on Sept. 13 in direct competition with NBC's Saturday &quot;Today&quot; show.</p>
<p>Journalists at the news conference bombarded Heyward with questions about whether he had crossed a line between politics and impartial journalism by picking Molinari. The first questioner asked, &quot;How can you make Susan Molinari an anchor when she's an absolute amateur?&quot;</p>
<p>Molinari cut in, saying, &quot;Hey, hey, hey,&quot; and Heyward answered by saying, &quot;We are creating a whole new program. ... It is wrong to be bound by the traditional.&quot;</p>
<p>Actually political figures have long made the transition into broadcast journalism, although usually as commentators. Former Bush White House Chief of Staff John Sununu broadcasts for CNN and former Clinton aide George Stephanopoulos is a commentator for ABC.</p>
<p>Molinari, 39, was hand-picked by Republican presidential candidate Bob Dole to be the keynote speaker at the party's convention in San Diego last summer.</p>
<p>Representing the same Staten Island, New York, district that her father did for many years in Congress, Molinari is the sixth ranking Republican in the House and is married to a Republican congressman, Bill Paxon, who many party figures say could be a future Speaker of the House.</p>
<p>Heyward, whose network has been frequently criticized by conservatives as being a bastion of liberalism, said politics had nothing to do with the move. &quot;This is not a political appointment,&quot; he said as both he and Molinari vowed that she would not be a commentator offering politcal views.</p>
<p>&quot;I might even do some cooking on the show,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;She brings the experience of knowing the inner workings of Washington,&quot; Heyward said, adding they would be cautious in identifying areas of possible conflicts of interest.</p>
<p>He said hiring Molinari was an idea he had when he met her at the Republican convention last July and he pursued the idea when he went to Washington in January for President Clinton's second inauguration.</p>
<p>Several Republicans hailed the move and wished her well, while Democrats said the Republicans were losing a woman who would have made a formidable candidate for higher office.</p>
<p>House Speaker Newt Gingrich said, &quot;It is a great loss to the House Republicans. She's one of our most creative and dynamic leaders. But she is a tremendously creative person and I think she will be great at CBS.</p>
<p>House Republican Conference Chairman John Boehner said: &quot;CBS is gaining one of the brightest people our party has to offer and the Republican Party will miss her for her talents as a forceful, articulate spokesperson.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C411">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
