<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="620571" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Actor Tim Allen faces Michigan drunk driving charge.</title>
<headline>Actor Tim Allen faces Michigan drunk driving charge.</headline>
<dateline>BLOOMFIELD TOWNSHIP, Mich. 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A not guilty plea was entered on behalf of actor Tim Allen during a court proceeding Wednesday on a drunk driving charge after a Memorial Day weekend arrest, a court spokesman said.</p>
<p>Allen, star of the popular television sitcom &quot;Home Improvement&quot; and of several movies, did not appear in Bloomfield Township's 48th District Court. The 43-year-old Michigan native was arrested in suburban Detroit Saturday night after he was caught going 70 miles-per-hour in a 40 mph zone in his 1988 Ferrari.</p>
<p>Police said Allen also failed a sobriety test. &quot;The sobriety tests were given that indicated ... there was a probability that drinking was involved with driving,&quot; Bloomfield Township Police Capt. James Anas said.</p>
<p>&quot;Due to the pending court action we cannot make any comment at this time,&quot; Michael Novak, Allen's attorney, told Reuters. Novak said Allen's plea was made by letter and Allen did not have to appear in court.</p>
<p>Allen, whose real name is Timothy Alan Dick, was scheduled to appear at a pre-trial conference June 25. He was held briefly and released after his attorney posted a $100 bond.</p>
<p>A first offence for drunk driving carries penalties that include community service, jail time, up to $500 in fines and a 30-day license suspension. Allen's publicist told local newspapers the actor was in Baltimore filming a movie.</p>
<p>Allen got his start as a comedian and became famous for a routine about men's fascination with power tools. He served 28 months in prison for selling cocaine in 1978.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BLOOMFIELD TOWNSHIP, Mich."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
