<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621130" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Sinking feeling as movie &quot;Titanic&quot; release delayed.</title>
<headline>Sinking feeling as movie &quot;Titanic&quot; release delayed.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Release of &quot;Titanic,&quot; the movie about the ill-fated liner, has been put back six months, fueling rumors it is struggling to avoid more financial and artistic icebergs.</p>
<p>Paramount Pictures announced on Tuesday that instead of its anticipated summer release, &quot;Titanic&quot; will open in theaters across the United States and Canada on Dec. 19</p>
<p>The film, starring Leonardo DiCaprio, Kate Winslet, Kathy Bates, David Warner and Bill Paxton, has been rumored for some time to be in trouble and some reports said the movie's budget had ballooned to around $200 million.</p>
<p>The trade magazine Variety quoted sources as saying the total cost could be $285 million, making &quot;Titanic&quot; the second most expensive movie of all time after &quot;Cleopatra&quot; which in 1963 cost the equivalent of $300 million in 1997 dollars.</p>
<p>A major factor in the delayed release could be that opening in the summer would put &quot;Titanic&quot; up against several other potential blockbusters, such as &quot;The Lost World:Jurassic Park,&quot; &quot;Speed 2&quot; and &quot;Batman and Robin.&quot;</p>
<p>However, in the announcement Tuesday, Robert Friedman, vice chairman of Paramount Pictures' Motion Picture Group made no mention of budget problems or shooting delays and problems.</p>
<p>&quot;'Titanic,' even in its unfinished state, is spectacular,&quot; Friedman said. &quot;The decision to push (back its release) was a difficult one which required us to compare the rising curve of compromises to the film against the descending curve of commercial gain in late summer,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;As both Paramount and Twentieth Century Fox believe strongly that the film can play well in any season, we elected to move out of an already crowded summer.&quot;</p>
<p>Writer and director James Cameron recently told Rolling Stone magazine he was working 16-17 hours a day on the computer special effects for the film.</p>
<p>In Tuesday's statement from Paramount he was quoted as saying: &quot;While my initial instinct was to stick with summer, as this project evolved I think we all became more and more confident that 'Titanic' did not necessarily need the hysteria of the summer season to be a box-office success.</p>
<p>&quot;Finishing this film is the culmination of a five year dream for me, and I greatly appreciate this tremendous vote of confidence from both Paramount and Fox.&quot;</p>
<p>The action movie set against the backdrop of the Titanic's ill-fated maiden voyage in 1912 is being distributed in the United States and Canada by Paramount which is owned by Viacom and internationally by Fox, which is owned by Rupert Murdoch's News Corp. Ltd..</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
