<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621367" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Molinari to co-anchor CBS news program - sources.</title>
<headline>Molinari to co-anchor CBS news program - sources.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Representative Susan Molinari of New York, one of the Republican Party's most visible politicians, will become a co-anchor on a new CBS Saturday morning news programme, broadcasting sources said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>CBS confirmed the appointment, but said no details would be available until a news conference on Wednesday morning at the network's headquarters in Manhattan.</p>
<p>CNN reported on Tuesday night that Molinari was expected to announce her resignation from Congress on Wednesday and would likely serve as congresswoman until Aug. 1.</p>
<p>The 39-year-old Molinari represents the New York City borough of Staten Island. She was not available for comment.</p>
<p>Molinari was the keynote speaker at the 1996 Republican National Convention in San Diego and is considered one of the party's leading women politicians.</p>
<p>She is married to Representative Bill Paxon, also a New York Republican. Her father, Guy Molinari, preceded her in Congress and is active in New York's Republican Party.</p>
<p>The two-hour CBS Saturday morning news programme, to be called &quot;CBS News Saturday Morning,&quot; is scheduled to begin airing in September, a CBS spokeswoman said. The co-anchor who will work with Molinari has not been announced.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
