<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621366" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Universal's &quot;Lost World&quot; smashes records.</title>
<headline>Universal's &quot;Lost World&quot; smashes records.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-05-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Steven Spielberg's dinosaur sequel, &quot;The Lost World: Jurassic Park,&quot; got off to a strong start last weekend, devouring every box office record in its path.</p>
<p>Universal Pictures, which distributed the film with Spielberg's Amblin Entertainment, said the action-adventure film took in nearly $93 million since last Thursday, easily surpassing last summer's record Memorial Day take of $56.8 million for &quot;Mission: Impossible.&quot;</p>
<p>The film, based on the novel by Michael Crichton and the sequel to Spielberg's 1993 film &quot;Jurassic Park,&quot; was shown at a record 3,281 theaters across the United States and Canada.</p>
<p>&quot;All of us at the studio are thrilled to be a part of history in the making,&quot; said Universal Pictures Chairman Casey Silver. &quot;Steven Spielberg and his outstanding creative team outdid themselves on 'The Lost World: Jurassic Park.' I also can't say enough about the efforts of Universal's marketing and distribution team in paving the way for this phenomenal opening.&quot;</p>
<p>The Variety trade paper quoted Spielberg as saying he was surprised by the film's performance.</p>
<p>&quot;I couldn't have dreamed it,&quot; he told the paper's gossip columnist, Army Archerd. &quot;When one of my pictures opens, I climb into a deep hole; I don't read reviews or take phone calls.&quot;</p>
<p>However, he seemed to rule out a third installment, telling Archerd: &quot;It would give me a tremendous Advil headache just to think about it.&quot;</p>
<p>In addition to the Memorial Day total, &quot;The Lost World&quot; established a new three-day opening record of $72.1 million, exceeding the previous mark of $52.8 million set by 1995's &quot;Batman Forever&quot; by nearly $20 million.</p>
<p>At that rate, the special-effects extravaganza, which cost about $80 million to make, nearly paid for itself in three days, leaving movie executives upbeat about the summer movie season.</p>
<p>Next weekend, &quot;The Lost World&quot; will be able to feast on moviegoers once again with little in the way of competition appearing on movie screens. However, the following weekend, Walt Disney Co. is expected to join the fray with &quot;Con Air&quot; an action film starring Oscar winner Nicolas Cage.</p>
<p>Universal is a unit of Seagram Co. Ltd.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
