<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621476" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French prosecutor urges two years jail for Tapie.</title>
<headline>French prosecutor urges two years jail for Tapie.</headline>
<dateline>MARSEILLE, France 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A public prosecutor urged a French court on Wednesday to jail bankrupt tycoon Bernard Tapie for two years, with another two years suspended, for embezzling funds from Marseille soccer club.</p>
<p>Prosecutor Evelyne Kitanoff also called for a two-million franc ($347,000) fine on the ex-cabinet minister, and a suspension of civic and family rights for five years.</p>
<p>She denounced the &quot;tyrannical methods&quot; of Tapie, saying that as far as he was concerned &quot;the end justifies the means, with no regard for the morality of sport&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The bad faith of the managers has been established. The image of the OM (team) and of Marseille has been tarnished by deplorable behaviour. The dream has been shattered for young people whose only passion is soccer,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Tapie, 54, is charged with embezzling 100 million francs ($17.5 million) when he was president of the Marseille club. He is standing trial in the Mediterranean port city while serving an earlier jail sentence for fixing a match.</p>
<p>The trial was repeatedly suspended after he spent 19 hours in a coronary intensive care unit last week after suffering chest pains and breathing difficulties.</p>
<p>Tapie went to prison nearly four months ago after the supreme court upheld an eight-month sentence for bribing players of league rival Valenciennes to give Marseille an easy game, days before Marseille beat AC Milan in the 1993 European Cup final.</p>
<p>Nineteen other soccer figures are standing trial along with Tapie in the case, which is expected to last another two weeks. He is charged with swindling, misusing corporate funds and falsifying documents between 1987 and 1993.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARSEILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
