<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621456" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: New rules on teen piercing advance in California.</title>
<headline>New rules on teen piercing advance in California.</headline>
<dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif. 1997-05-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>California teens wanting to have their ears, lips or tongues pierced would have to show they had mom or dad's permission under legislation passed by the state Assembly Tuesday.</p>
<p>On a 71-1 vote, the Assembly overwhelmingly approved a bill to force body piercers to get parental consent before they perform piercings on youths under the age of 18. Body piercers caught violating the rule could be fined $250.</p>
<p>The measure advanced to the Senate for review.</p>
<p>Body piercing is a growing fashion in California, especially among teenagers. Not only ear lobes, but lips, tongues, noses, abdomens, nipples and even genitals are pierced and rings or other devices inserted in the resulting holes.</p>
<p>&quot;Doctors need a parent's permission before they can touch a child and teachers need a parent's permission before they can give a child an aspirin,&quot; the bill's author, Republican Assemblyman George Runner, said in a statement. &quot;At the very least parents should be informed before a stranger pokes a hole in their child.&quot;</p>
<p>Runner said body piercing can lead to health problems for teens whose bodies are still developing.</p>
<p>Existing California law regulates tattoos for minors, but there is no law targeting body piercers.</p>
<p>Runner introduced the bill in response to a complaint from a woman whose teenage daughter had her bellybutton pierced without her knowledge after being dared to do so by friends.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SACRAMENTO, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
