<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621475" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Clinton rues precedent in Paula Jones ruling.</title>
<headline>Clinton rues precedent in Paula Jones ruling.</headline>
<byline>Gene Gibbons</byline>
<dateline>THE HAGUE 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton on Wednesday declined to comment on a U.S. Supreme Court decision to let a sexual harassment lawsuit against him go forward immediately, but he expressed concern about the precedent set by the ruling.</p>
<p>&quot;As regards my own case...I have really have nothing to add to what (lawyer Robert Bennett) said,&quot; the president told reporters. &quot;As to what might happen to future presidents, I am concerned about that, but there may not be anything to be done about that.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The Supreme Court has made its' decision,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>It was Clinton's first public comment on the Supreme Court's unanimous ruling on Tuesday that a sexual harrassment lawsuit brought against him by Paula Jones could go forward even while he was in office. He is now in the first year of his second four-year term.</p>
<p>The ruling cast a pall over his trip to Europe to sign a new agreement between the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation and Russia and to mark the 50th anniversary of the U.S. Marshall Plan for post-World War Two reconstruction in Europe.</p>
<p>The decision involved only the timing of the case, not the merits of Jones' allegations that Clinton made unwanted advances in 1991 when he was Arkansas governor and she was a state employee.</p>
<p>The court swept aside all legal obstacles Clinton's lawyers threw in Jones' path, rejecting arguments that allowing the lawsuit to go forward while he was in office would be a significant distraction, hinder his duties, and invite a deluge of frivolous cases from political opponents.</p>
<p>In a landmark ruling, all nine justices held for the first time that a lawsuit against a sitting president for conduct unrelated to official duties may proceed to trial. An Arkansas judge who is handling the case said on Tuesday she would decide on a trial date within two months.</p>
<p>Typically it would be set 10 to 12 months in advance.</p>
<p>Bennett, Clinton's private attorney, said he was &quot;a little surprised&quot; by the court's decision and he called the allegations &quot;malicious, baseless and politically inspired.&quot;</p>
<p>He declined to reveal his client's reaction, preferring to focus instead on on the president's trip.</p>
<p>&quot;The president is very happy and excited about events taking place abroad and that is the focal point of what he is thinking about, not this case,&quot; Bennett said in a CNN television interview.</p>
<p>Clinton, who paused to answer a reporter's question about the ruling while he was shaking hands on a streetcorner after a meeting with leaders of the European Union, said he would let his lawyer make all substantive comment on the case.</p>
<p>When asked if he was distracted during his trip by what at a minimum was a major embarrassment, Clinton tersely said over his shoulder, &quot;No.&quot;</p>
<p>Jones welcomed the court's decision, declaring that she was looking forward to her &quot;day in court&quot;.</p>
<p>Although Bennett was sceptical about an out-of-court settlement, another of Jones' lawyers set out what he called &quot;the bare minimum&quot; required to resolve the case.</p>
<p>&quot;Our mandate from Paula Jones is quite clear,&quot; Joseph Cammarata said in an interview on cable television's MSNBC.</p>
<p>&quot;She wants her good name and reputation restored. If there's some way to accomplish that through some statement the president may read or issue that says he remembers her, that she was in that room, that she did nothing wrong and that she is a good person, well that may be sufficient,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="THE HAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
