<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621451" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. pilot begins last leg of world flight.</title>
<headline>U.S. pilot begins last leg of world flight.</headline>
<dateline>HONOLULU, Hawaii 1997-05-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Texas woman who is aiming to complete the doomed flight of legendary aviator Amelia Earhart took off on Tuesday on the last leg of her journey around the world.</p>
<p>Linda Finch's restored 1935 Lockheed Electra 10E left Honolulu at about 3:15 p.m. local time (9:15 p.m. EDT) (0115 GMT on Wednesday) bound for Oakland, California, project spokeswoman Lynette Lo Tom said. The weather was clear and calm for the takeoff.</p>
<p>The last leg of the trip to Oakland, from where Finch set out on March 17, is the longest.</p>
<p>Finch is expected to take about 15 hours to cover the 2,400 mile (3,840 km) overnight flight across the Pacific Ocean. She is scheduled to arrive in Oakland about 9:30 a.m. PDT (12:30 p.m. EDT) (1630 GMT) on Wednesday where many well-wishers will be waiting to greet her.</p>
<p>Finch is attempting to recreate and complete Earhart's 1937 attempt to fly around the world, which ended in tragedy when her plane disappeared in the South Pacific.</p>
<p>Finch's plane, almost identical to Earhart's, will be strained by the heavy fuel load required for the long last leg of the flight. With just a two-hour margin on fuel, Finch said last week that she may have to turn back if the winds were too strong.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll be several tons over what the aircraft was designed for,&quot; Finch said. &quot;It will be a very critical takeoff and we'll have to do everything perfectly.&quot;</p>
<p>Finch's $4.5 million &quot;World Flight 1997&quot; project also commemorates the 100th anniversary of Earhart's birth.</p>
<p>Despite flying in the primitive plane, the 46-year-old Finch, a businesswoman and a grandmother, said her trip had been without major incident so far.</p>
<p>&quot;It is loud, small and somewhat uncomfortable, but there has really been no problem with it. The engines have run perfectly,&quot; she said last week. But she conceded her challenge was mild compared with the endeavours of the pioneering pilots of Earhart's day. One big difference is the modern navigation equipment installed in Finch's plane.</p>
<p>Finch's journey has taken her across the United States to Brazil, Africa, Europe, Egypt, India, Thailand and Singapore.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONOLULU, Hawaii"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
