<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="621526" id="root" date="1997-05-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Dalai Lama's Austrian tutor says was in Nazi party.</title>
<headline>Dalai Lama's Austrian tutor says was in Nazi party.</headline>
<byline>Julia Ferguson</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-05-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austrian mountaineer Heinrich Harrer, once tutor to the Dalai Lama and now subject of a Hollywood film starring heart-throb Brad Pitt, acknowledged on Wednesday that he was a member of Adolf Hitler's Nazi party.</p>
<p>Harrer, 84, the first to climb the north face of the Eiger, told Austrian state radio he was a member of the National Socialists and accepted an invitation to join the Nazi SS elite as a sports trainer.</p>
<p>Harrer was commenting on an 80-page file from the Berlin state archives, which was published in Thursday's German current affairs magazine Stern and which mentioned an &quot;SS-Oberscharfuehrer Heinrich Harrer&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I was enlisted in the Styrian SS as a sports teacher...I never actually filled in an application,&quot; he told the radio.</p>
<p>Pressed on whether he was a member of the SS, Harrer said: &quot;Yes, obviously I was in it.&quot;</p>
<p>An &quot;Oberscharfuehrer&quot; was an equivalent rank of sergeant and did not carry officer status.</p>
<p>Harrer was offered membership of the Nazi party after he attended a ceremony in 1938 in Breslau, now present-day Wroclaw in Poland, where he was congratulated by Austrian-born Adolf Hitler for his successful Eiger expedition before a cheering crowd of 30,000 people, Stern reported.</p>
<p>Stern published a photograph of Harrer with the Nazi dictator. Nazi Germany absorbed Austria into the Third Reich in March, 1938.</p>
<p>Speaking to Austrian news agency APA, Harrer said his SS membership was an unfortunate episode but added that he just had to &quot;grin and bear it&quot;.</p>
<p>I don't think I need to stress again that I have a clear conscience,&quot; he told APA from his home in Knappenberg in the southern Austrian province of Carinthia.</p>
<p>Harrer, whose best-seller biography will be portrayed in the Hollywood film &quot;Seven Years in Tibet&quot;, stressed he was only required to carry out sports duties for the SS and his career was curtailed by mountaineering expeditions.</p>
<p>He also denied eyewitness reports that he tried to plant a swastika flag on the Eiger's summit on his first ascent in 1938.</p>
<p>&quot;That's made up. There was a blizzard, we could hardly keep our eyes open. We were covered (with snow) so just managed to shake hands and then we set off again,&quot; Harrer told Austrian radio.</p>
<p>During World War Two, Harrer was imprisoned in India but managed to escape from his prison camp in 1944 and fled to Tibet where he stayed until 1951.</p>
<p>After his arrival in Tibet, he began teaching the 11-year-old Dalai Lama English, mathematics, geography and photography and also organised the building of a dam in the Himalayan kingdom, Stern reported.</p>
<p>He left Tibet in 1951 when Chinese troops marched into the country. The Dalai Lama and his followers fled in 1959 for India after Chinese troops suppressed a revolt in the region.</p>
<p>Harrer's biography, also entitled &quot;Seven Years in Tibet&quot;, recounts his experiences in Tibet, particularly as tutor and close friend to the Dalai Lama.</p>
<p>The Hollywood movie, directed by France's Jean-Jacques Annaud, is due to open in the United States in October. It is reported to have cost $60 million to produce.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
