<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="622907" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOTSWANA: BOTSWANA, S.AFRICA CLASH ON HYUNDAI CARS.</title>
<headline>BOTSWANA, S.AFRICA CLASH ON HYUNDAI CARS.</headline>
<byline>Barry Baxter</byline>
<dateline>GABORONE 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African officials visited neighbouring Botswana this week in a bid to defuse a row over imports of Korean-made Hyundai cars assembled in Botswana, officials and industry sources said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Commerce and industry minister George Kgoroba confirmed that the two sides had met to try and resolve the dispute, which centres on import duties.</p>
<p>Hyundai Motor Co imports semi-knocked down (SKD) cars into Botswana where it completes assembly before re-exporting most of them to South Africa.</p>
<p>Industry sources said Gaborone and Pretoria had clashed over this trade -- which is a thorn in the side of the South African motor industry -- following allegations that Hyundai was not paying its legally required duties to the Southern African Customs Union (SACU) for imports into the region.</p>
<p>This alleged non-payment of duties had led to cars being held at the South African border post at Kopfontein and released only after a South African High Court order which gave Hyundai until July 11 to prove it had paid, the sources said.</p>
<p>An average 1,000 Hyundai vehicles cross the Botswana border into South Africa each month, 90 percent of the plant's total production, and the vehicles retail at prices 10 to 15 percent below equivalent-range models.</p>
<p>Exports of motor vehicles from Botswana were worth 623.2 million pula in the first half alone of 1996, a valuable contribution in Botswana's drive to diversify its economy away from diamonds.</p>
<p>The 1996 car export figure represented 54 percent of total non-diamond exports.</p>
<p>Hyundai employs 500 people, but plans to double this over two years and add 950 more via component manufacturers as the plant converts to build finished vehicles from completely-knocked down (CKD) kits.</p>
<p>SACU groups Botswana, Lesotho, Namibia, South Africa and Swaziland.</p>
<p>-- Gaborone newsroom +9267-347182</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BOTS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GABORONE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOTSWANA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
