<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623054" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Hard Rock Cafe snaps up rock trophies at sale. [CORRECTED 18:07 GMT]</title>
<headline>Hard Rock Cafe snaps up rock trophies at sale. [CORRECTED 18:07 GMT]</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rock fans paid more than 250,000 pounds ($400,000) on Thursday for pop memorabilia ranging from Madonna's studded bra to Elvis's blue velvet shirt and John Lennon's garden furniture.</p>
<p>Ubiqitous restaurant chain the Hard Rock Cafe dominated bidding among the black-jeaned and open-collared crowd, snapping up more than 70 of the 429 lots on offer at Christie's auction house.</p>
<p>The day's additions to their collection included former Beatle Paul McCartney's official press statement after John Lennon's 1980 death for 11,500 pounds and Rolling Stone Keith Richard's guitar for 6,700 pounds.</p>
<p>The blue and white racing suit worn by Elvis Presley in the 1968 movie Speedway fetched nearly 10,000 pounds from the restaurant.</p>
<p>But they lost out on Elvis's midnight blue velvet shirt, bought by British comedian and television presenter Frank Skinner for 11,000 pounds.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone should have a bit of Elvis in their lives,&quot; Skinner said.</p>
<p>Asked what he would do with it, he said: &quot;I think I'll sleep in it tonight.&quot;</p>
<p>Madonna attracted heated bidding with a London collector paying 4,600 pounds for a beaded black bra worn by the singer during her provocative performance of Vogue.</p>
<p>(Corrects figure from 4,000 pounds).</p>
<p>&quot;I just love Madonna. She's so visual,&quot; said the 30-year-old buyer, who wished to remain anonymous, adding that he would put the bra on a mannequin at home.</p>
<p>Another of Madonna's outfits, a flamenco trouser suit by designer Jean-Paul Gaultier, doubled the pre-sale estimate to fetch 10,350 pounds from a Swedish collector.</p>
<p>($ = 0.611 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
