<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623099" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO: New Congo's Kabila -- democrat or closet dictator?.</title>
<headline>New Congo's Kabila -- democrat or closet dictator?.</headline>
<byline>Nicholas Phythian</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Veteran revolutionary Laurent Kabila consecrated a three-decades-old dream on Thursday when he took over formally as president of the Democratic Republic of Congo, having swept aside Mobutu Sese Seko.</p>
<p>Less than two weeks after his forces marched into the capital of Mobutu's Zaire, Kabila took an oath of office in the nation's main sports stadium, previously named Kamanyola after Mobutu's most famous victory -- against an earlier revolt.</p>
<p>The inauguration offered many citizens their first glimpse of the man who now controls their destiny and seems prepared to move forward at his own pace and on his own terms.</p>
<p>The 57-year-old Kabila -- seen as a free-market democrat by some, a closet dictator by others -- has not had an easy ride on the transition from rebel leader to head of state.</p>
<p>Western media and governments, particularly France, a long- time friend of Mobutu, have urged him to demonstrate greater commitment to democracy and human rights.</p>
<p>Some aid agencies working in the country, Africa's third biggest, have accused his followers of atrocities against Rwandan Hutu refugees in the east and north.</p>
<p>Against that, he has won a solid endorsement from the continent's foremost statesman, Nelson Mandela of South Africa, who accused some Western governments of demonising Kabila and ignoring his achievements.</p>
<p>&quot;What he has done in the areas he has conquered shows very clearly his commitment to democracy,&quot; Mandela said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Kabila declared himself president on May 17 from the southeastern town of Lubumbashi, capping a seven-month rebel campaign stretching from the Great Lakes of central Africa to the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
<p>His troops entered Kinshasa in triumph on the same day, scarcely more than 24 hours after the cancer-stricken Mobutu had fled the capital to end 32 years in power.</p>
<p>After the initial euphoria, supporters of veteran opposition leader Etienne Tshisekedi, enraged at his exclusion from the Kabila cabinet announced on May 22, took to the streets.</p>
<p>Kabila's soldiers broke up protests, firing in the air and beating demonstrators. His administration banned political activity and broke up a fresh march on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Later that same day, Kabila decreed himself sweeping powers to run the country until the adoption of a new transitional constitution by a promised constituent council.</p>
<p>Kabila on Thursday promised elections in April 1999 and made clear that foreign pressure would not change his timetable.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not in a hurry. This crumbling and shattered state must be organised so that the Congolese people can hold elections,&quot; he said in an address after his inauguration.</p>
<p>Kabila heads the Alliance of Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Congo, an alliance of four obscure political groups formed on October 8 with Banyamulenge ethnic Tutsis as the cutting edge of their revolt against Mobutu.</p>
<p>&quot;My long years of struggle were like spreading fertiliser on a field. But now it is time to harvest,&quot; Kabila, who speaks perfect English, told Reuters before moving on to Kinshasa.</p>
<p>Known by supporters as Mzee, the Swahili word for Grand Old Man, Kabila is not an ethnic Tutsi but he has forged close links to Tutsis over the years.</p>
<p>He is from mineral-rich Shaba in southern Zaire but has lived for many years among the Banyamulenge in the Mulenge Mountains south of Uvira, from where he plotted the uprising.</p>
<p>The civil war began in eastern Zaire began when the Banyamulenge, a community of roughly 400,000, resisted attempts to expel them to Rwanda, a land they left up to 200 years ago.</p>
<p>But its roots go deeper and his rebels had a hard core of veterans who fought with Rwanda's Tutsis after 1990. Rwanda says it backs Kabila but denies sending troops to help. Critics reject that and demand that all foreign troops leave the nation.</p>
<p>Kabila, stocky with a shaved head, is a former comrade-in -arms of the late Argentine-born revolutionary leader Ernesto &quot;Che&quot; Guevara, who fought in eastern Zaire in the early 1960s.</p>
<p>In 1965 Kabila joined a rebellion in the east led by Pierre Mulele, a minister in nationalist hero Patrice Lumumba's government after independence from Belgium in 1960.</p>
<p>A biography, &quot;Che Guevara - A Revolutionary Life&quot; by John Lee Anderson, includes sections of Che's unpublished memoir of the debacle in Congo, where he had pinned his hopes on Kabila.</p>
<p>Initially, Che was impresssed by Kabila, Anderson says.</p>
<p>&quot;Kabila understood perfectly that the principal enemy was North American imperialism,&quot; Che wrote. Kabila's revolutionary ideas were &quot;clear, concrete and firm.&quot;</p>
<p>After weeks in the eastern Congo jungle, however, Che became disillusioned, saying Kabila seemed reluctant to visit the front and drove around Dar es Salaam in a Mercedes Benz.</p>
<p>But Kabila stuck to his mission and was a regular visitor to Uganda in the 1980s after Yoweri Museveni's rebels took power.</p>
<p>Exiled Rwandan Tutsis in top positions in Museveni's army invaded Rwanda in 1990 and seized power in 1994 after genocide unleashed by Hutu extremists.</p>
<p>Some African states argue Kabila is at the head of a plot to carve out a &quot;Tutsiland&quot; in central Africa. Kabila denies it.</p>
<p>He is married with six children including Joseph, a military commander who captured the cities of Kisangani and Lubumbashi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
