<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623233" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>UZBEKISTAN: Uzbekistan halts 1997 wheat purchases temporarily.</title>
<headline>Uzbekistan halts 1997 wheat purchases temporarily.</headline>
<dateline>TASHKENT 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Uzbekistan has temporarily halted wheat imports, earlier forecast to hit 1.0-1.2 million tonnes in 1997, due to a lack of funds, a senior trade source told Reuters on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;The delays in wheat buying have occurred because of temporary absence of the necessary funds to import it into Uzbekistan,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan previously said a small wheat 1996 harvest of 2.7 million tonnes and increased consumption would mean it would need to import a minimum of 1.0 to 1.2 million tonnes of food wheat in 1997.</p>
<p>&quot;The republic won't be able to get around buying on the world market, but it has missed the favourable price situation where it could have saved $70 to $80 on each tonne of wheat bought,&quot; the source said.</p>
<p>He said Uzbekistan had imported 150,000 tonnes of wheat from Germany at $193.5 per tonne as of beginning of May, as well as 100,000 tonnes from Kazakhstan at $207 per tonne. Both deals were through commodity powerhouse Cargill of the United States.</p>
<p>The source said a final decision on wheat imports would be taken once the results of the 1997 harvest campaign, due to be completed in the second half of June, were known.</p>
<p>Previous estimates put annual food wheat demand from Uzbekistan's 23 million population at four million tonnes.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan announced in 1995 that it wanted to achieve self-sufficiency in grain, but its goal of producing 4.5 million tonnes a year proved impossible to fulfil due to harsh climactic conditions, underdeveloped infrastructure and a lack of the right kind of seeds.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan harvested 3.5 million tonnes of grain in 1996, including barley, rice and corn, of which the wheat yield was 2.73 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Uzbekistan imported 1.6 million tonnes of wheat in 1996, of which one million were imported through deals with Cargill and Swiss-based Glencore. --Shamil Baigin, Tashkent Newsroom, +3712 391 958</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UZBK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TASHKENT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UZBEKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
