<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623490" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: An American brainchild ousts HK's Suzie Wong image.</title>
<headline>An American brainchild ousts HK's Suzie Wong image.</headline>
<byline>James Flannery</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>A radical showpiece from real-life creator Larry K. Oltmanns is fast emerging to replace fictional good-time girl Suzie Wong as symbol of Hong Kong's once-raunchy Wan Chai district.</p>
<p>Larry who?</p>
<p>Oltmanns, from Chicago, is design architect of Hong Kong's biggest civic project, where Britain will hand the territory back to China at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>His convention-centre brainchild is growing hourly under rickety-looking bamboo scaffolding to meet a June 2 deadline.</p>
<p>In this hustling Asian city where buildings rise and fall in ceaseless property development, this one is meant to last a century or two at least, he says.</p>
<p>Oltmanns, of the Chicago firm Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, says the centre is intended to represent Hong Kong as precisely as the Eiffel Tower does for Paris or the Opera House for Sydney. &quot;It does look pretty good.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone around the world and here will recognise it,&quot; he says. &quot;It will reflect a sense of ascendancy which marks Hong Kong at this point in history.&quot;</p>
<p>When finished, all roads will lead to the centre in Wan Chai, which has long shed its X-rating, though shore-leave American sailors still roam its staid bars and nightclubs.</p>
<p>For a generation, a golden-hearted Wan Chai prostitute of Richard Mason's novel, &quot;The World of Suzie Wong&quot;, later a film, represented a version of Asian femininity. Most of that sexy exoticism vanished as Wan Chai built banks, luxury hotels and even arts centres.</p>
<p>A vacancy for a lasting symbol remained till the radically-designed centre took shape. It's meant to imprint for the world an exact image of Hong Kong, once a motley sweat-shop for Chinese refugees, now a major first-world-ranked economic centre.</p>
<p>On a flying visit to the territory, Oltmanns looked at his creation, evoking Hong Kong's spectacular meeting of sea and sky, and spoke rather like a preooccupied prospective parent.</p>
<p>&quot;It's on time,&quot; he said on Thursday, dismissing reports of delays. &quot;There are no real surprises. A lot of worry and anguish, yes. The surprises, pleasant ones, will be for all who see it finished outside, and inside a wonderful progression of spaces...&quot;</p>
<p>The 46-year-old architect, who speaks in slow, restrained Mid-Western tones, looked pleased at the HK$4.8 billion (US$ 620 million) harbourside Hong Kong Convention Centre.</p>
<p>The five-storey building of glass and aluminium, rising on land reclaimed from the sea, will be the world's focal point in 33 days, scene of an extraordinary change of power in the century's late years after the fall of European communism and South African apartheid.</p>
<p>An army of straw-hatted workers swarmed over a multi-layered curved roof, inspired by a bird soaring into flight, as construction teams toiled 24 hours a day in Hong Kong's hot steamy climate.</p>
<p>Now based back in the U.S., Oltmanns spent a year in Hong Kong, with his team, working up to 18 hours a day on the building which he says is comparable to the world's top five convention centres, two of them being in Asia - the Tokyo Forum and Tokyo Big Sight.</p>
<p>Here at a midnight ceremony British royal heir Prince Charles will hand Hong Kong back to China after 156 years of colonial rule, virtually ending centuries of global imperialism.</p>
<p>China's President Jiang Zemin is reported  planning to attend -- an event unprecedented in history.</p>
<p>He says the temple-like convention centres like this one are the modern markets of the world going back to the forum of the Roman empire.</p>
<p>Oltmanns says Hong Kong has plenty of distinctive buildings but they're all in private business hands. This one, formally known as the Hong Kong Convention and Exhibition Centre, breaks precedent as a public amenity.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
