<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623653" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Imported raspberries blamed for diarrheal illness.</title>
<headline>Imported raspberries blamed for diarrheal illness.</headline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Imported raspberries contaminated with the cyclospora parasite have caused about 90 people in five states to become ill in the past two months, federal health officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The Centres for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) said clusters of cases occurred in California, Florida, Nevada, New York and Texas in April and May. The agency said contaminated raspberries were served at eight different social events, sickening about 90 people.</p>
<p>For the second consecutive year, imported raspberries from Guatemala are being blamed for the illnesses. The CDC said berries from Chile might also have been contaminated this year. Outbreaks of diarrhoea caused by the cyclospora parasite occurred in 15 states and Canada last year.</p>
<p>Health officials recommend washing any produce that will be eaten raw but say this may not eliminate the risk of cyclospora. &quot;Thoroughly washing raspberries is difficult because they are fragile and full of cracks and crevices,&quot; Dr. Barbara Herwaldt, a CDC medical epidemiologist, said.</p>
<p>The first known human cases of cyclospora infection were diagnosed in the late 1970s. &quot;Cyclospora is one of the so-called emerging pathogens that we're studying and we don't have a good sense of how new it is,&quot; Herwaldt said.</p>
<p>Health officials say they do not know how common cyclospora infection is because laboratory tests do not routinely look for it.</p>
<p>Herwaldt said authorities do not know how the raspberries became contaminated. &quot;We have worked closely with the Food and Drug Administration and with berry growers in Guatemala to address some of the more likely causes of contamination.&quot;</p>
<p>Cyclospora, a microscopic single-cell parasite, infects the small intestine and usually causes watery diarrhoea. Other symptoms can include loss of appetite, weight loss, stomach cramps, nausea, vomiting, tiredness, muscle aches and flu-like symptoms such as fever. It can be treated with antibiotics but people previously infected can become infected again.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100206">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
