<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623678" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Military removes mystery canister from New Orleans.</title>
<headline>Military removes mystery canister from New Orleans.</headline>
<dateline>NEW ORLEANS 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>A mysterious canister found last week at New Orleans International Airport will be taken by army specialists to the Aberdeen Proving Ground for further inspection, authorities said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The 12-inch-long pressurized stainless steel canister was found on May 22 by airport security when an unidentified man tried to pass it through an X-ray machine en route to the concourse, airport authorities said.</p>
<p>Officials said the passenger said he could not open the cylinder because it would release a noxious odour. The man fled when security officers tried to question him, airport spokeswoman Michelle Duffourc said.</p>
<p>The Army Chemical Biological Defence Command will use special X-ray equipment to determine its contents and then take it to a laboratory at the Maryland facility for analysis, command spokeswoman Suzanne Fournier told Reuters on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't know how much time it will take to analyse. That depends on the initial findings,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>New Orleans authorities, fearing the canister was an explosive, first took it to a burn pit in a distant part of the airport before handing it over to the Environmental Protection Agency as a potentially hazardous material.</p>
<p>The EPA then called in military assistance, EPA spokesman John Casper told Reuters. The three-man team from the Technical Escord Detachment at Pine Bluff, Ark. will repack the canister into a hazardous material protective drum and then escort the drum to Maryland on a C-12 J2 military aircraft, Fournier said.</p>
<p>A description of the man carrying the canister was not released by authorities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW ORLEANS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
