<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623620" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Miami boy travels in style to Jamaica for free.</title>
<headline>Miami boy travels in style to Jamaica for free.</headline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dressed in a T-shirt and cut-off jeans, a 12-year-old boy walked through Miami airport security, boarded an American Airlines plane and flew first-class to Jamaica.</p>
<p>The boy had neither a ticket, money nor a passport. Now his mother, Darlene Livingstone, is seeking to sue American Airlines, the airport and U.S. government agencies.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a very amusing yet dangerous story,&quot; lawyer Ellis Rubin told a news conference on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The boy, whose name was not disclosed, began his adventure on May 19 when he walked out of a children's care centre to visit the airport. Without a dime in his pocket, he hopped aboard public transport and an airport shuttle bus.</p>
<p>At the airport he went through security with no one checking for a ticket or passport.</p>
<p>&quot;He didn't intend to fly,&quot; Rubin said.</p>
<p>But he joined a passenger line and was ushered on board to a first-class seat on a Jamaica-bound flight. It was only when he landed and tried to get to a resort that he was found out and flown home.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think he understands the seriousness. He thought it was a fun thing,&quot; his mother said.</p>
<p>American Airlines spokeswoman Martha Pantin would not say whether the boy had boarded the aircraft without a ticket.</p>
<p>&quot;The circumstances surrounding this matter are presently under investigation,&quot; she said. &quot;We have complete confidence in our security system, which is one of the most extensive in the industry.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
