<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623639" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Lawsuit filed in U.S. for jailed Egyptian cleric.</title>
<headline>Lawsuit filed in U.S. for jailed Egyptian cleric.</headline>
<byline>Jeanne King</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lawyers for Moslem cleric jailed in the United States filed a civil rights lawsuit on Thursday, arguing that the Egyptian preacher's health had deteriorated because of his time in solitary confinement.</p>
<p>&quot;Instead of having him in a hospital, they have him in a separate segregation punishment unit where he has been for over 16 months,&quot; one of his lawyers, Ramsay Clark, said.</p>
<p>Clark, a former U.S. Attorney, said he spoke with Sheikh Omar Abel-Rahman at the Springfield federal prison in Missouri on Thursday morning.</p>
<p>&quot;He told me that this past week is the worst week he's had. He has chest pains. The prison doctor told him his blood pressure is up. His nose and throat are inflamed. He has pains around his kidneys and liver. His stomach is bloated,&quot; Clark said.</p>
<p>The cleric and nine others were convicted In October 1995 of conspiracy to carry out a war of terrorism that included blowing up the United Nations, other New York City landmarks and plans to assassinate political leaders including Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak.</p>
<p>The lawyer said Abdel-Rahman's isolation in a basement cell had exacerbated his health problems. &quot;It's not reality. It's akin to torture,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The shiek is also blind and has long suffered from diabetes, asthma and a heart condition.</p>
<p>Clark said the aim of the lawsuit, filed in Sringfield, was to get Abdel-Rahman transferred to the general prison population and to restore his religious rights.</p>
<p>Among the complaints listed in the lawsuit is the claim that because prison officals have taken away a special Arabic braille watch and compass, the blind cleric does not know the time of day and direction of Mecca that he must face to pray.</p>
<p>Todd Craig, a Bureau of Prisons spokesman, said his office had not seen the lawsuit and would have no comment on it.</p>
<p>&quot;Inmate Abdel-Rahman's condition is stable and like any other inmate he is receiving medical care consistent with community standards,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Asked why the cleric could not have a watch and compass, Craig said: &quot;The procedures that have been invoked in his case include limiting some privileges.&quot;</p>
<p>Abdeen Jabara, another member of the defence legal team, said he found prison officials &quot;totally unresponsive&quot; to the sheikh's needs after he visited the cleric three weeks ago.</p>
<p>U.S. prison authorities said earlier this month that the cleric was being treated fairly under regulations introduced in May 1996 for prisoners linked with terrorism.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
