<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623785" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: PROFILE - Waigel looks tired as he sets record.</title>
<headline>PROFILE - Waigel looks tired as he sets record.</headline>
<byline>Tom Heneghan</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Theo Waigel sets a record on Friday as Bonn's longest-serving finance minister, but the howl of protest his grab for Bundesbank gold has provoked must make him wonder if he should have stayed around so long.</p>
<p>Waigel, normally the jolliest member of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's cabinet, looked tired and cheerless on Thursday when he met journalists in the Bavarian village of Ursberg to defend his plan to revalue the gold to help qualify for the euro.</p>
<p>His bushy brows rose and familiar smile returned when a reporter asked about his eight years in office.</p>
<p>&quot;It has been a great time, I wouldn't have missed it for anything,&quot; he said with a wistful smile.</p>
<p>But the questions quickly turned back to the Bundesbank controversy, and Waigel's eyes lost their twinkle again.</p>
<p>Waigel, 58, now stands at the centre of a storm the likes of which postwar Germany has never seen.</p>
<p>He and Kohl have taken on the Bundesbank, the most trusted institution in all of Germany, and intend to wrestle it to its knees to make it pay out 20 billion marks to help Bonn qualify for Europe's monetary union (EMU).</p>
<p>Proud of its image of independence that was sometimes more projected than real, the Bundesbank lashed back on Wednesday with a blistering critique of Waigel's plan. It called it meddling in the bank's affairs and a threat to the euro.</p>
<p>With the sides clearly drawn, Waigel is the point man in a campaign that --despite his protests to the contrary -- will cut the Bundesbank down a notch and put it under the political control German central bankers were supposed to be free of.</p>
<p>Given the reverence most Germans have for the august bank, it's hard to see how he can pull this off without looking like the villain of the piece.</p>
<p>&quot;We Germans like complicated decisions to be taken by independent bodies like the Bundesbank or the supreme court,&quot; one official from Kohl's Christian Democratic Union (CDU) said. &quot;But now the politicians are poking their noses into it. This is no better than what the French or the Italians do.&quot;</p>
<p>There couldn't be a less likely candidate for villain than Waigel, a man who is always quick with a joke and equally happy talking football and finance.</p>
<p>Now in his second marriage, to former skiing champion Irene Epple, he has a two-year-old son who often makes him look more like a doting young father than the longest-serving finance minister in the Group of Seven (G7) rich man's club.</p>
<p>The quick-witted Waigel is also probably the most widely derided politician in Germany. Calls for his resignation pour in every time budgets go wrong and debt-hating Germans are forced to borrow more money.</p>
<p>With German deficits surging in recent years, partly because of the costly unification with the formerly communist east and partly due to joblessness and the high cost of labour, Waigel has been a visible and convenient target for blame.</p>
<p>He jokes that if he ever succeeds in pushing through his plan to cut income tax rates, taxpayers will change their tune to &quot;Theo Gratias,&quot; a play on the Latin phrase for &quot;Thanks be to God&quot;.</p>
<p>Germany, once the star candidate for membership in Europe's economic and monetary union (EMU), is desperately trying to rein in its deficit to qualify for the euro's launch in 1999.</p>
<p>The Maastricht Treaty says countries joining EMU should have budget deficits no higher than three percent of gross domestic product and overall debts not more than 60 percent of gross domestic product (GDP).</p>
<p>Waigel's latest woes erupted earlier this month when a tax commission reported Bonn's expected tax revenues for 1997 would fall 18 billion marks short of earlier targets, blowing a huge hole in his budget and diminishing Germany's chances of qualifying for the euro.</p>
<p>That led him to propse that Bonn sell off some of its shares in Deutsche Telekom and revalue Bundesbank gold and currency reserves to realise the hidden profits lying there.</p>
<p>Waigel was born on April 22, 1939, in the Bavarian village of Oberrohr, the son of a foreman in charge of a team of bricklayers. He commutes to Oberrohr every weekend to his wife and infant son. He studied law in Munich and Wuerzberg before entering the Bonn parliament in 1972.</p>
<p>From 1976 he was deputy for the Neu-Ulm constituency. He served on the education and science committee, then the committees for budgetary affairs and economics and became finance spokesman for the CDU/CSU after the 1980 election.</p>
<p>After the sudden death of CSU leader Franz-Josef Strauss in November 1988, Waigel became party leader with 98.3 per cent of the vote. His hopes of returning to Bavaria were foiled in 1993 when he lost the race for state premier to Edmund Stoiber.</p>
<p>His first marriage to Karin Hoenig in 1966 ended in 1994. He had a daughter and son from that marriage. A month after the divorce was completed, he married Epple, then 37 years old.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
