<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="623851" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India unlikely to stop Australian wheat imports.</title>
<headline>India unlikely to stop Australian wheat imports.</headline>
<byline>Hari Ramachandran</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>India is unlikely to stop further wheat purchases from Australia after finding weeds in its shipments, but may suggest new quality norms for future arrivals, government officials and analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are thinking of putting some fresh conditions on wheat shipments from Australia,&quot; a senior official of the state-run State Trading Corporation (STC) who asked not to be identified, told Reuters. He declined to give details on the conditions being considered.</p>
<p>In December, India authorised STC to import two million tonnes of wheat in 1996/97 (April-March) to build stocks and check rising prices.</p>
<p>STC officials say they have so far contracted to import 1.75 million tonnes, mainly from Australia, Argentina and Canada. STC says the entire quantity has already arrived at Indian ports.</p>
<p>The government announced the fresh imports of two million tonnes of wheat in 1997/98, of which STC has contracted for one million tonnes, mainly from Australia.</p>
<p>The STC official said new wheat shipments from Australia were due between July and December 1997, and that he expected the arrivals to start in August.</p>
<p>&quot;We still have a lot of time (to set the conditions),&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Agriculture Minister Chaturanan Mishra said on Tuesday that the &quot;weed&quot; detected in wheat import shipments from Australia was not harmful and common in wheat of any origin.</p>
<p>Mishra said India had taken precautionary steps to ensure that the weed-infected imports were not diverted to wheat-growing areas.</p>
<p>On Monday, reports from Australia quoted Australian Wheat Board officials as saying that Australia had abided by all requirements in its wheat sales to India and had not received any official complaints about quality problems.</p>
<p>Officials said Australia, which has export contracts with India totalling 2.325 million tonnes, had so far shipped 1.3 million.</p>
<p>&quot;I personally think the fresh consignment will come,&quot; S.M. Virmani, an agriculture expert at the Hyderabad-based International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT).</p>
<p>Virmani said it appeared as though no one wanted to give an accurate picture of the weeds in the imported wheat.</p>
<p>&quot;Australia, Canada and the United States may be trying to get rid of wheat lying in the silos since their new crop will come in September and production last year has been good,&quot; Virmani said.</p>
<p>The STC official said India had contracted for Australian wheat at $155 per tonne while Pakistan was buying from the new crop at $185 a tonne.</p>
<p>Officials of the state-run Food Corporation of India (FCI) said up to Tuesday it had purchased 7.95 million tonnes of wheat from farmers compared with 8.03 million on the same date last year.</p>
<p>They said the purchases this year would exceed last year's and would even reach 10 million tonnes because market arrivals were expected to continue till June 10.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
