<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="624166" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: U.S., British first ladies usher in new era.</title>
<headline>U.S., British first ladies usher in new era.</headline>
<byline>Lyndsay Griffiths</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton visited her British counterpart Cherie Blair on Thursday in a closely-watched meeting of two of the world's most powerful wives.</p>
<p>Wifely status aside, both women are brainy, successful lawyers and devoted mothers who symbolise the shift in power on either side of the Atlantic to the post-war generation.</p>
<p>&quot;They have a certain position,&quot; said Hannah Davies, among the crowds jostling to see the first ladies out and about in London. &quot;They did not become the wife of the president or prime minister for nothing. I think they must lead interesting lives.&quot;</p>
<p>Yet while Hillary is in her second term as U.S. first lady, Cherie has had less than a month to settle into her new role as spouse to the most powerful man in Britain.</p>
<p>Labour leader Tony Blair was swept to power on May 1 and is known to share many many political leanings and generational traits with President Bill Clinton.</p>
<p>Much has also been made of their wives' similarities.</p>
<p>Stylish, opinionated and political, the two women ended a long tradition in both countries of first wives demurely staying home while their husbands ran the world.</p>
<p>Both are young mothers who have pursued very well-paid legal careers. They are also said to be brighter and more left-leaning than their husbands.</p>
<p>Yet while Hillary has courted controversy for her outspoken political comments and key role in shaping U.S. policy, Cherie is largely an unknown.</p>
<p>She stuck close to her husband during the election campaign but has doggedly avoided speaking to the media and made clear she plans to continue her job -- not meddle in his.</p>
<p>Yet true to tradition, their two-piece suits were duly pored over -- blonde Hillary wore sky blue while brunette Cherie chose dove grey -- and the agenda was a tried-and-tested formula of lunch folllowed by a spot of theatre.</p>
<p>&quot;They lunched privately, with some aides from Mrs Clinton's party and some staff from Downing Street,&quot; said a spokesman.</p>
<p>From Downing Street, the two women sped by stretch limo to the Globe theatre, an exquisite recreation of the riverside playhouse where Shakespeare's plays were staged 400 years ago.</p>
<p>The open-topped wooden playhouse officially opened this month after a painstaking renovation pioneered by the late U.S. actor-director Sam Wanamaker.</p>
<p>&quot;We're delighted that the only day the first lady is in town she has come to us,&quot; said Globe spokeswoman Nina Jacob. &quot;It was an American who hatched the idea and we owe them a lot for helping us re-discover something British. We already get lots of American visitors and I'm sure this will only encourage more.&quot;</p>
<p>The two women toured an exhibition before watching the first half of Henry V in baking sun. Most of the audience sat on wooden benches or stood while the VIPs peered down from the so-called gentlemen's rooms, precursor to the modern-day box.</p>
<p>One 51-year-old onlooker said the women, who chatted animatedly ahead of the performance, seemed to get along well.</p>
<p>&quot;The body language seemed to be all right,&quot; she said. &quot;I presume having a law background, they will have a lot in common. They're both quite bright cookies with their own careers.&quot;</p>
<p>The Clintons were due to head home later on Thursday after a one-day visit aimed at cementing the new &quot;special relationship&quot; between Blair's Britain and Clinton's United States.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
