<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="624309" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Egyptian writer gets year in jail for unsold book.</title>
<headline>Egyptian writer gets year in jail for unsold book.</headline>
<byline>Esmat Salaheddin</byline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Egyptian author has lost an appeal against a one-year prison sentence for writing a book that prosecutors said was blasphemous and sexually explicit, lawyers and human rights activists said on Thursday.</p>
<p>A Cairo court earlier this week rejected Alaa Hamed's appeal against the 1992 sentence, which included a 200 pound ($58.9) fine and the seizure of copies of &quot;El Firash (The Bed)&quot;, a collection of short stories.</p>
<p>&quot;Alaa Hamed was charged with writing for the sake of publication stories that offended public morality and mocked Moslem clerics,&quot; Hamed's lawyer Abdel-Malak Awadallah said.</p>
<p>Hamed was fired from his job at the tax authority in 1994 by an administrative court decision because of the same book.</p>
<p>Human rights groups attacked the latest court decision because the book has not been sold but was seized at press.</p>
<p>&quot;The stories are not immoral. This sentence was not unexpected. Militants have penetrated the justice system. The judge did not like Hamed because one of stories is about a judge doing sinful acts with his maid,&quot; Negad el-Borai, director of the independent Group for Democracy Development, told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said stories in the book took a critical look at figures of authority, such as judges and clerics, who have strayed.</p>
<p>Hamed's wife, Malak Mohammed Saleh, said prosecutors claimed each of the eight stories in the collection contained scenes that violated public morality, but she did not elaborate.</p>
<p>&quot;Thoughts should be discussed, not punished. Alaa refused to flee the country because he said 'I have my roots in Egypt and will fight in my country'. El Firash has never been promoted. It is a still-born baby,&quot; Saleh said.</p>
<p>Hamed, known as the Egyptian Salman Rushdie, was at the centre of an international outcry in 1991 when a state security court sentenced him to eight years in prison for a story questioning religion.</p>
<p>The court at the time said the book, &quot;A Distance in a Man's Mind,&quot; threatened national unity and peace.</p>
<p>But Hamed did not serve the sentence because former prime minister Atef Sedki, in his function as Egypt's deputy martial law governor, did not endorse it, Borai said. The verdict, however, will remain valid for 10 years.</p>
<p>Intellectuals in Egypt say they are under fire from Moslem militants who want to change Egypt into their vision of a strict Islamic state and from the court system, which Islamists have used to successfully curb freedom of expression.</p>
<p>Militants killed secular writer Farag Foda in 1992 and injured Nobel prize winner Naguib Mahfouz, 83, in 1994.</p>
<p>Last year, a group of Moslem fundamentalist lawyers successfully sued to separate a university professor from his wife on the ground that his writings had made him an apostate.</p>
<p>A human rights activist said his group would prepare a petition to suspend the one-year sentence until the Court of Cassation, the highest degree court, issued a final ruling.</p>
<p>Egypt's legal system allows the suspension of an appeal court sentence until the Court of Cassation studied the case.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
