<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="624409" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Sounds of Blackness says it is 'Time For Healing'.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Sounds of Blackness says it is 'Time For Healing'.</headline>
<byline>Franklin Paul</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>For 25 years, Gary Hines has found himself explaining the credo of his Grammy-winning musical ensemble, Sounds of Blackness, time and again.</p>
<p>They aren't a gospel group, although they sing gospel songs. Neither are they just a large vocal chorus. Hines, the director of the 40-member troupe, says it is a kind of museum of musical styles, showcasing the many faces of African American culture.</p>
<p>&quot;(It) performs all styles of black music -- jazz, blues, gospel, R&amp;B, hip-hop and rock. Each of those is a 'sound' of black people and collectively they are the sounds of blackness,&quot; he said in a telephone interview. &quot;(Our) vision is to continue the tradition of Duke Ellington and Quincy Jones, of establishing a legitimate black music ensemble.&quot;</p>
<p>That vision has proved quite successful since Hines and Russell Knight formed the group in the early 1970's, when both were students at Macalester College in St. Paul, Minnesota. Since then, the group has enjoyed both critical and popular acclaim. Three of its albums have gone platinum, including its debut, &quot;The Evolution of Gospel&quot; (A&amp;M), which won a 1991 Grammy Award for best gospel album by a choir or chorus.</p>
<p>Sounds released its latest album, &quot;Time For Healing&quot; (A&amp;M), in May.</p>
<p>While Hines is grateful for these achievements, winning awards was far from his mind when Sounds was in its infancy.</p>
<p>AN IDEA TO EDUCATE</p>
<p>Instead, Hines hoped to educate listeners on Afro-American history and the origins of the music of black people. Working from their home base in the chilly upper Midwest, Sounds garnered attention early on with performances of original musical theatre productions such as &quot;Africa to America&quot; and &quot;The Night Before Christmas.&quot; They also produced an occasional independent album.</p>
<p>In 1988, superproducers Jimmy &quot;Jam&quot; Harris and Terry Lewis -- friends of Hines and Minneapolis natives -- signed Sounds as their first act on their Perspective Records label. But when the group released &quot;The Evolution of Gospel&quot; in 1990, they were pigeonholed as a gospel group. And from within the gospel community, where the album was well received, there were grumblings by those who saw their sound as too secular.</p>
<p>Hines answered critics that the group's music combines the many branches of a vast African American musical heritage. In the past, he has labeled the message &quot;a spiritual, historical and musical testimony of a people, to, and for, all people.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The No. 1 goal is to glorify God by uplifting people of all nationalities through all styles of African American music,&quot; he said from his Minneapolis home. &quot;But I frequently say to people who've had criticism that you can't fully appreciate the 'Glory Hallelujah' of the gospel without understanding the pain of the blues.&quot;</p>
<p>POSITIVE MESSAGE</p>
<p>&quot;Time for Healing,&quot; like all of the group's previous CDs, is full of positive messages and songs urging the people of the world to learn to live and work together. The album was inspired in part by recent tragic events including the Oklahoma City and Atlanta bombings (they performed on the Olympic Park stage the night before the blast there), and the struggles for peace in the Middle East, Africa and Northern Ireland, as well as the plight of urban America.</p>
<p>&quot;We said, 'What can Sounds of Blackness do or say through what we've been blessed to do, this music of black experience, to have some positive impact?'&quot;</p>
<p>Hines addresses these and other issues with thoughtful lyrics that permeate the often disparate musical styles. Most of the songs were written by him, keyboardist Billy Steele and Levi Seacer, a former guitarist for Prince's band, New Power Generation.</p>
<p>On the album, &quot;A Spiritual Medley,&quot; a tight and majestic grouping of Negro spirituals is sandwiched between the sassy blues tune &quot;The Blackness Blues&quot; and &quot;So Far Away,&quot; a bossa nova cut co-written by Antonio Carlos Jobim. Dig deeper and you will hear gentle gospel (&quot;God Cares&quot;), some hip-hop flavor (&quot;Spirit&quot;) and even an animated update of Sly Stone's funk classic, &quot;You Can Make It If You Try.&quot;</p>
<p>The group, which includes a 10-piece orchestra, delivers complex harmonies, pleasant melodies and an unlimited supply of energy on every cut.</p>
<p>With his idols in mind, Hines says he will continue to create the music -- and explain it, if needed. &quot;I've read and listened to many interviews of Duke, and people would say to him, '... well as a jazz musician ...' and he would always correct them and say, 'I do the music of my people,'&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
