<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="624530" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac trump card Madelin a fiery free-marketeer.</title>
<headline>Chirac trump card Madelin a fiery free-marketeer.</headline>
<byline>John Follain</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Free-marketeer Alain Madelin, one of the right's last trump cards before Sunday's parliamentary French assembly election runoff, held office as finance minister for just four months before falling victim to his love of provocation.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Alain Juppe sacked him in August 1995 for denouncing the &quot;privileges&quot; of civil servants, a comment which sparked a furore.</p>
<p>This month, the irrepressible Madelin, who fought his first political battles on the extreme-right as a student, compared the elite ENA civil service breeding ground to a terrorist organisation, again drawing a barrage of criticism.</p>
<p>A thorn in Juppe's side since his dismissal, the 51-year-old intellectual is tipped to return to the finance portfolio if the right wins the poll, as part of a &quot;dream ticket&quot; with socially conscious Gaullist Philippe Seguin.</p>
<p>A crusader for a slimline state, Madelin is the closest France has to a Thatcherite or Reaganite, though he was careful to stress in the campaign that he wants to preserve a renovated version of the welfare state.</p>
<p>Outlining his credo in a book entitled &quot;Quand les autruches releveront la tete&quot; (When ostriches raise their heads), the laissez-faire champion wrote in late 1995 that France had much in common with its state on the eve of the 1789 Revolution.</p>
<p>&quot;The new aristocracy administers more than one in two francs of the country's resources, and regulates the rest. What is shocking is that the power of this new class is not counterbalanced by duties or responsibilities,&quot; he wrote.</p>
<p>In his eyes, the new class encompasses politicians and bureaucrats trained at prestigious schools such as the Ecole Nationale d'Administration (ENA).</p>
<p>The manifesto appealed to what Madelin dubbed France's silent majority, beyond his hard-core backers among small business, the liberal professions, shopkeepers and artisans.</p>
<p>Madelin was minister of economic development and small businesses under Juppe's predecessor Prime Minister Edouard Balladur when he launched a drive to his party -- which largely backed Balladur -- behind Chirac.</p>
<p>As campaign economic adviser, he played an important part in promoting Chirac's image as a bold reformer and was rewarded with the finance portfolio when Chirac was elected in May 1995.</p>
<p>Madelin's political stature grew after he left the cabinet, making him a possible alternative to Juppe and a gadfly calling for more radical reforms to cut public spending.</p>
<p>But in 1996, unable to rally support for his ultra-liberal ideas, he lost to Francois Leotard in his bid to be president of the UDF, junior partner in the ruling coalition.</p>
<p>Known for his biting wit and toughness in arguments, Madelin was one of the leaders of the Occident movement, a neo-fascist strong-arm group which terrorised political opponents and anti-Vietnam war activists, while attending Assas law school in Paris. The group was later outlawed.</p>
<p>As industry minister in France's first &quot;cohabitation&quot; government from 1986 to 1988, he waged a war against hands-on government, saying it was behind all France's economic woes.</p>
<p>He later softened his views and become a belated supporter of France's strong-franc policy, and now resents being referred to as a die-hard capitalist.</p>
<p>Born in 1946, Madelin grew up in a working class suburb of Paris and entered politics when he won his first seat in the National Assembly in 1978.</p>
<p>He runs a political think-tank -- Idees-Action (Ideas-Action) -- which maintains close ties with former Warsaw Pact countries and a network of conservative economic contacts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
