<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="624595" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Swiss banker and businessman Leutwiler dies at 72.</title>
<headline>Swiss banker and businessman Leutwiler dies at 72.</headline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fritz Leutwiler, a leading figure in Switzerland's post-World War Two banking and industrial era, has died aged 72, according a family death announcement published in a Swiss newspaper.</p>
<p>The announcement in the daily Neue Zuercher Zeitung cited serious illness as the cause of death. It did not elaborate.</p>
<p>Leutwiler, born in the Swiss canton of Aargau, remained active and outspoken until just months before his death, working with Swiss banks and industry in efforts to set up a fund to compensate Holocaust victims and their families who lost assets during the 1939-45 war.</p>
<p>Leutwiler had served from 1974 to 1984 as president of the Swiss National Bank, after joining the monetary institution in 1952 to work in its economics and statistics department.</p>
<p>He stepped down from the SNB a few years before mandatory retirement, but then became head of the Bank for International Settlements (BIS), the Basle-based bank for central bankers, in 1982.</p>
<p>The job gave Leutwiler a new role in crisis management, coinciding with major problems in world lending to developing countries.</p>
<p>In 1985, he took over as chairman of engineering company BBC Brown Boveri AG, helping restructure the firm.</p>
<p>Under his leadership, the Swiss industrial concern merged with Sweden's ASEA SA in 1987 to form the world's biggest electrical engineering concern, ABB Asea Brown Boveri. After the merger, he served as co-chairman from 1988 until retiring in 1992.</p>
<p>A slight, tough man, Leutwiler admitted to being at times abrasive. He developed a warm friendship with former German Bundesbank president Karl-Otto Poehl.</p>
<p>His career began after graduating from a Zurich university with an economics degree. He served a stint as editor of a monetary journal and three years later went to London for training with a Swiss commercial bank.</p>
<p>&quot;I never made up my mind whether journalism was better off for being rid of me, or I for being rid of journalism,&quot; he once commented.</p>
<p>He was married with two children.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
