<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="624909" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan Apr coffee imports rise as roasters rush.</title>
<headline>Japan Apr coffee imports rise as roasters rush.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>A rush to buy coffee by local roasters amidst tight global supplies and rising prices was behind the increase in Japan's April bean imports, coffee traders said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Japan's green coffee imports in April totalled 31,059 tonnes, up by 13.5 percent from the same month a year earlier, mainly from Brazil, Colombia and Indonesia, Finance Ministry data showed.</p>
<p>Total green coffee imports in the first four months of 1997 were 116,843 tonnes, against 93,193 tonnes the previous year.</p>
<p>&quot;Japanese roasters were trying to import coffee before world bean prices surged any further,&quot; a coffee trader at a major trade house said.</p>
<p>The hurried buying of coffee is expected to keep domestic inventories growing in the near term, traders said.</p>
<p>The Agriculture Ministry said on Tuesday Japan's warehouse coffee stocks were 67,298 tonnes at the end of April, up 22.7 percent from a year earlier.</p>
<p>Domestic stocks fell steadily last year, since at that time local roasters preferred to keep to the sidelines just covering immediate needs, as they expected prices to come down.</p>
<p>&quot;Domestic stocks are expected to continue growing this year, as local roasters rush to cover coffee at a pace which is quicker-than-usual,&quot; another coffee trader said.</p>
<p>Japan is the world's third-biggest coffee consumer after the United States and Germany.</p>
<p>-- Tokyo Commodities Desk (+81-3-3432-7391)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100137">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
