<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="625071" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesian minister seeks corn import tariff.</title>
<headline>Indonesian minister seeks corn import tariff.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesian Agriculture Minister Syarifuddin Baharsyah wants the government to implement an import tariff on corn, a ministry official said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Traders said the move, which was reported in local newspapers, took the industry by surprise.</p>
<p>Baharsyah was quoted by the Harian Ekonomi Neraca newspaper as saying he had asked the finance ministry to review the tariff on imported corn.</p>
<p>A ministry official confirmed that Baharsyah had written to Finance Minister Mar'ie Muhammad asking for the import tariff on corn to be reviewed, but had yet to receive a reply.</p>
<p>&quot;He has written to the finance minister but there has been no reply yet,&quot; the official told Reuters. &quot;It is because many companies are not keen on buying local corn.&quot;</p>
<p>The official said he did not have details on how much the tariff was on imported corn, but industry sources said imported corn was currently not subjected to any import duty.</p>
<p>&quot;This is really surprising and strange,&quot; one industry official said. &quot;At a time when countries in the region are bringing down import tariffs, we are proposing an increase.&quot;</p>
<p>The official said the move, if implemented, would have a significant impact on importers as they would have to pay higher prices for their imported corn, thus raising production costs.</p>
<p>&quot;Feedmills will be affected if this proposal is accepted and implemented by the government,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Minister Baharsyah was quoted in the Jakarta Post newspaper as saying he would raise his proposed move at the next cabinet meeting early next month.</p>
<p>Indonesia, in a bid to reduce its dependence on imported corn, has embarked on an ambitious programme to boost local production through the cultivation of a high-yielding hybrid.</p>
<p>A agriculture ministry official said in January that a total of 885,000 hectares would be planted with the hybrid variety this year, and another 900,000 hectares in 1998.</p>
<p>He said Indonesia's corn production was expected to rise to 9.2 million tonnes this year from 8.0 million in 1996, when imports amounted to some 1.6 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Traders said they expected 1997 imports to remain at last year's level because the success of the hybrid project had been overstated and that corn demand from feedmills was growing rapidly.</p>
<p>-- Jakarta newsroom + 6221 384-6364</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
