<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="625010" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan palladium imports remain high in April.</title>
<headline>Japan palladium imports remain high in April.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's imports of palladium in April remained high, as spot-market purchases remained robust amid uncertainty over Russian supplies, traders said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Japan's palladium imports in April totalled 6.078 tonnes, up 14.9 percent from a year earlier but down 35.0 percent from March, Finance Ministry data showed on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;Although palladium imports dipped from March, as end-users refrained from buying due to high prices and in reaction to the sales tax hike in April, uncertainty over Russian metal supplies kept April imports high,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Although Japan-Russia talks on export contract talks for platinum group metals are set for early June, palladium imports in May could remain steady to firmer as traders will be forced to cover their needs in the spot market until they receive shipments from Russia.</p>
<p>Japan's platinum imports in April fell by 20.1 percent from a year earlier to 4.68 tonnes, as the sales tax increase effective from April dampened platinum demand.</p>
<p>The figures showed that imports of platinum group metals from Russia in April totalled 2.834 tonnes for palladium and 0.05 tonnes for platinum, traders said this was mostly metal of Russian origin imported through third countries.</p>
<p>Traders said Japan's platinum imports in May are unlikely to rise as the Japan's jewellery industry has shown little sign of improvement.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see much change in platinum imports in May, as we have not seen spectacular platinum sales in May,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>--Tokyo Commodity Desk, +81-3-3432-7431</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22472">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
