<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="625335" id="root" date="1997-05-29" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Pope trip to Poland a bitter-sweet return.</title>
<headline>Pope trip to Poland a bitter-sweet return.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul begins a bitter-sweet return to Poland on Saturday to review the lights and shadows of his homeland eight years after it became the first East Bloc country to cast off communism.</p>
<p>The trip to 12 towns and cities in 11 days is in part a walk down memory lane for the Roman Catholic leader, who has suffered from a series of health problems in the last three years.</p>
<p>Coming just two weeks after he marked his 77th birthday, the trip, the Pope's 78th abroad and the longest to a single country since he visited Brazil in 1991, will be a major test of his stamina.</p>
<p>&quot;Certainly it will be more difficult than five or 10 years ago but what can you expect from a man who still works hard and has already passed his 76th year,&quot; said Bishop Tadeusz Pieronek, secretary of the Polish bishops' conference.</p>
<p>Still, aides say few things invigorate the Pontiff more than visits to the land that shaped his destiny, and in turn that of the 960 million-member Catholic Church in the 20th century.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a return to the places that are most dear to him,&quot; Pieronek said.</p>
<p>Vatican officials say that each time the Pope visits Poland he does so with the realisation that it could be his last.</p>
<p>The final part of the trip is centred on Krakow, where the Pope lived out part of World War Two with his widowed father and where he was later to become bishop and cardinal.</p>
<p>The most poignant momemt will most likely be a visit to his parents' graves in Krakow and the cathedral which he left in 1978, never dreaming he would be elected Pope.</p>
<p>He will also visit the shrine of Czestochowa and again give thanks to the Madonna for saving his life in a 1981 shooting.</p>
<p>Each of the Pope's six previous trips to Poland has struck deep political chords, most notably his first in 1979 which gave Poles a flush of pride while still in communism's grip.</p>
<p>&quot;The 1979 trip was like a reawakening,&quot; Father Adam Boniecki, former editor of the Polish edition of the Vatican newspaper L'Osservatore Romano, said in a radio interview.</p>
<p>&quot;The communist state and its police aparatus deprived the people of their faith and of the possibility of real change. Before the arrival of the Pope freedom was won centimetre by centemetre. Afterwards, Polish society felt stronger and the march towards freedom began,&quot; Boniecki said.</p>
<p>Historians have credited the Pope's unflagging support for the Solidarity trade union as a key factor in the domino fall of communism in the East Bloc.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no doubt that the Pope has always been a potent force in the Polish situation,&quot; Pieronek said.</p>
<p>As he has on all of his trips to Poland since 1989, the Pope is expected to warn his countrymen not to allow the spoils of their post-communist freedom to be eroded by moral decay, materialism and budding anti-clericalism.</p>
<p>&quot;Poland still finds itself in the process of coming out of the long illness of socialism. Like any body that is weak, it catches fever easily from episodes that in other societies are a routine part of public life,&quot; Boniecki said</p>
<p>As in other countries in the former Soviet Bloc, the breathless march of market forces since 1989 has left a wide gap between rich and poor and eroded communism's social safety net.</p>
<p>&quot;He will find Poles more divided and a little more lost because in the past few years there have been so many changes and not all of them are good for society,&quot; Pieronek said.</p>
<p>This time it will not be Lech Walesa, the former Solidarity leader who became president, greeting the Pope on his arrival in Wroclaw on Saturday and seeing him off in Krakow on June 10.</p>
<p>Former communists, who are now social democrats, have held the reins of government since 1993. President Aleksander Kwasniewski defeated Walesa in 1995.</p>
<p>The Church, once a rallying point for anti-communist forces, has had a scratchy relationship with the government over issues such as abortion and a still unratified concordat treaty with the Vatican to regulate the Church's status.</p>
<p>It was signed by the former government in 1993 but has since been delayed by leftists in parliament.</p>
<p>On June 3 in Gniezno the Pope will meet the heads of state of seven eastern and central European countries visiting Poland for the 1,000th anniversary of the martyrdom of St Adalbert, who helped Christianise the East.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-29"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
