<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="625434" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Harley-Davidson bikes hog roads in Maine city.</title>
<headline>Harley-Davidson bikes hog roads in Maine city.</headline>
<dateline>PORTLAND, Maine 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>It was &quot;Hog Heaven&quot; in Maine's largest city Friday and even the governor hopes to have his Harley-Davidson motorcycle on the road before the weekend is over.</p>
<p>A motorcycle parade kicked off the gathering of &quot;HOG&quot; -- Harley Owners Group -- which draws people from around the United States and Canada to show off their bikes and accompanying regalia.</p>
<p>&quot;All these people are having fun with their motorcycles. That's what it's all about,&quot; William Davidson, grandson of one of the company's founders, said.</p>
<p>The throaty roar of motorcycles echoed across downtown Portland, where some streets were closed except for bikes and a lighted message board atop a building flashed &quot;Hog Heaven.&quot;</p>
<p>Some 5,000 people are attending the two-day rally. The owners group, affiliated with Milwaukee-based Harley-Davidson Inc, claims to be the largest motorcycle group in the world with 320,000 members.</p>
<p>Events range from riding competitions to a &quot;Stud Your Duds&quot; demonstration of adding metal studs to leather clothes.</p>
<p>Gov. Angus King, who owns a Harley Dynaglide, had planned to participate in the parade but was kept at the statehouse in Augusta by legislative business. He still hoped to attend the rally Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;Why do I like to ride? It takes my mind off my work,&quot; said King, who sometimes goes riding with another Maine Harley-Davidson owner, the state supreme court chief justice.</p>
<p>Owners of other brands of motorcycles were noticeably absent from Portland streets in recent days, although a Honda motorcycle was spotted in HOG's impromptu street parking lot.</p>
<p>&quot;My dad's got the Harley. I'm going to get a real bike when I get the money,&quot; explained the owner, who then asked the reporter not to print his name.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTLAND, Maine"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
