<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="625530" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: No &quot;no smoking&quot; for Miami jury.</title>
<headline>No &quot;no smoking&quot; for Miami jury.</headline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The jury room in Miami's aged county courthouse normally is plastered with the typical range of anti-smoking signs found in public buildings, such as &quot;This is a NO SMOKING area,&quot; and simply &quot;No smoking.&quot;</p>
<p>But it won't be on Monday, when the first group of what eventually will be hundreds of potential jurors assembles and awaits selection in Broin vs. Philip Morris Cos Inc. et al, a landmark anti-tobacco case set to go to trial in the 1920s-era building next week.</p>
<p>&quot;I learned very early in my career 'Always check the jury room,'&quot; Dade County Circuit Judge Robert Kaye told a pre-trial hearing on Friday.</p>
<p>So he did, touring the jury room and noting the red signs adorning not just the room where jurors assemble and wait to be called, but also the only bathrooms available to them.</p>
<p>&quot;I intend to take those signs down,&quot; Kaye said. He envisioned the pool of jurors sitting in the jury room for hours on end surrounded by the placards. &quot;I don't want them to sit there and stare across the room (at the signs)... It could be prejudicial.&quot;</p>
<p>Jury selection, done in groups of 50 at a time, is expected to take days. Questionnaires have been prepared for 250 people.</p>
<p>Susan Rosenblatt, an attorney for the plaintiffs, an estimated 60,000 flight attendants who claim they were sickened by secondhand tobacco smoke, asked how the jurors would know they are not supposed to smoke if all the signs are removed.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm sure that someone will tell them,&quot; Kaye said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
