<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="625926" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: FUN IN BRUSSELS - JAZZ, TERVUREN, TROTT'ART.</title>
<headline>FUN IN BRUSSELS - JAZZ, TERVUREN, TROTT'ART.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>If you have time this weekend between barbecues, Brussels has plenty of music, art and exhibits on offer.</p>
<p>JAZZ MARATHON</p>
<p>On Friday through Sunday, the Brussels Jazz Marathon brings over 100 concerts to town in 50 cafes and three public squares. Full lists are available in any of the cafes.</p>
<p>Concerts in the Grand Place, Grand Sablon and Place Agora (where rue du Marche aux Herbes meets rue de la Montagne) are free. Among the best are....</p>
<p>Friday at 1700, Brazilian guitarist Flavio dell'Isola and his band are in the Sablon, followed at 2030 by Bab's All Stars, who play Louisiana cajun music. Later, Brazilian Marcia Maria appears at Place Agora at 2000 and Dutch saxophonist Candy Dulfer at 2100 in the Grand Place.</p>
<p>Flavio is back again on Saturday at 1300 in the Sablon. At the Grand Place, concerts start from 1500 on Saturday, with the Philippe Catherine quartet at 2100. Catherine is one of the best jazz guitarists around and is hugely popular in Brussels.</p>
<p>Among the best of the cafe concerts is Senegalese balafon (a xylophone-like instrument) player Emilien Sanou in Le Pantin, Matonge, Chaussee d'Ixelles 355.</p>
<p>PRACTICAL: You have to buy a 450 franc ticket at any of the cafes. In exchange, you get a bracelet, which gives you free access to all cafes and bars taking part. Marathon buses will cruise the city.</p>
<p>AVENUE DE TERVUREN</p>
<p>On Saturday, the Avenue de Tervuren, which links the Parc du Cinquantenaire to Tervuren, celebrates its 100th birthday. The entire avenue will be closed to traffic. The tram museum will be running its stock of vintage trams, there will be street parties and, in the evening, fireworks in the Parc de Woluwe at 2200. The Army Museum in the Jubelpark has an exhibition on the history of the avenue, closely linked to that of King Leopold II and Belgium's colonial past.</p>
<p>TROTT'ART BONIFACE</p>
<p>On Sunday, you can catch the 8th Ixelles' Trott'Art Boniface in the rue Ernest Solvay and rue Saint-Boniface.</p>
<p>Since 1994 this festival allows artists to exhibit and perform in the streets of the Boniface area, made famous by the Art Nouveau architect Ernest Blerot.</p>
<p>From 1100 onwards the streets are closed to traffic and will be filled with jazz, reggae, soul, pop or classical music, and new contemporary painters and sculptors.</p>
<p>The festival also has short-film projections and guided tours in the Art Nouveau houses. For children, there are workshops and animation.</p>
<p>PRACTICAL: Trott'Art is in the Boniface District, close to the Porte de Namur (Bus 34, 54, 71, 80 and subway). For more info, contact Animation Quartier Saint-Boniface, Tel. 513.51.34 or visit their site: www.netmania.be/netmania/trottart.</p>
<p>-- Geert De Clercq/Sybille de La Hamaide, Brussels Newsroom +32 2 287 6813, Fax +32 2 230 7710</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
