<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626167" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: &quot;Racist&quot; Canadian mountain to be renamed.</title>
<headline>&quot;Racist&quot; Canadian mountain to be renamed.</headline>
<dateline>CALGARY, Alberta 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Canadian provincial government must rename one of the Rocky Mountains after the name it had for more than a century was deemed racist.</p>
<p>The Western province of Alberta decided this week that Chinaman's Peak, near Banff National Park, would be given a new name after facing a mountain of criticism from its large Chinese community.</p>
<p>The mountain's original name dates back to 1896, when Ha Ling, a labourer for the Canadian Pacific Railway, scaled the 8,793 foot (2,680 metre) peak to win a $50 bet.</p>
<p>Provincial officials plan to research alternative names and elicit suggestions from local residents. They may sponsor a poll to rename the peak within the next year, said Merrily Aubrey, Alberta's geographical names programme co-ordinator.</p>
<p>Ha Ling's name has already been suggested for the peak.</p>
<p>Aubrey said there were no plans to change the names of other Alberta natural landmarks, which include Red Man Mountain, Stoney Squaw Mountain and White Man Pass. But they, too, could be renamed if enough people complained, she said.</p>
<p>The former Chinaman's Peak towers over the town of Canmore, Alberta, about 62 miles (100 km) west of Calgary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CALGARY, Alberta"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
