<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626313" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Political tensions overshadow Pope's Poland trip.</title>
<headline>Political tensions overshadow Pope's Poland trip.</headline>
<byline>Marcin Grajewski</byline>
<dateline>WROCLAW, Poland 1996-05-31</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul arrives in his homeland on Saturday for an 11-day visit overshadowed by political tensions between the Polish Church and a government dominated by ex-communists.</p>
<p>The Pope's pilgrimages to Poland during a 19-year pontificate have marked epochs in its long and difficult transition from communism to democracy.</p>
<p>His seventh trip takes place at the start of a wide-open general election campaign in which abortion and the role of the Church in the institutional life of the nation are key issues.</p>
<p>One of the Pope's first acts on Saturday, after reaching this southern industrial city, will be to confer with President Alexander Kwasniewski, an ex-communist who in common with some Catholic moderates says he wants to end the feud between the Church and leftists now in power.</p>
<p>Although he is 77, ailing and increasingly weak, John Paul will show himself in 12 cities during which masses and other events will be attended by an expected four million people.</p>
<p>For the Pope, a deeply emotional moment will be a visit to his parents' grave in Krakow where he was archbishop until his election in 1978.</p>
<p>Pilgrims of all ages from across Poland crowded into rainy Wroclaw, its sooty buildings brightened with Polish and Vatican flags, ahead of the Pope's arrival, some resigned to spending the night in the open as the city's population doubles.</p>
<p>Although the political activism of Poland's bishops irritates many Poles, some of the faithful gathering for the visit hoped the Pope would give unequivocal guidance for parliamentary elections due in September.</p>
<p>Jadwiga Dziwaltowska, a 54-year-old woman among the throng outside Wroclaw cathedral, said: &quot;I hope the Pope's visit will mobilise the nation ... ahead of the elections.&quot;</p>
<p>Warsaw schoolboy Antoni Nastelski, 16 and attending a papal visit for the first time, said: &quot;For many of my friends, Michael Jackson is their idol. For me, it is the Pope. My friends believe in Western, liberal values. I try to stick to my traditional Polish beliefs.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope is not expected to make overtly political statements but is unlikely to avoid commenting on the deeply controversial abortion issue about which he feels strongly.</p>
<p>Deep divisions have been fanned by the narrow adoption in a referendum this month of a new constitution, leaving open the possibility of abortion. The Church and its political allies strongly opposed the new charter.</p>
<p>Anti-abortion campaigners won fresh ground on Wednesday with a Constitutional Court ruling that the current liberal abortion legislation should be re-examined by parliament within six months.</p>
<p>With the ruling ex-communists and a pro-Church right-wing coalition led by the Solidarity union running almost level in pre-election polls, the Pope's words on this and other issues affecting current political debates will be carefully watched.</p>
<p>The Pope is more popular in Poland than the local Church partly because many Poles see him occupying a position above the country's political battleground.</p>
<p>The Church no long carries the authority among Poles it wielded during the Solidarity union's 1980s struggle for democracy which ended the communist stranglehold on power.</p>
<p>Despite erosion of their prestige, the bishops have become ever more outspoken since the return to government of the ex-communists in 1993.</p>
<p>Cardinal Josef Glemp, the Polish Primate, said on Thursday: &quot;Marxism as a system of government has passed, but people reared on Marxism remain, and in high places...the spirit of Marxism is rising over different public actions.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-05-31"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WROCLAW, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
