<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626369" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Poland torn over religious issues as Pope visits.</title>
<headline>Poland torn over religious issues as Pope visits.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland seethed with debate over abortion and the role of the Church on Friday as it prepared for the latest of Pope John Paul's visits to his homeland which have helped to define its recent history.</p>
<p>The 77-year-old Pope was to land in the western city of Wroclaw on Saturday and celebrate mass at the start of a gruelling journey around 12 towns and cities in 11 days, testing his resilience after a series of health problems.</p>
<p>His trip, the seventh since his momentous election in 1978, falls as society is riven over issues tied to religion in the prelude to elections due in September.</p>
<p>The pro-Catholic Solidarity trade union, whose struggle leading to the 1989 fall of communism was crucially heartened by the Pope's support, hopes his visit will boost the election chances of the rightist opposition alliance it heads.</p>
<p>The Solidarity Election Action (AWS) has printed hundreds of huge welcome posters of the Pope along with its own logo.</p>
<p>The government led by former communists -- now social democrats -- hopes the Pope will not explicitly involve himself in politics during the trip, unlike many Polish bishops who make their anti-government stance crystal clear.</p>
<p>&quot;Marxism as a system of government has passed, but people reared on Marxism remain, and in high places...the spirit of Marxism is rising over different public actions,&quot; Poland's Catholic Primate, Cardinal Jozef Glemp, said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The election campaign is tied up with current issues concerning religion, most crucially abortion.</p>
<p>Abortions were easily available under communism but in 1993 parliament imposed tough restrictions. To the Pope's anguish, a different parliament again liberalised the law last year.</p>
<p>In a bill which also provided easier contraception and sex education in schools, it allowed abortion on demand until the 12th week for women who are poor or face personal problems.</p>
<p>The Pope is certain to speak against abortion and this could help Solidarity, rivalling the ruling Democratic Left Alliance (SLD) in most opinion polls with 20-30 percent each.</p>
<p>The ex-communists, conscious that the Pope is more widely loved and respected than the Polish Church, hope any such statements will not be easily tied to party preferences.</p>
<p>&quot;Many will try to draw political benefits from the Pope's visit and we are aware that every word he says in Poland will have special weight,&quot; Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz, an ex-communist, told Spain's EFE news agency this week.</p>
<p>Anti-abortion campaigners got a boost on Wednesday from the Constitutional Tribunal which ruled that the liberalised rules clashed with Poland's fundamental law -- paving the way for a revision within six months or possibly a referendum.</p>
<p>The Church and its allies are also angered at delays imposed by leftist and sometimes stridently anti-clerical parliamentarians in ratifying a 1993 concordat treaty with the Vatican on such matters as religious education in schools.</p>
<p>The Pope's previous great pilgrimages to his homeland have been landmarks in the evolution of Poland's democracy.</p>
<p>In 1979 he lent heart to the opposition, which the following year gave birth to the Soviet bloc's first free trade union Solidarity, while in 1983 and 1987 his presence helped its recovery after the communists' 1981 martial law clampdown.</p>
<p>In 1991 the Pontiff warned Poles against letting moral decay and materialism mar their new freedoms.</p>
<p>For some Poles including liberals in the Church, this visit, expected to draw four million pilgrims, could help decide whether religious themes remain instruments of politics.</p>
<p>Every time the Pontiff returns to Poland he is conscious it could be his last visit, Vatican officials say, and this journey around the West and South may be charged with emotion.</p>
<p>The latter part is centred on Krakow, where the Pope was bishop and cardinal, and includes a visit to his parents' graves. He will also visit the Czestochowa shrine and give thanks to the Madonna for saving his life in a 1981 shooting.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
