<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626346" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Would-be Russian tsar to return for family ceremony.</title>
<headline>Would-be Russian tsar to return for family ceremony.</headline>
<byline>Alastair Macdonald</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's Romanov dynasty, all but extinguished in the Bolshevik revolution, begins a new chapter next month when Grand Prince Georgy, 16, is sworn in as head of the exiled imperial house at a ceremony in Russia.</p>
<p>With President Boris Yeltsin's republican officials said to be considering a form of legal recognition of the prince and the massacre of the last tsar's family now a fading memory, the biggest cloud over the plans for the event seemed to be the timimg of Georgy's school exams.</p>
<p>Officials from the Russian Nobility Assembly, whose members claim descent from the tsarist ruling class, told reporters on Friday the oath-taking ceremony may be held on June 21 in Kostroma, an ancient city 350 km (200 miles) north of Moscow.</p>
<p>But it might be delayed for a week or more because Georgy's exam schedule ahis school in Madrid is not yet certain.</p>
<p>&quot;It depends on Grand Prince Georgy Mikhailovich's exams,&quot; said Alexander Zakatov, a Nobility Assembly official and general secretary of the Russian Christian Monarchist Union.</p>
<p>He dismissed the idea that other claimants to the inheritance of Catherine the Great might take a dim view of the proceedings.</p>
<p>The Nobility Assembly, which claims the role of arbiter in such arcane matters, is firm in its view that the Romanov line must be headed by Georgy, whose great-grandfather was a cousin of the murdered last tsar, Nicholas II.</p>
<p>The nobles play down the political significance of the teenager's solemn pledge, part of a coming-of-age ceremony following his 16th birthday in March, to uphold the values of the Russian Orthodox Church and serve his country.</p>
<p>The ceremony marks his accession as head of his family but is only one of several visits to Russia in the past five years.</p>
<p>&quot;This is first and foremost a religious ceremony,&quot; said Stanislav Dumin, a historian and Nobility Assembly member. &quot;The imperial family...do not want what is a personal act between Georgy Mikhailovich and God to become a political event.&quot;</p>
<p>Zakatov said active discussions have been under way with the Kremlin on granting the imperial family some form of legal recognition to pave the way to Georgy's return to Russia with his mother and grandmother. But that did not mean Yeltsin was considering restoring the monarchy.</p>
<p>&quot;There is absolutely no question of that,&quot; Zakatov said, noting that even staunchly republican states, such as Italy, spelled out the legal status of their former monarchs.</p>
<p>&quot;The imperial family has no intention of thrusting itself on the Russian people. But it is ready to be of use to its motherland if the people want it,&quot; Zakatov said, repeating the position of the present head of the house, Georgy's mother Grand Princess Maria Vladimirovna.</p>
<p>The Kremlin has denied it is considering restoring the monarchy but the royal family insist it has had talks on being granted a special status to allow Georgy to live in Russia and attend a naval college once he finishes school in Spain.</p>
<p>If Russian government officials chose to attend the Kostroma ceremony -- in the same church where the first Romanov tsar, Mikhail, was crowned in 1613 -- it would only be as a mark of respect in their private capacities, Zakatov added.</p>
<p>Details on who might attend were not available but both officials said Yeltsin himself, who last year set aside an official residence for Princess Maria near Moscow, would not.</p>
<p>Zakatov denied reports that the head of the Russian Orthodox Church had refused to officiate at the ceremony.</p>
<p>Patriarch Alexiy had other commitments, Zakatov said. But he had given his blessing to the event.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
