<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626470" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>GUATEMALA: Artifact thieves take Guatemala church's archangel.</title>
<headline>Artifact thieves take Guatemala church's archangel.</headline>
<dateline>SAN GABRIEL SUCHITEPEQUEZ, Guatemala 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>For the first time in more than two centuries, when Mass is celebrated in San Gabriel Suchitepequez on Sunday it will not be under the gaze of the farming village's patron saint.</p>
<p>Thieves specialising in religious artifacts stole the statue of San Gabriel from the church in the village 190 miles (300 km) southwest of the capital on Tuesday night, authorities said.</p>
<p>&quot;This Sunday, we were going to celebrate Corpus Christi, but now we are mourning the loss of our patron saint,&quot; Francisco Alvarado, president of the Roman Catholic church committee, said on Friday.</p>
<p>The church caretaker discovered something amiss early on Wednesday and rang out the church bell to alert villagers. Thieves had removed a plastic skylight in the roof and, using a ladder, lowered themselves into the main nave, where the Archangel Gabriel was the centrepiece effigy. They then hauled the heavy statue back out through the roof.</p>
<p>Municipal employee Vicente Sacayon put the value of the wood, silver and gold statue dating back to the 18th century at up to $12,500. But its sentimental value is harder to quantify, Parish Priest Angel Ojoal said. &quot;In sentimental value, there are hundreds of years in San Gabriel,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The thieves also made off with antique wooden figures of the Christ child and Mary accompanying Joseph, statues used in the village's Easter week celebrations and processions. &quot;They left Joseph, left him a bachelor,&quot; Sacayon said.</p>
<p>The Institute of Anthropology and History in Guatemala's Culture Ministry has registered the theft of about 200 church items since 1979, of which perhaps five have been recovered, Luis Fernando Paniagua of the institute said.</p>
<p>Authorities strongly suspect the thefts are commissioned by collectors, often from outside the country.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GUAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN GABRIEL SUCHITEPEQUEZ, Guatemala"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GUATEMALA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
