<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626464" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: FEATURE - Circus on tightrope but Russian kids still love it.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Circus on tightrope but Russian kids still love it.</headline>
<byline>Alastair Macdonald</byline>
<dateline>IVANOVO, Russia 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>She flies through the air with the greatest of ease, but little Sveta, the 11-year-old baby of the Marchenko troupe, must work on her act if she is to make a career in the hard-up Russian circus.</p>
<p>Sveta wants to perform on the trapeze when she outgrows her lacy pink froufrou and, more importantly, gets too heavy for the elder Marchenkos to bounce her high into the air on the soles of their feet in their act's finale.</p>
<p>Lyudmila Marchenko, who runs the troupe with her husband Oleg, says Sveta has been encouraged to learn a whole range of other disciplines during three years on the road.</p>
<p>&quot;These days there are a lot of artists competing for jobs and there's not much money in Russian circus. You have to be adaptable,&quot; Lyudmila said backstage after a performance in Ivanovo, a depressed industrial city northeast of Moscow.</p>
<p>The theatre is one of dozens of purpose-built big tops scattered around Russia by Soviet leaders anxious to distract a circus-loving nation from the dreariness of everyday life.</p>
<p>Backstage it swarms with a menagerie of bears, tigers, horses, chickens, a llama and much else. A juggler calmly practises in a corner as the clowns, puffing fiercely on their cigarettes, work out new moves on their routine.</p>
<p>Out front, the band raucously accompanies every act, the spotlight picks out a slender girl turning somersaults on the high wire and several hundred youngsters, sticky buns and ice cream in hand, are having the time of their lives.</p>
<p>It is a sign of the times, however, that Sveta has spent half her brief career abroad, where the skills of the Russian circus draw in much bigger-money crowds than the 500 or so people who paid $2 each for the midweek show in Ivanovo.</p>
<p>&quot;We played to 80 full houses in Paris last year. Here people just don't have the money,&quot; grumbled Yuri, pausing to thump one of his agitated performing bears. &quot;Sometimes I wonder why we bother performing at all here. But we're a state troupe. We have to work. And at least the animals get to eat.&quot;</p>
<p>RUSSIANS' APPETITE FOR ESCAPIST FUN UNDIMMED</p>
<p>Alexei Yudin, director of the Ivanovo circus, one of 43 owned by the government's RosGosTsirkh (Russian State Circus) corporation, says the hardest part is keeping up the crumbling structure.</p>
<p>&quot;It's hard to keep up the building when we have to keep prices down because the city economy is doing badly.&quot;</p>
<p>Ivanovo, once home to the Soviet textile industry, has one of the highest unemployment rates in the country.</p>
<p>&quot;People don't have the money to spend on fun,&quot; Yudin said. &quot;It's a great shame. The circus is the best place to have fun.&quot;</p>
<p>Those people who do still manage to come, seem to agree.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the best culture Russia has,&quot; said Alla Kuzmina, treating grandchildren Viktoria, 6, and Pavel, 7, to distinctly unwholesome looking candy concoctions in the interval.</p>
<p>She remembers coming to the romantic old wooden circus as a child and now brings the youngsters to see every touring show in town -- meaning a trip to the circus every month or two.</p>
<p>&quot;It's much better than television,&quot; reckoned Ashot Sokhikyan, whose wide-eyed four-year-old daughter Zina is an avid fan of the animal acts and the clowns.</p>
<p>&quot;People forget what it's like but here they remember what it means to have atmosphere,&quot; said clown Adam, with an earnest maturity belying his 18 years and the fact he makes a living walking round with a live chicken on his head.</p>
<p>Few Western children would expect to see the circus more than once or twice a year, but RosGosTsirk ensures that its 10,000-odd state-employed artists are constantly touring its venues in Russia as well as starring in shows abroad.</p>
<p>&quot;We change the show all the time. The idea is to get people to come to the circus every month,&quot; Yudin said.</p>
<p>Non-afficionados might carp that one tightrope walker or juggler is much like another. But the real draw tends to be the animals. &quot;Last month it was sea lions,&quot; Yudin said. &quot;This month, it's tigers. They're generally the main attraction.&quot;</p>
<p>ANIMALS STILL BIGGEST DRAW IN RUSSIA</p>
<p>That emphasis on animals has seen circuses in the West come under criticism from animal welfare groups.</p>
<p>It is an experience that annoys Vladimir Shevchenko, tiger trainer and leader of the troupe on tour at Ivanovo.</p>
<p>&quot;Our animals are perfectly healthy. If they weren't happy they wouldn't reproduce would they?&quot; he said, still tense as he wound down in his dressing room after another night's work making tigers ride on horseback and lions roar with rage.</p>
<p>The tension is perhaps justifiable. He spent a week in hospital in March after a lion took a bite out of his leg.</p>
<p>&quot;It is dangerous. But it's worse if the animals hurt each other. There are always doctors for us. But where would I find a vet who knows tigers around here?&quot; he says, totally serious.</p>
<p>At least, though he complains bitterly about the paltry receipts in Russia, he does not face the same questions about the animals' welfare. It is simply not an issue here.</p>
<p>&quot;What else would we come to the circus for?&quot; said one puzzled young mother in the audience, when asked if the circus might be better without the captive big cats. &quot;The circus is the animals.&quot;</p>
<p>For all its money problems, a devoted and discerning public, modest but permanent state support and a steady flow of young new performers should see Russian circus into the next century.</p>
<p>&quot;We are all going through hardships, the circus no less than the rest of Russia. When people don't get paid, they don't go to the circus. But though we have our troubles we have successes too,&quot; said Galina Kirin, an official at RosGosTsirk in Moscow.</p>
<p>In Ivanovo, tumbling coach Lyudmila Marchenko was equally sanguine after a life spent under the big top: &quot; As long as youngsters like Sveta learn the trade, the circus will go on.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="IVANOVO, Russia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
