<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626723" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Tycoon Nadir threatens to sue British authorities.</title>
<headline>Tycoon Nadir threatens to sue British authorities.</headline>
<byline>Suna Erdem</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fugitive Turkish Cypriot tycoon Asil Nadir said on Friday his lawyers had prepared legal action against British authorities in connection with the collapse of his business empire.</p>
<p>Nadir, who is wanted for fraud in Britain, jumped bail four years ago after the collapse of his Polly Peck International fruit-to-electronics empire.</p>
<p>&quot;In the coming weeks I will have opened cases for compensation that will proceed very quickly at all levels,&quot; a sombre-looking Nadir told a news conference in Istanbul.</p>
<p>He later told Reuters the alleged wrongdoers included the Serious Fraud Office (SFO), Scotland Yard Staff, the London Stock Exchange and Inland Revenue.</p>
<p>Nadir told Reuters he was the victim of a plot motivated by a British and U.S. desire to force a solution on the divided island of Cyprus. He cited a report by British think tank.</p>
<p>&quot;Oxford Analytica...reaches the conclusion that if Polly Peck is destroyed then Turkey could compromise on the matter of Cyprus,&quot; said Nadir. &quot;It is all totally political.&quot;</p>
<p>Britain did not comment on the allegations or the legal action but urged the tycoon to return to London, saying he has nothing to fear from British justice.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Nadir is accused of serious fraud offences. It is imperative that he return to Britain to face them,&quot; Home Secretary (interior minister) Jack Straw said in a statement. &quot;This is the way Mr Nadir should seek to clear his name if he believes he has the evidence to do so.&quot;</p>
<p>Cyprus has been divided into Greek and Turkish sectors since Turkey invaded in 1974 in response to a coup engineered by the military junta then ruling Greece. Numerous international attempts to reconcile the two communities have failed.</p>
<p>Nadir said he was innocent and this was being proved in the courts.</p>
<p>Preparations for a trial of Nadir were thrown into chaos before he fled Britain when the authorities said they had discovered an attempt to pervert the course of justice. The charges were later found to be groundless.</p>
<p>In March, convictions against Nadir's former aide Elizabeth Forsyth were quashed but the SFO said it did not affect its case against Nadir.</p>
<p>Nadir told BBC radio on Friday he fled rather than face trial for theft and false accounting because he had no confidence in British justice. Nadir could not be extradited from northern Cyprus, which is recognised only by Ankara.</p>
<p>He said he would return to Britain if he had a guarantee he will not be arrested and the government held a public inquiry into the collapse of Polly Peck.</p>
<p>&quot;If I have an assurance to the government of Turkey that I will not be arrested...I'd be delighted to come back with a definite undertaking that there will be a public inquiry,&quot; he said. &quot;It is important for the British public to find out what actually went on.&quot;</p>
<p>Nadir, who holds a Turkish passport, flew to Istanbul on May 20 on his first trip out of his native Cyprus since he fled there from British justice four years ago.</p>
<p>Turkish police have said they will not hand Nadir over to British authorities. Britain and NATO ally Turkey do not have an extradition treaty but usually hand over criminal suspects to each other under a Council of Europe agreement.</p>
<p>Nadir told Reuters  he had served years of &quot;imprisonment&quot; in exile in Cyprus and paid a one billion pound sterling ($1.6 billion) &quot;fine&quot; in losses due to the collapse of Polly Peck.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
