<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626734" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish coalition partners begin polls meeting.</title>
<headline>Turkish coalition partners begin polls meeting.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkish Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan began a meeting with his coalition partner Tansu Ciller on Friday in bargaining about possible early elections to solve a government crisis over Islamist activism.</p>
<p>The talks, at Erbakan's official residence, started an hour later than planned but the reason for the delay was not immediately clear.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Ciller said on Thursday she would press Erbakan, modern Turkey's first Islamist leader, to make her prime minister in a caretaker government that would take the country to the polls.</p>
<p>Elections would normally be due by the year 2000.</p>
<p>The 11-month-old alliance between Erbakan and pro-Western Ciller has been crumbling under pressure from the secularist establishment, which sees Erbakan's Welfare Party as the source of an Islamist revival in officially secular Turkey.</p>
<p>An MP announced his resignation from Ciller's conservative True Path Party on Friday, robbing the government of its absolute majority in parliament.</p>
<p>The resignation reduces the number of government MPs to 275, one short of the absolute majority needed to win any vote of confidence at the 550-member assembly.</p>
<p>Erbakan and Ciller are set to swap jobs next year under a power-sharing deal that established their alliance last June. But Ciller says she can ward off anti-Islamist pressure on the government from the army if she takes the top job sooner.</p>
<p>The Turkish press said on Friday that Erbakan had agreed to hand over power to Ciller but that the pair disagreed on when new elections should take place.</p>
<p>The Hurriyet daily said Erbakan, whose party is facing closure in an anti-Islamist crackdown, wants to go to the nation in October while Ciller favours next March.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
