<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626769" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Earhart emulator faces lawsuit, fines in Texas.</title>
<headline>Earhart emulator faces lawsuit, fines in Texas.</headline>
<dateline>AUSTIN, Texas 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>The woman who completed the fateful around-the-world flight attempted by legendary aviator Amelia Earhart faces a lawsuit in Texas on allegations of neglect at a nursing home she owns, a state spokesman said on Friday.</p>
<p>Linda Finch, a 46-year-old San Antonio businesswoman, was sued after Texas health officials assessed potentially millions of dollars in fines over conditions in one of four nursing homes she owns with partners. The case is set for trial in September.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a lawsuit alleging violation of the health and safety codes,&quot; said Ward Tisdale, a spokesman with the state attorney general's office.</p>
<p>The suit stems from a May 1994 inspection that found several residents underweight and suffering from bedsores at the Dublin Nursing Home in Stephenville, about 50 miles (80 kms) southwest of Fort Worth, he said.</p>
<p>Finch said the findings were politically motivated to help then Gov. Ann Richards in her unsuccessful effort to win re-election, and told the Austin American-Statesman the nursing homes are a place where residents &quot;really feel like a family when they are there.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Over the past 24 years, my nursing homes have passed hundreds of inspections conducted by the Department of Human Services,&quot; Finch said in a statement released by her publicist.</p>
<p>&quot;In only one instance was one of my homes cited for serious deficiencies by the department. This occured three years ago and all deficiencies were corrected immediately and so documented by the department 10 days later,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The Texas Department of Human Services also sought civil penalties in March 1995 when a resident of a Finch nursing home near Austin died after allegedly failing to receive proper treatment for severe diabetes and a urinary tract infection.</p>
<p>&quot;If she's got money to buy an airplane and fly around the world, she's got money to hire another two or three aides&quot; at the nursing home, Essias Santa Ana, the youngest son of the man who died, told the newspaper.</p>
<p>Finch said Cruz Santa Ana, a diabetic, received regular blood tests at the nursing home but the tests were not documented by the staff. &quot;His death, however, was related to the infection and not to his diabetic condition,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Finch on Wednesday landed her 1935 Lockheed Electra 10E in Oakland, California, completing an around-the-world flight Earhart was attempting 60 years ago when she and a navigator disappeared near Howland Island in the Pacific Ocean.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AUSTIN, Texas"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
