<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626721" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish coalition plagued by defections, discord.</title>
<headline>Turkish coalition plagued by defections, discord.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Lyons</byline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's first Islamist-led government, reeling from months of attacks by the secularist elite, lost its absolute majority in parliament on Friday with the defection of a senior conservative MP.</p>
<p>Yildirim Aktuna, a member the junior coalition partner True Path Party (DYP), handed out copies of his resignation letter at a news conference and said he would submit it to party leader Tansu Ciller later in the day.</p>
<p>His decision, long anticipated, left the government of Islamist Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan clinging to just 275 seats in the 550-member parliament, one short of the majority needed to win a confidence vote. Two seats are vacant.</p>
<p>Erbakan held almost three hours of talks with Ciller late on Friday but the putative partners were unable to agree on True Path proposals for formation of an &quot;election government&quot; to lead the country to early polls.</p>
<p>&quot;We in the DYP have established that going to elections is the only solution,&quot; Ciller told reporters after the talks. &quot;We must act together with our partners and our work will continue in the coming days.&quot;</p>
<p>Erbakan left without comment to attend what remained of the annual Prime Minister's Cup football match at a city stadium.</p>
<p>&quot;The (Islamist) coalition partner is attempting to change the basic principles of the republic...and use religion as a political tool,&quot; said the dissident Aktuna, a former health minister well-known for his anti-Islamist views.</p>
<p>In a further twist of the knife, Aktuna said four more defections from True Path were in the pipeline, possibly as early as Monday. Four conservative MPs resigned over last weekend.</p>
<p>This latest blow to the coalition, already facing enormous pressure from the secularist armed forces and a court challenge to Erbakan's Islam-based Welfare Party, set the stage for tough bargaining between the coalition leaders.</p>
<p>The Istanbul Stock Exchange, which had widely expected Aktuna's departure, barely fluttered on the news. It later closed up 4.32 percent ahead of the Erbakan-Ciller meeting in active trade fuelled by liquidity, brokers said.</p>
<p>Ciller had promised her secularist, pro-Western party she would press Erbakan to make her prime minister in a caretaker government that would take the country to the polls in the coming months. Elections would normally be due by the year 2000.</p>
<p>The 11-month-old alliance between Erbakan, modern Turkey's first Islamist leader, and Ciller has been plagued by deep-set conflicts over the role of Islam in public life.</p>
<p>In February, top army officers demanded Erbakan approve and implement a package of 18 anti-Islamist measures, effectively a crackdown against his own grassroots voters.</p>
<p>These included the closing of Koranic education for young students, bans on Islamic-style clothing and tight restrictions on Islamist business and media.</p>
<p>Erbakan's subsequent foot-dragging set the government on a collision course with the secularist establishment led by the senior armed forces commanders, with pressure mounting by the day on True Path deputies to abandon the Islamists.</p>
<p>Erbakan and Ciller were set to swap jobs next year under their power-sharing deal.</p>
<p>But Ciller now says she can ward off anti-Islamist pressure on the government from the army if she takes the top job sooner.</p>
<p>That pressure was expected to increase further on Saturday when the National Security Council, dominated by the military, holds its next scheduled meeting to review progress in the anti-Islamist campaign.</p>
<p>It was a Council meeting on February 28, when demands for a crackdown were first foisted on Erbakan, starting the coalition on its downward spiral.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
