<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="626953" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: New Yorkers chasing $70 million lottery jackpot.</title>
<headline>New Yorkers chasing $70 million lottery jackpot.</headline>
<byline>Hagar Scher</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Yorkers from all walks of life Friday were lining up to buy tickets for this weekend's $70 million lottery, the third largest in the state's history.</p>
<p>The drawing of the winning numbers will take place Saturday at 11:21 p.m.</p>
<p>&quot;If I won, I'd probably pay off all my debt, all my friends' debt and all my family's debt,&quot; said Karen Iocca, an administrative assistant from New Jersey, who bought a handful of Lotto tickets Friday.</p>
<p>Queens computer consultant Shimon Lichtman, who says he has figured out a &quot;system&quot; for picking numbers that involves going diagonally down the ticket columns, took a similarly pragmatic view when asked what he would do if he hit it big.</p>
<p>&quot;Money brings power,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bobby Patel, manager of a cramped newsstand in a Manhattan office building, said he had sold about 15,000 Lotto tickets Friday. &quot;We had one winner a year and a half ago,&quot; he said. &quot;He came and shook my hand.&quot;</p>
<p>The odds of winning Saturday's drawing are 12.9 million to one, according to Ric Grenell, a spokesman for New York State Lottery. This lottery is the largest in North America, pulling in $4 billion in lottery game sales last year.</p>
<p>There are currently 250,000 compulsive gamblers in the state of New York, Laura Letson, a spokeswoman for the New York Council on Problem Gambling, said, placing New York behind only Louisiana in the prevalence of &quot;problem&quot; gambling.</p>
<p>&quot;The majority of people lose, many of whom lose big,&quot; Letson said. For most people, playing the lottery is a way to dream, but for some it can be a nightmare of debt, crime and ruined relationships, she added.</p>
<p>The biggest winner ever in the state's lottery history was Anthony Bueti, a Brooklyn resident who was the sole winner of a January 1990 jackpot of $35 million.</p>
<p>The largest lottery drawing was in January 1991 with a $90 jackpot; nine people split the winnings. In October 1994 a pot of $72.5 million was divvied up among four players. With both jackpots, five was one of the six numbers drawn, Grenell said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97912">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
