<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="627097" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Tony awards produce horse race for best musical.</title>
<headline>Tony awards produce horse race for best musical.</headline>
<byline>Christopher Michaud</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>If nothing else, the flood of mediocrity that washed over Broadway this spring has sparked a bit of genuine excitement: a real horse race for the Tony Awards' top honour, the coveted best musical prize.</p>
<p>Unlike so many past years, in which a mega-musical like &quot;Sunset Boulevard&quot; faced small, struggling or long-shuttered productions, this year the nominees include three shows all sharing mixed reviews and a shot at being named best musical.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the least-nominated of the big musicals just might take home the top honour. Broadway experts say &quot;Titanic,&quot; the season's most expensive production at $10 million, has taken a slight edge after early expectations that &quot;The Life,&quot; a tawdry tale of Times Square prostitutes that topped the Tonys with 12 nominations, would prevail.</p>
<p>If &quot;Titanic&quot; wins it will be an ironic take on David vs. Goliath. The bigger show managed only five Tony nominations.</p>
<p>But it may benefit from Tony voters' perception of it as the ambitious, high-minded and classy production. &quot;The Life,&quot; with its melodramatic rendering of drug addicted hookers, pimps and street hustlers double-crossing, beating and shooting each other, is far from a &quot;family&quot; show. It could turn off many out-of-town producers who are also Tony voters and are looking for a musical that will play in Peoria.</p>
<p>The other still-running nominee, &quot;Steel Pier&quot; -- &quot;Juan Darien: A Carnival Mass&quot; closed in January -- is probably the most traditional musical entertainment in the pack. Written by the Kander and Ebb team of &quot;Cabaret&quot; fame, it tells the tale of desperate hopefuls who dance themselves into physical exhaustion in Depression-era dance marathons.</p>
<p>&quot;Titanic&quot; and &quot;The Life&quot; both have fierce defenders and detractors, although few would bet the bank on which will capture the top honour.</p>
<p>After a season in which a revival of a 20-year-old show, &quot;Chicago,&quot; was the brightest spot, the Tonys' producers turned to a couple of big names to spark flagging interest in the awards -- Radio City Music Hall and Rosie O'Donnell.</p>
<p>O'Donnell, one of Broadway's biggest boosters, has been using her popular talk show to promote the Tonys, featuring nominees, clips and a plea to her audience to watch the show. And, for the first time, the awards are being presented somewhere other than a Broadway theatre -- at the giant Radio City Music Hall, allowing for bigger production numbers.</p>
<p>In another first, the show will be broadcast for three hours, the first hour on PBS and the final two hours on CBS, which is hoping to boost the show's dismal ratings with appearances by A-list stars such as Mary Tyler Moore, Glenn Close, Roseanne, Madonna, Christine Baranski, Matthew Broderick, Whoopi Goldberg, Martin Short and Julie Andrews.</p>
<p>For best play, critics expect Alfred Uhry's &quot;The Last Night of Ballyhoo,&quot; a comic drama of southern Jews in 1939, to win. Uhry's last play, &quot;Driving Miss Daisy,&quot; was wildly successful, and while David Hare's &quot;Skylight,&quot; a British import, was the critics' favourite and a hot ticket, it was a limited run that closed months ago.</p>
<p>The closest thing to a shoo-in is the acclaimed production of &quot;Chicago&quot; as best musical revival, which also stands to win Tonys for its stars Bebe Neuwirth and James Naughton and director Walter Bobbie.</p>
<p>Naughton could face stiff competition from Robert Cuccioli in the title role in &quot;Jekyll and Hyde,&quot; which was snubbed for best musical but remains popular with audiences. Naughton, who played a relatively small role in &quot;Chicago,&quot; is a Broadway favourite while Cuciolli is less well-known and has been tagged by some as having little stage presence.</p>
<p>Among plays, the best revival looks set to go to &quot;A Doll's House,&quot; as well as to Janet McTeer for her controversial, near-manic interpretation of Ibsen's heroine. The production should also win director Anthony Page a Tony, along with co-star Owen Teale for best featured actor.</p>
<p>Best actor in a play is a fairly good bet for veteran Christopher Plummer  for his one-man show &quot;Barrymore,&quot; in which he plays the late great actor John Barrymore.</p>
<p>Other good bets include Lillias White for featured actress in a musical -- as a tired, ageing hooker in &quot;The Life&quot; she delivers the show-stopping number &quot;The Oldest Profession&quot; -- and Andre DeShields, who had a similar moment with &quot;Rocks in My Bed&quot; in the now-closed &quot;Play On.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
