<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="627167" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Nobel Laureates launch campaign of disarmament.</title>
<headline>Nobel Laureates launch campaign of disarmament.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-05-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Five Nobel Peace Prize recipients, including the Dalai Lama, Tibet's exiled spiritual leader, called on the nations of the world on Thursday to curtail the transfer of weapons to repressive regimes.</p>
<p>&quot;In order to achieve general lasting world peace we need two kinds of disarmament -- internal and external,&quot; said the Dalai Lama, who won the prize in 1989 for his on-going, non-violent campaign for the autonomy of his Himalayan homeland. &quot;This has been a century of violence. The next century should be a century of dialogue.&quot;</p>
<p>The celebrated activists -- Holocaust survivor and writer Elie Wiesel, East Timor independence movement leader Dr. Jose Ramos Horta, Northern Ireland peace promotor Betty Williams and former Costa Rican President Dr. Oscar Arias -- joined the Dalai Lama in signing their self-authored &quot;International Code of Conduct on Arms Transfers.&quot;</p>
<p>The treaty, which has also been endorsed by former U.S. President Jimmy Carter, South African Archibishop Desmond Tutu and Polish politician Lech Walesa, stipulates that governments who abuse human rights, commit genocide or otherwise engage in aggression against other peoples would be barred from purchasing arms.</p>
<p>In addition, the code requires all governments to report their weapons purchases to the United Nations.</p>
<p>The covenant's supporters plan to lobby politicians worldwide to adopt it, but did not explain how the agreement would be enforced.</p>
<p>&quot;The time has come to introduce some ethical concerns into foreign policy matters,&quot; Wiesel told the audience of journalists and student activists gathered in the Cathedral of St. John the Divine.</p>
<p>The hall where the Nobel Prize recipients made their announcement was plastered with signs reading &quot;Boycott China's Goods&quot; and &quot;Independence for Tibet.&quot;</p>
<p>Many of the speakers criticised the U.S. government for consistently refusing to impose sanctions on China for its human rights abuses.</p>
<p>Clinton renewed China's status as a Most Favoured Nation (MFN) trade status on May 19, placing lower duties on Chinese exports to the United States.</p>
<p>Representative Cynthia McKinney, a Democrat from Georgia who moderated the event, said she would put pressure on the U.S. House of Representatives and Senate, as well as the Clinton administration, to sign on to the International Code.</p>
<p>&quot;We've had enough of the tyrants of the world inflicting pain on the common folk,&quot; she said. &quot;Our silence (has given them) a license to kill.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
