<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="627239" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FRENCH ELECTION - KEY PERSONALITIES.</title>
<headline>FRENCH ELECTION - KEY PERSONALITIES.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are brief portraits of French left-wing and centre-right figures likely to play a role in government if their parties win a June 1 parliamentary election runoff.</p>
<p>They are followed by thumbnail sketches of President Jacques Chirac and fellow Gaullist outgoing Prime Minister Alain Juppe, who has said he will stand down whatever the outcome.</p>
<p>----------------------</p>
<p>If the left wins:</p>
<p>Lionel JOSPIN, 59, would almost certainly be prime minister. He took over as leader of the Socialist Party from Francois Mitterrand on his election as president in 1981. Jospin held the post until 1988, when he became education minister. Disillusioned with the sleaze and drift of the late Mitterrand years, he left politics in 1992 but returned to become Socialist presidential candidate in 1995, winning 47.3 percent of the runoff vote. He took control of the party shortly afterwards.</p>
<p>Dominique STRAUSS-KAHN, 47, is the likely finance minister. The elegant &quot;DSK&quot; drafted the Socialist Party's economic policy and was its frontline spokesman on economic affairs. A believer in an active government industrial policy, he served as industry minister in 1991-93. A skilled debater with a sense of humour, he is married to star television interviewer Ann Sinclair.</p>
<p>Jacques DELORS, 71, would probably be a special adviser to Jospin on European affairs, without a cabinet post. The former European Commission president has acted as moral reference for the European credentials of Socialist leader Lionel Jospin in the campaign but has given no hint he is prepared to return to government. He was Socialist finance minister in 1981-84.</p>
<p>Martine AUBRY, 46, Delors' daughter, is tipped to be employment and/or social affairs minister. A former senior civil servant expert on employment policy, she was a respected labour minister in 1991-93. Sharp-minded and dynamic, she set up a Foundation for Action against Social Exclusion, working to bring the young unemployed and poor back into the world of work.</p>
<p>Michel ROCARD, 66, could be foreign minister. A leftist turned moderate social democrat, he earned Francois Mitterrand's enduring enmity for twice challenging him for the presidency. Mitterrand made him prime minister in 1988 but took revenge by firing him three years later. He briefly led the Socialist Party after its 1993 general election rout but was ousted a year later. He is a member of the French Senate and of the European parliament.</p>
<p>Elisabeth GUIGOU, 50, a possible Europe or social affairs minister, was a behind-the-scenes architect of France's European policy as personal adviser to Mitterrand. The cool, hard-working blonde was catapulted to prominence as European affairs minister at the time of the Maastricht Treaty. A skilled technocrat, she found it hard to communicate with ordinary voters.</p>
<p>Daniel VAILLANT, 47, a likely interior minister, is Jospin's closest ally and number two in the Socialist party. He gained expertise on urban safety and immigration after winning control of Paris's 18th district -- a hotbed of crime, prostitution and drug-use -- from the right in 1995. Vaillant managed Jospin's 1995 presidential campaign and has had the tough job of settling internal disputes in the faction-ridden party.</p>
<p>Bernard KOUCHNER, 57, tipped to return as health minister. The founder of the Medecins sans Frontieres medical charity stirs both admiration as the champion of refugees and war victims, and antipathy for his publicity-seeking. As minister of humanitarian action in 1991-93, he persuaded the United Nations to back the right to humanitarian intervention in civil wars.</p>
<p>Dominique VOYNET, 38, could be environment minister. The iron lady of France's Greens, she was the youngest candidate in the May 1995 presidential election. She became active in the ecology movement at age 18, campaigning against nuclear power, and was a co-founder of the Greens at 26. She advocates a major shift to public transport and rail haulage and away from motorway-building and private cars.</p>
<p>----------------------</p>
<p>If the ruling centre-right coalition is re-elected:</p>
<p>Philippe SEGUIN, 54, a socially-minded Gaullist would almost certainly be prime minister. The outgoing National Assembly speaker led the &quot;no&quot; campaign in France's 1992 referendum on the Maastricht Treaty on European union but says he would honour France's signature and wants to put the single currency to the service of employment. Social affairs minister in 1986-88, he supports a strong, protective state and regularly fulminates against the prevailing economic &quot;ultra-liberalism&quot;.</p>
<p>Alain MADELIN, 51, an irrepressible free-marketeer who was sacked as finance minister in 1995 after causing a furore by denouncing civil servants' &quot;privileges&quot;, is tipped to regain the finance portfolio as part of a &quot;dream ticket&quot; with Seguin. Before his brief period as finance minister, he was an energetic industry minister in 1986-88 and small business minister in 1993-95.</p>
<p>Charles PASQUA, 70, a hardline ex-interior minister, is tipped to return to the post. He earned hatred on the left and admiration, though little gratitude, on the right with tough laws to curb immigration. A blustering and charismatic Gaullist, Pasqua was one of the Right's most controversial figures until he fell from power in 1995.</p>
<p>Nicolas SARKOZY, 42, went into political exile after being the spokesman for ex-premier Edouard Balladur's unsuccessful 1995 presidential campaign against Jacques Chirac, the eventual winner. A skilled debater with a quick wit and sharp tongue, he became one of France's youngest cabinet members ever in 1993 when he was named budget minister at the age of 38.</p>
<p>Francois LEOTARD, 55, is tipped to return as defence or foreign minister. The leader of the centre-right UDF, junior partner in the ruling coalition, he has been nicknamed the &quot;French Clinton&quot; because of his media skills and ambition. An economic liberal and strong supporter of European integration, he served as culture minister in 1986-88 and defence minister in 1993-95 before backing Balladur's presidential bid and going down with him.</p>
<p>----------------</p>
<p>JACQUES CHIRAC, 64, a Gaullist, reached the goal of a 30-year career by winning the presidency over Socialist Lionel Jospin in May 1995, after two failed bids in 1981 and 1988.</p>
<p>His decision to call a snap election fits his image as a fighter who loves challenges. The gamble could ensure smooth sailing for the five remaining years of his seven-year term, or doom his presidency by making him a lame duck prematurely.</p>
<p>A graduate of the elite civil service school, Chirac entered government at 34 under his mentor, General Charles de Gaulle, making his mark as a farm minister. He became prime minister at 41 and resigned two years later in 1976.</p>
<p>The founder of the Gaullist Rally for the Republic (RPR) in 1976, he was elected mayor of Paris in 1977. He split the right-wing vote in his first presidential bid, helping ensure the election of the late Socialist Francois Mitterrand.</p>
<p>When the centre-right won 1986 parliamentary elections, he became prime minister in an unprecedented power sharing with Mitterrand who beat him to the presidency in 1988.</p>
<p>As president, he weathered a worldwide furore by ordering a final series of nuclear tests. Elected on promises to curb high uemployment, he soon turned around to order budget austerity to ensure France's entry into the single European currency in 1999.</p>
<p>He also abolished conscription, shook up the armed forces and moved France closer to the NATO alliance, while challenging U.S. dominance in European security and the Middle East.</p>
<p>--------------</p>
<p>ALAIN JUPPE, 51, set records as the least popular prime minister in France's Fifth Republic after starting with a record approval rating for a new premier when the newly-elected Chirac appointed him in May 1995.</p>
<p>Juppe accepted responsibility for the centre-right's dismal showing in the May 25 first round of voting and announced the following day that he would resign on June 2, whatever the outcome of the decisive second round.</p>
<p>A man with a brilliant brain but the image of an unfeeling technocrat, he remains president of the Gaullist RPR party founded by Chirac and mayor of Bordeaux.</p>
<p>Juppe incurred public anger and triggered labour unrest with an austerity drive to cut public deficits to three percent of gross domestic product to qualify for a European monetary union.</p>
<p>His plan to curb welfare spending and overhaul the loss-making SNCF state railway sparked a 24-day public service strike in November and December 1995. He maintained the core reforms but abandoned plans to make civil servants work longer for a full pension.</p>
<p>He increased the tax burden by some 120 billion francs to a record 45.7 percent of gross domestic product in his first 15 months in office, but has since begun a five-year programme of income tax cuts, abolishing dozens of special exemptions.</p>
<p>His privatisation efforts have had mixed success.</p>
<p>A highly respected foreign minister in 1993-95, Juppe joined Chirac as a speechwriter in 1976 and served as budget minister in his 1986-88 government before becoming RPR secretary-general.</p>
<p>His image of integrity suffered over 1995 revelations that he had obtained luxury city-owned apartments for himself and family members at below-market rents when Chirac was mayor of Paris and he was finance director.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
