<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="627338" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEPAL: Everest climber evokes grandfather's feat.</title>
<headline>Everest climber evokes grandfather's feat.</headline>
<byline>Gopal Sharma</byline>
<dateline>KATHMANDU 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tashi Tenzing, grandson of one of the first men to scale Mount Everest, said on Friday his grandfather was on his mind last week when he was standing atop the world's highest peak.</p>
<p>&quot;I had tears in my eyes because I was thinking of him and I was becoming emotional and proud of being his grandson,&quot; Tenzing told Reuters on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;It was something spiritual to me.&quot;</p>
<p>Tenzing, 32, reached the 8,848-metre (29,028-foot) Everest summit on May 23, six days ahead of the 44th anniversary of the first ascent of Mount Everest.</p>
<p>His grandfather, Tenzing Norgay Sherpa, and New Zealand's Sir Edmund Hillary were the first climbers in the world to conquer the peak, on May 29, 1953.</p>
<p>&quot;I was hoping also to climb on May 29 but could not take a risk if the weather went bad,&quot; Tenzing said, speaking in a mixture of English and Nepali.</p>
<p>He said his grandfather had inspired his love for mountains.</p>
<p>&quot;He wanted us to enjoy the mountains,&quot; Tenzing said.</p>
<p>The stout, soft-spoken climber arrived in the Nepali capital on Thursday after descending from Everest and was preparing to leave over the weekend for Australia, where he now lives.</p>
<p>His Nepali grandfather, who settled in the northeastern Indian town of Darjeeling and ran a climbing college, died in May 1986. Tenzing's parents still live in India.</p>
<p>Tenzing said he planned to work as a climbing instructor in Australia and train scientists and researchers in techniques for walking on glaciers in Antarctica.</p>
<p>Hillary's son, Peter, was the first son of an Everest conqueror to scale the peak, on May 10, 1990. Tenzing was the first grandson of an Everest mountaineer to climb the mountain.</p>
<p>More than 700 people from 43 countries have scaled Everest, 90 more than once. A total of 154 climbers have died on the mountain.</p>
<p>A devout Buddhist, Tenzing said he left a six-inch (15-cm) bronze statue of the Buddha on the peak to mark his ascent the day after Buddha Jayanti, Buddha's birthday.</p>
<p>&quot;It will give a message of peace and compassion to everyone from the top of the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tenzing said he had no plans to return to the world's highest peak.</p>
<p>&quot;It's enough. I have watched the whole view under my feet from the top and I don't want to go and spend time at the mountain again,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NEPAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KATHMANDU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEPAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
