<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="627894" id="root" date="1997-05-30" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Row as HK rejects Danish artist's &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot;.</title>
<headline>Row as HK rejects Danish artist's &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Carrie Lee</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-05-30</dateline>
<text>
<p>Democracy campaigners said on Friday local authorities had thwarted efforts to display a Danish sculptor's &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot;, just weeks before China takes over Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Carver Jens Galschiot said he was surprised at the rejection of his &quot;fight for freedom&quot; monument, portraying 50 human bodies twisted into an eight-metre high pillar symbolising oppression.</p>
<p>Civic chiefs turned down three applications by the Hong Kong Alliance in Support of Democratic Movements in China to display the pillar in public parks, the group said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is an act of suppression of freedom of speech and expression,&quot; said Szeto Wah, leader of the Alliance and a prominent pro-democracy legislator.</p>
<p>&quot;I recall the sculpture's creator has said that the Pillar of Shame is put in a place to test how far the authorities can tolerate human rights and freedom,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The rejection of the three applications proves that many works of art are politcally censored here even though Hong Kong has yet to return to China,&quot; Szeto said.</p>
<p>Some local councillors debating the application were quoted on Friday as saying the statue was &quot;terrible.&quot; One said it would have got approval if it had shown &quot;a beautiful girl.&quot;</p>
<p>China retakes the British colony of 6.4 million people at midnight on June 30. There's a mood in the media and some business and political quarters to avoid angering Beijing.</p>
<p>&quot;I was a little bit surprised,&quot; the Danish artist said. &quot;They have maybe a threat from Beijing's reaction,&quot; he told a news conference on arrival in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Galshiot seeks to display the pillar in countries he thinks face political oppression.</p>
<p>The artist said the sculpture, scheduled to arrive on Saturday after a five-day shipment delay, was aimed at protecting freedoms.</p>
<p>&quot;I am sure it will get a place in Hong Kong, somewhere,&quot; he said. &quot;People will go there and look at it and say, okay, this is our kind of freedom and expression, symbol of the Hong Kong city today. We don't want to lose our rights here.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked on the outlook for human rights in Hong Kong after the handover, the artist said: &quot;If I lived in Hong Kong, I would be really glad for a foreign passport.&quot;</p>
<p>Szeto said the alliance would continue to seek a place for the sculpture &quot;for it to witness the human rights conditions here after July 1&quot;.</p>
<p>Galchiot wants to re-assemble the sculpture on June 3 in a city park just before annual ceremonies to remember victims of Beijing's 1989 Tiananmen Square killings when Chinese troops crushed a student pro-democracy movement.</p>
<p>Public concern is rising over a possible cut in freedom. Future Hong Kong leader Tung Chee-hwa has launched plans, inspired by China's parliament, to curb civil liberties after the handover, with a ban on foreign political funding and new limits on the right to protest.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-05-30"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-05-30"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
