<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="630232" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Pope wants to lead Church into 21st century.</title>
<headline>Pope wants to lead Church into 21st century.</headline>
<byline>Robert Bogdanski</byline>
<dateline>GORZOW, Poland 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul, at an open air mass that evoked outpourings of emotion, confided to his countrymen on Monday that he had a mission to lead the Church into the next century.</p>
<p>The frail 77-year-old Pontiff looked close to tears as 300,000 pilgrims responded to his words with chants of &quot;we will help you&quot; and broke into the traditional Polish anthem of &quot;Sto Lat&quot; wishing him 100 years of life.</p>
<p>John Paul, believed to be suffering from Parkinson's disease, said he was visiting Poland to draw the strength from his native soil to fulfill his task.</p>
<p>Addressing a mass in Gorzow, he said the late Cardinal Stefan Wyszynski, a hero of Catholicism's struggle to survive under Polish communism, told him immediately after his 1978 election as pope: &quot;Now you must lead the Church into the Third Millennium.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope added: &quot;That is why I came to Poland ... I am here to ask, as I walk on the road to the millennium, for the grace to be able to fulfill the task which God put before me ... so you have to beg God on your knees that I will be able to meet this challenge.&quot;</p>
<p>His call was followed by a spontaneous outbreak of mingled emotion, support and nostalgia during which the Pope recalled youthful holidays in the Gorzow region and said:</p>
<p>&quot;The land in this area is beautiful ... memories of this land will stay with me for ever.&quot;</p>
<p>Despite concerns about his age and frailty and his ability to cope with ths strains of an 11-day pilgrimage, the Pope has seemed to draw vigour from his return to his homeland.</p>
<p>In Legnica and Gorzow on the third day of the visit, he spoke in a strong, clear voice at two long religious services.</p>
<p>Voicing concern for the moral condition of the country, he painted a bleak picture of life for the economic orphans of post-communist prosperity, saying many suffered poverty, homelessness and unemployment.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pope will speak out -- and he cannot fail to speak out -- on social problems because here man is involved, concrete individuals,&quot; John Paul told worshippers during mass at a former Soviet airbase near Legnica.</p>
<p>The crowd gave him a welcome reminiscent of the emotional masses he held during earlier pilgrimages to Poland, starting in 1979 when the country was still firmly under communist sway.</p>
<p>The Pope lamented that the breathless pace of capitalism since democracy was restored in 1989 was leaving many victims in its wake with a widening gap between the new rich, who have seized economic opportunities, and the poor.</p>
<p>&quot;Every day we become aware of how many families are suffering from poverty,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Pope said single mothers were struggling to raise their children, elderly people were being abandoned and many Poles had been made unemployed by industrial and economic restructuring.</p>
<p>&quot;On the streets and in the squares, the number of homeless people is increasing. I cannot pass over in silence the present long list of all these brothers and sisters ...&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He called on the nation's politicians &quot;to establish appropriate laws and guide the national economy in such a way that these painful phenomena of social life find a proper solution.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pope appealed to Poland's new entrepreneurs not to treat workers as mere tools of production.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GORZOW, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
