<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="630246" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Pope and presidents celebrate &quot;European&quot; martyr.</title>
<headline>Pope and presidents celebrate &quot;European&quot; martyr.</headline>
<byline>Phil Pullella</byline>
<dateline>GNIEZNO, Poland 1996-06-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul and five European countries once divided by the Iron Curtain will on Tuesday mark the martyrdom 1,000 years ago of an ecumenical saint whose life symbolised the continent's unity.</p>
<p>The presidents of Poland, Lithuania, Slovakia and Hungary, all of which have been striving for membership of the European Union since the 1989-90 fall of communism, will join the Pope and German President Roman Herzog to celebrate St Adelbert in Gniezno.</p>
<p>Adelbert is an icon of an undivided Europe in medieval times whose significance has bloomed since the end of the Cold War, whose demise the Pope is credited with helping to hasten.</p>
<p>Germany, the west European country with the closest historic ties to east Europe, is keen to see the former communist nations admitted to the EU to cement their transition to democracy.</p>
<p>A mass in Gniezno in western Poland, followed by a private meeting between the 77-year-old Pontiff and the presidents, will be held on the fourth day of his latest pilgrimage to his homeland.</p>
<p>Two distinct themes have emerged from the start of John Paul's seventh visit to his homeland as Pope - his desire to lead the Church into the next century and a crusade to uphold humanitarian moral values over free-market materialism.</p>
<p>Although the Polish church is struggling to maintain its historic influence in the country's life, pilgrims at open air masses have also reaffirmed the deep personal affection and reverence in which John Paul is held.</p>
<p>Frail and believed to be suffering from Parkinson's disease, the Pope told an open air mass for 300,000 people in Gorzow on Monday that the late Cardinal Stefan Wyszynski, his spiritual mentor, had urged him to &quot;lead the Church into the Third Millennium.&quot;</p>
<p>John Paul added: &quot;You have to beg God on your bended knees that I will be able to meet this challenge.&quot;</p>
<p>His words were greeted with a torrent of emotion during which the crowd chanted, &quot;We will help you,&quot; and the Pope seemed close to tears.</p>
<p>Visibly tired and weak at the start of his pilgrimage, John Paul has appeared to gather energy with each day spent in Poland and told worshippers that his return was intended to let him draw strength from his native soil.</p>
<p>Surrounded by the visible signs of Poland's new prosperity since democracy was restored in 1989, the Pope appealed to political and business leaders to protect the needy from the harsher aspects of capitalism.</p>
<p>&quot;Every day, we become aware of how many families are suffering from poverty,&quot; he said. &quot;On the streets and in the squares, the number of homeless people is increasing. I cannot pass over in silence the long list of all these brothers and sisters...&quot;</p>
<p>In a wider message, the Pope has also called on rich countries to share the world's plentiful food to &quot;end the plague of hunger.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LITH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GNIEZNO, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
