<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="630622" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK charities plan &quot;dress Chinese&quot; fundraiser.</title>
<headline>HK charities plan &quot;dress Chinese&quot; fundraiser.</headline>
<byline>Mishi Saran</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's largest charity grouping and an up-market fashion retailer on Monday urged everybody to get into the spirit of things when Hong Kong reverts to Beijing -- by dressing Chinese.</p>
<p>The Community Chest and Shanghai Tang, a retailer of up-market traditional Chinese clothing styles adapted to modern times, plan to cash in on China fever and handover exuberance to raise mountains of money. Shanghai Tang has launched a publicity drive for traditional style Chinese fashions this year with Chinese movie screen goddess Gong Li as its icon.</p>
<p>The Community Chest, more noted for fundraising events such as charity walks, is urging office-goers to wear traditional Chinese clothes on July 3, Hong Kong's first working day under Chinese rule, and at the same time to make a contribution to charity. Hong Kong reverts to China on midnight June 30, and the following two days are public holidays. Hong Kong people are invited to wear stylish cheungsams and jackets in the style of the 10th century Tang Dynasty, a golden era of Chinese civilisation, and send in donations to the charity.</p>
<p>&quot;People might cheat a bit, it's difficult to get Chinese underpants,&quot; said David Tang, co-organiser of the campaign and the head of retro-Chinese clothing store Shanghai Tang. Tang, who is aiming to raise a &quot;good few million (Hong Kong dollars)&quot; said he hoped around 20 to 25 percent of the workforce would go to their offices in Chinese-style clothing on July 3.</p>
<p>Shanghai Tang has underwritten the campaign's advertising costs and heart-throb singer Andy Lau has lent the copyright to his handover song, &quot;Chinese&quot;. &quot;Everything fits like a jigsaw, Shanghai Tang's Chinese clothes, Andy Lau's 'Chinese' song, and the Community Chest raising money for charity on a day which I should imagine being Chinese would be uppermost in people's minds,&quot; Tang said.</p>
<p>Andy Lau, sporting a jade-green suit, said his solemn song &quot;Chinese&quot; was about 5,000 years of Chinese history. &quot;Dress Chinese Day is a special occasion on which the community of Hong Kong can demonstrate an important aspect of Chinese culture and heighten the awareness of Chinese heritage,&quot; a press release said. China has pushed the message that the handover will be a great moment of pride for the Chinese nation, ending 156 years of national humiliation -- the period that Hong Kong has been a British colony.</p>
<p>The vast majority of Hong Kong's 6.4 million people are Chinese.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
