<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="630720" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: Egypt rights group slams book confiscation.</title>
<headline>Egypt rights group slams book confiscation.</headline>
<byline>Miral Fahmy</byline>
<dateline>CAIRO 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Egyptian human rights group said on Monday the research academy of one of Islam's most prestigious institutions had intimidated intellectuals by demanding the confiscation of 50 books.</p>
<p>The independent Egyptian Organisation for Human Rights (EOHR) said in a statement police had confiscated 50 titles after a report by the Islamic Research Academy of al-Azhar said they &quot;contradicted public morals, mocked religions and criticised the prophets&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the first time that the police have confiscated such a large number of books at a time on the basis of a report by the al-Azhar Islamic Research Academy,&quot; EOHR said.</p>
<p>&quot;The institution has gone so far as to try to impose its religious guardianship on the conscience of intellectuals, writers and artists, to confiscate books and intimidate those who oppose it.&quot;</p>
<p>It added that this was not the first time books had been confiscated based on the research academy's reports.</p>
<p>EOHR named some of the book titles as &quot;The Rabbaba (string instrument) songs on the Companions of Prophet Mohammed&quot; and &quot;The Yathreb Society in Mohammedan Era&quot; by lawyer Khalil Abdel-Karim.</p>
<p>It said other books were confiscated because the al-Azhar report said they included nude pictures and incited immorality.</p>
<p>&quot;EOHR condemns the report which demanded the confiscation of the 50 books and considers this measure a gross violation of the freedoms of opinion and expression, thought, belief and academic research,&quot; the group said.</p>
<p>Al-Azhar is Sunni Islam's most prestigious seat of learning. Another unit of the institution, the Azhar Front for Scholars (AFS), raised the ire of rights groups and intellectuals last month after it branded Egyptian philosophy professor Hassan Hanafi an apostate because his writings &quot;insulted Islam&quot;.</p>
<p>Mohamed Sayyed Tantawi, the liberal Grand Sheikh of al-Azhar, said in a recent interview that no one had the right to call another person an apostate and belittled the importance of the AFS, saying it only had two members who had no authority to pass judgement.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
