<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="630873" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Trumpet great &quot;Doc&quot; Cheatham dies.</title>
<headline>Trumpet great &quot;Doc&quot; Cheatham dies.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jazz trumpeter Adolphus &quot;Doc&quot; Cheatham, who played with such legends as Benny Goodman and Billie Holiday and later had a long solo career, died on Monday from a stroke. He was 91.</p>
<p>The jazz great died at George Washington University Hospital, a spokeswoman for the hospital said.</p>
<p>Cheatham recently released an album with Nicholas Payton, a 23-year-old trumpet player from New Orleans, titled &quot;Doc Cheatham &amp; Nicholas Payton&quot; and he completed a three-night stand at Blues Alley in Washington on Saturday night.</p>
<p>On Sunday morning, he suddenly felt ill, his manager, Vernon Hammond, said, adding that during his final performance Cheatham &quot;played very well. He was very pleased.&quot;</p>
<p>Cheatham failed to appear as scheduled at his weekly brunch gig at Sweet Basil in New York's Greenwich Village on Sunday, a show he had played for 17 years.</p>
<p>He was born outside Nashville, Tennessee, on June 13, 1905. Originally a soprano saxophonist, he became a featured trumpet player in big bands beginning in 1948. As a section player, he performed with such icons as Benny Goodman, Billie Holiday and Cab Calloway before a solo career that began when he was in his 60s.</p>
<p>&quot;He had a sense of curiousity rare in someone that age,&quot; said James Browne, musical director at Sweet Basil.</p>
<p>Cheatham's recordings include &quot;The Fabulous Doc Cheatham&quot; and &quot;The 87 Years of Doc Cheatham,&quot; released by Columbia Records in 1993 as part of a pioneers of jazz series.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
