<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="631016" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Search of river continues for U.S. singer Buckley.</title>
<headline>Search of river continues for U.S. singer Buckley.</headline>
<dateline>MEMPHIS, Tenn. 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Folk-rock singer Jeff Buckley was presumed dead on Monday, four days after he disappeared while swimming near the Mississippi River, authorities said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are still patrolling the area with our harbour control units,&quot; Memphis Police Lt. Richard True said. &quot;There's some current there and his body could have been pushed downstream.&quot;</p>
<p>Buckley, 30, was swimming off a marina on Thursday night when he disappeared underneath the surface after a boat passed. A friend on shore who lost sight of him reported him missing.</p>
<p>According to the latest issue of Billboard magazine, published before his disappearance, Buckley was in Memphis to record a new album that was scheduled to be released in early 1998.</p>
<p>Buckley emerged from the shadow of his late musician father Tim Buckley when he released his full-length debut album &quot;Grace&quot; on Columbia Records in 1994.</p>
<p>Critics heaped praise on Buckley, who was the only child from a brief marriage between the then-unknown singer and his teenaged bride, Mary.  Father and son met only once, spending a week together just two months before Tim died of a heroin and morphine overdose in June 1975, aged 28.</p>
<p>Buckley's music, which he launched on the New York club scene in 1991, was described as a fusion of underground, rock, folk and jazz, with influences including Bob Dylan and Van Morrison.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEMPHIS, Tenn."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
