<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="631222" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India urged to allow coffee imports to hold prices.</title>
<headline>India urged to allow coffee imports to hold prices.</headline>
<byline>Hari Ramachandran</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>India should allow free coffee imports to stabilise domestic prices that spurted after world coffee prices hit new highs and to bring out hoarded stocks, dealers said on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;The government should allow free imports of coffee to prevent hoarding and stabilise prices,&quot; said R.P. Sarathy, president of the All India Coffee Merchants' Association (AICMA).</p>
<p>India, which exports bulk of its coffee, has freed coffee trade from the five decade old marketing controls in the last four years. It allows free exports of coffee but does not permit imports.</p>
<p>Sarathy told Reuters by telephone from the southern city of Salem that traders were not keen to raise prices of coffee since it would hit domestic sales and add to their overheads.</p>
<p>He said AICMA had been forced to raise coffee prices by 10 rupees per kg a month since January due to high world prices.</p>
<p>&quot;On June 9 we will raise the price of pure coffee arabica grade by 10 rupees to 200 rupees per kg,&quot; Sarathy said.</p>
<p>Philipose Matthai, chairman of the state-run Coffee Board, said in the short term people were happy because they were making a killing from high global prices.</p>
<p>&quot;If the coffee drinking habit is blunted it is not good for the future,&quot; he said. &quot;What goes on very high can also come down with a thud.&quot;</p>
<p>Matthai said in New Delhi, after holding talks with commerce ministry officials on domestic coffee prices, traders were withholding coffee and if the situation went out of hand, as appeared likely, the government would have to intervene.</p>
<p>London robusta coffee futures tumbled in early trade on Monday with benchmark July opening a sharp $270 down to $2,200 per tonne as the market took a sharp reverse from last week's spectacular rally. By the end of the morning July was down further at $2,170.</p>
<p>The slide followed a steep 12-percent fall in New York on Friday on frantic speculative selling.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a sharp fall in Friday's trading...when markets get overheated like this it happens,&quot; said Arun Bidappa, chief executive of the Karnataka Coffee Brokers Pvt Ltd.</p>
<p>But he said the market would be strong for the remaining part of the year since there was not enough coffee available and the winter season would be starting in Europe.</p>
<p>Bidappa said coffee prices would stay around 20 year highs.</p>
<p>&quot;The only danger people foresee is bad weather in Brazil, then anything could happen,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bidappa said there were some indications that the government might take some action.</p>
<p>&quot;We have said free imports of coffee will not hurt the domestic producers,&quot; Bidappa said.</p>
<p>But Matthai said no action was being contemplated at present. He declined to go into details.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100137">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
