<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="632377" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Giant HK lanterns might get stuck in Pearl River.</title>
<headline>Giant HK lanterns might get stuck in Pearl River.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>A fleet of giant lanterns in the shape of pandas and other animals will sail from China to Hong Kong on barges to mark the territory's handover to Chinese control on July 1, but their size could leave them stuck on the Pearl River.</p>
<p>Storms could raise water levels in the river during the 20-hour voyage from Jiangmen in Guangdong province so that some of the lanterns would be unable to pass under bridges, the South China Morning Post newspaper said on Monday.</p>
<p>The tallest lantern, a 10.7 metre (35 feet) horse, would not make it through even if water levels remained constant, it said.</p>
<p>Technicians planned to tilt the barges by loading ballast on one side so the lanterns could squeeze under a low bridge 16 km (10 miles) from Jiangmen, it said.</p>
<p>The flotilla, including other symbols regarded as lucky by the Chinese such as peacocks, dolphins and goldfish, would leave Jiangmen shipyard on June 14 covered to protect them from the weather, often wet and stormy at this time of the year.</p>
<p>Hong Kong, a British colony for 156 years, reverts to China at midnight June 30. Many colourful celebrations are planned, including the giant lanterns, which will be paraded through Hong Kong harbour during a fireworks display on July 1.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
