<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="632500" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: FEATURE-Wartime birthday party venue in decay.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Wartime birthday party venue in decay.</headline>
<byline>Barry May</byline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>Franklin Roosevelt wished Winston Churchill happy birthday and Joseph Stalin joined in the fun.</p>
<p>What a birthday party! What a setting!</p>
<p>Churchill would splutter on his cigar to see it now.</p>
<p>The residence of the British Legation in Tehran, venue of Churchill's 69th birthday party in 1943, is nowadays a sad shadow of its former grandeur.</p>
<p>A wildly luxuriant Wistaria has damaged the structure, mortar is crumbling and, within, ornate plaster is in need of restoration. The roof needs attention and the guttering too.</p>
<p>The clock in the bell-tower, built by the same company that made London's Big Ben, has not struck in years.</p>
<p>The residence, built in 1870 during Iran's Qajar period, wears an air of grimy neglect like an aged aunt who can no longer afford to look after herself properly.</p>
<p>Local restorers have examined the fabric and an expert is due from London next week. The cost of restoration runs to 400,000 pounds ($650,000) for a proper job, one of the few diplomats left at what is now the British Embassy told Reuters.</p>
<p>The leaders of the three main allied powers fighting Nazi Germany met at the Tehran Conference for the first time. Subsequent meetings were at Yalta and Potsdam.</p>
<p>The British prime minister had met the American president in Cairo, but it was the Soviet supremo's first visit outside his country since he assumed power some two decades earlier.</p>
<p>Substantive meetings at the Tehran Conference were held across the street in the Soviet Embassy. They settled the date and scale of the Anglo-American landing in France and an associated Soviet offensive, and determined resources to be devoted to the Italian, Balkan and Burmese fronts.</p>
<p>Stalin said the Soviet Union would enter the war against Japan once Germany was defeated. They also discussed the future shape of Germany and Eastern Europe, and a framework for keeping the peace between the great powers after the war.</p>
<p>The now-famous photograph of the three allies sitting together was taken on the steps of the Soviet Embassy.</p>
<p>WHAT A BIRTHDAY PARTY</p>
<p>On November 30, Churchill's birthday, he hosted a formal dinner for nearly 40 guests, all political and military advisers of the three, at the Legation.</p>
<p>The cook had to scavenge around Tehran to find 69 candles that would fit on the birthday cake.</p>
<p>&quot;Stalin, arriving under heavy guard, was in the best of tempers, and the president, from his wheeled chair, beamed on us all in pleasure and goodwill,&quot; Churchill wrote later in his memoire &quot;The Second World War&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;This was a memorable occasion in my life. On my right sat the president of the United States, on my left the master of Russia...When the time came I proposed the health of our illustrious guests, and the president proposed my health and wished me many happy returns of the day. He was followed by Stalin, who spoke in a similar strain.&quot;</p>
<p>Many informal toasts followed according to the Russian custom, Churchill noted.</p>
<p>&quot;It must have been after two in the morning when we finally separated...I went to bed tired out but content, feeling sure that nothing but good had been done. It certainly was a happy birthday for me.&quot;</p>
<p>On their last day in Tehran the three leaders signed an agreement guaranteeing post-war territorial integrity and economic assistance to Iran.</p>
<p>GLORY DAYS IN THE PAST</p>
<p>The residence is set in sprawling gardens on Ferdowsi Avenue in the heart of the Iranian capital with a lily pond and large crows swooping down from tall pines, planes and poplars.</p>
<p>An additional wing built in 1963 with all the architectural character of a cheerless dormitory at a second-grade university once rang with the chatter of arms salesmen and oil executives during Iran's business boom in the pre-revolutionary days of the Shah.</p>
<p>Embassy staff took refuge in the residence basement from incoming Scud missiles during the Iran-Iraq war from 1980 to 1988. The residence has not been lived in since 1987.</p>
<p>Since the Shah's overthrow in 1979 by Shi'ite Moslem clergymen who abolished the monarchy and declared an Islamic Republic, diplomatic relations between Tehran and Western capitals have been uneasy and the British mission has declined in importance.</p>
<p>Relations were downgraded after the republic's founder Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini imposed a fatwa, or religious ruling, in 1989 calling on Moslems to kill British author Salman Rushdie for blaspheming Islam in his novel &quot;The Satanic Verses&quot;.</p>
<p>The charge d'affaires is now back in London, sitting things out in a state of diplomatic stalemate like the rest of the European Union ambassadors while each side waits for the other to make a move over German court charges of high Iranian involvement in political assassinations.</p>
<p>It seems unlikely there will be any more birthday parties at the residence for awhile.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
