<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="632602" id="root" date="1997-06-02" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: FEATURE - At 83, author O'Brian plans two more sea tomes.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - At 83, author O'Brian plans two more sea tomes.</headline>
<byline>Christopher Noble</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-02</dateline>
<text>
<p>At 83, Patrick O'Brian has penned 18 volumes of the rollicking, historical sea stories that have become his trademark, and the ink hasn't run dry yet.</p>
<p>He plans two more volumes to complete the series, a 1.5 million word saga describing the adventures of English Captain Jack Aubrey and his fellow voyager Stephen Maturin, who travel the globe during the Napoleonic Wars.</p>
<p>He is about a quarter of the way through the 19th of the series, which deals with the &quot;100 Days&quot;, Napoleon's doomed 1815 effort to regain power in France.</p>
<p>&quot;Then I think there will be a 20th which will bring the wheel full circle,&quot; O'Brian said in a rare interview during a recent trip to Paris.</p>
<p>Sitting in an armchair surrounded by scattered proof pages, O'Brian says his plans depend on his continued good health.</p>
<p>&quot;You see, I am 83 and you don't usually write much after about 84 or 85,&quot; he said. &quot;You very rarely last until 83. When you're much after 80 your teeth go and your memory goes.&quot;</p>
<p>Small but not slight, with white hair and a deeply lined face, O'Brian displays the courtesy and delicacy of manner of an earlier age.</p>
<p>GOOD FRENCH SALES DESPITE NAPOLEON BASHING</p>
<p>In Paris to meet journalists and promote the publication in French of &quot;The Mauritius Command&quot;, the fourth in the series, O'Brian says he is &quot;perfectly astonished&quot; at their popularity in France.</p>
<p>The books, whose heroes spend most of their time trying to undermine Napoleon's conquests, have sold well so far in France, with sales of 32,000 for the first three volumes in the series.</p>
<p>The Aubrey/Maturin novels have become an international sensation in the last decade, translated into 14 languages and selling about three million copies around the world.</p>
<p>O'Brian, however, has carefully kept himself out of the spotlight.</p>
<p>He is intensely private, refusing even to say where and when he was born, let alone give the name of the French village in which he now lives or details of his family and acquaintances.</p>
<p>He finds interest in him &quot;unhealthy&quot;, he says. &quot;All I wish to make public is in my books.&quot;</p>
<p>O'Brian has yielded some ground to the pressure of public curiosity, writing an essay in which he describes his childhood and some of his background.</p>
<p>Born shortly before or early in World War One, O'Brian was sent to live with relatives in Ireland when his mother died shortly after the war ended. He had a serious and lingering childhood illness, which he refuses to name, that confined him for long periods and led him to books.</p>
<p>He writes that though he spent long periods in England, he feels France and Ireland &quot;educated and formed&quot; him.</p>
<p>His love of the sea grew out of trips, prescribed for his illness, on boats belonging to friends and relatives.</p>
<p>He moved permanently to France after World War Two, during which he worked in naval intelligence and drove ambulances, taking up residence in a village in the Pyrenees not far from the Spanish border.</p>
<p>SEA STORY SUCCESS LAUNCHES EPIC SERIES</p>
<p>Though O'Brian's first books were not about the sea, he said he quickly realised that was where his heart resided after publishing his first naval tale, &quot;The Golden Ocean&quot;, in 1956.</p>
<p>It was in 1969 that O'Brian hit upon the successful formula with &quot;Master and Commander&quot; in which he introduced the now famous pair of Aubrey and the Irish Maturin.</p>
<p>He wrote the book at the request of a U.S. publisher who wanted a more adult sea story. Though he said he felt &quot;The Golden Ocean&quot; was a grown up book, he took another stab at the genre, launching an epic that is still attracting new readers.</p>
<p>O'Brian, who writes his books with a fountain pen on the back of proof pages from earlier books, develops an almost eerie mastery of the politics, science and manners of late 18th century England in the series.</p>
<p>Coupled with his ear for language, this combination has attracted men and women, doctors, academics and writers, all of whom find their own reasons to praise the books.</p>
<p>Which is to say that if you come to the Aubrey/Maturin tales for the adventure you will return for the science, and you might come back again for the romance.</p>
<p>GIBBON, AUSTEN HIS MAIN INFLUENCES</p>
<p>O'Brian says his influences include Chaucer, Alexander Pope, John Dryden, the 16th century historians William Camden and John Selden, as well as Rabelais and the &quot;obvious&quot; classics.</p>
<p>He reserves a special place for Edward Gibbon, whose &quot;The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire&quot; he says is peerless in English, and for Jane Austen.</p>
<p>He said he draws inspiration from &quot;her beautiful reticence, her intense observation and analytic power&quot; and her ability to bring her characters to life with deft descriptive touches.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the balance of a sentence and, this sounds absurd to say so, but above all, her use of the semicolon,&quot; O'Brian said.</p>
<p>O'Brian says he is trying to &quot;paint a fairly accurate picture&quot; of life in the British navy during the Napoleonic wars and offer good entertainment, too.</p>
<p>&quot;The really important element in it (the series) to my mind, is the immense value of friendship and honourable conduct,&quot; he said. &quot;It sounds like preaching, but I mean that's what emerges from the entirety.&quot;</p>
<p>He paused, lifted his hand and added: &quot;The ultimate horror of war, clearly, but the sometimes absolute necessity of it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-02"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-02"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
