<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="633309" id="root" date="1997-06-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Pope urges greater efforts for European unity.</title>
<headline>Pope urges greater efforts for European unity.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>GNIEZNO, Poland 1997-06-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul said on Tuesday a wall of economic and political selfishness as divisive as the communist-era Berlin Wall threatened unity in Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;Since the collapse of the visible wall, another invisible one has been discovered, one that continues to divide our continent -- the wall that exists in people's hearts,&quot; he said in a sermon at an open air mass.</p>
<p>Europe's future was the theme of the fourth day of the Pope's pilgrimage to his homeland during visits to Gniezno, where he met seven national presidents, and to Poznan where he celebrated a mass for young people.</p>
<p>A rapturous crowd of some 250,000 people, including seven heads of state, turned out on a rolling hillside below the 14th century Gniezno cathedral, traditional seat of Polish Catholicism, to see the 77-year-old Pontiff.</p>
<p>In contrast with concerns about his age and recent frailty, he spoke in a strong clear voice and one pilgrim in the crowd said: &quot;This is like the Pope of old, the Pope of 10 years ago.&quot;</p>
<p>Since the nostalgic trip began on Saturday, the Pope has attracted a million people to his masses to hear his calls for a spiritual renewal in post-communist Poland as it embraces economic and political freedom.</p>
<p>The presidents of Poland, Germany, Hungary, Czech  Republic, Slovakia, Lithuania and Ukraine attended the Gniezno service and later had a private meeting with the Pope.</p>
<p>He urged continued commitment towards cooperation between European countries and added: &quot;No country, even a weak one, can be left outside the sphere of the communities which are now arising.&quot;</p>
<p>Lithuanian President Algirdas Brazauskas told reporters later: &quot;The fact that seven presidents met shows that we are searching for roads so that on our continent peace and cooperation should reign.&quot;</p>
<p>While thanking God for the &quot;great gift of freedom&quot; granted to the nations of Europe with the fall of communism after decades of repression, the Pope declared: &quot;The recovery of the right to self-determination and growth of political and economic freedom are not sufficient to rebuild European unity.&quot;</p>
<p>He suggested in his sermon that the new invisible wall was no less insidious than the old one which physically divided the continent.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a wall made out of fear and aggressiveness, of a lack of understanding for people of different origins, different colour, different religious convictions,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is the wall of political and economic selfishness, of the weakening of sensitivity for the value of human life and the dignity of every human being.</p>
<p>&quot;Even the undeniable achievements of recent years in the economic, political and social fields do not hide the fact that this wall exists,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>This invisible wall, the Pope said, was casting a shadow over all of Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;The goal of the authentic unity of the European continent is still distant. There will be no European unity until it is based on unity of the spirit,&quot; the Pontiff said.</p>
<p>The Pope's mass in Poznan was held in a city square where security forces in 1956 put down the first big uprising against post-war communist rule in Poland.</p>
<p>He reminded 200,000 young people of the price paid by previous generations for their present freedom and added:</p>
<p>&quot;Awareness of our past helps us to take our place in the line of generations so that we can pass on to generations to come the common good, our homeland.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GNIEZNO, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
