<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="633324" id="root" date="1997-06-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Pope expects to meet ex-Solidarity leader Walesa.</title>
<headline>Pope expects to meet ex-Solidarity leader Walesa.</headline>
<byline>Jan Strupczewski</byline>
<dateline>GNIEZNO, Poland 1996-06-04</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul is expected to meet former Polish president Lech Walesa for a private audience on Wednesday when the Pontiff's pilgrimage to his homeland moves to Czestochowa.</p>
<p>Walesa headed the Solidarity free trade union movement which led a successful struggle in tandem with the Church to overthrow Polish communism in the 1980s.</p>
<p>The former Gdansk shipyard electrician and Nobel laureate became Poland's first post-communist president but has been a private citizen since being defeated in 1995 by President Aleksander Kwasniewski, who heads a social democratic government led by ex-communists.</p>
<p>Walesa, a favoured guest of the 77-year-old Pope during his return visits, refused to discuss the meeting in advance.</p>
<p>The 11-day pilgrimage enters its fifth day on Wednesday with John Paul looking invigorated by the enthusiasm of his reception at open air masses attended by more than a million people in south and west Poland.</p>
<p>Tired and frail at the outset, he appeared in good form during an informal religious celebration in the western city of Poznan on Tuesday when he bantered with 200,000 young people.</p>
<p>The mass was held in a central square notorious for the bloody suppression by security forces in 1956 of the first major worker's revolt against communist rule.</p>
<p>Earlier in the day, the Pope appealed for greater efforts to forge European unity at a mass in Gniezno which was also attended by the presidents of Poland, Germany, Hungary, Lithuania, Ukraine, Slovakia and the Czech republic.</p>
<p>He warned that an invisible wall of &quot;economic and political selfishness,&quot; as divisive as the old Berlin Wall, was shadowing the continent where developing former Soviet Bloc countries are knocking at the door of NATO and the wealthy European Union.</p>
<p>&quot;No country, even a weak one, can be left outside the sphere of the communities which are now arising,&quot; the Pope added.</p>
<p>John Paul said political and economic freedoms recovered after decades of communism &quot;are not sufficient in themselves to rebuild European unity.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-04"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GNIEZNO, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
