<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="634861" id="root" date="1997-06-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Sacked musician begs Israel forgive Hitler &quot;joke&quot;.</title>
<headline>Sacked musician begs Israel forgive Hitler &quot;joke&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-06-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>A German musician said he could not explain why he signed a hotel bill &quot;Adolf Hitler&quot; while touring Israel and asked forgiveness for the incident that sparked a storm of protest.</p>
<p>The Berlin Opera company said on Monday it had sacked Gerd Reinke, a 54-year-old double bass player, over the incident at a Tel Aviv hotel bar in the early hours of Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;What I did is unbelievable. I myself still cannot comprehend it. Only 24 hours afterwards did I understand what I had caused,&quot; Reinke told the Israeli newspaper Maariv in an interview conducted in Germany and published on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;On Saturday morning I was still teaching music students at (an Israeli) kibbutz. I ask in every way possible for forgiveness and a pardon from all citizens of Israel and especially from my hosts in Israel. There is no limit to my regret and I am suffering more than anyone,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Berlin Opera musicians still in Israel visited the Yad Vashem Holocaust Memorial in Jerusalem on Tuesday and laid a wreath there in the Hall of Remembrance for the six million Jews killed by Nazi Germany under Hitler in World War Two.</p>
<p>Opera officials, issuing hurried apologies for what they called an isolated incident, said the musician had been drinking heavily before he signed the bill.</p>
<p>But Germany's mass-circulation daily Bild newspaper, carrying the story on the front page, said Israeli journalists had shown he had only had two beers in the hotel bar.</p>
<p>Other German newspapers were equally unwilling to pass the affair off as a joke, with some suggesting it showed how deeply anti-Semitism ran in Germany and that it added fire to the debate over the role of ordinary Germans in the Holocaust.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
