<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="635645" id="root" date="1997-06-03" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Cult of Khomeini lives on in Iran.</title>
<headline>Cult of Khomeini lives on in Iran.</headline>
<byline>Barry May</byline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-06-03</dateline>
<text>
<p>Often baleful, sometimes benign, images of the Islamic revolution's spiritual leader Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini pervade Iran eight years after his death.</p>
<p>The stern gaze of the late Shi'ite Moslem clergyman with long white beard and loosely-wound black turban, revered in revolutionary Iran as an imam or saint, looks down from huge murals and posters throughout the Islamic republic.</p>
<p>Every town has its Khomeini street, Khomeini square, and Khomeini mosque. Newspapers laud him as &quot;the great man of the century&quot; and he is credited with reviving Islamic thought among a people too easily enticed by secular Western ways.</p>
<p>He is an icon of the revolution that overturned a monarchy which with some gaps had lasted 2,500 years in ancient Persia and modern Iran.</p>
<p>Khomeini died on June 3, 1989, 11 days after surgeons removed a cancerous third of his stomach and 10 years after his triumphant return from 15 years' exile in Turkey, Iraq and France. He was 86.</p>
<p>When Khomeini returned to Iran in 1979, the U.S.-backed Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi had just fled into exile. The shah died the following year in Egypt from cancer.</p>
<p>In the 1960s, the movement that was to topple the shah focused its ideals on Khomeini, a spiritual figure who had already attracted a following as a charismatic leader.</p>
<p>At Khomeini's tumultuous funeral in Tehran, hysterical mourners dragged his body from its coffin and tore at his shroud. Revolutionary Guards intervened, lifted the body back into the coffin and whisked it to safety by helicopter.</p>
<p>His tomb at Beheshte-e Zahra cemetery south of the capital became a shrine -- a still unfinished mosque whose gold dome and four minarets are tarnished by eight years of Tehran smog.</p>
<p>Millions of people go on pilgrimage to the mausoleum each year and leave spiritually enriched. Some go away financially poorer: audio cassettes of Khomeini's speeches, pictures, and even a clock fashioned from a 10,000 rial banknote that bears his portrait are popular souvenirs.</p>
<p>One of the first acts of president-elect Mohammad Khatami after last month's landslide election was to pay homage at Khomeini's tomb and renew allegiance to his ideals.</p>
<p>&quot;The late Imam's revolution was the accomplishment of a move to build a civilised society based on religion, whereas the West founded its civilisation by turning its back on religion,&quot; Khatami said at a seminar on Khomeini's thought.</p>
<p>University students around the world have presented more than 700 research works about Khomeini's character and thoughts, according to the secretary of the Imam Khomeini International Congress, a three-day event at Tehran University.</p>
<p>&quot;Intellectuals thought bridges to the past had been burned and Khomeini was just a catalyst to get rid of the shah,&quot; said a magazine editor. &quot;Not only was he not a catalyst, but he showed that history can be re-run.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody is interested in revolution any more. We middle-aged men have had enough of that. As for the youth, their ultimate dream is to emigrate...</p>
<p>&quot;Please don't mention my name.&quot;</p>
<p>In the early turbulent years of the revolution Khomeini's fundamentalist followers gradually pushed leftists and liberals out of the first post-shah government.</p>
<p>Revolutionary Iran's first elected president, Abolhassan Banisadr, was driven from office in 1981 and fled to France where he still lives.</p>
<p>Khomeini seemed to offer Iran two contradictory things, the editor said. &quot;One was the notion of freedom in the Western style, which is attractive to intellectuals, while the religious community thought he was bringing a stricter, more traditional adherence to the principles of Islam.</p>
<p>&quot;After the revolution, the traditionalists predominated.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-03"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-03"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
