<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645039" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: HORSE RACING-TOUCH GOLD UPSETS SILVER CHARM IN BELMONT.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-TOUCH GOLD UPSETS SILVER CHARM IN BELMONT.</headline>
<dateline>ELMONT, New York 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Touch Gold charged down the centre of the track to snatch a Triple Crown sweep from Silver Charm with a victory in the 129th Belmont Stakes on Saturday.</p>
<p>Touch Gold caught Silver Charm in the final hundred yards of the 1 1/2-mile race to win by 3/4 of a length.</p>
<p>Free House, who dueled with Silver Charm through the stretch, tired in the final yards and finished another length back in third.</p>
<p>Having won the Kentucky Derby and Preakness Stakes, Silver Charm was the first horse to come into the Belmont with a shot at the Triple Crown since Sunday Silence in 1989.</p>
<p>The last horse to win the Triple Crown was Affirmed in 1978. Only 11 horses in history have claimed all three jewels of thoroughbred racing's classic trio.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very hard to take,&quot; said Silver Star jockey Gary Stevens. &quot;It was a gallant race, but we gave it our all.&quot;</p>
<p>Crypto Star, Irish Silence, Wild Rush and Mr. Energiser completed the order of finish in the longest of the three Triple Crown events run over a span of just five weeks.</p>
<p>Touch Gold, coupled in the wagering with Wild Rush, returned $7.30 $3.30 and $2.60 on a $2 bet. Silver Charm paid $3.00 and $2.40. Free House paid $2.70 to show.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ELMONT, New York"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
