<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645048" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: CRICKET-TAYLOR ENDS HIS CRISIS WITH ASHES CENTURY.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-TAYLOR ENDS HIS CRISIS WITH ASHES CENTURY.</headline>
<byline>Steve Tongue</byline>
<dateline>BIRMINGHAM, England 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's captain Mark Taylor ended his 18 months form crisis with a courageous century to lead an Ashes fightback against England on Saturday.</p>
<p>Taylor battled to an unbeaten 108 as Australia, 360 behind on first innings, made 256 for one in their second innings by the close on the third day of the first test at Edgbaston.</p>
<p>Earlier, England added 29 for the loss of three wickets before declaring at 478 for nine.</p>
<p>Taylor, whose place was in jeopardy after 21 test innings without reaching 50, shared century stands with fellow opener Matthew Elliott (66) and Greg Blewett (61 not out).</p>
<p>The Australian skipper put on 133 with Elliott and then shared an unfinished second wicket partnership of 123 with Blewett.</p>
<p>Taylor, batting confidently until becoming tied down in the 80s, eventually passed 100 for the first time in a test since November 1995 and the first outside Australia since 1993. It took him almost five hours, with 10 fours and a six from 214 balls.</p>
<p>He received a warm ovation from another capacity crowd, who had found themselves watching the sort of cricket that pessimistic English followers had been expecting throughout the Ashes series.</p>
<p>In far less helpful conditions than the Australian first innings when the ball swung, the bowling of England's four seamers and off-spinner Robert Croft was made to look less penetrating.</p>
<p>Croft claimed the only wicket in 80 overs by bowling Elliott as he prodded forward.</p>
<p>Australia's heartening day was tempered by the news that Mark Waugh was detained in hospital for 24 hours after suffering stomach pains.</p>
<p>Coach Geoff Marsh said that it was not clear whether he would be able to bat.</p>
<p>Marsh, a former opening partner of Taylor's, said of his captain: &quot;It's a great moment for a great sportsman. The guy's been struggling, but no-one could break him. Once he got going, he looked like the Mark Taylor we all knew.&quot;</p>
<p>England batted on for nine and a half overs in the morning session, losing three wickets in adding 29 to their overnight total of 449 for six.</p>
<p>Mark Ealham was left not out on 53, emulating Nasser Hussain and Graham Thorpe in passing his previous highest test score.</p>
<p>Two more catches for wicketkeeper Ian Healy gave him six, a personal best in test cricket, which equalled the record for an Ashes innings jointly held by Rodney Marsh (Australia) and Jack Russell (England).</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BIRMINGHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
