<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645097" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-LIONS SUFFER FIRST TOUR DEFEAT.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-LIONS SUFFER FIRST TOUR DEFEAT.</headline>
<byline>Andy Colquhoun</byline>
<dateline>PRETORIA 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dropped Springbok centre Danie van Schalkwyk scored two tries for Northern Transvaal as a disjointed British Lions side crashed to a 35-30 defeat on Saturday -- their first South African tour loss.</p>
<p>The Lions threatened a revival when they closed to within five points of Northerns with 26 minutes remaining after trailing 25-7 two minutes into the second half.</p>
<p>But van Schalkwyk intercepted a Gregor Townsend pass two minutes later and with winger Casper Steyn kicking his third conversion the Lions were left with too much to do.</p>
<p>The Blue Bulls were without five players on Springbok duty but they put behind them some indifferent form which saw them finish eighth in the recently completed Super 12 competition.</p>
<p>They were aided by a Lions side which were unable to control possession, gave away too many penalties and committed numerous basic errors.</p>
<p>The one highlight for them was the majestic form of centre Jeremy Guscott who scored two of their three tries and made the break for Gregor Townsend to score the third.</p>
<p>Northerns led 18-7 at the interval after dominating the half with Steyn rounding off a fine backline move from halfway to score a try in the corner.</p>
<p>The tourists' vulnerability around the scrum was exploited on the narrow side for van Schalkwyk to score their second try with number eight Adriaan Richter scoring a similar try from the base of a scrum to make it 25-7 early in the second half.</p>
<p>Guscott scored the Lions' opening try after chipping over the defensive line and dribbling ahead to score under the posts in the 24th minute.</p>
<p>His second came after he backed up Townsend, who broke the line with a superb dummy.</p>
<p>Two Tim Stimpson penalties gave the Lions hope before van Schalkwyk's interception swung a gripping game back to Northerns. A Steyn penalty carried the score 35-23.</p>
<p>With five minutes remaining, Guscott's curving run gave centre Allan Tait space on the right wing before he turned the ball inside for Townsend to score.</p>
<p>However the Lions were unable to break out of their own half in the final minutes, falling to their first tour defeat in five matches.</p>
<p>Teams:</p>
<p>Northern Transvaal - 15-Graeme Bouwer, 14-Casper Steyn, 13-Johan Schutte, 12-Danie van Schalkwyk, 11-Wynand Lourens (Grant Esterhuizen, 34), 10-Roland de Marigny, 9-Conrad Breytenbach, 8-Adriaan Richter, 7-Schutte Bekker, 6-Nicky van der Walt (Ralf Scroeder, 65), 5-Derrick Badenhorst, 4-Derrick Grobbelaar (Gerhard Laufs, 39), 3-Piet Boer (Matthew Proudfoot, 70), 2-Henry Tromp (Jannie Brooks, 40), 1-Lourens Campher.</p>
<p>British Lions - 15-Tim Stimpson, 14-John Bentley (Scott Gibbs, 60), 13-Jeremy Guscott, 12-Allan Tait, 11-Tony Underwood, 10-Gregor Townsend, 9-Rob Howley, 8-Scott Quinnell, 7-Eric Miller, 6-Lawrence Dallaglio, 5-Simon Shaw, 4-Martin Johnson, 3-Jason Lonard (David Young, 74), 2-Mark Regan, 1-Graham Rowntree.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRETORIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
