<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645060" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: HORSE RACING-BENNY THE DIP STEALS DERBY THRILLER.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-BENNY THE DIP STEALS DERBY THRILLER.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>EPSOM, England 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Benny The Dip, a chance ride for Willie Ryan in the world's most famous horse race, won a thrilling Epsom Derby on Saturday in a nail-biting finish with Silver Patriarch.</p>
<p>The two colts flashed over the line together with the 11-1 shot just holding on by a short head from the 6-1 chance with 25-1 outsider Romanov third five lengths back.</p>
<p>The big shock of the million-pound race was the eclipse of the 6-4 on hot favourite Entrepreneur.</p>
<p>The colt, hailed as a super horse after his 2,000 Guineas win, palpably failed to stay and finished a disappointing fourth of the 13 runners.</p>
<p>&quot;This is every jockey's dream,&quot; said Ryan, punching the air with joy after hearing the photo finish result of his titanic struggle over the unique Epsom switchback.</p>
<p>&quot;My God he was impressive,&quot; Ryan said of the colt named after a Damon Runyan villain by his wheelchair-bound owner- breeder, the 72-year-old Ohio newspaper magnate Landon Knight.</p>
<p>Knight, who listened to the race over the phone in Ohio, sent his wife Cynthia over to cheer Benny The Dip home and asked her to put on a 100 pounds bet to help pay for the trip.</p>
<p>Ryan, who broke his ribs in the Derby three years ago when his mount Foyer came down at halfway, only sat on Benny The Dip for the first time on Thursday and was not that taken with the colt.</p>
<p>&quot;He wasn't that impressive riding him at out home, but my God he was impressive today,&quot; said Ryan.</p>
<p>He got the ride after French champion Olivier Peslier, who rode Benny the Dip to a brilliant victory in York's Dante Stakes, opted instead to partner the disappointing Cloudings. The French raider could only finish 10th.</p>
<p>Benny The Dip's triumph was also a first-time Epsom Derby win for trainer John Gosden who saw victory snatched from his grasp in 1995 when Tamure was narrowly beaten by Lammtarra.</p>
<p>The super-cool Gosden said: &quot;When you think you have won the Derby and it gets snatched away from you in the last 10 yards, you learn to be pretty hard inside.&quot;</p>
<p>He was full of praise for Ryan, a somewhat unfashionable journeyman jockey who has in the past missed out on big race rides to more celebrated names.</p>
<p>&quot;I picked Willie Ryan because he is a good friend and a very positive rider,&quot; Gosden said after watching one of the best finishes to an Epsom derby for years.</p>
<p>&quot;Willie had ridden in three Derbies and I do feel it is a daunting experience for any jockey. We felt we would go for someone who's been there before and knocked about in the ring,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Gosden so nearly missed out on the thrill of a lifetime.</p>
<p>&quot;Mr Knight was going to sell this horse at the sales but he got me to go and look at him in the paddock. I missed my plane home from America to do so and said I loved him.&quot;</p>
<p>The rest is now racing history -- and lightning could strike twice. Knight said: &quot;I now also have a two-year-old with John Gosden called Olive The Twist. Hopefully, she will win the Oaks next year.&quot;</p>
<p>Champion Pat Eddery, who was last five furlongs (1-km) out but came with a rattling late run on the runner-up, said: &quot;Silver Patriarch just would not go the early pace. He's a big galloping horse and needs a track to suit but even so one furlong out I thought I would get to the winner.&quot;</p>
<p>Benny The Dip had always been handily placed in the leading bunch and kicked five lengths clear halfway up the straight.</p>
<p>For a few moments it looked as though the colt might come home unchallenged, only for Silver Patriarch to emerge with an exciting challenge which was only just repelled.</p>
<p>Eddery is now looking forward to some revenge which could come in the Irish Derby.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, big-race specialist Michael Kinane was a bitterly disappointed man after the eclipse of the much touted Entrepreneur.</p>
<p>He said: &quot;I didn't get an easy passage out there and I wasn't expecting it from anybody, but I was a beaten horse a long way out.</p>
<p>&quot;I never got much of anything today...it was a very disappointing performance.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EPSOM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
