<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645042" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UKRAINE: SOCCER-LACKLUSTRE GERMANS HELD 0-0 IN UKRAINE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-LACKLUSTRE GERMANS HELD 0-0 IN UKRAINE.</headline>
<dateline>KIEV 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Group leaders Ukraine held European champions Germany to a scoreless draw in their World Cup European group nine qualifier on Saturday.</p>
<p>Dynamo Kiev striker Serhiy Rebrov had the best chance for the home team but his powerful shot from about 16 metres hit a post just before halftime.</p>
<p>The Germans started well but settled down after 10 minutes and rarely threatened Oleksander Shovkovsky's goal.</p>
<p>A Juergen Klinsmann header in the first half, which went wide, and a Thomas Helmer long range effort which Shovkovsky saved in the second accounted for the Germans' main offensive opportunities.</p>
<p>Ukraine still lead the group with 14 points after eight games, with Germany two points off the lead but with two games in hand.</p>
<p>Ukraine, six years after their emergence as an independent sporting nation after the collapse of the Soviet Union, had a fair chance of making a name if they could have capitalised on their possession to upset the European champions.</p>
<p>The home side dominated for most of the first half and later in the second, trying to redeem themselves after a 1-1 home draw against Armenia last month that dealt a serious blow to their chances of making their first ever big tournament finals.</p>
<p>The Germans, still odds on favourites to win the group after a comfortable 2-0 win over Ukraine in Bremen in April, seemed content to sit back and make do with a point away from home.</p>
<p>Klinsmann and Kirsten, Germany's upfront duo, were given little room for manoevre and did little to worry a well-organised back line based around players from Ukrainian champions Dynamo Kiev.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UKRN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KIEV"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UKRAINE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
