<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645091" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: CRICKET-PROLIFIC HAYDEN POWERS HAMPSHIRE TO VICTORY.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-PROLIFIC HAYDEN POWERS HAMPSHIRE TO VICTORY.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian opener Matthew Hayden hammered his third century in four county championship innings to power Hampshire to victory over Derbyshire on Saturday.</p>
<p>The left-hander from Queensland scored an unbeaten 136 as Hamsphire, set 310 to win from 65 overs, swept home by seven wickets with 3.1 overs to spare on the fourth and last day at Chesterfield.</p>
<p>The decision by Derbyshire's Australian captain Dean Jones to declare at lunch on 208 for four with a lead of 309 looked a gamble on a flat pitch and with Devon Malcolm on Ashes test duty and fellow paceman Dominic Cork injured.</p>
<p>His bowlers proved incapable of breaking through or containing as Hayden and Jason Laney (93) put on 213, Hampshire's highest ever opening stand against Derbyshire.</p>
<p>Hayden reached three figures from 113 balls with his 15th four and although Laney was bowled off his pads in the same over, former England batsman Robin Smith lashed a 48-ball half-century to sustain the winning tempo.</p>
<p>Yorkshire-born paceman Andy Smith returned to haunt his home county by helping Gloucestershire go back to the top of the table with a 164-run victory at Headingley.</p>
<p>Smith took four for 74 to finish with a 10-wicket match haul as Yorkshire, needing 411 to win, were all out for 246 on the fourth and final day.</p>
<p>The home side resumed on 194 for four, but once Smith had trapped Craig White leg before for 38 there was to be no way back for Yorkshire, who had opener Michael Vaughan missing with a cracked wrist.</p>
<p>Kent moved into second place after beating Warwickshire by four wickets on the fourth day at Tunbridge Wells.</p>
<p>Kent dismissed the visitors in their second innings for 280 during the morning session, leaving themselves 216 to win.</p>
<p>Neil Smith revived Warwickshire's hopes by taking four for 68 with his off-spin but Alan Wells (62 not out) and skipper Steve Marsh (32 not out) guided Kent home with an unbroken seventh-wicket stand of 58.</p>
<p>Mathew Dowman hit a brilliant 111 off 162 balls to spur Nottinghamshire to a three-wicket victory over Northamptonshire at Northampton which lifted them into third place.</p>
<p>Notts lost opener Guy Welton to Jonathan Taylor without scoring, but their victory charge was back on track when Dowman and new New Zealand signing Nathan Astle (64) put on 156 for the third wicket.</p>
<p>Taylor took every Notts' wicket to fall, finishing with seven for 87, but Paul Johnson's 57 helped guide the visitors home with three balls of their minimum 77 overs remaining.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
