<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645066" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: HORSE RACING-BENNY THE DIP WINS DERBY THRILLER.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-BENNY THE DIP WINS DERBY THRILLER.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>EPSOM, England 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The 11-1 shot Benny The Dip won one of the most thrilling Epsom Derbies for years on Saturday with a short-head victory over Silver Patriarch.</p>
<p>The courageous colt, named after a Damon Runyan villain, stole the world's most famous horse race with a pile-driving run up the Epsom straight.</p>
<p>&quot;This is every jockey's dream,&quot; said Willie Ryan as he rode in his first ever Epsom Derby winner and punched the air with delight after the photo finish result was announced.</p>
<p>&quot;He is a lovely horse, very game,&quot; said the 32-year-old Newmarket jockey after reaching the pinnacle of his career on a ride he only landed this week.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the best of spare rides. My God he was impressive,&quot; Ryan said.</p>
<p>The 25-1 chance Romanov ran home a distant third five lengths back. The 6-4 on hot-favourite Entrepreneur, the 2,000 Guineas winner, palpably failed to stay and finished a disappointing fourth.</p>
<p>&quot;He finished a very tired horse. It was a very disappointing performance,&quot; Entrepreneur's jockey Michael Kinane said afterwards.</p>
<p>Trainer John Gosden, also landing his first Epsom Derby, said: &quot;That was a beautiful ride from Willie. I told him you have got to be positive.</p>
<p>&quot;Having knocked on the door a few times in this race there is a welcome sense of relief,&quot; he said after the victory which he put on a par with the 1984 Breeders' Cup Mile triumph of Royal Heroine.</p>
<p>The colt is owned by the wheelchair-bound Ohio newspaper publisher Landon Knight, who was unable to attend at Epsom but his wife Cynthia was there cheering home the family champion.</p>
<p>Speaking from his home in Ohio, the 72-year-old Knight said; &quot;I listened to the race over the phone but I could not hear anything after Tattenham Corner because of the crowd noise.&quot;</p>
<p>Benny The Dip was a chance ride for Ryan, the stable jockey for Henry Cecil who has in the past so often missed out on the big race mounts.</p>
<p>French champion Olivier Peslier rode Benny The Dip to a brilliant tactical victory in the Dante Stakes at York but opted instead on Derby Day for Andre Fabre's Cloudings who finished 10th of the 13 runners.</p>
<p>Benny The Dip was always up with the pace but made his decisive move up the short Epsom straight.</p>
<p>For a moment it looked as if the colt might come home unchallenged, but Eddery on the grey 6-1 shot Silver Patriarch mounted a sustained and exciting challenge over the final 100 metres only to be denied by the shortest of margins.</p>
<p>Silver Patriarch had been last with five furlongs (1--km) to run but managed to weave through the field to deliver his challenge.</p>
<p>Entrepreneur was always struggling to go the pace and was only ninth as the field rounded Tattenham Corner. It was soon clear the much touted colt was not going to play a part in the finish.</p>
<p>Romanov, ridden by Northern Irishman John Reid, ran on gamely to be third without threatening the first two at any stage in the million-pound race.</p>
<p>It was certainly a welcome change of Derby luck for Ryan who three years ago broke his ribs in the great race when his mount Foyer stumbled at halfway.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EPSOM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
