<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645059" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: CYCLING-GOTTI DEFIES FRENZIED FANS AND CHIEF RIVAL.</title>
<headline>CYCLING-GOTTI DEFIES FRENZIED FANS AND CHIEF RIVAL.</headline>
<dateline>EDOLO, Italy 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ivan Gotti was 24 hours away from producing Italy's first Giro d'Italia triumph since 1991 on Saturday despite losing a duel with Russian rival Pavel Tonkov.</p>
<p>Tonkov snatched his third stage win of the 22-day event, but his hopes of a second overall victory faded on the feared ascent of the Mortirolo mountain.</p>
<p>He finished one second clear of Gotti with Italian Wladimir Belli surviving a 70 kph scare for third place on the 21st and longest stage of 238 km from Male' to Edolo.</p>
<p>Belli's attempt to escape off the front ended when he lost control and scraped along a wall for several metres.</p>
<p>Tonkov earned a time deduction for his success and trimmed Gotti's outright lead by five seconds to one minute 27 seconds.</p>
<p>Thousands of spectators swarmed over the 16 km climb, anticipating a gigantic struggle. In fact, there was more of a threat from frenzied fans packing the road than either rival.</p>
<p>Gotti fired off three short-lived attacks but a poker-faced Tonkov calmly held him.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought about attacking again, but there was something in me that stopped me. May be it is because we are friends,&quot; said Gotti.</p>
<p>The Italian angrily waved his arm as the excited crowds closed in, leaving just enough space to pedal a bike through. To confirm the hellish situation, a fan dressed as the devil complete with horns, tail, and fork joined in the melee.</p>
<p>&quot;I was afraid,&quot; said Gotti. &quot;So many people were touching me.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It was a very dangerous situation,&quot; said Tonkov. &quot;The Giro organisation should provide protection.&quot;</p>
<p>The Russian said he had mistakenly chosen gears that were too big for such a climb. &quot;Still, I am happy with three stage wins and being second overall. The stronger guy is winning the Giro.&quot;</p>
<p>For most of the race an old hero, Gianni Bugno, emerged to excite the roadside crowds. He rode alone for 170 km, reviving memories of his two world titles, and triumphs in the World Cup and the 1990 Giro.</p>
<p>As he climbed the Mortirolo mountain the tiring Bugno, Tonkov's team mate, was brought to a stop when motorcycles carrying photographers tangled and fell. After restarting he looked behind to see the duellists closing fast.</p>
<p>Accidents apart, Gotti should clinch victory on the final leg into Milan on Sunday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EDOLO, Italy"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
