<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645087" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: HORSE RACING-STOUTE CONFIDENT OF ENTREPRENEUR VICTORY.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-STOUTE CONFIDENT OF ENTREPRENEUR VICTORY.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>EPSOM, England 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Michael Stoute was confident on Saturday that Entrepreneur could join the ranks of racing immortals with a convincing win in the Epsom Derby.</p>
<p>The trainer, fresh from his Coronation Cup triumph with globetrotting champion Singspiel, said of Entrepreneur: &quot;This is the horse they all have to beat on Guineas form.&quot;</p>
<p>Entrepreneur showed blistering speed to land the Newmarket 2,000 Guineas and victory over the unique Epsom switchback would put the stamp of greatness on Entrepreneur.</p>
<p>&quot;Entrepreneur has never worked over the full Derby distance but he has galloped and cantered round a left-handed track so I am very hopeful that he will handle Epsom,&quot; Stoute said.</p>
<p>Victory would fulfil a lifetime ambition for former bookmaker Michael Tabor who has been a phenomenally successful owner around the world and already captured a Kentucky Derby with Thunder Gulch.</p>
<p>Bookmakers are expecting a  30 million pounds ($48.9 million) betting bonanza on the world's most famous horse race -- even if Entrepreneur is virtually unbackable for small-time punters at 4-5.</p>
<p>They will be looking for good each way value in the 13-horse field who might just surprise Entrepreneur and his jockey, big race specialist Michael Kinane.</p>
<p>The grey Silver Patriarch (11-2) scored a facile victory in the Lingfield Derby trial over a similar track and overnight rain at Epsom on Friday will have helped his chances.</p>
<p>French champion trainer Andre Fabre, who has just won his first French Derby with Peintre Celebre, hopes to complete the Epsom double with Cloudings (10-1).</p>
<p>But all the form lines keep coming back to Entrepreneur, the class act of the race whose victory will have a bittersweet taste for Stoute.</p>
<p>For his long-time stable jockey Walter Swinburn has taken a sabbatical from racing to battle weight problems after an horrific fall in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;I wanted so much to ride him at Epsom,&quot; Swinburn told the London Evening Standard.</p>
<p>&quot;In fact I've turned away from a champion. No one knows that better than me but my body was in trauma,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>And Swinburn, who as a teenager partnered the mighty Shergar to a breathtaking 10-length win in the 1981 Derby, paid Entrepreneur the ultimate compliment.</p>
<p>&quot;He has far more speed than Shergar who was an outstanding galloper of great quality. And don't believe anyone who tells you a horse as fast as him won't stay.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EPSOM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
