<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645034" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: HORSE RACING-TOUCH GOLD DENIES SILVER CHARM TRIPLE CROWN.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-TOUCH GOLD DENIES SILVER CHARM TRIPLE CROWN.</headline>
<byline>John Swenson</byline>
<dateline>ELMONT, New York 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Touch Gold charged powerfully down the centre of the track to defeat Silver Charm in the 129th running of the Belmont Stakes on Saturday, denying Silver Charm the Triple Crown.</p>
<p>Touch Gold caught Silver Charm in the final hundred yards of the race to win by 3/4 of a length, narrowly ending the gray colt's bid to become only the 12th Triple Crown winner in history.</p>
<p>Free House, who dueled with Silver Charm through the stretch, tired in the final yards and finished another length back in third.</p>
<p>Having won the Kentucky Derby and Preakness Stakes, Silver Charm was the first horse to come into the Belmont with a shot at the Triple Crown since Sunday Silence in 1989.</p>
<p>Silver Charm produced a valiant effort in defeat, turning back challenges from three horses, including Touch Gold, as he thundered around the 1 1/2 mile track.</p>
<p>But just as Easy Goer snatched a Triple Crown from Sunday Silence eight years ago, Touch Gold overhauled Silver Charm in the final stage of the most gruelling test of the three races to keep the number of Triple Crown winners at a mere 11.</p>
<p>The last horse to win the Triple Crown was Affirmed in 1978. Silver Charm became the 13th horse to lose the Belmont after winning the Kentucky Derby and Preakness, failing in a bid to join the immortals of racing, such as Secretariat, Count Fleet, Whirlaway and Citation.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very hard to take,&quot; said Silver Star jockey Gary Stevens. &quot;This was probably the best race that Silver Charm has run through the Triple Crown races and to have him come up just a bit short, it's hard to take.&quot;</p>
<p>Stevens, who road Silver Charm to victory in the first two jewels of the crown, said his heart went out to Silver Charm's owners and trainer Bob Baffert.</p>
<p>&quot;I know that what I'm feeling right now must be tenfold for them,&quot; the jockey said. &quot;But, it was a gallant race, we gave it our all.&quot;</p>
<p>In the post parade, Silver Charm snorted and tossed his head as if acknowledging the thunderous applause from the crowd of 70,682 -- third largest in Belmont Stakes history.</p>
<p>When the gates opened, Touch Gold went to the early lead, floating Wild Rush and Silver Charm wide into the first turn.</p>
<p>&quot;I stayed off the rail, since all the winners were in the middle of the track,&quot; said Touch Gold jockey Chris McCarron.</p>
<p>Entrymates Touch Gold and Wild Rush led Silver Charm and Free House through a slow pace of :49 1/5 for the half mile.</p>
<p>&quot;We were walking,&quot; Stevens said of the early pace.</p>
<p>Stevens edged Silver Charm to the front going down the backstretch and Wild Rush engaged him as Touch Gold was taken back off the pace by McCarron.</p>
<p>Going into the far turn Silver Charm put away Wild Rush and jockey Kent Desormeaux sent Free House after the leader.</p>
<p>Silver Charm and Free House ran side-by-side around the turn. At the top of the stretch, Silver Charm was a head in front and the race was on to the wire with a Triple Crown looking a very realistic possibility.</p>
<p>&quot;Neither one of us pushed the button until the quarter pole,&quot; said Stevens. &quot;When I did I got the most explosive move from Silver Charm of any of the three races.&quot;</p>
<p>Silver Charm gradually drew away from Free House in deep stretch, but never saw the onrushing Touch Gold.</p>
<p>&quot;Part of the plan was to close on the outside so that Silver Charm wouldn't see him,&quot; said McCarron. &quot;Silver Charm was dead fit and I didn't want him to fix that eye on me.&quot;</p>
<p>Stevens thought he had the race won when he passed Free House.</p>
<p>&quot;I saw a shadow out of the corner of my eye 75 yards out,&quot; said Stevens. &quot;I was surprised when I saw who it was.</p>
<p>&quot;Silver Charm never saw him until ten jumps to the wire and it was too late to build another head of steam.&quot;</p>
<p>Said Baffert: &quot;He ran his heart out. He showed up today, he just never saw that horse (Touch Gold).</p>
<p>&quot;These people came for a show and they got one.&quot;</p>
<p>Trainer David Hofmans did a masterful job of preparing Touch Gold for the Belmont after the colt suffered a hoof injury during the running of the Preakness.</p>
<p>Hofmans nursed Touch Gold along, applying patches to the tender hoof, and decided against working him out the week before the Belmont.</p>
<p>Hofmans is no stranger to upsets, having saddled longshot Alphabet Soup to win the Breeders' Cup Classic last November. After the Belmont, Hofmans relished the spoiler's role.</p>
<p>&quot;We're going to take the Belmont trophy and fill it with Alphabet Soup,&quot; Hofmans joked.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Silver Charm is a good horse, but he couldn't win the Triple Crown. He just ran into a better horse today.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ELMONT, New York"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
