<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645088" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: HORSE RACING-RIVALS ATTEMPT TO THWART SILVER CHARM IN BELMONT.</title>
<headline>HORSE RACING-RIVALS ATTEMPT TO THWART SILVER CHARM IN BELMONT.</headline>
<byline>John Swenson</byline>
<dateline>ELMONT, New York 1997-06-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>Silver Charm is poised for a place in history with a win Saturday in the Belmont Stakes, but four rivals are serious challengers to the horse who won the first two legs of the Triple Crown by the slimmest of margins.</p>
<p>Bob Baffert, who trains Silver Charm, and Gary Stevens, who rides him, have both predicted victory, and the extra distance of the 1 1-2 mile Belmont appears to suit the silver-gray colt with the splash of white across his forehead.</p>
<p>But the Belmont has proved in the past to be a stumbling block for Triple Crown contenders, coming at the end of a gruelling stretch of three races in five weeks.</p>
<p>Twelve horses have failed to add the final jewel after winning the Kentucky Derby and Preakness. Only 11 horses have swept all three, Affirmed being the last to do it in 1978.</p>
<p>Silver Charm's chief rival is Free House, who has raced against the big horse in all of his five starts as a 3-year-old. Silver Charm has only a 3-2 edge in head-to-head competition with Free House, but the last two wins came in the biggest events, The Kentucky Derby and Preakness.</p>
<p>Free House came within a bob of the head of beating Silver Charm in the Preakness and is likely to be right there again in the Belmont.</p>
<p>Two of the other challengers, Wild Rush and Touch Gold, are trained by upset specialists Dick Mandella and David Hofmans.</p>
<p>Mandella made history last August when he sent out Dare and Go to upset the seemingly invincible Cigar and deny that champion the chance to break Citation's modern winning-streak record.</p>
<p>Hofmans saddled longshot Alphabet Soup to win the Breeders' Cup Classic in November, ruining Cigar's retirment party in the process.</p>
<p>Ironically, the horses trained by this pair of giant killers are coupled in the Belmont wagering due to common ownership by Frank Stronach.</p>
<p>Wild Rush impressed speed handicappers with a sizzling wire-to-wire victory in the Illinois Derby, the fastest race he's ever run.</p>
<p>Other handicappers are set to bet on Touch Gold, who went to his knees breaking out of the gate in the Preakness, cutting his hoof in the process, but finished full of run to come fourth, beaten by only 1 1-2 lengths.</p>
<p>Hofmans thinks Touch Gold can turn the tables on Silver Charm this time.</p>
<p>&quot;Silver Charm has got to earn it if he wants to join Affirmed and Seattle Slew and the great ones,&quot; Hofmans vowed.</p>
<p>Crypto Star, the other main contender, finished a disappointing fifth in the Kentucky Derby after posting strong back-to-back victories in the Louisiana and Arkansas derbies.</p>
<p>After Crypto Star turned in a seven furlong work in 1:27 last Sunday morning at Belmont, trainer Wayne Catalano predicted his horse would win the Belmont. Catalano would like nothing better than to play the spoiler.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not a popularity contest, you know,&quot; said Catalano.</p>
<p>Crypto Star and Touch Gold will need a fast pace to set up their late runs. They may get help from one of the two outsiders in the race, Mr. Energiser, a Panamanian import who is making his first start in the United States.</p>
<p>The prospect of a blistering pace is enhanced as well by the presence of Wild Rush, whose speed is his strongest point, and Free House, who set or pressed the pace throughout both the Kentucky Derby and Preakness.</p>
<p>The problem for Silver Charm's opponents is that while a fast pace could help Crypto Star and Touch Gold, it won't necessarily hurt the favourite, whose running style allows him to stalk the leaders, then head for the front in the stretch.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ELMONT, New York"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
