<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645033" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: One French soldier dead, five hurt in Congo clash.</title>
<headline>One French soldier dead, five hurt in Congo clash.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-06-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A French soldier was killed and five others were wounded in a firefight in Congo Brazzaville on Saturday involving French and Congolese soldiers, the French Defence Ministry said on Sunday.</p>
<p>A senior officer in the Congolese army was also hurt in the clash, a ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;One French soldier has been killed and five others wounded, two of them seriously. In addition, one senior officer in the Congolese army was wounded,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>A ministry statement issued shortly afterwards said the confrontation was triggered when a group of foreign residents including some French citizens found themselves pinned down and requested help.</p>
<p>&quot;With the approval of the Congolese authorities, Congolese and French troops present in Brazzaville proceeded at the demand of the foreign citizens to help them get away,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;As a second wave of evacuations began, some of the French and Congolese troops came under fire from uncontrolled elements,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The incident occurred between 1900 and 2000 GMT on Saturday evening, the statement said.</p>
<p>Three days of clashes pitting supporters of former president Denis Sassou Nguesso against soldiers loyal to President Pascal Lissouba and other political and ethnic rivals have rocked Brazzaville, capital of the former French colony.</p>
<p>The French Foreign Ministry earlier on Saturday had appealed for calm in the region and had applauded an offer by Gabonese President Omar Bongo to mediate the crisis.</p>
<p>The ministry said at that time that it saw no reason for French residents of Brazzaville to leave the country but it advised them to remain in their homes for the time being.</p>
<p>French soldiers came to Brazzaville several months ago and like U.S., British, Belgian and Portuguese troops remained on standby to evacuate foreign nationals from Kinshasa in the event of a bloodbath there during the final days of the civil war that brought Laurent Kabila to power. The others all left.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
