<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645165" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: SOCCER-COACH RANIERI LEAVES FIORENTINA.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-COACH RANIERI LEAVES FIORENTINA.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fiorentina coach Claudio Ranieri has left the club after a disappointing season in which the side finished ninth in Serie A and failed to win a spot in the UEFA Cup, Italian newspapers reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>They said Vittorio Cecchi Gori, the Florentine club's movie mogul owner, and Ranieri agreed on the split over dinner in Rome on Friday night. Ranieri had two years of a four-year contract still to run.</p>
<p>Ranieri, 46, had been widely credited with the Florentine club's remarkable run from the second division three years ago to victory in the 1996 Italian Cup and in the Italian Supercup over AC Milan last September.</p>
<p>But he had been under fire most of the past season after failing to reach the top of the table despite several high-profile signings, including Brazilian-born Luis Oliveira and Russia's Andrei Kanchelskis.</p>
<p>A lacklustre season by Argentine ace Gabriel Batistuta also hurt Ranieri, whose team were knocked out of the semifinals of the Cup Winners' Cup by eventual winners Barcelona.</p>
<p>The papers said Alberto Malesani, coach of second division side Chievo, was likely to take over for Ranieri.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
