<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645126" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: MOTOR RACING-DEFERRAN CLAIMS POLE FOR CART DETROIT GRAND PRIX.</title>
<headline>MOTOR RACING-DEFERRAN CLAIMS POLE FOR CART DETROIT GRAND PRIX.</headline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's Gil de Ferran knocked Scott Pruett off the pole for the Detroit Grand Prix then avoided the same fate to earn the prime starting spot for Sunday's CART series Indy car race.</p>
<p>De Ferran, driving a Reynard Honda, set a track record of 1:09.052 (109.483 mph/176.191 kph) at Detroit's 2.1-mile (3.3 km) Belle Isle road course on his last set of tires and had to anxiously wait out the last seven minutes of Saturday's final qualifying session to claim his second pole of the year.</p>
<p>Provisional polesitter Pruett had turned his fast lap of the day only three tenths of a second slower than de Ferran, at 1:09.082 in a Reynard Ford.</p>
<p>With Pruett in the pits, that left Brazilian Roberto Moreno, driving a Swift Ford, as the only driver left on the track with the potential speed to sneak into the pole.</p>
<p>De Ferren waited in the pits, his eyes glued to a monitor that displayed lap times, as Moreno could manage no better than third fastest at 1:09.104.</p>
<p>&quot;My guys told me that he had a (fast) lap on his tires and I really didn't know what he had left,&quot; de Ferran said of Moreno's late charge at the pole.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't feel secure at all ... I was fairly anxious to the end,&quot; de Ferran admitted.</p>
<p>Alessandro Zanardi of Italy was fourth fastest in a Reynard Honda and rookie Dario Franchitti of Scotland posted the fifth fastest time in a Reynard Mercedes-Benz.</p>
<p>Twenty eight drivers qualified for the 77-lap, 161.7 mile (260 km) race.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
