<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645125" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NBA BASKETBALL-DENNIS RODMAN VOWS TO BE DENNIS RODMAN AGAIN.</title>
<headline>NBA BASKETBALL-DENNIS RODMAN VOWS TO BE DENNIS RODMAN AGAIN.</headline>
<byline>Gary Hill</byline>
<dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, Utah 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>No more Mr Nice Guy. Dennis Rodman plans to go back to his old outrageous ways.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to show face tomorrow,&quot; the Chicago Bulls' rebounding demon said before Saturday's practice for Game 4 of the NBA Finals on Sunday.</p>
<p>He still wears the multicolored hair, the tattoos, the body piercings, but on the court he has looked like a different Dennis Rodman the past three games.</p>
<p>Rodman's antics earned him a technical foul in every playoff game before the Finals, but once into the NBA championship series, he became a perfect gentleman.</p>
<p>The league's rebounding champion the last six seasons had an especially lackluster showing in the Bulls' loss to the Utah Jazz in Game 3, snagging just three rebounds and showing no intensity.</p>
<p>&quot;I wasn't performing well and wasn't doing the things that I normally do,&quot; said Rodman. &quot;I was just ineffective yesterday and let the team down completely.&quot;</p>
<p>There is always more than a little method to Rodman's madness, so he thinks he has to go back to his old tricks to get back his old fire.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to be Dennis Rodman and be wild and crazy and do the nutty things that got me in this position. I am trying to be a mild-mannered guy on the floor and I just can't seem to get in the flow of things without being crazy.&quot;</p>
<p>He promised: &quot;No matter what, if I foul out or get technicals, I've got to do my things to put a spark in things to get this team going. I am the spark plug of this team and I haven't been doing anything like that these last couple of games.&quot;</p>
<p>Bulls coach Phil Jackson agreed that the team looks for Rodman's spark.</p>
<p>&quot;We just talked to him about it in the locker room about how he has got to be out there as an energy motivator for us.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of times he provides us that source of energy that comes from the big guy in there that does some of the things that need to be done.</p>
<p>&quot;He's the kind of guy that plugs the lane for us and gets the rebound or makes the strip or a steal that changes the course of the game, and we need that,&quot; Jackson said.</p>
<p>&quot;He certainly didn't have his normal enthusiasm and energy and we expect it the next game,&quot; said teammate Michael Jordan. &quot;He brings so much energy to the game that it's infectious to us. Let's hope he can be ready for the next game.&quot;</p>
<p>The change in Rodman's intensity level was not lost on Chicago's All-Star forward Scottie Pippen.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm a little surprised because he's a great player, one of the greatest rebounders ever in the game, and he's not really showing that,&quot; said Pippen. &quot;He hasn't shown that throughout this series.&quot;</p>
<p>So does Pippen endorse the idea that Rodman should do something bizarre to get himself going? &quot;If it's going to get him to playing, getting 15 or 20 rebounds and being effective on the offensive boards, then yes, I endorse it.&quot;</p>
<p>Antoine &quot;Big Dog&quot; Carr said he and the other Jazz big men were not doing anything special to neutralise Rodman.</p>
<p>&quot;We are just trying to make sure we block everybody off of the boards and keep him away from there. That's his speciality and when you slow it down a little bit I think it takes a little bit away from his intensity.&quot;</p>
<p>Part of Rodman's problem may be that he has mostly been guarding the Greg Ostertags of the Jazz world rather than league Most Valuable Player Karl Malone, and the lesser challenge has left him a little deflated. But Jackson will have Rodman defending against Malone more on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;Tomorrow I will be playing Karl Malone and can get more involved in the offence and defence,&quot; Rodman said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Phil knows that I have to be active, more involved. I have to be tough. I have to do this and do that and he (Jackson) says 'Dennis, you have got to play Karl and get more involved and have some contact.'</p>
<p>&quot;I have to be in the middle banging around with the big guys,&quot; Rodman said.</p>
<p>There is one drawback to having Rodman guarding the muscular power forward who dominated Game 3. &quot;Dennis doesn't intimidate (Malone) at all,&quot; said Jackson.</p>
<p>But Rodman welcomes the challenge.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to put a lot of pressure on myself to perform,&quot; he said. &quot;I take all the blame, I've let my team down.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SALT LAKE CITY, Utah"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
