<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645121" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO: CRICKET-WINDIES OUTBAT SRI LANKA IN ONE-DAYER.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-WINDIES OUTBAT SRI LANKA IN ONE-DAYER.</headline>
<dateline>PORT OF SPAIN, Trinidad 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spirited half centuries from Sri Lankan batsmen Arjuna Ranatunga and Kumara Dharmasena failed to dent West Indies imposing total in their one-off limited overs match on Friday, and the home side won by 35 runs.</p>
<p>West Indies, put into bat and spearheaded by Stuart Williams and Brian Lara reached 283 for seven in their innings, reduced to 49 overs because of rain.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka, the World Cup holders, lost early wickets as they attempted the chase with opener Maravan Atapattu falling to Courtney Walsh for one and Aravinda de Silva to Curtly Ambrose for seven, both caught by Carl Hooper.</p>
<p>Hashan Tilllekeratne then fell to Laurie Williams for two, leaving the visitors in trouble at 39 for three.</p>
<p>A fourth-wicket parnership of 50 between Ranatunga, who scored 53 and opener Sanath Jayasuriya, who made 44, pulled Sri Lanka back but they were never pick up a an adequate scoring rate and ended their 49 overs with 248 for eight.</p>
<p>Earlier a scintillating third-wicket partnership of 124 between West Indies opener Williams, who made a one-day personal best total of 91 and Lara who thumped 68, put the home side in a commanding position.</p>
<p>The pair took the score from 46 for two to 170 for three before left-arm spinner Sanath Jayasuriya, who took five for 59, got the breakthrough.</p>
<p>Williams hit 12 fours in his 107 ball innings and Lara hit six fours and two sixes in his run-a-ball innings.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TRTO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="WEIND">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORT OF SPAIN, Trinidad"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
