<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645166" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: RALLYING-MAKINEN AND MCRAE CLASH IN ACROPOLIS.</title>
<headline>RALLYING-MAKINEN AND MCRAE CLASH IN ACROPOLIS.</headline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The duel between Tommi Makinen and Colin McRae resumes on Sunday as pressure mounts in the Acropolis Rally -- one of the toughest rounds of the world championship.</p>
<p>Finland's Makinen stormed to his third rally victory this year at Argentina in May, extending his lead at the top of the drivers' championship over McRae to six points.</p>
<p>The Mitsubishi driver has been buoyed by the resilience of his Lancer car during his last win on similar style roads, but differing conditions, to the Greek event.</p>
<p>&quot;The Lancer seems to be very competitive in all conditions and it has a good chance to score world championship points,&quot; Makinen said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have proved in Argentina that the car is also really good on twisty roads, which will help a lot.&quot;</p>
<p>Subaru driver McRae is equally confident, saying it is Makinen's turn to suffer in a title race.</p>
<p>A victory for McRae would equal Makinen's three wins this year, but both men are aware that this event will be tough on car and driver.</p>
<p>The rally has been moved forward from previous years and is likely to be even hotter than usual. As well as testing the stamina of the drivers, the dust and the roughness of the roads will highlight any car weaknesses.</p>
<p>&quot;We've got the strongest car for sure so this is never something we are concerned about.&quot; McRae said.</p>
<p>&quot;The big difference is the fact that the ground is a lot harder, more compacted, which is tough on tyres as well as cars.&quot;</p>
<p>Ford driver Carlos Sainz from Spain, who won here in 1990 and 1994, is lying joint third in the drivers' championship, 14 behind McRae who has 32 and 20 behind Makinen. Sainz and will again be partnered by four-times world champion Juha Kankkunen.</p>
<p>The rally begins on Sunday morning from the Acropolis for the first and longest leg of three. The cars head north beyond Kamena Vouria before the return dash to Athens, covering a total of 403 kilometres.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
