<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645179" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Reuters historical calendar - June 14.</title>
<headline>Reuters historical calendar - June 14.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the major events to have occurred on June 14 in history:</p>
<p>1645 - In the English Civil War, the Battle Of Naseby took place in Northamptonshire with the Parliamentarians under Oliver Cromwell and Sir Thomas Fairfax victorious over the Royalists, led by Prince Rupert of the Palatinate.</p>
<p>1777 - Congress adopted the &quot;Stars and Stripes&quot; as the official flag of the United States of America.</p>
<p>1789 - English Admiral Captain Bligh and 18 others, cast adrift from H.M.S. Bounty, eventually reached Timor in the East Indies after a voyage of nearly 4,000 miles in an open boat.</p>
<p>1798 - Frantisek Palacky, Czech historian, politician and campaigner for a separate Czech nation, born.</p>
<p>1800 - Napoleon defeated the Austrians at the Battle of Marengo, northern Italy, during the War of the Second Coalition.</p>
<p>1801 - Benedict Arnold, American general who shifted his allegiance to the British during the American Revolution, died in London.</p>
<p>1811 - Harriet Beecher Stowe, U.S. novelist famous for &quot;Uncle Tom's Cabin&quot;, born.</p>
<p>1839 - The first Henley Regatta took place on the River Thames in London.</p>
<p>1883 - Edward Fitzgerald, English poet best known for his &quot;Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam&quot;, died.</p>
<p>1919 - Sam Wanamaker, U.S. actor, director and producer, born. He was also the inspiration behind the rebuilding of Shakespeare's Globe Theatre on the River Thames in London.</p>
<p>1922 - President Warren G. Harding became the first U.S. president to broadcast by radio.</p>
<p>1928 - Ernesto &quot;Che&quot; Guevara, Cuban guerrilla leader, born in Argentina. He was executed in the Bolivian jungle in 1967.</p>
<p>1928 - Emmeline Pankhurst, English champion of women's rights, died. An act establishing voting equality for men and women was passed just after her death.</p>
<p>1936 - Maxim Gorky, Soviet short-story writer and novelist, died.</p>
<p>1940 - The German army entered and occupied Paris.</p>
<p>1941 - President Roosevelt ordered the freezing of all German and Italian assets in the U.S.</p>
<p>1946 - John Logie Baird, Scottish inventor who pioneered the development of television, died.</p>
<p>1962 - The European Space Research Organisation, later replaced by the European Space Agency, was established.</p>
<p>1966 - The Vatican announced the abolition of the Index of prohibited books.</p>
<p>1971 - The New York Times began publication of extracts from top-secret Pentagon papers on the Vietnam war.</p>
<p>1972 - A Japan Airlines DC-8 crashed at Delhi airport, killing 87 people.</p>
<p>1982 - In the Falkland Islands, the Argentine Military Commander signed a surrender document at Port Stanley.</p>
<p>1986 - Alan Jay Lerner, U.S. playwright and lyricist, died. With Frederick Lowe composed musicals such as &quot;My Fair Lady&quot; and &quot;Camelot&quot;.</p>
<p>1989 - Thousands of Bulgarian deportees poured into Turkey telling stories of brutal suppression of ethnic Turks by Bulgaria.</p>
<p>1989 - Former U.S. president Ronald Reagan was made an honorary knight by Queen Elizabeth.</p>
<p>1990 - Romanian President Ion Iliescu, backed by thousands of miners controlling the streets of Bucharest, vowed to round up leaders of a day of anti-government violence that tore the capital apart.</p>
<p>1993 - President Suleyman Demirel asked Tansu Ciller to form a new government, giving Moslem but secular Turkey its first woman prime minister.</p>
<p>1994 - Henry Mancini, U.S. composer of soundtracks for the &quot;Pink Panther&quot; movies, &quot;Days of Wine and Roses&quot; and dozens of other hit films, died.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
