<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645177" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britain's Blair to stage &quot;Talk to Tony&quot; shows.</title>
<headline>Britain's Blair to stage &quot;Talk to Tony&quot; shows.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's new Labour Prime Minister Tony Blair will stage regular question-and-answer sessions with members of the public, a government spokesman said on Saturday.</p>
<p>The first of the monthly 90-minute appearances will take place next Friday, when people in the English Midlands will have the chance to question Blair about law and order and juvenile crime.</p>
<p>The spokesman said the televised &quot;Talk to Tony&quot; sessions were intended to keep Blair in touch with what people were thinking and stop him developing a &quot;bunker mentality&quot;.</p>
<p>Blair has already come under fire for changing the way in which he can be questioned in the House of Commons and critics attacked the new public sessions as a means of avoiding expert questions from members of parliament and journalists.</p>
<p>But Blair has said that some of the toughest questions he faced during the election campaign came from members of the public.</p>
<p>Each of the planned sessions will revolve round a particular issue, although questioners will be able to bring up other matters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
