<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645154" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: TENNIS-MAJOLI WINS TITLE AS TIRED HINGIS FLOPS.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-MAJOLI WINS TITLE AS TIRED HINGIS FLOPS.</headline>
<byline>Robert Kitson</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Croatia's Iva Majoli won the French Open women's singles title amid extraordinary scenes at Roland Garros on Saturday after world number one Martina Hingis dramatically failed to live up to her advance billing.</p>
<p>A 6-4 6-2 victory earned Majoli, seeded ninth, the distinction of being the lowest-seeded player to win the French title in the Open era but the final will be remembered for the weak efforts of Hingis.</p>
<p>The Swiss 16-year-old, who became the youngest Grand Slam champion this century when she won the Australian Open in January, required lengthy attention both in the locker-rooms and on court during the second set but insisted she was simply tired at the end of a long tournament.</p>
<p>&quot;After two weeks I'm just at the end of my power. She just played an unbelievable match, it wasn't just because I was injured,&quot; said Hingis, previously unbeaten in 37 matches this year.</p>
<p>Hingis endured a tough three-set semifinal against Monica Seles on Thursday and was also involved in a marathon doubles encounter on Friday. Playing with Arantxa Sanchez Vicario, she lost 3-6 7-6 10-8 to Gigi Fernandez and Natasha Zvereva in the women's doubles semifinal.</p>
<p>All this, so soon after her five-week absence from the sport following a horse-riding accident in April which forced her to undergo minor knee surgery, clearly caught up with her at the worst possible moment.</p>
<p>It was her bad luck to find Majoli, who will rise to fifth in the world rankings next week, at the peak of her game and she was already a set and 3-2 down when she disappeared into the dressing-rooms for initial treatment.</p>
<p>She was absent for several minutes as officials made increasingly frantic efforts to get her back to centre court, and upon her return managed to win only three more points in the match.</p>
<p>At 5-2, with Majoli coolly practising a few serves to occupy herself, a WTA trainer made last-ditch efforts to ease apparent cramp in both Hingis's thighs with ice-packs, but the end was already in sight.</p>
<p>Majoli, 19, eventually claimed victory on her second match point after 79 minutes of fragmented action, becoming the first Croatian woman to secure a Grand Slam title.</p>
<p>&quot;She didn't play her best match today,&quot; acknowledged Majoli afterwards. &quot;But my plan was to keep her moving and concentrate on my serve. Today everything just worked and I guess God helped me a little bit.</p>
<p>&quot;It was the match of my life. This has always been my favourite Grand Slam. I've always dreamt of winning it and hopefully I'll have many more good years here.&quot;</p>
<p>At the prize giving ceremony, where Majoli picked up a winner's cheque for $654,115 and the trophy from ex-champion Chris Evert, Hingis had already recovered sufficiently to make a giggling speech in which she told Majoli to &quot;watch out&quot; in future.</p>
<p>&quot;I won 37 straight matches and you're the only one who's beaten me, so watch out,&quot; she said. Majoli smiled back and said she was sorry.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
