<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645183" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Oasis songwriter Noel Gallagher weds in Las Vegas.</title>
<headline>Oasis songwriter Noel Gallagher weds in Las Vegas.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Noel Gallagher, songwriter in the British rock band Oasis, has married his girlfriend Meg Matthews in a private ceremony in Las Vegas, his spokesman said on Saturday.</p>
<p>The couple had previously called off wedding plans in London after being besieged by the media.</p>
<p>&quot;Noel and Meg wanted a small private ceremony following the media intrusion last time they tried to wed in February,&quot; a spokesman for Oasis said.</p>
<p>Gallagher's brother Liam, who married his girlfriend Patsy Kensit in secret earlier this year, did not attend the ceremony at the Little Church of the West on Thursday.</p>
<p>Noel, 30 and Meg, 31 who works for a record company, were reported to have tied the knot to the sounds of songs by The Beatles rather than hymns.</p>
<p>Britain's Sun newspaper said the organist played &quot;Yesterday&quot; and &quot;All my Loving&quot; during the ceremony.</p>
<p>The outspoken Gallagher brothers have made Oasis one of Britain's most successful bands since the 1960s heyday of The Beatles. But their distaste for the media and reputation for partying and drug taking has earned them a reputation as the bad boys of British pop.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
