<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645172" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: HORN PLEDGES BETTER FUTURE AS SOCIALISTS CLOSE RANKS.</title>
<headline>HORN PLEDGES BETTER FUTURE AS SOCIALISTS CLOSE RANKS.</headline>
<byline>Duncan Shiels</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hungarian Prime Minister Gyula Horn ended a two-day conference of the Socialist Party (MSZP) he leads with promises of better times ahead and an appeal for the party to keep its cool ahead of elections next year.</p>
<p>&quot;For decades Hungary has never been able to find harmony,&quot; he told delegates. &quot;Now it has the chance to do so and it is our party's historic responsibilty to ensure that chance is taken. God forbid that we miss that opportunity.&quot;</p>
<p>In confident mood, Horn followed up on his opening speech to the conference in which he said the party could repeat its 1994 election victory in 1998 as the present economic policy would soon bear fruit and Hungary was about to be invited to join NATO and the European Union.</p>
<p>&quot;We can only be successful by improving the lot of ordinary people,&quot; he said. &quot;There can be no development and social stability without the Socialist Party.&quot;</p>
<p>Less than a year ahead of elections and following two years of austerity which have seen real wages fall 17 percent, the MSZP, the senior party of the governing coalition with the Free Democrats, is trailing two opposition parties in the polls</p>
<p>In April Horn was the 25th in a popularity survey featuring 26 politicians.</p>
<p>But as expected, recent criticism of Horn's leadership in Hungary's media was kept to a minimum during the conference, which had no power to take decisions on personnel changes.</p>
<p>The delegates did, however, pass a motion allowing the party's national executive to call a new congress either to extend the mandate of the current leadership beyond March 1998 or to organise a new mandate.</p>
<p>&quot;The mandate runs out next March and a congress has to be organised to extend or renew it,&quot; national executive chairman, Environment Minister Ferenc Baja told Reuters. &quot;It will be for the executive to choose the right political moment to make that decision. It depends a lot on when the elections are called.&quot;</p>
<p>Hungary's current parliamentary cycle is due to end in May 1998. Under the constitution President Arpad Goncz must call elections 60 days either side of that date.</p>
<p>Earlier, Finance Minister Peter Medgyessy, warned the party against making false promises to the electorate but said he was cautiously optimistic that an economic upturn would happen before the elections.</p>
<p>&quot;The economic policy has been a success but at the same time its (achievements) are still fragile. The danger is to overestimate the results and I would caution everyone against making unaffordable promises,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>After years of negative or minimal growth, Hungary expects gross domestic product to take off this year and to rise at an increasing pace of two to five percent on the next five years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
