<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645152" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: TENNIS-MAJOLI'S FONDEST DREAM COMES TRUE.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-MAJOLI'S FONDEST DREAM COMES TRUE.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Vignal</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iva Majoli found out that little girls' dreams sometimes come true by winning the French Open against all odds on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;Ever since I was little, I dreamt of winning here,&quot; said the 19-year-old Croat, after taming world number one Martina Hingis in straight sets in one of the biggest upsets in the recent history of women's tennis.</p>
<p>&quot;I like the atmosphere, the public, who have always been nice to me, and the red clay...I've always felt that if I could win a grand slam, I wanted it to be the French Open.&quot;</p>
<p>A clear underdog, the gifted but often somewhat erratic Majoli played a near-perfect match, using devastating forehands to wear down a tired Hingis.</p>
<p>&quot;I had to be aggressive and careful not to give Martina a chance of playing her game,&quot; she said. &quot;I felt the whole time I was in control.&quot;</p>
<p>Some felt that Majoli, described as a teenage sensation when she made her professional debut four years ago, was just another eternal hopeful, but on a day full of roses, she flowered at last.</p>
<p>Before the final, every female visitor had received a rose to celebrate the 100th anniversary of the women's competition of the Paris event.</p>
<p>That perhaps inspired Majoli, one in a long line of pupils of tennis guru Nick Bollettieri. She spent five years in his tennis academy in Bradenton, Florida, before deciding to return to live with her family in Croatia.</p>
<p>&quot;Nick is like my second dad,&quot; she said. &quot;He alway's been so kind to me. He was in the stands today and it was good to hear him say 'Come on'.&quot;</p>
<p>Majoli said that, unlike the 16-year-old Hingis, she had needed time before confirming how good she was.</p>
<p>&quot;When I was 16, I was like 13,&quot; she said. &quot;It's different for Martina, She already faces responsibilities and behaves like a grown-up. Nobody ever stopped me from doing other things like going out. Finally, last year, I decided I was ready and started to work really hard.&quot;</p>
<p>She still goes out now and again and was planning a special celebration after her unexpected triumph.</p>
<p>&quot;We'll go for dinner, then we'll just send home the older ones and party on,&quot; she said with a huge smile and her gleam in her eyes.</p>
<p>Among her most partisan fans on Saturday was her boyfriend.</p>
<p>&quot;He's been here for a few days but I didn't want him to come and see my matches because I didn't know how I would react,&quot; she said. &quot;He's been my prisoner. When I saw I was in the final, I released him.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if she had other dreams, Majoli said she had plenty but one in particular.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not putting any pressure on myself but I feel that I could fight with Martina, Monica and Steffi and, maybe, one day become number one,&quot; she said. &quot;That's a dream and that's my next goal.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
