<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645193" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO: Kabila agrees refugee probe as U.S. envoy visits.</title>
<headline>Kabila agrees refugee probe as U.S. envoy visits.</headline>
<byline>Matthew Tostevin</byline>
<dateline>LUBUMBASHI, Congo 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Laurent Kabila told U.S. envoy Bill Richardson on Saturday that his Democratic Republic of Congo would cooperate with a commission investigating the fate of Rwandan Hutu refugees in the country.</p>
<p>Richardson, Washington's ambassador to the United Nations, told reporters after talks with Kabila in the southern mining capital of Lubumbashi that an advance team would arrive by June 20 and would start investigating massacre reports by July 7.</p>
<p>&quot;This commission which is investigating these so-called massacres, let it come,&quot; Kabila told journalists travelling with Richardson. &quot;We are ready to put all facilities at its disposal... (but) the inquiry must be conducted in a way that respects our sovereignty.&quot;</p>
<p>Richardson welcomed Kabila's comments.</p>
<p>&quot;I was very pleased that President Kabila rassured me of his government's commitment to international humanitarian law and to prosecute any violators,&quot; he said. &quot;This is a major breakthrough ...we have made major progress on the human rights and humanitarian front.&quot;</p>
<p>Richardson flew on to Kisangani, where international concern about the plight of Rwandan Hutu refugees has coloured Kabila's takeover.</p>
<p>The refugees are the rump of over a million who fled Rwanda fearing reprisals in 1994 after Hutu hardliners slaughtered hundreds of thousands of minority Tutsis.</p>
<p>The U.N. refugee agency says some 815,000 have returned home since last November, while 46,000 have been found and about 247,000 remain unaccounted for.</p>
<p>Kabila's main allies are Tutsis from Rwanda. The refugees include many civilians but also fighters of Rwanda's former Hutu army who were blamed for the genocide.</p>
<p>Richardson was heading a team of over a dozen experts from different branches of the U.S. administration, who will brief Kabila's government on international expectations.</p>
<p>&quot;They will be sticking close to the ministers and advising them what the international community wants to see -- but not really telling them what to do,&quot; one U.S. official told Reuters.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said that the initiative was unprecedented for Africa and resembled something Washington organised for Eastern Europe following the collapse of Soviet Communism there.</p>
<p>Richardson and Kabila met at the Lubumbashi offices of the state mining giant Gecamines. &quot;We are here with a broad delegation... we are eager to have a dialogue,&quot; Richardson said.</p>
<p>His team included representatives from departments such as defence, treasury and commerce, together with aid and human rights experts.</p>
<p>Richardson was at the centre of diplomatic efforts to ensure what he called a &quot;soft landing&quot; when Kabila's forces arrived in Kinshasa, the capital of the former Zaire on May 17, one day after veteran dictator Mobutu Sese Seko fled the city.</p>
<p>Kabila and his Alliance of Democratic Forces ousted Mobutu after a seven-month civil war. Mobutu had ruled since a 1965 military coup.</p>
<p>Kabila proclaimed himself president with sweeping powers but has promised elections by April 1999.</p>
<p>Former Zaire, plundered by Mobutu and his cronies, is potentially one of Africa's richest nations with a wealth of minerals, hydroelectric energy and rich farmland.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RWANDA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUBUMBASHI, Congo"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
