<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645191" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>CONGO: Congo Brazzaville premier says killing must stop.</title>
<headline>Congo Brazzaville premier says killing must stop.</headline>
<byline>Helen Vesperini</byline>
<dateline>BRAZZAVILLE 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The prime minister of Congo Brazzaville called on Saturday for a halt to political and communal clashes rocking the capital and said President Pascal Lissouba would accept mediation and dialogue to end the crisis.</p>
<p>Charles David Ganao told state radio that Lissouba had accepted a mediation offer from Gabon's veteran president, Omar Bongo, and that a broad-based consultation between the government and the country's political class could begin as early as Sunday.</p>
<p>The appeal followed a third day of firefights and looting in Brazzaville in a standoff pitting supporters of ex-president Denis Sassou Nguesso against soldiers loyal to Lissouba and political and ethnic rivals ahead of a planned July 27 presidential election.</p>
<p>&quot;Peace today is seriously disturbed. The Congolese have started killing each other again,&quot; Ganao said, a reference to 1993 political and ethnic clashes among ethnic and political militias that killed at least 2,000 people in the city.</p>
<p>Shortly before he spoke, witnesses reported an exchange of fire around the presidential palace. Lissouba's whereabouts were not clear. One unconfirmed report said he was upcountry.</p>
<p>Ganao said that the election had to go ahead, adding that Lissouba had agreed to mediation by Bongo and national dialogue proposed by Brazzaville mayor and presidential hopeful Bernard Kolelas in the name of the Congolese political family.</p>
<p>&quot;The dialogue could begin tomorrow,&quot; he said, adding that international mediation would probably begin by June 10 depending on the heads of states' other commitments.</p>
<p>&quot;To advance towards these two meetings in serenity I call for all weapons to fall silent, I call for the immediate end of looting and all acts that dishonour the Congolese people,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A senior police officer said fighting mainly pitted gunmen from Sassou Nguesso's Mboshi tribe and members of the Kouyou tribe of former president and prime minister Jacques Joachim Yhombi Opango, Lissouba's campaign manager. &quot;There are many dead and wounded on both sides,&quot; the police officer told Reuters.</p>
<p>Fighting between supporters of Sassou Nguesso and Yhombi Opango in the north has killed 16 people in under a month.</p>
<p>The latest standoff began on Thursday when troops surrounded the northern suburban home of Sassou Nguesso, a former Marxist military leader named president in 1979 but voted out of office in 1992 after the advent of democratic reform.</p>
<p>Sassou Nguesso has accused Lissouba of fomenting violence to postpone the election. Officials said troops had gone there to arrest members of his entourage on murder charges in connection with the incidents in the north but they resisted.</p>
<p>Earlier, Lissouba's government ordered a crackdown on private militias and unauthorised possession of weapons.</p>
<p>There was no reliable death toll although police sources spoke of several dozen. Witnesses reported at least a dozen bodies in the streets on Friday. The senior police officer said 22 members of a police rapid intervention squad, including their commanders, were killed in a clash on Friday.</p>
<p>Lissouba, Sassou Nguesso and 1992 runner-up Kolelas are likely to be the front-runners among about a dozen hopefuls on July 27, if the polls take place. Kolelas's supporters control southern suburbs on the Congo River.</p>
<p>International telephone links were down. Telephone contacts remained possible through residents plugged into the mobile telephone network in Laurent Kabila's Congo to the south.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GABON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRAZZAVILLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
