<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645180" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's wartime bouncing bombs recovered from sea.</title>
<headline>UK's wartime bouncing bombs recovered from sea.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>British army engineers on Saturday recovered three prototypes of revolutionary bouncing bombs used in one of the most spectacular air attacks of of World War Two..</p>
<p>The cylindrical bombs, test models of those used in 1943 to attack dams in Germany's industrial heartland in the Ruhr valley, were found in the sea near Herne Bay, Kent, on Britain's south-east coast.</p>
<p>The bouncing bomb, invented by Barnes Wallis, were immortalised in the 1954 film &quot;The Dambusters&quot; as one of Britain's biggest triumphs in the war against Hitler's Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;Some people may ask why we are doing this after so long, but this is part of our military heritage and I feel it is important that we do not leave these bombs just rusting in the sea,&quot; said army spokesman Captain Alan Conroy.</p>
<p>&quot;They are still intact and many of the threads and bolts are still workable. The technology used at a time when resources and time was in short supply to develop these bombs is really incredible,&quot; Conroy said.</p>
<p>The bombs, which experts say may still contain explosives, were spotted just off the coast at low tide. They are destined for military museums once they have been made safe and cleaned.</p>
<p>The bombs were fixed to a device which made them spin and bounce across the surface of water when dropped from a plane.</p>
<p>They were devised for a 1943 bombing mission to breach dams in the Ruhr, creating a flood which damaged German power supplies and disrupted war industries.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
