<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645171" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: SADC STATES ACCUSED OF BLOCKING FREE TRADE TREATY.</title>
<headline>SADC STATES ACCUSED OF BLOCKING FREE TRADE TREATY.</headline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The five members of the Southern African Customs Union (SACU) came under fire on Saturday from fellow-members of a wider regional bloc who accused them of blocking ratification of a free trade protocol.</p>
<p>SACU members South Africa, Botswana, Namibia, Lesotho and Swaziland are also members of the 12-state Southern African Development Community (SADC), which is holding a trade workshop in Cape Town this weekend for regional members of parliament.</p>
<p>The other SADC members are Angola, Mozambique, Zimbabwe, Zambia, Malawi, Tanzania and Mauritius.</p>
<p>The 12 SADC states last September approved a trade protocol which will take effect once it has been ratified by eight members.</p>
<p>Once that happens the aim is to phase in a free trade area within eight years, but so far only Tanzania and Mauritius have ratified the treaty.</p>
<p>A delegate from Mauritius, Pradeep Jeeha, told the meeting on Saturday that the SACU states were likely to act as a bloc within SADC and could between them prevent implementation of the trade protocol.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm very concerned... (the smaller SACU states) will probably align themselves with the South African position and they will ratify only when South Africa does,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>South Africa's partners in SACU benefit from a system of pooled trade revenues. Lesotho for example, depends on the pool for more than 50 percent of its total revenue.</p>
<p>The customs union was set up about 100 years ago but renegotiation of the agreement began after South Africa's first democratic government was elected in 1994.</p>
<p>A Zambian delegate to the Cape Town meeting, Bob Sichinga, said aspects of the SACU agreement discriminated against non- SACU members of SADC.</p>
<p>&quot;We in Zambia are liberalising our markets so much that the immpact as been the flooding of our country by products from SACU,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Sichinga said that Zambian jobs had been lost as a result and as a member of parliament he found it difficult to justify to his constituency such sacrifices in the interests of an unequal treaty.</p>
<p>South African delegate Rob Davies said criticism of SACU appeared to be based partly on misunderstandings. He said South Africa supported the rapid ratification of the SADC trade protocol.</p>
<p>On Friday, South African officials said the country was wary of ratifying the protocol before it had more concrete details. They said further consultation was needed within the country but that ratification might be considered towards the end of the yar.</p>
<p>-- Cape Town newsroom +2721 403-2502</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BOTS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LESOT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MAURTN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NAMIB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWAZD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TANZA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAMBIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
