<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645176" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Anger as girl, 12, held in Isle of Man prison.</title>
<headline>Anger as girl, 12, held in Isle of Man prison.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-06-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Human rights campaigners on Saturday condemned authorities in the Isle of Man for allowing a 12-year-old girl suffering from spina bifida to be held in prison used to house adult inmates.</p>
<p>The girl, who has not been named, is on remand in the women and young offenders annex of the prison complex in the Manx capital Douglas after having been accused of assaulting social workers.</p>
<p>Manx officials said the girl would appear in court on Wednesday and was likely to be granted bail. Magistrates had not been aware the girl suffered from spina bifida, a congenital defect of the spinal cord, when she was ordered to be held on remand.</p>
<p>The Manx Council for Civil Liberty demanded an investigation of the case by the United Nations.</p>
<p>&quot;Our concern in this matter is further heightened by the recent revelation that the so-called segregated young offenders annex of the prison is also used on occasion to house adult prisoners,&quot; the council said in a letter to the U.N. Committee on the Rights of the Child.</p>
<p>Manx authorities said that while the island's law provided for the imprisonment of children as young as 12 in exceptional circumstances, the girl in this case had been strictly segregated from adult prisoners.</p>
<p>The Isle of Man, a dependency of the British crown located in the Irish Sea off northwestern England, has a reputation for taking a hard line on law and order.</p>
<p>The death penalty was only abolished in 1993 and punishment by the birch remains on the statute book.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
