<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645196" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: Dissident Kenyan politician forced back to Germany.</title>
<headline>Dissident Kenyan politician forced back to Germany.</headline>
<byline>Manoah Esipisu</byline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Kenyan dissident politician was refused entry to the country on Saturday and three opposition politicians were beaten by security officers as they waited to greet him, one of them told a news conference.</p>
<p>Sheikh Khalid Balala, a radical Moslem preacher and a leading voice of dissent against the government of President Daniel arap Moi, was forced to return to Germany after being turned back at the coastal resort of Mombasa.</p>
<p>State-run Kenyan radio quoted Coast provincial police chief Francis Gichuki as saying Balala flew into Mombasa &quot;illegally&quot; from Frankfurt aboard a German airliner on Saturday morning and was forced to fly out on the same plane two hours later.</p>
<p>Gichuki said police acted on a tip-off and blocked attempts by Balala to forcefully disembark.</p>
<p>Leading opposition politician Raila Odinga, limping and complaining of shoulder pains, said he and colleagues Kenneth Matiba and Ngengi Muigai, were beaten in a &quot;beastly manner&quot; by security officers at the airport.</p>
<p>He told reporters in Nairobi Matiba was unable to return to the capital because he needed urgent medical attention.</p>
<p>Reporters in Mombasa said Odinga and Matiba forced their way to the airport tarmac to try to stop the plane taking off. They were removed by paramilitary police and held for an hour after the plane had left, they added.</p>
<p>Odinga and his colleagues were beaten by gun butts as well as police truncheons, the reporters told Reuters by telephone.</p>
<p>President Moi, aged 73 and in power since 1978, must call elections in 1997 pitting the ruling KANU party against an opposition fractured mainly along ethnic and personal lines.</p>
<p>Odinga and Matiba on Friday announced that opposition groups would hold nine rallies across Kenya on June 21 to press for minimum constitutional reforms before the elections.</p>
<p>Riots erupted in Nairobi last weekend when police broke up a banned opposition rally. Moi has said he plans no meaningful constitutional reforms until after the elections.</p>
<p>The National Convention Assembly (NCA), the coalition of opposition parties, churches, and human rights group leading the campaign for change, had earlier called a rally in Mombasa this weekend but put it back to June 21 on logistics grounds.</p>
<p>The NCA wants the review or repeal of six laws including the Public Order Act, which it sees as an instrument of suppression. It also demands greater access to state-controlled media.</p>
<p>Balala flew into Kenya from Germany, where he has lived for the past two years. His passport had expired while he was away and Kenya's embassy in Bonn refused to renew it. Kenyan radio said his travel documents were not valid but gave no details.</p>
<p>Immigration officials said Balala, with a Kenyan mother and Yemeni father, automatically gave up his Kenyan citizenship when he failed to renounce his Yemeni citizenship at the age of 21.</p>
<p>Odinga said Balala was not allowed to leave the aircraft at Mombasa. &quot;The reason for making Balala stateless is political; mainly because of his stand (against the government). The Kenyan government is sending him to Germany knowing very well that he is not a German citizen. This is a beastly act,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
