<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645130" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NBA BASKETBALL-FIREWORKS AND EARPLUGS SPELL HOME VICTORY FOR JAZZ.</title>
<headline>NBA BASKETBALL-FIREWORKS AND EARPLUGS SPELL HOME VICTORY FOR JAZZ.</headline>
<dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, Utah 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Delta Centre is considered the loudest arena in the NBA, and that's just the way the Utah Jazz like it.</p>
<p>Before Friday's Game 3, the Jazz set off deafening fireworks inside the building and released thousands of balloons -- which promptly had to be popped, by fans and at least one Delta Centre worker with a knife.</p>
<p>&quot;You saw it tonight, It helps us tremendously,&quot; said bench hero Greg Foster after the 104-93 win that reduced the Chicago Bulls' lead in the best-of-seven series to 2-1. &quot;We have a lot of confidence playing here at home.</p>
<p>&quot;And the fans are very knowledgeable about the game, they really get after it. This is the only show in town, and they're behind us all the way.&quot;</p>
<p>Salt Lake City is the smallest city to boast an NBA team, but the Jazz -- cheered on by their screaming fans -- were the league's best team at home, losing just three games all season including the playoffs.</p>
<p>&quot;Energy-wise they're a different ball club at home,&quot; said Chicago coach Phil Jackson. &quot;Obviously, this crowd is outrageous, what they do before the game is totally beyond limits.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm bringing earplugs the next time before the game starts so I don't get hearing loss, or else I'm going to sue this organisation for hearing loss.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SALT LAKE CITY, Utah"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
