<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645157" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: TENNIS-ANALYSIS OF HINGIS V MAJOLI FINAL.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-ANALYSIS OF HINGIS V MAJOLI FINAL.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Analysis of Saturday's French Open women's singles final between top seed Martina Hingis of Switzerland and ninth seed Iva Majoli of Croatia, won 6-4 6-2 by Majoli.</p>
<p>First set: MAJOLI 6-4 (40 MINUTES)</p>
<p>Hot favourite Hingis made a sluggish start, losing the first two points of the match and struggled to hold her serve. The fifth game was especially telling as the Swiss had to save six break points before leading 3-2. Majoli, looking more relaxed, dictated the game thanks to her powerful forehand and she finally broke the world number one in the seventh game before winning her service game to love to lead 5-3. Serving for the set in the 10th game, Majoli took it after a long and tense rally which left Hingis breathless.</p>
<p>Second set: MAJOLI 6-2 (38 MINUTES)</p>
<p>Hingis, struggling with her first serve, looked more and more distressed and Majoli had three more break points in the first game of the set, which she failed to convert. But the Croat, far more powerful than her opponent, broke her again in the fifth set to lead 3-2. The 16-year-old then left the court for a few minutes and was booed on her return from the dressing rooms. Hingis lost her cool in the sixth game and was warned for racquet abuse after losing the game. She went 5-2 down before asking for another three-minute break in order to receive medical assistance. Majoli, serving for the match, did not lose her momentum and she became the first Croat to win a Grand Slam tournament in yet another upset in Paris this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
