<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645216" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Pope gives thanks for surviving assassination bid.</title>
<headline>Pope gives thanks for surviving assassination bid.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>ZAKOPANE, Poland 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul on Saturday emotionally recalled the day in 1981 when he was nearly killed by a would-be assassin's bullet and he thanked his countrymen for praying for his life to be spared.</p>
<p>The 77-year-old Pontiff made the rare public mention of his narrow escape from death before bidding farewell to his beloved native southern Polish highlands and travelling to Krakow during a demanding day that left him visibly exhausted.</p>
<p>The Pope will spend three days based mainly in Krakow, where he studied secretly for the priesthood during World War Two, was ordained and served as priest, bishop and cardinal.</p>
<p>He travels from there to Rome on Tuesday after his 11-day trip.</p>
<p>In the morning the Pope, ending three days in the mountain town of Zakopane, inaugurated a church built by local people in gratitude to the Madonna of Fatima for saving his life.</p>
<p>&quot;The history of this church is linked to the event which took place in St Peter's Square on May 13, 1981,&quot; the Pope said in a sermon.</p>
<p>&quot;At that time I experienced great mortal danger and suffering but also the great mercy of God,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Turkish gunman Mehmet Ali Agca shot him in the hand and abdomen in St Peter's Square as the Pontiff was riding in an open jeep before thousands of people at his general audience.</p>
<p>Emergency surgery saved his life. Agca, whom the Pope later forgave publicly and visited in jail, was wrestled to the ground by pilgrims and is serving a life sentence in Italy.</p>
<p>The Pope believes that his life was spared through the intercession of the Madonna of Fatima, because the shooting took place on the anniversary of the day in 1917 when she is said to have appeared for the first of six times to three poor Portuguese shepherd children.</p>
<p>&quot;By the intercession of Our Lady of Fatima, my life was given back to me. During my stay in hospital I was the object of a great outpouring of human kindness from all parts of the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The assassination attempt against the Pope is one of the enduring mysteries among the great crimes of the 20th century.</p>
<p>At a major trial in 1986 Italian prosecutors failed to prove their charges that the Bulgarian secret services had hired Agca on behalf of the Soviet Union in order to snuff out the Pope's support for the Solidarity union in his homeland.</p>
<p>At the time, Solidarity was threatening the stability of the Soviet bloc and the Pope reportedly told the late Soviet leader Leonid Brezhnev that if Moscow invaded Poland he would support resistance.</p>
<p>The so-called &quot;Bulgarian Connection&quot; trial ended with an &quot;acquittal for lack of sufficient evidence&quot; of three Turks and three Bulgarians charged with conspiring along with Agca.</p>
<p>After stopping to say a rosary before around 150,000 highlanders and pilgrims in the village of Ludzmierz, the Pope flew by helicopter in the evening to Krakow.</p>
<p>The Pope, formerly Cardinal Karol Wojtyla, landed at what remains of the Solvay factory where he worked in a stone quarry and an office during the Nazi wartime occupation.</p>
<p>Most of the factory has been demolished except one red-brick building which now bears a plaque, marking where the &quot;labourer Wojtyla&quot; worked for nearly three years.</p>
<p>The Pope's first stop in Krakow, which he has visited four times on past trips as Pontiff, was a church where his tiredness showed as he climbed steps to the sanctuary using his cane and assisted by aides. But he read a brief address to a group of nuns in a relatively strong voice.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAKOPANE, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
