<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645298" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>MOROCCO: Morocco arrests 67 opposition activists - rights group.</title>
<headline>Morocco arrests 67 opposition activists - rights group.</headline>
<dateline>RABAT 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Moroccan police arrested 67 opposition political activists for their campaign to boycott local elections due on June 13, a human rights group said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;A group of 67 militants, members of the opposition Avant-Garde Democratique Socialiste party (PADS), were arrested by police in 10 provinces while campaigning for the boycott of communal elections,&quot; a spokesman for the independent Moroccan Human Rights Association said.</p>
<p>Among Morocco's dozen active parties, the PADS was the only opposition group to call for the boycott of local elections.</p>
<p>&quot;Most of the arrested militants will be presented before the court of justice and tried next week,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Contacted by Reuters, a PADS leader said the arrests aimed at &quot;preventing&quot; the party from expressing its point of view on the elections.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;This is a real terror...a violation of speech freedom and basic principles of human rights,&quot; Ahmed Benjelloun, a prominent lawyer and leader of PADS said.</p>
<p>Interior ministry officials were not immediately available for comment.</p>
<p>Campaigning for the elections, which started on May 29, will end on June 12.</p>
<p>More than 102,000 candidates are expected to compete for 24,253 seats in Morocco's local council elections.</p>
<p>A group of 14,447 candidates are standing as independents. The remainder come from 12 political parties.</p>
<p>Local elections are the first of a series which will be capped by a parliamentary poll in September, with a new bicameral parliament being inaugurated by King Hassan on the second Friday of October.</p>
<p>Under the new constitution, the Lower House of parliament will be directly elected through universal suffrage.</p>
<p>Local councils will elect around 80 percent of the members of new Upper House of Parliament being set up under constitutional reforms approved last September.</p>
<p>The new house will have power to vote a no-confidence motion in the government and could topple it.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RABAT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MOROCCO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
