<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645235" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria closes ranks in fight against crime.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria closes ranks in fight against crime.</headline>
<byline>Liliana Semerdjieva</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgaria's new government, which took office last month vowing to stem corruption, met top police, intelligence, customs and justice officials on Saturday to discuss how to combat organised crime.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to equalise our criteria in the fight against crime and that is the main goal of our national meeting,&quot; Interior Minister Bogomil Bonev told reporters before the closed-door meeting attended by Prime Minister Ivan Kostov.</p>
<p>National Intelligence Service Director Boiko Rashkov said security services and legal authorities needed to close ranks &quot;to achieve more serious results in the fight against crime&quot;.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Kostov, whose Union of Democratic Forces government took over on May 21 after winning April general elections, appealed to deputies in parliament on Friday to tighten anti-crime laws.</p>
<p>He suggested specific amendments to the criminal code and said there was a need to combat economic crime by revamping laws related to fraud and embezzlement, tax evasion, unlawful insurance sales and misuse of official duties in the privatisation process.</p>
<p>Officials say the Bulgarian legal system has only a limited ability to fight organised crime and security services and the prosecutors office have been hampered by inadequate legislation. Organised crime has flourished in the seven years since the collapse of communism in the Balkan country.</p>
<p>Justice and European Legislative Integration Minister Vassil Gotsev said on Saturday amendments in several laws were almost ready.</p>
<p>&quot;The first amendments which the government will discuss on Monday will be the insurance law. The next laws will be the criminal code and the law for ill-gotten gains,&quot; Gotsev told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Thus we will establish a legislative basis which will be effective in the fight against crime in line with the European Union legal codes and the world democratic standards,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
