<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645222" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Foreign troops may stay in Albania to September.</title>
<headline>Foreign troops may stay in Albania to September.</headline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>International troops safeguarding security in Albania ahead of elections at the end of June could stay on until September, a spokesman for the Italian-led force said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Albanian television said the national unity government had agreed to ask the international community to extend the force's mandate by three months from June 28.</p>
<p>&quot;It is obvious that the mandate will be extended,&quot;, said the spokesman, Lieutenant-Colonel Giovanni Bernardi, but for how long was not yet clear.</p>
<p>The force, made up of troops from 10 European countries, had been due to move out on the day before the first round of polling.</p>
<p>Its mandate was set by the United Nations Security Council, but a Rome-based steering committee of all the participating countries may make a recommendation on its extension, Bernardi said.</p>
<p>Albanians are to vote in early parliamentary elections on June 29 after months of disruption triggered by the collapse of fraudulent savings schemes early this year.</p>
<p>Tension have been mounting as polling day approaches. Incidents this week included a failed attempt on the life of President Sali Berisha at an election rally.</p>
<p>The interim nine-party government of Socialist Prime Minister Bashkim Fino, formed in March to guide the country to elections, plans to step up security during the campaigning period, the television said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
