<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645242" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>PERU: Peru sets up army bases to flush out rebel leaders.</title>
<headline>Peru sets up army bases to flush out rebel leaders.</headline>
<byline>Saul Hudson</byline>
<dateline>LIMA 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Peru's army has set up bases in one of the most inaccessible areas of the jungle highlands in an operation to flush Maoist Shining Path rebel leaders from their hide-outs, President Alberto Fujimori said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;Vizcatan -- a remote zone in (the highland department of) Ayacucho -- is the scene where an army battalion ... night and day works to locate the whereabouts of certain Shining Path terrorists,&quot; Fujimori said in a speech.</p>
<p>A force of 200 soldiers has ringed Vizcatan with the goal of capturing Shining Path's comander-in-the-field Oscar Ramirez, who moves constantly around the area, guarded by about a dozen escorts, security forces sources said.</p>
<p>Shining Path also deploys in the zone an armed force of about 40 members, who frequently leave the rugged mountains to gather supplies for their leader, alias &quot;Feliciano,&quot; the sources said.</p>
<p>Rather than hunt down Ramirez, in these mountains, the army has identified the rebels' supply routes and plan to prevent food and medicine reaching the ill leader and force him to abandon the region, the sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;Comrade Feliciano&quot; suffers from a rare skin disease that has left his body riddled with parasites and will eventually kill him if the rebel is not treated, they added.</p>
<p>Vizcatan -- so isolated it is not named on maps -- lies on the edge of the central jungle forest 360 miles (570 km) east of Lima and two days walk from the nearest road accessible to motor vehicles at the source of the river Apurimac.</p>
<p>According to Peru's armed forces chief Nicolas Hermoza, the area is Shining Path's &quot;last refuge,&quot; but is &quot;impenetrable&quot; due to its extreme cold and ruggid terrain.</p>
<p>The push to capture the leader began after the violent end to Peru's hostage crisis, which saw the smaller rebel group, the Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement (MRTA), held 72 hostage for four months at the Japanese ambassador's home.</p>
<p>Following the security forces' April 22 hostage rescue, which reduced the MRTA to a largely spent force with the deaths of all 14 hostage-takers, the military has concentrated on trying to dismantle the Shining Path.</p>
<p>Last month, over a hundred soldiers swept through Shining Path strongholds in the Huallaga jungle valley, capturing two key rebels and a huge arms haul.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PERU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LIMA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PERU"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
