<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645266" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Nava Finance denies merger deal off.</title>
<headline>Nava Finance denies merger deal off.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thailand's Nava Finance and Securities Plc denied on Saturday it had scrapped a merger deal with other finance firms in favour of becoming a target of a commercial bank takeover, a company statement said.</p>
<p>Nava, which is an affiliate of Thai Military Bank, signed a memorandum of understanding with six other finance companies in April to jointly apply for a banking licence. These firms included CMIC Finance and Securities Plc, Thaimex Finance and Securities Plc, Thai Thanakorn Finance Plc and three other unlisted companies.</p>
<p>The Bank of Thailand, in a move to consolidate the ailing financial sector, has encouraged consolidation among Thailand's finance and securities companies and offered merging firms the chance to apply for a new commercial banking licence.</p>
<p>But some local press reported on Friday that Thai Military Bank had proposed a radical plan to take over affiliates -- excluding CMIC which is an affiliate of Thai Farmers Bank -- in return for incentives to broaden financial services.</p>
<p>&quot;These reports were factually wrong. The plan is making progress and the group is waiting for new guidelines from the Finance Ministry which would streamline the procedures and make the merger easier,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The recent collapse of merger deal between cash-strapped Finance One Plc and medium-sized Thai Danu Bank Ltd, billed a trailblazer for the rest of the sector, has raised doubts whether the government's attempt to ride out the current financial crisis through mergers and acquisitions will work.</p>
<p>-- Bangkok newsroom (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
