<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645224" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: Presidents urge swift but cautious EU integration.</title>
<headline>Presidents urge swift but cautious EU integration.</headline>
<byline>Steve Pagani</byline>
<dateline>PORTOROZ, Slovenia 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Eight central European presidents on Saturday backed the swift integration of ex-communist states into the European Union and NATO to put a final end to decades of division that tore the continent apart.</p>
<p>While the two-day meeting of heads of state on the Slovenian Adriatic coast was full of the usual idealistic chat about a united Europe, there were also some pointed words of caution.</p>
<p>Slovenian President Milan Kucan, hosting the meetings in the resorts of Portoroz and Piran, said closer integration was both crucial and desirable, but a nation's identity should not be lost in the scramble for unity.</p>
<p>Slovenia won independence from federal Yugoslavia in 1991 and many of its two million citizens are wary of joining what they believe will be another federation, this time ruled from Brussels and not Belgrade.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important that a state keeps its national identity. This is the most important part of this context,&quot; Kucan told a news conference attended by the seven other presidents.</p>
<p>Kucan was joined by the heads of states of three EU member countries -- Austria, Germany and Italy -- and former Warsaw Pact states the Czech Republic, Hungary, Poland and Slovakia.</p>
<p>Slovenian leaders are still hoping that the Alpine state may be included in the first wave of eastward expansion of the NATO military alliance.</p>
<p>NATO leaders meet in Madrid in July to invite new candidates to join the 16-nation defence pact and the Czech Republic, Hungary and Poland are almost guaranteed to be on the list. The same three nations are certain candidates for a fresh round of EU enlargement, expected to begin with a signing of a treaty at an EU summit in Amsterdam in nine days' time.</p>
<p>President Michal Kovac of Slovakia, which has little chance of being included in the first wave of EU and NATO expansion, warned Western leaders not to leave countries on the sidelines for too long, warning that isolation could create a breeding ground for nationalism.</p>
<p>&quot;Transition problems (in former communist states) could lead to a country to be left to the second and third rounds of enlargement,&quot; Kovac said. &quot;But this could stimulate the old ideas of nationalism...which could jeopardise respect for human dignity and human rights.&quot;</p>
<p>Kovac is at odds with Slovak Prime Minister Vladimir Meciar, who has come under international criticism for lack of democratic reform in his country.</p>
<p>While the focus of the Slovenia talks was on expansion, Austrian President Thomas Klestil said current EU members were having problems themselves getting the message of closer integration within the bloc over to their citizens.</p>
<p>&quot;Two-thirds of Austrians were in favour of the EU (in a referendum) but that atmosphere has changed and we have to ask why,&quot; Klestil said, adding that the merits of a single currency were hard to explain to people hurting from economic belt-tightening.</p>
<p>The presidents held a last round of talks while cruising along the Slovenian coast in a catamaran before leaving the country. The fifth annual meeting of central European presidents was expected to take place next year in either Slovakia or Italy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTOROZ, Slovenia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
