<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645229" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish right expects election boost from Pope trip.</title>
<headline>Polish right expects election boost from Pope trip.</headline>
<byline>Jan Strupczewski</byline>
<dateline>ZAKOPANE, Poland 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pope John Paul's current visit to his native Poland will boost the chances of opposition rightist parties in September's parliamentary polls, the leader of the biggest such group said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Marian Krzaklewski, head of a rightist alliance clustered around the pro-Catholic Solidarity trade union, said the Pope's homilies would bring about a &quot;moral renewal&quot; and convince many Poles to support politicians representing Christian values.</p>
<p>In what some Poles interpreted as a gesture of support for Solidarity, the Pope blessed Krzaklewski at the end of a televised open-air mass in Zakopane on Friday, when the Solidarity leader came to the altar and knelt before him.</p>
<p>Krzaklewski, an ardent Catholic, said the Pope had given him words of encouragement like those he and a Solidarity delegation received during a pilgrimage to Rome this year.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pope told me: 'Hold fast -- hold fast and don't let go'&quot;, Krzaklewski said.</p>
<p>&quot;I thanked the Holy Father for all his homilies and his visit and said that we will pray... that he may lead the Church and the world into the third millenium,&quot; Krzaklewski said.</p>
<p>In public during the trip the Pope has avoided being drawn into politics, although he has strongly condemned abortion which is also opposed by Solidarity, but which is legal under a 1996 law backed by the secular-minded ruling ex-communists.</p>
<p>He has met top ex-communists, including President Aleksander Kwasniewski, who asked him at the outset of the trip to build bridges rather than walls in Polish society.</p>
<p>Ex-communist politicians have expressed relief at the Pope's public statements, contrasting them with overtly political attacks on the left by Polish bishops.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite the expectations of some of our politicians and foreign commentators, there has been no 'clash' between the Pope and the ruling left,&quot; wrote Dariusz Szymczycha, editor of the Trybuna daily which is linked with the ruling party.</p>
<p>But Krzaklewski said the Papal trip would bring about a moral renewal among politicians and voters.</p>
<p>&quot;This moral renewal will mean that voters will elect those people who...represent Christian values,&quot; Krzaklewski told Reuters before a Saturday mass in the resort of Zakopane.</p>
<p>The September polls will pit the Solidarity-led alliance, grouping more than 30 small rightist parties, against the ex-communists, in power since 1993 with a peasant party.</p>
<p>Solidarity Election Action (AWS), has made restricting abortion -- an issue that divides Poles almost evenly -- a key election pledge.</p>
<p>In his homily in the town of Kalisz on Wednesday, John Paul railed against abortion saying &quot;a nation which kills its own children is a nation without a future.&quot;</p>
<p>Poland liberalised its abortion law last October by allowing it in cases of poverty or other personal difficulties. Until then abortion was allowed only if pregnancy resulted from rape, incest or when the foetus was severely damaged.</p>
<p>Solidarity is also linked with the Church by demands that parliament ratify a treaty with the Vatican, the concordat, which was signed by a former rightist government to regulate the Church's status but has since been delayed by leftists in parliament.</p>
<p>With the election campaign gaining momentum, Solidarity has taken advantage of the 11-day trip to put its logo on posters bearing the Pope's picture and advertising the visit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAKOPANE, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
