<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645232" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SLOVENIA: Slovak president warns EU not leave some in cold.</title>
<headline>Slovak president warns EU not leave some in cold.</headline>
<byline>Steve Pagani</byline>
<dateline>PORTOROZ, Slovenia 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Slovak President Michal Kovac said on Saturday a botched referendum in his country had probably ended Slovakia's hopes of early membership of NATO and the European Union but warned that indefinite exclusion could create a breeding ground for nationalism.</p>
<p>Kovac, speaking at a news conference with seven other central European presidents meeting in Slovenia, said he hoped leaders of the EU and the NATO military alliance would find a way to help shore up democracy in a country forced to wait for a second or third intake of new members.</p>
<p>&quot;I am realistic and I am aware that after the failure of this referendum we have sent another negative signal instead of sending a positive one,&quot; said Kovac, flanked by German President Roman Herzog and Czech President Vaclav Havel.</p>
<p>&quot;This could have serious consequences on the decision-making in Madrid on who will be invited into the first round (of enlargement),&quot; he added.</p>
<p>NATO leaders meet in the Spanish capital in July to decide which nations will lead the alliance's expansion into the heartlands of what was once the rival Warsaw Pact. The Czech Republic, Hungary and Poland are the favourites with Slovenia and Romania still clinging to hopes of being included.</p>
<p>When Czechoslovakia split into two independent states in 1993, both were believed to have a good chance of being integrated into the West's political and military organisations at the earliest opportunity.</p>
<p>While Prague forged ahead with democratic and free market reform, the process showed early signs of faltering over the border in Slovakia. Prime Minister Vladimir Meciar has come under international fire for failing to strengthen democracy.</p>
<p>A twin referendum last month on NATO membership and direct presidential elections was billed as Slovakia's last chance to prove its democratic credentials.</p>
<p>But the process merely highlighted the bitter political rivalry between Kovac and Meciar. When the question on presidential elections was struck off the ballot at the last moment, Kovac urged a boycott of the referendum.</p>
<p>The ballot was declared void because of the low turnout.</p>
<p>EU External Relations Commissioner Hans van den Broek, reacting to the referendum debacle, said the union was concerned that the rule of law and democracy had not sufficiently taken root in Slovakia.</p>
<p>&quot;Transition problems (in former communist states) could lead a country to be left to the second or third rounds of enlargement,&quot; Kovac told the news conference. &quot;But this could stimulate the old ideas of nationalism...which could jeopardise respect for human dignity and human rights.&quot;</p>
<p>Kovac, who had held talks with the presidents of Austria, Germany and Italy -- all EU members -- said the 15-nation bloc could not immediately open its doors to all and sundry but urged it not to forget those left behind.</p>
<p>In what sounded more like a plea for his own country rather than a general request, Kovac added: &quot;I believe they will be able to find solutions which will not promote radical nationalism but will support democracy and integration forces in those countries.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVAK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTOROZ, Slovenia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SLOVENIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
