<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645201" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>CONGO: French soldier killed in Congo Brazzaville.</title>
<headline>French soldier killed in Congo Brazzaville.</headline>
<dateline>BRAZZAVILLE 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>One French soldier was shot dead and two wounded in the capital of Congo Brazzaville on Saturday, after they came under fire during a day of clashes between rival militias, Western diplomatic sources said.  </p>
<p>&quot;The shooting was in one direction, the militias opened fire near the presidency on the French soldiers who were also accompanied by Congolese (soldiers),&quot; one source told Reuters.</p>
<p>In a separate incident, French troops in the city opened fire on government soldiers trying to loot a building housing French cooperation workers, Western military and diplomatic sources said. The French troops drove off the would-be looters and evacuated the cooperation workers to another building.</p>
<p>Three days of clashes pitting supporters of former president Denis Sassou Nguesso against soldiers loyal to President Pascal Lissouba and other political and ethnic rivals have rocked Brazzaville, capital of the former French colony.</p>
<p>French soldiers came to Brazzaville several months ago and like U.S., British, Belgian and Portuguese troops remained on standby to evacuate foreign nationals from Kinshasa in the event of a bloodbath there during the final days of the civil war that brought Laurent Kabila to power. The others all left.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRAZZAVILLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
