<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645291" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: First Israeli witnesses to appear in Jordan trial.</title>
<headline>First Israeli witnesses to appear in Jordan trial.</headline>
<dateline>MARJ AL-HAMAM, Jordan 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The first group of Israeli witnesses will testify on Monday in a trial of a Jordanian soldier charged with shooting dead seven Israeli schoolgirls, the prosecution said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Brigadier Mamoun al-Khasawneh, head of a five-man military tribunal, told the court it had no objection to a request made by chief prosecutor Lieutenant General Muhanad Hijazi to summon the first three Israeli witnesses at the next court hearing on Monday.</p>
<p>The court heard witness accounts from six comrades of the Private Ahmed al-Daqamsa who retold details of last March's killing of the Israeli girls, six of them 13 years old and one just 11 years old, in the Jordanian border territory of Baqoura leased to Israel under a 1994 peace treaty.</p>
<p>Under the peace accord Jordanian soldiers patrol the area but Israelis have free access and Israelis farmers own land there. Israelis call it 'The Island of Peace'.</p>
<p>Judicial experts said the appearance of Israeli citizens in a public trial in Jordan would be unprecedented and was made possible by the peace treaty which normalised ties after a 46-year state of war.</p>
<p>Daqamsa faces the death penalty if found guilty. He faces four charges including premeditated murder and military disobedience. His lawyers says he does not deny shooting the teenage girls but that he acted impulsively after they teased him while he was praying.</p>
<p>The prosecution said Daqamsa had planned for years to kill Israelis and had volunteered extra guard duties so he would have an opportunity to strike.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARJ AL-HAMAM, Jordan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
