<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645209" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: Kenyan dissident Balala refused entry on return.</title>
<headline>Kenyan dissident Balala refused entry on return.</headline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kenyan dissident Sheikh Khalid Balala was forced to return to Germany when he arrived in the coastal resort of Mombasa on Saturday, leading politician Raila Odinga said.</p>
<p>Odinga and fellow opposition leaders Kenneth Matiba and Ngengi Muigai, who went to Mombasa airport to welcome Balala, were beaten in a &quot;beastly manner&quot; by security officers, Odinga told a news conference on return to Nairobi.</p>
<p>Balala flew into Kenya from Germany, where he has lived the last two years. His passport expired while he was away and Kenya's embassy in Bonn refused to renew it. It was not clear what documents he used to travel.</p>
<p>Balala was born in Kenya of a Kenyan mother and Yemeni father. Kenyan immigration officials say Balala automatically gave up his Kenyan citizenship when he failed to renounce his Yemeni ancestry at the age of 21.</p>
<p>Balala is a radical Moslem preacher who was among Kenyans calling for a return to multi-party politics in 1991.</p>
<p>&quot;Balala was not allowed to come out of the aircraft,&quot; Odinga told reporters in Nairobi after returning from Mombasa. &quot;We all know that Sheikh Balala is a Kenyan citizen and he should be allowed to Kenya to sort out his problems.&quot;</p>
<p>The Kenyan High Court on Thursday rejected a plea by Balala to have his passport returned. The judge said Balala held dual nationality, illegal under Kenyan law.</p>
<p>But Yemen has said Balala was not a citizen and Odinga said Balala always sought a Yemeni visa when he travelled there.</p>
<p>&quot;The reason of making Balala stateless is political; mainly because of his stand (against the government). The Kenyan government is sending him to Germany knowing very well that he is not a German citizen. This is a beastly act,&quot; Odinga said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
