<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645292" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>QATAR: Qatar to seek partners at MENA summit.</title>
<headline>Qatar to seek partners at MENA summit.</headline>
<dateline>DOHA 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Qatar will seek foreign partners for 15 medium-size chemical projects at the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) economic summit it plans to host in November, a Qatari official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;We will offer these projects as joint ventures and seek direct foreign investment from multinational corporations which will be attending the conference,&quot; a press statement by Sheikh Abdullah bin Ahmed al-Thani, Assistant Undersecretary at the Ministry of Energy and Industry, said.</p>
<p>Sheikh Abdullah said the ministry's department of industrial development has signed a contract with India's Tata Economic Consultancy Services (TECS) to prepare feasibility reports for 40 projects which could use Qatar's abundant gas and petrochemical production as raw materials to produce value-added products.</p>
<p>TECS director, Narendra Sheth, told reporters all projects would be export oriented and would have a maximum price tag of $200 million each.</p>
<p>Qatar expects about 3,000 businessmen and officials from Asia, the Middle East, Europe and the U.S. to attend the MENA summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Our focus will be on recommending those downstream projects which have wide applications in the plastic industry and markets in all parts of the world,&quot; said Sheikh Abdullah.</p>
<p>Qatar controls the world's third largest reservoir of gas, after Russia and Iran. So far, it has been working on major liquefied natural gas (LNG) and other cost-intensive petrochemical projects.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="QATAR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DOHA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="QATAR"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
