<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645290" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALGERIA: Algeria poll shows disillusion among voters.</title>
<headline>Algeria poll shows disillusion among voters.</headline>
<byline>Lamine Ghanmi</byline>
<dateline>ALGIERS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The outcome of Algeria's multi-party parliamentary election showed widespread disenchantment among voters, coupled with a demand for change through consensus in the violence-ridden country, diplomats and analysts said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;The first party now in Algeria is the one of the Algerians who abstained from voting,&quot; analyst Yacine Abdelkrim said.</p>
<p>Western diplomats said the abstention rate of about 45 percent in Thursday's voting reflected disillusion among large sectors of the population, mostly in the main cities, who had pinned their hopes on President Liamine Zeroual to restore peace and ease economic hardships and corruption.</p>
<p>The National Democratic Party (RND), grouping Zeroual's backers, won 33.69 percent of votes cast, with 155 seats in the 380-seat National Assembly (lower house).</p>
<p>But two legal Islamist parties between them won more than 100 seats, prompting one secular-oriented newspaper to see them as the real victors.</p>
<p>&quot;Moslem fundamentalism emerged as the great winner of the legislative election...(the two parties) have more than 100 parliament members and can weigh on the country's future policy,&quot; wrote Hassane Zerrouky, editor of Le Matin newspaper, on Saturday.</p>
<p>Although his party won most seats, many people feel Zeroual, who wields paramount power in this nation of 29 million people, has not fulfilled the hopes of voters who helped him overwhelm Islamist Mahfoud Nahnah and secularist Said Sadi in the presidential poll 18 months ago.</p>
<p>&quot;Zeroual had sparked hope among voters then. But most people feel there has been no improvement in their daily life under the shadow of Moslem guerrilla violence which turned into random terror,&quot; said a senior western diplomat.</p>
<p>About 60,000 people have died in Algeria since 1992 when the authorities cancelled a general election in which the radical Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) took a huge lead.</p>
<p>The Movement for a Peaceful Society (MPS) led by Mahfoud Nahnah, the main Islamist-oriented party since the FIS was outlawed, was way behind the RND in Thursday's poll with 14.8 percent of the vote, giving it 69 seats.</p>
<p>Nahnah won one third of the vote in the presidential poll in 1995.</p>
<p>The second legal Islamist-oriented party, Nahda, emerged as the surprise of the poll with 34 seats. The Nahda movement ranked fourth behind the formerly ruling National Liberation Front (FLN) which gained 64 seats.</p>
<p>Diplomats said the Nahda party had become the niche of hard- core militant Islam in Algeria by winning to its ranks some militants of the outlawed FIS.</p>
<p>Diplomats and analysts interviewed by Reuters said that the voter abstention rate was a warning to the parties which gained seats in the new parliament to pull together to bring about change and to forget ideological differences.</p>
<p>Only 10 among the 39 competing political parties won seats in the lower house with notable casualties including former prime minister Redha Malek who failed to win a seat in Algiers and the Algerian Renewal Party (PRA) led by moderate intellectual Noureddine Boukrouh, which scored only 1.8 percent of the vote, far below the five percent threshold to gain seats.</p>
<p>Malek, who focused his campaigning on attacking Moslem guerrillas and moderate legal Islamist parties, was humiliated by voters. His Republican National Alliance (ANR) failed to gain even one seat.</p>
<p>Analysts said although the abstention rate was nearly that of the country's first parliamentary poll in 1991, the interpretation differed.</p>
<p>&quot;Abstainers this time expressed their anger. Those who abstained in 1991 were mainly voters who expressed their rejection of the strongest (Islamic Salvation Front) party programme to establish an Islamist state,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>Another who watched the campaign said many candidates had mobilised only their own party activists, failing to convince mainstream voters.</p>
<p>Some parties which gained seats in the lower house still hope to improve their scores by applying to the Constitutional Council to look into what they called irregularities in the voting process.</p>
<p>The Council, which endorses the vote results after examining party complaints and the voting operations, can order new by-elections in constituencies if it finds the complaints are well-founded.</p>
<p>But western diplomats said the poll seemed to have been largely fair regarding the country's context and the Council decisions would not change much of the outcome.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALGIERS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
