<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645285" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>KUWAIT: Kuwait urges calm after MP assassination attempt.</title>
<headline>Kuwait urges calm after MP assassination attempt.</headline>
<byline>Inal Ersan</byline>
<dateline>KUWAIT 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kuwait's government on Saturday urged parliamentarians debating the attempted assassination of an opposition MP to avoid saying things that could stir internal strife.</p>
<p>&quot;Please do not pour petrol on the fire. Starting a fire would not only harm us but will harm the whole of Kuwait,&quot; the tiny Gulf Arab state's acting premier and foreign minister, Sheikh Sabah al-Ahmad al-Sabah, told parliament.</p>
<p>Leading liberal MP Abdullah al-Naibari, a government critic, was in hospital after unidentified gunmen shot him and his wife on Friday. Relatives and officials said they were in good condition.</p>
<p>Several MPs linked the attack to charges in parliament that former officials mismanaged and squandered public funds. Naibari played a key role in efforts to combat corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;The country is in real danger...These people are not without allies. They will continue on this path unless there is a clear position,&quot; speaker Ahmad al-Saadoun told parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;Their final goal is to seize power...When they felt that the noose was tightening they started hitting in every direction ...What is the difference between those people and (Iraqi leader) Saddam Hussein...The message is not to Abdullah al-Naibari, it is to you and to the judiciary,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>There are several cases before the courts of alleged illegal profits by former officials, including some involving operations at the state-owned Kuwait Oil Tanker Company (KOTC).</p>
<p>Sheikh Sabah said: &quot;I had hoped that my brother Saadoun would make an address to calm matters and not to provoke them. I am sure that what happaned was not carried out by Kuwaitis. Let us not link the Abdullah al-Naibari affair with this matter so that we do not trigger strife.</p>
<p>&quot;We are keen to safeguard public funds. We are above covering up for those who steal,&quot; he added, reminding MPs that Kuwaitis are only 27 percent of the country's two million people and needed to be &quot;hand-in-hand&quot;.</p>
<p>Although there were strong hints during the debate of who was behind the shooting no person was named.</p>
<p>Gunmen ambushed Naibari's car as he drove to Kuwait City from a beach near the southern border with Saudi Arabia. He was hit in the jaw and shoulder while his wife suffered a superficial bullet wound near her left shoulder.</p>
<p>Diplomats said Western embassies were assessing the security situation but do not expect visits to Kuwait this month by U.S. and British ministers to be postponed.</p>
<p>Kuwait, which has about 10 percent of the world's proven oil reserves, is the only one of the six Sunni Moslem-ruled Gulf Arab states with an elected parliament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KUWAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
