<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645255" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Future HK chamber defies legal threat, makes laws.</title>
<headline>Future HK chamber defies legal threat, makes laws.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Future legislators on Saturday defied an imminent legal challenge and passed a string of laws for Hong Kong which will come into effect after the territory reverts to Chinese rule at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>The 60-member provisional legislature met in Shenzhen, just across the border in China, where it was presented with a series of bills by officials of the future administration led by Hong Kong's chief executive-designate Tung Chee-hwa.</p>
<p>A crucial bill governing residency rights in Hong Kong after Britain hands it back to China on July 1 passed through two readings, Hong Kong's Wharf Cable TV station reported.</p>
<p>Three bills governing the membership of municipal bodies after the handover were ratified after being read the required three times, it added.</p>
<p>Under rules laid down earlier by the future chamber, ratified bills will take effect on July 1 as post-handover Hong Kong laws.</p>
<p>The meeting was held despite a ruling by Hong Kong's Supreme Court on Thursday that the Democratic Party could use government funds to challenge laws passed by the provisional legislature, which will replace the current elected Legislative Council on July 1.</p>
<p>The Democrats, who hold 19 seats in the current Legco and have much to lose when it is disbanded in just 24 days, argue it is illegal to have two legislatures operating simultaneously. A Democratic Party spokesman earlier said his party would file its legal action within the next few days.</p>
<p>In Shenzhen, members of the provisional legislature -- who, like Tung, were carefully selected under Beijing's auspices in December -- scoffed at the imminent legal challenge and claimed the future chamber had a strong legal basis.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm only sad that Hong Kong must spend so much money over something when the outcome, everyone knows, is a foregone conclusion,&quot; said provisional legislator Tam Yiu-chung.</p>
<p>The president of the shadow body, Rita Fan, shrugged off the legal challenge.</p>
<p>&quot;It (the threatened lawsuit) won't affect the work of the provisional legislature,&quot; she told reporters.</p>
<p>The provisional chamber holds regular meetings in Shenzhen, instead of on Hong Kong soil, in a bid to fend off potential legal attacks.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
