<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645237" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAJIKISTAN: Tajik peace accord due to be signed on June 27.</title>
<headline>Tajik peace accord due to be signed on June 27.</headline>
<dateline>DUSHANBE 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The rival sides in Tajikistan's protracted civil war are expected to sign a peace accord in Moscow on June 27, a spokesman for the United Nations mission in the former Soviet republic said on Saturday.</p>
<p>The Tajik government and the United Tajik Opposition, who have been fighting since 1992, postponed the signing of the long awaited peace deal earlier this month citing undisclosed &quot;technical reasons&quot;.</p>
<p>The U.N. spokesman in Dushanbe said the deal, due to be signed by Tajik President Imomali Rakhmonov and the opposition leader Sayid Abdullo Nuri will also embrace a series of protocols signed earlier in the course of peace talks.</p>
<p>The talks started last December when Rakhmonov's secular government and Nuri's Islamist opposition guerrillas agreed a ceasefire.</p>
<p>The conflict has killed tens of thousands and displaced many more. The ceasefire, brokered by the United Nations, Russia and Iran, has largely held.</p>
<p>The two sides have hammered out a power sharing deal but the issue of legalising opposition parties and media remains outstanding.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TADZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUSHANBE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAJIKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
