<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645207" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BURUNDI: Burundi's Ntibantunganya tasted effects of hate.</title>
<headline>Burundi's Ntibantunganya tasted effects of hate.</headline>
<dateline>BUJUMBURA 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sylvestre Ntibantunganya, freed on Saturday from &quot;exile&quot; in the U.S. embassy in the capital, was Burundi's third president in less than a year from the majority Hutu tribe, after his two predecessors died violently.</p>
<p>He fled to the U.S. embassy last July after a bloodless coup returned former military ruler Pierre Buyoya to power and ended Burundi's experiment with democracy.</p>
<p>Regional leaders reacted furiously, slapping an economic embargo on the landlocked tiny central African country. They have continued to pressure Buyoya to free Ntibantunganya.</p>
<p>Diplomats said they expected Ntibantunganya to be invited to help in negotiations with the militant Hutu rebel group CNDD, which has fought for several years to end Tutsi dominance of government.</p>
<p>Like most of the six million people in Burundi, the former president had tragic first-hand experience of the seemingly endless ethnic conflict between Hutus and Tutsis.</p>
<p>His wife Eusebie was bayoneted to death by Tutsi soldiers on October 21, 1993, in the same failed coup that killed Burundi's first democratically elected president, Melchior Ndadaye.</p>
<p>The soldiers hunted in vain for Ntibantunganya, then foreign minister and one of Ndadaye's closest friends.</p>
<p>The putsch fizzled out but at least 50,000 people died as a result. Enraged Hutus slaughtered isolated Tutsi communities in mountain villages and then suffered massive reprisals by the army, 95 percent of which is Tutsi.</p>
<p>Ndadaye's successor as president, Cyprien Ntaryamira, survived less than six months. He was travelling with Rwandan President Juvenal Habyarimana's when their plane was shot down over Kigali on April 6, 1994.</p>
<p>The two Hutu presidents died and Habyarimana's hardline supporters launched a genocidal plan to exterminate as many of Rwanda's Tutsi minority and moderate Hutus as possible.</p>
<p>An estimated 800,000 ethnic Tutsis were slaughtered before the exiled Tutsi-led Rwanda Patriotic Front won the civil war in July, 1994. Rwanda and Burundi, former German colonies later placed under Belgian tutelage, have similar histories of huge-scale tribal massacres between Hutus and Tutsis.</p>
<p>In Burundi the Tutsis, despite being only about 15 percent of the population, remained in command after independence in 1962. All that was set to change when Ndadaye's party, the mainly-Hutu Frodebu, inevitably won the country's first democratic polls in 1993.</p>
<p>The officers and men involved in the October 1993 coup provided the proof that many Tutsis would not accept Hutu rule. The Rwandan genocide of Tutsis strengthened the resolve of the Burundian minority.</p>
<p>This was the dramatic context in which Ntibantunganya, as speaker of parliament, became interim president in April 1994 after Ntaryamira's death in the plane crash.</p>
<p>Friends said Ntibantunganya, now aged 41, reluctantly accepted one of the most dangerous presidencies in the world.</p>
<p>French security experts came to Burundi to train his personal bodyguard and he was officially inaugurated as head of state in October, 1994, after the signing of a power-sharing convention brokered by the United Nations and other diplomats.</p>
<p>Broadly, the document sought to buy relative peace by boosting the Tutsi share of government and civil service jobs while cementing the Tutsi army's involvement in public life.</p>
<p>Ntibantunganya was accused by many Hutus of betraying the tribe by accepting the convention which reduced parliament to a marginal role. Former minister Leonard Nyangoma declared war on the army and Ntibantunganya's government, and a low-level Hutu rebellion began in the last months of 1994.</p>
<p>Buyoya moved in on July 25, 1996, saying Ntibantunganya was no longer able to guarantee Burundi's security.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BURUN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUJUMBURA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BURUNDI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
