<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645234" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Romania court cuts sentences on revolution police.</title>
<headline>Romania court cuts sentences on revolution police.</headline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Romania's Supreme Court has reduced sentences imposed on former top Communist Party officials convicted of killing demonstrators in the city where the country's December 1989 anti-communist revolt was launched.</p>
<p>Bucharest media said on Saturday that most of 16 former top officials from Timisoara, a city near the border with Serbia and Hungary, had jail terms reduced on Friday in a trial ending seven years of legal proceedings.</p>
<p>State television said Ion Coman, a Party Politburo member sent by dictator Nicolae Ceausescu to crush the Timisoara uprising, had his term reduced to 15 from 25 years.</p>
<p>The heads of the local police and Securitate secret police were given more lenient sentences of 15 years. Twenty-five people were originally charged with genocide and eight given life sentences. Nine defendants of junior rank were acquitted.</p>
<p>Unrest erupted in Timisoara on December 16, 1989 when protesters massed in front of a church to prevent its dissident ethnic Hungarian priest from being sent into internal exile.</p>
<p>Police and Securitate forces confronted the demonstrators for several days in the city's central square and chased down a number desperately trying to take refuge in the locked Orthodox cathedral. Evidence showed that local officials tried to burn and dispose of the bodies of several dozen demonstrators.</p>
<p>Eyewitness accounts said the Securitate led the assault against the uprising, with the army siding with the population when the extent of rage against Ceausescu became apparent.</p>
<p>Protests spread to other cities and to Bucharest, with Ceausescu fleeing the capital by helicopter on December 22. He was captured, summarily tried and executed, together with his wife Elena, on Christmas day.</p>
<p>Debate still rages on whether the December events were a spontaneous uprising or a carefully engineered bid by ex-communists to remain in power. Liberal politicians say questions remain on why most of the 1,100 victims were killed after Ceausescu had already been seized.</p>
<p>The Timisoara officials eventually faced scaled-down charges of first-degree murder in connection with 72 deaths. All the defendants had been released from detention at various stages of the trial on medical grounds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
