<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645218" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Kinkel advises Poles to sit back, relax over NATO.</title>
<headline>Kinkel advises Poles to sit back, relax over NATO.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel, visiting his Warsaw counterpart on Saturday, advised Poles to relax and trust the Western partners they hope soon to join in NATO.</p>
<p>So easy-going was the informal visit by Kinkel to Poland's Dariusz Rosati that they rang up new French Socialist Foreign Minister Hubert Vedrine from a public payphone on the street in the east Poland resort town of Kazimierz.</p>
<p>Poland shook off Moscow's domination with the fall of communism in 1989 and is anxious to join the Western alliance quickly. Warsaw's diplomats are constantly on guard for any possible threats to this process.</p>
<p>Kinkel, whose country is among Poland's strongest advocates with the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation and the European Union, said Poles should have more faith, PAP news agency reported.</p>
<p>&quot;If I was a Pole I would sit back in a chair and wait,&quot; the agency quoted Kinkel as telling reporters as he and Poland's Rosati, neckties off, took a Wisla riverboat cruise.</p>
<p>Kinkel dismissed fears in the country of nearly 40 million people that last month's deal between NATO and Russia, paving the way for the organisation's eastward enlargement, might mean the two sides talking about Poland without giving it a say.</p>
<p>&quot;Poland is too important and too big for anyone to do anything over the heads of Poles,&quot; Kinkel was quoted as saying.</p>
<p>Nevertheless Poland's Rosati said his country was working on ideas for ways to ensure that nothing was decided concerning Poland's security, without its participation, at meetings of the new NATO-Russia council.</p>
<p>Poland is confident of being in the first group of prospective new members which will be asked to start NATO entry talks at the defence pact's summit in Madrid in July.</p>
<p>Polish public television news said the two ministers rang France's Vedrine from the payphone, with congratulations on his appointment, after a mobile phone failed to work.</p>
<p>The public gesture, in front of reporters, was also designed to underline the Weimar Triangle, a loose framework for friendly cooperation between the three countries.</p>
<p>The French foreign ministry in Paris announced that Vedrine had conferred by telephone with his two fellow ministers on forthcoming diplomatic events.</p>
<p>A ministry spokesman said Kinkel and Vedrine discussed an EU summit in Amsterdam on June 16-17 and a Franco-German summit set for Friday in the French city Poitiers.</p>
<p>The Amsterdam EU summit is expected to reach agreement on a new pact on EU institutional reforms, intended to update the Maastricht treaty, and will clear the way for talks on entry of new members such as Poland to the union.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
