<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645231" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish centrists leave coalition options open.</title>
<headline>Polish centrists leave coalition options open.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The chief of Poland's centrist Union for Freedom party on Saturday denied reports he had ruled out a future coalition with either the ruling ex-communists or the right-leaning opposition led by the Solidarity union.</p>
<p>In a letter to Gazeta Wyborcza daily, Leszek Balcerowicz said he had never made the statement, attributed to him at a meeting in the southern city of Katowice, concerning the ex-communist SLD party or the Solidarity Election Action (AWS).</p>
<p>&quot;Neither with the AWS nor the Democratic Left Alliance (SLD),&quot; he said, adding: &quot;I only pointed out the differences between the Union for Freedom (UW) and the AWS and SLD.</p>
<p>&quot;With the AWS we share our common Solidarity origins, but we are divided by programme issues, especially economic ones. But we are separated from the SLD both by origins and programme as well as political style.&quot;</p>
<p>During a meeting with students in Katowice on Thursday, Balcerowicz was quoted by PAP news agency as saying: &quot;These groupings are very similar conglomerates, which merely have different names. It is hard to say which of these two would be worse for Poland.&quot;</p>
<p>Parliamentary elections due around September are likely to be dominated by the SLD and their bitter foes, the more than 30 right-leaning parties grouped round the Solidarity trade union.</p>
<p>Opinion polls suggest that they may each gain about one third of parliamentary seats, meaning that smaller parties like the UW could be crucial to forming a governing coalition.</p>
<p>The UW includes intellectuals who were behind the pre-1989 opposition to communist rule and then formed the first democratic governments, but who differ strongly with many former Solidarity allies over some current policies.</p>
<p>The ex-communists are eager to lure the UW into a coalition to help them to shed the stigma of their communist origins.</p>
<p>Some supporters of the AWS would also like a coalition with the UW to reassure voters that the union-led group, which has some radical populist factions, would pursue market reforms. -- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
