<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645254" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korea President Kim says N.Korea must be watched.</title>
<headline>S.Korea President Kim says N.Korea must be watched.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean President Kim Young-sam said on Saturday communist North Korea remained a threat because it could stage military provocations and it needed to be watched closely.</p>
<p>&quot;If a crisis of North Korea's system reaches the very end, there is a high possibility that the North in despair will commit military provocations as a last resort,&quot; Kim said at a luncheon meeting of military leaders including Defence Minister Kim Dong-jin.</p>
<p>President Kim said the South Korean military must not be idle in keeping vigilance on the North and should increase its preparedness against possible intrusion, the presidential Blue House said in a statement.</p>
<p>Earlier on Saturday, Defence Minister Kim told military leaders famine and a faltering economy in North Korea could trigger &quot;adventurist&quot; military provocation.</p>
<p>He called on the South's military to increase its readiness for &quot;any type of military provocation&quot;.</p>
<p>The meeting was held two days after North and South Korean naval vessels exchanged fire on Thursday after a Northern patrol boat strayed South with a fleet of nine fishing boats.</p>
<p>The North Korean boat fired three rounds at three South Korean naval ships as they steamed to intercept it. The Southern side returned fire with two rounds.</p>
<p>A defence ministry spokesman said the meeting of military leaders had been previously scheduled.</p>
<p>The state-run Korea Broadcasting System (KBS) radio said military leaders discussed the possibility of more intrusions by North Korean naval vessels. They decided they would act instantly to block any further misjudgements by the rival communist neighbour.</p>
<p>But the ministry spokesman said he could not confirm the report.</p>
<p>Minister Kim warned against complacency in national security. He said North Korean leader Kim Jong-il had strengthened his grip on the military and was pursuing a &quot;military-first policy&quot;.</p>
<p>Impoverished North Korea had focused its resources on building up its war machine despite an acute food shortage and economic difficulties, he said.</p>
<p>Kim Jong-il, North Korea's &quot;Great Leader&quot; Kim Il-sung's son, has taken control of the Stalinist state since his father's death but has yet to be confirmed as the state's president and head of the ruling Workers Party.</p>
<p>South Korea has become edgy over reports of a food crisis in the North.</p>
<p>South Korea said on Thursday the North could overcome its food shortage and the government in Pyongyang may be overstating the problem, contradicting U.N. warnings that North Korea faces famine with no food left by June 20.</p>
<p>The two Koreas are still technically at war since the 1950-53 Korean War.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
