<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645214" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: PRESS DIGEST - Kenya - June 7.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Kenya - June 7.</headline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Kenyan press on Saturday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAILY NATION</p>
<p>- Opposition pressure for constitutional reforms before presidential and parliamentary elections later this year mount with leaders Kenneth Matiba and Raila Odinga announcing that pro-reform rallies will be held simultaneously in nine towns across Kenya on June 21.</p>
<p>- Three opposition FORD-Asili party members of parliament and councillors dismiss the sacking of chairman Kenneth Matiba as fraudulent and inconsequential.</p>
<p>- A human rights public lecture in Lodwar, northwestern Kenya due to be addressed by Amnesty International Secretary-General Pierre Sane is disrupted by rowdy youths loyal to ruling KANU party.</p>
<p>- Kenya's Harambee Stars, the national football team, meet Super Eagles of Nigeria in crucial World Cup qualifier in Lagos. Winner may qualify for the World Cup finals in France in June of next year.</p>
<p>EAST AFRICAN STANDARD</p>
<p>- Thousands of primary and secondary school teachers enjoy major salary boost after new scheme comes into effect. Salary arrears to be backdated by almost a year.</p>
<p>- Organisation of African Unity (OAU) Secretary-General Salim Ahmed Salim says there are no plans to establish a standing peacekeeping army on the continent. Also condemns coup in Sierra Leone and says ballot answer to power changes.</p>
<p>KENYA TIMES</p>
<p>- The opposition National Development Party of Kenya has instructed its youth wingers to physically eject National Electoral Commission officials and voter registration clerks from its stronghold Nyanza province of western Kenya.</p>
<p>- Nigeria has slapped visa embargo on Kenyans in a move that denied soccer fans a chance to travel to cheer national soccer team Harambee Stars in epic match against Super Eagles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
