<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645271" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan stocks end up on plastics and electronics.</title>
<headline>Taiwan stocks end up on plastics and electronics.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Late buying in plastics pushed Taiwan share prices to a slightly higher close on Saturday, brokers said. Electronics again performed strongly as well.</p>
<p>The benchmark index ended up 24.52 points or 0.29 percent at 8,367.46, off an intraday high of 8,436.00.</p>
<p>Turnover was a heavy T$152.2 billion.</p>
<p>Plastics surged 5.27 percent as buying emerged after leading maker Nan Ya Plastics rose by the daily seven percent limit to T$82.5. &quot;Investors are afraid electronics might have risen too much so some have turned to plastics, which had lagged recent gains,&quot; said Ben Lee of Nomura Securities.  </p>
<p>China Petrochemical also was limit up to T$45.5.</p>
<p>Taiwan's trendsetting electronics shares remained investors' favorite, rising 1.11 percent. Chipmaker United Microelectronics rose T$3.5 to T$89.</p>
<p>Top chipmaker Taiwan Semiconductor surged T$7.5 to T$135 after saying on Friday its May sales rose 16 percent from April, though they were still 16.1 percent below May 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;Buying continues to focus on Taiwan Semiconductor, which will go ex-bonus issue on June 12, as its sales are expected to recover significantly in the second half,&quot; Lee said.  </p>
<p>Financial and construction shares fell, somewhat offsetting Saturday's gains.</p>
<p>Brokers said they expected a firming trend, with the broad index testing resistance around 8,500-8,600 points.</p>
<p>For next week, a 8,200-8,600 trading range was seen.</p>
<p>The market is closed on Monday for a national holiday.</p>
<p>-- James Peng (5080815)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
