<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645252" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK Telecom seen benefiting as China stake rises.</title>
<headline>HK Telecom seen benefiting as China stake rises.</headline>
<byline>Andrea Ricci</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The future of Hong Kong Telecommunications looks brighter now that its parent Cable and Wireless Plc has sold a stake to state-owned China Telecom, analysts in Hong Kong said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;The shareholding changes will provide an opportunity for Hongkong Telecom to get exposure to the fast-growing telecom industry in China,&quot; said Ben Kwong, director of research at Dharmala Securities.</p>
<p>Britain's Cable &amp; Wireless (C&amp;W) on Friday ended months of speculation by announcing that it would sell to China Telecom a 5.5 percent, or US$1.185 billion, stake in HK Telecom -- its most lucrative asset -- for HK$14.25 per share.</p>
<p>Before the sale, C&amp;W held 59.2 percent of HK Telecom.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect this partnership to deepen and develop further as new opportunities for investment in China are identified and quantified,&quot; C&amp;W chief executive Richard Brown said in a statement released on Friday.</p>
<p>Hong Kong analysts said the deal paved the way for HK Telecom's participation in China's developing telecommunications sector, helping it diversify away from a saturated Hong Kong market.</p>
<p>&quot;Hong Kong Telecom's main business is not exciting at all. What would make it more exciting is its participation in the China market,&quot; said Stanley Ng, research manager at Mansion House Securities.</p>
<p>HK Telecom has lagged the local stock market over the past two years because of sluggish growth prospects for fixed-line services and increased competition in the cellular phone market.</p>
<p>But Ng said it is too early to tell how much business HK Telecom can hope to generate in China.</p>
<p>&quot;We can expect China to open up the telecom market to outsiders and that it will allow HK Telecom to participate. But at what pace and how much will Telecom get?&quot; said Ng.</p>
<p>China Telecom is controlled by Telpo Communications Development Ltd, a holding company of China's Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications (MPT).</p>
<p>In May, China Everbright, which is controlled by China's State Council, said it would buy CITIC Pacific Ltd's 7.74 percent stake in HK Telecom for HK$12.60 per share.</p>
<p>China Everbright is one of 16 equal holders of China United Telecommunications Corp, China's second-biggest telecommunications vendor.</p>
<p>Under terms of the deal with China Telecom, C&amp;W can transfer shares to the Chinese company until both become equal partners.</p>
<p>Linus Cheung, HK Telecom chief executive, said on Friday that neither Telecom nor C&amp;W had been under any political pressure from China to make a deal.</p>
<p>Stephen Ip, Hong Kong's Secretary for Economic Services, told a Hong Kong cable television station on Saturday that the deal did not imply Chinese interference in Hong Kong's telecommunications sector.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very clear that in Hong Kong, China Telecom's business will be monitored under Hong Kong law,&quot; said Ip.</p>
<p>He also said C&amp;W would need approval from the Hong Kong government to cut its stake in HK Telecom to below 50 percent.</p>
<p>HK Telecom surged to a record high of HK$19.25 on Friday on speculation of an impending deal before drifting slightly to close at HK$19.00.</p>
<p>Analysts said that after the frenzied buying of the past two months, the change in shareholding was already reflected in Telecom's price. They also said the HK$14.25 price at which C&amp;W sold its shares to China Telecom was fair.</p>
<p>&quot;The deal is beneficial to both parties, so of course Cable &amp; Wireless would have to make some concession,&quot; said Dharmala Securities' Kwong.</p>
<p>HK Telecom's Cheung said on Friday said the price reflected the shares' average close for the past 30 trading days.</p>
<p>Some analysts have questioned China Telecom's ability to finance the purchase of a large stake in HK Telecom.</p>
<p>But Mansion House Securities's Ng said the company should have no problem funding the US$1.185 billion, or HK$9.17 billion, 5.5 percent stake.</p>
<p>&quot;Quite a lot of banks will be willing to lend the money, especially when you are talking about the Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843-6371</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
