<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645221" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>KAZAKHSTAN: Kazakhs, Trans-World open $1.2 bln aluminium project.</title>
<headline>Kazakhs, Trans-World open $1.2 bln aluminium project.</headline>
<byline>Dmitry Solovyov</byline>
<dateline>PAVLODAR, Kazakhstan 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kazakhstan and metals trading firm Trans-World Group announced on Saturday the start of a $1.2 billion project to build the ex-Soviet state's first aluminium smelter and raise its output of alumina.</p>
<p>&quot;An important historic event is happening today,&quot; said Kazakh President Nursultan Nazarbayev, launching the plan with the London-based company near the industrial town of Pavlodar, some 1,500 km (937 miles) north of the Kazakh capital, Almaty.</p>
<p>&quot;I always dreamed that Kazakhstan...must achieve a high degree of processing of its resources and not export just raw materials, allowing others to cash in on them,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Nazarbayev said that in 1985, when he headed the government of the then Soviet republic of Kazakhstan, his plan of building a modern aluminium smelter was frustrated by Moscow bureaucrats.</p>
<p>A few minutes later he cemented a metal capsule bearing the date of the project's start into a stone installed on the site of the future smelter.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a $1.2 billion project. Our group will put in $200 million,&quot; Trans-World chairman David Rubin told Reuters.</p>
<p>The remaining sum is being raised from international financial institutions, he added.</p>
<p>Rubin said the project aims to increase alumina output at Kazakhstan's only alumina plant near Pavlodar by 400,000 tonnes to 1.5 million tonnes and to build in its vicinity the country's first aluminium smelter with an estimated annual capacity of some 200,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Kazakhstan -- a resource-rich Central Asian country five times the size of France and with a population of just 16.7 million -- has huge reserves of bauxite estimated at 150 million tonnes but processes them only into alumina, or raw aluminium, which is sold to aluminium smelters in Russia.</p>
<p>The alumina plant is controlled by White Swan Ltd, a British-registered company cooperating with Trans-World, which last year bought a power plant in the neighbourhood.</p>
<p>&quot;We have now alumina production and a power plant nearby... so we have the ingredients for the successful building of a plant,&quot; Rubin said.</p>
<p>In his speech, Nazarbayev said the construction of the smelter would take some three years.</p>
<p>U.S. company Bechtel, which specialises in the construction of aluminium smelters worldwide, is currently working on a feasibility study.</p>
<p>Hans Bohner, technology vice-president of London-based INTEC Engineering which cooperates with Trans-World on technology, told Reuters that the construction of the smelter would cost some $720 million, while around $190 million would be spent to boost alumina output and open several new bauxite mines.</p>
<p>&quot;Kazakhstan will not be the largest (aluminium) producer in the CIS but it will be a very sizeable producer,&quot; Jack Nounou, head of INTEC Engineering, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Bohner said that &quot;the overwhelming part&quot; of Kazakh aluminium would be exported to neighbouring China, whose consumption of aluminium in the next 10 years would be higher than production.</p>
<p>&quot;Besides, China has landlocked fabrication sites, and transportation costs from Kazakhstan would not be much different than from Chinese sea ports,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The planned increase of alumina production is sufficient to produce the targeted amount of some 200,000 tonnes of aluminium without cutting alumina exports to Russia, Bohner added.</p>
<p>Currently all Pavlodar alumina is delivered to Russia -- mostly to Bratsk, Russia's largest plant, and Sayansk, the country's third biggest, in which Trans-World has large stakes.</p>
<p>--Almaty Newsroom, +7 3272 509409</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22450">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PAVLODAR, Kazakhstan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KAZAKHSTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
