<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645267" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Khmer Rouge hardliners deny rumours of exile deal.</title>
<headline>Khmer Rouge hardliners deny rumours of exile deal.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The political party of Khieu Samphan, the nominal leader of the Khmer Rouge, on Saturday denied reports that hard-line rebels had struck a deal to join the Cambodian government.</p>
<p>Clandestine Khmer Rouge radio broadcast a party statement dismissing reports of an imminent peace deal as &quot;completely exaggerated&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;The spokesperson of the National Solidarity Party of His Excellency Khieu Samphan would like to strongly deny there are negotiations, and there is no plan to join forces at all,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Khieu Samphan is the official leader of a hard-line faction of the Khmer Rouge that is still at war with the government.</p>
<p>Earlier this week a senior military commander loyal to co-Premier Prince Norodom Ranariddh told the Cambodian Daily newspaper that he was concluding an agreement with the Khmer Rouge, architects of the 1975-1979 &quot;killing fields&quot; regime.</p>
<p>Under the reported agreement, Khieu Samphan would be allowed to enter politics while notorious rebel Pol Pot and two other senior commanders would abandon their last jungle stronghold and go into exile. Rank-and-file troops would join the government.</p>
<p>Ranariddh said on Friday no deal had been worked out yet, but he earlier welcomed the prospect of exile for Pol Pot.</p>
<p>In Saturday's radio broadcast, Khieu Samphan's party also reiterated support for Ranariddh's FUNCINPEC party, urging provincial troops loyal to FUNCINPEC to go to the &quot;hot battlefield&quot; of Phnom Penh to defend the royalists against co-Premier Hun Sen.</p>
<p>Relations between Ranariddh and co-Premier Hun Sen, who formed an uneasy coalition government following U.N.-sponsored polls in 1993, have plummeted in recent months as the two leaders feuded over power-sharing and vied to lure Khmer Rouge defectors to their own ranks.</p>
<p>Hun Sen has expressed disapproval of Ranariddh's reported talks with Khieu Samphan and said the rebel leader would face physical danger if he returned to Phnom Penh.</p>
<p>In his monthly bulletin released on Saturday, King Norodom Sihanouk also expressed disapproval over talks with hardliners.</p>
<p>In annotations to news articles reporting Khieu Samphan's support for Ranariddh's political alliance, Sihanouk called such ties a heavy political handicap for the prince ahead of elections next year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
