<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645385" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWEDEN: Swedish publisher Marieberg also eyes share move.</title>
<headline>Swedish publisher Marieberg also eyes share move.</headline>
<dateline>STOCKHOLM 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scandinavia's largest newspaper publisher, Marieberg AB, is the latest company to consider moving its shares from the Stockholm bourse's main A list because of a new, punitive tax law, a Swedish newspaper said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Family-controlled Swedish companies are lining up to leave the A list and head for the smaller O list as a new law forces their owners to pay higher wealth tax.</p>
<p>&quot;It is correct that we want Marieberg to be transferred from the A-list,&quot; Carl-Johan Bonnier, president of the Bonnier group which is the main owner of Marieberg, told business newspaper Dagens Industri.</p>
<p>By moving Marieberg to the O-list, the media orientated Bonnier family can save over 11 million crown in taxes a year, the newspaper calculated.</p>
<p>A new law that took effect in late 1996 forces Swedes with wealth exceeding 900,000 crowns to pay 1.5 percent tax on 100 percent of the value of shares listed on the A list, up from 75 percent, while shares on the O list remain exempt from tax.</p>
<p>Several companies waited to see if this law would be changed when it was presented to parliament but last week the law was adopted. This has triggered the moves.</p>
<p>Fashion retailer Hennes &amp; Mauritz announced on Thursday it would transfer its shares while construction group Lundbergs said it would do so a day earlier and investment company Latour decided to act last week.</p>
<p>Hennes &amp; Mauritz shares plunged on the transfer announcement as some institutional investors have internal rules saying they can only invest in shares on the A list.</p>
<p>Dagens Industri said the list of possible movers also included shipping company Bylock &amp; Norsjofrakt, investment company Oresund, security company Securitas, and real estate firm Klover.</p>
<p>-- Belinda Goldsmith, Stockholm newsroom +46-8-700 1045</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SCAND">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I64500">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83954">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STOCKHOLM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWEDEN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
