<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645378" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Algerian exiles say 20 died in pre-poll massacre.</title>
<headline>Algerian exiles say 20 died in pre-poll massacre.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Algeria's banned Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) said on Saturday that 20 people had died in a clash between Moslem guerrillas and the Algerian authorities on the eve of Thursday's general election.</p>
<p>The FIS leadership, in exile in Germany, said in a statement received by a Western news agency in Paris that 17 members of Algeria's security forces or private militias had died in the clash along with three guerrillas.</p>
<p>It said the clash had taken place in the western Algerian city of Tlemsan.</p>
<p>It gave no other details in the statement, whose contents could not be independently verified.</p>
<p>Mahfoud Nahnah, Algeria's leading moderate Islamist leader said on Friday in Algiers that a &quot;real massacre&quot; had taken place in Tlemsan.</p>
<p>&quot;A real massacre took place in which there were (people) killed and wounded in Boudgham district,&quot; Nahnah told a news conference. &quot;It is related to the elections.&quot;</p>
<p>There was no immediate word on the reported incident from the authorities.</p>
<p>In the elections, held after five years of bloodshed blamed by the authorities on militant Islamic fundamentalists, the National Democratic Party (RND), grouping staunch supporters of President Liamine Zeroual, won 155 seats in the 380-member lower house, way ahead of the second-placed Movement of a Peaceful Society (MPS) of moderate Islamist Mahfoud Nahnah with 69 seats.</p>
<p>The MPS, the National Liberation Front (FLN), which won 64 seats, the Nahda Movement, with 34, and the Socialist Forces Front (FFS) and the Rally for Culture and Democracy (RCD), both with 19, have all complained of electoral irregularities.</p>
<p>The complaints fuelled doubts whether the election could lead to an end to the violence which has claimed an estimated 60,000 lives and was triggered by the cancellation of 1992 polls which the FIS was poised to win.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
