<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645381" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Mafia boss's arrest won't change much, say experts.</title>
<headline>Mafia boss's arrest won't change much, say experts.</headline>
<byline>Jeffrey Donovan</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mafia experts hailed the arrest of godfather Pietro Aglieri on Saturday but warned it would not improve the lives of millions of Italians who continue to live in the shadow of the Mob.</p>
<p>&quot;Aglieri's arrest is truly important. He had a crucial role inside Cosa Nostra,&quot; Giancarlo Caselli, chief prosecutor in the Sicilian capital Palermo, told La Repubblica daily.</p>
<p>&quot;But we won't have a real democracy so long as a third of the country continues to suffer the presence of the Mafia,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Police stormed a Sicilian farmhouse early on Friday to arrest Aglieri, who many investigators belive may have taken control of Cosa Nostra after godfather Salvatore &quot;The Beast&quot; Riina was captured in 1993.</p>
<p>Around 300 police agents took part in the operation, with some 100 using ladders to enter the grounds of the house east of Palermo and another 200 surrounding the premises and hiding in a nearby orange grove.</p>
<p>Aglieri ranked closely behind Italy's most wanted man -- fugitive Mafia boss Bernardo Provenzano -- and his arrest was hailed as the most important since Sicilian boss Giovanni Brusca was seized last year.</p>
<p>Educated to high school level in a Roman Catholic seminary, Aglieri was knicknamed &quot;U Signurinu&quot; (The Young Gentleman) in Sicilian dialect for his supposed elegance and unusual level of culture for a mobster.</p>
<p>Newspapers said police found books by 19-century Danish philospher Soren Kierkegaard and Edith Stein -- a philosopher and Catholic nun who died in the Nazi deathcamp at Auschwitz -- on Aglieri's bedside table.</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps he was undergoing some kind of mystical crisis,&quot; one commentator suggested in Turin's La Stampa.</p>
<p>Aglieri had been on the run since December 1989 when he was sentenced in absentia to life for killing boss Benedetto Grado, though that has yet to become definitive in Italy's exhaustive appeals procedure.</p>
<p>He was also sentenced to 12 years for drug trafficking and is accused of involvement in the car bomb killings of judges Paolo Borsellino and Giovanni Falcone in 1992 as well as of former European parliamentarian Salvo Lima in the same year.</p>
<p>Aglieri, who turns 38 on Monday, was believed to have been spearheading a reorganisation of the Mafia in the belief that Riina's strategy of bombings and killings had backfired.</p>
<p>&quot;He wanted to give back Cosa Nostra the role of a criminal organisation that lives not against the state and society, but in the state and society,&quot; La Repubblica said.</p>
<p>Caselli said part of Aglieri's reorganisation involved reviving severed ties with other crime groups, especially the Colombian drug cartels, and &quot;heavily increasing its presence in its own local territory through extortion&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Seen from Palermo...where one still must ask permission from the neighbourhood 'godfather' in order to undertake any kind of economic activity...Aglieri's arrest doesn't change much,&quot; La Repubblica concluded.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
