<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645380" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Kok sees no EMU date change, more jobs cooperation.</title>
<headline>Kok sees no EMU date change, more jobs cooperation.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dutch Prime Minister Wim Kok, who holds the rotating European Union presidency, said on Saturday he saw &quot;no reason&quot; to think there would be a change in the schedule for Europe's monetary union.</p>
<p>&quot;There is absolutely no reason to speculate about a change of dates at the end of Amsterdam (EU summit),&quot; Kok told a news conference in Madrid.</p>
<p>He also said European states should cooperate more on social issues as well as creating solid economic ties.</p>
<p>&quot;I want Europe to be strong on an economic level, but also on a social level,&quot; Kok said in response to a question about a call from France's new Socialist Prime Minister for increased EU focus on growth and job creation rather than strict adherence to deficit targets set out in the Maastricht Treaty on EMU.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be wrong to say that Europe could take responsibility for employment for each of its members, that is the responsibility of each state,&quot; he said. &quot;But Europe should find a way to increase cooperation in that area.&quot;</p>
<p>Kok was in Madrid meeting Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar in the final stop of a round of meetings with European leaders before two important summits on the future of Europe's single currency.</p>
<p>He said he was optimistic all the remaining issues on European economic and monetary union could be resolved by the end of the second summit in Amsterdam on June 16 and 17.</p>
<p>&quot;Attitudes (among European leaders) seem very optimistic. They don't want to be pessimistic about the difficulties that exist in some European capitals,&quot; he said. &quot;Everyone knows we are at a crucial point in the European process.&quot;</p>
<p>The Dutch prime minister also said Spain had made some important proposals and he praised Spain's efforts to ensure Europe's single currency launch proceeded smoothly.</p>
<p>Aznar added that he also sensed there was a great deal of political will in Europe to resolve the remaining questions on EMU at the Amsterdam summit.</p>
<p>&quot;In the general panorama I see a lot of optimism,&quot; Aznar told the joint news conference. &quot;The political will is very determined.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
