<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645339" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Hung parliament seen in inconclusive Irish vote.</title>
<headline>Hung parliament seen in inconclusive Irish vote.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ireland's election may produce a hung parliament with neither the centre-left government nor centre-right opposition able to form a majority government, according to unofficial estimates on Saturday.</p>
<p>The estimates, carried out by so-called tallymen working for major political parties, suggested that voters had dumped Prime Minister John Bruton's three-party coalition but failed to give the opposition Fianna Fail-led alliance a winning mandate.</p>
<p>According to initial indications, Fianna Fail's electoral ally, the right wing Progressive Democrats of Mary Harney would lose several of the eight seats they hold in parliament.</p>
<p>This would leave Fianna Fail leader Bertie Ahern casting around smaller parties to win the 85 seats he needs to control the 166-seat Dail or lower house of parliament.</p>
<p>A separate exit poll conducted by the semi-state RTE broadcasting network confirmed the tallymen's findings and said the outgoing coalition would win 39.8 percent of total votes and the rival alliance 45.5 percent.</p>
<p>An inconclusive result is the outcome most feared by financial markets. Economists say the resultant uncertainty about economic policy and the prospect of a precarious government could cast a shadow over Irish markets and worry international investors.</p>
<p>Fianna Fail spokesmen refused to accept the prospect of a hung parliament as counting continued in all 41 constituencies and Fine Gael activists said it was too early to accept defeat.</p>
<p>The big loser in the election appeared to be Bruton's key ally, the Labour party of Dick Spring, which has been in government for 10 of the last 15 years.</p>
<p>According to early counts, the party could lose up to nine of its 32 parliamentary seats, and with it the balance of power.</p>
<p>But Finance Minister Ruairi Quinn of the Labour party said he would not concede defeat. &quot;Of course I am disappointed,&quot; Quinn told RTE as the national trend was broadcast. &quot;We have delivered the best performing economy in Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>Bruton campaigned on the platform of unprecedented prosperity since his coalition took over from a Fianna Fail and Labour administration at the end of 1994.</p>
<p>A major victor in the election could be Sinn Fein, political wing of Irish Republican Army (IRA) guerrillas fighting British rule of Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>Early estimates showed Sinn Fein's Caoimhghin O Caolain winning one of the five seats being contested in the border area of Cavan Monaghan.</p>
<p>It would be the first time Sinn Fein entered the Irish parliament since the birth of the Irish state in the 1920s and would cap a spectacular year for the party.</p>
<p>Held at arm's length by most established political parties because of continued IRA violence, Sinn Fein lifted its share of votes in Northern Ireland's British elections from 11 percent in 1992 to a record 17 percent last month.</p>
<p>The party is expected to use its Irish mandate to argue for automatic inclusion in Northern Ireland peace talks in Belfast from which it is currently barred because of the IRA's ending of a 17-month ceasefire in February 1996.</p>
<p>Both major Irish coalitions have ruled out any electoral deal with Sinn Fein, to register disapproval of the IRA's failure to end its war and embrace democratic politics to achieve its goals.</p>
<p>This means that the next government will have to rely on the support of small independent parties which are expected to get around 11 percent of the national vote.</p>
<p>These include the Green party, which has one member of parliament at present, and anti-abortion &quot;family values&quot; groupings which want a referendums to outlaw abortion and to reverse the legalisation of divorce.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
