<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645337" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: IRA allies Sinn Fein win seat in Irish parliament.</title>
<headline>IRA allies Sinn Fein win seat in Irish parliament.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Marshall</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sinn Fein, political wing of the outlawed IRA, will enter parliament for the first time since the birth of the Irish state in the 1920s after winning a seat on Saturday in the border constituency of Cavan Monaghan.</p>
<p>Caoimhghin O Caolain's election victory sends signals beyond Ireland's borders to Washington, London and Dublin and will reinforce the party's demand for entry to talks on the future of Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>Britain, Ireland and the United States refuse ministerial-level talks with Sinn Fein until its gets its Irish Republican Army (IRA) allies to call a lasting truce in its 28-year war against British rule of Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>It was the first time since 1981 that Sinn Fein had won a seat in Dublin's Leinster House assembly and capped a year in which the party won two seats in Northern Ireland in Britain's May 1 election, its best result in 40 years.</p>
<p>Previous successful Sinn Fein candidates refused to take up their seats but O Caolain plans to participate and use his parliamentary leverage to win concessions from the British and Irish governments in Sinn Fein's campaign to end British rule of Northern Ireland and unite the region with the Irish Republic.</p>
<p>The party, led by Gerry Adams, says it is a separate organisation from the Irish Republican Army, the Catholic-backed guerrilla force whose war against Britain is at the heart of a conflict which has killed 3,200 people.</p>
<p>It is barred by Britain and Ireland from Northern Ireland peace talks because the IRA has not restored a ceasefire it broke in February 1996 with a huge bomb in London. But Sinn Fein insists it is committed to peace and demands entry to the talks.</p>
<p>&quot;Our vote is on the up,&quot; Adams told Irish radio. &quot;It's a signal because we now have a T.D. (member of parliament) in Leinster House who cannot be excluded. We have made the point time and again there is a need for inclusiveness and equality.&quot;</p>
<p>O Caolain said his victory demonstrated a &quot;clear acceptance and understanding of the central role Sinn Fein has played in an earnest endeavour to ensure that we have an inclusive peace process in place.&quot;</p>
<p>Two other Sinn Fein candidates had outside chances of winning seats, according to early counts, and many of the party's candidates were recording a dramatic increase in their share of the vote since the last election in 1992.</p>
<p>With an exit poll and initial tallies predicting a hung parliament, the support of smaller parties like Sinn Fein could be crucial for any coalition trying to form a majority.</p>
<p>Both of Ireland's competing coalition blocs have ruled out a deal with the party while its IRA allies are still at war.</p>
<p>O Caolain said it was too early to say how he would vote in parliament. &quot;Clearly we will await the outcome of this election,&quot; he said. &quot;Under the direction of...the national executive of Sinn Fein, I will vote in accordance with their judgement.&quot;</p>
<p>Adams said the party would seek a &quot;positive&quot; role in parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;We will look to help to form, or to work with those parties who wish to form, a government here,&quot; he said. &quot;We want to see a stable government. We want to see it established with all speed.&quot;</p>
<p>Sinn Fein also fields candidates in Northern Ireland in British elections. Adams and senior strategist Martin McGuinness were elected to Britain's House of Commons in the May 1 election, but have refused to take their seats as this would entail swearing allegiance to the Queen.</p>
<p>The party decided in 1986 to abandon its long-standing policy of boycotting the Irish parliament, but until now has failed to capture any seats in subsequent elections.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
