<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645357" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac signals active role despite power-sharing.</title>
<headline>Chirac signals active role despite power-sharing.</headline>
<byline>Marie-Benedicte Allaire</byline>
<dateline>LILLE, France 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gaullist President Jacques Chirac signalled on Saturday he would keep an active role in governing France despite having to share power with a new leftist government headed by Prime Minister Lionel Jospin.</p>
<p>Addressing a health cooperative conference in the northern city of Lille, the conservative head of state ticked off a series of areas in which he intended to watch over things, ranging from ensuring that France honoured its European commitments to working to expand French trade.</p>
<p>He had experience in &quot;cohabitation&quot; -- what the French call power-sharing -- and was thus able &quot;to appreciate the fundamental role of the president as guardian of our institutions,&quot; he said during his first outing since his centre-right allies were swept from power in last Sunday's parliamentary election.</p>
<p>Chirac served as prime minister in 1986-88 under late Socialist president Francois Mitterrand, who was widely credited with outmanoeuvring Chirac in a series of political confrontations.</p>
<p>&quot;Today my duty is to preserve our European advantages...and to continue to advance, despite the obstacles, towards a Europe that is united, strong and just,&quot; Chirac said.</p>
<p>He had spent the past week closeted in his presidential palace, publicly sighted just once, when television cameras captured a grim-looking Chirac presiding over the first meeting of France's new leftist cabinet.</p>
<p>Jospin, meanwhile, pledged that his government would be &quot;that much more efficient and rigorous&quot; in order to meet the enormous expectations of the French people.</p>
<p>In an order published in France's official journal, he said citizens want a government adapted to modern times but also providing social safeguards &quot;which cannot be assured by marketplace mechanisms alone.&quot;</p>
<p>New Socialist Foreign Minister Hubert Vedrine conferred by telephone with his German and Polish counterparts on forthcoming diplomatic events, the French Foreign Ministry announced.</p>
<p>German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel and Polish Foreign Minister Dariusz Rosati telephoned from Warsaw, where Kinkel was visiting, to congratule Vedrine on his new portfolio and discuss a range of diplomatic topics, a ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>He declined to give details but said Kinkel and Vedrine discussed a European Union summit in Amsterdam on June 16-17 and a Franco-German summit set for next Friday in Poitiers, France.</p>
<p>Jospin and Chirac will both attend the Poitiers summit, their first official joint outing.</p>
<p>The Franco-German meeting will take place among growing uncertainty surrounding the conditions and timetable for a single European currency, in which Paris and Bonn are the key players.</p>
<p>During the election campaign, Jospin said he would impose conditions on Paris joining European monetary union, including a ban on additional austerity measures for France to qualify for the euro.</p>
<p>The Amsterdam EU summit is expected to reach agreement on a new pact on EU institutional reforms, intended to update the Maastricht treaty, and French officials said in Brussels on Friday that they did not intend to delay the pact.</p>
<p>The meeting will also focus on a stability pact intended to assure fiscal discipline on the part of states participating in European monetary union. The pact has already been drafted but the new French government has yet to make clear if it will accept it or seek changes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
