<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645335" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Jospin stand on Renault closure due this week.</title>
<headline>Jospin stand on Renault closure due this week.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene said on Saturday his newly appointed French counterpart Lionel Jospin would disclose his stance this week on carmaker Renault's plans to close a plant in Belgium.</p>
<p>Jospin &quot;cleared up&quot; his position on the proposed plant closure in Vilvoorde, Dehaene said after his talks with Jospin.</p>
<p>&quot;I think he will get into this matter in the next few days,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>Until now, Paris has taken a hands-off stance on the Vilvoorde plant closing. But France has a new leftist government, swept into office in last Sunday's upset parliamentary election.</p>
<p>Dehaene had explained he wanted to come to Paris immediately after Jospin took power because he needed to talk to him about the threatened closure of the Renault prior to June 10, when both the carmaker's board of directors and its shareholders have set meetings.</p>
<p>The French state is a minority shareholder in Renault.</p>
<p>Jospin aides said after the talks that the state would disclose its views in time for the shareholder meeting.</p>
<p>One aide said it was natural for Jospin to welcome Dehaene so quickly after coming to power, as part of his ongoing efforts to get better acquainted with France's European partners.</p>
<p>&quot;In addition, it was a sign of the prime minister's desire to immediately launch work on a matter which has caused a storm,&quot; the aide said.</p>
<p>Renault, which announced the closure with 3,100 job losses in February, reiterated on Wednesday its intention to go ahead with plans to cut costs and streamline its European car assembly operations.</p>
<p>Dehaene, who lives in Vilvoorde, has branded next month's planned closure as &quot;unacceptable.&quot; The French Socialist Party, part of Jospin's government, has also said it opposed the closure.</p>
<p>Jospin pledged during the parliamentary election campaign that he would ask Renault to study alternatives to allow the plant to remain open.</p>
<p>Jospin Aides said the two men also discussed Europe and bilateral issues. But they gave no details of those talks.</p>
<p>Dehaene said, &quot;we had an exchange of views on the entire range of our shared problems.&quot;</p>
<p>Dehaene's Paris trip was part of a campaign to preserve jobs. Louis Tobback, head of the Flemish Socialist Party, has urged Jospin to delay the closure of the assembly plant and start discussions about alternatives.</p>
<p>Renault lost 5.25 billion francs ($901.2 million) last year and is struggling to break even this year.</p>
<p>Renault-Vilvoorde workers have said they will halt work ahead of the June 10 meetings. Production at the plant has been patchy since employees voted to end a six-week strike which followed February's news of the closure.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
