<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645333" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>DENMARK: One dead, three wounded in Danish biker clash.</title>
<headline>One dead, three wounded in Danish biker clash.</headline>
<dateline>COPENHAGEN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A member of the Bandidos motorcycle gang was shot dead in Denmark on Saturday in what police said was the latest clash in a Nordic biker war with the rival Hells Angels that had already taken nine lives.</p>
<p>Police in the seaside town of Liseleje, 30 km (20 miles) northwest of Copenhagen, said four members of the Bandidos gang were hit by a burst fired from an automatic weapon from a passing car as they left a hamburger bar. One of them was killed and the other three were wounded.</p>
<p>Witnesses said two or three men were in the car, which drove off after the shooting. Police set up roadblocks in the area in an effort to catch the attackers.</p>
<p>Last Wednesday a car bomb exploded at a Bandidos clubhouse in the Norwegian town of Drammen, killing a woman passer-by and prompting Prime Minister Thorbjoern Jagland to promise to crack down on the Nordic offshoots of U.S. motorcycle clans.</p>
<p>A Nordic vendetta between the two gangs has festered since 1993 when the Bandidos first began to challenge the Hells Angels for dominance in the region.</p>
<p>A member of the Hells Angels-affiliated Rednecks died in a gunfight with Bandidos in Sweden in 1994 and two Bandidos were killed in Sweden and Finland in the following two years.</p>
<p>Full-scale war erupted in March 1996 when gunmen outside Copenhagen airport shot dead Danish Bandido leader Uffe Larsen and wounded three of his companions.</p>
<p>A Danish Bandidos member was fatally shot in the head near the Norwegian town of Drammen in July that year and in October, in an apparent act of revenge, a shoulder-fired missile ploughed into Hells Angels headquarters in Copenhagen, killing a member and a women party guest.</p>
<p>A Hells Angel was shot dead last january in the west Danish town of Aalborg.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COPENHAGEN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DENMARK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
