<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645349" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Jospin backs scrapping canal plan.</title>
<headline>France's Jospin backs scrapping canal plan.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Prime Minister Lionel Jospin backs scrapping the controversial Rhine-Rhone canal project but has not made up his mind on the fate of a nuclear fast breeder reactor, Environment Minister Dominique Voynet said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Voynet, an ecologist member of Jospin's new leftist government, told the weekly Le Journal du Dimanche that she favours scrapping both projects but that as far as Jospin was concerned, only the fate of the canal project had been decided.</p>
<p>&quot;Lionel Jospin told me on Monday evening: 'You can go ahead with scrapping the (canal) project. For the Superphenix (fast breeder reactor), I have to take a decision',&quot; Voynet said.</p>
<p>France's former centre-right government was divided over what to do with the 60-billion-franc ($10.3 billion) reactor, which has been plagued by problems since it was built 20 years ago.</p>
<p>Environmental groups have branded the reactor a costly and dangerous dinosaur and have urged that it be shut down.</p>
<p>But the nuclear lobby has asked that it be kept in operation as a research reactor, with the possibility of also generating power.</p>
<p>The decision to cancel the planned 230-km (140-mile) Rhine-Rhone canal &quot;is irrevocable,&quot; Voynet said.</p>
<p>The canal was designed to accommodate barge traffic from the Rhine River where it passes by the city of Mulhouse to the Saone River near Saint-Jean-de-Losne.</p>
<p>Opponents denounced both its cost -- an estimated 50 billion francs ($8.6 billion) -- and the damage it would have caused to the environment as it cut through unspoiled valleys and farmland.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
