<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645315" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Gingrich offers support to U.S. Nicaraguans.</title>
<headline>Gingrich offers support to U.S. Nicaraguans.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Zengerle</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>House Speaker Newt Gingrich said on Saturday he had sent a letter to Attorney General Janet Reno asking her to extend for a year a special programme protecting the immigration status of Nicaraguans in the United States.</p>
<p>&quot;It is totally wrong to punish innocent people,&quot; he said at a meeting on immigration and other issues with Miami-area political and community leaders. The letter to Reno was dated June 6 and distributed on Saturday.</p>
<p>The meeting was attended by most of Miami's leading Republicans, among them Reps. Ileana Ros-Lehtinen and Lincoln Diaz-Balart and Jeb Bush, the son of former President George Bush and a narrow loser in Florida's gubernatorial election in 1994.</p>
<p>Many members of Miami's Latin American community, traditionally dominated by staunchly Republican Cuban-Americans, have questioned recently what they see as the Republican Party's hostility to newcomers.</p>
<p>In particular, some have protested plans to make English the official U.S. language, eliminate government benefits to legal immigrants and allow deportation of tens of thousands of Central Americans who came to the United States during the civil wars of the 1980s.</p>
<p>An estimated 40,000 Nicaraguans living in the Miami area are at risk of being kicked out of the United States under the tough new immigration rules.</p>
<p>The Miami Nicaraguans have filed suit against the government, saying they are taxpaying workers who should not be deported to a country that remains unstable by a government that offered them asylum. Immigrant advocates have argued many of them fled their homeland at the behest of the Reagan and Bush administrations as a form of protest of the ruling leftist Sandinistas.</p>
<p>During the meeting, Gingrich said he opposed forcing new laws retroactively on immigrants already in the United States, although he said he favoured making changes that would affect new immigrants, including development of a private insurance system for legal residents.</p>
<p>&quot;It's one thing to say about the future, let's set ground rules we all understand,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>After the meeting, immigrant activists gave Gingrich's remarks reserved approval. Haydee Marin, Nicaraguan human rights ambassador to the United Nations, said she was pleased he had made a commitment to immigrants from Nicaragua in public.</p>
<p>&quot;I am pleased that he has spoken in a public forum,&quot; she said. &quot;The letter and the promise that he will ... (support) legislation, for me that's really good,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>During the meeting, Gingrich also said he supported plans to turn the former Homestead Air Force base into a commercial airport, expressed support for measures to preserve the nearby Everglades, and said he favoured including funding for the Caribbean Basin Initiative in the budget now making its way through Washington.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NICG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
