<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645360" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: Storm strikes Netherlands, many people hurt.</title>
<headline>Storm strikes Netherlands, many people hurt.</headline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Many people were injured in the Netherlands on Saturday after a brief but ferocious storm broke over the country, with strong winds capsizing boats, uprooting trees and disrupting train services.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Dutch coastguard described the situation as chaotic, with many capsized vessels. Some were off the coast but the most serious problems concerned pleasure craft on the huge inland IJsselmeer lake, just north of Amsterdam.</p>
<p>Coastguard boats and helicopters were alerted to rescue those thrown overboard in more than 100 separate incidents. There were no deaths reported, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are many people in trouble, the storm is moving very fast. We are trying to get everybody out of the water.&quot;</p>
<p>The spokesman said the storm, which had force 10 winds and lashing rain, first appeared in the south-west of the country in the early afternoon, reaching Amsterdam around an hour and a half later. It has since moved swiftly on north-eastwards.</p>
<p>In other parts of the country, trains were severely disrupted and traffic across the the main bridge in the port city of Rotterdam stopped due to a car overturning. Witnesses there reported debris and uprooted trees littering the streets.</p>
<p>&quot;Rotterdam was particuarly badly affected. We have a few people injured by falling trees but nothing more serious. A few also fell overboard from boats that capsized but thankfully we have recovered them all,&quot; a police spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>At Rotterdam airport four small planes were badly damaged by the high winds. An airport spokesman said the planes were grounded at the time and international traffic was unaffected.</p>
<p>At the country's main Schiphol airport in Amsterdam, planes were slightly delayed but there was no damage.</p>
<p>The high winds uprooted trees across the country. In the southwestern town of Bergen-op-Zoom, about 20 people were reported to have been injured by a marquee collapsing.</p>
<p>The precise number of casualties nationwide was not yet available.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
