<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645383" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac says will ensure all serve French interests.</title>
<headline>Chirac says will ensure all serve French interests.</headline>
<dateline>LILLE, France 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gaullist President Jacques Chirac, on his first outing since a parliamentary election obliged him to share power with a leftist government, said on Saturday he would ensure the arrangement served France's best interests.</p>
<p>&quot;Today my duty is to ensure that each has his place and respects the other, and that together we serve the interests and values...that unite us,&quot; Chirac told a health care cooperative in the northern city of Lille.  </p>
<p>Chirac, who spent the last week closeted in the Elysee presidential palace after a leftist alliance led by Socialist Lionel Jospin swept the previous centre-right majority from power, said the interests and values he referred to included equality of opportunity, civic duty and republican virtue.</p>
<p>His duty was also to &quot;continue to advance, despite the obstacles, towards a Europe that is united, strong and just,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Today my duty is to ensure that France enters the era of high technology, without which we would be without economic growth and full employment,&quot; the French head of state added.</p>
<p>Chirac noted that he had experience in power-sharing or &quot;cohabitation&quot; as he had served as a rightist prime minister under the late Socialist president Francois Mitterrand and thus was able &quot;to appreciate the fundamental role of the president as guardian of our institutions.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
