<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645347" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ireland heads for political unknown.</title>
<headline>Ireland heads for political unknown.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1996-06-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ireland headed into the political unknown on Sunday.</p>
<p>Election results suggested neither the centre-left government of Prime Minister John Bruton nor his centre-right rival, Bertie Ahern, would have a clear majority.</p>
<p>The only party to register unqualified pleasure was Sinn Fein, political wing of IRA guerrillas, which will claim its first seat in the Irish parliament since the 1920s, complicating Anglo-Irish efforts to forge Northern Ireland peace.</p>
<p>The British, Irish and U.S. governments refuse ministerial contact with Sinn Fein until its Irish Republican Army (IRA) allies restore a 17-month truce they broke in February 1996.</p>
<p>With 106 of the 166 seats accounted for, the pro-business Fianna Fail party of Ahern was registering the highest percentage vote but analysts said it looked unlikely the party and its smaller Progressive Democrats ally could command a majority in parliament.</p>
<p>Instead the nation seemed set for days of horse-trading between Ahern's alliance and smaller parties such as the Greens to try to reach the 85-seat backing needed to govern.</p>
<p>It appeared the worst possible outcome for financial markets which had feared a hung parliament and the absence of a firm government to spell out economic policy for domestic and international investors.</p>
<p>&quot;What the market really does not want to see is a hung parliament. That is the greatest negative,&quot; Padhraic Garvey, economist at Riada Stockbrokers told Reuters.</p>
<p>Ahern's challenge was further blunted by the poor showing of the Progressive Democrats of Mary Harney, which polled around 4.7 percent of votes and was expected to lose many of its eight seats.</p>
<p>Bruton delayed issuing a detailed assessment of the results. &quot;It would be inappropriate to make further comment until the outlook becomes much clearer,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>His &quot;Rainbow Coalition&quot; was torpedoed by the poor showing of Dick Spring's Labour party, which has held a balance of power in several governments over the past 15 years.</p>
<p>Voters spurned Labour, probably to punish the party for pulling out of a Fianna Fail-led coalition in 1992 when it joined Bruton's Fine Gael and the smaller Democratic Left in government.</p>
<p>&quot;We seem to be the fall guys,&quot; a rueful Spring commented as results came in showing that his party's support has ebbed from around 20 per cent in 1992 to 10.5 at the weekend. &quot;It strikes me that neither side will have a majority.&quot;</p>
<p>Spring, and his chief lieutenant, Finance Minister Ruairi Quinn, ruled out any new coalition with Ahern's Fianna Fail, which may have to look to Independents and Greens for help.</p>
<p>But Quinn said every party would have to look at its options once final results are known on Sunday.</p>
<p>Fianna Fail, Fine Gael and Labour all refuse to envisage an electoral deal with Sinn Fein until the IRA renews its truce.</p>
<p>&quot;If we are a few seats short, there are many options. I would not go seeking Sinn Fein's vote, though I would not refuse any support,&quot; Ahern said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not going looking for Sinn Fein support. That is definite,&quot; Spring said.</p>
<p>Gerry Adams, the Sinn Fein president, said: &quot;It is our fervent hope that it is a strong government, able to act decisively on rebuilding the peace process.</p>
<p>&quot;Sinn Fein will endeavour to work with it, to realise the hope and expectation which undoubtedly exists following three elections on this island, the change of government in Britain and the outcome of today's election.&quot;</p>
<p>On May 1 Adams and his chief negotiator, Martin McGuinness, were elected to the British parliament with a record 16 percent of the vote against 11 percent five years earlier.</p>
<p>They refuse to take their seats because it would entail swearing allegiance to Britain's Queen.</p>
<p>But Caoimhghin O Caolain, Sinn Fein's successful candidate in Cavan Monaghan, will be taking his seat in the Irish parliament because of a change of strategy by the party in 1986 when it decided to end its boycott of the Dublin assembly.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
