<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645377" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy's Ciampi urges respect of Maastricht timetable.</title>
<headline>Italy's Ciampi urges respect of Maastricht timetable.</headline>
<dateline>VENICE, Italy 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italian Treasury Minister Carlo Azeglio Ciampi said on Saturday he was convinced that the European Union must respect the Maastrict timetable on monetary union to regain its competitive edge in the world.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm convinced that it is opportune and in everybody's interest to procede along the planned route, according to the agreed upon dates and according to what is clearly indicated in the Maastricht Treaty,&quot; Ciampi said.</p>
<p>He was responding to reporters' questions on whether there should be a weakening of the criteria for economic and monetary union (EMU) laid out in the treaty or a delay of the launch of Europe's single currency, planned for January 1, 1999.</p>
<p>Ciampi praised the competitiveness of the economy of the United States, saying that EMU was supposed to help Europe achieve a similar ability to compete in the world economy.</p>
<p>&quot;European integration, according to the Maastricht Treaty, is one of the main conditions for obtaining this (competitive) capacity in Europe, for having a long-lasting period of stability,&quot; he told reporters at the inauguration of a new university in Venice. -- Rome newsroom +396 678 2501</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VENICE, Italy"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
