<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645341" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac to assure France honours Europe commitments.</title>
<headline>Chirac to assure France honours Europe commitments.</headline>
<byline>Marie-Benedicte Allaire</byline>
<dateline>LILLE, France 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gaullist President Jacques Chirac, on his first outing since a parliamentary election obliged him to share power with a leftist government, said on Saturday he would ensure that France honoured its European commitments.</p>
<p>&quot;Today my duty is to preserve our European advantages...and to continue to advance, despite the obstacles, towards a Europe that is united, strong and just,&quot; Chirac told a health care cooperative in the northern city of Lille.</p>
<p>Chirac said he was obliged, during the new era of power-sharing, to ensure that each branch of government &quot;has its place and respects the other, and that together we serve the interests and values...that unite us.&quot;</p>
<p>Those values included equality of opportunity, civic duty and republican virtue, he said.</p>
<p>The comments were the first extended remarks made by Chirac since a leftist alliance led by Socialist Lionel Jospin swept the previous centre-right majority from power in last Sunday's parlaimentary election.</p>
<p>The president had spent the past week closeted in the Elysee presidential palace.</p>
<p>He was been seen just once during the week, when television cameras captured a grim-looking Chirac presiding over the first meeting of France's new cabinet headed by Socialist Prime Minister Lionel Jospin.</p>
<p>He later declined to appear with the new cabinet on the presidential palace steps for a group photograph.</p>
<p>Chirac's comments on Europe were significant as the Socialists, during the parliamentary election campaign, raised questions about what line they would follow on Europe.</p>
<p>They said they would impose new conditions on France's commitment to a single European currency and other European Union plans in progress.</p>
<p>In particular, the Socialists ruled out new austerity to bring about the shift to a single European currency and have suggested they may take a new look at the stability pact intended to impose fiscal restraint on states participating in European monetary union.</p>
<p>On another European front, however, France's new government told its European Union partners in Brussels on Friday that it did not intend to delay a new EU treaty on institutional reforms.</p>
<p>Some EU countries had questioned whether the election of the Socialists in France might mean a delay in the treaty in order to give them time to prepare new positions.</p>
<p>But France's ambassador to the EU Pierre de Boissieu said in Brussels on Friday that the government intended to wrap up negotiations at the EU summit in Amsterdam on June 16 and 17, as scheduled, an official said.</p>
<p>Chirac, in his speech in Lille, noted that he had experience in power-sharing or &quot;cohabitation&quot; as it is known in France, and was thus able &quot;to appreciate the fundamental role of the president as guardian of our institutions.&quot; He served as a rightist prime minister under the late Socialist president Francois Mitterrand.</p>
<p>He said he was prepared to do battle wherever needed to ensure France's security and influence and increase its share of the international marketplace.</p>
<p>Other duties were to ensure social unity and welfare and full French participation in &quot;the era of high technology, without which we would be without economic growth and full employment.&quot;</p>
<p>Chirac was in Lille to inaugurate the renovated Fine Arts Museum. The outing had been planned before the right's defeat. Accompanying him was new Socialist Employment and Solidarity Minister Martine Aubry, and new junior minister for health Bernard Kouchner of the leftist Radical-Socialist Party.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
