<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645336" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ireland on way to hung parliament with Sinn Fein.</title>
<headline>Ireland on way to hung parliament with Sinn Fein.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ireland headed for political uncertainty after voters apparently denied a clear majority to either the centre-left government of Prime Minister John Bruton or his challenger, Bertie Ahern.</p>
<p>Early returns from Friday's election showed Ahern's Fianna Fail commanding the biggest share of the vote but his electoral ally, the Progressive Democrats, were set to lose seats and spoil his plan to form a right-of-centre two-party government.</p>
<p>Ahern, bidding at 45 to become Ireland's youngest premier, might have to depend for support on small parties, including Sinn Fein, the political wing of IRA guerrillas, which is set to enter parliament for the first time since the 1920s.</p>
<p>But both Ahern and Bruton have ruled out a coalition with Sinn Fein until its Irish Republican Army allies end the war against British rule of Northern Ireland that they resumed last year with a London bomb after a 17-month truce.</p>
<p>Financial markets had feared an inconclusive result. Economists say the resultant uncertainty about economic policy and the prospect of a precarious government could cast a shadow over markets and worry investors.</p>
<p>The days of Bruton's three-party &quot;Rainbow coalition&quot;, so-called because of its political mix, seemed numbered.</p>
<p>An exit poll by state broadcaster RTE gave it 39.8 per cent of votes against 45.5 for the combined Fianna Fail and Progressive Democrats. Small parties, including independents, the Green party, anti-abortion parties and Sinn Fein took the remainder.</p>
<p>But with counting set to continue until late on Saturday, none of the Rainbow parties -- Bruton's Fine Gael, the Labour party of Dick Spring or Democratic Left -- would admit defeat and Fianna Fail would say only that it was confident.</p>
<p>Spring, probably Ireland's best-known politician, was returned with an increased vote in his native Kerry but acknowledged that his party appeared to have fared worse than at any time in the last 15 years. &quot;We seem to be the fall guys,&quot; he told RTE.</p>
<p>His party colleague, Finance Minister Ruairi Quinn, said: &quot;Of course I am disappointed. We've delivered the best performing economy in Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>Bruton campaigned on the platform of unprecedented prosperity since his coalition took over from a Fianna Fail and Labour coalition at the end of 1994.</p>
<p>Spring ruled out seeking the support of Sinn Fein's Caoimhghin O Caolain (kwivin o keelan), who won a seat in the border constituency of Cavan Monaghan.&quot; We are not going looking for Sinn Fein support. That is definite,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But he added: &quot;I hope Mr O Caolain comes into the Dail (parliament) and lets us know he is committed to democratic politics.&quot;</p>
<p>Britain, Ireland and the United States do not regard Sinn Fein as a legitimate political party because of its support from the IRA and refuse ministerial-level talks with its leaders.</p>
<p>But Sinn Fein, which says it is committed to ending the 28-year Northern Ireland conflict, has scored stunning successes this year, raising its vote in Northern Ireland from 11 to 17 percent to elect its two key leaders to Britain's parliament on May 1.</p>
<p>Political analysts said Labour, in government for 10 of the last 15 years, appeared to be suffering a backlash for abandoning a Fianna Fail-led government in late 1994 in a row over legal appointments and then switching support to Fine Gael.</p>
<p>Its poor showing was mirrored by Mary Harney's Progressive Democrats, a right-wing party with eight seats in the outgoing parliament but slim chances of getting more than five in the new assembly, analysts said.</p>
<p>Voters appeared to have punished Harney's party for suggesting that 25,000 civil service jobs should be cut and that unmarried mothers should stay with their parents. Under pressure from Ahern, Harney modified both policies during the campaign.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
