<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645314" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Claudette Colbert's Oscar fails to attract bidders.</title>
<headline>Claudette Colbert's Oscar fails to attract bidders.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Claudette Colbert's 1934 Oscar statuette failed to attract a high enough bid on Saturday and was withdrawn from a sale of Hollywood memorabilia at Christie's inaugural West Coast auction.</p>
<p>The prestigious auction house, which last week opened its first Los Angeles salesroom, had hoped Colbert's Academy Award for Best Actress for the comedy &quot;It Happened One Night&quot; would fetch between $150,000 and $200,000.</p>
<p>But it attracted no bids at the starting price and was pulled from the sale, which was entitled &quot;Unforgettable Hollywood.&quot;</p>
<p>Marcia Hobbs, chairman of Christie's West Coast, said the gilded statuette still might be sold to an after-sale bidder following talks with the consigner.</p>
<p>&quot;The feeling was that the sale, less than six months after the record sale of Clark Gable's Oscar for the same film, at a stunning price, might have put people off,&quot; Hobbs said. She said Gable's Oscar for the Frank Capra-directed film sold at Christie's for $600,000 last December.</p>
<p>It is not unusual for items that do not attract estimated bids to be put back on sale later. &quot;It depends on the wishes of the consigner,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The French-born Colbert died at her home in Barbados last July at age 92. The Oscar statuette -- the only Academy Award she won in her Hollywood career -- was believed to have been put up for auction by her estate. She had no children.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
