<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645317" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. military sex laws to be reviewed.</title>
<headline>U.S. military sex laws to be reviewed.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Defence Secretary William Cohen said Saturday he will set up panels to review military training practices, privacy issues and enforcement of laws against adultery.</p>
<p>&quot;A key to military effectiveness is a disciplinary system that is fair, equitable and clear,&quot; Cohen said in a statement. &quot;Recent perceptions that our system is inconsistent damage the morale of our troops. The actions I am taking today will assure that our training remains superb and that our rules are well understood at all levels of command.&quot;</p>
<p>The Pentagon is trying to grapple with a number of sex scandals that have rocked the military involving sex between superiors and subordinates at training bases and adultery that forced the Air Force's first woman bomber pilot, Lt. Kelly Flinn, to leave last month. She was facing a possible court-martial on charges of adultery, having sex with an enlisted man and lying about the matter.</p>
<p>Air Force Gen. Joseph Ralston, a top candidate to become chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, was under fire because of an adulterous affair 13 years ago. The Flinn and Ralston cases have raised questions about whether adultery is treated the same for both sexes and among all ranks.</p>
<p>Cohen instructed the Defence Department General Counsel to review along with the Joint Service Committee on Military Justice the guidance given to military commanders on enforcing laws against adultry.</p>
<p>Pentagon officials said they will not be changing the laws, but looking at how to make sure they are fairly enforced.</p>
<p>A second panel of civilians and military officials will review disciplinary actions and advise the secretary on how to maintain good order and discipline in the military while respecting individuals' privacy, the Pentagon said.</p>
<p>A third panel, headed by former Sen. Nancy Kassebaum Baker will look at the issues associated with training women and men together.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
