<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645308" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. ethics panel urges ban on human cloning.</title>
<headline>U.S. ethics panel urges ban on human cloning.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Wilson</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. ethics panel recommended on Saturday that Congress enact legislation to ban the cloning of entire human beings for now but allow the cloning of human embryos for private laboratory research.</p>
<p>Under the scenario proposed by the National Bioethics Advisory Commission, scientists or doctors could make cloned human embryos for research purposes but would be prohibited from implanting them into women's wombs to make viable babies.</p>
<p>&quot;Human cloning that leads to the birth of a child should be forbidden by law for at least three to five years,&quot; the panel said in its report, which will be sent to President Bill Clinton on Monday.</p>
<p>Clinton asked the advisory group in February to review the complex legal and ethical ramifications of cloning after scientists in Scotland reported they had cloned a lamb -- which they named Dolly -- from a single cell taken from an adult sheep.</p>
<p>Their success was controversial, raising the prospect that the procedure could be used to make humans genetically identical to an existing man or woman.</p>
<p>The U.S. commission of 18 scientists, lawyers and theologians was faced with trying to reconcile the views of opponents of cloning who regard it as an affront to nature and demand a complete ban, and supporters who see it as a stunning scientific breakthrough with promising medical repercussions.</p>
<p>Polls taken shortly after the announcement of the cloning of Dolly showed 90 percent of Americans opposed human cloning.</p>
<p>Clinton in March broadened his 1994 prohibition on government-funded human embryo research to include federal funding of human cloning work, saying it raised deep concerns &quot;given our most cherished concepts of faith and humanity.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Each human life is unique, born of a miracle that reaches beyond laboratory science. I believe we must respect this profound gift and resist the temptation to replicate ourselves,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The panel's proposal would extend that human cloning ban to include privately funded work, but leave in place the current policy allowing private embryo research.</p>
<p>The commission's recommendations appeared to meet the most immediate concern of many Americans -- that the scientific procedure that produced Dolly might be used to make children who would be exact genetic copies of a single adult.</p>
<p>But critics complained the commission had not gone far enough. Sen. Christopher Bond, a Missouri Republican, said it left the door wide open to future cloning.</p>
<p>&quot;I had hoped that the federal ethics commission would not be afraid to make a strong moral statement that human cloning is wrong, period, and should be banned,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bond, who introduced a bill that would impose a total ban on human cloning, said it would be up to Congress and state legislatures to resolve the issue.</p>
<p>The Family Research Council accused the commission of &quot;completely avoiding the subject of ethics.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;FRC strongly opposes this recommendation ... Such a policy is premised on the false assumption that human beings less than 14 days old are not completely human, thereby condoning the destruction of countless numbers of embryonic children for the sake of 'research,'&quot; the organisation said.</p>
<p>American Life League president Judie Brown said the commission had made &quot;a terrible mistake.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The persistent effort by members of the scientific community to redefine the human being and equate him with members of the animal kingdom can only lead to moral chaos and social ruin,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>A pharmaceutical industry group welcomed the recognition of the importance of genetic research, but said any ban on cloning complete human beings should be narrowly defined.</p>
<p>&quot;Any legislative prohibition on the cloning of entire human beings must not jeopardise biomedical research that involves the cloning of human genes, cells or tissues,&quot; the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
