<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645362" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italian court upholds sentences in graft trial.</title>
<headline>Italian court upholds sentences in graft trial.</headline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Italian appeals court upheld sentences against top politicians on Saturday, including former prime minister Aldo Forlani in what has become known as &quot;the mother of all corruption trials&quot;.</p>
<p>The Milan court took six days to arrive at its decision in a case that originally lasted 16 months when it was spearheaded by former anti-graft magistrate Antonio Di Pietro and televised across Italy.</p>
<p>The trial will now pass to the Cassation Court, the final stage in Italian justice.</p>
<p>The court upheld convictions for illegal party financing against both Forlani, a former Christian Democrat who faces a prison term of 28 months, and Northern League leader Umberto Bossi. Neither man was in court on Saturday.</p>
<p>The fiery secessionist was found guilty of accepting some 200 million lire ($118,000) in bribes for use by the League in their 1992 electoral campaign.</p>
<p>Also upheld were a three years' jail sentence for former Christian Democrat minister Severino Citaristi and six months for Republican Party leader Giorgio La Malfa. Both were sentenced for illegal party financing.</p>
<p>The Enimont trial involved the chemical company Montedison, which paid more than $100 million in kickbacks to extricate itself from a disastrous joint venture with state energy company ENI.</p>
<p>The court accepted plea-bargain requests from four former Montedison managers while former Milan mayor Paolo Pillitteri was cleared of all charges.</p>
<p>&quot;I heard about my acquittal from television -- my wife turned it on and what great news it was,&quot; said Pillitteri, the brother-in-law of former prime minister Bettino Craxi.</p>
<p>Craxi, who has had several convictions for corruption and who lives in self-imposed exile in Tunisia, was also sentenced, but his appeal will be considered separately by the court on July 2.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
