<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645392" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Products Outlook - Refinery run rates eyed.</title>
<headline>U.S. Products Outlook - Refinery run rates eyed.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gasoline prices in the U.S. Gulf should remain the focus of U.S. refined products traders this week, as players eye refinery operations for signs of slowing output or unplanned outages.</p>
<p>Midcontinent gasoline markets should track the movement in the U.S. Gulf, while New York Harbor markets are likely to remain well supplied due to high levels of imports.</p>
<p>Early Monday activity showed regular conventional gasoline on the Gulf firming about 0.50 cent ahead of scheduling deadline at the end of the day, with Midcontinent differentials firming in sympathy.</p>
<p>U.S. GULF COAST</p>
<p>The high level of refinery operations on the crowded &quot;Refinery Row&quot; should prevent any shortfalls in product, traders said, though short-term tightness may still occur.</p>
<p>Scheduling deadlines on the Colonial Pipeline, the main products artery to the East Coast, drove regular conventional gasoline differentials up sharply on two occasions in the past 10 days, though that strength was short-lived and concentrated on barrels for prompt delivery.</p>
<p>Monday's Colonial deadline pushed that &quot;M1&quot; regular conventional gasoline to 0.50 cent under the July NYMEX gasoline futures Monday morning from more than 1.00 cent under as of late Friday.</p>
<p>The strong refinery runs -- put at 96.7 percent of capacity in the American Petroleum Institute's (API) latest report -- heightened fears that unexpected problems could lead to production outages.</p>
<p>&quot;As long as we continue to see strong refinery production, I expect to see refinery problems,&quot; said Tom Knight, a refined products trader with Fina Inc.</p>
<p>Distillate trade appeared sluggish most of last week and was expected to stay that way as ample supplies kept prices mostly steady despite what some futures traders called a mild squeeze on NYMEX barrels for delivery during June.</p>
<p>NEW YORK HARBOR</p>
<p>Trading began slowly early Monday as players sought clearer indications of bids and offers following the basis roll to the July NYMEX contract following the expiration of June refined products last Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Mondays are tough to get a read on the market anyway,&quot; one NYH player said.</p>
<p>Bullish NYH traders may face another frustrating week as the strong gasoline imports continue to prevent any major upswings in differentials.</p>
<p>&quot;There are sellers on everything, and they're mostly looking for buyers,&quot; said Tom Knight, the Fina trader.</p>
<p>Gasoline imports of over 600,000 barrels per day reached the U.S. in the week ended May 23, according to the latest API inventory data, higher than the strong levels recorded for the same period last year.</p>
<p>However, that massive amount should fall in the coming weeks, as fewer European barrels head to the U.S. because of reduced operations there and due to expected changes in the United Kingdom's tax structure, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's going to be hard to maintain imports of 600,000 barrels per day. It's inevitable that it will fall back,&quot; Knight said.</p>
<p>But for the coming week, steady imports coupled with increased output, including the 110,000 bpd of gasoline coming from Tosco Corp's recently restarted Trainer refinery near Philadelphia, should limit any bullish moves, traders said.</p>
<p>MIDCONTINENT</p>
<p>Midcontinent markets were called mixed this week. In Group Three, unleaded gasoline differentials may come down by about 0.75 cent due to expected shipments through the Williams Co's pipeline system.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a bunch of gasoline coming in and we've seen a rise in the days of supply,&quot; said a Group Three trader.</p>
<p>The trader said she was expecting about 6 million barrels to arrive on the 17 million-barrel capacity line by early this week.</p>
<p>Supply in the Williams system rose to about 20 days on Monday from 17 days early last week.</p>
<p>On Monday, unleaded gasoline for prompt delivery in Group Three traded at 5.00 cents over July NYMEX. Diesel was expected to hold steady but may begin to rise next week amid a final round of spring planting.</p>
<p>The Chicago markets were seen trading sideways to slightly higher by the end of week.</p>
<p>&quot;I think overall the market will follow NYMEX. We've been stuck in a trading range,&quot; said a Houston-based player.</p>
<p>Chicago unleaded differentials rose about a quarter cent Monday, on the strength of the U.S. Gulf after differentials rose late last week by about a cent amid solid buying interest from a large number of refiners in the midcontinent region.</p>
<p>-- New York Energy Desk, 1 212 859 1633</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
