<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645374" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Germany's Schaueble warns against EMU delay.</title>
<headline>Germany's Schaueble warns against EMU delay.</headline>
<byline>Emma Thomasson</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A leading member of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian Democrats (CDU) was quoted on Saturday as criticising growing calls for a delay to Europe's single currency.</p>
<p>&quot;A start to currency union as outlined in the treaty is an an extremely high-ranking goal of prime importance to German policy,&quot; Wolfgang Schaeuble, CDU parliamentary leader told the Berliner Zeitung daily in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;The problem is that people like Lower Saxony premier Gerhard Schroeder intentionally destroy trust and bring a delay into play. That is irresponsible,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Schroeder, a leading opposition Social Democrat (SPD) potential candidate for chancellor, was quoted this week as saying he believed it would be better to delay the launch of the euro than to soften the entry criteria.</p>
<p>Schaeuble's statement was the latest in a widening public debate in Germany over how to launch Europe's economic and monetary union (EMU) now that Bonn looks unable to meet the criteria precisely.</p>
<p>Members of Finance Minister Theo Waigel's Christian Social Union (CSU), are committed to a strict interpretation of the three percent target for budget deficits as part of gross domestic product.</p>
<p>But Waigel has denied media reports that the party is discussing a delay to the planned 1999 EMU start date, if the target could not be fulfilled.</p>
<p>Several CSU members, however, have said the criteria determined EMU's launch, not the 1999 deadline.</p>
<p>&quot;A softening of the criteria is not an option for the CSU. Then we would rather delay the euro,&quot; CSU board member Markus Soeder was quoted as telling Bild am Sonntag in a release ahead of publication on Sunday.</p>
<p>The debate, which flared up after Waigel's failed grab for Bundesbank gold and the left-wing shift in France, revealed cracks in the political elite's hitherto united pro-EMU stand which is not shared by the more sceptical voters. New opinion polls say 71 percent of Germans want EMU put off.</p>
<p>But former European Commission president Jaques Delors told Focus news magazine a delay to EMU would be disastrous.</p>
<p>&quot;Even only a one year delay to the start of the currency union would be the end of the project,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Senior figures in the CDU and junior coalition partners the Free Democrats (FDP) have said Bonn had set itself a trap with its &quot;criteria fetishism&quot; over the euro.</p>
<p>&quot;We must not make the decision about the euro dependent on whether a zero or a two comes after the decimal point,&quot; Heiner Geissler, deputy CDU parliamentary leader, told Cologne's Express in a release ahead of publication on Sunday.</p>
<p>Waigel, who set a record as Bonn's longest-serving finance minister last week after eight years, has long demanded that all EMU members meet the deficit target precisely.</p>
<p>&quot;We won't talk about decimal points. There is only one figure in the Maastricht Treaty. That is the (number) three,&quot; he told journalists on Saturday.</p>
<p>But a shortfall of at least 19 billion marks ($11 billion) in his 1997 budget, caused mainly by high unemployment and falling tax revenues, has meant Waigel has had to grasp for new funds with what critics say is the same kind of &quot;creative accounting&quot; he and the Bundesbank have long condemmed.</p>
<p>Waigel was humiliated this week when the Bundesbank forced him to back down from a hostile plan to force the central bank to revalue its gold stocks and help his deficit woes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
