<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645306" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: PRESS DIGEST - Turkey - June 7.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Turkey - June 7.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-06-06</dateline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Turkish press on Saturday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>SABAH</p>
<p>- Turkey says the PKK (Kurdistan Workers Party) hit two of its helicopters.</p>
<p>- Turkey's industrial output rose 7.6 percent in April despite political uncertainities.</p>
<p>MILLIYET</p>
<p>- Islamist business group MUSIAD says any embargo on their products will fuel polarisation in the country.</p>
<p>HURRIYET</p>
<p>- The True Path Party (DYP) accepted a draft to rescue the Welfare Party. The government will change the political parties law on June 18-19.</p>
<p>- Turkbank general manger Erol Okuyan resigns. Garanti Investment Bank head Mustafa Gurtin will be appointed as the new Turkbank general manager.</p>
<p>YENI YUZYIL</p>
<p>- The PKK bought missiles from Armenia. The missiles which hit two Turkish helicopters were brought to northern Iraq via Iran.</p>
<p>- The government did not give money to the army for the operation (in northern Iraq against the PKK guerrillas). Erol Ozkasnak, secretary general of the general staff, said their demands were refused by the government.</p>
<p>RADIKAL</p>
<p>- Army says Syria, Armenia, Iran, Greece, Serbia and Cyprus have been providing the PKK with missiles. It accuses the foreign ministry of doing nothing to prevent them.</p>
<p>- The regime wins in Algeria.</p>
<p>DUNYA</p>
<p>- Unregistered systems threaten textiles exports.</p>
<p>- An 18.75 percent Vestel share was sold to foreigners.</p>
<p>ZAMAN</p>
<p>- Turkey is not a part of the European Union support plans.</p>
<p>CUMHURIYET:</p>
<p>- Turkey suspends helicopter flights temporarily after the PKK shoot down two army helicopters. Defence systems of helicopters will be modified by considering all possible cruised missiles the PKK may have.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-06"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
