<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645355" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ex-banker takes Sinn Fein into Irish parliament.</title>
<headline>Ex-banker takes Sinn Fein into Irish parliament.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Marshall</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A dapper former banker made history on Saturday when he won a seat in Ireland's election to become the first member of Sinn Fein, political wing of the outlawed IRA, to enter Ireland's parliament.</p>
<p>The victory by Caoimhghin O Caolain will reverberate beyond his border constituency of Cavan Monaghan and strengthen Sinn Fein's hand in Washington, Dublin and London in its battle to join Belfast talks on the future of Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>All three governments sent Sinn Fein into the wilderness in 1996 after its Irish Republican Army guerrilla allies ended a 17-month ceasefire and bombed London in a renewed war to end British rule of Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>Unlike previous successful Sinn Fein candidates, who refused to take up their seats, O Caolain plans to take part in parliamentary busines.</p>
<p>With exit polls and initial counts predicting a hung parliament, support of smaller parties like Sinn Fein could be crucial for whatever government emerges in Dublin.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein shares the IRA's goals of merging Northern Ireland with the Irish Republic, but it remains barred from multi-party talks on the province's future because the IRA has not restored its ceasefire.</p>
<p>It says it is determined to end the 28-year conflict, which has claimed 3,200 lives, and says O Caolain was involved in the drive for peace. One of his main roles was lobbying U.S. opinion to win support for Sinn Fein's cause.</p>
<p>&quot;Centrally involved in the development of Sinn Fein's peace strategy, Councillor O Caolain is a key figure in the party's efforts to inform and involve both U.S. public opinion and the Washington administration in the search for a solution to the conflict in Ireland,&quot; Sinn Fein said in a statement.</p>
<p>O Caolain said his victory demonstrated a &quot;clear acceptance and understanding of the central role Sinn Fein has played in an earnest endeavour to ensure that we have an inclusive peace process in place.&quot;</p>
<p>But in the deprived estates of Monaghan which provided the core of his support, O Caolain was elected as much for his promises to fight unemployment, win investment for the region and solve the day-to-day problems of local people as for his republican ideals.</p>
<p>&quot;The issue of Northern Ireland hardly arises at all,&quot; wrote an Irish Times reporter who accompanied him on the campaign trail. &quot;In some doorways, women dressed in the council house uniform of baggy teeshirts and leggings bring up problems with rent allowances or defective windows.&quot;</p>
<p>O Caolain campaigned on three platforms -- the struggle for peace in Northern Ireland, job creation and the fight against drugs and crime.</p>
<p>&quot;Sinn Fein is a very vibrant and very important political force on the ground here in Cavan Monaghan,&quot; he said. &quot;We are very much at the coal face of local politics in this border constituency.&quot;</p>
<p>Married with four children, O Caolain left banking in the 1980s to become a county councillor and community activist.</p>
<p>His fondness for sharp suits has become his trademark. &quot;O Caolain still looks the part of the senior bank official he used to be,&quot; the Irish Times said.</p>
<p>For decades, Sinn Fein refused to recognise Ireland's parliament, saying a legitimate Irish assembly should rule the entire island of Ireland. But the party decided in 1986 to take up any seats they won, paving the way for O Caolain's entry into parliament.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein also contests elections in Northern Ireland and won two seats in Britain's May 1 poll. But party leader Gerry Adams and senior strategist Martin McGuinness will not take their seats in Britain's House of Commons as this would involve swearing an oath of allegiance to the Queen.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
