<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645334" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Chirac sees active role in spite of power-sharing.</title>
<headline>Chirac sees active role in spite of power-sharing.</headline>
<dateline>LILLE, France 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Marie-Benedicte Allaire</p>
<p>Gaullist President Jacques Chirac vowed on Saturday to stay active in governing France despite power-sharing with a leftist government as new Socialist Prime Minister Lionel Jospin began work on some urgent issues.</p>
<p>The conservative head of state, addressing a health cooperative conference in the northern city of Lille, ticked off a series of areas in which he intended to watch over things, ranging from holding France to its European commitments to expanding foreign trade and adopting new technology.</p>
<p>But Jospin dismissed the president's remarks as simply a reflection of the text of the French Constitution.</p>
<p>&quot;The president described things as he sees them, and it is not surprising that he would define his role according to the Constitution. I also will act within the framework of the Constitution,&quot; he told the weekly Le Journal du Dimanche.</p>
<p>Chirac, in his first outing since his centre-right allies were swept from power in last Sunday's parliamentary election. said he had experience in power-sharing -- known in France as &quot;cohabitation&quot; -- and so was able &quot;to appreciate the fundamental role of the president as guardian of our institutions.&quot;</p>
<p>Chirac served as prime minister in 1986-88 under late Socialist president Francois Mitterrand, who was widely credited with outmanoeuvring Chirac in a series of confrontations.</p>
<p>Chirac had spent the past week closeted in his presidential palace, publicly sighted just once, when television cameras captured a grim-looking president presiding over the first meeting of France's new leftist cabinet.</p>
<p>Jospin, meanwhile, got to work on several pressing problems.</p>
<p>He sent out word that he was still eyeing changes in a stability pact governing fiscal policy in the era of European monetary union and would soon disclose his stance on a controversial plan by carmaker Renault to close an assembly plant in Vilvoorde, Belgium.</p>
<p>A spokesman said the new prime minister would assemble his cabinet for a special meeting on Thursday, in preparation for his general statement of policy to parliament, which the Journal du Dimanche said would be on June 19.</p>
<p>The policy statement is intended as an outline of the new cabinet's ambitions and generally is followed by a parliamentary vote on a motion of confidence in the new government.</p>
<p>New Socialist Foreign Minister Hubert Vedrine conferred by telephone with his German and Polish counterparts on forthcoming diplomatic events, the Foreign Ministry announced.</p>
<p>German Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel and Polish Foreign Minister Dariusz Rosati telephoned from Warsaw, where Kinkel was visiting, to congratule him on his new portfolio and discuss a range of diplomatic topics, a ministry spokesman said.</p>
<p>He declined to give details but said Kinkel and Vedrine discussed a European Union summit in Amsterdam on June 16-17 and a Franco-German summit set for next Friday in Poitiers, France.</p>
<p>Jospin and Chirac will both attend the Poitiers summit, their first official joint outing.</p>
<p>The Franco-German meeting will take place among growing uncertainty over the conditions and timetable for a single European currency, in which Paris and Bonn are the key players.</p>
<p>During the election campaign, Jospin said he would impose conditions on Paris joining European monetary union, including a ban on new austerity measures for France to qualify for the euro and a requirement that Italy and Spain join from the outset.</p>
<p>The Amsterdam EU summit is expected to reach agreement on a new pact on EU institutional reforms, intended to update the Maastricht treaty, and French officials said in Brussels on Friday that they did not intend to delay the pact.</p>
<p>The meeting will also focus on the stability pact intended to assure fiscal discipline on the part of states participating in European monetary union, due to be launched in 1999.</p>
<p>During his election campaign, Jospin said he did not feel bound by the pact's terms and wanted to renegotiate it with more focus on employment.</p>
<p>There has been growing speculation in financial markets that the new government could cause tension with other EU states, especially Germany, and possibly delay the launch of the euro.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LILLE, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
