<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645404" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - June 7.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Indian newspapers - June 7.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Indian business and political stories in leading newspapers prepared for REUTERS by Business News and Information Services Pvt Ltd, New Delhi Tel:3324842, 3351006, 3761233 Fax:+91-11-3351006 Internet: biznis@giasbm01.vsnl.net.in</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>		   -------oo0oo-------</p>
<p>			  TOP STORIES</p>
<p>The Hindustan Times</p>
<p>LALOO YADAV SACKS FOUR REBEL MINISTERS</p>
<p>Bihar chief minister and Janata Dal president Laloo Prasad Yadav sacked four of his cabinet ministers who were campaigning against him and canvassing for his rival in the party presidential election. The ministers were fired on a day when at least 42 Janata Dal legislators, six of them ministers, revolted against Laloo and attended a party workers' meet in honour of his rival, Sharad Yadav. The meeting, attended by a large number of state legislators and MPs, was otherwise poorly attended. The dissidents blamed the district administration for preventing people from entering the state capital.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Economic Times</p>
<p>FLAGSHIPS REGAIN GUARANTEE RIGHTS</p>
<p>The revised Companies Bill 1997 will not have any restrictions on the quantum of guarantees which can be provided by one company to another. Companies under the same management can once again seek succour from the flagship company when it comes to raising loans. By passing a special resolution, the flagship company will be able to stand guarantor. The expert committee set up to review the Companies Act 1956 in their draft report had suggested combining existing provisions relating to intercorporate loans and investments as these have stifled industrial growth and raised the cost of capital.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS TO STOP FUNDING SUGAR UNITS</p>
<p>Financial institutions have declared the sugar industry unviable and decided to stop funding all cooperative and private sector sugar projects. As a result, no new sugar mills are likely to come up in the country in the near future and promoters looking for easy profits will be weeded out. Companies which have already placed orders for new plant equipment and machinery without tying up loans will also be hit. For instance, in Maharashtra state alone, 16 new sugar mills have placed orders for machinery and even paid advances totalling around five million rupees.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>PENSION FUND VENTURES TO HAVE FLEXIBLE INVESTMENT NORMS</p>
<p>The Life Insurance Corporation's (LIC's) proposed joint venture with the private sector for running pension funds will be governed by a different set of norms. These pension funds will have greater flexibility in investing their corpus than the LIC, which has to put 75 percent of its funds in government securities. The fund may also give an assured minimum return to the pensioners which will be comparable to the rate of return in the market. The LIC may initially take a majority stake in these pension fund companies in order to gain the confidence of the investors.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>U.S. PANEL ON BROADCAST BILL OPPOSES STAKE DILUTION</p>
<p>Members of the sectoral panel on broadcasting set up by the American Business Council (ABC) are close to finalising a paper with a focus on major issues that they oppose in the proposed Broadcast Bill. The ABC committee is opposed to divestment of stake, mandatory uplinking, and registration of their services in India. These foreign broadcasters have little confidence in the financial status of Indian entrepreneurs and are therefore against joint ventures. While the focus of their argument is more or less clear, at the time of their presentation to the parliamentary select committee they may tone down their demands.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Financial Express</p>
<p>THREE OIL GIANTS FLOAT NEW PIPELINE COMPANY</p>
<p>India's three largest oil refining companies have reached agreement to form a new five billion rupee pipeline company called Petronet. Indian Oil, Bharat Petroleum and Hindustan Petroleum will hold 50 percent of Petronet's equity between them. Infrastructure Leasing &amp; Financial Services will be offered another 10 percent of the equity. The remaining 40 percent will be placed with other financial institutions. A high-level meeting was held in New Delhi recently to approve the Petronet idea and another is scheduled on June 16. Petronet will kick off with a nominal equity of 20 million rupees. It will be raised to five billion rupees in due course.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>STOCK MARKET TO ENTER A DECISIVE PHASE AFTER OIL PRICE HIKE</p>
<p>The domestic stock market could move up decisively once the petroleum price hike is announced, a report by Morgan Stanley says. The market may move up decisively after the hike in petroleum products prices is announced, especially if the government raises the prices of subsidised petroleum products more than the price for other products. The government looks fairly certain to raise prices of major petroleum products in the next few days.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>STATE TRADING CORP SET TO OPEN SUBSIDIARY IN MOSCOW</p>
<p>The State Trading Corporation (STC) is all set to open a wholly owned subsidiary in Russia. This will be done by converting its representative office in Moscow into a trading entity through local incorporation. The subsidiary will be an independent company with a board of directors, and there will be sufficient representation from STC. A formal approval of the cabinet is awaited. The cabinet has already received a detailed note on the subject.</p>
<p>----  </p>
<p>SERVICE TAX NORMS FOR CUSTOMS AGENTS EFFECTIVE FROM JUNE 15</p>
<p>The government has issued guidelines for levying service tax on custom house agents and steamer agents that will come into effect from June 15. The service tax will be levied at the rate of five percent on the gross service charge. It will be collected and enforced by the commissionerates of central excise within their jurisdiction. It was further specified that the service tax will be collected by the custom house agent or the steamer agent in respect of the services rendered by them. The value of the taxable service in case of custom house agents will be only the service and attendancy charges/fee/commission charged to the customer.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Standard</p>
<p>10-20 PCT CONCESSSION ON IRON, STEEL FREIGHT RATES LIKELY</p>
<p>The railway ministry will announce a new package of concessions on freight rates for iron and steel, railway board chairman M. Ravindra said. The concessional rates are likely to range between 10 and 20 percent. The full package is still on the anvil but some concessions may be announced in the next few days, said Ravindra. The incentive scheme is part of an exercise to boost freight traffic in general, and iron and steel traffic in particular, he added. The railway board chief expressed concern over the static tonnage of iron and steel moved by the railways in the last two years despite the increase in steel production.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>INDIA'S TRADING PARTNERS THREATEN TO MOVE WTO</p>
<p>India's major trading partners have threatened to resort to dispute settlement under the auspices of the World Trade Organisation if New Delhi fails to soften its stand on removing import curbs. A U.S. team, which has arrived in Geneva, will hold bilateral talks with India prior to the final meetings on June 10 and 11. The Indian team is already holding preliminary meetings in Geneva. India has offered to remove all import curbs in three phases. The first phase will end after three years, while the other two phases will end after six and nine years respectively.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>GUJRAL COMMITTED TO OPEN SKIES POLICY</p>
<p>Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral has virtually committed his government to opening up India's civil aviation policy. He publicly asked the civil aviation secretary to note his commitment on the issue at a luncheon meeting in Kathmandu. &quot;I am totally dissatisfied with India's civil aviation policy,&quot; Gujral said and added that one could not think of modernisation or of openness if the country's skies were not open. Gujral's talk of open skies indicates a determination to reverse the restrictive policies of the civil aviation minister.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>BOMBAY SENSITIVE INDEX DROPS BY 37 POINTS</p>
<p>The 30-share Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE) sensitive index dropped 37.41 points as the market witnessed selling by domestic institutions. The index opened at 3,875.13 and touched an intra-day high of 3,878.99 and a low of 3,830.98 before closing at 3,836.44 against the previous close of 3,873.85. The share-trading turnover on the bourse touched 6.06 billion rupees. The National bourse-50 opened at 1,087.50 and touched an intra-day high of 1,091.65 and a low of 1,081.30 before closing at 1,082.75 against the previous close of 1,086.60. Brokers said the fall is an indication of a correction to the rally witnessed earlier during the week.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Line</p>
<p>INDIA WINS LAW SUIT AGAINST BASMATI CLONES</p>
<p>India has won an international law suit against a U.S. commodity trading firm which had filed for registration of trademarks on rice varieties claimed to be analogous to the basmati varieties grown in India. The decision of the statutory Trademark Administrative Committee in Greece comes as a shot in the arm for rice exporters protesting against foreign firms attempting to encroach on the basmati market worldwide through the introduction of basmati analogues or clones. Buoyed by the victory, India plans to file a similar suit against a firm which has applied for registration of the trademark in Thailand.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Observer</p>
<p>IMPORTS DUTY PAYMENTS CAN BE UNDER NEW SCHEME</p>
<p>The government has decided to allow credit under the duty entitlement pass book (DEPB) scheme to be utilised for payment of duty against imports under special import licences (SIL). This will be officially notified soon and will meet the demand of electronic product exporters who want to utilise credit under DEPB for import of electronics items appearing in the SIL list. The scheme entitles the exporter to duty free credit at notified rates to import inputs required for export production. Under the DEPB scheme the ports will be treated as the same place for export and import.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>DHDS PROJECTS FOR NINE REFINERIES</p>
<p>The government has approved diesel hydro de-sulphurisation (DHDS) projects at nine refineries. The total estimated cost of these projects is 55.68 billion rupees including a foreign exchange component of 96.68 billion rupees. The DHDS units and other related facilities will be installed at the Gujrat, Haldia, Mathura and Panipat at refineries of the Indian Oil Corporation, the Bombay and Vishakhapatnam refineries of the Hindustan Petroleum Corporation, the Bombay refinery of the Bharat Petroleum Corporation, the Manali refinery of the Madras Refineries and at Cochin refineries.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
