<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645408" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>AFGHANISTAN: Afghan Shi'ite leader foresees softened Taleban.</title>
<headline>Afghan Shi'ite leader foresees softened Taleban.</headline>
<byline>Tim Johnston</byline>
<dateline>MAZAR-I-SHARIF, Afghanistan 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior Afghan opposition alliance member said on Saturday he believed recent losses of the Taleban militia in the north would make it more flexible in talks on the country's future.</p>
<p>Ustad Mohammad Mohaqiq, northern representative of the mainly Shi'ite Moslem Hezb-i-Wahdat party, was speaking to journalists in the opposition stronghold of Mazar-i-Sharif, from where the Taleban forces were driven out on May 28 with heavy casualties just four days after taking it.</p>
<p>Mohaqiq said the Taleban's rout in the area would provide greater opportunity for talks and understanding.</p>
<p>&quot;Before their defeat, the Taleban had never expressed a readiness for accommodation with the other side,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Taleban, which controls more than two-thirds of Afghanistan, took Mazar-i-Sharif when General Abdul Malik, a powerful opposition commander, apparently revolted against opposition leader General Abdul Rashid Dostum and defected to the Taleban.</p>
<p>Dostum was forced to leave Afghanistan when the combined forces of Malik and the Taleban took Mazar-i-Sharif after a rapid advance in the west.</p>
<p>However, Mohaqiq said that, after arriving in Mazar-i-Sharif, the Taleban reneged on the deal Malik had worked with them.</p>
<p>&quot;An understanding was reached between Malik and the Taleban that Malik would enforce Islamic law in the north, the Taleban would not disarm the groups here and would leave the military and political authority in the north with these groups. But when they (Taleban) arrived in Mazar-i-Sharif, they breached all those promises.&quot;</p>
<p>The Taleban accuse Malik of the breaking the agreement.</p>
<p>Forces commanded by Malik and Wahdat attacked the Taleban forces in Mazar-i-Sharif, killing as many as 300 of them, according to some estimates, and took hundreds of prisoners, including the Taleban foreign minister and head of the central bank who were there at the time.</p>
<p>Hezb-i-Wahdat officials said many of the prisoners were Pakistani citizens. They showed journalists videotapes of prisoners sitting in a compound and documents including Pakistani high school diplomas and notepaper of the hardline Pakistani religious group Sipah-i-Sahaba.</p>
<p>Taleban forces in northern Afghanistan are now confined to a small pocket of territory around the town of Pul-i-Khumri, 177 km (110 miles) south of Mazar-i-Sharif, where they are surrounded by opposition forces.</p>
<p>Mohaqiq said Hezb-i-Wahdat wanted the same degree of autonomy for the Shi'ite heartland in central Afghanistan as Malik had apparently negotiated for the northern provinces.</p>
<p>&quot;We want for the central parts of Afghanistan the same thing as General Malik wants for the north,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said his party wanted a federated Afghanistan split into four provinces and a federal capital territory.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like autonomous provinces which recognise, and are recognised by, a central government. These will be four provinces -- northwest and northeast, south and centre, with a central government area,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>At present Afghanistan has 32 small provinces.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MAZAR-I-SHARIF, Afghanistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AFGHANISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
