<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645420" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEPAL: Gujral urges Nepal to seize India trade options.</title>
<headline>Gujral urges Nepal to seize India trade options.</headline>
<byline>Gopal Sharma</byline>
<dateline>KATHMANDU 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral on Saturday urged Nepal to seize the opportunities created by India's economic reforms to bridge the Himalayan kingdom's yawning trade deficit with New Delhi.</p>
<p>He said India's liberalisation process, initiated in 1991, offered an array of opportunities to the business communities of both countries. India gives almost all Nepali products duty-free entry into its market.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a challenge and opportunity for business sectors to utilise,&quot; Gujral told a news conference in the Nepali capital at the end of a three-day official visit to the kingdom. He was scheduled to return to India late on Saturday.</p>
<p>Gujral, the first foreign leader to visit Nepal since Prime Minister Lokendra Bahadur Chand took power in March, has met King Birendra, Chand and other leaders during his visit.</p>
<p>Nepal and India on Thursday signed a pathbreaking agreement allowing private firms of both nations to produce and trade electric power, and formalised a water sharing treaty.</p>
<p>India also agreed to allow traders from landlocked Nepal to cross its territory to reach ports in Bangladesh through a new transit route -- a longstanding Nepali demand.</p>
<p>The water-sharing treaty defines terms for the construction in west Nepal of a multi-billion dollar dam that can produce 6,000 megawatts of hydroelectric power, which the neighbours will share equally.</p>
<p>Nepali officials said hydroelectric power exports could help the kingdom trim its $380.7 million trade gap with New Delhi.</p>
<p>Gujral said the treaty would &quot;turn out to be an epoch-making blueprint&quot; for Nepal's overall economic development.</p>
<p>The Indian leader, who has been credited with improving India's relations with its smaller neighbours, said he hoped the &quot;new South Asian spirit&quot; would also prevail in his country's ties with archrival Pakistan.</p>
<p>&quot;If that happens....South Asia will no longer be perceived by the outside world as a conflict-prone region,&quot; Gujral said.</p>
<p>India and Pakistan have fought three wars since 1947. Their prime ministers met for the first time in four years in May, and senior foreign ministry officials are due to hold talks later in June.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NEPAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KATHMANDU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEPAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
