<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645432" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SRI LANKA: Sri Lankan forces recover Tamil rebel bodies.</title>
<headline>Sri Lankan forces recover Tamil rebel bodies.</headline>
<dateline>COLOMBO 1997-06-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sri Lankan troops have recovered the bodies of more than 15 Tamil Tiger guerrillas after overcoming heavy rebel resistance during a drive into their northern stronghold, military officials said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Several guerrillas were missing after Friday's action in which the army captured Periyamadu, an area near the fortified rebel-held junction town of Puliyankulam, about 245 km (150 miles) north of the capital Colombo, they said. Ground troops estimated at least 25 Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) guerrillas were killed and more than 50 wounded mostly in air and artillery attacks, the Defence Ministry said.</p>
<p>The army lost one officer and eight soldiers in the battle while another officer and 11 soldiers were wounded, it said.</p>
<p>Military officials said the rebels' failure to recover their own dead indicated they had been forced to fall back in disarray in the face of the advance by government troops backed by tanks, artillery and air support.</p>
<p>Some 20,000 troops are advancing on two flanks into the mostly jungle-covered Wanni region. Residents in Vavuniya, the gateway to the Wanni some 25 km (16 miles) to the south of Puliyankulam, reported a lull in aircraft movements on Saturday. The army had earlier captured the towns of Omanthai, 14 km (nine miles) north of Vavuniya, and Nedunkeni, 40 km (25 miles) northeast of Vavuniya, in an offensive codenamed Operation Jaya Sikuru, or Sure of Victory, that was launched from Vavuniya on May 13.</p>
<p>Deputy Defence Minister Anuruddha Ratwatte told a news conference on Friday the aim of the offensive was to open a land supply route to Jaffna, 100 km (60 miles) further north, that would help rehabilitation work there.</p>
<p>The north-south highway has been closed for more than 10 years due to battles between the rebels and government forces.</p>
<p>The LTTE, fighting a separate homeland for minority Tamils in mainly Sinhalese Sri Lanka's north and east, has accused the military of systematically demolishing Tamil towns through artillery attacks, forcing civilians to seek refuge in the jungle.</p>
<p>The military has denied their shells were aimed at civilians, saying they fired only at identified rebel targets.</p>
<p>The rebels also said Tamil property and food were looted by the armed forces at Nedunkeni. The Defence Ministry spokesman denied the charge.</p>
<p>Independent confirmation of the events was not possible as international media have not been allowed in the war zone.</p>
<p>The government says more than 50,000 people have been killed since the war began in 1983. The rebels say the toll is higher.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SRILAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOMBO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SRI LANKA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
