<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="645402" id="root" date="1997-06-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: PRESS DIGEST - Pakistan - June 7.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - Pakistan - June 7.</headline>
<text>
<p>These are the leading stories in the Pakistani newspapers on Tuesday. Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their accuracy.</p>
<p>DAWN</p>
<p>- The government has imposed a five percent regulatory duty on sugar imports with immediate effect, in addition to a 10 percent ad-volrem duty and a five percent witholding tax already being charged on sugar imports.</p>
<p>- The United States has again urged the Pakistani government to release Ayaz Baloch, a Pakistani employee of the U.S. Drug Enforcement Agency, who was arrested in Islamabad by Pakistani authorities on April 28.</p>
<p>- A senior Supreme Court lawyer and leader of a Shi'ite Moslem faction was shot dead by two unidentified gunmen in Lahore.</p>
<p>- A flight lieutentant of the Pakistan Air Force charged of abetting smuggling of electronic items has been sentenced to 10 years imprisonment by a military court.</p>
<p>- The United States Information Service said the State Department has no evidence of a heroin smuggling ring in Pakistan's Inter-Services Intelligence Directorate.</p>
<p>- Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif will pay a two-day visit to Tehran from June 16 on his way back from Istanbul, for where he is leaving on June 14 to attend a summit conference of Developing-Eight (D-8) economic cooperation group of Islamic countries.</p>
<p>- The state Board of Investment has expressed disagreement with the Water and Power Ministry over the question of cancellation of a letter of support issued to Consolidated Electric Power Asia to build a coal-fired power station at Keti Bunder.</p>
<p>- The third executive committee and general assembly meeting of the Federation of Euro-Asian Stock Exchanges will be held in Pakistan in October this year.</p>
<p>- The International Telecommunication Union has indicated that it will raise its investment level in Pakistan under a phased programme to $1 billion to provide a larger network of telephones both in urban and rural areas.</p>
<p>- The Punjab Agriculture Department has expressed fears of a severe potato shortage in the coming months amid a sharp fall in domestic production.</p>
<p>BUSINESS RECODER</p>
<p>- The Pakistani government is in a fix over the award of a 5.5 billion rupees contract of the Chashma Right Bank Irrigation Project after the Asian Development Bank opposed giving the contract to a Chinese firm that offered the lowest bid, saying the company was not capable of handling such a huge project.</p>
<p>- The U.S.-based Citibank has been appointed as the financial adviser for the privatisation of state-run Habib Bank Ltd at a fee of $1 million plus expenses capped at $385,000, sources said.</p>
<p>- The World Bank has asked the government to develop a new blueprint for an appropriate agriculture income tax along with an implementation plan to raise substantial revenues over the medium term.</p>
<p>- Cooking oil manufacturers have reduced the lifting of palm oil by almost 50 percent amid reports that the government plans to cut import duty on palm oil imports by 1,000 rupees a tonne in the forthcoming budget for 1997/98 (July-June).</p>
<p>- The World Bank has asked the Pakistani government to allow the setting up of more independent power plants to get an additional 1,600 megawatts of electricity capacity by the year 2000.</p>
<p>- The state-run Karachi Atomic Nuclear Power Plant has resumed 60-megawatt of power supply to the state-run Karachi Electric Supply Corp distribution network.</p>
<p>- The state-run Trading Corporation of Pakistan has cancelled its June 7 tender for for 25,000 tonnes of white refined crystal sugar for delivery at Karachi Port or the nearby Port Qasim by July 31.</p>
<p>FINANCIAL POST</p>
<p>- The state Board of Investment said on Friday that foreign direct investment in the first nine months of fiscal 1996/97 (July-June) had totalled $448.4 million.</p>
<p>- Officials at the Pakistani government's Central Board of Revenue say the revised revenue collection target of 283 billion rupees set for fiscal 1996/97 is unlikely to be met as the shortfall has reached 70 billion rupees by May 31.</p>
<p>THE NEWS</p>
<p>- Pakistan's top nuclear scientist, Dr. Abdul Qadeer Khan, has said in an interview that Pakisan has adequate defence system to thwart any aggression.</p>
<p>THE MUSLIM</p>
<p>- Russian deputy foreign minister Viktor Pasouvaluk arrived in Islamabad on Friday night on for talks with Pakistani officials due to be held on Saturday.</p>
<p>THE NATION</p>
<p>- Sadruddin Hashwani, chairman of Hashoo group of companies, has agreed to deposit 1,110 million rupees in government coffers to get his name deleted from the exit control list.</p>
<p>-- Islamabad newsroom 274757</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
