<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="655753" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK has no idea when EU might lift ban on its beef.</title>
<headline>UK has no idea when EU might lift ban on its beef.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fifteen months after the European Union slapped a worldwide ban on British beef exports because of fears of mad cow disease, the new Labour government said on Thursday it had no idea how long it would take to lift the ban.</p>
<p>Agriculture Minister Jack Cunningham told parliament it would be foolish to name a date, especially after EU veterinary scientists on Wednesday rejected a British bid to ease the ban by exempting herds certified free of the killer disease.</p>
<p>Cunningham said the stance taken by the vets was disappointing but not surprising and he promised a swift detailed response to the technical points they had raised.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be foolish in the extreme for me to start speculating about dates, and I'm certainly not going to raise false hopes.</p>
<p>&quot;I shall work as effectively and as quickly as I can to resolve these problems, but I'm not going to speculate on how long that will take,&quot; Cunningham said.</p>
<p>The EU banned exports of British beef in March 1996 after Britain said it was possible that mad cow disease, or bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE), could be transmitted to humans in the form of brain-eating Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease (CJD).</p>
<p>Cunningham said it would be especially unrealistic and misleading to say when exports might resume given the record of the previous Conservative administration.</p>
<p>&quot;After all, the previous prime minister promised the nation that the whole of the ban would be lifted by November 1996. Here we are in June 1997 and none of the ban has been lifted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Cunningham disclosed that he had approached the big beefburger chains to try to get them to resume purchases of British beef, which they halted when the crisis broke.</p>
<p>Cunningham said that because of doubts about the quality of home-reared meat, Britain was likely to import 160,000 tonnes of beef this year -- 20-25 percent of its total consumption.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41220">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
