<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="655894" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: Zimbabwe media fear aid sanctions over ivory trade.</title>
<headline>Zimbabwe media fear aid sanctions over ivory trade.</headline>
<byline>Cris Chinaka</byline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zimbabwe state media accused some Western environmental pressure groups on Thursday of threatening to block crucial development aid to African states supporting the country's controversial proposal to resume trade in ivory.</p>
<p>The accused flatly denied the charge, saying Zimbabwe was &quot;making it all up&quot; after encountering strong opposition to its ivory proposal at a 10-day Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) that opened in Harare on Monday.</p>
<p>The official Herald newspaper said &quot;the dollar power&quot; was winning the battle over ivory.</p>
<p>&quot;Animal protectionists from the north continue to intimidate and divide African states threatening to withdraw development aid from those who support Zimbabwe, Namibia and Botswana's proposal to lift the ban on trade in ivory and other elephant products,&quot; it said in a story entitled &quot;African States Divided Over Ivory Issue&quot;.</p>
<p>State radio also quoted a wildlife official as saying that many green movements at the Harare meeting were threatening to block Western aid to some unnamed Third World states in the 138-member CITES who supported unbanning ivory sales.</p>
<p>A senior Zimbabwean government official, who declined to be named, repeated the same charges to Reuters, accusing by name the London-based Enviromental Investigation Agency (EIA) and the Humane Society of the United States.</p>
<p>EIA chairman Allan Thornton dismissed the allegations as fantasy. &quot;That is ridiculous. We have made no such threats because it is not in our nature or within our power.</p>
<p>&quot;I can understand the frustration...but we must all strive to debate on these issues at a solid level, separating facts from fantasy,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Wayne Pacelle, a spokesman for Humane Society, also said there were no such threats, emphasising that his organisation was only involved in decent opposition to ivory trade on grounds that it would endanger all African elephants.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, Tichaona Jokonya, the Zimbabwe chairman of the Harare CITES conference, called on CITES to curtail the activities of non-governmental organisations (NGOs), accusing some of them of promoting extreme policies on wildlife.</p>
<p>Zimbabwe has come under assault from dozens of Western-based green movements opposed to its Japanese-backed proposal for a partial lifting of a 1989 ban on ivory sales.</p>
<p>Its opponents on the issue say although Zimbabwe, Namibia and Botswana are rich in elephants, any resumption in ivory trade would endanger elephants, not just in southern Africa but around the globe.</p>
<p>The ivory debate is the most heated at the Zimbabwe CITES meeting where about 80 other proposals on endangered species are being discussed by more than 2,000 delegates and observers.</p>
<p>They will vote on the issues towards the end of the conference next week.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BOTS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NAMIB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
