<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656050" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Two men face hard fight against Croatia's Tudjman.</title>
<headline>Two men face hard fight against Croatia's Tudjman.</headline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are portraits of the two men running against Croatian President Franjo Tudjman in Sunday's presidential election.</p>
<p>Both say they would change Croatia's governmental system if elected to hand more power to parliament and reduce that of the president. Tudjman is expected to win the election.</p>
<p>VLADO GOTOVAC, leader of the Social Liberal Party (HSLS), is a rare poet among politicians and will challenge the ailing but largely popular President Franjo Tudjman at a time when his rating in his own Social Liberal party is rapidly sinking.</p>
<p>A philospher by education, Gotovac emerged in politics in 1990 to become co-founder of the HSLS, but has rarely managed to translate his personal charisma into political points.</p>
<p>In 1972 he was sentenced to four years in prison by the communist Yugoslav authorities for taking part in the Croatian nationalist movement the year before and was banned from public work until 1990, when federal Yugoslavia began disintegrating.</p>
<p>By delivering fiery speeches to enthusiastic crowds of Croats enjoying re-awakened national sentiments, Gotovac had the stature of an inspired orator rather than that of a serious and practical politician.</p>
<p>The 66-year old writer and poet was elected president of the HSLS in February 1996 while it was being torn apart by internal power struggles and its leading role among the opposition parties started to wane.</p>
<p>Gotovac has failed to rein in the more nationalist and conservative HSLS members and establish himself as undisputed leader.</p>
<p>His growing disagreement with the party's second-in-charge and more nationalist Drazen Budisa has undermined his own authority within the party and diminished its popular appeal.</p>
<p>Married to his second wife Simona -- a former nun and now a cardiologist in Rome -- Gotovac has one daughter and two grandchildren.</p>
<p>ZDRAVKO TOMAC, the youngest of the three presidential candidates and the only career politician in Sunday's poll, is handicapped by his communist past in a country desperate to shake off 50 years of ties to the Yugoslav federation.</p>
<p>He is also hampered by the fact that he alone among the three does not have a dissident past -- both Tudjman and Gotovac were prosecuted and briefly jailed as Croatian nationalists in the 1970s and 80s while Tomac was a professor at Zagreb's faculty of politics.</p>
<p>In his speeches he often cites France and Britain, where conservatives recently lost elections to labour and leftist parties, and calls on voters to follow their example.</p>
<p>Overweight and with heavy lidded eyes, 60-year-old Tomac says he would publicise results of a health examination if elected -- a veiled criticism of Tudjman who tried to conceal from the public that he was suffering from cancer.</p>
<p>He has also pledged to cut lavish presidential spending, to sell the presidential airplane and open the famous Brijuni national park, once the summer residence of late communist ruler Josip Broz Tito and now a private holiday resort for Tudjman's family.</p>
<p>He is tipped to get more votes than the Social Liberal candidate Vlado Gotovac, thought to be too intellectual for the majority of voters. But he has said he would suppport Gotovac if between them they manage to force Tudjman, often referred to as the 'father of the nation', into a second round.</p>
<p>His challenge is to overcome public distrust of the communists who ruled Croatia while it was part of federal, Serb-dominated Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>Though Tomac steered clear of executive positions in the communist government, he kept close ties to the authorities, working as adviser to the republic's parliament from 1972-74. With the start of a multi-party system in Croatia he became a co-leader of the Social Democrats -- the reformed communists.</p>
<p>He has since managed to build an image of a patriot and a responsible politician while serving as deputy prime minister in an all-party &quot;Government of National Unity&quot;, which steered Croatia during the 1991 war with minority Serbs.</p>
<p>His popularity suffered a blow from his poor handling of a crisis in Zagreb in 1995, when he, then speaker of the opposition-dominated city council, failed to prevent Tudjman from ignoring election results and naming his own mayor.</p>
<p>He is married with one son who is a student.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
