<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656083" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: FEATURE - Spectre of early death haunts Russian men.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Spectre of early death haunts Russian men.</headline>
<byline>Adam Tanner</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Andrei, a 34-year-old factory worker, ignored his high-blood pressure until it was too late. He suffered a brain haemorrhage and fell into a coma.</p>
<p>&quot;This would never have happened and he would have lived a much longer life if only he had taken care of the problem and taken medicine,&quot; said Nikolai Zubanov, head of the intensive care ward at Moscow's Hospital 13.</p>
<p>&quot;Now he'll die in the next few days.&quot;</p>
<p>Successful businessman Sergei, 47, also ignored his health, did little exercise and engaged in a number of bad habits, doctors said. When he suffered a heart attack recently, Hospital 13 could do nothing to save him.</p>
<p>Men of working age like Andrei and Sergei are dying in ever greater numbers in today's Russia.</p>
<p>With a host of bad health habits and surrounded by threats from the environment and society, Russian men are dying at a far younger age -- 58 on average in 1996 -- and contributing to a sharp fall in the population, health experts say.</p>
<p>In May a report from a presidential commission on demographics said male life expectancy had fallen by seven years in less than a decade. A Russian man was more likely to reach the age of 60 a century ago than today, the report said.</p>
<p>Post-communist life has taken a staggering toll on all Russians but on its men in particular, who live 15 to 17 years less on average than Western European men, according to official government statistics.</p>
<p>Russia women, by contrast, live far longer, an average of 71 years in 1996, down from 75 in the mid 1980s but still not far short of their Western counterparts.</p>
<p>&quot;Men have an especially unsatisfactory lifestyle,&quot; said Nikolai Gerasimenko, head of the lower house of parliament's health committee. &quot;Most of the population understands freedom as the possibility to do anything.&quot;</p>
<p>ORGY OF BAD HABITS</p>
<p>To a large extent Russian men doom themselves by living unhealthily.</p>
<p>&quot;Every man has his own vice,&quot; said 47-year-old Dr Viktor Kochenov, a smoker and head of one of Moscow's children's hospitals. &quot;The job of doctor is one of great stress and pressure, so I maintain the bad habit of smoking.&quot;</p>
<p>About two thirds of all Russian men smoke, accounting for nearly a third of all male deaths, according to the World Health Organisation. They estimate that tobacco causes about 280,000 Russian deaths a year.</p>
<p>Car drivers, most of whom are men, rarely use seatbelts, and drive unsafe cars on poorly maintained roads. The result: accidents are fatal 10 times more often than in Europe on average, according to Interior Ministry data.</p>
<p>By 1996 Russian men drank themselves to death and committed suicide twice as often as in 1990. Russian men were 20 times more likely to be murdered than their fellows in Western Europe.</p>
<p>Many eat a diet high in fat and fail to exercise regularly, shortcomings which increase the likelihood of heart disease, the country's leading cause of death. Tight budgets also make it hard for many families to eat well, experts say.</p>
<p>&quot;Today, living healthily is just not in style. People put too low a value on their lives,&quot; said Yekaterina Lakhova, head of the demographics commission.</p>
<p>A SOCIETY OF RISKS</p>
<p>At the same time, Russia surrounds even a health-minded individual with a range of dangers.</p>
<p>Environmental officials say about half the country's drinking water falls short of sanitary norms, and a wide variety of other environmental hazards -- such as toxins in the soil and smog in the air -- threaten citizens every day.</p>
<p>The stress of adjusting to new conditions after generations under communism also hits Russia's men especially hard.</p>
<p>&quot;Men suffer in the current economic situation even worse than women because their role as the chief breadwinner has not changed,&quot; said sociologist Marina Malysheva. &quot;They feel the stress and anxiety.&quot;</p>
<p>Hospitals are badly underfunded and even Moscow facilities -- the country's best such as Hospital 13 -- often have darkened hallways, cracked tiles and an overall gloomy feel.</p>
<p>Regional facilities on the other hand lag behind in their ability to administer the latest medical treatments, and ambulances everywhere are slow in reaching victims.</p>
<p>&quot;We have many cases today where people die for such simple reasons as a lack of medicine like insulin,&quot; Gerasimenko said.</p>
<p>Deputy health minister Alexander Tsaregorodtsev responded that speeding up ambulance services and emergency health care is far more pressing than medicine supplies.</p>
<p>He also advocates freeing hospital beds by treating less urgent cases in out-patient departments.</p>
<p>PREVENTION THE BEST MEDICINE</p>
<p>Health experts say the government must take a leading role in fostering more public health consciousness, teaching children in school and adults via television.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to beat it into the people to live more healthily and with more care,&quot; said Zubanov of Hospital 13. &quot;But we are not rational people compared to the West; we are barbarians when it comes to health.&quot;</p>
<p>So far the government has devoted little attention to the problem, and even President Boris Yeltsin has had quintuple heart bypass surgery and pneumonia over the past seven months.</p>
<p>Tsaregorodtsev said Yeltsin could lead the way in educating the public by using his medical history to inspire better living.</p>
<p>&quot;There are very many cases where people seek help only when it's too late and there's nothing doctors can do,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Without government-led health efforts, experts fear the number of Russians will continue to dwindle for years to come.</p>
<p>&quot;There are about one million more deaths than births every year,&quot; Gerasimenko said. &quot;If the population falls by a million a year, in 40 to 50 years the population could fall to 100 million. It would be a catastrophe for Russia.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
