<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656114" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Fidel Castro a bad father and leader - daughter.</title>
<headline>Fidel Castro a bad father and leader - daughter.</headline>
<byline>Martin Roberts</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Alina Fernandez Revuelta accused Cuban President Fidel Castro on Thursday of failing her personally as a father and the Cuban people in general as a leader.</p>
<p>Fernandez Revuelta told Reuters in an interview that Castro certainly had his reasons as &quot;the busiest father in Cuba,&quot; but that he was nonetheless an &quot;unconcerned father.&quot;</p>
<p>Fernandez, who escaped from Cuba disguised as a Spanish tourist in 1993 and now lives in the United States, was in Mexico to promote her autobiography, &quot;Alina: Las memorias de la hija rebelde de Fidel Castro,&quot; (&quot;Alina: Memoirs of Fidel Castro's rebel daughter&quot;).</p>
<p>The book is mainly a personal account, but contains a heavy dose of often critical observations on how Cuban society has fared since the revolution led by Castro in 1959.</p>
<p>&quot;I go along with the revolution, through the eyes of the girl that saw it take power through to the woman who had to leave,&quot; Fernandez said.</p>
<p>Alina Fernandez was born in Havana in 1956. Her mother, Nati Revuelta, met Fidel Castro in the early 1950s and worked clandestinely with other rebels who plotted to overthrow the dictatorship of Fulgencio Batista.</p>
<p>Alina was registered under her mother's husband's surname, Fernandez. Nonetheless, her mother confessed when Alina was 10 years old that Fidel Castro, an occasional visitor to the Fernandez household, was her real father.</p>
<p>She said her book does not attempt to pass judgment, but admits she does not have a high opinion of Cuba's revolution.</p>
<p>&quot;The only merit I do concede is in that first stage at the beginning of the revolution, which was so idealistic, so romantic and so driven to achieve social justice,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Fernandez said the Cuban revolution lost its way and impoverished its people due to the cost of maintaining Cuban troops in Africa and supporting guerrillas in different parts of Latin America.</p>
<p>&quot;What I don't like about this revolution is that it did nothing for Cubans,&quot; she said. &quot;It has done everything for it's public image and the international stage,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>After Fernandez left Cuba in December 1993, it took the Cuban government 10 days to allow her teenaged daughter, Castro's grandchild Alina Maria Salgado, to join her abroad.</p>
<p>Castro, 70, has always kept an extremely tight rein on his private life and almost never mentions even his personal feelings, let alone his family, in public.</p>
<p>The only child whom Castro publicly acknowledges as his is called Fidel, from his marriage to Mirta Diaz-Balart.</p>
<p>Alina's mother, Nati Revuelta, always a supporter of the Cuban revolution, remains in Havana and is occasionally seen in public at diplomatic cocktail parties.</p>
<p>&quot;She's the heroine of the story, in the end,&quot; Fernandez said. &quot;Because she is the only one who sticks to her guns, to her ideals, throughout her life. Fidel has changed his line.&quot;</p>
<p>Fernandez hopes to see her mother soon, but said that would have to happen &quot;outside Cuba, for the time being.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
