<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656125" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>HAITI: Haiti culture minister responds to Fugees flap.</title>
<headline>Haiti culture minister responds to Fugees flap.</headline>
<byline>Anna Wardenburg</byline>
<dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Haiti's culture minister on Thursday dismissed as irresponsible allegations that money from an April benefit concert by the award-winning Haitian-American rap group The Fugees had been stolen.</p>
<p>Minister Raoul Peck deplored the negative images of Haiti created by the controversy and said more than half the concert's expenses had gone to a U.S. sound and light company chosen by The Fugees.</p>
<p>&quot;The Ministry of Culture believes that neither Haiti nor any of the persons linked close or far to the organisation of these concerts deserves such ingratitude,&quot; the minister's statement said.</p>
<p>The April 12 benefit in Port-au-Prince and another concert on April 11 at Haiti's Club Med were intended to help refugees and improve the impoverished country's image abroad.</p>
<p>Instead, Fugees lead singer Wyclef Jean and various refugee groups criticised Peck and the Haitian government when they learned the events had generated no money for refugees, suggesting the proceeds had been stolen.</p>
<p>&quot;The Ministry of Culture regrets that Mr. Wyclef Jean found it necessary to make these irresponsible declarations, particularly since he could have at any given moment asked to verify the accounting,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The Fugees, who soared with their hit album, The Score, performed the benefit concert to raise money for thousands of refugees repatriated from the Dominican Republic to Haiti. The two nations share the Caribbean island of Hispaniola.</p>
<p>Peck's statement said that of $476,327 in concert costs, 50.3 percent went to BML, a New Jersey-based company chosen by The Fugees to stage the concert.</p>
<p>A further 10.3 percent went to transporting equipment from New York to Haiti, and 11.1 percent went to hotel and living expenses for the band and technical team. The statement did not indicate how much money was taken in from the concert.</p>
<p>The rest of the expense money went to meals, construction of stands and bleachers, advertising and public relations, the statement said. The Haitian newspaper Haiti Progres reported that Haitian workers recieved $808 for their participation.</p>
<p>&quot;The Ministry of Culture deplores that an event that should have given another image to Haiti has transformed itself into negative news releases and Internet messages,&quot; the statement said. &quot;It appears that our country, once again, only served as a welcome stage for the next video clip of the group and to give a 'national' tone to their press kit.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HAITI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
