<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656284" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China wheat crop seen a record, imports low.</title>
<headline>China wheat crop seen a record, imports low.</headline>
<byline>Lynne O'Donnell</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>China could be heading for its second successive record wheat crop, and wheat imports for the year could total no more than five million tonnes, traders and analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>China's total wheat harvest this year could range between 100 million tonnes and 116 million tonnes, according to experts polled this week by Reuters.</p>
<p>High carryover stocks from the record 1996 harvest of between about 109 million and 111 million tonnes were dampening demand for imports, they said.</p>
<p>Despite the wide divergence in output expectations, trade, industry and diplomatic sources generally agreed China's wheat imports in the 1996-97 crop year would not exceed five million tonnes.</p>
<p>China's summer harvest of winter wheat will get under way in the two major winter wheat-growing regions on the northern plain around the Yellow river and the southern belt along the Yangtze river in the coming weeks.</p>
<p>Traders and other industry sources who have been touring the wheat belts to check the condition of the crop have said yield potential looks high, with no weather problems to date and little trouble expected before harvest.</p>
<p>Wheat harvested at this time of year accounts for about 90 percent of the annual total. The remaining 10 percent would be planted soon, mostly in the far northern province of Heilongjiang, for harvest in September.</p>
<p>&quot;The (summer) harvest looks good and there is no (import) demand,&quot; said a North American wheat marketing executive.</p>
<p>Most diplomatic and trade sources put the total summer harvest at around 100 million tonnes. Another nine to 10 million tonnes would be expected in the autumn, they said.</p>
<p>But an agriculture consultant in Beijing told Reuters these figures vastly underestimated likely output, which he forecast at 116 million tonnes compared with more than 109 million tonnes traders said was grown in 1996.</p>
<p>X. Lyn Wu, general manager of East-West Consultants Ltd, an affiliate of U.S. crop and weather forecaster Sparks, said China's wheat imports in the year to the end of August 1997 would be 4.8 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Wheat output in calendar 1996 was 111.9 million tonnes, Wu said.</p>
<p>Output in 1995 totalled 102 million tonnes, of which 91.5 million tonnes were harvested in the summer, and 10.5 million in the autumn, China's figures show.</p>
<p>Wu said the Chinese government's policy of encouraging wheat production was one reason behind his high estimate. Another was under-reporting by provincial grain bureaux.</p>
<p>Carryover stocks from previous record years were keeping import demand low, sources across the board said. Imports would be of high quality wheat for blending by flour millers.</p>
<p>China's wheat imports in the August 1994-July 1995 year were five million tonnes, with Canadian wheat accounting for 42 percent of the total, the North American executive said.</p>
<p>Since August 1996, only 1.5 million tonnes of Canadian wheat had arrived in China, none of it in the past couple of months, he said.</p>
<p>China's customs figures show wheat imports of 550,000 tonnes in the first four months, down 72.5 percent compared with the same period in 1996. April imports were 210,000 tonnes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
