<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656365" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: China says U.S.-made supercomputers for research.</title>
<headline>China says U.S.-made supercomputers for research.</headline>
<byline>Benjamin Kang Lim</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>China on Thursday dismissed U.S. charges that it had diverted purchases of U.S.-made supercomputers for military use, saying these were used for scientific research.</p>
<p>&quot;China through normal trade channels bought some supercomputers from the United States and their purpose is for weather forecasting, earthquake prevention and other scientific research,&quot; Foreign Ministry spokesman Cui Tiankai said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a totally normal commercial action,&quot; Cui told a news briefing. &quot;The Chinese side...strictly abided by the terms of the contract.</p>
<p>&quot;This kind of purchase went through a comprehensive examination and approval process,&quot; he said without elaborating.</p>
<p>Washington said on Tuesday it was investigating possible Chinese diversions of U.S.-made supercomputers for military use and was reviewing the affected sales.</p>
<p>The New York Times reported this week that the U.S. Commerce Department was investigating a 1996 sale by Silicon Graphics of a supercomputer that performs almost six billion operations per second -- 10 times the speed of the fastest personal computer -- to a Chinese science academy.</p>
<p>The newspaper quoted the company as saying the buyer was a benign civilian institution but nuclear experts said the academy had other functions, such as helping China to develop long-range missiles.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton deregulated the export of computers in 1995 on the grounds that increasingly powerful supercomputers were becoming more available worldwide with the United States holding a comparative advantage in the technology.</p>
<p>The administration made special provision for licensing supercomputers to China to ensure against sales for military use, officials said. As a result, licences were required for all military-related sales of supercomputers to China in the range of two billion to seven billion operations per second.</p>
<p>The New York Times said that after Clinton's 1995 deregulation decision, China went on a &quot;shopping spree&quot;, buying 46 U.S.-made supercomputers.</p>
<p>The newspaper, citing U.S. intelligence officials and nuclear experts, also asserted that the supercomputers could help China to conduct secret nuclear tests to judge the viability of their nuclear forces.</p>
<p>Cui said U.S. curbs on high technology exports to China were to blame for the bulging U.S. trade deficit with China.</p>
<p>&quot;The U.S. side set up some obstacles to high technology exports to China. This is not conducive to the development of trade and economic relations between the two countries&quot;.</p>
<p>Asked to comment on U.S. concerns that China was trading arms for oil in the Middle East, Cui did not comment but said the United States outstripped China in terms of weapons sales.</p>
<p>&quot;U.S. arms export figures far exceeds that of China,&quot; Cui said. &quot;The United States is probably the world's biggest arms exporter. China's arms exports are negligible compared with those of the United States.</p>
<p>&quot;We have our own principles. We never harm the stability of concerned regions or countries. We only help concerned countries cultivate their defence capabilities.</p>
<p>&quot;We never stir up conflicts in any region,&quot; Cui said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
