<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656484" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Judge declares mistrial in Kevorkian case.</title>
<headline>Judge declares mistrial in Kevorkian case.</headline>
<byline>Russell Gregory</byline>
<dateline>IONIA, Mich. 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A judge declared a mistrial in Jack Kevorkian's fourth assisted suicide trial on Thursday, saying inflammatory opening statements by the retired pathologist's defence attorney tainted the jury.</p>
<p>The decision by Ionia County Circuit Judge Charles Miel on the trial's second day abruptly ended a bid by a small-town prosecutor to convict the assisted suicide activist after three trials elsewhere in the state ended in acquittals.</p>
<p>Prosecutor Raymond Voet said he was not sure whether he would attempt to re-try Kevorkian on the same charges. If he does, a new trial could be six months away, added Voet, who initiated the proceeding's collapse with a highly unusual request for a mistrial following Wednesday's opening statement by defence attorney Geoffrey Fieger.</p>
<p>Kevorkian, 69, was charged with four felonies for his involvement in the Aug. 30 death of Loretta Peabody including violating unwritten Michigan &quot;common law&quot; banning assisted suicide and practicing medicine without a license. Peabody, 54, suffered from multiple sclerosis.</p>
<p>&quot;I have to consider what to do. It is tough to come up empty-handed,&quot; Voet said after the ruling. &quot;My theory is that Fieger's strategy was to blow up this case one way or another. It's as if he put gasoline in the jury box and lighted it.&quot;</p>
<p>Miel said he believed Fieger's legal errors in his opening statement were so severe that Kevorkian could be re-tried without violating double jeopardy laws that prohibit defendants from being tried twice for the same crime.</p>
<p>Fieger disagreed and said he would appeal any attempt to re-try Kevorkian.</p>
<p>&quot;We won't be back here again,&quot; he said, adding that he believed Voet simply gave up. &quot;I think he saved face here. I think he ended the case because he knew what I was going to do to him,&quot; Fieger said.</p>
<p>Voet asked for the mistrial on Thursday in response to Fieger's opening statement, which accused prosecutors of a &quot;witch hunt&quot; against Kevorkian. He said Fieger improperly accused him of tampering with evidence and of conspiring with other prosecutors to pursue Kevorkian even though, Fieger said, Michigan had no law against assisted suicide.</p>
<p>&quot;The extent of the possible bias cannot be measured but the court feels there is a high likelihood that the impartiality of one or more of the jurors may be affected by the opening statement of defendant's counsel,&quot; Miel said.</p>
<p>&quot;Prejudice of the jury cannot be repaired by any corrective instructions,&quot; the judge added.</p>
<p>Kevorkian, who has admitted attending 45 deaths since 1990, has been acquitted of assisted suicide charge in three previous trials, once in 1994 and twice in 1996.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="IONIA, Mich."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
