<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656570" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Report says cost-cutting threatens Alaska pipeline.</title>
<headline>Report says cost-cutting threatens Alaska pipeline.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Twenty years after oil began flowing through the trans-Alaska pipeline, the safety of the system that delivers a fifth of the nation's domestically produced oil is imperiled by cost-cutting, said a report issued Thursday by an environmental coalition.</p>
<p>Alyeska Pipeline Service Co, the consortium that operates the system, has improved environmental and safety protections, said the report, titled &quot;Pipeline in Peril.&quot;</p>
<p>But Alyeska economies threaten the aging 800-mile pipeline just as new North Slope oil is being discovered, said the report, issued in Washington by the Alaska Forum for Environmental Responsibility and the Alaska Wilderness League.</p>
<p>&quot;As it becomes clear that Alaska's North Slope will continue to pump oil for decades to come, it becomes increasingly important to assure that TAPS is maintained in top-flight condition,&quot; the report said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is difficult to imagine how Alyeska can accomplish this goal...while the company continues to cut operating costs.&quot;</p>
<p>The environmentalists' report, an update of a similar study issued last September, said Alyeska deserves credit for a management reorganization.</p>
<p>By next year, the Anchorage-based company will have shifted most of its workers to business units based in Fairbanks and Valdez to better oversee pipeline corridor and marine operations.</p>
<p>But cost-cutting strategies, including a total workforce reduction to 1,750 from 2,230, are cause for concern, the report said.</p>
<p>It praised the company for adopting high performance standards, but criticized what it said were slow responses to specific problems, such as an episode of violent pipeline shaking at Thompson Pass north of Valdez and a leak of weathered oil from the marine terminal's malfunctioning ballast-water-treatment plant.</p>
<p>Alyeska spokeswoman Jennifer Ruys said the company welcomed the report's scrutiny, and found that despite its criticisms, there were &quot;quite a few compliments sprinkled through the whole thing.&quot;</p>
<p>New demands on the system can be met, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;Our philosophy is the pipeline has an indefinite life if we maintain it and operate it well, so that's what we do,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Even though Alyeska plans to shut down two more pump stations next month, after closing two other stations last year, there will be no cut to the number of technicians along the pipeline corridor, Ruys said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are on the line 24 hours a day, making sure it's working well,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The &quot;Pipeline in Peril&quot; report also criticized government agencies for what it said were oversight failings.</p>
<p>Although Congress in 1990 mandated a presidential task force to study the system's safety, it has never provided funding for such a project.</p>
<p>The Joint Pipeline Office, a consortium of federal and state agencies that oversee pipeline operations, has failed to follow through on an external audit it promised last year, the report said.</p>
<p>John Shively, commissioner of the Alaska Department of Natural Resources, said improvements were being made by the company and by regulators.</p>
<p>He acknowledged that some woes persist at Alyeska, including a failure to complete important safety repairs.</p>
<p>The challenge will be ensuring future safety, at a reasonable cost, as production of new oil extends the pipeline's operating life, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;That pipeline could be around for another 20, 30 or 40 years,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Alyeska is owned by seven oil copmanies with interests on Alaska's North Slope. British Petroleum, Atlantic Richfield and Exxon own major shares.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
