<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656585" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Congress approves disaster aid, sends to Clinton.</title>
<headline>Congress approves disaster aid, sends to Clinton.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Congress approved on Thursday a multibillion dollar disaster aid bill with none of the political riders that prompted President Bill Clinton to veto an earlier version.</p>
<p>Clinton, who vetoed the first version on Monday, praised Congress for its &quot;common sense&quot; in passing the disaster aid in a form he would sign into law. It is expected to be sent to him on Thursday night.</p>
<p>In his veto message, Clinton had urged Congress to pass it again without political riders attached by Republicans. They would have prevented a government shutdown over the budget this fall and restricted the 2000 census to the traditional house-by-house count, rather than using statistical sampling to estimate numbers of minorities.</p>
<p>The bill provides $5.6 billion for North and South Dakota and Minnesota to recover from damage to homes and businesses from record floods and for 32 other states hurt by other natural disasters. It also restores $1.9 billion to military accounts to pay for past activities in Bosnia and the Gulf.</p>
<p>Republican leaders of Congress, barraged by negative press and hounded by lawmakers from flood-ravaged states, gave in to White House demands while agreeing to the full $8.9 billion in the original bill.</p>
<p>&quot;The leadership's position is we lost and let's get out of town quickly,&quot; said Rep. David McIntosh, Republican of Indiana.</p>
<p>Voting simultaneously, the House passed it 348-74 and the Senate passed it 78-21 without support of Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott, Republican of Mississippi. The bipartisan votes ended a week of wrangling by both parties.</p>
<p>Lawmakers called state and local officials in the flooded Upper Midwest to inform them of the long-awaited passage.</p>
<p>Sen. Kent Conrad, whose state of North Dakota suffered from floods said: &quot;This is going to help the rebuilding process to proceed. It's going to make a difference in the lives of thousands of people, many of whom are still sleeping on cots and staying in cars, people who have had their homes and their businesses destroyed.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton said in a statement: &quot;I am especially pleased that the congressional majority heeded the call of common sense by ensuring that the people who need this assistance will get it.</p>
<p>&quot;Above all, today's vote shows that while we may not agree on everything, we can still work together and move forward on those crucial priorities that are beyond dispute,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Addressing the president from the House floor, Appropriations Committee chairman Bob Livingston, Republican of Louisiana, acknowledged that Clinton won his demands. &quot;This is a perfect bill. Sign it into law.&quot;</p>
<p>Lott won the right to offer later in the year a measure to continue funding after Oct. 1 if regular spending bills have not been approved. A Republican aide called this Lott's &quot;ace in the hole&quot; to attempt to avert another government shutdown if budget battles escalate.</p>
<p>The administration will no longer be barred from using statistical sampling in the 2000 census, a method it hopes will help avoid undercounting of minorities.</p>
<p>Republicans agreed to a watered-down provision calling for a report on how the administration would conduct a person-by-person count.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
