<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656576" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: CEOs need not fret over global warming pact - Clinton.</title>
<headline>CEOs need not fret over global warming pact - Clinton.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Clinton Thursday sought to reassure chief executives of the nation's biggest companies that he was not out to wipe out their businesses with new policies to protect the environment.</p>
<p>Clinton attempted to respond to concerns raised by the Business Roundtable of CEOs from more than 100 companies in a $1 million newspaper ad campaign this week, which urged the administration not to rush into an international treaty in December designed to slow down global warming.</p>
<p>&quot;We know from all the scientific studies what is happening to the temperature of the globe,&quot; Clinton said in a speech to the group. &quot;What I ask you to do is work with me in good faith to give our children a world worth living in.&quot;</p>
<p>Companies fear that at an international summit in Kyoto, Japan, in December, the administration is going to commit to strict new limits on carbon emissions, which are believed to cause global warming. They have not yet seen the administration's position on emissions targets and deadlines.</p>
<p>But they fear they will be forced to burn less oil, gas and coal, pay more for energy or use expensive new technologies in cars and elsewhere to meet the standards, while developing nations will not have to meet the same requirements.</p>
<p>In their ads in major newspapers in Washington, the CEO's complained that &quot;there has been little public debate on the treaty even though it could have a dramatic effect on the way we live and work here in the United States.&quot;</p>
<p>In response Clinton said: &quot;I think we have to prove we can grow the economy while not only preserving but actually enhancing the environment.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;So I ask you to join with us in partnership. There is no secret plan or scheme here to try to put thousands of Americans out of business,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton encouraged companies to invest in new, environmentally friendly technologies to cut back on America's massive energy use and to sell to developing countries.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to find an environmentally responsible way for China to grow,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
