<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656650" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. broadcasters may get to keep some airwave rights.</title>
<headline>U.S. broadcasters may get to keep some airwave rights.</headline>
<byline>Roger Fillion</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Budget legislation making its way through Congress would let television broadcasters keep a valuable piece of the airwaves they are supposed to return to the government after the transition to digital TV.</p>
<p>Supporters say the measure, approved late on Wednesday by a House panel, is meant to ensure that consumers who do not buy a high-definition digital TV set will not be saddled with a worthless analogue set unable to receive digital broadcasts.</p>
<p>It would allow broadcasters to keep their existing analogue broadcast licenses beyond 2006 if 5 percent of their audience relies exclusively on existing over-the-air analogue signals.</p>
<p>&quot;It's designed to be a safety valve to ensure that nobody's TV set goes black because they couldn't afford to buy a digital TV set,&quot; said Ken Johnson, a spokesman for Representative W.J. (Billy) Tauzin, a Louisiana Republican.</p>
<p>But critics charge it would leave the government without a guarantee that TV stations will return the analogue spectrum to the Federal Communications Commission for auction. And they say it would dampen eventual bidding for those airwaves.</p>
<p>New FCC rules require the licenses be returned by 2006 so the spectrum can be made available to communications firms for other uses, following the conversion to digital TV.</p>
<p>&quot;The government will never see that spectrum,&quot; said Gigi Sohn of the Media Access Project, a public-interest law firm. &quot;It's a very backhanded way of reversing what the FCC did two months ago.&quot;</p>
<p>The fate of the legislation is unclear. But the analogue license provision is likely to face scepticism in the Senate.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for Sen. John McCain, an Arizona Republican who chairs the committee responsible for dealing with such matters, said the measure &quot;would create a large loophole.&quot;</p>
<p>It comes soon after the FCC gave TV stations digital-TV licenses free of charge on the assumption the analogue permits would be returned. McCain and other critics called the free digital licenses a multibillion dollar giveaway.</p>
<p>The budget measure approved by the House Commerce Committee is part of a bill meant to implement the fiscal 1998 budget accord agreed to by President Clinton and cleared by Congress.</p>
<p>The agreement calls for the government to raise $26.3 billion through airwave auctions -- including $5.4 billion from the sale of the analogue spectrum in the year 2001.</p>
<p>The auction would be made ahead of the 2006 target date set by the FCC for the return of the analogue spectrum.</p>
<p>FCC Chairman Reed Hundt said the provision to allow TV stations to keep the airwaves if 5 percent of their audience continued to rely on analogue signals would hurt the auction, thereby robbing the government of money.</p>
<p>&quot;The uncertainy created by such mandatory license extensions could discourage potential future users from bidding for this spectrum,&quot; he told Representative Tauzin in a letter.</p>
<p>But Tauzin spokesman Ken Johnson said: &quot;None of us have a crystal ball to know for certain by what date consumers are going to embrace digital TV. That's why you need a little wiggle room.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
