<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656617" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. astronaut's stay on Mir a fight for survival.</title>
<headline>U.S. astronaut's stay on Mir a fight for survival.</headline>
<byline>Steven Young</byline>
<dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four months aboard Russia's ageing Mir space station was a fight for survival at times, U.S. astronaut Jerry Linenger said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Linenger flew to Mir in January for a four-month stay, but a dramatic fire, a near collision with another spacecraft and a seemingly endless string of mechanical breakdowns left the 42-year-old astronaut frustrated that he was not always able to complete his scientific programme.</p>
<p>&quot;You feel like all you're doing is just trying to stay alive,&quot; Linenger told Reuters in one of his first interviews since returning to Earth in May. &quot;You say to yourself 'what are we accomplishing here other than just existing?'&quot;</p>
<p>The U.S. Navy captain and medical doctor often worked into the night to conduct his scientific experiments.</p>
<p>The fire in February marked the start of Linenger's trouble. A chemical oxygen generator burst into flame, shooting sparks and molten metal across one of Mir's seven modules. Within a minute, the sprawling station had filled with thick, choking smoke.</p>
<p>At the time there were six crew members aboard Mir -- four Russians, a German researcher and Linenger. The men grabbed emergency breathing masks as the air became unbreathable. They faced a desperate situation as fire blocked the route to one of the station's two Soyuz escape ships, which can each seat three people.</p>
<p>Although the crew prepared one Soyuz for an emergency departure, there was never any thought of leaving half the crew behind, according to Linenger.</p>
<p>The crew feared the fire's blow torch-like flame could puncture the space station's aluminium hull and cause an explosive decompression.</p>
<p>An unnatural calm descended on the station when the flames died down about 14 minutes later. Crew members had to sit still and relax to conserve their emergency oxygen supplies, while the air cleared of smoke. There was some smoke inhalation but no one was seriously injured, he said.</p>
<p>The space station problems seemed to snowball after that. The main oxygen generator failed, cooling systems sprang toxic leaks, carbon dioxide could not be removed from the breathing air and there was a near collision with an unmanned cargo craft.</p>
<p>The cooling problems sent temperatures soaring as high as 96 degrees Fahrenheit (34 Celsius). High humidity added to the miserable conditions and water would condense on the station's walls. And anti-freeze leaking from corroded cooling pipes caused breathing problems, allergic reactions and swollen eyes.</p>
<p>The corroded cooling system will probably determine the lifetime of the station, Linenger said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a fundamental part of the Mir; it's like the foundation of a house,&quot; he said. &quot;The corrosion in the cooling loops might be the show stopper.&quot;</p>
<p>There was more drama when the crew lost control of a remote control unmanned Progress cargo carrier approaching Mir. &quot;It looked like it was coming very fast and it looked like it was coming directly at us,&quot; Linenger said. &quot;That was a very tense moment.&quot;</p>
<p>The craft veered off and passed below the station.</p>
<p>Linenger, the fourth American to live aboard Mir, returned to Earth on May 24 and is recovering from the debilitating effects of weightlessness. He is looking forward to the birth of his second child later this month and will probably retire from NASA and the U.S. Navy.</p>
<p>&quot;Right now the number-one choice is just to retire,&quot; he said. &quot;I had one heck of an adventure and I survived.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
