<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656677" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FDA enters youth smoking rule pact with Florida.</title>
<headline>FDA enters youth smoking rule pact with Florida.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Florida became the first state to join the Food and Drug Administration to enforce new rules aimed at preventing the sale of tobacco products to children, the agency said Thursday.</p>
<p>Under the arrangement, Florida will conduct unannounced checks on hundreds of retail stores and send the information to the FDA. In turn, the agency will warn retailers the first time if they are found selling tobacco to minors. Second offences will result in a $250 fine with greater amounts for subsequent violations.</p>
<p>&quot;With this contract, we're taking concrete steps to keep tobacco out of the hands of kids,&quot; Health Secretary Donna Shalala said in a statement.</p>
<p>The FDA rules prohibit the sale of cigarettes and smokeless tobacco to people under 18 years of age. They also requires retailers to check identification with a photograph of anyone under 27 who is buying tobacco.</p>
<p>The aim is to reduce by half the number of young people smoking over the next seven years.</p>
<p>FDA said Florida would check about 300 retail stores a month over the next eight months. It was negotiating with nine other states to establish similar programmes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C32">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
