<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656780" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Whistleblower nurse testifies at doctor's Fla. trial.</title>
<headline>Whistleblower nurse testifies at doctor's Fla. trial.</headline>
<byline>Brad Liston</byline>
<dateline>SEBRING, Fla. 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A nurse testified Thursday she watched a Colombian physician on trial for murder inject potassium chloride, a drug used in lethal injection executions, directly into the intravenous tube of a patient.</p>
<p>Carole Drew, a nurse at Highlands Regional Medical Centre who prosecutors say blew the whistle on Dr. Ernesto Pinzon, told the court she later saw Pinzon lie about the injection on medical forms.</p>
<p>Pinzon, 37, is on trial for first-degree murder in the death of patient Rosario &quot;Roy&quot; Gurrieri and would face life in prison without parole if convicted.</p>
<p>Prosecutors alleged that Pinzon, 37, methodically murdered his patient while the man's grieving family stood confused by his bedside.</p>
<p>Drew told the court she was in Gurrieri's room when Pinzon administered 15 cubic centimetres (CCs) of potassium chloride directly into the patient's IV tube.</p>
<p>&quot;I've never seen potassium used that way before,&quot; she said she told Pinzon when they were out of the room.</p>
<p>She said the doctor then made a comment about how fast the patient's heart was beating and said &quot;I won't be writing it that way.&quot;</p>
<p>Drew testified, she later saw Pinzon's notes, which said he had injected the potassium chloride into 500 CCs of saline solution, which would have taken more time to reach Gurrieri's bloodstream.</p>
<p>Drew said Pinzon's notes were not true.</p>
<p>In prosecutors' opening arguments, they said Pinzon had admitted to lying on the form when he was questioned by state regulators.</p>
<p>Drew said she alerted two hospital supervisors to the inaccuracy on Pinzon's forms.</p>
<p>Pinzon's lawyers said in their opening arguments that Drew did not trust foreign doctors and was ready to believe the worst of Pinzon, who moved to Florida 17 months ago from Puerto Rico, where his family had lived since leaving Bogota when he was a child.</p>
<p>Gurrieri, 70, entered the Sebring hospital Oct. 5 with lung cancer that had spread to his spine and vital organs. His doctor had given him no more than two days to live.</p>
<p>Pinzon's lawyers say Gurrieri, who died the night of the injection, was killed by his illnesses, not by Pinzon.</p>
<p>Pinzon administerd morphine in high doses because the patient's family begged that his pain be relieved, and the potassium chloride was meant to slow a racing heartbeat, his lawyers said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEBRING, Fla."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
