<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656775" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Blizzards, floods and now drought hit North Dakota.</title>
<headline>Blizzards, floods and now drought hit North Dakota.</headline>
<byline>Greg Frost</byline>
<dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo. 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Blizzards, floods and now an early summer drought have plagued North Dakota, putting stress on crops and providing even more hardship for farmers, agricultural sources said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Record winter snowfall resulted in severe spring floods that devastated communities along the Red River, which flows north along the North Dakota-Minnesota border into Canada. Now a lack of rainfall has produced drought conditions in the northwest part of the state.</p>
<p>&quot;Mother Nature is very unpredictable and not always that kind,&quot; Bob Gulsvig, a spokesman for the North Dakota Barley Council, said on Thursday. &quot;We've gone through three different extremes in the span of 4-1/2 months. We've got it all.&quot;</p>
<p>The National Weather Service (NWS) said Bismarck, N.D., usually had an average of 2.72 inches (6.909 cm) of rain in June, making it the wettest month of the year. But so far this June, Bismarck has only received 13/100 inch (.33 cm) of rain.</p>
<p>&quot;Farmers are crying out for moisture for their crops,&quot; said Larry Manthe, NWS meteorologist in Bismarck.</p>
<p>North Dakota's agricultural statistics service said in a weekly crop report issued on Monday that topsoil moisture supplies were more than two-thirds short to very short across the state, making this the driest June since 1988.</p>
<p>The report also said the condition of all crops except sugarbeets deteriorated during the previous week because of the dry soil conditions.</p>
<p>North Dakota Agriculture Commissioner Roger Johnson said the drought was a huge problem for livestock producers who lost their hay crop last fall and fed all the hay they had in storage during the long hard winter.</p>
<p>Blizzards and floods have already cost North Dakota's economy at least $866 million in agriculture-related losses, according to estimates by Dwight Aakre, agricultural economist for the North Dakota State University Extension Service.</p>
<p>Aakre said snowstorms and bitter cold weather killed about 123,000 cattle and other livestock, valued altogether at about $59 million. Other losses came from buildings that collapsed under the weight of the record snowfall.</p>
<p>Residents of the northern U.S. Plains are becoming increasingly bitter over the hold-up of a disaster relief package due to partisan bickering in Washington.</p>
<p>The delay has rankled voters like Bob Clark, a South Dakota truck driver. Clark has been telling fellow truckers on his Citizen Band radio to call for the impeachment of members of Congress who have held up the flood relief money.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KANSAS CITY, Mo."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
