<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656848" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mass. legal chief doubts tobacco deal is possible.</title>
<headline>Mass. legal chief doubts tobacco deal is possible.</headline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Massachusetts Attorney General Scott Harshbarger told reporters on Thursday he was skeptical about whether the tobacco industry could settle with the 34 state attorneys general suing them to recover Medicaid costs.</p>
<p>&quot;I remain somewhat skeptical about whether there will be a settlement,&quot; Harshbarger told reporters after testifying before the state's Department of Public Health on Massachusett's tobacco ingredient disclosure law set to go into effect November 1.</p>
<p>But when asked if the industry had agreed to make ingredient disclosure part of any settlement, Harshbarger replied, &quot;I would say yes with the caveat that nothing is accepted until you see the final package.&quot;  </p>
<p>Harshbarger, a Democratic candidate for the 1998 gubernatorial race, said he would vigorously defend the state's disclosure law, saying &quot;it would be a major benefit to the public health and the kids and the public of Massachusetts.&quot;</p>
<p>Lead by Philip Morris Cos Inc, the industry has challenged the measure, which requires tobacco makers to reveal the contents by weight or measure of each brand of cigarette or smokeless tobacco sold in the state to the department of public health. The department, after a review by Harshbarger's office, can then make that information available to the public.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
