<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656864" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Ireland's Robinson gets top U.N. human rights job.</title>
<headline>Ireland's Robinson gets top U.N. human rights job.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Mary Robinson of Ireland on Thursday was named to the top U.N. human rights post by Secretary-General Kofi Annan who asked her to step down from the Irish presidency by September to take up the post.</p>
<p>Robinson, a lawyer and human rights expert, had been the favourite for the Geneva-based post of U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights for several weeks and Annan called her an &quot;extraordinary leader&quot; who would bring &quot;dynamism to the job.&quot;</p>
<p>But she does not end her seven-year term as president until December 2. However, Annan said he had asked her to begin the Geneva-based U.N. post by the time the 52nd General Assembly session starts in September.</p>
<p>He said she understood the urgency of starting the job earlier but he did not say she had agreed to his terms. She will come to New York next month to discuss the issue.</p>
<p>The 165-member General Assembly must still endorse the appointment.</p>
<p>In Dublin, Robinson, 53, said in a statement: &quot;I deeply appreciate the trust and confidence which the Secretary-General has placed in me.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I am greatly indebted to all those who supported my candidature, especially to the Irish government and officials in the (Irish) Department of Foreign Affairs who spared no effort in promoting it.&quot;</p>
<p>Annan, in a news conference, said: &quot;I have identified someone who is an extraordinary leader who has done lots of work in the human rights field and who will bring dynamism, credibility and leadership to the Human Right Centre.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;And I have therefore decided to name Mrs Mary Robinson as the next high Commissioner for Human Rights,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said he realised she was a sitting president. But he said it &quot;would be preferable if she could assume her functions before the beginning of the 52nd session of the General Assembly. I believe Mrs Robinson understands the urgency and the need to start as soon as she can.&quot;</p>
<p>Robinson is known for championing the rights of the poor, the oppressed and the under-privileged. As president of Ireland, she turned what was a largely ceremonial job of cutting the tape at flower shows and opening community centres into a focus for the injustices of the world.</p>
<p>Supported by Britain as well as U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright, Robinson had faced some objections from Third World countries because she was a European. Annan said he would appoint a deputy shortly and the deputy would come from a developing country.</p>
<p>The first reaction came from Russia's ambassador Sergei Lavrov, this month's Security Council president. &quot;She is a very well-known personality and had been mentioned as one of the candidates and I am sure she will be a very efficient international official.&quot;</p>
<p>The job, first proposed nearly 50 years ago, became vacant after Jose Ayala Lasso resigned in March as the first human rights commissioner to become Ecuador's foreign minister.</p>
<p>He had been appointed in 1994 for four years and was criticised by several human rights groups for being too cautious on abuses by governments.</p>
<p>In Geneva, news of Robinson's appointed was welcomed by staff at the U.N. Centre for Human Rights, who had hoped for a new chief who would speak out publicly on rights violations.</p>
<p>&quot;It is fantastic. She will bring prestige to the post,&quot; said one employee.</p>
<p>Robinson, an attorney with special expertise in constitutional and European human rights law, had pleaded landmark cases before the European Commission.</p>
<p>She was the first head of state to visit Rwanda in the aftermath of the 1994 genocide there as well as the U.N. tribunal on the former Yugoslavia in the Hague.</p>
<p>Her closest competitor, Sonia Picado, Costa Rica's ambassador to Washington, was rejected late last month, making it nearly certain Annan would appoint Robinson. Picado, however, indicated she she had been offered the deputy post but would not accept it. But she said she might work in another related-U.N. human rights field.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
