<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656920" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: EU assembly demands immediate leghold trap ban.</title>
<headline>EU assembly demands immediate leghold trap ban.</headline>
<dateline>STRASBOURG 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Parliament demanded on Thursday that the European Union reject a draft deal with fur exporters Canada and Russia which would allow the continued use of leg-hold traps to catch animals for their fur.</p>
<p>The proposed agreement on so-called humane trapping standards was &quot;totally inadequate and ineffective&quot; because it would allow third countries to continue exporting to the EU pelts of animals caught in steel-jawed leg-hold traps even though they are banned in the Union, Euro-MPs said.</p>
<p>EU ministers agreed in 1991 to a ban on fur imports from Canada, Russia, the United States and other countries that still use the traps, which do not kill animals outright but often break their legs and imprison them until they bleed or starve to death.</p>
<p>But the European Commission delayed the introduction of the ban, which had provoked threats of trade sanctions from the fur exporting countries, in the hope that it could be replaced by an intnernational agreement on more &quot;humane&quot; trapping standards.</p>
<p>The provisional deal which the Commission has reached with Toronto and Moscow sets no deadline for outlawing the leg-hold trap but instead allows the signatories to submit unilateral declarations saying when they intend to stop using them.</p>
<p>The EU assembly reacted in dismay to the deal, which the United States has rejected as too strict, saying it might even allow some types of leg-hold trap to be classed as &quot;humane&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a con,&quot; Portuguese Christian Democrat Carlos Pimenta, the author of the assembly's report on the traps, told Reuters last week.</p>
<p>In a move designed to put pressure on EU environment ministers, who will have the final say on June 19-20, parliament demanded the immediate introduction of the EU's ban on all types of leg-hold traps and said negotiations should continue with the fur exporters to establish genuinely humane trapping standards.</p>
<p>This meant traps which killed within 30 seconds and procedures for strictly enforcing the rules, Euro-MPs said.</p>
<p>A U.S. official last week told Reuters that Washington did not accept that leg-hold traps were necessarily inhumane.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I45600">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G156">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STRASBOURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
