<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656917" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Fabius again in public eye as speaker.</title>
<headline>France's Fabius again in public eye as speaker.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Laurent Fabius, once France's youngest prime minister but later relegated to the obscurity of Socialist parliamentary leader, returned to the spotlight on Thursday by becoming National Assembly speaker for a second time.</p>
<p>Fabius, 50, was prime minister from 1984 to 86 and presided over the assembly from 1988 to January 1992 when he resigned to become Socialist Party leader.</p>
<p>He owes his new prominence to the upset victory of Socialist Prime Minister Lionel Jospin's leftist alliance which swept the centre-right government from power in the June 1 elections.</p>
<p>However, a cabinet job was out of the question as Fabius is formally under investigation in connection with a major scandal over the spread of AIDS through contaminated blood products in the mid-1980s when he was prime minister.</p>
<p>Jospin has said that no one can serve in his cabinet while the target of a justice inquiry. The state prosecutor in the special court investigating whether Fabius should tried on charges of poisoning in the blood scandal has recommended that he should be cleared.</p>
<p>Fabius left his post as parliamentary speaker in 1992 to try to out-manoeuvre fellow-Socialist Michel Rocard, also an ex-prime minister, in the race for the left's 1995 presidential nomination.</p>
<p>In the event, neither man won the prize. It went instead to Jospin, whose respectable performance against the victorious Gaullist Jacques Chirac in the presidential election led to his unchallenged leadership of the Socialists' 1997 campaign.</p>
<p>Fabius was only 37 when he became prime minister in July 1984. Prematurely bald, sharply tailored and pragmatic rather than doctrinaire, he snugly matched the modern mood of France's increasingly &quot;social democratic&quot; Socialist Party.</p>
<p>But he stumbled over the 1985 Rainbow Warrior affair, when months of stony denial ended in a red-faced admission that French agents had blown up a Greenpeace anti-nuclear ship in New Zealand, killing a photographer.</p>
<p>He also had a public disagreement with then-president Francois Mitterrand over a state visit of Polish President Wozchiek Jaruselski, giving rise to a well-remembered remark to parliament: &quot;He (Mitterrand) is him and I am me.&quot;</p>
<p>In March 1986 the Fabius government was defeated at the ballot box by Chirac's conservative coalition.</p>
<p>Throughout his career, Fabius, the son of a rich Paris antiques dealer, has been dogged by his privileged background and doubts about his left-wing credentials.</p>
<p>Educated at France's elite school for technocrats, the Ecole Nationale d'Administration (ENA), he joined the Socialist Party relatively late and owed much of his career to the personal attentions of Mitterrand, who made him his economic adviser in 1975.</p>
<p>When the Socialists came to power in 1981, he was rewarded with the budget ministry where his pragmatic approach and easy way with the media put him in prime position to lead the government three years later.</p>
<p>His Jewish origins became the butt of jokes by the extreme right, but his impassioned defence of human rights and image as a family man -- he is married with three children -- proved more persuasive with voters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
