<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="656928" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>REPUBLIC OF IRELAND: Ireland's Mary Robinson, the people's champion. [CORRECTED 22:45 GMT]</title>
<headline>Ireland's Mary Robinson, the people's champion. [CORRECTED 22:45 GMT]</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>DUBLIN 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ireland's President Mary Robinson, named U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights on Thursday, has been a champion of the poor, the oppressed and the under-privileged and won the hearts of millions.</p>
<p>She turned the ceremonial post of Irish head of state, previously a matter of cutting the tape at flower shows and opening community centres, into a celebration of the uniqueness of being Irish and a focus for the injustices of the world, especially the developing world.</p>
<p>&quot;My grandfather was a lawyer,&quot; Robinson told Reuters Television in a recent interview. &quot;He instilled into us from an early age a sense of natural justice which has been a guiding light for me.&quot;</p>
<p>That guiding light took her three times to the stricken East African nation of Somalia, into the ethnic killing fields of Rwanda and to the United Nations, where she urged the world's most powerful nations to do more than send instant aid.</p>
<p>The 53-year-old lawyer (corrects age) urged the developed West to seek political solutions to what she saw as essentially political problems and to do more than provide quick-fix aid packages for nations torn asunder by years of political instability.</p>
<p>According to United Nations insiders, the post awarded her by United Nations Secretary-General Koffi Annan was tailor-made for her mix of humanitarian concern and political skill.</p>
<p>By their account it is a position that has received little world publicity or recognition. &quot;It's a job waiting to be filled, and she will make it happen,&quot; said one insider based in the European U.N. capital, Geneva.</p>
<p>Robinson would be the first to admit that she has never held a major executive post in her political career, in which she was a leading member of Ireland's left-leaning Labour party.</p>
<p>The U.N. job will stretch her, demanding that she balance her goals of championing human rights against the U.N.'s current concern to keep costs down and bureaucracy lean and efficient.</p>
<p>&quot;The challenges that the new post will bring are daunting but they are ones I am gladly prepared to accept,&quot; Robinson said in a statement faxed to Reuters in Dublin.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope to avail of the opportunities which now exist, with the support of the international community, to make significant progress in the protection and promotion of human rights world wide,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Robinson became in the words of Prime Minister John Bruton, &quot;the best President we ever had.&quot;</p>
<p>She crossed frontiers, even in Ireland, and broke down barriers. The weekly diary she faxed to the nations' newsdesks was as thick as that of her predecessors' were thin.</p>
<p>The new job, she told Reuters recently, meets a lifelong interest in justice both natural and constitutional and will allow her to take an active part in shaping a &quot;new world order&quot; which she believes has its natural heart in Ireland.</p>
<p>Perhaps her best known gesture in Ireland was the placing of a candle in the kitchen of her grand official residence in Dublin's Phoenix Park as a beacon to the 40 million Irish diaspora, many of whom trace their displacement to the great Irish potato famine of 150 years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The idea came from my mother when I was a child in Mayo. We always lit one in the window to symbolise shelter for anyone at that time of year. We lived opposite the Cathedral, so there was a certain pressure to get ours up first,&quot; she joked.</p>
<p>The Irish government publicly announced its wholehearted support for her candidature to succeed Jose Ayalo-Lasso who returned to Ecuador to become Foreign Minister.</p>
<p>She has also received key support from the White House, which is keen to reform the U.N. bureaucracy and keep down costs - Washington is the single biggest contributor.</p>
<p>Robinson's husband, Nicholas, is a businessman who says he has no trouble &quot;standing in the shadow&quot; of Ireland's best-known international figure.</p>
<p>She says that when she gets a day off from a whirlwind diary of official engagements, &quot;I like to return to Mayo, thrown on my jeans and go for a walk with the dogs.&quot;</p>
<p>Typically, Robinson's candidature for the post was made public when she was travelling abroad - no other Irish President spent so much time overseas.</p>
<p>It was announced in March as she became the first head of state to visit the War Crimes Tribunal in The Hague. It shares a common prosecutor with the U.N. tribunal into the genocide in Rwanda, which she has visited three times.</p>
<p>A constitutional lawyer by training, Robinson shared a determination to be the People's president with a desire to fly the flag of Irish concern at the plight of the poor and the oppressed all over the world.</p>
<p>Ireland is one of the few countries in the developed world which is on course for reaching U.N. targets for per capita donations of aid, a tradition, she says, whose origins are Ireland's own sufferings.</p>
<p>&quot;It was the great Irish potato famine which we have been remembering for these past three years. It killed more than a million people and it has taken us this long to get over it. That's why we remember the less fortunate,&quot; she told Reuters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="REPUBLIC OF IRELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
