<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657026" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Ecuador urges EU to play fair on bananas.</title>
<headline>Ecuador urges EU to play fair on bananas.</headline>
<byline>Peter Blackburn</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ecuador, a poor country heavily dependent on banana exports, urged the European Union on Thursday to implement rapidly a World Trade Organisation ruling and change unfair banana import licensing rules.</p>
<p>The WTO in May upheld a complaint by the United States, backed by Ecuador, Honduras, Guatemala and Mexico, that EU banana import quotas imposed in 1993 favoured former European colonies against U.S. and Latin American suppliers.</p>
<p>Ecuador's Foreign Trade Minister, Benigno Sotomayor, said the EU's allocation of 30 percent of a special tariff quota to operators with no history of importing Latin American bananas was illegal under WTO rules.</p>
<p>In order to maintain market share, Ecuador was forced to buy the licences from the operators, paying up to $7.0 a box of bananas at an annual cost of some $40 million, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have lost earnings and market growth, Sotomayor told Reuters in an interview, adding, &quot;We want to trade bananas, not pieces of paper.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Most of the profit is being made by middlemen, not ACP banana producers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Sotomayor was referring to poor producers in African, Caribbean and Pacific countries who enjoy aid and trade preferences under the Lome Convention.</p>
<p>Ecuador's minister, appointed two months ago, stressed that Ecuador was not attacking ACP trade benefits but the unfair distribution of import licences.</p>
<p>Ecuador, the world's biggest banana exporter, can produce bananas at less than one third of the cost of African and Caribbean producers.</p>
<p>&quot;We are being punished for being efficient,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Sotomayor has this week been pressing Ecuador's case before Sir Leon Brittan, Franz Fischler and Manuel Marin -- the EU commissioners responsible for foreign trade, agriculture and Latin America.</p>
<p>The meetings were part of a European tour covering Germany, France, Spain, Italy, Belgium and Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;We want better access to the EU market, to make them aware of the importance of bananas to Ecuador's export earnings and to seek a speedy resolution of the dispute,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A European Commission spokesman said that the EU had explained that it was appealing against its banana ruling. The appeal is due to be heard on July 11 with a possible decision on September 9.</p>
<p>Ecuador is concerned that the EU could drag its feet and take advantage of a 15 months deadline for implementing the WTO's binding ruling.</p>
<p>Caribbean banana producers have bitterly criticised the United States for bringing the case, which they say is aimed at ensuring profits for big U.S. companies like Chiquita Brands and Dole and ignores their dependence on the fruit.</p>
<p>Ecuador's banana industry is 80 percent in local, private hands and some 10 percent of the population, or more than 1.2 million people, depend on bananas for a living.</p>
<p>Since the EU imposed tariff quotas in 1993, Ecuador has had to close nearly 17,000 hectares of banana plantations and some 65,000 people, mostly dock workers, have lost their jobs.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ECU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GUAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100206">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
