<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657191" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Health support grows for tobacco pact.</title>
<headline>Health support grows for tobacco pact.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Gail Appleson, Law Correspondent</p>
<p>In a sign of growing support from the health community for a tobacco settlement, several groups on Thursday revealed and praised health care provisions that have been agreed upon by negotiating parties.</p>
<p>The move comes as attorneys general, the highest ranking legal officers of each state, hope to announce a settlement with cigarette makers next week. The White House has said it would not approve any accord that did not have the blessing of the public health community.</p>
<p>Although health groups have been sceptical since negotiations began in early April, the American Cancer Society, the American Heart Association and the Campaign for Tobacco Free Kids held a press briefing explaining why they felt a settlement could do far more to reduce smoking and provide funds to pay for injuries than any litigation.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a moral imperative to look at a settlement if one comes forward,&quot; said John Seffrin, chief executive officer of the American Cancer Society. &quot;...This would insure a leveling of the killing field.&quot;</p>
<p>Seffrin is a member of the Advisory Committee on Tobacco Policy and Public Health, an independent panel of public health advocates formed to monitor tobacco talks. The committee is chaired by former Surgeon General C. Everett Koop and former FDA Commissioner David Kessler.</p>
<p>Not all groups represented on the committee, which is scheduled to meet next week, support the concept of a settlement at this time.</p>
<p>But participants at Thursday's briefing, including Lonnie Bristow, immediate past president of the American Medical Association, stressed that a settlement could provide health benefits that might never be obtained any other way.</p>
<p>Matthew Myers, executive vice president and general counsel of the Campaign for Tobacco-Free Kids, said the tobacco industry has found a way to &quot;circumvent and undermine every rule, every regulation that has ever been imposed on them. It is the most creative, irresponsible outlaw industry in the history of mankind.</p>
<p>&quot;This agreement is designed for the first time to make them pay if they continue to behave in the same manner,&quot; Myers said. &quot;For the first time in history it puts a price on luring our kids into a lifetime of addiction.&quot;</p>
<p>Myers cautioned that while the parties have agreed to certain health care provisions, there are still sticking issues that could sabotage an accord. These include the Food and Drug Administration's authority to regulate cigarettes and certain civil liability issues such as punitive damages.</p>
<p>He said if an agreement can be reached on FDA authority, the industry has agreed to drop its appeal of a federal court ruling in April upholding the agency's power to regulate tobacco products as drugs.</p>
<p>A pact would also resolve lawsuits brought by state attorneys general seeking reimbursement for Medicaid costs of smokers as well as suits seeking class action action status. On Thursday, California becamse the 37th state where the attorney general has sued the tobacco industry seeking to recoup the health care costs of smokers.</p>
<p>Myers said the industry has agreed to set up a fund to pay for awards in individual lawsuits.</p>
<p>A final figure has not yet been decided, but there would be an annual ceiling so that the industry would have certainty about how much it would have pay on a yearly basis.</p>
<p>&quot;This fund will dwarf any fund that has ever been created by the tort system,&quot; Myers said. &quot;To reach the cap you would need to have thousands of million-dollar-judgments against the industry.&quot;</p>
<p>He said there would be no cap on individual judgments. In the unlikely event damage awards would exceed the fund's annual amount, the claimaint would receive the full payment during the next year.</p>
<p>The following are some of the health provisions the group said have been agreed upon by negotiators.</p>
<p>-- The tobacco industry would be subject to penalties if youth tobacco use fails to drop by 30 percent in five years, 50 percent in seven years and 60 percent in 10 years. The penalty would be based on the value of a teen tobacco user to the industry over his or her lifetime.</p>
<p>-- Advertising that has the greatest influence on children would be eliminated. This would include barring the use of cartoon characters, such as Joe Camel, and all human images from all advertising and from all cigarette packages.</p>
<p>-- Cigarette package warnings would be strengthened to include such language as cigarettes are addictive and can cause fatal lung disease in non-smokers. The warnings will be increased in size and placed on the front of packages.</p>
<p>-- Companies would be required to set up internal monitoring programmes.</p>
<p>-- The industry would fund smoking cessation programmes and devices for those who cannot afford them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I95100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
