<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657175" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: FEATURE - Gandhi follower hails end of British empire.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Gandhi follower hails end of British empire.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Verma</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>When he travelled across the dusty dirt roads of rural India with Mahatma Gandhi half a century ago, Sailen Chatterjee never thought he would live to see the end of the British empire.</p>
<p>Fifty years after India became the first major British colony to attain independence in the 20th century, and weeks before Hong Kong becomes one of the last, Chatterjee says he wishes Gandhi was still alive to witness the waning days of the British realm.</p>
<p>&quot;At that time, I did not realise that the granting of Indian independence would be the forerunner for the fall of the great empire, bit by bit,&quot; Chatterjee, 72, told Reuters in a recent interview.</p>
<p>&quot;But the Mahatma had some premonition. He used to say, 'However great an empire may be, they must realise they cannot exploit the people of a country for long'.&quot;</p>
<p>GANDHI'S LEGACY LIVES ON</p>
<p>Chatterjee says he first met Gandhi in 1944 as a young journalist and spent the next three years travelling with the spiritual father of independent India as he visited villages spreading the message of non-violent opposition to British rule.</p>
<p>When Gandhi was assassinated by a Hindu fanatic in 1948, Chatterjee says he was standing a few yards behind him.</p>
<p>&quot;I wish Gandhiji would have been alive to see the end of empire,&quot; he said sadly, using the term that many Indians use to refer to Gandhi. The suffix &quot;ji&quot; denotes respect; the title &quot;Mahatma&quot; is Sanskrit for &quot;great soul&quot;.</p>
<p>Now a special correspondent at the Daily Kesari newspaper, founded in 1881, Chatterjee wears thick glasses and a shirt of handspun cotton that Gandhi popularised as a symbol of self-reliance, and speaks without bitterness.</p>
<p>&quot;The Mahatma used to clearly say, 'We are fighting the empire not the people',&quot; he says softly. &quot;He would have been the best friend of the British people.&quot;</p>
<p>Chatterjee says he remembers Gandhi taking off his slippers and walking barefoot on dirt tracks from village to village with a religious devotion to his causes of sectarian unity and peaceful resistance to colonial rule.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, Gandhi's feet would be studded with thorns and bleeding, Chatterjee said.</p>
<p>&quot;One day I asked him, 'Mahatmaji, why are you suffering like this at the age of 76?' He said, 'Sailen, do you go into a religous place with your dirty shoes on? Please remember I am going into a temple, trying to influence the human mind and heart'.&quot;</p>
<p>India's independence in 1947 sparked a chain reaction, inspiring many other colonies to achieve freedom, Chatterjee says.</p>
<p>&quot;The grant of independence by the British rulers to India was the beginning of the slow fall of various parts of the empire,&quot; he said. &quot;Of course, I was really happy when one after another, British colonies were freeing themselves.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Gandhiji knew we could not match the British in their mighty armed power. So, his method was non-violence. And now, years later, Nelson Mandela practised the same method,&quot; Chatterjee said. &quot;Gandhi is still relevant almost 50 years after his death.&quot;</p>
<p>DON'T FORGET THE BRITISH</p>
<p>As Hong Kong returns to China at midnight on June 30 after a century and a half of colonial rule, its people must not forget the benefits of British governance, which transformed the unremarkable outpost in the Far East into a rich, glittering city, Chatterjee said.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that after it goes back to China, the people of Hong Kong do not forget the contributions of the British, just as we in India have not,&quot; Chatterjee said.</p>
<p>He was referring to India's vast bureaucracy and the mammoth railway network that the British began building in the 1850s to move food -- and troops -- swiftly across the sprawling nation.</p>
<p>&quot;And after being freed from colonial rule, Hong Kong will face new kinds of problems, like any other country, from the administrative point of view and the political angle,&quot; Chatterjee said.</p>
<p>He added: &quot;Nobody would like that someone from a foreign country would come and rule his country or her country forever. I am happy that the British are realising they must give self-governance to various countries in a friendly manner.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
