<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657182" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: The Bronx to Wall Street -- Ralph Lauren's journey.</title>
<headline>The Bronx to Wall Street -- Ralph Lauren's journey.</headline>
<byline>Judith Schoolman</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Bronx-born son of a housepainter and a one-time necktie designer, Ralph Lauren has made a fortune turning plain cloth into elegant attire.</p>
<p>Along the way, the Lauren name has become synonymous with an image of the country club set, with polo players and yacht sailing. His clothes, home furnishings, even line of house paints, are designed to promote a sense of comfort -- with classic styles and quality construction -- leaving ostentatious fashion-of-the-moment to someone else.</p>
<p>From the employees at Lauren's Madison Avenue flagship store to the models in his ads, there is a Ralph Lauren look. Be the models dark skinned or light, they are uniformly tall, lithe and wearing an expression of upper-crust ennui.</p>
<p>Lauren's particular genius has been in marketing, observers noted, particularly of himself.</p>
<p>His most recent foray, onto Wall Street, met with heady success, with Polo Ralph Lauren Corp. stock making a stellar debut on the New York Stock Exchange Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;My goal in design is to achieve the ultimate dream -- the best reality imaginable,&quot; he said in company documents.</p>
<p>In keeping with the image of romance, innovation and tradition, Lauren's New York City store, opened in 1986, is housed in the former Rhinelander mansion on New York's chic Upper East Side.</p>
<p>Lauren, born Ralph Lifshitz on Oct. 14, 1939, the son of Frank, a housepainter, and Frieda, changed his name in the mid-1950s.</p>
<p>In his teens, he worked as a stock boy at the now defunct Alexander's department store. After attending New York's City College and serving in the military, he worked as an assistant buyer for Allied Stores, and as a salesman for Brooks Brothers and Bloomingdale's.</p>
<p>Lauren moved to design ties for Beau Brummel Ties, a New York City firm, and a year later, in 1968, used $50,000 in financing to form Polo Ralph Lauren.</p>
<p>In 1971 he branched out into women's wear, and from there introduced leather goods, children's wear, fragrances, home furnishings and house paints, all under the Ralph Lauren name.</p>
<p>Lauren made his first waves as a tie designer, abandoning the standard 2 1/2-inch widths for four-inch-wide ties using patterned silks that suggested upholstery fabrics.</p>
<p>Lauren launched his first brand, Polo, in 1967 with a collection of men's ties and later moved into menswear. The now-famous logo of a polo player astride a horse appeared in 1971. Costly and opulent, Polo ties caught on with younger men who wanted to set trends.</p>
<p>Hollywood took notice of Lauren's updated classic styles and tapped him to outfit Robert Redford as &quot;The Great Gatsby&quot; in the 1974 film. A few years later, Diane Keaton reportedly built her famed &quot;Annie Hall&quot; look from Ralph Lauren separates.</p>
<p>The success of both films brought the designer's name from high end boutiques into the lexicon of average Americans.</p>
<p>His women's collections generally have won warm praise from the fashion press. Relying on classic styles, Lauren said some years ago, &quot;I didn't think it was necessary for a women to dress like a vamp, like Jean Harlow or Marilyn Monroe.&quot;</p>
<p>He found that the best marketing tool for his products has been himself, and the tanned, fit, often blue jean-clad designer has appeared in ads since 1974. After a brief experiment with television ads, Lauren abandoned them for print because he found TV too hard-sell.</p>
<p>Lauren's retailing and marketing empire has continued to grow in the past decade. His label now includes infants' and toddlers' clothes, Safari and Polo Sport fragrances, intimate apparel under a licensing agreement with Sara Lee Corp., and a new line of petite size fashions.</p>
<p>Sales at Polo Ralph Lauren grew to $1.2 billion in the year ended in March 1997 from about $1 billion a year earlier, while earnings jumped to $117.3 million from $98.8 million.</p>
<p>On its first day of trading Thursday, the stock jumped $5.125 from the offer price to $31.125 and was the most active issue on the New York Stock Exchange. The company sold the stock on Wednesday in the second biggest initial public offering this year, raising roughly $767 million.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I45300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
