<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657180" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: House tax panel working through tax cut bill.</title>
<headline>House tax panel working through tax cut bill.</headline>
<byline>Tabassum Zakaria</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The House tax-writing committee Thursday turned back Democratic efforts to change education initiatives in the Republican tax bill to more closely mirror those proposed by President Clinton.</p>
<p>The White House contends House Ways and Means Committee Chairman Bill Archer's legislation to cut taxes by $85 billion over five years did not live up to a budget agreement made with congressional leaders.</p>
<p>The first 90 minutes of committee debate was on an amendment offered by the panel's ranking Democrat, Representative Charles Rangel of New York, who proposed Clinton's HOPE scholarship programme with some modifications.</p>
<p>Clinton's HOPE scholarship would provide a $1,500 tax credit for higher education. Legislation being considered in the tax committee was crafted by Archer, a Texas Republican, and would allow individual taxpayers to claim a HOPE tax credit for 50 percent of tuition up to $1,500.</p>
<p>The administration has argued that would penalise students going to less-expensive schools like community colleges who would not then get the full tax credit.</p>
<p>The budget agreement called for &quot;roughly&quot; $35 billion in tax cuts over five years for Clinton's education tax initiatives. Archer's bill contains $31 billion for education tax initiatives, but the White House argued that only $22 billion of that amount went for the types of programmes that were promised in the budget accord.</p>
<p>&quot;We support the Rangel amendment, it increases access to higher education,&quot; Karl Scholz, deputy assistant Treasury secretary for tax analysis, told the committee. The amendment was defeated 21-15.</p>
<p>House Speaker Newt Gringich took to task Vice President Al Gore's assertion earlier this week that Archer's tax bill did not live up to the budget agreement.</p>
<p>&quot;How would he know?&quot; Gingrich said, adding that Gore was not in the room when the deal was made last month. &quot;The deal he (Gore) described isn't the deal we made, I mean he may have a fantasy deal.&quot; The Georgia Republican said Gore &quot;totally mischaracterized&quot; the agreement.</p>
<p>Gingrich said the Republican bill would save a &quot;typical family&quot; about $10,000 in taxes through childhood for a baby born this year.</p>
<p>The House Ways and Means committee approved two other amendments offered by Democrats.</p>
<p>One offered by Representative Benjamin Cardin, a Maryland Democrat, would provide a tax credit up to $150 for 50 percent of tuition costs for remedial tutoring programmes for students in kindergarten through high school.</p>
<p>&quot;These are students who are having problems with a subject at school, maybe math, maybe science, and they need special help,&quot; Cardin said.</p>
<p>A tutoring programme would help them prepare for college, he said. The cost of the tax credit would be $252 million over five years, which would be offset by limiting  contributions to pre-paid college tuition programmes to $5,000 a year toward a $50,000 limit that is in Archer's bill, Cardin said.</p>
<p>Another amendment that was approved, offered by Representative Xavier Becerra, a California Democrat, would allow students not to be taxed for a student loan forgiven by private colleges because they went into a community profession such as police officer.</p>
<p>Currently forgiveness of that loan would be counted as income for the student and taxed. The cost of the provision was $5 million over five years.</p>
<p>The committee defeated several Democratic amendments in the capital gains tax cut area, but adopted a Republican congressman's proposal to allow companies to offset ordinary losses against capital gains.</p>
<p>The measure would alleviate a problem commonly referred to as the corporate capital gains &quot;tax trap,&quot; said Pennsylvania Republican Representative Phil English. The proposal was not expected to result in any additional cost to the government.</p>
<p>The committee finished consideration of child tax credit provisions in its Wednesday session, leaving Archer's plan untouched by defeating Democratic amendments.</p>
<p>The child tax credit is the single biggest item in the proposed tax bill at a cost of $71 billion over five years. Under Archer's plan, families would receive a $400 tax credit in 1998 for each child under age 17, increased to $500 in following years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
