<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657147" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistani mill owners plead for raw sugar import.</title>
<headline>Pakistani mill owners plead for raw sugar import.</headline>
<byline>Ibrahim Khan</byline>
<dateline>KARACHI, Pakistan 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistani sugar mill owners pleaded on Thursday for the import of raw sugar instead of refined white crystal sugar, saying this could save at least $50 million a year in foreign exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;We should concentrate on importing raw sugar instead of refined sugar,&quot; Khadim Ali Qazilbash, secretary general of the Pakistan Sugar Mills Association, told Reuters, adding that raw sugar costs about $60 a tonne less than refined sugar.</p>
<p>&quot;Some sugar mills imported raw sugar and sold it after refining in the past few weeks,&quot; he said. &quot;The experiment was very encouraging.&quot;</p>
<p>Mian Fawad Ahmed Sheikh, a director of Fatima Sugar Mills near the central city of Multan, said he had imported 5,000 tonnes of raw sugar, refined it and sold it for a moderate profit. He has now imported another 12,000 tonnes of raw sugar.</p>
<p>Sheikh said buying raw sugar from abroad could keep mills, which now operate seasonally, busy for the whole year.</p>
<p>&quot;The only drawback is the government's high excise duty,&quot; he said. &quot;If it is waived, then refined sugar could be cheaper than that produced by crushing locally cultivated sugarcane.&quot;</p>
<p>He was speaking one day before Finance Minister Sartaj Aziz was due to present his budget for fiscal 1997/98 (July-June).</p>
<p>&quot;Pakistan could earn foreign exchange by refining raw sugar and exporting refined sugar as is done in China, South Korea, the United Arab Emirates and other countries,&quot; Sheikh said.</p>
<p>Pakistan imported 518,976 tonnes of sugar worth $197 million in the first 10 months of 1996/97, compared to a negligible 2,759 tonnes in the year-ago period.</p>
<p>In April sugar imports rose to 34,388 tonnes worth $12 million compared to 16,134 tonnes worth $6 million in March.</p>
<p>Mill owners had hoped to produce 2.65 million tonnes in 1996/97, but output had reached only 2.32 million by April 15 due to a shortage of sugarcane.</p>
<p>Qazilbash said production was likely to reach 2.38 million tonnes by the end of the year, compared to 2.47 million tonnes in 1995/96 and three million tonnes in 1994/95.</p>
<p>Sugar consumption is likely to rise to 2.85 million tonnes in 1997/98, up from an expected 2.7 million tonnes this year, he said. The forecast includes 1.8 million tonnes for domestic use, 900,000 tonnes for industry and 150,000 tonnes for Afghanistan.</p>
<p>-- Karachi newsroom 9221-5685192</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100136">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I42000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARACHI, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
