<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657336" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. CEOs urge caution on global climate policy.</title>
<headline>U.S. CEOs urge caution on global climate policy.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Paul</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>A group of the biggest U.S. corporations spent $1 million on an advertising blitz to raise concern about the White House plan to combat climate change, a spokeswoman for the Business Roundtable said Wednesday.</p>
<p>In three-page ads in the Wall Street Journal, Washington Post and other Washington publications, 130 chief executives from companies ranging from General Mills to General Motors urged the Clinton administration not to rush into an international treaty that could hurt the U.S. economy.</p>
<p>The administration is working on a proposal for a December summit in Kyoto, Japan, for a treaty that would set binding targets after 2000 on industrialized countries' emissions of carbon dioxide, which are believed to cause global warming.</p>
<p>Lawmakers, environmentalists and industry officials complain that six months ahead of a major treaty signing, they have not seen the administration's analyses of various policies to trim carbon emissions, nor do they know what targets or timetables it will propose.</p>
<p>In a clear message to Vice President Al Gore, who is taking the lead on climate change policy in the White House, the CEOs borrowed the title of his book &quot;Earth in the Balance&quot; in their ad urging the administration to broaden the debate on the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;How do you protect an earth in the balance? With a balanced approach,&quot; the ad said. &quot;But a balanced approach is only possible with careful study, input from a wide vareity of sources, and extensive public debate.&quot;</p>
<p>Industrial companies are concerned that moves to curb carbon emissions are going to require policies that discourage fossil fuel use, by raising the price of oil, gas and coal, encouraging use of different fuels and technologies, or requiring expensive new pollution curbs.</p>
<p>They argue that the costs of such policies would cripple the economies of industrialized countries, especially if developing countries do not have to adopt similar policies, as expected in the Kyoto treaty.</p>
<p>&quot;It's an international competitiveness issue. It would make us totally non-competitive,&quot; said Thomas Usher, chairman and CEO of USX Corp.</p>
<p>Usher said his message to Gore, a likely candidate for  the White House in 2000, would be: &quot;One of the things this past administration was elected on was an excellent economy.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;This is the type of thing that could be very damaging to the economy,&quot; he said in an interview.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton is scheduled to address the Business Roundtable Thursday, and will discuss climate change, among other topics, a White House official said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
