<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657458" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British Moslems hail tomato &quot;miracle message&quot;.</title>
<headline>British Moslems hail tomato &quot;miracle message&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Moslems on Thursday hailed what was described as a &quot;miracle message&quot; from God written inside a tomato.</p>
<p>When schoolgirl Shaista Javed, 14, sliced the tomato in half, she found the message spelled out in Arabic by its veins, British newspapers reported.</p>
<p>On one side she read &quot;There is only one God&quot;, while the other said &quot;Mohammed is the messenger&quot;.</p>
<p>Shaista, a Moslem, believes she has witnessed a miracle.</p>
<p>&quot;God made me buy that tomato,&quot; the Daily Mail quoted her as saying. &quot;These words are a message from God.&quot;</p>
<p>Since Sunday, when she bought the tomato in the northern city of Huddersfield, word has spread throughout the Moslem community. About 200 people, some from as far afield as London, have visited the household to see the fruit, wrapped in plastic clingfilm to keep it fresh.</p>
<p>A local shopkeeper said demand for tomatoes had surged, but the nearby mosque was cautious. &quot;We don't consider it a miracle but it is certainly a blessing,&quot; a spokesman was quoted as saying.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
