<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657441" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Princess Diana calls for worldwide landmine ban.</title>
<headline>Princess Diana calls for worldwide landmine ban.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Princess Diana on Thursday lashed out at countries which trade in landmines and called for an international ban on the hidden killers that blow up 25,000 people a year.</p>
<p>&quot;How can countries which manufacture and trade in these weapons square their conscience with such human devastation?&quot; she asked in an impassioned appeal to a London conference.</p>
<p>Diana, who has launched a high-profile campaign to help landmine victims around the globe, insisted her backing was not political, but humanitarian.</p>
<p>The princess, who toured war-ravaged Angola in January to meet some landmine victims, said: &quot;Since then, we are glad to see, some real progress has been made. There are indeed signs of a change of heart at least in some parts of the world.&quot;</p>
<p>Last month, Britain's new Labour government promised to destroy all Britain's anti-personnel mines by 2005, pursuing its pledge to put human rights at the centre of foreign policy.</p>
<p>Diana, briefed by British ministers on Wednesday in advance of a U.S. fund-raising gala for mine victims, argued that it was always the innocent that suffered.</p>
<p>&quot;These mines inflict most of their casualties on people who are trying to meet the elementary needs of life. They strike the wife or the grandmother gathering firewood for cooking. They ambush the child collecting water for the family.</p>
<p>&quot;One of my objectives in visiting Angola was to forward the cause of those, like the International Red Cross, striving in the name of humanity to secure an international ban on these weapons.&quot;</p>
<p>She said it would take generations to clear the scourge from the face of the earth.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if the world decided tomorrow to ban these weapons, this terrible legacy of mines already in the earth will continue to plague the poor nations of the globe. The evil men do lives after them.&quot;</p>
<p>Mines are blamed for killing 25,000 people a year and maiming thousands more. The Red Cross estimates there are 120 million mines around the world. Many are in poor, war-torn countries like Cambodia and Angola.</p>
<p>Diana, who is to attend a U.S. Red Cross fund-raising dinner in Washington on June 17, has been keen to adopt a new role as an unofficial &quot;Queen of Hearts&quot; ambassador for Britain since her divorce from heir to the throne Prince Charles.</p>
<p>This campaign has proved to be a political minefield for the princess with the British establishment prickling at the suggestion of her being a roaming ambassador at large.</p>
<p>The Foreign Office stressed Diana's visit to Washington was in a strictly private capacity. &quot;There is no question of the princess acting for the government,&quot; a spokesman said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
