<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657581" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Lawmakers close to deal on disaster aid legislation.</title>
<headline>Lawmakers close to deal on disaster aid legislation.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>Republicans moved closer to a deal on on Wednesday that would strip a disaster aid bill of contentious provisions opposed by the White House, with Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott predicting quick action on a scaled-down measure.</p>
<p>&quot;We're coming to closure ... we think we have the parameters of an agreement we can go with,&quot; the Mississippi Republican told reporters, saying a vote on a compromise bill was possible as early as Thursday. However negotiations had not produced agreement on a compromise in the House which must also pass the disaster bill.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton vetoed the $8.6 billion spending bill Monday and urged Congress to pass it again without political riders attached by Republicans to prevent a government shutdown this fall and to restrict the 2000 census to the traditional house-by-house count.</p>
<p>Barraged by negative press and hounded by lawmakers from flood-ravaged states, Republicans signalled they were willing to give in to many White House demands.</p>
<p>Lott said the compromise would cut the money bill by as much as a third from the $8.6 billion allocated for disaster aid, U.S. military operations overseas and other non-emergency government activities.</p>
<p>He said Republicans were willing to revise the two provisions that drew Clinton's veto.</p>
<p>Congress would vote on a separate bill to continue government funding for 45 days rather than the entire year in the event the White House and Congress could not agree on regular spending bills.</p>
<p>And, Republicans may also water down a provision that would have prevented the use of statistical sampling in the 2000 census to more accurately count minorities. House Republican aides said negotiators were considering a plan to require the White House issue a report on the census proposal.</p>
<p>While outside experts support sampling, Republicans fear increased minority representation could harm their political chances in dozens of House districts across the nation.</p>
<p>Senate Democrats Wednesday blocked legislation and prevented committees from meeting for a second day as they tried to persuade Republicans to release disaster funds.</p>
<p>Senate Democratic Leader Tom Daschle, bleary-eyed from an all-night talkathon to draw public attention to the plight of states waiting for the disaster aid, remained firm that no legislation would be voted on until the impasse was broken.</p>
<p>During what they called a &quot;vigil&quot; for disaster victims, 40 Democratic members of Congress met in Daschle's office until 6 a.m. to participate in interviews with more than 75 radio and television stations across the country.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't think when I came to the U.S. Senate I would be talking at 2 a.m. with 'The Trucking Bozo,'&quot; said Sen. Byron Dorgan, a Democrat from North Dakota, who was interviewed on a nationwide radio programme aimed at truck drivers.</p>
<p>Democrats originally wanted to keep the Senate in session all night but were blocked in that attempt. Instead, they refused to give permission for any legislation to be brought to the floor or to allow any committee to meet.</p>
<p>At least one senior Republican said it was time to negotiate with the White House. &quot;They've got the political leverage. They think they are winning the (public relations) battle, and perhaps they are,&quot; said John McCain of Arizona.</p>
<p>In the House, 20 moderate Republicans asked Speaker Newt Gingrich asking him to quickly bring a clean bill to a vote.</p>
<p>&quot;Over the past few weeks, the president and the Congress have participated in a game of rhetorical jousting, acting irresponsibly on this much-needed disaster relief bill,&quot; said the letter sponsored by Delaware Republican Representative Mike Castle.</p>
<p>The bill provided $5.4 billion for disaster assistance in 32 states plus North and South Dakota and Minnesota, which were reeling from the worst floods of the century.</p>
<p>What raised Democratic ire was a Republican rider to guarantee federal agencies funding at the 1997 level if the Republican-led Congress and the Democratic White House failed to agree by the Oct. 1 start of the fiscal year. The White House and congressional Democrats saw this as a strategem that would enable Republicans to prevail in spending disputes.</p>
<p>The original bill also would have provided $1.9 billion to pay for military operations in Bosnia and the Gulf.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
