<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657665" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Major campaign planned against inhalant abuse.</title>
<headline>Major campaign planned against inhalant abuse.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-11</dateline>
<text>
<p>The federal government and industry leaders will launch a national education campaign against America's &quot;silent epidemic&quot; -- teenage abuse of inhalants like glue, lighter fluid or propane -- on June 18.</p>
<p>Every month nearly half a million U.S. teenagers abuse or experiment with inhalants, sniffing concentrated fumes of common household products to get high, according to the National Inhalant Prevention Coalition.</p>
<p>But most news reports have focused on teen drug abuse rather than this epidemic, which can lead to long-term effects such as short term memory loss, hearing impairment, limb spasms, permanent brain damage, as well as sudden death.</p>
<p>The U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission, Partnership for a Drug Free America, and a group of industry leaders will unveil a major education campaign later this month to educate parents about the dangers of inhalant abuse, the coalition said.</p>
<p>The campaign will feature a new public service announcement featuring Deloris Jordan, mother of Chicago Bulls basketball star Michael Jordan, to be aired on television stations around the country.</p>
<p>The campaign would also include the results of a study on parents' awareness of inhalant abuse, and new information to be distributed by campaign participants.</p>
<p>According to the National Institute on Drug Abuse, more than one-in-five children abuse inhalants to get high before finishing high school, and inhalant abuse ranks third in use after alcohol and tobacco for children in first through seventh grade.</p>
<p>Young people in the 12-17 age group most commonly abuse gasoline and lighter fluid, followed by glue and toluene, while young adults in the 18-25 age group most commonly abuse nitrous oxide or &quot;whippets.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-11"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
