<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657699" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Kohl's government wins healthcare reform fight.</title>
<headline>Kohl's government wins healthcare reform fight.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chancellor Helmut Kohl's government mustered an absolute majority in the lower house of parliament on Thursday to overrule an upper house veto and pass a healthcare reform package into law.</p>
<p>The convincing 342-318 result showed that Kohl could still maintain discipline in his three-party centre-right coalition, which has squabbled bitterly in recent weeks over the separate issue of budget cuts.</p>
<p>The health reform, which takes effect on July 1, leaves it to health insurers to decide whether or not to pay for a range of &quot;optional&quot; treatments, mostly involving home care and rehabilitation.</p>
<p>The opposition Social Democrats (SPD), who say the new law will make health care more expensive, had used their upper house majority to block the bill, forcing the coalition to secure a majority of all sitting lower house deputies.</p>
<p>The measure provides for patients to pay a higher share of their own health costs in a bid to stem abuse and cut the spiralling costs of the German system, one of the world's most comprehensive.</p>
<p>Health workers have protested against the law, which they say will cost up to 100,000 jobs. Last year they handed Health Minister Horst Seehofer a petition with 1.2 million signatures opposing his proposals.</p>
<p>Seehofer says claims for treatments and therapies have ben rising much faster than medical needs.</p>
<p>&quot;A greater degree of self-responsibility is needed in order to finance the high level of care and medical advances in Germany,&quot; he told parliament before the vote. He said the law made special allowances for people with low incomes.</p>
<p>&quot;Even people who are chronically ill will not have to pay more than one percent of gross income,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But SPD health expert Rudolf Dressler retorted that &quot;the new motto of the government is -- those who are ill should pay for it themselves&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;In reality, the reform will not save the government a single mark,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
