<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657785" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Never a dull moment as Swiss army knife turns 100.</title>
<headline>Never a dull moment as Swiss army knife turns 100.</headline>
<byline>Alice Ratcliffe</byline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Swiss army knife, the all-purpose implement favoured by presidents, polar explorers, astronauts and millions of ordinary people reluctant to carry a tool box around with them, turned 100 on Thursday.</p>
<p>From humble beginnings as a pocket knife with six fold-out blades and tools, the implement has spawned dozens of ever more complex variations featuring gizmos designed to unclog car windscreen washer jets or remove a fish's scales.</p>
<p>Manufacturer Victorinox laconically calls the penknife, patented by cutlery maker Carl Elsener on June 12, 1897, a &quot;useful pocket tool&quot;, but the stories of its exploits are legion.</p>
<p>Last May, Hansjoerg Schwob, a Swiss policeman, was trapped in an attic of a customs office in Basle as he was looking for a meeting on a Friday afternoon when a door blew shut behind him.</p>
<p>&quot;I cried out, yelled, pounded and knocked, but it was all no use,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Luckily, his &quot;City Knife&quot; model was equipped with a screwdriver on the end of a fruit-peeler which quickly dismantled the lock.</p>
<p>In another incident, a Swiss army knife was successfully used as a scalpel for an emergency tracheotomy on a child choking on a hard candy on a flight from Bombay to Bangalore.</p>
<p>American astronauts on the space shuttle use the knives.</p>
<p>During an expedition to the North Pole in 1976/77, explorer Charles Burton found his knife invaluable for more than just de-icing sleigh runners and opening tins.</p>
<p>&quot;When one of our team broke through the ice, we were able to cut off his clothes with the knife,&quot; he wrote in an account of the expedition. If his clothes, rapidly freezing at minus 37 Celsius, had not been cut off, he would probably have died rapidly.</p>
<p>Some 34,000 Swiss army knives leave the Victorinox factory in Ibach in central Switzerland daily. Its 950 staff make it the biggest employer in the regional canton of Schywz.</p>
<p>The company, named after Elsener's mother Victoria and &quot;Inox&quot;, a designation for stainless steel, is now run by the founder's grandson, Carl Elsener III, aged 75.</p>
<p>Elsener's classic six-tool red knife, emblazoned with the Swiss cross trademark, sports a large and a small blade, a can opener, a bottle opener, a corkscrew, and an awl with a hole for sewing.</p>
<p>&quot;Our knives are not intended as weapons,&quot; said Hans Schorno, spokesman for Victorinox.</p>
<p>Other models feature scissors, magnifying glasses, saws, rulers, pliers or fish-scaling implements, right up to the &quot;Swiss Champ&quot;, the most luxurious of around 100 models, which has 33 blades and tools.</p>
<p>Over 450 steps are required in its manufacture. It weighs 185 grams and was included in the New York Museum of Modern Art's collection of excellence in design.</p>
<p>A commemorative centenary edition is also being produced.</p>
<p>Victorinox says every U.S. president since Lyndon Johnson has presented guests to the White House with its knives, making use of perhaps their most appreciated function of all, as a souvenir.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
