<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="657857" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French Communist to wear overalls to parliament.</title>
<headline>French Communist to wear overalls to parliament.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A newly-elected French Communist deputy said he would wear blue overalls to the first session of parliament on Thursday to symbolise his working class roots.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a symbol to show that...I am the only working class deputy starting this session, so I represent 70 percent of the French people who are in the same position as me as wage earners,&quot; Patrice Carvalho told France Info radio.</p>
<p>A mechanic who works at a French glassmakers, Carvalho said the National Assembly had many graduates from elite schools, civil servants or teachers, even though &quot;they are not the essence of our nation.&quot;</p>
<p>Carvalho, 45, was one of 38 Communists elected to the 577-member Assembly in a Socialist-led victory last week. Male deputies usually wear dark suits in the Assembly.</p>
<p>The new Assembly was holding its first session at 3 p.m. (1300 GMT) on Thursday, with former Socialist prime minister Laurent Fabius set to be elected speaker.</p>
<p>Former Socialist culture minister Jack Lang caused a sensation in the 1980s by turning up to the Assembly dressed in a plain Chinese suit popularised by late chairman Mao Zedong.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
