<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658053" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Japanese fish market lures Australia.</title>
<headline>Japanese fish market lures Australia.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>A major Australian government report into the huge Japanese import market highlights the US$8.28 billion market for imported fish, shrimp and prawn as an area where Australia could tap big demand.</p>
<p>Australia's food exports to Japan are presently dominated by the exports of beef (worth US$1.24 billion in 1995), raw sugar (US$253.8 million) and wheat (US$250.8 million).</p>
<p>But Japan's total imports of shrimp and prawns, worth US$3.94 billion in 1995, of bonito and tuna, worth US$2.01 billion, and of processed fish, worth $2.34 billion in the same year, are together worth almost three times the country's imported beef market of US$3.26 billion, the report shows.</p>
<p>The report, A New Japan? Change in Asia's Megamarket, emphasises Australia's low market share in processed fish.</p>
<p>In 1995, Australia exported only US$34.1 million worth of processed fish, US$134.1 million worth of shrimps and prawns and US$64.5 million worth of tuna to Japan.</p>
<p>Fish and prawns are just two big Japanese markets --- although very notable examples --- which Australian agricultural commodities could tap, the report says.  </p>
<p>In 1995 Australia supplied only US$4.6 million worth of exports to a US$1.24 billion Japanese imported vegetable, roots and tubers market. It exported only US$13.4 million of preserved fruits and foods to a total Japanese import market of US$854.2 million. And it exported only US$1.2 million to a US$315.9 million non-alcoholic beverages (mainly mineral water) market.</p>
<p>&quot;Australia could improve substantially its exports of fish, vegetables, roots and tubers, preserved fruit and foods and non-alcoholic beverages,&quot; said the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade's (DFAT) East Asia Analytical Unit.  </p>
<p>Japanese processed foods markets where Australian exports are performing well are fruit and vegetable juices (US$46.7 million Australian exports in total Japanese imports of US$538.9 million), chocolate and other foods containing cocoa (US$37.5 million in total imports of US$319.3 million), malt (US$54.3 million in imports of US$300.0 million) and alcoholic beverages (US$16.8 million in imports of US$1.96 billion).</p>
<p>The DFAT report closely follows a report by the Australian government's official commodity forecasting group, the Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics (ABARE), into Australian aquaculture.  </p>
<p>This report said aquaculture was a rapidly-growing Australian industry, now accounting for 25 percent of Australia's fisheries production.</p>
<p>But Australia remained a relatively small producer in world prawn aquaculture, with Thailand the world's largest producer. Thailand has a market share of 27 percent of world farmed prawn production, followed by Indonesia on 19 percent, the Philippines 12 percent, China 11 percent, and Ecuador 11 percent.</p>
<p>Of the two prawn species farmed in Australia, black tiger and kuruma prawns, Australia contributed less than one percent of total world supplies of 443,128 tonnes, it said.  </p>
<p>In 1995, Japan imported 172 tonnes of Australian prawns in total imports of 474 tonnes of live prawns, with China the leading supplier, the study showed.</p>
<p>Total Australian agrifood exports to Japan in 1995 amounted to US$3.23 billion, with Australia ranking as Japan's largest foreign supplier of sugar, dairy foods and rice, its second-largest supplier of beef, cattle and canola and its third largest supplier of meat, wheat and other food products.</p>
<p>DFAT officials who prepared the Japan report said they were not aware of structural or other difficulties which would bar Australia supplying Japan's big fish and prawn markets.  </p>
<p>-- Michael Byrnes, Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
