<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658060" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FOCUS-Drought fears grip Australian agri-trade.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Drought fears grip Australian agri-trade.</headline>
<byline>Michael Byrnes</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's agricultural commodity trade remains dominated by fear that the strongest El Nino weather pattern since 1983 will cut rural production or depress prices over the next two years.</p>
<p>The impact of drought from the El Nino, which Australia's weather bureau has said will persist and strengthen throughout 1997, would involve all major crops and rural industries, producers, brokers and industry officials told Reuters.  </p>
<p>An official with a state grain marketing board, who asked not to be named, discounted the entire range of recent 1997/98 forecasts by the government's Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics (ABARE) because of the El Nino threat.</p>
<p>ABARE forecasts of 19.2 million tonne of wheat, 883,000 tonnes of canola and 2.11 million tonnes of oilseeds overall were all &quot;very optimistic&quot; if drought occurred, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Canola tends to be in safer country (than other crops), but that'll be devastated as well,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>ABARE officials said on Wednesday that ABARE's forecasts did not take account of the possibility of an El Nino drought.  </p>
<p>Bob Quirk, executive director of the Australian Council of Wool Exporters, said the quality and quantity of Australian wool could fall significantly in 1998/99 because of El Nino drought.</p>
<p>An El Nino drought would be &quot;a really significant negative&quot; in wool's ability to meet increasing demand, he said.</p>
<p>Drought affects wool because the quality of the fibre depends on &quot;what goes down the sheep's throat&quot;, Quirk said. Drought-affected wool was finer than usual because of light or interrupted feeding by the sheep, but was of lesser strength and therefore of reduced processing value, he said.  </p>
<p>Current wool was being produced in good conditions but drought would affect 1998/99 production, he said.</p>
<p>Cattle and beef also face bleak times if Australia is plunged back into drought. The Australian beef industry was definitely concerned about the prospect of another drought, Richard Koch, economist with the government's meat industry statutory authority Australian Meat and Livestock Corp, said.</p>
<p>Beef had just emerged from a severe early 1990s drought and had had sustained dryness in southern areas this year.</p>
<p>&quot;To see another long-term period of dryness would have substantial ramifications,&quot; Koch said.  </p>
<p>Australia's herd-building ambition would be eliminated.</p>
<p>Initial signs of the El Nino could perhaps be already seen in southern Australia, where a prolonged dry period had depressed cattle prices through forced sales, he said.</p>
<p>While canola production in New South Wales would be hit hard by drought, oilseed production in the northern east-side state of Queensland was likely to escape harm from El Nino drought, an official with Queensland's grains co-operative Grainco said.  </p>
<p>Queensland oilseed is mainly produced from the summer crop of sunflowers, which are planted late in the calendar year and harvested up to half way through the next year. This meant they would escape El Nino devastation, the official said.</p>
<p>But Australian wheat futures trading on Thursday remained dominated by fear that an El Nino drought loomed, brokers said.</p>
<p>The Australian Bureau of Meteorology, which on June 3 issued warnings about the prospect of a serious and worsening El Nino effect, is treating the weather pattern very seriously.  </p>
<p>A four-page research paper by the bureau highlights a close correlation between Southern Oscillation Index (SOI) values and Australian wheat yields.</p>
<p>The SOI measures major air pressure shifts between the Asian and east Pacific regions, with negative values associated with dry conditions.</p>
<p>El Nino weather effects, which flow from warm sea surface temperatures off the South American coast which then interact with atmospheric conditions, are a dry weather extreme of the SOI range, the Bureau of Metrorology said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
