<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658137" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: FEATURE-HK &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot; first meant for Oklah.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-HK &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot; first meant for Oklah.</headline>
<byline>Justin Jin</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pain contorts</p>
<p>the 50 or so faces depicted in Hong Kong's &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot;, a focus for China democracy campaigners, but something else catches the eye.</p>
<p>Bystanders are puzzled, because the writhing victims mainly do not resemble Asians, raising a question whether the Danish artist had China in mind when he carved features that he says symbolise oppression by Beijing.</p>
<p>Banned from Hong Kong's public parks in the weeks before the handover to Beijing's rule, the &quot;Pillar of Shame&quot; has been praised and denounced here as an artistic political symbol.</p>
<p>It became a centre-piece of this year's Tiananmen massacre commemoration in Hong Kong, which drew 55,000 people to a candle-lit vigil, amid concern about the future of civil liberties under Chinese rule.</p>
<p>The statue, excluded from civic areas by legislators who called it &quot;terrible&quot; and lacking in beauty, has been permitted to stand for two weeks on an isolated university campus after demands by student demonstrators.</p>
<p>In a strange irony, it now seems that this icon for current anti-China protests was once meant for Oklahoma City in the United States, target of a terrorist attack that fearful Americans originally blamed on foreign groups.</p>
<p>According to the 43-year-old artist Jens Galschiot, of Odense, the eight-metre (26 feet) grey tower of twisted bodies was built for Oklahoma City after a bomb in a federal government building killed 168 people in April, 1995.</p>
<p>OKLAHOMA CITY WAS FIRST CHOICE</p>
<p>&quot;Oklahoma City was the first choice,&quot; he said in an interview. &quot;I was afraid if I put a political sculpture in Asia people might see me as imperialist with double standards.&quot;</p>
<p>Galschiot used fewer than eight Oriental models for the pillar, with the others mostly Europeans.</p>
<p>Some Hong Kong residents have wondered why the Pillar contained so many Caucasian-looking faces.</p>
<p>This was the second of up to 20 such pillars he wanted to make and place all over the world, the next one being in Russia's war-torn Chechnya region. The first one was an exhibition piece in Rome.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pillar of Shame is about the discussions of the right wing in the United States that produce the kind of people who bomb their own people,&quot; Galschiot said.</p>
<p>Defence attorneys for the convicted bomber Timothy McVeigh, who may face the death penalty for the Oklahoma attack, say the ex-soldier thought the U.S. government was at war with the American people.</p>
<p>When Galschiot found the U.S. government had already commissioned another piece for Oklahoma, he then considered Hong Kong, the British colony on the southern edge of China, as a site for his political artwork.</p>
<p>Now, just weeks before July 1, when China retakes Hong Kong, the sculpture is hailed here as a symbol of the June 4, 1989 Tiananmen massacre by Chinese soldiers of hundreds of pro-democracy students.</p>
<p>ORIGINS AROUSE MIXED FEELINGS</p>
<p>&quot;I do not think (initial intentions to put the sculpture in Oklahoma) would affect the symbolism because Galschiot said he would send it to wherever there is suppression of human rights,&quot; said Szeto Wah, leader of the Hong Kong Alliance in support of Patriotic Democratic Movements in China.</p>
<p>Democrats and hundreds of Hong Kong students who fought for a home for the sculpture in Hong Kong's public area may have different feelings.</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that the pillar was intended for Oklahoma makes us feel betrayed,&quot; said one Hong Kong University activist.</p>
<p>Hong Kong University officials overturned an earlier ban and agreed to allow the sculpture on campus for two weeks, after about 500 students protested when authorities blocked its way.</p>
<p>Civic authorities refused to allow the sculpture to remain in public parks after a brief appearance on June 4.</p>
<p>Some art critics have reservations about the pillar. &quot;I do not think this is great art because it is very sensational, but it uses the event very successfully,&quot; Lau Kin Wai, a freelance art commmentator, said.</p>
<p>The fibre-clay sculpture, which cost HK$1 million (US$128,000), is not for sale --&quot;It is a gift to the Chinese people.&quot;</p>
<p>Galschiot, whose birthday coincides with the Tiananmen anniversary, says: &quot;This was my best birthday, because the candle light vigil was the strongest demonstration I have ever seen,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
