<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658215" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Five green mice seen as cancer breakthrough.</title>
<headline>Five green mice seen as cancer breakthrough.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>By injecting genes with protein from fluorescent jellyfish, Japanese scientists have produced mice that glow green under artificial light, an achievement they term a breakthrough for cancer and transplant research.</p>
<p>Five of the mice were born earlier this week at Osaka University's Microbiology Disease Research Institute and could open the way for the technology to be used to trace cells in laboratory animals without surgery. a researcher at the centre said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;This would not only aid in cancer treatment and organ transplants but can be widely used in biotechnology in general,&quot; said the researcher, a member of a team headed by Assistant Professor Masaru Okabe, who announced the results.</p>
<p>The technique involves injecting green fluorescent protein taken from the DNA of a North American glowing jellyfish called Aequorea Victoria, into genes of laboratory mice.</p>
<p>The researcher said the mice appeared green if light, such as that from a torch, was shone on them.</p>
<p>In the past, such protein injections into genes were only possible with certain insects and fish, not mammals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32040">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
