<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658333" id="root" date="1997-06-12" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Cheers! Correspondents club braces for HK handover.</title>
<headline>Cheers! Correspondents club braces for HK handover.</headline>
<byline>Kurt Schork</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>The address has changed many times over the decades but Hong Kong's Foreign Correspondents' Club never lost its reputation as a world-class watering hole for reporters brimming with inside information, fierce opinions and tales of derring-do.</p>
<p>Crowded round the club's race track-shaped bar on a Friday evening are some of Asia's greatest reporters, their numbers swelled by a huge influx of foreign correspondents temporaily assigned to Hong Kong to cover the territory's handover from Britain to China at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>Also well-represented are the city's public relations and advertising communities, writers and artists, thirsty officers of the nearly-demobilised British garrison and, it is rumoured, the occasional intelligence agent nursing contacts and cruising for information.</p>
<p>Snatches of conversation in English, Mandarin and Cantonese float above the din as one regular tells the story of a Wan Chai bar girl by the name of Ling Ling whom he swears bore a tattoo which read &quot;God Bless the Shropshire Light Infantry&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;When I used to work for the government here, I avoided getting drunk nn Friday nights,&quot; explained Hong Kong historian Arthur Hacker as he leaned into the bar with a vodka and soda. &quot;It was my policy never to be hung over in my own time.&quot;</p>
<p>So sparkling are the club's atmosphere and characters that the Foreign Correspondents' Club, or FCC as it is ubiquitously known here, is fabled in film and novel.</p>
<p>&quot;Love Is A Many Splendoured Thing&quot;, with William Holden and Jennifer Jones, was shot in the elegant mansion which served as the club's Hong Kong headquarters in the 1950's.</p>
<p>John le Carre borrowed from the FCC and its members in writing &quot;The Honourable Schoolboy.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The loo with a view&quot; of Hong Kong harbour on the top floor of the club's old Sutherland House headquarters found its way into le Carre's espionage thriller and he used flamboyant London Sunday Times correspondent and FCC stalwart Dick Hughes as his model for the M16 agent Old Craw.</p>
<p>Ian Fleming also had a go with Hughes as Dikko Henderson in &quot;You Only Live Twice.&quot;</p>
<p>The real life adventures of some FCC members would give even the most inventive novelists a run for their money.</p>
<p>Former Reuters correspondent Graham Jenkins had been served his last meal, wrote his will and was about to be executed for &quot;rumour mongering&quot; by Nationalist Chinese troops in Shanghai in 1949 when he won a last-minute reprieve from the nationalist leader General Chiang Kai-Shek.</p>
<p>Jenkins, who died early this year, credited his rescue to FCC members in Shanghai who had intervened with the General to secure his release.</p>
<p>FCC doyenne Clare Hollingworth reported the German advance into Poland for the Sunday Telegraph at the start of World War Two. Jon Swain, who currently writes for the Sunday Times, was on the spot in Phnom Penh when the Khmer Rouge took over.</p>
<p>UPI's Hubert van Es was shot down twice during the Vietnam war and took the icon photograph of an American helicopter crewman helping to evacuate civilians from the roof of a building in Saigon in the waning days of the conflict.</p>
<p>Sandra Burton of Time chronicled Ferdinand Marcos' fall from power in the Philippines and BBC's James Miles reported live from Tiananmen Square.</p>
<p>In a way history has finally caught up with one of the world's most interesting press clubs. When Britain hands Hong Kong back to China at midnight on June 30 it will be the consummation of a bitter-sweet affair between the FCC and the mainland stretching back over half a century.</p>
<p>Founded by a handful of Western war reporters on the mainland in Chungking in 1943, the club moved to Nanking after Japanese occupation forces surrendered at the end of World War Two and then on to Shanghai where it wrested control of the top floors of an 18-storey tower block from the U.S. Air Force.</p>
<p>As communist troops advanced south during the Chinese civil war in 1949 the club moved out ahead of them, first to Canton and then to Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Having recorded the defeat of the Japanese, the fall of Chiang Kai-shek and the rise of Mao, wars in Korea, Vietnam and Cambodia and the massacre at Tiananmen Square, FCC members can be expected to take the handover in stride, another deadline, then up to the club bar for toasts and tall tales.</p>
<p>While its members chronicle daily developments in Asia the FCC is also buffeted by winds of change. Some in the club wonder whether the photographs hanging on its walls of Chinese army tanks in Tiananmen Square will survive the Hong Kong handover.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I66100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-12"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
