<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658697" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: FEATURE-S.AFRICA BATTLES INVASION OF ALIEN WATER-SNATCHERS.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-S.AFRICA BATTLES INVASION OF ALIEN WATER-SNATCHERS.</headline>
<byline>Anton Ferreira</byline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bands of destitute South Africans are roaming some of the country's most beautiful landscapes, ruthlessly hacking down thousands of trees.</p>
<p>But environmentalists are happy, so happy they are paying the hackers to do it.</p>
<p>For the trees they are targetting are bad trees, rapacious alien invaders that are sucking dry pristine streams and rivers, driving out indigenous plants and encouraging soil erosion.</p>
<p>The invaders -- eucalyptus, pines, wattles and other species from across the world -- were introduced over the centuries for commercial and ornamental use.</p>
<p>But, liberated from the natural pests that controlled their numbers at home, the trees proliferated in South Africa, spreading across mountain sides and choking river courses.</p>
<p>Many nature lovers have long considered the aliens a blight, but it was after the African National Congress took office in 1994 that South Africa's army of unemployed were offered the chance to make a living by chopping them down.</p>
<p>Scientists persuaded Water Affairs and Forestry Minister Kader Asmal that the invader trees were one of the worst culprits in wasting the arid country's sparse water resources.</p>
<p>&quot;A GREEN CANCER&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;People often view trees and forests as good,&quot; said Caroline Gelderblom, an ecologist with the state-funded Council for Scientific and Industrial Research.</p>
<p>&quot;But the exotics form thickets under which absolutely nothing grows. We almost view it as a green cancer, where the alien plants flood out the natural vegetation and form a dense stand and don't allow anything to grow underneath,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The alien trees are much bigger than the native species they supplant, so they use more water -- a big Australian gum tree can suck up 120 litres a day.</p>
<p>&quot;Put a whole lot of those next to a river, and the river will dry up,&quot; Gelderblom said.</p>
<p>The sheer size and weight of alien vegetation also causes major problems when bush fires start.</p>
<p>&quot;Fires, which are an integral part of our ecosystem, get a lot more intense,&quot; Gelderblom said.</p>
<p>&quot;The intensity of the fire sterilises the top layer of seeds in the soil, inhibiting regeneration, and drives an impervious layer down into the soil, so it makes it more difficult for water to soak in,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;So you find very devastating destruction after fire has gone through a stand of alien plants...Fire plus aliens are not a good combination.&quot;</p>
<p>FROM SUPER PLANTS TO THE LIVING DEAD</p>
<p>Gelderblom said the aliens were transformed into &quot;super plants&quot; once they were removed from their natural habitat and transplanted in South Africa.</p>
<p>&quot;These exotic plants don't have any enemies here, so of the thousands of seeds each plant produces, almost all will survive,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>To boost mortality among aliens, South Africa has imported the insect pests that prey on them at home, with dramatic success in some cases.</p>
<p>&quot;Acacia saligna we view as the living dead because biocontrol has been so effective,&quot; Gelderblom said, referring to an Australian species that was widespread in the region around Cape Town.</p>
<p>Now vast stands of the trees are dying, but some farmers are unhappy because they used the leaves for animal fodder and the wood for fuel.</p>
<p>The same argument applies to the American prosopis species, also known as mesquite.</p>
<p>&quot;It is being used as a fodder plant here, but it's having a very severe affect and it's spreading very rapidly,&quot; Gelderblom said. &quot;One may have to evaluate whether it's justified to plant it as a fodder plant in view of its damage to the environment and water.&quot;</p>
<p>The programme to physically chop down aliens was launched 18 months ago. In the first six months, 33,000 hectares (82,000 acres) were cleared, saving the country 17.5 million cubic metres of water.</p>
<p>NOW A RIVER RUNS THROUGH IT</p>
<p>&quot;In specific areas where we're operating projects we've had a tremendous impact,&quot; Gelderblom said.</p>
<p>&quot;You literally see the dams filling and the streams start flowing. It's very exciting. In some areas, they've cleared the area and there's been a dry river bed and the next day there's a trickle and after a month they had to build a bridge.&quot;</p>
<p>The project has combined the aims of saving water and natural vegetation with that of creating jobs, a priority in a country where around a third of the workforce is unemployed.</p>
<p>About 7,000 people -- many of them women or youths -- have found employment in the project countrywide.</p>
<p>The annual budget for the programme has been increased from 25 million rand ($5.6 million) when it started to about 100 million rand for the current financial year.</p>
<p>Half the funds come from new water tariffs imposed on users specifically to help pay for management of catchment areas.</p>
<p>&quot;To clear all the aliens in the country, we're looking at at least 2 billion rand, if not more,&quot; Gelderblom said, adding that the programme would have to run for 15 to 20 years.</p>
<p>&quot;We've modelled the effect that aliens have had on South Africa's water supply, and the results show we don't really have a choice, we have to do something,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
