<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658875" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: Japan loses endangered species vote on whale link.</title>
<headline>Japan loses endangered species vote on whale link.</headline>
<byline>Emelia Sithole</byline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan, pushing to ease a world ban on commercial whaling, lost on Friday a controversial vote to delink a convention on international trade in endangered species from the International Whaling Commission.</p>
<p>Delegates at the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) meeting in Harare said the conference rejected 51 to 27 in a secret ballot a resolution by Japan to make CITES independent of the International Whaling Commission (IWC) which slapped a moratorium on commercial whaling in 1986.</p>
<p>Japan, supported by Norway which is also seeking permission to resume commercial whaling, was seeking to delink CITES from the IWC, alleging the convention was automatically adopting the commission's measures to protect the whale without taking into account other independent findings on the issue.</p>
<p>It alleges that the IWC has been hijacked by some leading environmental groups with undue political influence.</p>
<p>&quot;It's impossible to win resumption of whaling for as long as CITES continues basing its decisions on that of the IWC,&quot; said Masayuki Komatsu, senior deputy director of Japan's Far Seas division and Oceanic Fisheries department.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a dilemma in achieving our goals in the IWC because it's now a body occupied by environmental groups which deny any sustainable use of natural resources,&quot; he told Reuters at the 10-day Harare conference which ends on June 20.</p>
<p>Leading environment groups applauded the meeting's decision, saying it showed that CITES was firmly coupled to the IWC and was unlikely to change its stance on whaling unless the IWC acted otherwise.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's (the Japanese and Norwegian proposal on whaling going to fail particularly because of what happened today...&quot; said Michael Sutton, director of the British-based World Wide Fund for Nature's Endangered Seas Campaign.</p>
<p>&quot;CITES sent a clear signal today that they won't change their stance on whaling until the IWC acts otherwise,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>The 139-nation CITES votes on the two countries' proposals at the end of the conference.</p>
<p>Sutton and Amsterdam-based Greenpeace's Isabel McCrea, however said they were disappointed at the conference's rejection -- in another secret ballot also pushed by Japan -- of a United States proposal to set up a CITES working group on marine fish.</p>
<p>The working group was aimed at addressing practical issues associated with the listing of commercially valuable marine fish and invertebrae species on CITES appendices.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
