<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="658920" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Nigerian folklore writer Amos Tutuola dies at 77.</title>
<headline>Nigerian folklore writer Amos Tutuola dies at 77.</headline>
<dateline>LAGOS 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nigerian folklore writer Amos Tutuola, who wrote several novels in his own peculiar English language, has died at the age of 77, newspapers said on Friday.</p>
<p>The independent Guardian said Tutuola died last Sunday in the southwestern Nigerian city of Ibadan. He had suffered for a long time from hypertension and diabetes.</p>
<p>Nigerian playwright Femi Osofisan of the University of Ibadan said Tutuola's death was a great loss to literature.</p>
<p>&quot;I take it as another milestone in the passing away of that remarkable generation of extremely talented and profound individuals, which I refer to as the action group generation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tutuola had only basic education but made a name in the literary world writing a series of novels in the 1950s and 60s published by Faber and Faber of London.</p>
<p>Among his most celebrated works were The Palmwine Drinkard and My Life in the Bush of Ghosts, which were also adapted into plays.</p>
<p>&quot;He wrote English as best as he knows it and 'The Palmwine Drinkard' is a classic which told the story of village life in Nigeria poignantly,&quot; said Nigerian translator Buki Jukwey.</p>
<p>&quot;He translated his native language Yoruba literally into English in his writings,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Born in 1920 in Abeokuta, southwestern Nigeria, Tutuola attended the Salvation Army School in Lagos. Before coming to the limelight as a writer he was a trainee blacksmith and served in the Royal Air Force in Lagos during the second world war.</p>
<p>He worked variously as messenger in the Lagos labour office, storekeeper and later as a clerk in then Nigerian Broadcasting Corporation, now the Federal Radio Corporation of Nigeria.</p>
<p>&quot;His works are African classics because they deal in folklores which are uniquely presented in refreshing idoms, imagery and similes that are truly African,&quot; said Remi Adedokun, a theatre arts lecturer at University of Ibadan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAGOS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
