<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659292" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Manila halt of agriculture imports to hit economy.</title>
<headline>Manila halt of agriculture imports to hit economy.</headline>
<byline>Dolly Aglay</byline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Philippine court order stopping imports of agricultural products at lower tariff rates would push up food prices, officials and analysts said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The court order has far reaching implication because some sectors of the agricultural sector like meat processors have to bring frozen beef at higher tariffs if the issue is not resolved,&quot; said Ramon Clarete, economist at the University of the Philippines.</p>
<p>The Manila Regional Trial Court, in a ruling on June 5, restrained Agriculture Secretary Salvador Escudero from implementing an order in 1996 setting regulations on the minimum volume of annual farm products imports.</p>
<p>Philippine imports on agricultural products are part of the country's commitment to the World Trade organisation (WTO).</p>
<p>The court's decision was in response to a petition filed by the Philippine Federation of Food Industries Inc which represents traders and commodities importers. The group said the benefits of lower tariffs were available only to existing players, which meant new entrants were shut out.</p>
<p>&quot;We need to resolve this immediately, otherwise our trading partners will file a case against us,&quot; Clarete said.</p>
<p>Even before the Philippine court issued a restraining order on agricultural imports, U.S. meat producers had complained that Manila was blocking fair market access to U.S. pork.</p>
<p>Manila denied the charge, saying imports were low because Filipinos did not like the taste of frozen pork.</p>
<p>The court order will affect additional imports of corn, beef, pork, chicken and sugar, Agriculture officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;This (court order) is an economic sabotage,&quot; an official of the Philippine Association of Meat Processors (PAMPI) said.</p>
<p>PAMPI said its members will have to spend 300 million pesos in additional tariff for its annual 42,000 tonnes imports of frozen beef if the court order is not lifted.</p>
<p>The government had earlier approved importation of 57,054 tonnes of frozen beef at 30 percent tariff under the minimum access volume (MAV) scheme.</p>
<p>PAMPI members, who sought licenses for the import of 42,000 tonnes frozen beef imports early this year, asked the government to import an additional 29,000 tonnes under the MAV for the rest of 1997.</p>
<p>If the proposed additional frozen beef imports are not included under the MAV, meat processors have to bring the beef at 60 percent tariff, an official of PAMPI told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Higher raw material costs mean higher food prices,&quot; the PAMPI official said.</p>
<p>&quot;This will put us again in very difficult situation since we compete with canned goods pouring out from duty free shops.&quot;</p>
<p>Poultry and livestock farmers said the court order would further delay their proposal to the government to import an additional 300,000 tonnes of yellow corn because of a local shortage.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we have to buy corn on our own- even at high tariffs,&quot; said a local poultry firm executive.</p>
<p>Market talk was that hog raisers planned to import at least 25,000 tonnes of yellow corn at 80 percent tariff for July.</p>
<p>Corn imports under the MAV are slapped a 35 percent tariff.</p>
<p>But traders said even at 80 percent tariff on imported yellow corn prices are still cheaper compared to domestic prices.</p>
<p>-- Manila newsroom (632) 841 8936</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
