<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659399" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. warns Turkish army to respect constitution.</title>
<headline>U.S. warns Turkish army to respect constitution.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Worsnip</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States fired a shot across the bows of the Turkish military on Friday, warning army leaders against &quot;extra-constitutional&quot; attempts to combat growing Islamic influence in Turkey.</p>
<p>But Secretary of State Madeleine Albright also reaffirmed strong U.S. support for a secular system in Turkey, the goal to which Turkish military leaders say they are attached.</p>
<p>Turkey's chief of military intelligence, Gen. Fevzi Turkeri, urged Turks on Wednesday to fight the danger of Islamic activism and said the army's role was to protect the country &quot;by force of arms&quot; from domestic and external threats.</p>
<p>&quot;We obviously are watching and have been watching the situation very carefully,&quot; Albright told reporters before talks with Latvian Foreign Minister Valdis Birkavs.</p>
<p>&quot;We have made very clear that it is essential that Turkey continue in a secular, democratic way,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have also made clear that it's very important that whatever issues are going on there, whatever discussions and whatever changes people are thinking about, that they have to be within a democratic context and with no extra-constitutional approach.&quot;</p>
<p>But Albright added: &quot;We appreciate the way that Turkey has in fact been a secular democracy.&quot;</p>
<p>Turkey has an Islamic-led government under Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan. But the administration, riven by internal dissent, appears close to collapse.</p>
<p>Erbakan has said he will step down in favour of his conservative coalition partner Tansu Ciller, perhaps as early as next week, and go for snap elections.</p>
<p>While continuing to hail Turkey as a valued NATO ally, Washington has viewed Erbakan with thinly disguised distaste, especially since he visited Libya last year. Officials make clear in private a strong preference for Ciller.</p>
<p>But Turkeri's remarks, which received major coverage Friday in the New York Times and Washington Post, appear to have raised fears in Washington of another military intervention in Turkish politics.</p>
<p>State Department spokesman Nicholas Burns said Albright had chosen her words carefully at what he called &quot;a very difficult time for Turkey.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's prudent for us to remind everyone at a time like this that the basis of Turkey's success as a country in the last decade or so has been its democratic tradition and its secular tradition,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;Certainly, the military has a role to play in Turkish political life, if you look at the Turkish constitution and look at Turkish history,&quot; Burns said.</p>
<p>But, he said: &quot;We believe that the democratic institutions of Turkey ought to be allowed to function according to the Turkish constitution. We are confident that will take place.&quot;</p>
<p>Burns said Deputy Secretary of State Strobe Talbott had dicussed the Turkish military's role in political life with Gen. Cevik Bir, second-in-command of the armed forces, and political leaders during a visit to Ankara this month.</p>
<p>He gave no details.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
