<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659377" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: New dinosaur king reigns in U.S. museum.</title>
<headline>New dinosaur king reigns in U.S. museum.</headline>
<byline>Randall Mikkelsen</byline>
<dateline>PHILADELPHIA 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The usurper to the title &quot;King of the Dinosaurs&quot; took its place of honour in a Philadelphia museum on Friday and left T. rex skulking in the background.</p>
<p>The first reconstructed skeleton of a giganotosaurus, a fearsome, flesh-ripping predator whose bones were discovered in Argentina in 1993, went on display at the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.</p>
<p>The dinosaur was an estimated 45-47 feet (14 metres) long and weighed about eight tonnes when it roamed what is now South America about 100 million years ago. It eclipses Tyrannosaurus rex as the largest meat-eating dinosaur ever known.</p>
<p>&quot;It deserves that title,&quot; museum paleontologist Ted Daeschler said of the new dinosaur. &quot;That's hard to talk about scientifically but certainly in the public eye,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The giganotosaurus skeleton -- a resin casting of the fossil bones, which remain in Argentina -- is on permanent display, looming over the ticket counter in the academy's entry hall.</p>
<p>Its rear legs are spread in a stalking stance and its head is low on an outstretched neck, as if looking for something to gobble.</p>
<p>Nearby in the museum's dinosaur hall is the T. rex skeleton, still imposing but now looking like a younger -- by about 30 million years -- sibling of the new attraction.</p>
<p>The two dinosaurs were roughly similar in appearance, with tall rear legs, tiny forelegs, large heads and big teeth.</p>
<p>But the giganotosaurus, whose name means &quot;giant southern reptile,&quot; had three fingers or toes on each limb, compared with T. rex's two.</p>
<p>Its head was relatively narrow, and it had daggerlike teeth, as opposed to the wider skull and conical, bone-crushing teeth of T. rex.</p>
<p>Scientists speculate that T. rex was a scavenger, while the giganotosaurus hunted live prey, possibly even the 100-foot-long (30-metre-long) plant-eating dinosaurs it lived alongside.</p>
<p>&quot;You have potentially two different lifestyles here,&quot; Phelan Fretz, the museum's director, said.</p>
<p>The dinosaurs were members of different families and were widely separated by age and geography. T. rex lived around 65 million years ago and lorded it over North America.</p>
<p>The gap makes their superficial similarity all the more interesting, Daeschler said. &quot;It was a successful design,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Asked a question certain to seize the imagination of many dinosaur fans -- which of the beasts would prevail in a clash of the titans? -- Fretz and Daeschler offered differing opinions.</p>
<p>Daeschler said T. rex, which is thought to be smarter, might prevail by using his heavier head as a battering ram. Fretz said a fight between &quot;the Cuisinart and the bone-crusher&quot; might go to the giganotosaurus by virtue of its overall size advantage and &quot;razor-sharp attack teeth.&quot;</p>
<p>Both men accompanied their guesses with disclaimers that such a battle could not have occurred in real life and that scientists don't really study such issues, at least during working hours.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think any scientific journal wants to publish on which would win a battle, so we'll leave it up to the kids, for the most part,&quot; Daeschler said. &quot;But it might be really fun to get some scientists together with some kids and talk it out.&quot;</p>
<p>Eleven-year-old Derek Coates, attending the unveiling ceremony Friday evening, had no doubt as to the outcome. &quot;Giganotosaurus would win,&quot; he said. &quot;It's bigger, more bloodthirsty.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHILADELPHIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
