<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659472" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Senate lawmakers divided over child health plan.</title>
<headline>Senate lawmakers divided over child health plan.</headline>
<byline>Sue Kirchhoff</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Senate Republicans Friday inched closer to the White House on key budget issues including welfare benefits to legal immigrants, but were divided over how to extend health care to uninsured children.</p>
<p>The Senate Finance Committee unveiled mammoth legislation to implement $115 billion in Medicare and $13.6 billion in net Medicaid spending cuts called for in a five-year balanced budget deal between the White House and Congress.</p>
<p>The measure, to be voted on next week, includes new initiatives such as $16 billion for kid's health and continued aid to hundreds of thousands of legal immigrants slated to lose benefits this summer under a new welfare law.</p>
<p>But lawmakers are split over how to craft the children's health plan, which is designed to cover up to half the nation's 10 million uninsured children. The proposal is one of the biggest domestic initiatives in the budget.</p>
<p>Conservative Republicans, backed by many state governors, want to provide broad block grants to states to design their own health programmes. They say states can deliver health care more cheaply and efficiently than Washington.</p>
<p>Moderate Republicans and many Democrats support delivering much of the aid through the existing Medicaid programme for the poor. They want to require states to expand the current programme as a condition for receiving much of the $16 billion.</p>
<p>Finance Committee Chairman William Roth appointed a bipartisan task force to resolve the controversy, but aides said the work was at an impasse and the issue might be fought out next week.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the expectation that the ad hoc group would generate a proposal that would be a bipartisan solution isn't going to materialise,&quot; said Nicholas Graham, a spokesman for Sen. John Chafee, a Rhode Island Republican.</p>
<p>Chafee and West Virginia Democratic Sen. Jay Rockefeller have introduced a bill to give states money to expand Medicaid to children in families where earnings are about $24,000 for a family of four. To be eligible, states would have to expand coverage to children up to 18 whose family is on the poverty line and meet other rules.</p>
<p>A House committee Thursday passed legislation devoting most of the new money to block grants that states could use to design their own programmes. Governors could use vouchers, contract out with private firms or use other approaches.</p>
<p>The National Governor's Association prefers that plan.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of states are concerned they wouldn't be able to participate because they wouldn't be able to draw down funds,&quot; said one state official.</p>
<p>In a further break from the budget agreement, the bill does not include $1.5 billion set aside to subsidise the Medicare premiums of poor recipients. Aides said lawmakers were trying to work out a position on the issue.</p>
<p>The American Association of Retired Persons sent a letter to the committee calling on them to include the full amount. They are also concerned about a provision of the bill gradually raising the Medicare eligibility age to 67 from 65.</p>
<p>On another issue, the committee moved closer to the White House on continuing aid to legal immigrants, but does not go as far as the administration wants.</p>
<p>The bill would continue aid to 700,000 legal immigrants in the United States on Aug. 22, 1996, who were receiving Supplemental Security Income (SSI).</p>
<p>It sets aside $700 million to aid immigrants in the United States at that time who may become disabled in the future. The budget plan would have covered all those who became disabled, but would have cut off benefits to immigrants now receiving SSI due to age and poverty rather than physical ailment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
