<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659464" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: McVeigh -- from model soldier to bomber.</title>
<headline>McVeigh -- from model soldier to bomber.</headline>
<dateline>DENVER 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The defence portrayed him as an all-American boy gone astray and prosecutors said he was a monster, but Timothy McVeigh gave scarcely a hint of his own feelings during his trial.</p>
<p>Tall and bony, with light brown hair cut short in military-style, the decorated 29-year-old ex-soldier showed no emotion as victims told their heart-wrenching tales of surviving the bombing or losing loved ones, of hands sticking out of the rubble waving frantically for help.</p>
<p>Neither did he betray any feelings when a jury of seven men and five woman convicted him of the bombing on June 2 and then sentenced him to death on Friday.</p>
<p>McVeigh sat expressionless as the judge read the verdict. When the judge excused him from the courtroom, he turned and looked at his parents and appeared to mouth the words, &quot;It's all right.&quot;</p>
<p>Some observers of the case said they thought McVeigh saw himself as a prisoner of war captured by a hostile government and decided to conduct himself that way.</p>
<p>&quot;I think that is what he wanted to convey to the jury -- that he is a good soldier, name, rank and serial number only, a straight face to the end,&quot; said Denver legal expert Scott Robinson.</p>
<p>His lawyers in the penalty phase of the trial dwelt on McVeigh's political beliefs -- admitting he bombed the Alfred P. Murrah building in Oklahoma City in rage over the federal government's fiery onslaught on the Branch Davidian cult complex in Waco, Texas, in 1993.</p>
<p>As they spoke, McVeigh remained emotionless. When his weeping mother Mildred Frazer testified, saying, &quot;He is not the monster he has been portrayed as,&quot; McVeigh dabbed his eyes, but he might as well have been flicking away flies for all the emotion that gesture displayed.</p>
<p>Sometimes during harrowing testimony about how 168 people went to their deaths in the April 19, 1995, explosion, McVeigh would clasp his hands together tightly but that was all.</p>
<p>During the trial he did not take the stand and only spoke to answer questions from Judge Richard Matsch about whether he understood some points of law.</p>
<p>The Washington Post, echoing the feelings of many reporters covering the trial, called McVeigh's personality &quot;an unfathomable mystery.&quot; The paper said the prosecution's question of &quot;Who could do such a thing&quot; remained unanswered.</p>
<p>His neighbours from the upstate New York town of Pendleton remembered a warm, loving boy who played Little League baseball and joined the army out of patriotism. They recalled that he feared he would die in the Gulf War and come back in a body bag.</p>
<p>His army buddies spoke of a brave soldier who risked his own life to save others.</p>
<p>&quot;If you don't consider what happened in Oklahoma, Tim was a good person,&quot; said star prosecution witness Michael Fortier, who testified against McVeigh in hopes of avoiding a lengthy jail term for himself and any jail time for his wife Lori.</p>
<p>McVeigh had an ordinary childhood, marked by his passion for guns and by his parents' separation when he was 10 years old. In school, he was listed in a yearbook as the most talkative boy in class. He excelled in the Army, where his obsession with neatness and fitness impressed commanders.</p>
<p>But his life seemed to fall apart when he left the Army soon after failing to achieve his dream of joining the elite Special Forces. From 1992 to 1995, he drifted around the country, becoming increasingly drawn to far right-wing politics.</p>
<p>A racist, anti-Semitic tract called &quot;The Turner Diaries&quot; became his Bible, with its plot of &quot;patriots&quot; blowing up FBI headquarters in Washington. The author of the book denied it could have influenced him.</p>
<p>As McVeigh wandered the country he sent wild, rambling letters back home, urging his sister, Jennifer, to read &quot;The Turner Diaries.&quot; He warned her that her phone might be bugged, told her before the bombing that &quot;something big&quot; was going to happen.</p>
<p>He said he had moved from propaganda to action, had gone from &quot;the intellectual stage to the animal.&quot;</p>
<p>He found inspiration in the &quot;Star Wars&quot; movies and thought he was up against an &quot;evil empire&quot; -- the U.S. government.</p>
<p>He visited Waco, where he believed the government had murdered 80 innocent men, women and children.</p>
<p>Then, five months before the explosion, Fortier said he and McVeigh made a trip to Oklahoma City to scout out the Murrah building, where McVeigh believed, erroneously, the plans for Waco had been made.</p>
<p>Fortier said he asked about the innocent people in the building who would be hurt, maimed and killed in an explosion and said that McVeigh thought of them as individually innocent but part of the evil empire.&quot;</p>
<p>Two years to the day after the Waco showdown, the Murrah building was blown up. That was the day that Timothy McVeigh, the good soldier who liked to munch on McDonald's hot apple pies, became what one biographer called an &quot;All American Monster.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DENVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
