<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659580" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Asthmatic tenants blame bugs and landlord in NY.</title>
<headline>Asthmatic tenants blame bugs and landlord in NY.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tenants of a Bronx apartment building who link asthma-related problems to their landlord's alleged failure to rid their homes of cockroaches may file a class action lawsuit, their lawyer said on Friday.</p>
<p>Jayson Lutzky said he would pursue litigation against owners of the building &quot;if there are enough complaints.&quot;</p>
<p>Residents of 264 East 199th Street were spurred to action by their former neighbour, Carmen Marty, 30, who filed a lawsuit Monday at Bronx Supreme Court on behalf of her two sons, Jonathon, 8, and Steven, 5. She is seeking $22 million for &quot;painful personal injuries&quot; and &quot;emotional trauma&quot; caused by frequent, severe asthma attacks that she said were triggered by the swarms of bugs roaming their previous home.</p>
<p>Last month, a study in the New England Journal of Medicine linked the rates of U.S. inner-city children with asthma to high levels of cockroach allergens. Marty's lawsuit was the first filed in New York based on this data, Lutzky said.</p>
<p>Marty, who said her sons' asthma improved when the family moved to a new apartment, told Lutzky that despite frequent complaints the 199th Street building owners, HKH Enterprises and Norwax Associates, had sent an exterminator to the building only twice in 10 years.</p>
<p>The companies were not immediately available for comment.</p>
<p>Since Monday, several of Marty's former neighbours, including a man who claims he lost part of his lung to asthma, have approached Lutzky about pursuing litigation, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Landlords are trying to get rid of rent control and raise rents but they don't spend money to fix apartments,&quot; Lutzky said. &quot;I hope this sends a message that people have a right to safe apartments.&quot;</p>
<p>A few years ago, Lutzky won $20 million for a client who held his landlord accountable for vermin or insect bites on his testicles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
