<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659643" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Basketball player Camby arrested on marijuana charge.</title>
<headline>Basketball player Camby arrested on marijuana charge.</headline>
<dateline>SOUTH WINDSOR, Conn 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Basketball player Marcus Camby, 23, was arrested on a marijuana charge and released on bond early Friday, police said.</p>
<p>Camby, a centre for the Toronto Raptors of the National Basketball Association (NBA), was released on a $1,000 bond and faces a June 25 court appearance in Manchester, Conn., said Sgt. Matthew Reed.</p>
<p>He was charged with possession of less than four ounces of marijuana and failure to drive in the proper lane. If convicted, he faces a maximum penalty of one year in jail and a possible fine of $2,000, Reed said.</p>
<p>Camby was driving a rented car at around 2 a.m. when a police officer noticed it was weaving slightly, Reed said. &quot;As the officer spoke with Camby, he noticed the smell of burned marijuana,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Police then discovered two marijuana cigarette ends in the ashtray and an unlighted marijuana cigarette.</p>
<p>Reed said Camby did not act impaired at the time of arrest. &quot;There was no evidence of intoxication by alcohol or drugs,&quot; he said. &quot;The officer felt comfortable not making him take a sobriety test.&quot;</p>
<p>Camby, a Hartford native, was a college basketball standout at the University of Massachusetts. He lives in South Windsor, Conn.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOUTH WINDSOR, Conn"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
