<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659647" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Bristol-Myers aims to triple drug output.</title>
<headline>Bristol-Myers aims to triple drug output.</headline>
<byline>Ransdell Pierson</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bristol-Myers Squibb Co aims by 2005 to triple the number of drugs it introduces each year and speed drug development by beefing up its number of scientists fifty percent by 2002, the company's research chief said.</p>
<p>Peter Ringrose, president of the company's Pharmaceutical Research Institute, said the expanded pipeline is necessary to at least match the industry's projected 15 percent sales growth trajectory over the next five years.  </p>
<p>Ringrose, who headed Pfizer Inc's worldwide discovery operations before being hired by Bristol-Myers in January, laid out his game plan in a dinner meeting Thursday with reporters.</p>
<p>He said the company in recent years has introduced an average of one new drug a year. &quot;But we're aiming to get three new products launched (each year) during the next decade,&quot; he said, with each drug targetted to garner at least $500 million in sales.  </p>
<p>&quot;Some of our products do well in the $200 million range, but it doesn't hurt to shoot for $500 million,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Over the next five years, we will have to grow the organization by fifty percent&quot; to meet sales goals, he said, including the hiring of 2,000 new scientists by 2002.</p>
<p>The Princeton, N.J.-based company had worldwide sales of $15.1 billion in 1996. Pharmaceuticals, the largest component at $8.7 billion, posted sales growth of 11 percent after accounting for negative foreign exchange rate fluctuations.  </p>
<p>Bristol-Myers said the sales increase was impressive given the loss of U.S. patent exclusivity in February 1996 for the blockbuster Capoten heart drug. Capoten's worldwide sales of $1.5 billion in 1995 slid to $1.0 billion in 1996.</p>
<p>Excluding Capoten sales, the company said pharmaceutical sales jumped 21 percent during 1996.</p>
<p>Capoten will lose its exclusivity in several European countries this year, putting pressure on the company to introduce new products to fill the sales void.  </p>
<p>The biggest near-term hopes, Ringrose said, are two drugs being co-developed with French pharmaceuticals group Sanofi, a unit of Elf Aquitaine.</p>
<p>The partners filed worldwide approvals in 1996 for hypertension drug irbesartan, and expect marketing clearance from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration by autumn.</p>
<p>And the two companies in April sought marketing approval in the U.S. and Europe for Clopidogrel, an antiplatelet agent.</p>
<p>Ringrose said Bristol-Myers will accelerate its collaborations with biotech companies to protect its strong position in cardiovascular, oncology and anti-infective drugs, and will strengthen its focus on drugs affecting the central nervous system.</p>
<p>The company's current roster of drugs includes Pravachol, a cholesterol-lowering drug with sales of $1.1 billion in 1996. Its leading anti-cancer agent, Taxol, captured sales of $813 million last year. But its U.S. patent expires in December, the company said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
