<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659606" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S Senate iron man Thurmond gets Cal Ripken bat.</title>
<headline>U.S Senate iron man Thurmond gets Cal Ripken bat.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The man who holds the endurance record in the U.S. Senate was presented with a Louisville Slugger bat Friday autographed by the man who holds the endurance record on the baseball diamond.</p>
<p>In the latest of what threatens to become the longest-running series of Congressional accolades, colleagues presented South Carolina Republican Sen. Strom Thurmond with a bat signed by Baltimore Oriole Cal Ripken.</p>
<p>Handing the wooden baseball to the 94-year-old Thurmond at a Senate Judiciary hearing, committee chairman Orrin Hatch, a Utah Republican, said, &quot;I hesitate to give this to him since he's been known to give me a rough time.&quot;</p>
<p>Thurmond picked up the bat, felt its heft, announced his position on the nomination pending before the panel, and departed to make a speech at a school back home.</p>
<p>Ripkin, who was not present, set the record in 1995 with 2,131 straight Major League games and has played another 200 since as the streak continues. Thurmond last month broke the Senate service mark with 41 years and 10 months in office, and he has been showered for weeks with speeches, luncheons, cakes and now sports paraphernalia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
