<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659646" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Right-to-die forces suffer setback in Wisconsin.</title>
<headline>Right-to-die forces suffer setback in Wisconsin.</headline>
<dateline>MADISON, Wis. 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Right-to-die advocates have suffered a setback in Wisconsin with a state Supreme Court ruling that a feeding tube may not be removed from a woman dying of Alzheimer's disease.</p>
<p>&quot;It will have a huge impact,&quot; attorney Mark Wittman said after Thursday's unanimous ruling.</p>
<p>&quot;It (also) could have a chilling effect on whether guardians are going to allow the beginning of life-sustaining treatment (in the first place),&quot; added Wittman, who annually acts as guardian for about 100 people with debilitating illnesses.</p>
<p>The case involves 73-year-old Edna M. Folz of Evansville, Indiana, whose brain functions are ebbing and who is in a Marshfield, Wisconsin, nursing home.</p>
<p>Folz's sister and guardian, Betty Spahn, wants to have a feeding tube disconnected and let her die.</p>
<p>Spahn, of Rockford, Illinois, agreed to have the tube inserted in 1988 because her sister was sick but still somewhat alert. By 1994, her condition had worsened considerably.</p>
<p>Spahn asked to have the feeding tube taken out, and the Marshfield Nursing and Rehabilitation Centre agreed. The courts got involved, however, when one of Folz's nieces objected for religious reasons.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel like I have to do this for her,&quot; Spahn said of her sister. &quot;I'm fighting for her right to refuse medical treatment.&quot;</p>
<p>But the justices said the case was not clear-cut because Folz did not leave written instructions or otherwise clearly express a desire to die. Also, the justices said, Folz was not diagnosed as being in a &quot;persistent vegetative state.&quot;</p>
<p>Writing for the court, Justice Donald Steinmetz said: &quot;We decline to go down this slippery slope, for the consequences and the confusion may be great.</p>
<p>&quot;We understand how difficult Edna's illness has been on her loved ones, and we sympathise with their plight, but the evidence contained in the record is simply not sufficient to rebut the presumption that Edna would choose to live.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADISON, Wis."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
