<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="659869" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Battle looms over French nuclear fast-breeder.</title>
<headline>Battle looms over French nuclear fast-breeder.</headline>
<byline>Frederic Niel</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1996-06-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Battle lines are being drawn around France's controversial Superphenix fast-breeder nuclear reactor, now that its worst enemy is installed in government.</p>
<p>New Environment Minister Dominique Voynet, the Greens leader, has set her sights on scrapping the fault-prone plant, which has been the ecologists' bete noire since it was built 20 years ago near the Alpine town of Grenoble.</p>
<p>The future of the 1,200 megawatt reactor may become clearer next Thursday when Socialist Prime Minister Lionel Jospin outlines his programme in his first policy statement to the National Assembly.</p>
<p>Voynet, before she joined the government after the left's sweep to power in June 1 elections, denounced the 60-billion-franc ($10.5 billion) reactor as &quot;stupid financial waste&quot; and vowed: &quot;We shall close down Superphenix.&quot;</p>
<p>Environmentalists describe the plant as a dangerous dinosaur, although nuclear experts say it is as safe as any other plant.</p>
<p>Its supporters are organising, warning of the high cost of an early closure for its majority owner, state-run Electricite de France, and of dire losses of jobs and tax income for the region.</p>
<p>A disputed 1995 government study said it would cost up to 20 billion francs ($3 billion) to close the plant two decades ahead of the scheduled date of 2020.</p>
<p>Superphenix, owned at 51 percent by Electricite de France, with Italy's ENEL and a Dutch-German-Belgian consortium as partners, was constructed to produce more plutonium than it consumed.</p>
<p>But it has been on line for only 30 months and fed the electricity grid for only 10 months. The government downgraded it in 1994 to a research reactor working at reduced power as a tool of research into disposing of nuclear waste.</p>
<p>Nuclear experts in parliament are divided. Centrist deputy Claude Birreaux said Voynet would soon face a dilemma.</p>
<p>&quot;Either she understands the major consequences of closing the plant down and she gets cut off from her supporters or she sticks to her promises and gets cut off from her cabinet colleagues,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Socialist deputy Christian Bataille said parliament should take any decision on the fate of Superphenix.</p>
<p>The reactor was due to restart this month after shutting down six months ago because of more faults. But the Council of State, France's top administrative court, cancelled its 1994 authorisation to operate as a research reactor.</p>
<p>The council ruled that the procedure for transforming the power plant into a research prototype was flawed and required a new public inquiry.</p>
<p>Conservative prime minister Alain Juppe was believed to have wanted to keep the plant operating. But his defeat in the June 1 elections may have sounded Superphenix's death knell.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
