<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660203" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Congress panel OKs health plan conscience rule.</title>
<headline>Congress panel OKs health plan conscience rule.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Health plans contracting with Medicare would not have to provide end-of-life or abortion services if they objected on moral grounds, a House committee decided Thursday.</p>
<p>The plans also would not be required to provide palliative care, which lessens pain without curing. The House Commerce Committee approved the &quot;conscience clause&quot; as it debated legislation creating a new program to cover up to 5 million uninsured children and cut Medicare and Medicaid spending.</p>
<p>The measure is one of the most significant domestic initiatives to move through Congress this year. It calls for $15 billion in savings in the Medicaid health program for the poor, elderly and disabled while providing $16 billion in grants to states to cover uninsured children.</p>
<p>The bill is needed to implement a five-year balanced budget deal between Congress and the White House. It was expected to be approved later Thursday.</p>
<p>The committee by 33-12 vote approved an amendment making it clear that health plans contracting with Medicare would not have to provide, pay for or cover counseling or referral for services such as end-of-life, abortion or family planning to which they object on moral grounds.</p>
<p>While Medicare primarily covers senior citizens, it also provides care to younger, disabled individuals.</p>
<p>&quot;A health plan doesn't have a conscience,&quot; California Democratic Rep. Henry Waxman said. Oklahoma Republican Tom Coburn protested that &quot;killing somebody is not health care.&quot;</p>
<p>During debate, Democrats offered a series of unsuccessful amendments to eliminate or trim a pilot project allowing 500,000 seniors to set up tax-free medical savings accounts rather than participating in the traditional Medicare program.</p>
<p>Democrats worry the healthiest, wealthiest seniors will use the accounts, leaving older, sicker people in the Medicare program and increasing spending by at least $2 billion. They tried to persuade the committee to use the $2 billion instead to subsidize Medicare premiums of low-income seniors or cover co-payments for preventive care.</p>
<p>&quot;Medicare is going to be in a death spiral as (medical savings account expansion) goes on,&quot; New Jersey Democrat Frank Pallone said.</p>
<p>Republicans argued that the accounts, used in conjunction with high-deductible insurance plans, would make seniors more careful health care shoppers. &quot;Medical savings accounts are something whose time is coming .... People will use that money more rationally for their health care needs,&quot; Texas Republican Joe Barton said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I95100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
