<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660390" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Power cut in west Turkey after court shuts plants.</title>
<headline>Power cut in west Turkey after court shuts plants.</headline>
<byline>Ercan Ersoy</byline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's western regions began suffering on Friday from power cuts lasting several hours at a time after a local court ruled that three key thermal power plants should be closed to protect the environment.</p>
<p>&quot;We shut down the plants yesterday after the court ruling,&quot; said Energy Ministry undersecretary Ugur Dogan.</p>
<p>&quot;But a government decree has been prepared to reopen them for reasons of national security. The government has the right to do that despite court decisions,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>The Yenikoy, Kemerkoy and Yatagan coal-fired power plants -- all close to Turkey's tourist attractions and leading industrial sites -- were shut on Thursday at the end of a 30-day period given on May 13 by the court to state power producer TEAS to implement the ruling.</p>
<p>The Energy Ministry said in a statement that the plants, with combined capacity of 1,050 megawatts (MW) and producing 5.3 billion kilowatt-hours of electricity annually, were shut &quot;out of respect for the law&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Power cuts are inevitable because only 40 percent of the region's electricity needs will be supplied from other regions,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The court, whose decision came after a lawsuit was filed by local environmentalists, has ruled in the past that all three plants polluted the region and the Kemerkoy plant should be closed down completely.</p>
<p>Its past decisions were overruled by government decrees, which ordered reopening of the plants on national security grounds.</p>
<p>However, the court said Yatagan and Yenikoy could be operated after their chimneys were equipped with desulphurisation units.</p>
<p>The power cuts, to last five hours a day, have hit the major industrial cities of Izmir and Denizli and the tourist resort provinces of Aydin and Mugla.</p>
<p>Industrialists in western Turkey criticised the closure and urged the government to reopen the plants.</p>
<p>Some 100 businessmen who gathered at the Aegean Chamber of Industry, based in Izmir, said about 20,000 workers and employers from industrial plants would demonstrate in Izmir on Monday unless the plants were reopened.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a very bad thing to happen at a time when industrial production was going up and tourism's high season was beginning,&quot; said Atil Akkan, head of the Aegean Chamber of Industry.</p>
<p>He said Ufuk Soylemez, state minister in charge of the treasury and an MP from Izmir province, told him that 21 members of the cabinet had signed the decree to reopen the plants.</p>
<p>&quot;God willing, the problem will be solved by tonight,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>He earlier said they would appeal to the Council of State, Turkey's top administrative body, to have the plants reopened immediately.</p>
<p>&quot;There are about 7,000 industrialists in this region and some of them have already begun to reduce capacity by 50 percent,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He also said that thousands of workers might be laid off.</p>
<p>Selami Gurguc, president of textile producer EGS, said his company's losses since the power cuts began had exceeded the cost of desulphurisation filters to be installed on the plants.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a weakness of the government, of the energy minister. They knew power cuts were imminent but they did not do anything,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
