<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660486" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Record number of Lyme disease cases in U.S.</title>
<headline>Record number of Lyme disease cases in U.S.</headline>
<byline>Mike Cooper</byline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cases of Lyme disease, a bacterial infection transmitted by the bite of certain ticks, reached a record high last year, federal health officials said Thursday.</p>
<p>The Centres for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) said there were 16,461 Lyme disease cases reported last year, a 41 percent increase from the 11,700 cases in 1995. The agency said the annual total of reported cases has increased 32-fold since 1982.</p>
<p>New York had the largest number of cases last year with 5,301, followed by 3,104 in Connecticut and 2,814 in Pennsylvania. Those states, as well as Rhode Island, New Jersey, Delaware, Maryland and Wisconsin, accounted for 91 percent of the cases reported in 45 states and the District of Columbia last year.</p>
<p>CDC epidemiologist Kathy Orloski said last year's increase probably occurred because of changes in the tick population, greater awareness of Lyme disease and better reporting.</p>
<p>&quot;The population densities of the tick seem to fluctuate from year to year and it appears as though human disease rates are tied to those,&quot; Orloski said.</p>
<p>In the East, the disease is usually transmitted by the black-legged or deer tick. In the West, the primary vector is the western black-legged tick, the CDC said.</p>
<p>Lyme disease takes its name from the town of Lyme, Connecticut, where the illness was first identified in the United States in 1975. Almost 100,000 cases have since been reported. Initial symptoms can include a skin rash, fever, headache, swollen lymph nodes and muscle aches and pains.</p>
<p>Most people with Lyme disease can be treated with antibiotics. Pasteur Merieux Connaught said Tuesday it planned to submit a product license application to the Food and Drug Administration for its candidate Lyme disease vaccine.</p>
<p>Health officials say people can reduce their chances of being bitten by a tick by wearing light-coloured clothing, tucking long pants into socks, using insect repellants and thoroughly checking themselves for ticks at least once a day.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
