<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660467" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton signs disaster bill after week's strife.</title>
<headline>Clinton signs disaster bill after week's strife.</headline>
<byline>Jackie Frank</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton signed a multibillion-dollar disaster aid bill into law on Thursday after Congress stripped it of the political riders that prompted a presidential veto earlier in the week.</p>
<p>Clinton underlined his signature twice and raised his clenched his fist, prompting applause from lawmakers attending the Oval Office ceremony, including Sen. Byron Dorgan, a North Dakota Democrat, Sen. Barbara Boxer, a California Democrat and Sen. Paul Wellstone, a Minnesota Democrat.</p>
<p>&quot;This bill provides the desperately needed resources for hundreds of thousands of people who have suffered terribly from the flooding and other natural disasters in the Dakotas, Minnesota, California and 29 other states,&quot; Clinton said in a statement released by the White House.</p>
<p>&quot;When our people are in need, we Americans come to their assistance as one nation,&quot; the president said, applauding Congress for stripping the legislation of political riders attached by Republicans.</p>
<p>Republican leaders of Congress, battered by a negative press and hounded by lawmakers from flood-ravaged states, gave in to White House demands earlier on Thursday and passed the full $8.9 billion in the original bill.</p>
<p>The bill provides $5.6 billion to help North and South Dakota and Minnesota recover from flood damage to homes and businesses and to aid 32 other states hurt by natural disasters. It also restores $1.9 billion to military accounts to pay for past activities in Bosnia and the Gulf.</p>
<p>Clinton, who vetoed the first version of the bill on Monday, praised Congress for its &quot;common sense&quot; in passing the disaster aid in a form he would sign into law.</p>
<p>In his veto message, Clinton had urged Congress to pass the bill again without the political riders attached by Republicans. They would have prevented a government shutdown over the budget this fall and restricted the 2000 census to the traditional house-by-house count, rather than using statistical sampling to estimate the size of minorities.</p>
<p>Voting simultaneously, the House of Representatives passed the bill 348-74 and the Senate passed it 78-21 without the support of Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott, Republican of Mississippi.</p>
<p>Sen. Kent Conrad, whose state of North Dakota suffered from floods, said: &quot;This is going to help the rebuilding process to proceed. It's going to make a difference in the lives of thousands of people, many of whom are still sleeping on cots and staying in cars, people who have had their homes and their businesses destroyed.&quot;</p>
<p>Addressing the president from the House floor, Appropriations Committee Chairman Bob Livingston, Republican of Louisiana, acknowledged that Clinton won his demands. &quot;This is a perfect bill. Sign it into law,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
