<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660419" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish minister quits Islamist-led cabinet.</title>
<headline>Turkish minister quits Islamist-led cabinet.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkish Tourism Minister Bahattin Yucel said on Friday he had quit the Islamist-led coalition government, already reeling from resignations in a fight with the secularist army over Moslem activism.</p>
<p>&quot;I anounce to the public that I am withdawing from the tourism ministry,&quot; Yucel, of the coalition's secularist True Path Party wing, told a news conference.  </p>
<p>Yucel had been quoted in the Turkish press as urging party leader Tansu Ciller, the foreign minister, to immediately pull out of the ruling alliance with Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan.</p>
<p>He told Friday's news conference that the government's Islamist leanings put it at odds with Turkey's decades-old secularist tradition.</p>
<p>&quot;I felt that it went against my parliamentary oath to stay in power, with the contradictions to our country's values that were involved,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Pressure from the secularist army has brought the coalition close to collapse. A government plan to set up a caretaker administration to take the country to early polls has run into trouble.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
