<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660404" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Lebanon to slash food imports.</title>
<headline>Lebanon to slash food imports.</headline>
<byline>Zeina Soufan</byline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lebanon's food import bill will be cut by about $300 million a year when a ban on the import of foods grown in the country takes effect in October, Agriculture Minister Shawki Fakhoury said on Friday.</p>
<p>Fakhoury said the ban, approved by the government on Wednesday, would prohibit the import of about 20 percent of the items on its $1.5 billion food import bill.</p>
<p>The government's goal was to slash the total by half, he told a news conference at which he outlined a five-year plan to boost the agricultural sector.</p>
<p>&quot;We must gradually lower the prohibitively high import bill to $750 million a year from the current $1.5 billion as a first step,&quot; Falkhoury said.</p>
<p>The import ban would enhance productivity, encourage new agro-industries and increase agricultural exports to $600 million from $300 million within two years, Fakhoury said.</p>
<p>It would be coupled with increased customs duties on luxury foods, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;The protection affects only products that can be produced in Lebanon, which means that it protects the whole of national production,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>A detailed list of banned items would be finalised in a few days. Some products would be banned throughout the year while seasonal crops would be allowed in only during their off-season in Lebanon.</p>
<p>Fakhoury said Lebanon imported 80 percent of the food it consumed compared with 35 percent in Israel.</p>
<p>The government's goal was to raise to 20 percent the contribution of the agricultural sector to Gross Domestic Product from the current figure of less than seven percent.</p>
<p>Fakhoury dismissed fears voiced by some politicians and traders that protection would lead to a deterioration in the quality of local goods and a rise in prices.</p>
<p>&quot;We have formed specialised committees to control the quality and cost of all protected goods,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;In the worst of cases, we will practise our right of reopening the door to importing any produce which is being sold above the average set by a daily pricing list to be issued by the ministry of agriculture in coordination with the ministry of economy.&quot;</p>
<p>The government's plan has raised a storm of protest but Fakhoury denied accusations by opposition members of parliament that it was altering Lebanon's free market economy.</p>
<p>&quot;This protection is not absolute nor is it closed. It is movable according to the actual needs of the country and its higher economic interest,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He cited the European Union, Japan and the United States as examples of countries adopting some form of agricultural protectionism. &quot;Has protecting national production on which Lebanese exist become an abnormal issue?&quot; he asked.</p>
<p>He said 40 percent of Lebanon's 3.3 million population lived on agriculture and related businesses and blamed the sector's decline on &quot;historic neglect&quot; of agriculture to the benefit of the service-oriented sectors.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1996, the share of both the industrial and agricultural sectors from bank credits and loans did not exceed 15 percent against 51.26 percent for services sectors. There are a number of other indicators to the traditional neglect over the previous eras,&quot; Fakhoury said.</p>
<p>Asked if exporters would retaliate against the ban, Fakhoury said his ministry was contacting Lebanon's trading partners.</p>
<p>&quot;The exchange of agricultural products is limited to some Arab countries. The trade balance has always been in their favour. We have started contacting them to correct this balance and to establish a relationship based on equal duties and rights,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I42000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
