<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660469" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Democrats block immunity for witnesses in scandal.</title>
<headline>Democrats block immunity for witnesses in scandal.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Alan Elsner, Political Correspondent</p>
<p>Democrats Thursday blocked a proposal to grant immunity from prosecution to a group of Buddhist monks and nuns who may have made illegal campaign contributions to the Democratic Party.</p>
<p>Meeting behind closed doors, the Senate Governmental Affairs Committee voted along party lines by 9-7 not to grant immunity to 16 individuals in exchange for their testimony. Democratic Sen. Joseph Lieberman of Connecticut joined the Republicans in voting to grant immunity to a further two witnesses, committee sources said.</p>
<p>However, both resolutions failed since 11 votes were needed to approve them. The votes came at the end of an angry meeting marked by fierce partisan clashes.</p>
<p>The committee was probing whether Asian business interests or the Chinese government tried to influence the 1996 presidential election by illegally donating funds to the Democratic Party through Asian-American intermediaries.</p>
<p>It was also investigating whether foreigners attempted to win influence or favours or gained access to classified information in return for their illegal financial support.</p>
<p>Committee chairman Tennessee Sen. Fred Thompson accused Democrats of doing everything they could to impede the investigation but said the truth would eventually emerge.</p>
<p>Thompson announced he would begin public hearings on campaign finance scandals the week of July 8.</p>
<p>&quot;We will begin hearings the week of July 8 and they will be good hearings. We will begin to get answers to questions concerning whether or not the fundamental integrity of our government has been abused or compromised,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The 18 witnesses to whom he wanted to grant immunity were not named but congressional sources said several were Buddhist clergy who participated in a 1996 Democratic fund-raising event held in a Buddhist temple in California attended by Vice President Al Gore.</p>
<p>The event at the Buddhist temple apparently violated the tax-exempt status of that religious institution. Several Buddhist monks and nuns who had taken vows of poverty wrote checks for thousands of dollars to the Democratic Party and were reimbursed a few days later.</p>
<p>Republicans believe that granting these witnesses immunity would persuade them to reveal where the money came from.</p>
<p>&quot;These are not criminals that we're dealing with here. These are Buddhist monks and nuns who were taken advantage of,&quot; Thompson said.</p>
<p>But Lieberman shot back: &quot;If these folks are not criminals, then why is their counsel asking for immunity?&quot;</p>
<p>The Buddhist fund raising event has already become a major embarrassment for Gore, who first said the occasion was not designed to raise money and had to correct himself when it was revealed that his staff knew in advance that it was.</p>
<p>The seven Democrats on the committee had the power to block Thompson from issuing immunity since he needed at least two of their votes to proceed.</p>
<p>Ohio Sen. John Glenn, the ranking Democrat on the committee, said Thompson was running a biased investigation.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see that we're having that fair, evenhanded investigation that Sen. Thompson promised,&quot; Glenn said.</p>
<p>He said he would not go along with granting immunity until the Justice Department gave assurances that doing so would not interfere with possible criminal proceedings.</p>
<p>&quot;To go ahead with a blanket immunity would be the height of irresponsibility,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
