<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660558" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Sandra Bullock shows her niceness to a fault.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Sandra Bullock shows her niceness to a fault.</headline>
<byline>Steve James</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Even if she is annoyingly nice, at least Sandra Bullock can admit to her faults.</p>
<p>&quot;I am the biggest control freak who ever lived and it has been the biggest problem and hindrance in my life,&quot; said the latest fresh-faced actress to be dubbed &quot;America's Sweetheart&quot; and then hint that she has a darker side. &quot;I have bad days, I do horrible things, I make huge mistakes, (but) I do apologise for them eventually,&quot; she added with a smile that warned against asking further details.</p>
<p>Oh, and she is always right. &quot;I will argue till I'm blue in the face because I just want to win.&quot;</p>
<p>Her screen roles have perpetuated the squeaky-clean &quot;girl- next-door&quot; image, but Sandra Bullock the movie star says she keeps the real Sandra Bullock carefully hidden. &quot;I make a separation between my public life and my private life. None of my private life has ever made the papers,&quot; she told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Speculation, yes, but...&quot; her voice intriguingly trailed off as the wall around her private life went up again.</p>
<p>That speculation had her dating her co-star Matthew McConaughey from &quot;A Time to Kill&quot; and now has her linked with Jason Patric, who stars with her in &quot;Speed 2 - Cruise Control,&quot; which opens in the United States on Friday.</p>
<p>Patric said he was in a steady relationship with someone else but he did little to dampen the rumours coming from the big-budget action film. &quot;They say Sandy is cute and bubbly -- well, she's more than that,&quot; he told reporters. And in the latest Rolling Stone magazine, he was even more cryptic: &quot;She's everything you think she is and not.&quot;</p>
<p>HIGH PAID, A-LIST LADY</p>
<p>What she is, in public anyway, is one of the highest-paid actresses in movies today, raking in an estimated $12.5 million for &quot;Speed 2&quot; and $11 million for her next film, &quot;Hope Floats.&quot; Her roles in box-office successes like 1994's &quot;Speed,&quot; &quot;While You Were Sleeping&quot; and &quot;The Net&quot; have rocketed Bullock onto the Hollywood A-list.</p>
<p>But she has had flops too - most notably the recent &quot;In Love and War&quot; opposite her male &quot;Mr Nice Guy&quot; counterpart, Chris O'Donnell, who played a young Ernest Hemingway in Sir Richard Attenborough's sweeping First World War drama.</p>
<p>True to her Pollyanna persona though, Bullock has a knack of putting a positive spin on apparent failure.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm so thankful for the films that didn't work. I'm thankful that they weren't huge box-office successes because they were exactly what I needed to do to grow as an actor,&quot; she said. &quot;Anything that didn't make $200 million at the box-office seems to be looked at as a failure, which is sad.&quot;</p>
<p>Honesty is the stock-in-trade of a woman who points to the solid moral upbringing she received from a German opera-singer mother and American military father. &quot;I've made horrible mistakes, things that I wish I had never done -- choices, decisions, movies, but at the time they were exactly what I should have done.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked if she was terribly disappointed about &quot;In Love and War,&quot; she pondered before replying. &quot;No I was not. It wasn't 'Speed,' it wasn't 'Batman.' It was an honour to work with Richard Attenborough, it was an honour to work with Penny Rose, the costume designer.&quot;</p>
<p>AGAIN IN HARM'S WAY</p>
<p>In &quot;Speed 2,&quot; director Jan De Bont's sequel to the hit about a runaway, booby-trapped bus, Bullock is again in harm's way as villain Willem Dafoe overrides a cruise ship's computer to set it on a deadly collision course with an oil tanker and a Caribbean island. But this time she plays opposite Patric rather than Keanu Reeves, who passed on the &quot;Speed&quot; sequel to keep playing in his rock band Dogstar.</p>
<p>&quot;I love Keanu -- not love as in looooooove Keanu,&quot; she said parenthetically, &quot;but there's something so dear about him; we had this incredible experience together. So when he dropped out I was like 'Here I am committed to this film, now what element is gone. What do you do?'</p>
<p>&quot;I said don't replace (Reeves). Get someone who is strong and is his own man and can lift it to a whole other level. Jason was the only person I could think of.&quot;</p>
<p>Bullock is blunt about a movie that features lots of action and mayhem at, and in, the sea. &quot;It's not an acting film, it's an action film. There are millions of other actors who are more talented and should be in my position. Any number of actresses could have done a great job with the first 'Speed,'&quot; she said, adding humility to her disarming arsenal.</p>
<p>Is she different now, three years later?</p>
<p>&quot;Same sense of humour, same sense of optimism, not as controlling, a lot calmer,&quot; she checked off. &quot;If I can at least conduct myself honourably, improve my work, take chances -- as stupid, as nice, as silly or as girl-next-door as that might sound.&quot;</p>
<p>Girl-next-door -- she said it.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
