<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660716" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Nordics seen successful in EU reform talks.</title>
<headline>Nordics seen successful in EU reform talks.</headline>
<byline>Fredrik Dahl</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The three Nordic countries in the European Union may be among the bloc's smaller member states but they still seem set to succeed in leaving a clear mark in the new EU treaty to be agreed in Amsterdam next week.</p>
<p>Sweden, Finland and Denmark have pushed hard during 15 months of EU negotiations to include stronger language in the treaty on traditional Nordic issues such as jobs, openness, the environment and equality between the sexes.</p>
<p>Sweden and Finland, militarily non-aligned, also launched a largely well-received joint initiative defining the EU's defence policy as involving peacekeeping and humanitarian tasks.</p>
<p>Even if they do not get everything they wanted on these issues, Stockholm, Helsinki and Copenhagen will be able to boast some successes at the Amsterdam summit on June 16-17.</p>
<p>&quot;The Nordics are probably the most conspicuous winners. They knew what they wanted. They have by and large got it,&quot; wrote Peter Ludlow, director of the Centre for European Policy Studies, in a report on the treaty talks published this month.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, Swedish chief negotiator Gunnar Lund agreed. &quot;We've had successes in the areas we have given priority to,&quot; he told Reuters this week.</p>
<p>Others, however, were less enthusiastic, pointing to the generally modest outcome of the treaty talks as a whole compared with previous inter-governmental conference (IGC) treaty talks, which resulted in the single market and plans for economic and monetary union.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm afraid no one has got what they wanted in the IGC except those who did not want anything to happen,&quot; said Stanley Crossick, chairman of think-tank the European Policy Centre.</p>
<p>Diplomats also stressed that no victories should be taken for granted, well aware that tough negotiations remain.</p>
<p>The Nordics' choice of issues to advocate in the IGC reflect an ambition to make the bloc more popular at home, not least in Sweden and Denmark where a large part of the population is at best sceptical.</p>
<p>Even if they reject talk about a &quot;Nordic EU bloc&quot;, the three Social Democrat-led governments often have similar views.</p>
<p>The most notable Nordic contribution is the inclusion of a chapter on employment in the EU, seen certain to be agreed after the political shift to the left in France and Britain.</p>
<p>Even Germany, despite initial misgivings that it might interfere with EMU, has come around to the idea as long as it does not create costly jobs schemes.</p>
<p>&quot;Employment is one place where they have succeeded because now that Germany has come over to support the insertion of an employment clause there is unanimity on that,&quot; said Kristen Sukalac, information officer at the Philip Morris Institute for Public Policy Research.</p>
<p>Such a chapter has also gained further in political importance and visibility after the new Socialist-led government in France demanded an increased role for job creation in EMU.</p>
<p>At least partly reflecting Nordic influence, the new treaty will also incorporate text on increased transparency in the EU, on the environment and on equality between men and women.</p>
<p>However, not all is joy for the Nordics. Denmark -- whose voters threw the bloc into chaos by initially rejecting the Maastricht treaty in a 1992 referendum -- has major problems handling proposals on EU visa, immigration and asylum policies.</p>
<p>The Nordics will also fight hard to the end to avoid losing much power in the EU to its larger member states, and resist attempts to create a joint defence.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G156">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
