<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660875" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's Dobson rules nothing in or out of NHS review.</title>
<headline>UK's Dobson rules nothing in or out of NHS review.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Health Secretary Frank Dobson refused on Friday to rule out new charges for patients in Britain's National Health Service but said the Labour government would meet its election pledges on health.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to have a thorough-going review,&quot; Dobson told BBC radio. &quot;But the test will be would any of these proposals put people off getting treated and would it break our election promise that access to the health service will be based on need and need alone, not on people's ability to pay.&quot;</p>
<p>Dobson said he would rule nothing in or out of the NHS review. Newspapers reported that the idea of patients being charged to see their doctor or paying &quot;hotel&quot; bills while in hospital was doing the rounds in government circles.</p>
<p>&quot;We are looking at every aspect so that we can get the health service finances on an even keel,&quot; Dobson said. &quot;We are going to have to look at charges but it may be that some charges will be reduced or removed.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the NHS funding shortfall was worse than he had expected. &quot;I didn't realise during the election that a quarter of all hospitals in this country entered this financial year in debt, two-thirds of the health authorities entered this financial year in debt.&quot;</p>
<p>But he said Britain's new government was not reneging on campaign promises. &quot;We said we would cut bureaucracy and we're reducing it by 100 million pounds.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the government had already shifted 10 million stg into breast cancer services and had now found five million pounds to spend on children's intensive care services.</p>
<p>Earlier, former Conservative health secretary Stephen Dorrell said it was a &quot;betrayal&quot; for the Government to consider patient charges. &quot;They should have told the British people this would be their policy before the election, and not two months afterwards,&quot; he told BBC Radio.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
