<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660813" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: S.AFRICA TO CLAMP DOWN ON NON-WTO SHOE IMPORTS.</title>
<headline>S.AFRICA TO CLAMP DOWN ON NON-WTO SHOE IMPORTS.</headline>
<dateline>CAPE TOWN 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Africa, under pressure to act against the growing flood of cheap imported footwear, mainly from China, said on Friday it will impose import controls for at least a year.</p>
<p>The trade and industry department (DTI) said on Friday that imported shoes from non World Trade Organisation (WTO) members, including China, will be limited to 15 million pairs. </p>
<p>Imports from WTO members will not be limited, but will be carefully monitored to ensure shoes from non-WTO countries do not enter South Africa via WTO members.</p>
<p>Controls will be phased in over three months from a date still to be advertised.</p>
<p>DTI chief director in charge of the sector Alwyn Kraamwinkel told the parliamentary trade and industry committee that the introduction of controls was necessary given the effect of the import flood from the Far East on local industry.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a dramatic decline over the last seven years in the footwear industry from a total production of 88 million pairs a year to 44 million pairs,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The reasons for this included the fact that South African producers were not competitive in plastic and cloth footwear and could not match the influx of cheap shoes from the Far East.</p>
<p>Instead, their strength lay in developing middle range leather footwear.</p>
<p>Kraamwinkel said that to give the industry time to restructure and become more competitive in this area, it had been decided to limit cheap imports for a year.</p>
<p>&quot;This is an extreme measure, it is a temporary measure and it really tries to give some breathing space for the industry  to shift production from certain areas to leather,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>There had been extensive consultations with the industry, including retailers, who would also be affected by import controls.</p>
<p>Kraamwinkel said the controls would be phased in to allow retailers to balance seasonal orders. Supply-side measures would be introduced to help manufacturers become more competitive.</p>
<p>-- Parliamentary newsroom +27 21 403-2502</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CAPE TOWN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
