<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660846" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British studies find race link to sexual diseases.</title>
<headline>British studies find race link to sexual diseases.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Two studies published on Friday found blacks and people from poorer areas in Britain have a much higher risk of sexually transmitted diseases.</p>
<p>Researchers said the findings were important both for doctors screening for disease and for community leaders, but urged they not be used to discriminate.</p>
<p>Charles Lacey of the Leeds General Infirmary and colleagues found sex, age, race, socio-economic group and where one lived were all good predictors of gonorrhoea risk in Leeds, a northern English city of 700,000.</p>
<p>&quot;Young black men aged 20 to 29 were at highest risk, with incidences of three to four percent per year,&quot; they wrote in a report in the British Medical Journal.</p>
<p>&quot;Black subjects were 10 times more likely than white subjects to acquire infection, and subjects from the most deprived socio-economic areas were more than four times more likely than those from the most affluent areas to acquire infection.&quot;</p>
<p>Nicola Low and colleagues at the King's College School of Medicine found similar results in a London study of nearly 2,000 cases of gonorrhoea.</p>
<p>&quot;At all ages gonorrhoea rates were higher in non-white minority ethnic groups,&quot; they wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no known biological reasons to explain why racial or ethnic factors alone should alter the risk for sexually transmitted diseases,&quot; Kevin Fenton and Anne Johnson of the University College London medical school said in a commentary.</p>
<p>It could be behaviour, which is affected by culture, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Gonorrhoea is curable, and HIV infection is increasingly treatable. Both are preventable,&quot; they added.</p>
<p>&quot;Acknowledging ethnic disparities in rates of HIV infection and other sexually transmitted diseases is one of the first steps in empowering affected communities to organise and focus on this problem.&quot;</p>
<p>But, they added, this was no excuse for stereotyping.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
