<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660939" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australian Grain-ABARE seen cutting wheat forecast.</title>
<headline>Australian Grain-ABARE seen cutting wheat forecast.</headline>
<byline>Michael Byrnes</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's official commodities forecasting agency is expected to cut its forecast for the 1997/98 wheat crop in a report to be issued next Tuesday because of the threat of a severe El Nino drought.</p>
<p>The Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics (ABARE) would base the prediction in its next Australian Commodities quarterly on the possibility of drought, an ABARE official told Reuters on Friday.</p>
<p>ABARE's forecasts are closely guarded secrets until the moment of their release.  </p>
<p>But a switch to possible drought assumptions would change the basis of ABARE's previous forecast of a 19.2 million tonne wheat crop, which assumed a normal season.</p>
<p>In its Crop Report, issued June 3, ABARE noted that very dry El Nino weather could reduce forecast production to 16.3 million tonnes because of reduced yields, from 1.74 tonnes per hectare in average weather to 1.47 tonnes per ha in very dry weather.</p>
<p>The report was issued the same day the Bureau of Meteorology warned Australia faced a serious and worsening El Nino weather effect, which was likely to make large areas of eastern Australia significantly drier than normal in winter and spring.  </p>
<p>&quot;Current conditions are ripe and excellent,&quot; he said. &quot;The majority of our crop is in the ground now and rains received last night in South Australia and Victoria are going to finalise planting operations there -- we're getting light to moderate rainfall right in the areas that we need it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's continuing to look great in Western Australia, the crop is coming up in great shape in northern New South Wales and Queensland, so for all intents and purposes we're right on track and feel very good about it,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Shean pointed out that Thursday's steady USDA estimate of an Australian crop of 18.5 million tonnes was &quot;in the ballpark&quot; with the AWB forecast.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot needs to develop. We've got to see some indication that drought really is on top of us before I'm going to be convinced that there needs to be a revision,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Shean said brokers' views of a possible 14.5 million tonne crop &quot;assumed the worse&quot;.</p>
<p>Brian Bailey's private forecast group Australian Wheat Forecasters Pty Ltd is also unmoved by the El Nino threat.  </p>
<p>AWF's last forecast, issued June 5, put the wheat crop at 17.85 million tonnes. The next forecast was likely to be increased to about 18 million tonnes, Bailey told Reuters.</p>
<p>Sydney wheat futures, however, reflected drought concern by staying firm over the week, with market leader January 1998 closing Friday on a steady settlement price of A$174.50 a tonne.</p>
<p>Most settlement prices closed steady over the week after falling by about A$3.50 a tonne on Friday.</p>
<p>Physical markets were steady over the past week, Bill Mitchell of New England Agricultural traders said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
