<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="660935" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Skin cancer researchers search for &quot;vaccine&quot;.</title>
<headline>Skin cancer researchers search for &quot;vaccine&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Richard Pullin</byline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-06-12</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scientists worldwide are testing a wide range of potential vaccines to counter melanoma, the deadliest form of skin cancer that claims thousands of lives each year.</p>
<p>Promising early results were reported at the fourth World Conference on Melanoma in Sydney this week, although researchers warned the technology was still in its early stages.</p>
<p>&quot;Vaccines are the hope of the future for the prevention of recurrence of melanoma,&quot; Professor William McCarthy of Sydney's Royal Prince Alfred Hospital told Reuters.</p>
<p>More than 90,000 new cases of melanoma are reported around the world each year, about 6,000 in Australia which has the highest incidence of the lifestyle-related disease.</p>
<p>The outdoor activies of many Australians -- surfing, yachting, golf and fishing -- have led to an epidemic of melanoma in the past 20 years with the leisured rich worst hit.</p>
<p>About 900 Australians die of the disease each year.</p>
<p>While the rate of increase in Australia has started to level off, particularly among women, it is rising in other countries where the message to spurn sunbathing and splash on the sunscreen has yet to take hold.</p>
<p>Hawaii has the second-highest incidence of the disease after Australia, with New Zealand, and the U.S. mainland states of Arizona, Texas and Colarado also high on the list, said McCarthy.</p>
<p>Traditional treatment is to remove tumours by surgery, but the new hope is to combine surgery with a therapeutic vaccine, manufactured from the tumourous cells, to boost the body's immune system and help it attack the disease.</p>
<p>Peter Hersey, professor of oncology at Australia's Newcastle University, said at least half a dozen new compounds were being tested in Australian, U.S. and European research centres.</p>
<p>Vaccine trials are focussing on patients with a 50-percent risk of recurrence.</p>
<p>&quot;If you can cut that down to 10 or 15 percent you have obviously done a lot of people a lot of good,&quot; said McCarthy.</p>
<p>One of the biggest and longest running trials is an Australian study of 648 patients which began in 1989.</p>
<p>Early results reported to the conference found patients given the vaccine lived 17 percent longer than those who had surgery only, although the trial is not yet complete.</p>
<p>Hersey noted the study was based on first-generation vaccine technology developed in the 1980s, aimed simply at boosting the immunce system.</p>
<p>More sophisticated techniques were now trying to persuade the immune system to develop a &quot;killer&quot; response, rather than just produce anti-bodies.</p>
<p>However, problems remained.</p>
<p>Hersey said new research had shown tumour cells were not passive targets and had the ability to fight back and defend themselves against the immune system.</p>
<p>Different types of melanoma also existed and future research should aim to identify which patients were more likely to respond to different treatments.</p>
<p>The good news is that melanoma is eminently curable. Only five percent of patients die if they get to the doctor early.</p>
<p>&quot;The best way to cure skin cancer is not to get it,&quot; said McCarthy. &quot;Melanoma is essentially preventable for a large majority of the population because it is a lifestyle illness.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-12"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
