<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="661020" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Make Information Age relevant to poor - academic.</title>
<headline>Make Information Age relevant to poor - academic.</headline>
<byline>Nick Edwards</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>All the talk about the new information age and its amazing technology during one of the world's leading telecommunications gatherings this week will not change the lives of the poor, a senior academic said on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;Companies spend all their time looking for killer applications for this technology,&quot; said William Melody, chairman of the international advisory board at the Technical University of Denmark.</p>
<p>&quot;So far the biggest two are gambling and pornography,&quot; Melody told delegates attending the Asia Telecom 97 trade fair.</p>
<p>&quot;If these are the killer applications of the intelligent network age we have to redefine the meaning of intelligence,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;What has been talked about here is of no relevance to the poorest half of the world's population,&quot; Melody told Reuters after his speech.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not going to improve their lives in any way.&quot;</p>
<p>Melody said the intelligent technology and networks of the Information Age were wasted on lowest common denominator -- entertainment -- while its potential as an educational, life-improving tool was being ignored.</p>
<p>&quot;Should we use intelligent networks to make unintelligent people intelligent, or just use them to throw out the applications that the unintelligent wealthy want?&quot; he asked.</p>
<p>Melody dismissed the bulk of discussions at the gatherings of telecommunications and technology executives as &quot;unimportant&quot; in terms of their contribution to the debate on how to use technology to improve the lives of the world's poor.</p>
<p>He said most exhibitors were delivering services designed for developed countries and aiming content at the world's richest consumers.</p>
<p>And he said too much money and effort was expended on esoteric issues like infrastructure architecture and building intelligent cities.</p>
<p>&quot;Are we investing as much in trying to create intelligent people?&quot; he asked.</p>
<p>With about two thirds of Asia's population not even connected to the most basic telephone services, it was clear that &quot;if you do not have access to a telephone, you are not going to be able to participate in any of this,&quot; Melody said.</p>
<p>&quot;If people cannot participate properly, how can we educate them to allow them to participate.&quot;</p>
<p>Melody described the major challenge facing telecommunications companies in the Information Age was &quot;how to take the technology and apply it to the poorest cities in the world&quot;.</p>
<p>Failure to do so would create a society of information have and have-nots, &quot;bifurcated into people who are much better off and those who are very poor&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom (65-870-3080)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83940">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
