<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="661283" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Pol Pot, Cambodia's hated &quot;Brother Number One&quot;.</title>
<headline>Pol Pot, Cambodia's hated &quot;Brother Number One&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pol Pot, shadowy leader of the infamous Khmer Rouge, ruled Cambodia for nearly four years of a revolution that turned the country into a nightmare of killing and deprivation.</p>
<p>On Friday the leader of the 1975-79 &quot;killing fields&quot; reign of terror was reported to be on the run, having killed his defence chief in a brutal attack and fled the last stronghold of his reviled Maoist movement.</p>
<p>Cambodian co-premier Prince Norodom Ranariddh said he had reports that Pol Pot, his health failing, had fled his northern base at Anlong Veng with just 200 loyalists and the movement's nominal leader Khieu Samphan as a hostage.</p>
<p>Ranariddh did not say where Pol Pot was headed but the Thai government immediately announced it would close part of the Thai-Cambodian border and would cooperate with Phnom Penh to capture him.</p>
<p>China, a former ally, said earlier in the week Pol Pot could expect no welcome there.</p>
<p>The guerrilla movement has unravelled over the past year as thousands of its leaders and rank-and-file defected to the Cambodian government, including former foreign minister Ieng Sary.</p>
<p>Phnom Penh has pardoned Ieng Sary for his role in the genocidal rule but stressed there can be no reconciliation with Pol Pot, whom King Norodom Sihanouk has called one of &quot;the biggest criminals in the history of Cambodia&quot;.</p>
<p>Born Saloth Sar on May 19, 1928, Pol Pot led a Cambodian peasant army to victory against the U.S.-backed Lon Nol republic in 1975, or Year Zero, as the Khmer Rouge called it. They immediately embarked on a bloody restructuring of society.</p>
<p>Pol Pot's guerrillas emptied Phnom Penh at gunpoint, forcing the sick from their beds. Women, children and the old were ordered into the countryside and put to work in vast labour camps.</p>
<p>More than one million people were executed as enemies of Pol Pot's utopian revolution or died of disease, starvation or overwork until the Vietnamese invasion launched on December 25, 1978, drove the Khmer Rouge from power.</p>
<p>Shortly after he was ousted from Phnom Penh, a smiling and healthy-looking Pol Pot told journalists that several thousand Cambodians had died &quot;due to some mistakes&quot; in implementing his policies, but he denied committing crimes against humanity.</p>
<p>That was the last time Pol Pot, known to his subordinates as Brother Number One, was seen in public and though he had since officially been retired from leadership posts no one doubted that he remained the movement's helmsman.</p>
<p>He was born to a reasonably prosperous rural family in central Cambodia's Kompong Thom province and spent part of his youth as a novice monk and student at a pagoda in Phnom Penh, where relatives worked in the royal household.</p>
<p>As a student between 1940 and 1948 he developed nationalist ideas. Awarded a scholarship to study in France, Pol Pot became so involved in radical student politics that he failed his exams and returned home without completing his studies.</p>
<p>He joined an underground movement opposed to the French colonialists and went on to teach history and geography in a private school in Phnom Penh from 1954 to 1963.</p>
<p>That year he fled the capital for the countryside because of police suspicions against him.</p>
<p>Pol Pot became party secretary in 1963 and in 1968 his guerrillas, which the Cambodian leader, the then Prince Norodom Sihanouk, dubbed &quot;les Khmers Rouges&quot;, launched their first attacks against army and police posts.</p>
<p>Efforts by Sihanouk to keep his country out of the Vietnam War failed and the Khmer Rouge thrived on the bitterness engendered by massive U.S. bombing of the countryside.</p>
<p>During the war, the Cambodian communists were uneasy allies of their Vietnamese comrades but historical enmity surfaced less than three years after the 1975 communist victories.</p>
<p>Pol Pot, by then prime minister, unleashed a purge of his ranks in 1977. Vietnamese-trained Khmer Rouge cadres, and in many cases their whole families as well, were tortured to death at a Phnom Penh school converted into Pol Pot's interrogation centre.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
