<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="661470" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Russian poet and singer Okudzhava dies in Paris.</title>
<headline>Russian poet and singer Okudzhava dies in Paris.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russian poet and singer Bulat Okudzhava, whose dissident lyrics once filled stadiums with fans, has died in France. He was 73.</p>
<p>Okudzhava died on Thusday at Percy military hospital in Clamart in the Paris suburbs, a French armed forces spokeswoman said. The cause of death was not immediately disclosed.</p>
<p>French military hospitals are open to the general public, treating civilian patients who live nearby.</p>
<p>Although especially influential in the 1960s and 1970s, Okudzhava's simple melodies and moving lyrics, usually accompanied by acoustic guitar, attracted generations of fans.</p>
<p>Love, war and everyday life were the focus of his lyrics.</p>
<p>In one of his songs about Moscow's most famous streets, he sang: &quot;Ah Arbat, my Arbat, you are my melody, you are my Fatherland, you are my joy and sorrow.&quot;</p>
<p>Born in Moscow in May 1924, Okudzhava served in World War Two and then became a school teacher. His songs and writing thrived during the political thaw in Russia introduced by Soviet leader Nikita Khrushchev in the 1950s, and he later also wrote historical novels.</p>
<p>He was poetry editor of the Moscow Literary Gazette from 1956-64 and made the first of many trips to France in the late 1960s.</p>
<p>Half Georgian and half Armenian, Okudzhava was long out of favour with the Soviet communist regime, but won the approval of reform-minded authorities in the late 1980s.</p>
<p>In December 1994 he won the 10,000 pound ($15,000) Russian Booker literary prize, but did not attend the award ceremony because of poor health. He was also named a member of President Boris Yeltsin's council on culture and art.</p>
<p>In recent years he developed heart problems and kept a low public profile. He had heart surgery in the United States several years ago, and in August last year suffered a heart attack.</p>
<p>Ekho Moskva radio said he died from complications related to pneumonia and kidney failure. But Itar Tass news agency quoted his wife Olga as saying he died &quot;from the psychological stress of loneliness&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
