<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="661569" id="root" date="1997-06-13" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan's car fleet seen up over 8.0 pct by 2001.</title>
<headline>Taiwan's car fleet seen up over 8.0 pct by 2001.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-06-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>The number of cars on Taiwan's congested roads is expected to rise by more than eight percent by 2001, adding to the country's already serious pollution problems, a Transport Ministry spokesman said on Friday.</p>
<p>He told reporters more than 400,000 additional cars would be clogging the country's streets over roughly the next four years, bringing the total to 5.5 million vehicles from 5.078 million.</p>
<p>The number of motorcycles, the vast majority of them scooters under 150 ccs, is expected to reach 10 million by 2001 from 9.465 million now.  </p>
<p>Heavily industrialised Taiwan suffers serious air pollution problems in most cities, though the sources of pollution vary significantly.</p>
<p>In the capital Taipei, vehicle emissions are the primary pollutant, while in southern Kaohsiung, Taiwan's second-largest city, industrial emissions are the main culprit.</p>
<p>Taiwan recently adopted an air-quality warning system that alerts the public to poor air quality in their communities.  </p>
<p>In 1991, Taiwan's Environmental Protection Administration introduced a strict emission standard requiring all car and motorcycle emissions to contain less than 4.5 percent of carbon monoxide and 9,000 ppm of hydrocarbons.</p>
<p>The standard forced car owners and makers to install catalytic converters to meet it.</p>
<p>No official statistics about the number of converters used in Taiwan was available, as the device is not a mandatory part, Transport Ministry officials said.  </p>
<p>&quot;We don't require car owners to install catalytic converters, but that is a very effective way to meet our emission standard,&quot; a ministry official said.</p>
<p>He estimated roughly 85 percent of Taiwan's cars and motorcycles have catalytic converters.</p>
<p>Taiwan uses two main types of converter -- metal-based using platinum, palladium or rhodium and non-metal using pottery and porcelain, ministry officials said.</p>
<p>Taiwan oil monopoly Chinese Petroleum introduced unleaded gasoline in 1990 and will phase out leaded gasoline entirely by 2000, a Chinese Petroleum official said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I36300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-13"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-13"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
