<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662152" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Greenpeace activists declare new state on Rockall.</title>
<headline>Greenpeace activists declare new state on Rockall.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greenpeace activists who seized the tiny, barren Atlantic island of Rockall rejected British claims to it on Sunday and declared it the new state of Waveland.</p>
<p>Three protesters, a Briton, Australian and German, from the international environmental group hoisted the new flag on Waveland and named the capital Rockall. They said they hoped it would be the start of a peaceful revolution.</p>
<p>&quot;We reject the governance of a country which permits new oil exploration despite professed concern for the climate. Waveland is a new kind of country designed to protect the global commons rather than to exploit it,&quot; they said in a statement released in London.</p>
<p>The declaration of the new state is the latest move in Greenpeace's campaign to protect the Atlantic Frontier from oil exploration.</p>
<p>Chris Rose, the deputy executive director of Greenpeace, stressed that the group did not want to own the island but to protect its oil.</p>
<p>&quot;Four nations want the oil around Rockall, we do not recognise their right to develop it. We have told (British prime minister) Tony Blair that we don't want Rockall itself but that the oil should be set aside for the common good. We are borrowing it until it is freed from the threat of development.&quot;</p>
<p>The three Greenpeace activists were taken by helicopter to the island on Wednesday. They set up a base in a solar survival capsule screwed by steel pins into a rocky ledge.</p>
<p>Greepeace said they would be using their capsule as a campaign base for monitoring the expansion of oil fields around the island that is situated about 3,000 miles from the Scottish mainland.</p>
<p>Eleven exploration licences covering 58 full and partial blocks in the Rockall Trough, where water depths exceed 1,500 metres (4,920 ft), were awarded on June 4.</p>
<p>Greenpeace argues that encouraging new oil development is senseless and a danger to both the atmosphere and the ocean.</p>
<p>The protesters offered immediate citizenship of Waveland to anyone who would pledge to defend nature, reform industrialism, protect the global environment and to secure peace.</p>
<p>Anyone wishing to apply was encouraged to contact the environmental group or to visit its Internet website.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
