<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662166" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Prince Charles turns architect's dream into reality.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Prince Charles turns architect's dream into reality.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>POUNDBURY, England 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>On a lush green hillside in rural Dorset, one man's vision of Utopia is being realised.</p>
<p>No ugly television aerials sprout from the roofs, no garish neon lights compete with the sunset, cars are tucked away in paved courtyards and there's not a block of concrete to be found.</p>
<p>After years of attacking modern architecture, Britain's future king Prince Charles has put theory into practice and tried to show the world how the traditions of the rural past can live in harmony with the needs of modern development.</p>
<p>The urban village of Poundbury, now taking shape on the outskirts of the southwestern market town of Dorchester, is being built on a 400-acre (162-hectare) site sold off by the prince's Duchy of Cornwall estate.</p>
<p>With its winding streets, flint-stone cottages, Georgian-style stone houses and mix of luxury houses and low cost homes for rent, Poundbury embodies the ideals set out by the philosopher prince in his book &quot;A Vision of Britain&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;If development in the countryside is going to take place, then I believe it must be done in such a way as to enhance rather than detract from the surrounding landscape.</p>
<p>&quot;That is what we are trying to do at Poundbury, as well as attempt to engender a sense of community within an environment comprising economic activity and residential use,&quot; Charles wrote.</p>
<p>LEGENDARY DISTATE FOR MODERN ARCHITECTURE</p>
<p>The prince's distaste of modern architecture is legendary. He once slammed a proposed extension to London's classically proportioned 18th century National Gallery as a &quot;monstrous carbuncle&quot; and has since set up his own Institute of Architecture to remedy the onslaught of steel and glass buildings.</p>
<p>He was closely involved in every step of the development at Poundbury, right down to the selection of bricks and street lamps.</p>
<p>About 100 of the planned 2,500 houses are now built and occupied as well as a handful of small craft workshops.</p>
<p>Shops and, crucially, an English village pub are planned over the next two years as the development expands.</p>
<p>The result has been a mixture of styles creating the kind of village that might be recognised by Dorchester's 19th century rural romantic novelist Thomas Hardy.</p>
<p>Sheep graze in a field outside a converted Victorian farmhouse occupied by a U.S. high-technology firm SMTech.</p>
<p>Wrought-iron wall lamps shed an orange glow at night. All Poundbury lacks are thatched roofs and horses in the streets.</p>
<p>Critics, many of them victims of royal wrath, call it &quot;retrophilia&quot;, pastiche and Disneyland.</p>
<p>&quot;It's ambitions are simply retrogressive. It simulates a world of the past and a hierarchy in architecture that doesn't really have a place any more,&quot; said architect Piers Gough as building got under way three years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;On the other hand I am glad Prince Charles is building it because at least he can get his teeth into something other than architects. It was about time he either put up or shut up,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>TOURIST ATTRACTION</p>
<p>Despite, or because of, its unique design and royal patronage, Poundbury has already become a tourist attraction in its own right.</p>
<p>&quot;We get tourists, architects, journalists, school trips, you name it,&quot; said Peter Bryant, chairman of the Poundbury resident's association.</p>
<p>&quot;They expect you to jump about and perform a circus act occasionally...that's the only snag with living here,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Poundbury villagers, as they like to call themselves, certainly don't feel as if they are living out someone else's dream, although the social mix of retired people, single mothers, young families and a handful of Canadian and Spanish residents is working just as Charles envisaged.</p>
<p>&quot;There is quite a team spirit, quite a togetherness. We had a bonfire night and a rounders evening and those who couldn't play turned out to cheer,&quot; said Bryant.</p>
<p>&quot;A pub is planned but nobody is rioting in the streets. There is quite a social exchange going on here anyway with people popping into each other's places for a glass of wine, a natter or a coffee,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Charles is still a frequent visitor to Poundbury, keen to see reinforced the principles of creating a village atmosphere with a sense of identity in an urban context.</p>
<p>Poundbury's shopping, leisure, workplace and housing will be closely integrated in a move away from the thinking behind Britain's 1950s &quot;new towns&quot; where factories and shops were well separated from homes.</p>
<p>Furniture restorer Spencer Robertson welcomes the chance to have a workshop in Poundbury with both character and central heating.</p>
<p>&quot;Most workshops are out on industrial estates and are just like double garages. But I'm a little disappointed that there are not more craftsmen here. There was a bakery, but that closed down for lack of trade,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Charles has said his aim in promoting a return to traditional building on a human scale is so that his children will inherit a &quot;less ugly and less ecologically damaged world.&quot;</p>
<p>Bryant, enjoying an idyllic retirement in Poundbury, has less lofty hopes.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm just grateful that he (Charles) decided to sell off a plot of land and get on with it,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="POUNDBURY, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
