<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662151" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Teachers angered by Prince Charles remarks.</title>
<headline>Teachers angered by Prince Charles remarks.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Reaney</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Prince Charles caused outrage on Sunday when he criticised the country's &quot;failed&quot; education system and said his charity had to bail out students who were victims of trendy teaching methods.</p>
<p>In a BBC television interview to mark the 21st birthday of his Prince's Trust charity, the heir-to-the-throne who is no stranger to controversy spoke about the discipline needed to succeed in life and which seemed to be lacking in education.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe that education needs to rediscover those important features which have been abandoned in the last 30 or 40 years out of a fashionable approach,&quot; he told interviewer David Frost.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't believe it's served young people well at all, in fact in many ways my Trust has been picking up the pieces of a somewhat failed system and I've felt for a long time that it needs a great deal more attention.&quot;</p>
<p>His comments angered education officials, who claimed he had not gotten his facts right and that members of the royal family should not be meddling in political matters.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't know where he is getting his advice from. Standards have never been higher, results have never been better,&quot; Nigel Gates of the Association of University and College Lecturers told ITV television.</p>
<p>Another official accused the prince of being biased and prejudiced. &quot;I am outraged as I'm sure hundreds of thousands of teachers are,&quot; said Nigel de Gruchy of the NASUWT Teacher's Union.</p>
<p>&quot;Does he want to be a politician or a member of the royal family? It is not his role to intervene and furthermore not to intervene in a highly controversial way expressing views which are frankly biased and prejudiced and simply not in accordance with the facts.&quot;</p>
<p>Britain's new Labour government, still enjoying a honeymoon after it ousted the Conservatives in the May 1 election, did its best to play down the controversy.</p>
<p>Education minister Stephen Byers said Charles was right to speak out and that his comments would add to the debate on how to raise education standards.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for Prince Charles preferred not to comment on the controversy.</p>
<p>Sunday's interview was not the first time the 49-year-old prince has left himself open to criticism.</p>
<p>His outspoken views on architecture and his dismissal of a planned modernist extension to London's National Gallery as a &quot;carbuncle on the face of a well-loved friend&quot; have angered professionals.</p>
<p>But his admission of adultery during another Frost television interview in 1995 led to the biggest public backlash against the king-in-waiting. Many Britons regarded the affair with his long-time love Camilla Parker Bowles as a betrayal of his immensely popular then-wife Princess Diana.</p>
<p>The Prince's Trust, one of Britain's most effective and respected charities, helps thousands of unemployed youngsters in Britain's deprived areas. Since it was set up in 1976 almost 500,000 youngsters have benefited from it.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
