<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662247" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia Deputy PM urges quick uranium mine OK.</title>
<headline>Australia Deputy PM urges quick uranium mine OK.</headline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian Deputy Prime Minister Tim Fischer on Sunday urged quick approval for the proposed Jabiluka uranium mine in the Northern Territory to create more jobs.</p>
<p>&quot;We can stuff around and see another mine open in Canada with jobs going to Canada or we can get on with it and have more jobs in Western Australia, Northern Territory and elsewhere from processing Jabiluka properly, but quickly,&quot; he said on Seven Network television.</p>
<p>Energy Resources of Australia Ltd (ERA) is seeking regulatory approval to develop Jabiluka, which is adjacent to its Ranger uranium mine.</p>
<p>But like Ranger the Jabiluka lease is within the Kakadu National Park and development of the mine is opposed by some traditional Aboriginal land owners, who last week launched a legal challenge.</p>
<p>ERA, 68 percent owned by North Ltd, said last week it would shortly lodge a final environmental impact assessment of the mine with Environment Minister Robert Hill.</p>
<p>Development of the mine was impossible until the Liberal-National government won last year's federal election. The former Labor government allowed only three particular uranium mines, one which was defunct.</p>
<p>Australia has about 29 percent of the world's known uranium reserves but only 11 percent of production.</p>
<p>While the &quot;three-mines&quot; policy was in place, preventing new developments, Canada's share of the market increased at Australia's expense.</p>
<p>Fischer's National Party, the junior member of the ruling coalition, strongly supports primary production.</p>
<p>The deputy prime minister argued that the mine was desirable on environmental grounds.</p>
<p>&quot;It helps on the greenhouse gas emission side,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>ERA said last week that it expected approval for the mine in January of or February. Production would begin in 2000.</p>
<p>-- Canberra Bureau 61-6 273-2730</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I15000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
