<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662269" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Educators alarmed as keyring-size craze sweeps HK.</title>
<headline>Educators alarmed as keyring-size craze sweeps HK.</headline>
<byline>Dominic Lau</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>A key problem gripping Hong Kong before Chinese rule in two weeks' time isn't the economy or Sino-British squabbling -- but an electronic egg from the Land of the Rising Sun.</p>
<p>The Japanese-made &quot;virtual pet&quot;, Tamagotchi, is sweeping Hong Kong, with fans paying high prices for the keyring-sized computer game, which &quot;grows to a kind of chicken&quot; if the right buttons are pushed.</p>
<p>Educators and pyschologists have expressed fears that the &quot;death&quot; of a virtual pet will traumatise young children and affect their mental development.</p>
<p>Counselling has been ordered for grieving youngsters.</p>
<p>But a new Tamagotchi game on sale next month, featuring a young triad gangster hero, is set to heighten their concerns.</p>
<p>The owner needs to feed cigarettes and alcohol to this variant &quot;pet&quot; so it matures as a triad (secret society) member. A knife fight is an optional extra.</p>
<p>The new game is based on a popular weekly local comic, Young Triads, chronicling the adventures and sexual exploits of its narrator Chan Ho-nam.</p>
<p>The original comic can only be sold to adults. It is not clear whether the new Tamagotchi will be off-limit to those under 18.</p>
<p>But educators have already called on the government to ban the new game.</p>
<p>The electronic egg, also popular in Japan, hit Hong Kong three months ago. The suggested retail price is HK$150 (US$19) but has since rocketed up to HK$3,000 (US$387) a piece.</p>
<p>Many schools in the territory have banned the Tamagotchi after many students were found playing it during lessons.</p>
<p>The virtual pets require 24-hour attention or they can &quot;die&quot; easily. Many schoolchildren rear their pets even during school lessons.</p>
<p>But educators worry that children did not know how to cope with the death of their &quot;pets&quot;.</p>
<p>As a result the Education Department and non-prfit organisations have decided to provide counselling for pupils unable to deal with the loss.</p>
<p>Counsellors will also help students upset becuse they cannot rear their &quot;pets&quot; during school hours.</p>
<p>But all is not completely lost when the pets die. They can be buried on the Internet and a home page, the Virtual Graveyard for Your Beloved Tamagotchi, on the World Wide Web.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
