<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662270" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesia's Madura calm after fresh violence.</title>
<headline>Indonesia's Madura calm after fresh violence.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Calm returned to the town of Bangkalan on the Indonesian island of Madura on Sunday after a Moslem crowd went on a rampage, burning a shops, a Protestant church and Buddhist temple, residents said.</p>
<p>They said the crowd on the mostly Moslem island off East Java took to the streets around 8 p.m. on Saturday night after a service to commerate the recent death of a local religious leader, also a legislator for the Moslem-backed United Development Party (PPP).</p>
<p>The incident follows a number of violent attacks on government buildings in various towns on Madura since the general election on May 29 was overwhelmingly won by the ruling Golkar party amid claims from the PPP of widespread polling irregularities.</p>
<p>The election campaign before the poll was regarded as the most violent in the country's history with repeated clashes, mostly on the main Java island, between supporters of the ruling Golkar party and the PPP.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not clear why they went on the rampage,&quot; one resident, who declined to identify himself, told Reuters by telephone on Sunday. He said town remained tense with rumours circulating that further violence was planned.</p>
<p>Police in Bangkalan, about 900 km (560 miles) east of Jakarta, confirmed the incident, adding calm had returned to the town. An officer said no one had been killed in the incident. He declined to comment further.</p>
<p>Residents said they believed two government officials had been hurt and admited to the local hospital, but doctors were not immediately available for comment.</p>
<p>They said the crowd was dispersed after riot police arrived from elsehwere on Madura around midnight.</p>
<p>A cinema was burnt to the ground and a number of shops owned by ethnic Chinese were damaged or attacked, they said. Two government vehicles were also burnt, one resident said.</p>
<p>At least eight people were injured, mainly with gunshot wounds, in a riot by PPP supporters in the town of Jember in East Java last week. The rioters were angry that the PPP may not receive any seats in the local legislature after last month's poll.</p>
<p>Golkar received more than 74 percent of the national vote at last month's election, with PPP taking around 23 percent and the fractured Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI) the remaining three percent.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
