<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662254" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: FEATURE - Hanson offers old-time vision to Australia.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Hanson offers old-time vision to Australia.</headline>
<byline>Marie McInerney</byline>
<dateline>ADELAIDE 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian politician Pauline Hanson, at the heart of a growing race row, is offering her country a new vision -- the good old days, before security and certainty were lost.</p>
<p>The tinny sounds of an old-style newsreel herald the arrival of the controversial politician at the launch of her One Nation party at a suburban wedding venue in this south Australian city.</p>
<p>Images of Australians fighting and falling on the battlefields of the two world wars and of Korea and Vietnam are followed by heroic feats in the Antarctic and on Olympic fields.</p>
<p>It is mostly elderly people who fill the 700 seats at the launch of Hanson's party the night of June 11. The audience, sipping soft drinks and coffee in Styrofoam cups, are entertained during the breaks by golden oldies from a cabaret group called Memory Lane.</p>
<p>Many mob Hanson for autographs, and party faithful prompt a sing-along to the tune of &quot;Onward Christian Soldiers&quot; -- renamed &quot;Onward Aussie Battlers&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Pauline is our mouthpiece, pointing out the foe,&quot; they sing hoarsely. &quot;Forward into battle, see how truth will go.&quot;</p>
<p>Leading opinion polls say Hanson, a twice-divorced mother-of-four from conservative Queensland state, is now heading the third largest political force in Australia. POPULIST VIEWS</p>
<p>Her populist views on immigration, multiculturalism and Aboriginal welfare, which have split the nation, are the core of an ever-widening agenda that takes on free trade, economic rationalism, multinationals and the United Nations.</p>
<p>Yes, she tells the crowd, she will support referenda on immigration, on whether Australia should change its flag or become a republic.</p>
<p>Oh yes, she says, she would cut Australia's foreign aid. The country had to help itself before it helped others.</p>
<p>&quot;Being a mother of four children, the thing is you must look after your own household first,&quot; she says to heavy applause.</p>
<p>Political correctness has destroyed the right to free speech, &quot;reverse racism&quot; has made the white Anglo-Saxon male the most downtrodden figure in modern Australia, and free trade is destroying Australian manufacturing.</p>
<p>&quot;No-one controls me,&quot; the redheaded former chip shop-owner tells the crowd. &quot;If my husbands could not, do you think anybody else would have a chance?&quot;</p>
<p>NOT A RACIST</p>
<p>Hanson, who thinks Australia could be swamped by Asians, denies she is racist, saying she was critical of Aboriginal welfare funding because it defined need on a racial basis, not according to the individual.</p>
<p>&quot;Criticism is not racism, patriotism is not racism,&quot; she says.</p>
<p>And when she spoke of Asian gang-related crime, particularly drug trafficking, that did not mean all Asian-Australians were criminals but just acknowledged that most of these problems came from &quot;one section of the community&quot;.</p>
<p>These criminals were afforded protection through the closed and secretive nature of Asian communities here, where failure by many to assimilate had created little pockets &quot;more like parts of other countries than suburbs of Australia&quot;, she said.</p>
<p>Whose idea was it, she asked, to spend A$10 million (US$7.5 million) a year on helping new Australians maintain their native languages?</p>
<p>&quot;This is not the Australia in which we were born, it is not the Australia we grew up in, it is not the Australia so many found when they first decided to make this place their home,&quot; she told cheering supporters. STRIKING A CHORD</p>
<p>Talkback radio in the town resounded with her views before and after the launch of One Nation.</p>
<p>One woman complained she had been verbally abused by an Aboriginal but that it was a criminal offence to return the abuse. Another asked how politicians could talk of migrants creating demand for goods when she herself could not afford a new lounge.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, thousands of protesters took to Adelaide's quiet streets, with one radio caller declaring that Hanson represented &quot;the real voice of the Australian people -- pig ignorant, a chip on both shoulders and pugnacious to boot&quot;.</p>
<p>Stumbling occasionally during her speech, Hanson was more relaxed taking questions from the crowd, declaring that she had no ambition to be a polished politician and that she could not explain why she struck such fear into her opponents.</p>
<p>&quot;I have got six brothers and sisters and I am the quiet one of the family,&quot; she laughed. &quot;You have not met my mother yet!&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ADELAIDE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
