<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662460" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Vintage cars recreate 100-year-old journey.</title>
<headline>Vintage cars recreate 100-year-old journey.</headline>
<byline>Jay Miller</byline>
<dateline>CLEVELAND 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>A group of 11 nearly century-old cars set off on Sunday to re-enact a landmark 1897 cross-country road trip that helped popularise a new mode of transportation in America -- the automobile.</p>
<p>Two of the cars were driven by great-grandsons of Alexander Winton, who made the 700-mile (1,130-km) trip from Cleveland, Ohio, to New York City over the rough roads of 100 years ago in an experimental motor car.</p>
<p>A crowd of several hundred car buffs, family members and the curious gathered on Cleveland's Public Square to cheer on participants in the commemorative journey, called &quot;The Winton Centennial.&quot;</p>
<p>Winton, whose Cleveland company built most of the cars making the current trip, had hoped the long journey would prove to a sceptical public the reliability of the new form of transportation.</p>
<p>On July 28, 1897, he and his shop superintendent, William A. Hatcher, set out for New York, arriving on August 7 largely unnoticed after 78 hours and 43 minutes of driving.</p>
<p>Winton was disappointed by the continuing obscurity of motor transportation, but by March 1898 he completed what is considered to be the first car sale in the United States.</p>
<p>That year he sold 21 cars and eight delivery wagons. Winton continued to improve both his vehicles and his marketing, advertising in &quot;Scientific American&quot; and taking a second reliability run to New York in May 1899.</p>
<p>That drive took 47 hours and 34 minutes. As important as the shortened driving time was the presence of Charles B. Shanks, a reporter for the Cleveland Plain Dealer, who sent back reports that appeared in about 30 newspapers.</p>
<p>The publicity generated by the trip stimulated interest and sales in motor vehicles in the United States. Shanks' use of the French term &quot;automobile&quot; in his reports fixed that word in the American psyche.</p>
<p>The Winton company reached its peak in 1920, selling 2,500 cars. It stopped making vehicles in 1924, but a successor diesel engine-making company was bought by General Motors Corp. in 1930.</p>
<p>The commemorative trip is led by Charles F. Wake of Sarasota, Florida, and James A. Winton Jr., of Rocky River, Ohio, great grandsons of Alexander Winton. Wake is driving a 1899 Winton, and Winton is driving a 1916.</p>
<p>At the wheel of a 1921-vintage Winton is James R. Garfield, great-grandson of President James A. Garfield, who grew up in northeastern Ohio.</p>
<p>The commemorative journey also will include Wintons built in 1903, two 1904s, a 1906, 1907, and three 1912s. The oddball is a 1930s-era Chevrolet.</p>
<p>Wake, who posed for pictures in his leather driving helmet, goggles and long driving coat, said a Winton registry had located about 100 Wintons, most not drivable.</p>
<p>He spent six years planning the trip and getting the cars in running shape. &quot;Many of these cars hadn't been driven in many years, so we had to update them,&quot; Winton said.</p>
<p>The updating won't speed the journey very much, which is expected to take seven days of eight-hours-a-day driving. Top speed of the 1897 model is about 20 mph (32 kph).</p>
<p>The group is expected to arrive in New York on June 22.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CLEVELAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
