<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662438" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>EGYPT: FEATURE - Egypt's Jews cling to remnants of their community.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Egypt's Jews cling to remnants of their community.</headline>
<byline>Christine Hauser</byline>
<dateline>ALEXANDRIA, Egypt 1996-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Jewish community in Egypt is slowly dying.</p>
<p>The only signs of life at the century-old Menasce temple in this port city are boys playing at a vacant guard post next to its rusty gates.</p>
<p>The temple is locked, the windows broken. Old bedding litters the yard.</p>
<p>The community's Jewish school is now an Arabic school and only the Hebrew letters on the walls serve as a reminder of its former role.</p>
<p>&quot;The Jewish community became too few. They went abroad,&quot; said Victor Balassiano, a former teacher.</p>
<p>For the weekly Sabbath prayer, not even the quorum of 10 men can be rounded up from the leftover Jewish population.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no Sabbath prayer. On the feasts a rabbi comes from Israel. He brings with him some men,&quot; said Balassiano, one of the few men left in Alexandria's Jewish community.</p>
<p>As if too few men weren't bad enough, the ones who remain are getting old. &quot;Unfortunately we lost two old men a few months ago,&quot; said Balassiano.</p>
<p>The dwindling Jewish population in Egypt is trying to keep its community alive by clinging to the remnants of what was once one of the Arab world's most flourishing Jewish societies.</p>
<p>DECLINING NUMBERS</p>
<p>The community has fallen to no more than 80 people shared between Alexandria and Cairo from about 70,000 at its peak in 1947, historians say.</p>
<p>Many brush off suggestions that tense relations with Israel, most recently over the Middle East peace process, are all to blame.</p>
<p>&quot;Anti-Semitism? Against 50 old women?&quot; said 72-year-old Lina Mattatia, administrator at Alexandria's Jewish community centre.</p>
<p>From his quiet room at an Alexandria nursing home, Salomon Nathan, in his 80s, musters some spirit.</p>
<p>&quot;I tell Lina that if she is one-tenth away from holding a prayer in the synagogue, I will make every effort to be there.&quot;</p>
<p>JEWISH DEPARTURE HAS TAKEN ITS TOLL</p>
<p>The exodus of Jews from Egypt was prompted by Arab-Israeli conflict, especially in the 1950s and 1960s, said Yoram Meital, Middle East Studies professor at Israel's Ben Gurion University.</p>
<p>&quot;There are difficulties...a lot of psychological barriers that developed during the war years and they're still affecting many sides of the relations between Egypt and Israel,&quot; he said. &quot;Of course this includes the question of Jewish life in Egypt.&quot;</p>
<p>Mattatia says the Jewish community in Alexandria is active in charity work and receives support from groups abroad.</p>
<p>But there are signs that the Jewish departure has taken its toll.</p>
<p>About a dozen centuries-old synagogues, schools and Jewish institutions which were sold or closed as the community shrank now live on only in faded photographs in an oversized album in the office of community centre president Joseph Harari.</p>
<p>Former rabbis look down from portraits on the walls of the vacant chief rabbi's office. Dusty cupboards spill over with ledgers of death certificates dating back more than half a century.</p>
<p>Jewish community sources think that the last time Cairo and Alexandria had a chief rabbi was in the 1960s.</p>
<p>The only other surviving synagogue in Alexandria is well-tended by its Moslem caretaker Abdel-Zaher. But it too betrays that the once-thriving Jewish community is fading.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very well kept even though there is no service,&quot; said Mattatia as she draws back the curtain covering the Ark, its wooden doors gleaming with silver Hebrew letters.</p>
<p>Inside, more than 20 Torah scrolls in elaborate casings are packed together in the gloom like huddled refugees.</p>
<p>&quot;We brought the Torahs here from synagogues which were closed,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;What does it mean? It means that the community is dying out. It's as simple as that,&quot; said Shimon Shamir, professor of Middle East history from a Tel Aviv university, on a visit to Cairo.</p>
<p>JEWS CONTRIBUTED TO ECONOMY AND SOCIETY</p>
<p>Jews have lived in Egypt for thousands of years. But around the turn of the century a wave of Jewish families emigrated from Europe and Palestine to add to their numbers, said Meital.</p>
<p>They set up banks and railways and contributed to other aspects of society, speakers told a recent seminar in Cairo on Jewish history.</p>
<p>Historians say waves of Jews left Egypt after Israel was set up in 1948. More followed with the ups and downs of Arab-Israeli relations -- in 1956, 1967 and 1973.</p>
<p>Between 1949 and 1951, 15,000 to 20,000 Egyptian Jews emigrated to Israel, historians say.</p>
<p>The current population is hard to pinpoint.</p>
<p>Meital said, &quot;Each time I come here I hear, 'This one passed away'. My estimation, only a personal estimation, is that we have something like between 60 to 80 in Cairo and Alexandria. Total.&quot;</p>
<p>Israel and Egypt signed a peace treaty in 1979. Their ties recently have been frosty over differences in the peace process between Israelis and Palestinians and Israeli settlement policy.</p>
<p>&quot;You can say whatever you want about the political situation but there is no hate,&quot; said Nathan. But growing up &quot;there was anti-Zionism. That's another thing. They want their land.&quot;</p>
<p>COMMUNITY FACES CHALLENGES</p>
<p>Robert Nahman, aged 80, said: &quot;There are no small boys and girls. There are only four men. There is no future at all here. It is far bigger than a tragedy.&quot;</p>
<p>Carmen Weinstein, a board member of the Jewish Community of Cairo, said Jewish groups abroad want some of the Torahs still in Egypt sent out.</p>
<p>&quot;We are still here and still a community in Cairo despite what everybody is saying,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Community president Esther Weinstein said in an open letter they had no quorum of 10 men but &quot;we have Jewish tourists by the thousands...eager to visit the Jewish patrimony&quot;. She said Egyptian Jews abroad should offer to repair monuments.</p>
<p>&quot;Taking the Jewish Sefarims (Torahs), books, records, out of Egypt because there are very few of us left is tantamount to saying Egypt should demolish the pyramids and Temple of Luxor because there are no pharaohs left,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;If there is one Jew living in all of Egypt, nothing can be taken away,&quot; she told Reuters.</p>
<p>Meital takes an historical perspective. &quot;Heritage can survive centuries after people pass away. If we are talking about Jewish persons who are living in Egypt, this is definitely one of the last historical days of this community.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EGYPT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ALEXANDRIA, Egypt"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="EGYPT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
