<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662473" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Naomi Campbell quits hospital after emergency care.</title>
<headline>Naomi Campbell quits hospital after emergency care.</headline>
<byline>Merissa Marr</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>British supermodel Naomi Campbell was discharged from a hospital in the Canary Islands on Sunday after receiving emergency treatment for what a hospital official described as a drug overdose.</p>
<p>The 26-year-old model's lawyers denied she had overdosed and insisted she had been rushed to hospital after an allergic reaction to antibiotics.</p>
<p>Officials at the hospital on the Spanish island of Gran Canaria said the 26-year-old model was treated in the intensive care unit in the early hours of Sunday, but had made a steady recovery and was released on Sunday evening.</p>
<p>&quot;Naomi Campbell was discharged from the hospital shortly after 10.00 p.m. (2000 GMT),&quot; a nurse told Reuters.</p>
<p>A hospital official earlier said Campbell had been admitted into intensive care after some kind of &quot;overdose&quot;. The hospital would not reveal further details of Campbell's condition, but local media reported that she had taken sedatives.</p>
<p>However, a spokesman for Campbell, Jonathan Goldstein of law firm Olswang, ruled out any kind of overdose.</p>
<p>&quot;Ms Campbell is perfectly well and fully recovered and will be leaving hospital later today,&quot; Olswang said earlier.</p>
<p>&quot;She wishes to make it clear that there is absolutely no foundation whatsoever to the story that she had taken an overdose,&quot; he said in a statement issued to Britain's Press Association news agency.</p>
<p>Local media reported that Campbell had arrived on the island on Friday on the same plane as her boyfriend, 28-year-old flamenco dancer Joaquin Cortes.</p>
<p>At around 0200 GMT on Sunday she was taken semi-conscious from her five-star hotel in the island capital Las Palmas to the Nuestra Senora del Pino hospital, officials said.</p>
<p>Local media said the catwalk model had earlier had an argument with Cortes, who is in Gran Canaria with his hugely successful &quot;Gypsy Passion&quot; dance show.</p>
<p>Residents at the luxury hotel, where Campbell and Cortes had been staying in separate rooms, had reportedly complained about a heated conversation between the two.</p>
<p>Hotel staff said Campbell had appeared extremely nervous after the discussion and had taken some form of medicine, local media reported. The hotel would not comment on the reports.</p>
<p>Cortes arrived at the hospital on Sunday afternoon dressed in black to visit the supermodel, who commands tens of thousands of dollars for a morning's work.</p>
<p>He spent several hours at the hospital and left later to star in his hit show at a local theatre.</p>
<p>Local media reported that Campbell left the hospital by the kitchen exit and fled in a Mercedes car to the airport.</p>
<p>It was not clear where the supermodel was headed, but a spokesman for Campbell at the hospital earlier said she intended to fly to Paris.</p>
<p>Campbell has been linked to the long-haired flamenco star, dubbed &quot;sex on legs&quot; for his steamy dancing, for several months.</p>
<p>But gossip magazines recently reported that the Spanish dancer had broken up with Campbell and was pictured with another woman on holiday in the southern resort of Marbella.</p>
<p>His &quot;Gypsy Passion&quot; show is thrilling audiences across Europe and North America with erotic dancing which blends flamenco, ballet and jazz.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
