<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662482" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Naomi Campbell in Spanish hospital after overdose.</title>
<headline>Naomi Campbell in Spanish hospital after overdose.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>British supermodel Naomi Campbell was admitted to hospital in the Canary Islands on Sunday after taking a drugs overdose, hospital officials said.</p>
<p>Officials at the hospital on the island of Gran Canaria said the 26-year-old model was treated in the intensive care unit at the hospital in the early hours of Sunday, but could be discharged within hours.</p>
<p>&quot;Naomi Campbell is now in a stable state and may be able to be released in the next few hours,&quot; a spokeswoman at the hospital in the capital Las Palmas told Reuters.</p>
<p>Hospital officials would make no further comment but said a news conference would be held either later on Sunday or Monday.</p>
<p>Local media reported that Campbell had arrived on the island on Friday by plane with her boyfriend, 28-year-old flamenco dancer Joaquin Cortes.</p>
<p>She was taken from her five-star hotel at around 0400 GMT to the Nuestra Senora del Pino hospital.</p>
<p>Local media said the catwalk model had earlier had an argument with Cortes, who is in Gran Canaria during a tour of his hugely successful &quot;Gypsy Passion&quot; dance show.</p>
<p>The two, who were staying in the same hotel but in separate rooms, were spotted strolling in Las Palmas on Saturday. Local agency Europa Press said they had planned to take a trip on a yacht on Sunday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
