<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662425" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Iran centrists plan to form political party.</title>
<headline>Iran centrists plan to form political party.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>An influential group of Iranian centrists and technocrats who helped elect moderate cleric Mohammad Khatami as Iran's next president said they would soon form a political party.</p>
<p>The Servants of Construction, also known as the Group of Six (G6), said they hoped there would be no legal impediment to Interior Ministry approval, Iranian newspapers said on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;A formal announcement of the political party will be made after two months,&quot; Iran News daily quoted a source close to the centrists as saying.</p>
<p>The reason was that they expected it would be easier to form a political party after Khatami's inauguration in August as President Akbar Hashemi Rafsanjani's successor, newspapers said.</p>
<p>The group, formed ahead of March 1996 parliamentary elections, includes Vice-President Mohammed Hashemi, Central Bank Governor Mohsen Nourbaksh and Tehran mayor Gholamhussein Karbaschi.</p>
<p>Iranian newspapers said four more prominent politicians had joined including Faezeh Hashemi, Rafsanjani's daughter who was elected to parliament for the first time last year.</p>
<p>Political parties were banned in Iran after the 1979 Islamic revolution. Groups or factions, such as G6, form to support individual politicians.</p>
<p>Others include the Association of Militant Clergy, a group of conservative Shi'ite Moslem clerics including parliament speaker Ali Akbar Nateq-Nouri, who was heavily defeated in the May 23 presidential election.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
