<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662523" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Dead but rich -- 30,000 disabled Italians.</title>
<headline>Dead but rich -- 30,000 disabled Italians.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Italian government has been paying disability pensions to 30,000 dead people, some of whom passed away years ago, according to newspaper reports on Sunday.</p>
<p>They said the payments, which in some cases had probably been cashed by relatives, had been stopped after a Treasury census of 1.4 million Italians who have been drawing state disability pensions.</p>
<p>In addition to the 30,000 deceased, 140,000 of the pensioners had failed to return their census forms.</p>
<p>Their payments would be suspended in November and they would then have three months to complete the forms or have the pensions stopped for good, senior Treasury official Michelangelo Bergamini told Corriere della Sera newspaper.</p>
<p>&quot;It's difficult to give a forecast, but I believe that when (the exercise) is completed, 70,000 to 80,000 pensions will have been stopped, including those paid to the 30,000 dead and another 1,000 people who say they've been cured,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The newspaper estimated that annual savings would range from 280 billion to 700 billion lire ($164 million to $410 million).</p>
<p>Disability pensions are paid to a further 4.7 million Italians by state insurance fund INAIL and welfare fund INPS.</p>
<p>Stories abound of able-bodied Italians doing jobs and banking disability payments thanks to bogus medical certificates or favours from corrupt politicians in the past.</p>
<p>The system was rife for abuse because disabled Italians get not only payments but also access to jobs through a quota system that obliges public sector employers to hire a certain number of disabled.</p>
<p>Corriere said around 131,000 Italians drawing disability pensions had been obliged to undergo medical examinations to determine the validity of their payment.</p>
<p>Of those 30,000, or more than one in five, had had payments stopped or been advised they would cease, it added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
