<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="662593" id="root" date="1997-06-15" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Tobacco negotiators see make-or-break week.</title>
<headline>Tobacco negotiators see make-or-break week.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-06-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Gail Appleson, Law Correspondent</p>
<p>Negotiators are entering what they believe will be a make-or-break week to settle the huge claims against the tobacco industry as they try to reach a deal before the first state Medicaid case goes to trial.</p>
<p>State officials and tobacco representatives are scheduled to resume talks on Monday in Washington in a bid to resolve difficult issues that remain unresolved, including whether cigarette makers can be sued for punitive damages and the Food and Drug Administration's authority to regulate cigarettes.</p>
<p>During a conference call of state attorneys general last week, negotiators were optimistic a settlement proposal could be drafted this week and presented to the White House.</p>
<p>Negotiators are under intense pressure to reach an agreement this week because Mississippi Attorney General Mike Moore, a key player in the talks, will have to leave to prepare for his state's trial scheduled to begin on July 7.</p>
<p>Moore was the first of 37 attorneys general to sue the tobacco industry to recoup Medicaid health care costs of treating smokers. As recently as Thursday, California, the largest state, joined the battle by seeking to recover some $433 million it estimates it spends each year on sick smokers.</p>
<p>&quot;The attorneys general suits are the biggest threat to the industry,&quot; said Matthew Myers, the negotiator representing the health community. Myers is executive vice president of the Campaign for Tobacco-Free Kids, an anti-smoking group.</p>
<p>Legal experts believe Moore has a good chance of winning the state case because of favorable state law and the fact that there will be no jury. It is a big gamble, though, because if the industry wins it might mean defeat in other states where cases are weaker.</p>
<p>Such a scenario would give cigarette makers little reason to stay in settlement talks and could lead to years of costly litigation. If the industry loses the Mississippi case, that would step up the pressure on cigarette makers to settle.</p>
<p>Some health organizations have raised concerns that a settlement would not be in the public interest and set up a committee to monitor the negotiations. The group, chaired by former Surgeon General C. Everett Koop and former FDA Commissioner David Kessler, is scheduled to meet next week.</p>
<p>In the meantime, the American Cancer Society and American Heart Association said last week they would support a pact that contains health care provisions that have tentatively been agreed upon by negotiators. They said a settlement could provide benefits that might never be obtained any other way.</p>
<p>Myers said that the provisions represent &quot;the best of what we know about how to rein in an outlaw industry and reduce the number of people who die from their products.&quot;</p>
<p>Under the terms discussed so far, the industry would set up a fund to pay for awards in individual lawsuits. A final figure has not been decided, but there would be an annual ceiling so the industry would know about how much it would have to pay each year.</p>
<p>In the health area, the industry has agreed to sharp limits on cigarette advertising, including a ban on the use of cartoon characters and human figures.</p>
<p>The industry has agreed to penalties if smoking by youngsters fails to fall 30 percent in five years and 60 percent in 10. Penalties would be based on how much the industry can earn from a teen-age smoker over his or her life.</p>
<p>Cigarette package warnings would also be strengthened to include language such as cigarettes are addictive and can cause fatal lung disease in non-smokers. The warnings will be increased in size and placed on the front of packages.</p>
<p>The industry has also agreed to fund smoking cessation programs and devices for those who cannot afford them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-15"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-15"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
