<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="665769" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S lawmakers agree on kid's health plan.</title>
<headline>U.S lawmakers agree on kid's health plan.</headline>
<byline>Sue Kirchhoff</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A bipartisan group of senators Monday reached agreement on a compromise plan that would deliver health care to up to half the nation's uninsured children through a major expansion of the Medicaid program.</p>
<p>The $16 billion proposal appears to have the votes to pass the key Senate Finance Committee possibly as early as Tuesday, congressional aides said.</p>
<p>It is opposed, however, by committee chairman William Roth of Delaware and Republican leaders who instead want to provide broad grants to states to design their own health programs.</p>
<p>&quot;Right now it looks like a close vote,&quot; said Finance Committee spokeswoman Ginny Flynn.</p>
<p>Even if the compromise, sponsored by Rhode Island Republican John Chafee and West Virginia Democrat Jay Rockefeller, were approved, it would almost certainly face a battle when it reached the full Senate.</p>
<p>The competing health bills are designed to implement a five-year budget deal between Congress and the White House setting aside $16 billion to insure poor children.</p>
<p>The idea of kids' care has been wildly popular in Congress, but the actual mechanics of writing legislation to implement the budget have exposed fault lines between Republicans and the White House and within the Republican party itself.</p>
<p>Conservative Republicans and the National Governors' Association want block grants that states could use to design their own programs. A House panel last week approved such a plan.</p>
<p>Democrats and some moderate Republicans want to work through the Medicaid program for the poor, elderly and disabled. Medicaid already insures 25 percent of U.S. children under age 18. The White House prefers the Chafee approach.</p>
<p>At the same time, some lawmakers want to go beyond the budget to try reach more of the 10 million uninsured children.</p>
<p>Utah Republican Orrin Hatch plans to offer amendments in the Finance Committee to boost the federal tobacco tax to fund a further expansion of health insurance.</p>
<p>Hatch has introduced a bill with Massachusetts Democratic Sen. Edward Kennedy that would increase the cigarette tax by 43 cents a pack to fund grants to states.</p>
<p>A spokesman said Hatch might also offer a smaller tobacco tax increase. &quot;Something is better than nothing,&quot; said spokesman Paul Smith.</p>
<p>The Chafee plan, supported by at least three Republicans on Finance, would allocate $12 billion to expand Medicaid and $4 billion in new grants to states.</p>
<p>The program would be voluntary. To receive new Medicaid funds, states would have to expand the program to all poor children under 18 and keep many kids on the rolls a year at a time, rather than cutting them off if income increased.</p>
<p>The $12 billion could be used to expand Medicaid to children up to 150 percent of poverty, about $24,000 for a family of four.</p>
<p>To be eligible for the block grant, states would have to provide one-year of continuous coverage for poor children up to 133 percent of poverty, about $21,000 for a family of four.</p>
<p>State govenors are leery of the plan, arguing they cannot afford to put up the additional money that would be required to become eligible for the new Medicaid funds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
