<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666170" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>zimbabwe: Japan, Norway lose bid to ease ban on whaling.</title>
<headline>Japan, Norway lose bid to ease ban on whaling.</headline>
<byline>Emelia Sithole</byline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>An international convention on endangered species on Tuesday rejected contentious proposals by Japan and Norway to relax an 11-year ban on commercial whaling.</p>
<p>They failed to win a two-thirds majority in a secret ballot by the 138-member Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) on their bid to resume catches of various whale species which they say are abundant and not endangered.</p>
<p>This is the third time that Japan and Norway have tried and lost their push for a relaxation of the embargo which CITES adopted after the International Whaling Commission (IWC) slapped a moratorium on commercial whaling in 1986.</p>
<p>Last Friday, the conference also rejected a Japanese proposal, backed by Norway, seeking to lessen the CITES' dependence on the IWC which is regarded as the world's foremost authority on whaling issues.</p>
<p>The two countries accused CITES of automatically adopting IWC resolutions and measures to protect whales without taking into account scientific findings on the issue.</p>
<p>They alleged that the IWC had been hijacked by environmental groups with undue political influence.</p>
<p>In a statement to the conference ahead of voting on its proposal on Tuesday, Norway accused the IWC of disregrading scientific findings of its experts which it said supported the view that there were abundant minke whales in the northeast Atlantic and they were not threatened with extinction.</p>
<p>&quot;The IWC does not respect its own scientific committee. CITES shouldn't follow this practice and continue to disregard scientific findings,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Leading international environmental watchdogs at the 10-day conference ending on Friday had been campaigning against the two countries' proposals, saying they would endanger dwindling whale species.</p>
<p>The most vocal on the issue, Amsterdam-based Greenpeace dismissed the two countries' arguments that opponents of a resumption of commercial whaling were rich countries trying to deny the poor access to their natural resources.</p>
<p>&quot;They (Japan and Norway) are two of the richest countries in the world and their economic power and influence on other countries is very much in evidence at this conference,&quot; Isabel McCrea, head of Greenpeace's CITES delegation, said during heated debate ahead of the vote.</p>
<p>While applauding the conference for upholding the whaling embargo, she hit out at Japan's push for secret ballots, saying it went against the principles of transparency and democracy at international conventions.</p>
<p>Norway and Japan asked for secret ballots alleging that some animal rights groups were planning to harass countries which supported their proposals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NORW">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
