<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666240" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>ZIMBABWE: Conference considers appplication for ivory trade.</title>
<headline>Conference considers appplication for ivory trade.</headline>
<dateline>HARARE 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A world conference on endangered species is likely to vote later on Tuesday on a controversial proposal by three southern African states to resume trade in ivory, conference officials said.</p>
<p>Tichaona Jokonya, the Zimbabwe chairman of the 10-day Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) ending on Friday, said he expected the application by Botswana, Namibia and Zimbabwe to be debated during the day.</p>
<p>&quot;We will consider it today in our closed meetings and I think we will have a vote and a decision before the end of the day,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>The proposal, backed by Japan, has been the most controversial at the meeting.</p>
<p>It is fiercely opposed by dozens of international environmental movements and some African and Western countries, including the United States and France, who say ending the 1989 world ban on ivory sales would endanger elephants, not just in southern Africa but around the globe.</p>
<p>But Botswana, Namibia and Zimbabwe say they must be allowed to trade because they have a healthy elephant population, which was growing steadily even before the ivory trade ban and is now over twice the land's carrying capacity.</p>
<p>The three countries' elephant herd is estimated at around 150,000, and their bid is supported by the 12-nation Southern African Development Community to which they belong.</p>
<p>Zimbabwe served notice on Monday that it would defy the world ban on ivory trade if it failed to win an exemption from the CITES conference where it needs the support of at least two-thirds of the 138 members.</p>
<p>Environment and Tourism Minister Chen Chimutengwende said Zimbabwe would not accept a compromise, but environmental pressure groups said Zimbabwe's threat would not influence their position.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BOTS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NAMIB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZIMBAB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARARE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ZIMBABWE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
