<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666292" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Zhirinovsky proposes &quot;Lenin, The Farewell Tour&quot;.</title>
<headline>Zhirinovsky proposes &quot;Lenin, The Farewell Tour&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Vladimir Zhirinovsky's Russian ultra-nationalists have waded into the latest row over the fate of the mummified remains of Lenin by proposing to buy the body from the Kremlin and take it on a money-making roadshow.</p>
<p>Izvestia daily, reporting a news release by Zhirinovsky's LDPR movement in its Wednesday edition, said: &quot;The party has decided to try its hand at the impresario business, organising a farewell tour for the leader of the international proletariat.&quot;</p>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin caused a storm of protest from his communist opponents this month when he renewed his call to remove the 73-year-old mummy from its mausoleum on Red Square and bury it. He said he may hold a referendum on the issue.</p>
<p>The liberal newspaper quoted LDPR spokesman Oleg Lurye as saying the party, which rejects communism and liberalism alike, did not expect the offer to be accepted and so had not figured out exactly how much to offer for the body.</p>
<p>But the nationalists, whose leader is famed for colourful stunts, felt the tour could attract voters and make money from ageing Leninists and youngsters wanting to see the &quot;curiosity&quot;.</p>
<p>Millions of Russians still revere the Bolshevik revolutionary leader, whose remains were turned into the focus of a quasi-religious cult by his successors. But few now visit the tomb by the Kremlin where once thousands queued for hours.</p>
<p>&quot;This news should cause a big jump in visitors...who want to take a look at the mummy while it's still free,&quot; Izvestia said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
