<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666208" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>ETHIOPIA: Ethiopia to import oil products directly.</title>
<headline>Ethiopia to import oil products directly.</headline>
<dateline>ADDIS ABABA 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ethiopia will import refined oil products itself from August instead of using the refinery in the Eritrean port of Assab, officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Ethiopia's products needs stand at 1.6 million tonnes valued at $294 million. It will start importing directly from its main suppliers from August 1, said Yigzaw Mekonnen, general manager of the Ethiopian Petroleum Enterprise.</p>
<p>He said the cost of oil refined at Assab was rising annually whereas world market prices were decreasing.</p>
<p>Gasoline from Assab cost $268 per tonne compared to $224 per tonne for direct imports, Yigzaw told Reuters.</p>
<p>Yigzaw did not explain the rising costs at Assab. He said Ethiopia would issue an international tender for the supply of gasoline and those who won the bid will get the contract.</p>
<p>The origins of Ethiopia's petroleum imports were not immediately known. Direct imports will reach Ethiopia through the Eritrean ports of Massawa and Assab and also via Djibouti.</p>
<p>Yigzaw said that the the decision to import refined oil directly was made following an agreement between the Ethiopian and Eritrean governments regarding &quot;the cost effectiveness of importing (refined) rather than using the refinery at Assab&quot;.</p>
<p>According to previous agreements between the two countries, Ethiopia importeed crude oil which was then refined at Assab.</p>
<p>Ethiopia's needs accounted for 80 percent of the oil refined at Assab while 20 percent went to Eritrea, oil officials said.</p>
<p>Eritrea was a part of Ethiopia until 1993 when it won its independence. The refinery was built for Ethiopia with aid from the then Soviet Union and Eritrea took it over in 1993.</p>
<p>--Addis Ababa ++2511-511058.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ERTRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ETHPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ADDIS ABABA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ETHIOPIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
