<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666308" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Hungarian PM sees no favouritism in Vatican pact.</title>
<headline>Hungarian PM sees no favouritism in Vatican pact.</headline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Gyula Horn on Tuesday defended a pact he is to sign with the Vatican against criticism that it means preferential treatment for Hungary's Roman Catholic church.</p>
<p>&quot;During the amendment of the law (on church financing) we will take into the account the agreement with the Vatican to the maximum extent possible,&quot; Horn told a news conference after meeting the leaders of Hungary's four &quot;historic churches&quot;.</p>
<p>Asked by reporters if there would be any preferential treatment for the Catholic church, Horn responded: &quot;No&quot;.</p>
<p>The four traditional religions in Hungary are Roman Catholic, Reformed, Evangelical and Jewish.</p>
<p>The meeting had been convened to discuss some of the churches' misgivings about financing, such as fears of inadequate funding of church schools and over the distribution of one percent of individuals' income tax which they will be allowed to redirect towards a chosen charity or church.</p>
<p>Hungary plans to amend legislation on church financing this autumn and negotiated an agreement with the Holy See, to be signed on June 20, as only the Vatican is entitled to sign financial agreements concerning Roman Catholic churches.</p>
<p>Horn's coalition partners, the Free Democrats, have criticised the agreement on the grounds that singling out one religion for support might be unconstitutional and could have a negative effect on the funding of other independent schools.</p>
<p>Horn said the parliamentary ratification of the pact with the Vatican required a simple majority, which his Socialists have, and it is up to the Free Democrats how they will vote.</p>
<p>He added that a May 15 government meeting approved the signing of the pact although two ministers voiced their concern about &quot;some aspects of church financing&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
