<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666593" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>CUBA: Dengue fever hits eastern Cuban city.</title>
<headline>Dengue fever hits eastern Cuban city.</headline>
<dateline>HAVANA 1997-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>An outbreak of dengue fever has hit the eastern Cuban city of Santiago de Cuba in the first cases of the disease on the island in 16 years, diplomatic sources said on Monday.</p>
<p>Cuba's communist government has not given any public information on the outbreak of the disease, a tropical illness transmitted by the Aedes Aegypti mosquito. Dengue fever last appeared in Cuba in 1981.</p>
<p>The diplomatic sources said that they had heard there was an outbreak in Santiago de Cuba. Their estimates of how many people have been affected ranged from several hundred cases to up to 1,000.</p>
<p>A Cuban resident of Santiago said several of the city's hospitals were dealing with the illness. He added that preventive measures such as fumigation were underway.</p>
<p>Officials from the Health Ministry's disease control department were not available for comment on Monday. There has been no word of the disease in the state-controlled media.</p>
<p>Dengue fever causes headaches and body aches, high fever and a rash and usually lasts for about one week. In its most serious form, which is rare, the disease can cause haemorrhages and can sometimes be fatal.</p>
<p>The Foreign Ministry sent a note to foreign diplomatic missions in Havana last week asking diplomats to cooperate as their houses would be fumigated in the coming days against the mosquito that carries dengue, as a preventative measure.</p>
<p>The diplomatic sources quoted the note as saying the fumigation was in line with a national campaign to eliminate the &quot;carrier (mosquito) responsible for the appearance of some points of infection of dengue in the country&quot;. However it did not give any further details.</p>
<p>The weekly trade union newspaper Trabajadores published a report two weeks ago urging citizens' cooperation in a campaign to eliminate the Aedes Aegypti mosquito, saying the insect was present in parts of Santiago, Havana and the eastern city of Guantanamo.</p>
<p>The newspaper noted the Aedes Aegypti mosquito is a carrier of dengue fever, but it but did not say any cases of the disease had been reported on the island.</p>
<p>An epidemic of dengue in Cuba 1977-78 involved more than half a million cases. There were several hundred thousand cases in another outbreak in 1981.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAVANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CUBA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
