<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666517" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chile to defend salmon producers in U.S. spat.</title>
<headline>Chile to defend salmon producers in U.S. spat.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Chilean government will defend local salmon producers in a case brought by U.S. salmon farmers who claim their Chilean competitors are receiving state subsidies, said Economy Minister Alvaro Garcia.</p>
<p>&quot;We are putting together the information and we have been in contact with lawyers in the United States who will represent the government,&quot; Garcia told a news conference.</p>
<p>Garcia said the government is working closely with Chile's private salmon farmers to obtain the information necessary to respond to the allegations.</p>
<p>U.S. farmers have accused Chilean producers of illegally dumping salmon in the American market and of receiving government subsidies.</p>
<p>The government will focus its attention on the subsidy claims which relate to it directly, said Garcia.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the area in which the state must respond,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>To prove dumping charges, the accuser must generally show that the producer is selling below cost, or below the cost at which it sells the product in its home market.  </p>
<p>Garcia said he will travel to the United States July 15 to meet with U.S. Commerce Secretary William Daley to discuss the simmering trade dispute.</p>
<p>In the past 15 years, Chile has become a major producer of farmed salmon. Output has gone from virtually zero in the last 1970s to about 100,000 tonnes in 1995, making it the world's second largest producer of farmed salmon after Norway.</p>
<p>U.S. consumers account for 30 percent of Chile's total salmon exports, with shipments to the American market worth around $180 million.</p>
<p>((-- Paulina Modiano, Santiago newsroom, 562-699-5595x212))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
