<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666742" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Fan says Patten is Hong Kong's last emperor.</title>
<headline>Fan says Patten is Hong Kong's last emperor.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The president of the Beijing-selected Hong Kong legislature flung a dart at Britain's departing Governor Chris Patten on Tuesday, describing him as the &quot;last emperor&quot; in the colony's 156 year history.</p>
<p>Rita Fan, who presides over the 60-strong shadow chamber selected by Beijing to replace the present elected legislature, said Patten, like his previous colonial predecessors, was the absolute ruler of Hong Kong.</p>
<p>In contrast, she said Hong Kong's new leader Tung Chee-hwa, selected by a 400-strong committee, would be very different as his power would be checked by her legislature.</p>
<p>Fan said Patten and his adminstration were sending misleading messages to Western countries about her legislature being &quot;handpicked&quot; and &quot;controlled&quot; by China.</p>
<p>&quot;(Patten is) the most authoritive person in Hong Kong, the ruler of Hong Kong ... our emperor, the last emperor,&quot; she told reporters.</p>
<p>The interim chamber has been attacked by Britain and Hong Kong democrats as a rollback of freedom in the colony.</p>
<p>British Prime Minister Tony Blair and U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright will not join the chamber's swearing-in on July 1, though they are going to attend the handover ceremony held shortly before it.</p>
<p>The Democratic Party had tried to seek an legal injunction to stop the body from passing bills before the handover but the application was turned down by the court last week.</p>
<p>Hong Kong will return to China and become a Special Administrative Region under Chinese rule on July 1.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
