<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666880" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: El Nino droughts in S. Africa, Australia -- U.S. officials say.</title>
<headline>El Nino droughts in S. Africa, Australia -- U.S. officials say.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A strong &quot;El Nino&quot; weather pattern now developing in the tropical Pacific will trigger cooler- and wetter-than-normal weather in the Southern U.S this winter and drought conditions in South Africa, Northeastern Brazil and Australia, U.S. officials said Tuesday.</p>
<p>At a briefing for reporters, Ants Leetmaa, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Climate Prediction Center, said El Nino has already triggered a drought in India this summer, as evidenced by the weak start to that country's annual monsoon.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a big event,&quot; Leetmaa said, referring to the size of the latest El Nino, a warm ocean temperature phenomenon that occurs approximately every two to seven years with profound consequences for global weather.</p>
<p>Leetma added his personal prediction that the Southeastern U.S. would experienced hotter- and dryer-than-normal conditions this summer.</p>
<p>But in general, scientists at the Climate Prediction Center are uncomfortable drawing conclusions about summer US weather based on the presence of an El Nino because not enough is known yet about the links between the two, Leetma said.</p>
<p>At a press conference Tuesday, Leetmaa reiterated many of the points contained in the Climate Prediction Center's monthly El Nino update released last week on its Internet home page.</p>
<p>In addition to the wetter, cooler weather expected in the Southern half of the U.S. from November through March, the northern U.S. from Washington east to the Western Great Lakes will be warmer-than-normal over the same period, Leetmaa said.</p>
<p>&quot;In Australia, we anticipate the dryness we're seeing is going to develop into a full-scale drought&quot; during its summer season in November through March, when the Australian monsoon normally appears, he said.</p>
<p>Drought conditions are also expected in Northeastern Brazil and South Africa during the same time period, Leetma said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, &quot;record-breaking floods&quot; now occuring in Northern Chile and stretching across to the other side of South America indicate the type of weather that could develop in the Southern half of the U.S. next winter, he said.</p>
<p>El Nino also is associated with flooding in the Midwest, the most dramatic example being the huge Mississippi river floods of 1993, Leetmaa said.</p>
<p>&quot;We certainly don't anticipate, at this stage,... anything like the 1993 flooding,&quot; Leetma said.</p>
<p>But there is &quot;some suggestion&quot; that above-normal precipitation could occur in areas, such as Texas up to the Pacific Northwest, where below-normal temperatures are expected next winter, he said.</p>
<p>((Doug Palmer -- 202 898 8341))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
