<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666819" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>MOROCCO: Islamic body urges Moslems to ban human cloning.</title>
<headline>Islamic body urges Moslems to ban human cloning.</headline>
<byline>Ali Bouzerda</byline>
<dateline>CASABLANCA 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A meeting of Islamic religious experts and scholars urged Moslem countries on Tuesday to ban human cloning but to allow the process to be used for animals and plants.</p>
<p>A spokesman for the Islamic Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (ISESCO), which sponsored a four-day forum of delegates from 12 countries, told the closing session:</p>
<p>&quot;The symposium recommends the ban of normal human cloning unless exceptional cases occur in future which will then require the Sharia (Islamic law) permission.&quot;</p>
<p>The Religious and Medical Symposium, co-sponsored by ISESCO, in Casablanca issued a series of recommendations related to the &quot;Islamic view on modern medical issues, including human cloning&quot;.</p>
<p>Among these was a call for ISESCO members to follow up human cloning, scientific findings and to meet &quot;to determine the Sharia view on these issues&quot;.</p>
<p>The Casablanca meeting said it agreed on the principle of &quot;cloning techniquess and genetic engineering in the field of animals and plants&quot;.</p>
<p>Earlier, ISESCO director-general Abdulaziz Othman Altwaijri of Saudi Arabia called on delegates to find a &quot;religious-and-science based Islamic perception&quot; to give guidance on the issue of human cloning.</p>
<p>He said the ever-accelerating pace and acute competition among scientific researchers provided &quot;evidence that science is treading an unsafe path and evolving towards immoral objectives&quot;.</p>
<p>The Casablanca meeting urged Islamic governments &quot;to draw up the necessary legislation to close doors directly and indirectly in the face of foreign research institutions and experts to stop them using Islamic countries as a field for human cloning experiments and its publicity&quot;.</p>
<p>According to an Egyptian delegate, some ISESCO members during the four-day discussions would not discuss the cloning issue because &quot;it was not mentioned by the holy (Moslem) Koran&quot;.</p>
<p>Others were more flexible and wanted see science pursue its experiments on animals and plants before taking a final stand, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a negative position to simply close the door and adopt a rigid position against human cloning...We should wait and see..,&quot; said another delegate.</p>
<p>The Casablanca recommendations are not considered as a final &quot;fatwa&quot; -- religious ruling -- nor a final scientific opinion.</p>
<p>ISESCO is joining the world community in moving towards setting up rules for scientific research in the field of genetic engineering, including human cloning, the organisation said.</p>
<p>The organisation is a cultural arm of the Organisation of the Islamic Conference.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CASABLANCA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MOROCCO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
