<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666883" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Veterans say McVeigh entitled to military burial.</title>
<headline>Veterans say McVeigh entitled to military burial.</headline>
<byline>Deborah Zabarenko</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Convicted bomber Timothy McVeigh, who at times seemed at war with the U.S. government, is entitled to burial with full military honours in a national cemetery, a veterans affairs official said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Like all honourably discharged U.S. military veterans, McVeigh has the right by law to be buried alongside American heroes, according to Linda Stalvey of the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA), which administers such benefits.</p>
<p>The fact that McVeigh, a Gulf War veteran, was convicted in the April 19, 1995, bombing of the Oklahoma City federal building does not revoke this right, nor does the fact that a federal jury sentenced him to death for the crime, she said.</p>
<p>During his federal trial for the bombing, which killed 168 people, McVeigh's lawyers stressed his political beliefs, admitting he bombed the Alfred P. Murrah building in Oklahoma City in rage over the federal government's fiery onslaught on the Branch Davidian cult complex in Waco, Texas, in 1993.</p>
<p>&quot;There is nothing under current law that would revoke his burial eligibility,&quot; Stalvey said. There are certain crimes -- treason, sedition, aiding the enemy, spying and harbouring spies -- that do eliminate that right, but some of these must be committed during the individual's military service for the burial eligibility to be taken away, she added.</p>
<p>In a moved aimed at McVeigh, a Michigan congressman said on Tuesday he would offer a bill to prevent death penalty convicts from getting a military honours burial at veterans' cemeteries.</p>
<p>&quot;This man was convicted of the worst domestic terrorist attack in the history of the United States,&quot; Republican Representative Joe Knollenberg said in a statement. &quot;I don't think it is right to bury him in sacred ground with the fallen heroes who gave their lives for our freedom.&quot;</p>
<p>It is unlikely McVeigh would be buried in Arlington National Cemetery, which has more limited eligibility than other national cemeteries, but McVeigh's cremated remains could repose in a columbarium at Arlington, according to a VA document.</p>
<p>There are 114 national VA cemeteries. VA burial benefits include the gravesite, opening and closing of the grave and perpetual care, and the U.S. government provides headstones and markers, the document says.</p>
<p>McVeigh's neighbours from Pendleton, New York, recalled a boy who joined the army out of patriotism. His army buddies spoke of a brave soldier who risked his life to save others.</p>
<p>But he left the Army soon after failing to achieve his dream of joining the elite Special Forces. From 1992 to 1995 he drifted around the United States, becoming increasingly drawn to extreme right-wing politics. He also found inspiration in the &quot;Star Wars&quot; movies and thought he was up against an &quot;evil empire&quot; -- the U.S. government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
