<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="666911" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton endorses compromise plan on kid's health.</title>
<headline>Clinton endorses compromise plan on kid's health.</headline>
<byline>Sue Kirchhoff</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Clinton threw his weight Tuesday behind a compromise Senate plan that would deliver health care to up to half the nation's uninsured children through a major expansion of the Medicaid programme.</p>
<p>Clinton said the $16 billion proposal, sponsored by a bipartisan group of senators, would &quot;help to give a lot of our young children a healthy start in life.&quot;</p>
<p>Congressional aides said it appeared to have the votes to pass the key Senate Finance Committee, possibly as early as Tuesday, even though it is opposed by committee chairman Republican William Roth of Delaware and other Senate leaders.</p>
<p>Top congressional Republicans and state governors have been pushing instead to expand health care to many of the nation's 10 million uninsured children through grants that states could use to design their own programmes.</p>
<p>&quot;This legislation would be the biggest investment in children's health care since Medicaid passed in 1965,&quot; Clinton said at an unrelated White House ceremony.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be the most significant thing that we could do ... by committing us to providing health insurance coverage to up to five million uninsured children,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The competing health plans are designed to implement a five-year budget deal between Congress and the White House by setting aside $16 billion to insure poor children.</p>
<p>Even if the compromise were approved, it would almost certainly face a battle when it reached the full Senate. The compromise was sponsored by Rhode Island Republican John Chafee and West Virginia Democrat Jay Rockefeller.</p>
<p>A House committee has already passed its version of the children's health bill, which provides block grants to states. The White House argues the House approach is too broad because it allows states to fund services rather than health insurance.</p>
<p>The National Governors' Association supports the House plan and says states could not afford to put up the additional money that would be required to become eligible for expanded Medicaid funds under the Chafee plan.</p>
<p>&quot;In many cases it would be so expensive for states to meet the preconditions that participation will prove impossible,&quot; governors said in a letter to Congress.</p>
<p>Democrats argue that Medicaid, which already insures a quarter of the nation's children, is the most effective way to reach uninsured kids -- and provide consistent care.</p>
<p>Roth unveiled changes to his grant plan Tuesday as the Finance Committee opened debate on mammoth budget legislation to make $115 billion in Medicare savings, $13.6 billion in Medicaid savings and fund new welfare initiatives.</p>
<p>Under Roth's revised plan, states would have to agree to expand Medicaid to poor children through age 18 before they could have access to the block grant money.</p>
<p>The Chafee plan allocates $12 billion to expand Medicaid and $4 billion in new grants to states. To receive new Medicaid funds, states would have to expand the programme to all poor children under 18 and keep many kids on the rolls a year at a time, rather than cutting them off if income increased.</p>
<p>The Finance Committee is expected to work late Tuesday and most of Wednesday, with nearly 300 amendments pending. Debate opened on a bipartisan tone though there were rumblings.</p>
<p>Oklahoma Republican Sen. Don Nickles complained the bill used accounting sleight of hand to extend the solvency of the Medicare programme. &quot;It's a shell game and I'm not proud of it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In a letter, the White House opposed provisions of the bill to raise the Medicare eligibility age gradually to 67 from 65 and to create a pilot programme allowing up to 500,000 people to set up tax free medical savings accounts as an alternative to traditional Medicare.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
