<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667013" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Scientists urge WTO to back U.S. shrimp import law.</title>
<headline>Scientists urge WTO to back U.S. shrimp import law.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Paul</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Scientists and environmental groups urged the World Trade Organisation on Tuesday to support a U.S. law that bans imports of shrimp caught in nets that also entrap endangered sea turtles.</p>
<p>A trade organisation panel this week is reviewing the law, which requires that all shrimp sold in the United States must be caught in nets that have turtle excluder devices. Without the devices, turtles get entangled in the nets and drown.</p>
<p>&quot;Numerous scientific studies have indicated that shrimp trawling, which incidentally captures and drowns sea turtles in nets, is a major threat to sea turtles,&quot; more than 160 scientists from 24 countries said in a statement to the organisations.</p>
<p>The U.S. embargo was challenged by Thailand, Malaysia, Pakistan and India on the grounds that it discriminated against shrimp exports from countries that do not require turtle protections.</p>
<p>Under international trade rules, countries may not make distinctions between products based on the way they are produced.</p>
<p>But the Clinton administration is arguing that the law is fully consistent with World Trade Organisation rule exceptions that allow countries to impose restrictions needed to protect human, animal or plant life.</p>
<p>U.S. trade officials pointed out that if the U.S. law was a barrier to free trade, imports of shrimp would have fallen since the law went into effect.</p>
<p>However, U.S. imports of shrimp from India and Pakistan rose in 1996 from the previous year; while imports from Thailand were down in 1996 from 1995, they were on par with the average of the previous three years.</p>
<p>Environmentalists raised concern that if the trade organisation ruled against the U.S. law, other laws protecting animals, such as dolphin trapped in tuna nets, could be challenged.</p>
<p>&quot;The World Trade Organisation should respect the value of the scientific method and should not interfere with the ability of countries to take measures that are necessary to protect sea turtles, as well as all other endangered species,&quot; the scientists' statement said.</p>
<p>At least one group was pessimistic that the WTO would come out in favour of the U.S. embargo. &quot;They have never ruled favourably with respect to what are exceptions in WTO rules that allow for protection of the environment,&quot; said Martin Wagner, an attorney for the Sierra Club Legal Defence Fund.</p>
<p>The trade organisation is expected to issue a final decision on the law in December.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
