<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667115" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FDA warns of abortion, sterilization Internet kits.</title>
<headline>FDA warns of abortion, sterilization Internet kits.</headline>
<byline>Deborah Zabarenko</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Do-it-yourself kits promoted on the Internet for home abortions and female self-sterilisations can be lethal and should not be used, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration warned on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The FDA said these products pose &quot;significant, possibly life-threatening risks,&quot; and the sterilisation kit uses drugs not adequately tested on humans for mutations and cancer.</p>
<p>In addition, because the source of the drugs is unknown their purity may be suspect, said Dr. Lisa Rarick, an obstetrician-gynecologist who heads the FDA's division of reproductive and urologic drug products.</p>
<p>The FDA urged consumers not to buy such kits through the Internet or any other way, and noted that U.S. law prohibits the sale and promotion of unapproved medical products.</p>
<p>Possible penalties range from fines and other civil and criminal penalties, depending on how severe the adverse effects of the kits were, FDA spokesman Brad Stone said.</p>
<p>Another danger with both kits is that both abortion and sterilisation require extensive monitoring by health care professionals, which would be lacking, Rarick said in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>The abortion kit inaccurately touts itself as a &quot;complete kit for early pregnancy termination without surgery ... scientifically proved safe and unrisky,&quot; the FDA said.</p>
<p>This kit uses a combination of drugs -- methotrexate and misoprostol -- not approved by the FDA to terminate pregnancy, and an FDA health assessment found that using the kit without a doctor's supervision could cause heavy vaginal bleeding or even death.</p>
<p>In addition, birth defects can result if a pregnancy is carried to term after taking these drugs.</p>
<p>&quot;Certainly the risk with the abortion kit is that there are specific conditions for use of these kind of products,&quot; Rarick said. &quot;You usually have to see your doctor three times, and they can't be used after certain pregnancy dates. It's an involved process that involves counselling.&quot; This process would not be followed with the home kit, she said.</p>
<p>The self-sterilisation kit for women claims to use a method similar to inserting an intra-uterine contraceptive device and to have a lower risk than surgical sterilisation, according to the FDA statement.</p>
<p>But Rarick said the kit uses pellets of quinacrine hydrochloride, an unapproved drug that can cause ectopic pregnancy, other abnormal pregnancies and permanent damage to reproductive organs.</p>
<p>If used as designed, the pellets would be inserted into the uterus, where they would produce a chemical burn that left scarring which would permanently close the fallopian tubes, preventing future pregnancies, Rarick said.</p>
<p>The method has been used in Vietnam, she said, but she noted that usually two doses of the drug, administered a month apart, are required for sterilisation. Rarick also said inadequate testing had been performed on the drug's safety for humans.</p>
<p>The drug also could be used for coercive sterilisation of women without their knowledge, she said.</p>
<p>Consumers who have been injured or suffered adverse effects as a result of using these kits should call 1-800-FDA-4010. Health professionals who have treated patients suffering such adverse effects should call 1-800-FDA-1088.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I37200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
