<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667144" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Green groups push Clinton on global warming.</title>
<headline>Green groups push Clinton on global warming.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Environmentalists urged U.S. President Bill Clinton on Tuesday to use a speech at the United Nations next week to take the &quot;high ground&quot; in talks to curb global warming.</p>
<p>&quot;If the United States does not move swiftly to reassert its leadership in this area, the unfortunate comparison will inevitably be made between your administration and that of your predecessor,&quot; 14 advocacy groups said in a letter to Clinton.</p>
<p>They said the approach to global warming of the previous administration of President George Bush, defeated in November 1992, had been criticised for &quot;indecisiveness and obstructionism&quot;.</p>
<p>Clinton is to speak June 26 at a U.N. Earth Summit being held to discuss issues including global climate change, deforestation and unsustainable use of natural resources five years after the groundbreaking Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
<p>The advocacy groups urged Clinton to use his speech to make a commitment to legally binding limits on heat-trapping gases from burning fossil fuels at levels that would limit the rise in the earth's average temperature to one degree Celsius.</p>
<p>They also urged him to push policies to reduce emissions below 1990 levels by no later than 2005. Current U.S. carbon emissions are eight percent above 1990 levels, despite voluntary measures to curb emissions launched by the Bush administration.</p>
<p>The Clinton administration in international talks has pushed a system of buying and selling credits to pollute under a legally binding cap as a way to reduce emissions. But the administration has not yet said what the cap should be, and has indicated it wants a later timeframe than 2005.</p>
<p>The environmental groups said the administration &quot;has failed to develop a credible domestic action plan for limiting greenhouse gas emissions.&quot; This, they said, &quot;denies the U.S. the high ground that it staked out last July.&quot;</p>
<p>Groups signing the letter included the Natural Resources Defence Council, the Union of Concerned Scientists and the Sierra Club.</p>
<p>Scientists have cautioned that global warming should be limited to one degree Celsius over the next century to avoid possibly devastating consequences of extreme storms, droughts, rising sea levels and spread of diseases.</p>
<p>The European Union wants industrialised nations to cut emissions to 15 percent below 1990 levels by 2010, a more ambitious plan than the Clinton administration has indicated it wants.</p>
<p>In other developments, environmental groups released a study that said U.S. fossil fuel emissions could be cut to 10 percent below 1990 levels by 2010 by using policies to spur new technologies and more use of renewable energy sources.</p>
<p>Energy costs would drop by $530 per household annually and 800,000 jobs could be created, the study said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
