<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667359" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE-First woman on McKinley marks 50-year anniversary.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-First woman on McKinley marks 50-year anniversary.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>TALKEETNA, Alaska 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>When Barbara Washburn became the first woman to scale North America's tallest peak 50 years ago, she did not think of herself as a pioneer for her gender.</p>
<p>She was a loyal wife accompanying her husband on a summer adventure to explore mysterious Mount McKinley, she said. Brad Washburn, directed by several U.S. government agencies and bankrolled by a movie producer, was launching a lengthy survey that would produce the maps climbers now rely on to tackle the peak Alaskans and mountaineers refer to as Denali, the Athabaskan Indian name meaning &quot;The High One.&quot;</p>
<p>The film's producer, when he learned that Barbara Washburn also was a mountain climber, argued passionately in favour of including her in the project. &quot;He said, 'Can't you persuade your wife to come along, because we'd have a better movie if we had a girl in it?'&quot; she recounted.</p>
<p>In those days, she worried that she would be condemned as a neglectful mother for leaving her three small children at home under their grandparents' care. Instead, she became a mountaineering icon.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see myself that way, but the young women do,&quot; she said as she and her husband were feted in Alaska on the 50th anniversary of their climb this month. &quot;They come up to me and say, you're a role model.&quot;</p>
<p>Young women clutching posters and books for autographs did just that in this tiny town that serves as the launching site for most McKinley expeditions.</p>
<p>WOMEN WERE NOT SUPPOSED TO EXERCISE</p>
<p>In 1947, women were not supposed to exercise and &quot;they had to wear dresses and stuff,&quot; said 14-year-old Merrick Johnston, an Anchorage girl who two years ago was the youngest person ever to reach McKinley's summit.</p>
<p>&quot;And then I look at Barbara 50 years ago standing on the top of Denali,&quot; Johnston said. &quot;I think it's so rad that she did that because I've always been a tomboy, sort of.&quot;</p>
<p>Despite her protestations, Barbara Washburn was no ordinary housewife when she left her Boston home for the Alaska peak. The 1935 graduate of Smith College, with a degree in French, was well-acquainted with the mountains. She and her husband spent their 1940 honeymoon completing the first ascent of Alaska's 10,182-foot (3,103 metre) Mount Bertha. A year later, they made the first ascent of 13,740-foot (4,188 metre) Mount Hayes.</p>
<p>Such shared experiences are key to a strong marriage, the blonde, diminuative and still-fresh-faced 82-year-old said. &quot;We wanted to do things together; that was it.&quot;</p>
<p>At a presentation in the Talkeetna school, the Washburns narrated some film of their trip, which followed a longer and more difficult route than that used by most modern McKinley expeditions. Members of the audience -- local school children, guides, bush pilots and deeply tanned climbers just off the mountain -- gasped at the primative clothing and equipment used in the 1947 expedition.</p>
<p>NOTHING FANCY IN THOSE DAYS</p>
<p>When Barbara Washburn stood atop McKinley's 20,320-foot (6,194 metre) summit on June 6, 1947, facing into the wind and braving temperatures of about 20 degrees below zero (minus seven C), she wore a simple parka, wool Army pants and felt boots. A thick rope around her waist -- but no fancy climbing harness -- secured her to her expedition partners.</p>
<p>The Washburns dismiss the younger generation's obsession with high-tech gear. &quot;There's an awful lot of expensive and unnecessary equipment out there,&quot; Barbara Washburn said. With just rudimentary gear, she added, &quot;we didn't freeze a thing. The kids today are freezing all the time.&quot;</p>
<p>When they made their historic trip, only a handful of people had scaled McKinley. Barbara Washburn was only the 16th person to reach the summit, a perch that seemed to her like &quot;a window into heaven.&quot;</p>
<p>It would be 16 years before another woman would climb McKinley.</p>
<p>Alaska was a raw frontier then. Anchorage, now home to more than 250,000 residents, had only about 3,000 then, and no roads led north to connect the city with what is now Denali National Park.</p>
<p>Today, more than 1,000 people climb McKinley each summer, and the 10,000th person was reported to have made the summit early this month. But even in this liberated era, only 7 percent of climbers on the mountain are women, according to Denali National Park rangers.</p>
<p>&quot;That's going to go up, definitely,&quot; said Merrick Johnston, who plans another trip on the mountain next summer.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TALKEETNA, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
