<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667365" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Mom may suffer from &quot;Internet addiction&quot;.</title>
<headline>Mom may suffer from &quot;Internet addiction&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>CINCINNATI 1997-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 24-year-old woman was released on bond on Monday after pleading not guilty to charges of child neglect that investigators said might have grown out of an addiction to the Internet.</p>
<p>Sandra Hacker was jailed on Sunday on three counts of child endangering after her estranged husband, Alexander, reported that she was spending up to 12 hours a day at her computer and leaving her three children to take care of themselves.</p>
<p>Police said they found broken glass, other debris and human feces on the walls of a playroom of her apartment, where she allegedly kept the toddlers locked up while preoccupied with the computer.</p>
<p>The Cincinnati Enquirer quoted David Greenfield, a psychologist from Hartford, Connecticut, as saying the case had all the earmarks of &quot;Internet Addiction Disorder.&quot;</p>
<p>Greenfield, who has done considerable study on the problem, said the disorder overtakes its victims in much the same way that people get hooked on gambling.</p>
<p>&quot;The normalcies for time and space disappear,&quot; he told The newspaper. &quot;It becomes a pretty powerful drug.&quot;</p>
<p>Hacker told police that his wife's computer obsession led to the breakup of their marriage.  The three children, ages 5, 3, and 2, were temporarily placed in his custody pending disposition of Mrs. Hacker's case.</p>
<p>She was freed on bond following a court hearing on Monday at which she pleaded not guilty.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CINCINNATI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
