<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667444" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France orders studies on radioactivity in Channel.</title>
<headline>France orders studies on radioactivity in Channel.</headline>
<byline>Lee Yanowitch</byline>
<dateline>CHERBOURG, France 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>France's new left-wing government on Tuesday ordered studies into the levels of radioactive waste in the Channel near the La Hague nuclear reprocessing plant in Cherbourg, northern France.</p>
<p>Health Minister Bernard Kouchner told the daily Le Monde in an interview that he had asked a state agency which polices ionising radiation to &quot;verify as quickly as possible the contamination level at La Hague and propose necessary measures&quot;.</p>
<p>Kouchner's decision follows claims by the Greenpeace environmental group last week that it had found &quot;stupefying&quot; radioactivity levels, above those allowed by the European Union, in sludge on the seabed near the end of a pipe discharging waste from the plant into the Channel.</p>
<p>Simultaneously, Environment Minister Dominique Voynet asked for &quot;independent measures to verify the information.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;In any case, a review of the decree setting norms for the plant's waste discharge will be undertaken in concert with all those concerned, Voynet, head of the Greens party, said in a statement.</p>
<p>Demands for new data coincide with a report by a commission appointed by the previous conservative government to explore scientists' claims that children who play on the beach or people who eat seafood from the area run a higher risk of developing leukaemia.</p>
<p>The report, brief excerpts of which were published in Le Monde, states there is a &quot;higher rate&quot; of leukaemia in the area, but that it is unlikely to be due to radioactivity levels from the La Hague plant which is run by the state company Cogema.</p>
<p>The report also suggests improvements in the way cancer cases are recorded throughout the country.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Cogema acknowledged it had removed Greenpeace's equipment monitoring radioactivity levels around the discharge pipe, after the environmental group had accused it of sending frogmen and armed men to steal their gear on Monday night.</p>
<p>Cogema said its divers had removed Greenpeace's equipment from the pipe for security reasons. The armed men were maritime para-military gendarmes, it said.</p>
<p>&quot;In order to ensure the security of our site, we are required to take measures to prevent the possibility of dangerous incidents resulting from ill-intentioned acts, such as obstructing the discharge pipe,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>But Greenpeace said Cogema was trying to silence it after it announced last week it had found high levels of radioactive isotopes including cobalt, americium, barium, antimony and europium in sediment taken near the pipe's end.</p>
<p>Cogema, which reprocesses spent nuclear fuel from countries including Germany and Japan, has accused Greenpeace of skewing its results by measuring too close to the pipe's end.</p>
<p>&quot;La Hague is clearly desperate to block our efforts to inform the public about radioactive contamination from La Hague plutonium factory,&quot; Damon Moglen of Greenpeace said.</p>
<p>Greenpeace said in a statement it had filmed the &quot;armed intervention&quot; to remove its gear. A spokesman said some of the Cogema workers can be seen on videotape trying to cover their faces with their hands and coats to avoid being identified. Two people could be seen carrying revolvers, he said.</p>
<p>It was the second time Cogema divers had taken Greenpeace equipment, the group said. The first time was early on Sunday.</p>
<p>Greenpeace was filing a lawsuit with the public prosecutor in Cherbourg, the statement said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I32040">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHERBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
