<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667486" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: UNESCO condemns attacks on Bosnian monuments.</title>
<headline>UNESCO condemns attacks on Bosnian monuments.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>UNESCO on Tuesday condemned attacks on religious monuments in Bosnia and urged the international community to prevent them to fully enforce the 1995 Dayton peace agreement.</p>
<p>Federico Mayor, director general of the U.N. Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation, said in a statement such attacks harmed &quot;the very foundations of both the present and the future&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;Every shot targeting cultural and religious monuments in Bosnia and Herzegovina, over and above material damage, constitutes an attack on the principle of a multicultural society which is at the heart of the Bosnian state,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I appeal to the international community to give itself the necessary means for the full implementation of the Dayton agreement,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hundreds of churches and mosques were deliberately destroyed during Bosnia's 3 1/2-year war and some such attacks have continued since it ended in late 1995.</p>
<p>A NATO-led international force is overseeing the implementation of the accord which ended the war between Moslems, Serbs and Croats. The force is scheduled to leave in June next year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
