<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667550" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Stasi clues back Sofia role in Pope attack - paper.</title>
<headline>Stasi clues back Sofia role in Pope attack - paper.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A German newspaper said on Tuesday information from former communist East German intelligence added weight to suspicions Bulgaria's secret service was involved in the 1981 assassination attempt on Pope John Paul.</p>
<p>The mass-circulation daily Bild said Rosario Priore, the Italian magistrate investigating the attack by Turkish gunman Ali Mehmet Agca, had visited Berlin in April to seek help with his inquiry.</p>
<p>The assassination attempt against the Pope is one of the enduring mysteries among the great crimes of the 20th century. Agca is serving a life sentence in Italy for the shooting, but prosecutors are still trying to find out exactly why he did it.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Berlin justice authorities confirmed an interrogation had taken place as a result of a request for assistance by Italian officials. He declined to comment further.</p>
<p>Bild said the interrogation had involved a former officer from East Berlin's Ministry for State Security (Stasi).</p>
<p>The paper said he told prosecutors the Bulgarian secret service had asked the Stasi to help deflect suspicion that Sofia was behind the shooting in St Peter's Square, which seriously injured the pope.</p>
<p>A year after the attack, Agca implicated the Bulgarians in a plot carried out on behalf of the former Soviet Union because of the Pontiff's support for the Solidarity movement in his native Poland. Agca has since said he acted alone.</p>
<p>Bild quoted the unnamed officer as saying the Stasi had the task of trying to implicate the CIA in the attack and to &quot;back this up with rumours and other clues&quot;.</p>
<p>Citing a transcript of the interrogation, Bild said the officer and his Stasi colleagues had met the Bulgarians several times in the year of the attack. Normally they would have met only once a year, the officer said.</p>
<p>The Vatican said in a statement in Rome that it had a policy of not commenting on such reports. &quot;Since 1981, we have never made statements on theories, indiscretions and inquiries relating to the attack,&quot; chief Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro-Valls said.</p>
<p>At a major trial in 1986 Italian prosecutors failed to prove their charges that the Bulgarian secret services had hired Agca on behalf of the Soviet Union in order to snuff out the Pope's support for Solidarity..</p>
<p>The so-called &quot;Bulgarian Connection&quot; trial ended with an &quot;acquittal for lack of sufficient evidence&quot; of three Turks and three Bulgarians who had been charged with conspiring with Agca.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
