<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667612" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: EU leaders move up a gear with Dutch bicycles.</title>
<headline>EU leaders move up a gear with Dutch bicycles.</headline>
<byline>Lorrayne Smith</byline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>France and Germany may be key players in driving the European Union forward, but it was the British, Dutch and Austrians who led the way on Tuesday when EU leaders at the Amsterdam summit got on their bikes.</p>
<p>Taking a break before lunch at their meeting in Amsterdam, the leaders gathered on a canal bridge for a traditional summit &quot;family photograph&quot; and to receive shiny new seven-speed bicycles from the Mayor of Amsterdam.</p>
<p>After a mayoral warning to avoid getting caught in the tram tracks, &quot;because I'll have to pick up the hospital bill&quot;, British Prime Minister Tony Blair made the fastest start and sped ahead.</p>
<p>Blair, who earlier called for a &quot;change in gear&quot; to bring Europe closer to its citizens, was among the first to cross the finishing line 100 metres away, together with Dutch Premier Wim Kok and Austrian Chancellor Viktor Klima.</p>
<p>Portly Belgian Prime Minister Jean-Luc Dehaene came in closely behind the front runners. New French Prime Minister Lionel Jospin, Sweden's Goran Persson, and Spain's Jose Maria Aznar also joined in the fun.</p>
<p>Another to welcome the gift was Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi, a keen cyclist, who complained of having to go without his usual cycle ride on Sunday because he had had to prepare for the summit.</p>
<p>But German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, French President Jacques Chirac, European Commission President Jacques Santer, and some others politely declined to mount their Dutch gifts.</p>
<p>With over one bicycle per head and not a hill in sight, Amsterdam is renowned for being the most cycle-friendly town in Europe.</p>
<p>Asked beforehand whether the bikes would fit all and accommodate the weight of Europe's bulkier leaders, such as Kohl, a city official noted the Dutch-made cycle frames were &quot;one size, but very strong&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
