<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667771" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: Bangladesh struggles to save forest from gas fire.</title>
<headline>Bangladesh struggles to save forest from gas fire.</headline>
<byline>Shakeel Anwar</byline>
<dateline>SRIMANGAL, Bangladesh 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Workers struggled on Tuesday to save a rich timber forest in northeast Bangladesh from a raging fire that engulfed a natural gas field at the weekend.</p>
<p>Fire-fighting experts from Singapore arrived to assess the blaze at the Mugrachhara gas field, in the heart of the country's tea-growing Moulavi Bazar district.</p>
<p>Energy Ministry officials said more experts and equipment were expected soon from the U.S. headquarters of Occidental Petroleum Corp, which was drilling at the field when a rig hit trapped gas on Sunday and ignited the blaze.</p>
<p>&quot;The large, thick forest surrounding the fire site is under serious threat,&quot; Badrul Anam, Assistant Conservationist from the Sylhet Forest told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;We are worried what would happen in the scorching summer heat if a big wind comes up -- the flames are drying leaves and branches and can spark fire any time. It will be a disaster then,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The fire, which Occidental executives say could burn for weeks, has already destroyed parts of two nearby tea gardens and plantations belonging to tribal Khasia villagers.</p>
<p>Workers were trying to make a fireline by cutting rows of trees around the blazing well, but Anam said there were no resources to tackle a large forest fire. The 10,000-acre reserve forest surrounding the field is rich with timber planted since the early 1920s.</p>
<p>Mohammad Atiqul Azam, a divisional forest officer in Sylhet, said a preliminary damage assessment would be ready in two days.</p>
<p>&quot;We don't know what the (biological) impact will be as it depends how long the fire will rage. But as of now we are fearing major damage... I am afraid it may take many years for the area to recover.&quot;</p>
<p>Forest workers were unable to approach the fire because of flames leaping 300-to-500 feet (100-to-150 metres) into the air. Four Bangladeshis were hurt in the blaze and nearby railway tracks also caught fire.</p>
<p>Police have surrounded the area, allowing only experts and officials near the fire.</p>
<p>Rafiq Ahmed, a forest guard who was on a routine patrol at the time of the accident, said he had wondered whether the world was ending.</p>
<p>&quot;I suddenly heard a big sound like a roaring railway engine and saw the forest had been lit by a huge fire. Workers at the rig were running into the jungle for (their) life. I too rushed back to my jungle camp and immediately began running away,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Sheikh Hasina was due to visit the fire site on Tuesday, her aides said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SRIMANGAL, Bangladesh"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
