<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667837" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: NORDICS PUSH ENVIRONMENT RULE IN NEW EU TREATY.</title>
<headline>NORDICS PUSH ENVIRONMENT RULE IN NEW EU TREATY.</headline>
<byline>Fredrik Dahl</byline>
<dateline>AMSTERDAM 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Denmark, supported by Sweden, seemed set to secure an agreement at the European Union summit in Amsterdam on Tuesday enabling individual member states to introduce tougher environmental rules on their own.</p>
<p>EU leaders were expected to agree to incorporate language in the new EU treaty which was being negotiated at the two-day summit, making it possible for EU countries to maintain and introduce stricter environmental provisions under conditions.</p>
<p>Danish Prime Minister Poul Nyrup Rasmussen, who intervened several times on the issue duotiations, said he believed the outcome would be &quot;satisfactory&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a big step forward,&quot; Swedish Foreign Minister Lena Hjelm-Wallen told reporters.</p>
<p>The issue is controversial because stricter environmental rules in one member state could run counter to the bloc's single market, in which goods are supposed to move across internal borders without restrictions.</p>
<p>Fearing new barriers to trade, industry is likely to criticise the idea.</p>
<p>But the Nordics argue that the bloc must be seen as giving priority to issues which matter for ordinary people, such as jobs and the environment.</p>
<p>This also reflects the fact that large parts of their populations are at best eurosceptical. Denmark will probably need to hold a referendum to approve the revised treaty, expected to be agreed later on Tuesday or early Wednesday.</p>
<p>Under a compromise proposal, a member state which finds it necessary to introduce national rules based on new scientific evidence relating the protection of the environment must notify the European Commission.</p>
<p>The Brussels-based EU executive must approve or reject the provisions within six months. Following Nordic pressure, the new rules are approved if the Commission has not taken a decision on the issue within six months. The original proposal had it the other way around.</p>
<p>However, the proposed text also states that the stricter environmental rules must not constitute a disguised restriction on trade in the EU.</p>
<p>Gunnar Lund, Swedish foreign ministry state secretary, said the proposed text would lead to a &quot;fundamental change&quot; on environmental issues.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="DEN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G155">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMSTERDAM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
