<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="667834" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish court freezes Islamist group's accounts.</title>
<headline>Turkish court freezes Islamist group's accounts.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Turkish court on Tuesday froze over $100 million worth of accounts and securities belonging to a leading Islamist group of companies in the wake of an army claim that businessmen were supporting religious activism.</p>
<p>Court officials said the action was taken after Kombassan Holding failed to seek the necessary permission for raising capital from Turkey's Capital Markets Board (SPK).</p>
<p>&quot;After the application from the SPK we have frozen bank accounts and securities worth 14.9 trillion lira ($102 million) belonging to Kombassan Holding,&quot; a official at Ankara Commercial Court told Reuters.</p>
<p>Turkey's powerful military, engaged in a fierce battle with the Islamist-led government, said last week at strongly-worded briefings to senior civil servants and the media that political Islam was financially backed by &quot;100 Islamist businessmen.&quot;</p>
<p>No companies were identified, but newspaper reports pointed to Kombassan and food retailer Yimpas Holding, based in the conservative town of Yozgat, as among the leading Islamist firms targeted by the military.</p>
<p>The SPK said at the weekend it had started legal proceedings against Kombassan, saying &quot;the company attempted to raise its capital without being registered on the board's books.&quot;</p>
<p>Kombassan, involved in printing, paper and machinery production and construction, wants to raise its capital to 100 trillion lira from 39.5 trillion -- currently the highest capital of any Turkish company.</p>
<p>Run from Islamist Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan's stronghold of Konya, Kombassan caught the public eye when it bought a state tyre company in a government sell-off shortly after Erbakan took office last June.</p>
<p>Its activities were highlighted last month when a company courier arriving at Ankara airport was allegedly caught importing 1.7 million marks ($979,000) illegally from Germany.</p>
<p>Kombassan and other leading Islamist companies launched an advertising campaign on Monday to defend themselves against accusations that they were fostering an Islamic revival.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a very serious mistake to show us among the so-called 'companies helping fundamentalism' in newspapers and on TVs,&quot; read a full-page advertisement by Yimpas in many newspapers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
