<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668130" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: ERA lodges environmental impact study.</title>
<headline>ERA lodges environmental impact study.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Energy Resources of Australia Ltd (ERA) said on Tuesday it has lodged with the federal government the final environmental impact statement (EIS) for a second uranium mine in the Northern Territory.</p>
<p>ERA is seeking government approval to develop a mine at Jabiluka, 20 km north of its existing Ranger mine, either by trucking ore to the Ranger mill for processing - its preferred option - or by mining and milling the ore at Jabiluka.</p>
<p>The project faces opposition from a group of traditional Aboriginal land owners who lodged a legal challenge last week.  </p>
<p>ERA chief executive Phillip Shirvington said the EIS addressed social and safety issues raised by land owner and environmental groups.</p>
<p>ERA has made public commitments to work with the Northern Land Council and local communities to minimise the impact from mining and maximise the benefits to the region.</p>
<p>Shirvington said a separate study had found ERA's mining operations would generate more than A$12 billion in revenue over the 28-year life of Jabiluka.  </p>
<p>&quot;The Aboriginal community would receive A$210 million in royalties from ERA in return for leasing the Jabiluka site,&quot; Shirvington said in a statement.</p>
<p>The Jabiluka and Ranger leases lie within the boundaries of the Kakadu National Park, but are excised from the park.</p>
<p>Shirvington said last week the government would have 42 days to examine the EIS and, barring new delays, he expected approval for the mine in January or February, with production starting in 2000.  </p>
<p>The Gundjehmi Aboriginal Corp said last week that lawyers had lodged documents in the Federal Court claiming the issuing of the mining lease in 1982 for Jabiluka was not proper or legal.</p>
<p>The claim was lodged on behalf of traditional owner, Yvonne Margula.</p>
<p>Shirvington said ERA had the support of other traditional owners in the region.</p>
<p>ERA is 68 percent owned by resources group North Ltd.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I15000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
