<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668187" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Vietnam urged to release Buddhist church leaders.</title>
<headline>Vietnam urged to release Buddhist church leaders.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Buddhists from 20 countries have called on Vietnam to release dozens of detained leaders of the outlawed Unified Buddhist Church of Vietnam (UBCV), a Paris-based group representing the movement said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The International Buddhist Information Bureau said in a statement that a letter demanding the immediate and unconditional release of Buddhist monks, nuns and others was sent to Hanoi after an international conference in Kanchanaburi, Thailand.</p>
<p>The letter called for the restoration of the UBCV's freedom of religious activity, a halt to a campaign aimed at disbanding the Buddhist Youth Movement and the restoration of all property confiscated by the authorities from the UBCV.</p>
<p>&quot;In Vietnam today, the traditional Unified Buddhist Buddhist Church of Vietnam...is banned, its pagodas are confiscated and its network of educational, social and cultural institutions are closed down,&quot; the letter said.</p>
<p>&quot;Monks, nuns and lay-Buddhists have suffered torture, detention and intimidation, and today virtually all of the UBCV leadership is in prison or under house arrest.&quot;</p>
<p>An official at the Paris-based group said there were currently 70 UBCV members detained in Vietnam.&quot;</p>
<p>The letter was signed by 50 monks, nuns and lay-Buddhists from Asia, the United States and Europe at the conference of the International Network of Engaged Buddhists (INEB).</p>
<p>The UBCV was the Buddhist church organisation in former South Vietnam until the victory of Hanoi's communist forces over the South in 1975.</p>
<p>The UBCV is still regarded by Buddhists in the south and abroad as the sole legitimate church organisation. But the government views the state-sponsored Vietnam Buddhist Church (VBC) as the only legal organisation for Buddhists in Vietnam.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
