<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668262" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Rickshaw-era set to die of old age in Hong Kong.</title>
<headline>Rickshaw-era set to die of old age in Hong Kong.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The rickshaw, relic of an imperial past, will survive Hong Kong's handover to China but may be lucky to last three years to the millennium.</p>
<p>For the rickshaw &quot;boys&quot; are venerable 80-year-olds, target of a health warning in guide books -- stick to a trip around the block in case they keel over.</p>
<p>Drawing deeply on his cigarette as he touts for business outside the Star Ferry terminal, 80-year-old Chan Yip said: &quot;I wll keep going as long as I can.</p>
<p>&quot;I've been doing this for 50 years. I have to keep fit but I still smoke and also drink beer.&quot;</p>
<p>He singled out American and Japanese tourists as his favourite customers for the ride condemned by critics as a degrading social embarrassment but still treasured in tourist photo albums around the world.</p>
<p>Bartering skills are much needed to get a bargain from these grizzled veterans and Chan was quick to break off from talking when he spotted a photographer wielding his lenses.</p>
<p>&quot;This country is getting more like America every day,&quot; grumbled Florida photographer Gary Bouchard as he buried deep in his pockets to give Chan all his spare change.</p>
<p>The &quot;Rough Guide to Hong Kong&quot; advises tourists to keep the trips short for the sake of the venerable rickshaw pullers.</p>
<p>&quot;Try to get them to take you any further than around the block and whatever you pay them, you could end up on manslaughter charges as most of them don't look fit enough to blow their noses,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong once had a vast fleet of rickshaws that numbered 8,000 as late as the end of World War Two.</p>
<p>Britain's colonial authorities, who hand Hong Kong back to China at the end of the month, have not issued any new rickshaw licences since 1975. Now the trade is gradually dying out.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no move to stamp it out. It is going to die a natural death. When they retire that is the end,&quot; said a Hong Kong Tourist Association official.</p>
<p>&quot;There are seven licencees left who pay 50 Hong Kong dollars (US$ 7) a year. Their charges for tourists are purely negotiable. It is elastic depending on your bartering powers,&quot; the official added.</p>
<p>The rickshaw, from the Japanese jin-riki-sha which means &quot;Man's strength cart,&quot; has had a colourful history since U.S. 19th century missionary Jonathon Goble first designed one for his wife.</p>
<p>Local Hong Kong records show its many uses -- in 1917, 60 of the colony's 1,750 registered rickshaws were used by brothels.</p>
<p>At the height of the Vietnam War, troops on &quot;Rest and Recreation&quot; leave in Hong Kong would race each other to the &quot;Suzie Wong&quot; bars of Wanchai and -- much to the amusement of the owners -- even swap places with the Chinese pullers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
