<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668257" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: FOCUS-India raises diesel imports with new tender.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-India raises diesel imports with new tender.</headline>
<byline>Ang Bee Lin</byline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's latest tender to buy diesel on an eight-month term basis is unlikely to lead to a reduction in its regular spot purchases as domestic demand is soaring, traders said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>State-owned Indian Oil Corp issued a tender to buy up to 1.08 million tonnes of 0.5 percent and 1.0 percent diesel for August to March delivery.</p>
<p>&quot;India's domestic demand is rising very rapidly at about 10 percent a year and domestic output is insufficent to meet rising demand,&quot; said a western trader familiar with India's diesel imports.</p>
<p>He said the import volume of just over one million tonnes spread over eight months is not very large.</p>
<p>India, one of Asia's largest diesel consumer, next to China imports an average of 400,000 to 600,000 tonnes of diesel monthly.</p>
<p>But imports might rise above this average as seen in its July purchases when it imported 855,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>India's monthly diesel tender has always been a center of focus in the Singapore benchmark diesel market as prices may swing either ways, depending on the country's import volume.</p>
<p>India consumes about 30 million tonnes of diesel a year and over a third of this is imported, traders said.</p>
<p>India's domestic refining capacity is not expected to rise sharply within the next two years.</p>
<p>The first large expansions are not expected until 1999, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;India's move to tie more imports on term is also evident that the country maybe concern with security of supplies,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>IOC has in its last term tender purchased a total of 3.2 million tonnes of 1.0-percent sulphur deisel and 540,000 tonnes of 0.25 percent sulphur deisel for deliveries between June 1997 and May 1998.</p>
<p>IOC purchased the one-year term diesel from Kuwait Petroleum Corp (KPC), BB Energy, Glencore and Marubeni.</p>
<p>The company also has long term tenders to purchase diesel from Middle East producers such as Kuwait Petroleum Corp totalling over 1.5 million tonnes, Abu Dhabi National Oil Co about 500,000 tonnes and Bahrain National Oil Co for about 1.32 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Currently, India is also considering plans to raise domestic diesel and kerosene prices that would trim about $1.5 billion from its subsidy bill.</p>
<p>The move is aimed at closing the gap btween international and domestic oil prices. Current Indian prices are way below international levels.</p>
<p>-- Singapore newsroom (65-870-3082)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
