<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668559" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>KUWAIT: Pentagon studies Gulf illness report, Cohen says.</title>
<headline>Pentagon studies Gulf illness report, Cohen says.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>KUWAIT 1997-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Responding to a critical congressional report on Gulf War illnesses, Defence Secretary William Cohen promised on Monday to pursue all possible links between biological weapons and complaints by thousands of U.S. veterans.</p>
<p>&quot;We think that we are making a very strong, good-faith effort to get to the bottom of it,&quot; Cohen said at a news conference on a visit to Kuwait. &quot;That is exactly why we have the investigation under way.&quot;</p>
<p>He also assured Kuwait of Washington's firm commitment to its security and to containing former occupier Iraq and neighbouring Iran.</p>
<p>&quot;I can summarize the United States policy towards Kuwait in three words: commitment, cooperation and containment,&quot; Cohen said.</p>
<p>He later visited U.S. troops aboard ships off Bahrain and told them they were helping protect half the world's oil supply from Iran and Iraq.</p>
<p>Cohen said he had been critical of previous Pentagon investigation efforts on Gulf War illnesses and they had been augmented to include 85 studies in areas including possible biological agents.</p>
<p>Cohen spoke after The New York Times reported that the General Accounting Office, the investigating arm of Congress, would issue a report soon criticising the Pentagon and a White House panel for discounting any link between biological agents and troop complaints.</p>
<p>The Defence Department has investigated complaints by more than 60,000 veterans but has found no links to chemical or biological weapons and has said there was no evidence that such arms were used by Iraqi forces during the 1991 war.</p>
<p>Bernard Rostker, the Pentagon's special assistant for Gulf War illnesses, told reporters that aspects of the draft report were &quot;not factually correct or up to date.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the report relied on the same data used by a Pentagon team of investigators and a White House expert panel, and that he was not prepared to draw conclusions linking various ailments suffered by Gulf War veterans with low-level exposure to chemical weapons.</p>
<p>Rostker acknowledged, however, that the Pentagon had been slow to fully &quot;search down the potential, possible causes of some of the undiagnosed, unexplained illnesses of the Gulf.&quot;</p>
<p>Cohen said &quot;I think we need more evidence, obviously, and we will look very closely at the GAO report,&quot; adding that the Pentagon was overseeing broad internal and private studies and would continue its efforts to check every possible source of the complaints, which range from loss of memory to joint aches and headaches.</p>
<p>He told reporters he had not read the report, a draft of which was obtained by the Times, but cautioned that it apparently did not establish a definite link between veterans' complaints and the possible release of biological agents.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't believe that the reports established that there was a linkage, simply that there was a premature judgment that there was no linkage,&quot; Cohen said.</p>
<p>&quot;I have criticised the Defence Department's handling of the investigation myself on several occasions,&quot; he told reporters. &quot;I think that the work that was done previously was not adequate, has a lack of information, maintenance of records, loss of records.&quot;</p>
<p>The Times said the report had also found that there was &quot;substantial evidence&quot; linking nerve gas and other chemical weapons to the sorts of health problems among the veterans.</p>
<p>The newspaper said the report cautioned that the Defence Department should not rule out the possibility that Iraqi biological weapons, especially a group of potent liver carcinogens, might be responsible for some of the ailments.</p>
<p>The Pentagon and a White House panel -- the Presidential Advisory Committee on Gulf War Veterans' Illnesses -- had both concluded that Iraqi chemical and biological weapons were probably not responsible for the veterans' health problems.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KUWAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KUWAIT"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
