<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668674" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Cogema admits taking Greenpeace gear.</title>
<headline>France's Cogema admits taking Greenpeace gear.</headline>
<byline>Lee Yanowitch</byline>
<dateline>CHERBOURG, France 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The French state nuclear company Cogema said on Tuesday that it had removed Greenpeace radioactivity monitoring equipment from a pipe discharging waste from a nuclear plant into the English Channel.</p>
<p>A statement from Cogema came after the environmental group had accused Cogema of sending frogmen and armed men to steal their equipment on Monday night.</p>
<p>Cogema said its divers had removed Greenpeace's equipment from a discharge pipe at its La Hague nuclear reprocessing plant in Cherbourg, northern France, for security reasons.</p>
<p>&quot;In order to ensure the security of our site, we are required to take measures to prevent the possibility of dangerous incidents resulting from ill-intentioned acts, such as obstructing the discharge pipe,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>But Greenpeace said Cogema was trying to silence it after the activist group announced last week it had found &quot;stupefying&quot; radioactivity levels, above those allowed by the European Union, in sludge on the seabed near the end of the discharge pipe.</p>
<p>&quot;La Hague is clearly desperate to block our efforts to inform the public about radioactive contamination from La Hague plutonium factory,&quot; Damon Moglen of Greenpeace said.</p>
<p>New Health Minister Bernard Kouchner told the daily Le Monde in an interview published on Tuesday that he had asked a state agency which polices ionising radiation to &quot;verify as quickly as possible the contamination level at La Hague and propose necessary measures&quot;.</p>
<p>Greenpeace said in a statement its activists had witnessed and filmed the &quot;armed intervention&quot; to remove its monitoring equipment.</p>
<p>A Greenpeace spokesman said some of the Cogema workers were seen on videotape trying to cover their faces with their hands and their coats to avoid being identified. Two people could be seen carrying revolvers, he said.</p>
<p>It was the second time Cogema divers had taken Greenpeace equipment, the group said. The first time was early on Sunday.</p>
<p>Greenpeace was filing a lawsuit with the public prosecutor in Cherbourg, the statement said.</p>
<p>Greenpeace said last week it found high levels of radioactive isotopes including cobalt, americium, barium, antimony and europium from 10 kg (22 lbs) of sediment taken near the end of the pipe.</p>
<p>La Hague, which reprocesses spent nuclear fuel from countries including Germany and Japan, has accused Greenpeace of skewing its results by measuring too close to the pipe's end.</p>
<p>In January two French scientists said children who regularly played on the beach, or people who ate local seafood, had a higher risk of leukemia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I1610109">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I32040">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHERBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
