<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668666" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Last-minute jitters hit environmental conference.</title>
<headline>Last-minute jitters hit environmental conference.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Forests, farmlands and coral reefs are dwindling, pollution is increasing, oceans are overfished and one billion people are so poor they threaten to use any resource available just to stay alive.</p>
<p>Environmentalists are jittery. And so are the organisers of the second Earth Summit from June 23-27, apprehensive that speeches from world leaders will be bereft of concrete action.</p>
<p>As the fifth anniversary of the landmark Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro approaches, more than 65 heads of state or government will meet at U.N. headquarters to set new targets on &quot;sustainable development&quot; -- economic growth moving in tandem with ecological goals.</p>
<p>But days before next week's conference, experts are huddling to complete a draft paper that lacks agreement on several basic issues -- financing for poor nations, climate change, energy, fishing and forests preservation.</p>
<p>&quot;This should be a wake-up call,&quot; said Clifton Curtis of the environmental group, Greenpeace International. &quot;We should be beyond promises of Rio and into implementation.&quot;</p>
<p>German Chancellor Helmut Kohl is expected to propose that all the U.N. environmental bodies locate themselves in one place -- Bonn -- when his government moves to Berlin. And U.S. President Bill Clinton has promised some initiatives, although Europeans find Washington shying away from specific goals.</p>
<p>And many developing nations are refusing any commitments until rich states keep their promises in Rio for assistance they need for basic technological, health and educational programmes. But such aid is decreasing rather than rising.</p>
<p>&quot;If it becomes universally accepted that even aid is no longer an option, then one can predict that discussions on international cooperation will collapse,&quot; Tanzania's minister plenipotentiary Msuya Waldi Mangachi told a recent meeting. &quot;What remains is a call for each country to find its own resources, if it can, and do whatever it can or wants.&quot;</p>
<p>In Rio some 10,000 diplomats produced &quot;Agenda 21&quot; of some 2,500 goals, followed over the last few years by treaties on climate change, biological diversity or conservation and &quot;desertifaction&quot; or land degradation. And at least 1,800 communities set up their own environmental programmes.</p>
<p>But the growing scarcity of fresh water, the loss of agricultural land and forests and the downward spiral of poverty are undermining a rise in food production, health standards and a slower population growth.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall, we haven't made the fundamental change of course promised in Rio,&quot; said Canadian businessman Maurice Strong, who was secretary-general of that conference.</p>
<p>According to John Gummer, Britain's former environment minister, &quot;We do have to recognise that the rich nations have to pay the price. We benefit from pollution, from over-exploitation of fishing and so on. And richer nations are more able to cope with geographical catastrophes.&quot;</p>
<p>But Gummer said developing countries could not opt out of negotiations. &quot;The North cannot operate unless it is seen that the South is part of the process,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Another highly contentious issue is climate change and energy efficiency. The European Union has set targets to reduce so-called &quot;greenhouse gases&quot; such as carbon dioxide or nitrous oxide, to roll back global warming affecting climate changes.</p>
<p>The EU formula calls for a 15 percent reduction in greenhouse gas emissions below the 1990 level by the year 2010. Small island states are fighting for a 20 percent reduction by the year 2005.</p>
<p>To achieve these goals, energy usage has to be more efficient, subsidies for fossil fuels have to be phased out and wind or solar energy alternatives have to be explored.</p>
<p>But the United States wants no specific targets now, preferring to leave itself negotiating room at a December conference on the issue in Kyoto, Japan.</p>
<p>And not much can be done without full participation from Washington. Despite many U.S. innovations toward energy efficiency, experts say it still takes 120 workers to produce the energy needs for the average American, 60 for each European but only eight for each Chinese and one for each person in Bangladesh.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
