<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668665" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Issues to be discussed at Earth Summit June 23.</title>
<headline>Issues to be discussed at Earth Summit June 23.</headline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-06-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are the main issues facing the Earth Summit to be held at U.N. headquarters on June 23-27. The meeting is a follow-up to the 1992 environmental summit in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>FINANCING - The most contentious issue is the broken promise in Rio by rich states to make available about $125 billion a year in assistance until the year 2000. Direct government aid has declined and private investment is concentrated in a small number of Third World countries. Many developing countries in preparatory meetings blocked environmental initiatives until there was progress on financing. The European Community has suggested a tax on aviation fuel, which will most likely be rejected. Norway wants the heads of state at the summit to hold a special meeting on financing but this is in doubt.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>CLIMATE - The planet's climate system faces potentially massive disruption from climate change. Fossil fuels, such as coal and oil, are the main sources of polluting &quot;greenhouse gases,&quot; through the release of carbon dioxide and other gases. Governments could not agree on action needed. The European Union proposed a 15 percent reduction in emissions below the 1990 level by the year 2019. Small island states wanted a much higher reduction. The United States wants no specific targets at this time, preferring to wait for a December conference on the topic in Kyoto, Japan.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>ENERGY - The European Union proposed governments and the private sector adopt energy pricing to reflect economic and environmental costs and benefits and to reduce and eliminate gradually subsidies for fossil fuels. But developing countries, among them energy producers, as well as the United States, opposed this. Preparatory discussions did not arrive at agreement on proposals to set guidelines for renewable sources of energy such as solar or wind. Europe and the United States also want to phase out unleaded gasoline as soon as possible. The developing countries oppose it.</p>
<p>------</p>
<p>OCEANS-FISHING - The Food and Agricultural Organisation says 70 percent of the world's major fisheries are now either depleted or over-exploited. The draft document for the conference says there is an urgent need for governments to prevent or eliminate overfishing and excess fishing capacity and to consider the impact of government subsidies. But it does not set specific goals.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>FORESTS - Logging, agriculture and the need for firewood are devastating remaining rich forest reserves in the world at an alarming rate. Canada, Malaysia and most European nations want a treaty on forests to codify over 100 proposals made by a group of government envoys in February. The United States, Australia, Japan, Brazil and seven other Latin American states are opposed. Environmental groups also are against a treaty, saying it would serve as an excuse to defer immediate action. A related treaty on biodiversity has not been ratified by the United States.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>WATER - One-third of the world's population lives in countries facing moderate to severe clean water shortages. By the year 2025 that number may reach two-thirds. A fifth of the world's population does not have safe drinking water while more than one-half of humanity lacks adequate sanitation. No major dispute emerged and governments are expected to agree to convene a 1998 session on a global strategy.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>TOXIC SUBSTANCES - Toxic chemicals and radioactive wastes continue to threaten health and the environment. An estimated 3 million tons of toxic and hazardous waste cross national borders each year. The Basel Convention in 1995 banned the export of hazardous wastes to developing countries. The document before delegates agrees to strengthen the treaty and devise a protocol for liabiity from wastes shipped across borders. In dispute is whether radioactive wastes should be stored or deposed in the country in which they are generated.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
