<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668855" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada province paves way for tobacco lawsuit.</title>
<headline>Canada province paves way for tobacco lawsuit.</headline>
<byline>Cynthia Osterman</byline>
<dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia 1997-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Copying a U.S. tactic, British Columbia announced legislation on Monday that lays the groundwork for the province to become the first in Canada to sue tobacco companies to recoup medical costs for treating smokers.</p>
<p>The province is believed to be the first government outside the United States to pursue such action against tobacco manufacturers, similar to the approach taken by 37 U.S. states.</p>
<p>&quot;I am declaring war on the tobacco companies,&quot; declared British Columbia Premier Glen Clark on Canadian television.</p>
<p>Several other provinces and the federal government were considering following suit, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;The legal battle against the tobacco industry is spreading as governments not only in the United States but worldwide believe this is a battle that should be fought and won,&quot; British Columbia Health Minister Joy MacPhail told a news conference.</p>
<p>Before the province files its lawsuit, it is asking the tobacco industry to compensate it voluntarily for tobacco-related illness and smoking prevention programs.</p>
<p>While no figure was put on that demand, MacPhail estimated the province's direct and indirect medical costs related to smoking and the price of smoking prevention programs at about C$1.6 billion ($1.2 billion) a year.</p>
<p>Clark rated the chance of tobacco companies agreeing to the proposal as slim. He said it was virtually certain the province would go to court in coming months and hoped the legal action would prod cigarette makers to negotiate a settlement.</p>
<p>In a letter to the presidents of the three biggest tobacco companies in Canada, MacPhail also demanded they stop marketing aimed at youth and acknowledge publicly that &quot;tobacco is addictive, deadly and causes cancer and lung and heart disease.&quot;</p>
<p>She said the province was prepared to consider &quot;other revenue measures such as licensing fees to ensure the industry pays its share of the cost of smoking prevention and the treatment of tobacco-related illnesses.&quot;</p>
<p>Cigarette makers reacted swiftly and derisively. The Canadian Tobacco Manufacturers Council labeled the move a hypocritical, politically motivated tax grab.</p>
<p>&quot;It appears that they've imported a U.S. idea that isn't working very well there and is likely to be inapplicable here,&quot; said Rob Parker, president of the council.</p>
<p>Anti-smoking activists applauded the news, saying it could transform the U.S. campaign against tobacco companies into an international effort.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a groundbreaking, landmark announcement,&quot; said Rob Cunningham of the Canadian Cancer Society. &quot;It really is a global war.&quot;</p>
<p>In the United States, negotiations were set to resume on Monday between state and federal government officials and cigarette makers over a multi-billion dollar settlement.</p>
<p>In Ottawa, Canada's Health Minister Allan Rock said he was watching British Columbia's action &quot;with great interest&quot; and hoped to discuss a coordinated approach with Canaada's provinces on the issue.</p>
<p>Incentives for governments to sue in Canada are even greater than in the United States because health care is provided universally and funded publicly.</p>
<p>Imperial Tobacco Ltd., a unit of Imasco Ltd. is the biggest cigarette company in Canada and is 40 percent owned by B.A.T Industries Plc of Britain.</p>
<p>The second biggest company, Rothmans, Benson and Hedges Inc., is 60 percent owned by Rothmans Inc. and 40 percent by Philip Morris Cos Inc.. Rothmans Inc is a unit of Rothmans International Plc, which is owned by Swiss luxury goods holding company Cie Financiere Richmont AG.</p>
<p>Third-ranked RJR MacDonald is wholly owned by RJR Nabisco Holdings Corp. unit R.J. Reynolds Tobacco International. American cigarette brands are also sold in Canada.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VANCOUVER, British Columbia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
