<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="668858" id="root" date="1997-06-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Monitor Radio network to cease operation.</title>
<headline>U.S. Monitor Radio network to cease operation.</headline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-06-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Christian Science church said on Monday it had failed to sell Monitor Radio and the news network used by more than 200 public radio stations in the United States will stop broadcasting on June 27.</p>
<p>A last-minute bid to sell the broadcast operation to World Times Inc. failed because not enough stations had agreed to carry the programming when new owners took over July 1, officials said.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of the timing, a number of key stations had moved ahead and made other binding commitments for July 1,&quot; Monitor Radio's Marketing and Development Director Susan Schardt told public radio stations.</p>
<p>The Christian Science church, which also publishes The Christian Science Monitor newspaper, announced in April it would sell or discontinue the radio network by the end of June to concentrate financial resources on other projects.</p>
<p>&quot;We were really working against the clock,&quot; said Crocker Snow, president of World Times, which publishes WorldPaper, a weekly supplement used by newspapers and magazines in 26 countries. The company announced its bid June 2.</p>
<p>Nearly 70 Monitor Radio employees will lose their jobs at the network's Boston headquarters in addition to staff and stringers in several bureaus, Schardt said.</p>
<p>Monitor Radio began operation in 1984 and now distributes three weekday magazine-style programmes and an hourly headline service. It is often used by stations to supplement programming by the larger National Public Radio network.</p>
<p>The church in 1992 shut down its short-lived cable television network, The Monitor Channel, and sold a Boston television station because of financial problems. It is also attempting to sell two shortwave radio stations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
