<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694295" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: TENNIS-IVANISEVIC FELLED DESPITE RECORD ACE TALLY.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-IVANISEVIC FELLED DESPITE RECORD ACE TALLY.</headline>
<byline>Robert Kitson</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Big-serving Goran Ivanisevic fell victim to one of the most courageous displays in recent Wimbledon history on Saturday as tennis finally resurfaced at the rainswept All England Club after two blank days.</p>
<p>Ivanisevic, the second seed and twice a losing finalist, set a new record for the number of aces in a match at Wimbledon but still sank to a remarkable 6-3 2-6 7-6 4-6 14-12 second round defeat against Sweden's Magnus Norman.</p>
<p>Norman beat world number one Pete Sampras at the recent French Open, but is also notable for forging a successful professional career despite a long-standing heart problem.</p>
<p>An extra valve which led to him suffering an irregular heartbeat has not stopped him rising to 38th in the world, even though doctors have warned him that he would require surgery if the condition resurfaced.</p>
<p>After two years with a clean bill of health, there were thus more than the usual flutterings of concern when, on game point at 6-6 in the fifth set, the 21-year-old called for medical staff and appeared to indicate a problem with pons.</p>
<p>After lengthy discussions and a couple of pills, he opted to continue and somehow ignored the fusillade of aces flying past him to clinch an extraordinary win in the 26th game of a fifth set which lasted almost an hour and a half.</p>
<p>Ivanisevic finished with 46 aces and the prospect of a fine after declining to attend his post-match press conference, clearly furious at his second successive early exit from a grand slam tournament.</p>
<p>It turned out to be a hectic day for the first-aid staff with defending champion Richard Krajicek and Briton's Greg Rusedski both riding their luck to reach the third round.</p>
<p>The fourth-seeded Krajicek won 3-6 6-4 6-7 6-3 6-3 against Andrei Pavel of Romania, but was trailing by a set and 3-2 when his opponent required lengthy treatment on a wrist injury.</p>
<p>Rusedski, meanwhile, had to fight back from two sets down for the first time in his career after overcoming a back injury which required him to wear a supporting corset.</p>
<p>He eventually outlasted American Jonathan Stark 4-6 6-7 6-4 6-3 11-9 in a contest which contained plenty of needle and also saw Rusedski receive a warning for time wasting.</p>
<p>&quot;My physio cancelled all his appointments to come down here and fix me up,&quot; said Rusedski, who strained a muscle in his back during morning practice.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't want to let down all the people who came to watch me today.&quot;</p>
<p>With Tim Henman easing past Frenchman Jerome Golmard and Andrew Richardson beating Spain's Juan Albert Viloca, Britain have three representatives in the third round for the first time in 20 years.</p>
<p>Before they celebrate too hard, though, they should note the familiar names still lurking in the men's draw. Boris Becker was a smooth straight sets winner over Thomas Johansson of Sweden and another former champion, Michael Stich, is also through.</p>
<p>Tenth seed Carlos Moya was a casualty, however, falling 6-4 6-3 6-3 to American Richey Reneberg to leave South African Wayne Ferreira as the only remaining seed in the bottom quarter of the draw.</p>
<p>In the women's singles, world number one Martina Hingis breezed through but 16-year-old Russian Anna Kournikova had to fight for her life against Germany's Barbara Rittner.</p>
<p>Rittner led by a set and 5-1, only for Kournikova to battle back and take a second set tiebreak 9-7 before winning the last 6-3 to reach the third round.</p>
<p>There will be little chance for anyone to reflect on the day's drama and incident as the All England Club announced on Saturday there would be play on the middle Sunday for only the second time in history.</p>
<p>The heavy rain in the opening week has caused a huge backlog of matches which even a dry day on Saturday failed to clear completely.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
