<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694285" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: SOCCER-10-MAN NEW ZEALAND CRUSHED BY SOCCEROOS.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-10-MAN NEW ZEALAND CRUSHED BY SOCCEROOS.</headline>
<dateline>AUCKLAND 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia took a stranglehold on their World Cup Oceania zone play-off when they beat 10-man New Zealand 3-0 in the first leg on Saturday.</p>
<p>New Zealand played the final 23 minutes with 10 men after midfielder Chris Jackson was booked for a second time for a clumsy challenge on Ned Zelic.</p>
<p>The Socceroos, boasting a string of European-based professionals in their line-up, translated their superiority on paper on to the pitch.</p>
<p>They dominated the midfield through Zelic and Aurelio Vidmar, were full of running up front and rarely allowed New Zealand to threaten their goal.</p>
<p>Australia's opening goal in the 19th minute came after a defensive error, Craig Foster latching on to the loose ball to set up John Aloisi.</p>
<p>They were two up in the 42nd minute thanks to a fine strike by Vidmar from outside the penalty area. Foster made it 3-0 midway through the second half when he chipped New Zealand goalkeeper Jason Batty.</p>
<p>The return leg is in Sydney next Saturday, with the winners going on to face the fourth-ranked Asian nation for a place in the World Cup finals in France next year.</p>
<p>Teams:</p>
<p>New Zealand - Jason Batty, Danny Hay, Ivan Vicelich, Gavin Wilkinson, Mark Atkinson, Simon Elliot, Michael McGarry, Chris Jackson, Riki van Steeden, Wynton Rufer, Vaughen Coveny.</p>
<p>Australia - Mark Bosnich, Craig Moore, Steve Horvat, Alex Tobin, Robbie Slater, Stan Lazaridis, Craig Foster, Ned Zelic, Aurelio Vidmar, Graham Arnold, John Aloisi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AUCKLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
