<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694292" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: TENNIS-HEART PROBLEM NORMAN PUTS OUT ACE-MAN IVANISEVIC.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-HEART PROBLEM NORMAN PUTS OUT ACE-MAN IVANISEVIC.</headline>
<byline>Clare Lovell</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Battling Swede Magnus Norman, who suffers from a heart problem, might have to pull out of the Wimbledon despite beating big-hitting number two seed Goran Ivanisevic in a marathon five-set tussle on Saturday.</p>
<p>The brave Swede, who needed courtside treatment for a racing heart beat during the 14-12 final set, ran down everything to win despite the Croatian beating the championship record for aces served in a match.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm going to phone my doctor in Sweden and we're going to take the decision tomorrow,&quot; the 21-year-old Swede said when asked whether he might have to scratch from the tournament.</p>
<p>&quot;I've had the problem twice before. The last time it lasted 40 minutes. Today it was only 30 seconds,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ivanisevic, who stalked off court after the three hour 23 minute match and refused to be interviewed, thumped down 46 aces, surpassing the previous record of 42 set by Britain's John Feaver against John Newcombe also in the second round in 1976. Feaver also lost.</p>
<p>It was Norman, who totalled a respectable 25 aces in the match, who made the running. He won the first set 6-3 with one break of serve in 26 minutes.</p>
<p>Ivanisevic, renowned for his volatile temperament, stormed back in the 22-minute second set which he won 6-2 with two breaks after some fine returns.</p>
<p>But Norman, steeled himself to the task, ran the net whenever possible and hit flurries of volley winners to put the Croatian, twice runner-up here, on the defensive.</p>
<p>Though the 21-year-old Swede has played in only five Grand Slam tournaments to Ivanisevic's 32, he showed remarkable nerve, winning a tie-break in the third set 7-4. By this time the Croatian was angrily berating himself in his native tongue.</p>
<p>Ivanisevic won the fourth set 6-4 in just 24 minutes and then the pair embarked on their 88-minute final stretch.</p>
<p>But at 6-6 and advantage, Norman, ranked 38 in the world, clutched his chest and asked the umpire to call for help. He sat at the side of the court, looking pale and in obvious distress.</p>
<p>His trainer arrived and gave him some tablets. After some deep breathing he was able to resume serving. Ivanisevic put a volley out and Norman won the game.</p>
<p>He said he had been very worried when he sat down and called for assistance. &quot;If it had continued throughout the three minute break I would have defaulted,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But the Swede, who put world number one out of the French Open earlier this year, played on apparently unaffected by the episode.</p>
<p>He went back on the attack earning two match points in the 22nd game and saving four break points in a nail-biting 23rd game before producing a scathing cross court pass for the match.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
