<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694269" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-LIONS SHOW TRUE GRIT TO CLINCH SERIES WIN.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-LIONS SHOW TRUE GRIT TO CLINCH SERIES WIN.</headline>
<byline>Mark Stokes</byline>
<dateline>DURBAN 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stout defence under extreme pressure and the accurate boot of Welsh fullback Neil Jenkins clinched a memorable series victory for the 1997 British Lions over South Africa on Saturday.</p>
<p>Although outscored by three tries to nil, the Lions produced a remarkably gritty display to win a match 18-15 which was largely dominated by the Springboks.</p>
<p>The Lions, in emulating the achievement of Willie John McBride's great side of 1974, had to come back from a 15-9 deficit with under half an hour remaining.</p>
<p>The nerveless Jenkins kicked five penalties out of five and English centre Jeremy Guscott coolly slotted a drop goal three minutes from time to give the Lions only their second series win over South Africa this century.</p>
<p>The Lions won the first test of the three-match series 25-16 in Cape Town a week ago.</p>
<p>Yet the Lions had to withstand a furious onslaught from a committed Springbok pack and three well-taken tries from scrumhalf Joost van der Westhuizen, test debutant Percy Montgomery and fullback Andre Joubert.</p>
<p>South Africa produced a high-octane start from the very first whistle, with a muscular forward drive advancing them to the edge of the Lions' 22-metre line.</p>
<p>Springbok flyhalf Henry Honiball, who produced some telling tactical kicking in the second half, missed two penalties in the first seven minutes but South Africa dominated territorially as they punched several holes upfield with some powerful driving.</p>
<p>Against the run of play, Jenkins opened a 3-0 lead in the 17th minute with a penalty from just inside the Springbok half and then, 10 minutes before the break, added a second after South Africa were penalised for collapsing a maul.</p>
<p>But South Africa hit back with the first try of the match when van der Westhuizen burrowed over the line in the right-hand corner after peeling off the back of a maul.</p>
<p>With prop Os du Randt outside him, van der Westhuizen sold an outrageous dummy and managed to fight his way over for the score with Lions hooker Keith Wood on his back.</p>
<p>Montgomery's failure to convert gave the Lions a 6-5 advantage at the break.</p>
<p>From the re-start, South Africa took the lead for the first time in the match when Montgomery crossed the line by the right-hand corner flag.</p>
<p>Honiball regained possession after launching an up-and-under at left wing Alan Tait and inside centre Danie van Schalkwyk was on hand to take the pass and create space for Montgomery to cross unchallenged.</p>
<p>Jenkins hauled the Lions back to within a point with a third penalty from in front of the posts but Springbok fullback Joubert hit back quickly, shrugging off both John Bentley and Neil Jenkins to score South Africa's third try in the 54th minute.</p>
<p>Joubert missed his first attempt at the posts but with a 15-9 lead, the Springboks looked set to level the series.</p>
<p>However, the metronomic Jenkins equalised at 15-15 with two more penalties in the final quarter before Guscott's well-timed drop goal sealed both the match and the series.</p>
<p>South Africa: 15-Andre Joubert; 14-Andre Snyman, 13-Percy Montgomery, 12-Danie van Schalkwyk, 11-Pieter Rossouw; 10-Henry Honiball, 9-Joost van der Westhuizen; 8-Gary Teichmann (captain), 7-Andre Venter, 6-Ruben Kruger (Fritz van Heerden 51), 5-Mark Andrews, 4-Hannes Strydom, 3-Adrian Garvey (Dawie Theron 67), 2-Naka Drotske, 1-Os du Randt.</p>
<p>British Lions: 15-Neil Jenkins; 14-John Bentley, 13-Scott Gibbs, 12-Jeremy Guscott, 11-Alan Tait (Austin Healey 76); 10-Gregor Townsend, 9-Matt Dawson; 8-Tim Rodber (Eric Miller 77), 7-Richard Hill (Neil Back 56), 6-Lawrence Dallaglio, 5-Jeremy Davidson, 4-Martin Johnson (captain), 3-Paul Wallace, 2-Keith Wood, 1-Tom Smith.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DURBAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
