<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694275" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>NETHERLANDS: MOTORCYCLING-DOOHAN CONTINUES 500CC SUPREMACY.</title>
<headline>MOTORCYCLING-DOOHAN CONTINUES 500CC SUPREMACY.</headline>
<byline>Bert Lauwers</byline>
<dateline>ASSEN, Netherlands 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>World champion Michael Doohan claimed his sixth success of the season by winning the rain-interrupted Dutch 500cc motorcycling grand prix on Saturday.</p>
<p>It was the Australian's 40th career victory and fourth consecutive win in Assen, giving him a 68-point championship lead over Honda team mate Alex Criville, who did not race after injuring his hand badly in a high-speed crash in Thursday's practice.</p>
<p>Doohan, who started from pole position, won both sections of the race which was split in two when rain prompted officials to call a halt with 11 laps completed.</p>
<p>Honda rider Carlos Checa of Spain, who was in second place when the race was interrupted, came third in the second part of the 20-lap race to take second place overall ahead of Italian Aprilia rider Doriano Romboni.</p>
<p>&quot;Conditions were definitely tricky today and had it not been for a five-minute delay for some reason we would have completed enough of the race distance in race one and we wouldn't have had to take so many risks in race two. I just hope this never happens again,&quot; a disgruntled Doohan said.</p>
<p>If the race is more than two-thirds completed, positions at the time of the stoppage become final results, according to championship rules.</p>
<p>The fast changing weather conditions made it hard for riders to decide which tyres to put on for the second part of the race.</p>
<p>&quot;We had to take a gamble with an intermediate in the rear and a wet on the front because we didn't know what the situation would bring,&quot; Doohan said.</p>
<p>&quot;In the beginning I had quite a few moments with the rear letting go and as the race progressed...the race track became completely dry and I got problems at the front of the bike, and a lot of spinning in the rear,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Japan's Tetsuya Harada, riding an Aprilia, surged past Honda rider Ralf Waldmann of Germany in the final kilometre to win his second consecutive 250cc race.</p>
<p>Waldmann snatched the championship lead from Italian Max Biaggi, who was disqualified on lap six for failing to comply with a stop-and-go penalty given after mechanics continued to work on his bike on the circuit less than three minutes before the start of the warm-up lap.</p>
<p>Defending champion Biaggi, who had decided to change his front tyre shortly before the race, was black-flagged after he failed to acknowledge his pit signals for three laps.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm really angry,&quot; said Biaggi, who is now trailing seven points behind Waldmann, with Harada a further five points adrift.</p>
<p>&quot;To lose a race through a misunderstanding is really bad. There was only one of the team showing me the board, I can't understand why there weren't more guys waving at me,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Italian teenager Valentino Rossi toyed with the opposition en route to his fifth victory of the season in the 125cc category to extend his championship lead to 33 points over Noboru Ueda of Japan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ASSEN, Netherlands"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NETHERLANDS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
