<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694376" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: U.N. helps capture Serb war crimes suspect.</title>
<headline>U.N. helps capture Serb war crimes suspect.</headline>
<byline>Zoran Radosavljevic</byline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.N. peacekeepers have for the first time helped the International War Crimes Tribunal in former Yugoslavia capture a war crimes suspect, a U.N. official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Tribunal officials arrested Slavko Dokmanovic in Croatia's Eastern Slavonia region on Friday. The predominantly Serb region, monitored by a provisional U.N. Administration, is due to revert to Croatian rule soon.</p>
<p>&quot;We gave support to the (Tribunal) officials on the ground within instructions from a U.N. resolution that says the (UN Administration) shall cooperate with the Tribunal,&quot; a U.N. official in the enclave told Reuters. &quot;It's the first time that has happened&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;But (the Tribunal) did the actual arrest,&quot; the official who asked to remain anonymous said, refusing to elaborate on the kind of support some of the 5,000 UN Administration soldiers provided.</p>
<p>Dokmanovic was president of Vukovar in November 1991, when the Yugoslavia People's Army and Serb paramilitaries were alleged to have abducted from its hospital and killed around 260 men after a brutal three-month siege of the city.</p>
<p>The Yugoslav government protested strongly to the U.N. administrator Jacques Klein, saying the arrest was an &quot;action which brings into question the credibility of UNTAES&quot;.</p>
<p>Describing it as a &quot;most serious incident&quot;, Yugoslavia said it could &quot;have serious consequences for the further course of the peace process&quot;.</p>
<p>UNTAES's current mandate expires on July 15, when Croatia wants to take full control of the enclave.</p>
<p>The Yugoslav news agency Tanjug, quoting a statement by Serb leaders in Eastern Slavonia, said that Dokmanovic was innocent of the war crimes charges as &quot;he was not in any position of authority&quot; in November, 1991.</p>
<p>It said he was then a member of the rebel Croatian Serb government in Erdut in Eastern Slavonia, in charge of agriculture. &quot;So he could not be linked to any of the events for which The Hague is charging him,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Another Belgrade agency, Beta, said Serbs in the area were alarmed by the arrest, fearing they might unknowingly be Tribunal suspects, but UNTAES said in a statement Dokmanovic was the only person in the region indicted by the Tribunal.</p>
<p>The Tribunal, established in May, 1993, has indicted 75 suspects, mostly Serbs, but holds only nine in custody. The two main indictees at liberty are are former Bosnian Serb leader Radovan Karadzic and his military commander Ratko Mladic.</p>
<p>Both are at large somewhere in Bosnia, which is patrolled by thousands of NATO troops with no powers of arrest.</p>
<p>U.S. dipomat Robert Frowick, who heads the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) mission in Bosnia, on Saturday urged greater vigour in the pursuit of war criminals.</p>
<p>He told an international business conference in Switzerland that failure to detain them undermined the peace process and that other &quot;creative&quot; ways to arrest them should be found if NATO cannot do the job.</p>
<p>The U.N. official said Dokmanovic had left Eastern Slavonia some six months ago and settled in Serbia's northern province of Vojvodina, across the Danube river, but paid occasional visits to the area.</p>
<p>Dokmanovic was indicted on March 26 last year in an unpublished amendment to the so-called &quot;Vukovar indictment&quot; earlier issued against three Yugoslav People's Army (JNA) officers for their involvement in the alleged massacre.</p>
<p>The three officers are now believed to be living in Yugoslavia, which has so far made no move to hand them over to the Tribunal.</p>
<p>Details of the charges against Dokmanovic had not been made public at the time in order to facilitate his arrest. &quot;It was a so-called sealed indictment,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;It sends a signal that international community cares that individuals who committed crimes against humanity are brought to justice,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
