<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694394" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAJIKISTAN: Tajik capital celebrates end of civil war.</title>
<headline>Tajik capital celebrates end of civil war.</headline>
<byline>Sergei Yakovlev</byline>
<dateline>DUSHANBE 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tajik people flocked to lavish street festivities on Saturday to celebrate a peace agreement ending four years of civil war in their former Soviet republic.</p>
<p>The celebrations in Tajikistan's capital, Dushanbe, were decreed by President Imomali Rakhmonov after he and Islamic opposition leader Sayid Abdullo Nuri signed the peace agreement in Moscow on Friday.</p>
<p>Folk music boomed out of loudspeakers and crowds of people rushed to squares and parks where tables were laden with meat and sweet dishes. Farmers from neighbouring villages were selling fruit and vegetables at improvised fairs.</p>
<p>&quot;In the long run, peace has come to Tajikistan and enmity has ended,&quot; Rakhmonov told a rally.</p>
<p>&quot;In Tajikistan, there are no people who would be against peace and prosperity, but even if there are, those are the enemies of the Tajik people.&quot;</p>
<p>The civil war killed tens of thousands of people and forced many more from their homes before a ceasefire was agreed last December. The truce has largely held.</p>
<p>The peace accord -- brokered by Iran, Russia and the United Nations and completed despite last-minute wrangling over a stalled prisoner exchange and power-sharing -- is a major hope for peace in the Central Asian state of 5.7 million people.</p>
<p>In Washington, the U.S. State Department said the deal offered a historic opportunity for Tajikistan to enter into a new political era and urged all sides to forge a lasting peace.</p>
<p>&quot;We urge the negotiating sides, and the whole Tajik nation, to take full advantage of this opportunity to move beyond its civil conflict, as it is only the Tajik sides themselves that can fulfil implementation of the accords,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>But Nuri -- who did not attend the festivities in Dushanbe -- said in Moscow after the signing that Tajikistan's troubles were still far from over. &quot;Both sides need to make more sacrifice and effort,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hardliners in both camps, an economy which is in tatters and a profusion of armed criminal bands make the peace fragile.</p>
<p>The agreement envisages the creation of a 26-member National Commission for Reconciliation, to be chaired by Nuri, with places to be divided equally between each side and which must start work before July 7.</p>
<p>Rakhmonov remains president but 30 percent of government posts must be given over to the opposition.</p>
<p>Elections for a new parliament must take place before the end of 1998 while opposition guerrillas must integrate with government forces or lay down their arms.</p>
<p>Russia, which fears the advent of a militant, Taleban-style Islam from neighbouring Afghanistan and keeps in Tajikistan some 20,000 of its servicemen who guard the Afghan border, is an important factor for the peace process.</p>
<p>Lieutenent-General Pavel Tarasenko, commander of Russian border guards in Tajikistan, told a news conference on Saturday that Tajik refugees and unarmed opposition fighters would soon be allowed to return from Afghanistan through two checkpoints.</p>
<p>He said border tensions, fanned by armed bands and drug traders operating from bases in Afghanistan, should now subside.</p>
<p>&quot;We, Russian border guards, hail the signing of this document. We believe...the situation will become more stable and quiet,&quot; Tarasenko said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TADZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUSHANBE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAJIKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
