<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694316" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: ATHLETICS-KOMEN TRIUMPHS AT KENYA TRIALS.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-KOMEN TRIUMPHS AT KENYA TRIALS.</headline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Daniel Komen won a demanding 5,000 metres at Kenya's national trials for the world championships on Saturday, then declared his prize would be a victory over Ethiopian Haile Gebrselassie.</p>
<p>While Komen triumphed over a world-class field, a number of top performers including Olympic 3,000 metres steeplechase champion Josephat Keter were well beaten in their specialities.</p>
<p>Double 5,000 metres world champion Ishmael Kirui was the first casualty, clocking 13:46.0 for sixth place in the event.</p>
<p>Kenyan selectors delayed naming the team for the world championships in Athens in August until July 16 when top athletes will have completed their Grand Prix assignments.</p>
<p>Under current Kenya Amateur Athletic Association rules, the first two finishers automatically qualify. The third place will be based on training.</p>
<p>Senior sports sources said the selectors were attempting to avoid the type of error that led to Komen's absence from the Atlanta Olympics. At the time, Komen had failed to come through at the Kenyan trials but had a successful Grand Prix run.</p>
<p>&quot;I will meet with Gebrselassie, then we shall see who is who. I am confident that I shall win,&quot; Komen said after returning 13 minutes 23.8 seconds, beating Tom Nyariki, who clocked 13:25.1, and Paul Bitok, who was timed at 13:27.0.</p>
<p>World 3,000 metres steeplechase champion and record holder Moses Kiptanui confirmed he was returning to his winning ways after claiming his speciality in 8:13.0.</p>
<p>&quot;I am definitely going for my fourth world title and hope to hang on until the 2000 Olympics, then I (will) retire,&quot; Kiptanui said. &quot;Last year I felt stronger than now but lost at the Olympics because of illness. I am okay now.&quot;</p>
<p>Kiptanui eased to the front from the start and maintained his lead until midway when Bernard Barmasai and Patrick Sang briefly went ahead. But with two laps to go, Kiptanui, showing no sign of stress, regained his lead and won easily.</p>
<p>In the 800 metres, Olympic bronze medalist Fredrick Onyancha also fell by the wayside, in seventh place. Commonwealth champion Patrick Konchellah, making a comeback after an accident nearly ruined his career in 1995, won in 1:46.2 ahead of Benson Koech, who posted 1:46.03, and David Kiptoo, who recorded 1:46.4.</p>
<p>Big names to fall in the 1,500 metres included Barcelona Olympics 800 metres champion William Tanui, who was in fourth place and Martin Keino, son of legendary Kipchoge Keino, who finished in a poor sixth place in 3:40.5.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ETHPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
