<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694365" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMEROON: Cameroon president extends budget year.</title>
<headline>Cameroon president extends budget year.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Wotany</byline>
<dateline>YAOUNDE 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cameroon President Paul Biya issued a decree on Saturday extending the government's financial year by a month while the newly elected parliament debates a new budget for the Central African nation.</p>
<p>State radio reported that the extension would run from July 1 to 31 with a budget of one twelfth of the 1996/97 allocation.</p>
<p>Officials said the new national assembly, where Biya's party won a crushing majority in a May 17 parliamentary election denounced as rigged by the opposition, would begin its debate on the 1997/98 budget on Tuesday.</p>
<p>They attributed the delay to postponement of the parliamentary election from March to May. The institutions of the new assembly did not take proper shape until Friday.</p>
<p>Cameroon's new parliament held its inaugural session on June 17 with the opposition attending and vowing to play a full part, despite a boycott threat. Biya's Cameroon People's Democratic Rally (RDPC) holds 109 of the 180 seats.</p>
<p>The opposition Social democratic Front of John Fru Ndi has 43 seats, the National Union for Democracy and Progress (UNDP) of Bello Bouba Maigari 13, the Cameroon Democratic Union (UDC) five, and three small parties one each.</p>
<p>Results were cancelled in three constituencies -- seven seats -- because of what the supreme court described as &quot;severe irregularities and massive fraud&quot;.</p>
<p>The SDF and the UNDP called for all results to be scrapped. International observers highlighted problems during polling, in the second elections of a multi-party era begun in 1990.</p>
<p>Biya, who took over from independence president Ahmadou Ahidjo in 1982, seeks reelection in October. Fru Ndi narrowly lost the 1992 election, which the opposition says was rigged.</p>
<p>The parliament, meeting late on Friday, reelected northerner Cavaye Yegue Djibril, a member of the ruling party and the longest-serving legislator, as speaker for the next five years.</p>
<p>Sources close to the assembly said that even opposition politicians voted for him.</p>
<p>The north has most of the nation's voters and provided the majority of the ruling party's assembly members in May.</p>
<p>Earlier, state radio reported that oil producer Cameroon would raise gasoline prices by up to 7.2 percent from July 1 because of rising prices on the world market and the strengthening of the U.S. dollar against the CFA franc.</p>
<p>An official statement said a litre of top-grade gasoline would rise to 380 from 360 CFA francs, diesel to 295 CFA from 275 CFA and ordinary gasoline to 160 CFA from 150 CFA.</p>
<p>($1=595 CFA)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CAMER">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="YAOUNDE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMEROON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
