<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694312" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-GUSCOTT DROP GOAL CLINCHES HISTORIC LIONS WIN.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-GUSCOTT DROP GOAL CLINCHES HISTORIC LIONS WIN.</headline>
<dateline>DURBAN, South Africa 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The British Lions clinched a historic series victory in South Africa for only the second time this century as they edged to a fraught 18-15 victory in the second test in Durban on Saturday.</p>
<p>The victory put Martin Johnson's 1997 tourists on a par with the 'immortal' 1974 Lions of Willie John McBride who became the first British combination since 1896 to win a series against the Springboks.</p>
<p>The victory was founded once again on staunch defence and the boot of Neil Jenkins who kicked five out of five penalties to keep the Lions in touch as they were pinned in their own half for much of the game.</p>
<p>A South African side ferociously bent on revenge for their 25-16 defeat in the first test scored tries through scrum-half Joost van der Westhuizen, centre Percival Montgomery and Andre Joubert.</p>
<p>But three different kickers missed all six of their kicks at goal allowing a Jeremy Guscott drop goal three minutes from time to clinch the series amid scenes of delirious celebration among the tourists.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DURBAN, South Africa"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
