<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694349" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK pledges help for volcano-hit Montserrat.</title>
<headline>UK pledges help for volcano-hit Montserrat.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain expressed sympathy on Saturday for the victims of Montserrat's volcanic eruption and promised help for the Caribbean colony this weekend.</p>
<p>At least nine people were killed when Montserrat's rumbling volcano doused the island with ash on Wednesday and scientists warned that another eruption could be imminent. It was the first fatal incident since the volcano burst to life two years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The government takes its responsibility for the people of Montserrat very seriously. My deepest sympathy goes out to those who have been bereaved by last Wednesday's eruption, and to the others who have suffered. We sincerely hope that those people who are still missing will be found safe and sound,&quot; junior foreign minister Baroness Symons said in a statement.</p>
<p>Symons said she would be visiting the Caribbean island, a British territory, on Sunday and Monday.</p>
<p>HMS Liverpool is due to arrive off Monserrat on Sunday evening and the Black Rover tanker is due the following day to provide medical help and carry out search and rescue misions.</p>
<p>George Foulkes, minister at the Department of International Development, said Britain had set up a task force of officials to consider the crisis &quot;as a matter of the utmost urgency&quot;.</p>
<p>Governor Frank Savage has said there is no plan for an island-wide evacuation but at least 14 people are still missing and villages remain covered in ash and volcanic material.</p>
<p>Symons said the British were doing their utmost to help.</p>
<p>&quot;The governor and his staff and the government and officials of Montserrat have been working around the clock and although I visited the island only two weeks ago, I thought it was essential to see for myself what help is needed by the people of Montserrat at this extremely testing time,&quot; Symons said.</p>
<p>Montserrat is a British colony in the eastern Caribbean, close to Antigua. It has about 6,800 residents, a third lower than the 11,000 it had when the volcano first became active.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MONT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
