<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694360" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CONGO: Angry troops block French envoy in Brazzaville.</title>
<headline>Angry troops block French envoy in Brazzaville.</headline>
<byline>Emmanuel Braun</byline>
<dateline>BRAZZAVILLE 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Angry soldiers loyal to Congo Republic President Pascal Lissouba prevented France's ambassador leaving Brazzaville's embattled city centre on Saturday, effectively trapping him in his embassy.</p>
<p>The soldiers, who were manning a roadblock, refused to let Ambassador Raymond Cesaire, other French diplomats and journalists leave the area in a convoy for the comparative safety of the ambassador's residence even though they had an official Congolese escort with them.</p>
<p>The soldiers appeared to have no commander and an anti-French attitude.</p>
<p>Earlier, commanders in the warring factions in the capital agreed verbally to a new week-long ceasefire.</p>
<p>Fighting eased on Saturday but as during previous truces in a three-week showdown between Lissouba and his predecessor, former Marxist military ruler Denis Sassou Nguesso, some shooting continued as the rival forces jockeyed for position.</p>
<p>Civilians, fearing for their lives after battles in which the indiscriminate use of rockets and mortars has made anyone and everyone a target, jostled to take trucks and buses out of the southern suburbs -- relatively unscathed to date.</p>
<p>Military chiefs agreed late on Friday to order a truce for a week, but neutral mediators under mayor Bernard Kolelas, having seen previous accords fall apart, were cautious.</p>
<p>&quot;This was agreed orally but not in writing because we prefer that the population should be the ones who decide if the ceasefire really takes hold,&quot; an aide to Kolelas, whose own fighters have kept out of the conflict to date, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;The ceasefires here are like fish -- good when fresh, then they go off,&quot; one French official in the city commented.</p>
<p>Cesaire tried to take advantage of Saturday's lull to make a dash to his residence, a former home of General Charles de Gaulle, in the calmer southern Bacongo suburb.</p>
<p>It was his first trip out in several days.</p>
<p>Former colonial power France protested to Lissouba last week after his men assaulted Cesaire, beat up his bodyguard and fired shots at his escort after a visit to the presidency.</p>
<p>Tens of thousands of people fled the city on Thursday and Friday after a battle to control the international airport ignited the heaviest artillery exchanges so far. Both sides claimed victory but independent confirmation was not possible.</p>
<p>More of the city's one million residents jostled to get a place on trucks or buses that were leaving on Saturday, heading into the countryside from the southern suburbs.</p>
<p>These suburbs, held by Kolelas militia, had provided refuge to people fleeing the front line that bisects the city centre. This week dozens of shells, presumably strays, landed there.</p>
<p>Medical workers estimate that 1,000 to 3,000 people, mostly civilians caught in crossfire, have died since the clashes began on June 5 when Lissouba moved to disarm Sassou's &quot;Cobra&quot; militia in the run-up to a July 27 presidential election.</p>
<p>The president has accused Sassou Nguesso of trying to stage a coup, Sassou Nguesso says Lissouba provoked trouble to cling on to power beyond the now suspended presidential election.</p>
<p>Lissouba has pleaded for immediate military help from France via his ambassador in Paris. &quot;If France does not act as rapidly as possible, Congo's democratic regime will live or perish in bloodshed,&quot; wrote Pierre-Michel Nguimbi.</p>
<p>Paris pulled out some 1,250 soldiers over a week ago after evacuating almost 6,000 foreign nationals, and has declined to supply troops for a proposed U.N. peacekeeping force.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CONGO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRAZZAVILLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
