<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694352" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Britons usher in summer with rain, mud and humour.</title>
<headline>Britons usher in summer with rain, mud and humour.</headline>
<byline>Lyndsay Griffiths</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Wimbledon is a washout, Glastonbury is a mud-bath and cinemas are packed.</p>
<p>Day in, day out, the rain buckets down, just as Britain settles into its beloved summer season of sport, society events and garden parties.</p>
<p>From racing at Ascot to rowing at Henley, opera at Glyndebourne to pop and folk music at Glastonbury, the short but sweet season of summer events is based on the premise that the sun will actually shine.</p>
<p>No such luck this year.</p>
<p>&quot;Typical. Just typical. You vote for these politicians. They promise you balmy days and a long hot summer, and what happens? It rains,&quot; said the Independent newspaper in an editorial. &quot;Same old story: game, set and match to the weather.&quot;</p>
<p>The Wimbledon tennis tournament faced a 256-match backlog as England heads for its wettest June since 1879. Amid threats to abandon the entire tournament, officials were frantically looking at ways to squeeze play into the dry patches -- if and when they come.</p>
<p>Local traders said they were swamped in unwanted merchandise: 40,000 cans of warm soda sat unsold after the wettest first week in Wimbledon history and T-shirts were offered cut-price before local heroes even fell.</p>
<p>In slushy Somerset, south-west England, 90,000 music fans huddled under umbrellas, bin-liners and makeshift tents as they squelched to the beat at the annual Glastonbury festival. Umbrellas were sold as quickly as illicit drugs; mud-wrestling was the sport of choice.</p>
<p>Festival organisersl had a refugee village of 100 tents bought from Oxfam and lamented its decision to save money by skipping rain insurance.</p>
<p>But plenty of other people have banked on that most British of natural phenomena, and the insurance industry was predicting a 20 million pound ($33 million) bill for floods, accidents and events washed out by rain.</p>
<p>Tour operators reported a rush of requests for sunny getaways, but for those stuck at home, life ambled on.</p>
<p>&quot;The statisticians are playing wettest Junes and the British public is getting on with what it is best at: sitting in the rain in a triumph of hope over expectation of a nice day,&quot; said the Times.</p>
<p>&quot;Wading through, with a dripping upper lip and the bullfrog spirit, is the last summer sport at which the British naturally excel.&quot;</p>
<p>Mastershoe store in Bristol sold a year's supply of rubber Wellington boots in two days, and drought-plagued water companies were ecstatic over their good luck.</p>
<p>&quot;Water is our commodity and the more of it that falls the better,&quot; said Yorkshire Water.</p>
<p>At Blackpool, the beaches were deserted but tourism officer Mike Chadwick insisted spirits weren't dampened.</p>
<p>&quot;Rain doesn't stop play here,&quot; he said. &quot;It rained the day Blackpool Tower was opened 100 years ago so we are used to it.&quot;</p>
<p>Indeed, some political commentators even found a silver lining in all the clouds.</p>
<p>&quot;You could be wet and cold and still living under a Tory (Conservative) government,&quot; said the left-leaning Mirror newspaper. &quot;And if it rains every day between now and September, England's cricketers will still win the Ashes 1-0 and our tennis players won't have lost at Wimbledon.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
