<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694301" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: TENNIS SPOTLIGHT-WILLIAMS MEETS HER MATCH IN GRZYBOWSKA.</title>
<headline>TENNIS SPOTLIGHT-WILLIAMS MEETS HER MATCH IN GRZYBOWSKA.</headline>
<byline>Clare Fallon</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Venus Williams made her eagerly-awaited debut at Wimbledon on Saturday after five days of rain delays -- and promptly lost in the first round.</p>
<p>In keeping with her name, the American teenager is being touted as the rising star of women's tennis but she met her match in Poland's 18-year-old Magdalena Grzybowska.</p>
<p>Williams's weapons are her height -- 1.86 metres -- her power and her intelligent all-court game. Unluckily for her, Grzybowska possesses exactly the same attributes.</p>
<p>Grzybowska, ranked 91 in the world to Williams's 59, won the match 4-6 6-2 6-4 in one hour 49 minutes.</p>
<p>But Williams, who had covered her braided hair with beads in Wimbledon's purple and green colours for the occasion, was not down-hearted.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not too disappointed,&quot; the 17-year-old said. &quot;It's my first Wimbledon and there will be many more to come.&quot;</p>
<p>Williams looked likely to make hard work of the tie from the start, hitting the first of 11 double faults to cede the first point of her opening service game.</p>
<p>Beads clattering in the cold air on Court One, Williams fought off two breakpoints to hold for 3-3 and then broke Grzybowska in the next game. The Pole, in her turn, contributed a double fault on breakpoint.</p>
<p>Williams had played only one previous tournament on grass -- last week's Eastbourne event -- but despite her lack of experience on the surface she was not afraid to come to the net.</p>
<p>She wrapped up the first set in 38 minutes with a service winner on her third set point.</p>
<p>Grzybowska, perhaps down-hearted by her lost opportunities in the opening set, hit three double faults at the start of the second to help the American to a 1-0 lead.</p>
<p>Williams saved two breakpoints, one with an ace, in the next game which saw some excellent volleying at the net by both women.</p>
<p>But Grzybowska got a break in the fourth game to draw level, fended off four breakpoints to hold in the next game and then broke again with a pass at the net to go 4-2 up.</p>
<p>She won the next game to love, finishing with the flourish of an ace, and took advantage of several forehand errors by Williams to win the set.</p>
<p>Williams continued to have trouble with the accuracy of her shots in the third set and found that luck was not on her side either.</p>
<p>At breakpoint up in the third game she slipped over and Grzybowska passed her. In the eighth game she double faulted, unaware that she was serving with a broken string until umpire Tony Little pointed it out.</p>
<p>As the set drew to a close, Williams grew impatient. She barely sat down at changeovers and was always out pacing the baseline well before Grzybowska had left her chair.</p>
<p>Grzybowska kept her head and calmly broke Williams to love in her final two service games to go through to Wimbledon's second round for the first time in her career.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
