<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694348" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Paisley urges London to back disputed march.</title>
<headline>Paisley urges London to back disputed march.</headline>
<byline>Martin Cowley</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hardline Protestant leader Ian Paisley urged Britain on Saturday to ensure that the most controversial Protestant parade of Northern Ireland's &quot;marching season&quot; is not blocked from a Catholic zone.</p>
<p>The outspoken politician-cleric made the demand after British-led talks failed to produce a compromise about the Drumcree parade near Portadown on July 6.</p>
<p>Paisley said there was only one way that the controversy could be settled and &quot;that is by the British government establishing for all time the right of people to walk on the Queen's highway&quot;.</p>
<p>He said there could be &quot;no fudging, no negotiation, no nonsense&quot; over the matter.</p>
<p>Catholic nationalists along the route have strongly opposed the plan and say they will hold &quot;a street festival&quot; in its path.</p>
<p>Britain is expected next week to decide to ban one or other of the demonstrations amid fears that clashes might break out, repeating the violence of last year.</p>
<p>Paisley, who says Protestant marches have been banned in the past to placate nationalists, is a popular figurehead among Protestant right-wingers.</p>
<p>The annual parade has been organised by the Orange Order, a staunchly pro-British fraternity which holds hundreds of marches.</p>
<p>They climax in province-wide processions on July 12, the anniversary of a landmark Protestant battlefield victory of the Catholic Irish in 1690.</p>
<p>British Northern Ireland Secretary Mo Mowlam brought the Order and Catholic residents under one roof on Friday but the two sides remained in separate rooms and Mowlam said no resolution was found.</p>
<p>The province has been tense for months after a surge in attacks on security forces by the outlawed Irish Republican Army and attacks on Catholics by Protestant extremists.</p>
<p>New Irish Prime Minister Bertie Ahern is due to have talks about Northern Ireland with his British counterpart Tony Blair in London on Thursday.</p>
<p>It is the first meeting between them since Ahern succeeded John Bruton last Thursday.</p>
<p>Last week Blair unveiled a new package, including the launch of full-scale negotations on Northern Ireland's future in September, in a bid to revive stalled peace efforts.</p>
<p>Britain and Ireland say that Sinn Fein will continue to be barred from peace talks until the IRA abandons its hostilities.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
