<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694369" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MAURITANIA: Mauritania opposition to boycott presidential poll.</title>
<headline>Mauritania opposition to boycott presidential poll.</headline>
<dateline>NOUAKCHOTT 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mauritania's mainstream opposition has announced plans to boycott the country's second presidential election since the 1991 advent of multi-party democracy, planned for December 12.</p>
<p>But the five opposition parties, who announced their boycott plans to supporters in the former French colony's capital Nouakchott late on Friday, have left the door open for dialogue on creating conditions for free and fair elections.</p>
<p>&quot;Today there is no democratic process,&quot; Ahmed Ould Daddah, runner-up on the 1992 presidential election, told Radio France International in an interview.</p>
<p>He accused the administration of President Maaouya Ould Sid'Ahmed Taya of fraud, saying this rendered participation in elections under current conditions pointless.</p>
<p>&quot;We have always said and we still say that we are open to dialogue and that for us dialogue and transparency alone can release Mauritanians from the impasse,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Ould Daddah, leader of the Union of Democratic Forces, said the opposition wanted an independent national electoral commission, a trustworthy register of citizens and an administration serving all Mauritanians &quot;not just one clan&quot;.</p>
<p>Taya, then army chief of staff, came to power in the West African state straddling black and Arab Africa in a bloodless coup in 1984, deposing the then military president.</p>
<p>He won the 1992 election in the first round with over 62 percent of the vote, defeating Ould Daddah, half-brother of the country's first president. The opposition cried fraud.</p>
<p>Taya's ruling Democratic and Social Republican Party (DSRP) party won a landslide victory in October legislative elections.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MAURTN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOUAKCHOTT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MAURITANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
