<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694385" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Chronology of Albanian unrest leading up to poll.</title>
<headline>Chronology of Albanian unrest leading up to poll.</headline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The following is a chronology of key events in Albania, where the first round of a general election is being held on Sunday to halt the country's slide into anarchy sparked by the collapse of shady investment funds.</p>
<p>Jan 16 - Unrest breaks out in the southern port town of Vlore after a local investment firm stops payouts.</p>
<p>Jan 19 - Some 3,000 people, led by opposition politicians, break through police cordons to protest in Tirana's centre.</p>
<p>Jan 23 - Parliament bans pyramid schemes.</p>
<p>Jan 24 - Around 5,000 people go on the rampage in the southern town of Lushnje.</p>
<p>Jan 26 - Thousands of people converge on central Tirana and clash with riot police. Government buildings are set ablaze in towns and cities across the country.</p>
<p>Jan 30 - Ten opposition parties form a Forum for Democracy, urging President Sali Berisha to form a technocrat government.</p>
<p>Feb 6 - Over 30,000 people take to the streets in Vlore.</p>
<p>Feb 9 - Enraged protesters attack Vlore police station. One person dies and 40 are injured in the fighting.</p>
<p>Feb 15 - Berisha admits mistakes in handling of pyramid schemes but says the state cannot compensate all investors.</p>
<p>Feb 28 - Democratic Party and main opposition Socialists hold first talks since general election in May 1996. Socialists demand formation of technocrat government and early elections.</p>
<p>Feb 28 - Night-time gunbattle erupts in Vlore after police armoury is looted. At least three civilians and one one secret policeman die and 22 people are injured..</p>
<p>March 1 - Berisha says his government will resign and broad-based successor cabinet will be formed.</p>
<p>March 2 - Rioters in the Adriatic town of Sarande ransack police headquarters, seize weapons, loot shops and banks. Four people are killed and 22 wounded by gunfire in the south.</p>
<p>Parliament declares a state of emergency, banning large gatherings, intorducing night curfew, giving police power to open fire to disperse crowds and imposing media controls.</p>
<p>March 3 - Parliament elects Berisha unopposed for a second five-year term.</p>
<p>March 6 - Berisha, backed by opposition parties, suspends military action against rebels and offers them an amnesty.</p>
<p>March 7 - Rebels reject the amnesty offer.</p>
<p>March 8 - Rebels seize last southern government stronghold of Gjirokaster and ransack main army base after troops flee.</p>
<p>March 9 - Berisha signs agreement with all political parties calling for a unity government and June elections.</p>
<p>March 10 - Representatives from Vlore agree to lay down arms, but unrest continues to spread throughout the south.</p>
<p>March 11 - Bashkim Fino of the opposition Socialist Party appointed as Prime Minister. Violence spreads to the north.</p>
<p>March 12 - Fino says he wants talks with armed rebels as the unrest moves closer to the capital. Following appeals from the West, Fino meets other political parties to discuss forming an interim government to oversee new elections.</p>
<p>March 13 - The government calls for foreign intervention as the United States and European nations evacuate their nationals. Socialist Party head Fatos Nano released from jail.</p>
<p>March 14 - International envoy Franz Vranitzky holds talks with the Albanian government aboard an Italian warship.</p>
<p>March 16 - Berisha pardons Nano.</p>
<p>March 27 - Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) approves international protection force.</p>
<p>April 12 - Albania's King Leka I returns home after 58 years in exile and campaigns for restoration of monarchy. April 15 - International force begins arriving in Albania.</p>
<p>May 16 - President Berisha calls poll for June 29.</p>
<p>May 21 - Prime Minister Fino asks the international community for &quot;intensive&quot; monitoring of the vote.</p>
<p>May 26 - Italy warns continued economic aid to Albania depends on the vote being free and fair.</p>
<p>June 2 - Bomb attacks injure 27 people in Tirana.</p>
<p>June 4 - A grenade is thrown at President Berisha during a campaign rally outside Tirana but can be deactivated.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
