<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694310" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: RUGBY UNION-TEAM SPIRIT SEALED SERIES - LIONS COACH.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-TEAM SPIRIT SEALED SERIES - LIONS COACH.</headline>
<dateline>DURBAN, South Africa 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The unity and team spirit of the 1997 British Lions were instrumental in sealing the historic series triumph over South Africa, coach Ian McGeechan said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a very special group of Lions. From the word go, they've displayed fantastic unity and team spirit and Great Britain and Ireland can be very proud of them,&quot; McGeechan said after his side's 18-15 win in the second test at King's Park.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of points went begging for the Springboks and test rugby is about taking your chances. We took ours 100 percent and we ended up winning.&quot;</p>
<p>McGeechan said he was very pleased with the Lions scrummaging in the face of a furious onslaught by the Springbok pack. &quot;I thought it went very well -- again, it was a very tight unit went it mattered. The Springbok runs off the side of the scrums and mauls were a lot tighter than last week and we had to watch that closely.&quot;</p>
<p>For Lions manager Fran Cotton, the tenacity with which the Lions came back from 15-9 down midway through the second half was awesome. &quot;I don't think anything has been better in my experience and this victory was dug out of sheer character and guts. Brtish rugby can be very proud of all 35 players.&quot;</p>
<p>Lions captain Martin Johnson said his side simply had to hang on after Andre Joubert's try -- South Africa's third -- gave the hosts a significant six-point lead.</p>
<p>&quot;You've got to keep yourself in the game. You might be down 9-15, but just another penalty and you're right back in it. We simply had to hold on to the ball for a passage of play -- or two or three.</p>
<p>&quot;There were still 20 minutes to go when Joubert scored and we knew we had to play for 20 minutes. Jenks' tremendous kicks kept us in the game and Jerry was there at the end. We'll take a win any way we can get it here in South Africa.&quot;</p>
<p>Welsh fullback Neil Jenkins, who maintained a 100 percent kicking record in the match with his five penalties, said the win &quot;was huge&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I've been on the receiving end of a few hidings from the Springboks with Wales -- to come here today and win is a great achievement. I just tried to block out the crowd and get the points required. Luckily for me, the kicks all went over and that was he difference in the end.&quot;</p>
<p>English centre Jeremy Guscott, whose drop goal three minutes from time sealed the series result, will always treasure the memory.</p>
<p>&quot;That was a massive moment and it will be difficult to override. To finish the series with a drop goal brings back memories for me of that man Rob Andrew with his drop goal against Australia in the quarter-finals of the 1995 World Cup in 1995. It's jst great.&quot;</p>
<p>Defeated Springbok captain Gary Teichmann and team coach Carel du Plessis agreed the six missed kicks between Henry Honiball, Percy Montgomery and Andre Joubert had been critical.</p>
<p>&quot;Unfortunately we missed a few kicks and opportunities to score but I'm very proud of the team's efforts, they threw everything into this match,&quot; Teichmann said.</p>
<p>&quot;This was a big improvement on last week at Newlands. We had a few disruptions in the build-up to this test but I think the young guys who came into the side did well.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I admit our goal-kicking cost us the match but that's the way it can go in test rugby. You've got to take your chances, everyone knows that, and it's frustrating it didn't go for us on the day,&quot; du Plessis said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DURBAN, South Africa"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
