<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694382" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: Bosnian Serb president moves to suspend minister.</title>
<headline>Bosnian Serb president moves to suspend minister.</headline>
<byline>Dan De Luce</byline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The president of Bosnia's Serb republic has ordered the suspension of the powerful interior minister, accusing him of taking decisions without her approval, Serb media reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>President Biljana Plavsic, trying to assert her flagging authority over political foes, also declared that recent decisions by Interior Minister Dragan Kijac were illegal, independent Banja Luka television reported.</p>
<p>Kijac, who runs a vast police force in Serb-controlled territory, is allied with Plavsic's political rivals in the government seat of Pale, outside Sarajevo. He has declined to pursue her requests to investigate war profiteering.</p>
<p>Plavsic's order stated that Kijac had displayed contempt for the office of the president and the Serb army commander and had taken decisions without consulting her, the television said.</p>
<p>The order accused Kijac of reshuffling officers in the Banja Luka police &quot;anti-terrorist brigade&quot;, abolishing its department for intelligence and counter-intelligence and sacking a police chief in Mrkonjic Grad without authority from the president, it said.</p>
<p>Plavsic, who issued the order before leaving this weekend on a private visit to Britain, declared that these decisions were invalid and said she had told the Banja Luka brigade commander &quot;not to deploy until further notice.&quot;</p>
<p>Envoys from the United States, Britain, France, Germany and Russia met in Sarajevo to discuss the power struggle. &quot;She has issued an order but we don't know what will come of this,&quot; one Western diplomat, who asked not to be named, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The Serb member of Bosnia's collective presidency, Momcilo Krajisnik, and his ruling party have isolated Plavsic and excluded her from important decisions after she criticised a cooperation pact with Yugoslavia and called for probes into alleged state corruption.</p>
<p>Plavsic was known as a hardline nationalist during the Bosnian war, but Western diplomats now view her as more willing to abide by the Dayton peace agreement and have tried to bolster her position.</p>
<p>Kijac and the rest of the political leadership remain loyal to former Bosnian Serb president Radovan Karadzic, who has been indicted as a war criminal but still wields influence behind-the-scenes in Serb territory.</p>
<p>Plavsic was not invited when leaders of the ruling Serb Democratic Party met at Karadzic's headquarters last week to discuss strategy for local elections this September, Serb officials in Pale said.</p>
<p>Political analysts say Plavsic has no realistic chance of prevailing against the Pale circle but could possibly expose embarassing details of wartime profiteering operations.</p>
<p>The dispute between Plavsic and the rest of the leadership also illustrates a long-running rivalry between the northwest town of Banja Luka and the mountain village of Pale that emerged during the war.</p>
<p>Some Banja Luka residents accuse the Pale leadership of profiting from the war while ignoring the interests of the largest town in Serb territory.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
