<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694353" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: British charity to offer lunch-hour abortion.</title>
<headline>British charity to offer lunch-hour abortion.</headline>
<byline>Lyndsay Griffiths</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Critics call it barbaric, grotesque and horrific but a British charity said on Saturday it would go ahead with plans to offer working women abortions in their lunch break.</p>
<p>The charity Marie Stopes International -- named after an early British champion of birth control -- said it would launch the operation at clinics in London and in Leeds and Manchester to the north next month.</p>
<p>&quot;Women don't lease their bodies from the state or even from the church. They own them themselves and, if under the 1967 Abortion Act, they have an unwanted pregnancy...they have a right to the best service possible,&quot; Dr Tim Black, chief executive of the charity, told BBC radio.</p>
<p>He said the abortions would be offered to women who are less than 12 weeks pregnant as &quot;a new seamless service without medical drama or moral censure&quot;.</p>
<p>Black said three decades had passed since the legalisation of abortion and there was no need to make women suffer unduly or feel guilty for terminating a pregnancy in today's society.</p>
<p>&quot;Why, 30 years later, is there this preoccupation of making women have to climb over fences and do back-flips and censure them, if they want to have an abortion and it conforms to the terms of the 1967 Abortion Act?&quot;</p>
<p>Yet critics say the procedure, carried out under local anaesthetic in three to four minutes, trivialises abortion and offers inadequate support for the women involved.</p>
<p>&quot;We are taking now about making abortion available rather like something you buy over the counter and that means people do not have a chance to consider seriously what they are doing,&quot; said a spokesman for the Catholic Bishops' Conference.</p>
<p>&quot;This would be the ultimate in a fast economy, you have fast food and now you can have a fast abortion,&quot; said Josephine Quintavalle of the anti-abortion group Life. &quot;I don't think a child's life should be disposed of in a lunch hour.&quot;</p>
<p>The new &quot;walk in-walk out&quot; operation will be performed in a treatment chair and patients will be taken to a recovery room for a snack and a drink. Abortions are usually performed under a general anaesthetic with follow-up surveillance in hospital.</p>
<p>Health Minister Tessa Jowell has said she welcomes any medical advance that reduces &quot;the pain and trauma&quot; of abortion but has voiced fears about trivialising a decision that proves agonising for most women.</p>
<p>About 160,000 abortions were carried out last year in Britain, which has largely avoided the divisive and violent debate over a woman's right to choose seen in the United States.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
