<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694325" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-MADDUX SIX-HITS PHILLIES.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-MADDUX SIX-HITS PHILLIES.</headline>
<dateline>ATLANTA 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Greg Maddux came within one out of a shutout and fired a six-hitter as the National League-best Atlanta Braves mowed down the major league-worst Philadelphia Phillies 7-1 Friday.</p>
<p>Maddux (10-3) picked up his third straight win and tossed his third complete game in 17 starts this season. Maddux did not walk a batter and struck out eight. He threw only 89 pitches, including 71 for strikes.</p>
<p>&quot;I was just trying to make the pitches,&quot; said Maddux. &quot;My stuff was pretty good.&quot;</p>
<p>Rico Brogna's double in the ninth, driving in Mickey Morandini, spoiled Maddux's shutout.</p>
<p>Atlanta, which has won three straight and six of its last eight, has taken all five games with Philadelphia this season.</p>
<p>The Braves (50-28) jumped out to a 4-0 lead in the first with Fred McGriff's two-run double the big blow. Atlanta extended the lead to 6-0 in the fifth on a two-run homer by Jeff Blauser. A solo homer by Andruw Jones an inning later completed the Braves' scoring.</p>
<p>Garrett Stephenson (2-4) was reached for six runs and seven hits in five innings. The Phillies (23-53) have lost four straight and 12 of their last 13.</p>
<p>In Los Angeles, Joey Hamilton allowed two runs over seven innings and helped himself at the plate with a solo homer as the San Diego Padres beat the Dodgers 7-5 victory.</p>
<p>Hamilton (5-3) allowed eight hits with a walk and four strikeouts. Trevor Hoffman got the final two outs for his 15th save.</p>
<p>Tony Gwynn added a three-run double for the Padres.</p>
<p>Chan Ho Park (5-5) suffered the loss, going 5 1/3 innings and giving up four runs. He has dropped three of his last four decisions and has yielded at least three runs in each of his last five starts.</p>
<p>Todd Zeile hit a two-run homer and Mike Piazza added a solo shot and a two-run single for Los Angeles, which has dropped three of its last four games.</p>
<p>In Chicago, Kevin Foster and two relievers combined on a seven-hitter as the Cubs snapped a three-game losing streak with a 2-1 victory over the Houston Astros.</p>
<p>Foster (9-5) scattered seven hits and three walks over 6 2/3 innings with five strikeouts. Ramon Tatis recorded the final out of the seventh and Turk Wendell pitched two scoreless innings to notch his fourth save.</p>
<p>The Cubs won for the second time in their last 10 games.</p>
<p>Chicago scored its two runs in the first, the second on a groundout by Sammy Sosa, who signed the richest contract in club history -- a four-year extension believed to be worth more than $48 million.</p>
<p>At Florida, Vladimir Guerrero had a career-high four hits and an RBI and four pitchers combined on a six-hitter as the Montreal Expos blanked the Marlins 2-0.</p>
<p>Dustin Hermanson started for the Expos and lasted only two innings before leaving with a cramp in his left leg. Marc Valdes (3-2) pitched the next three innings, allowing one hit, Dave Veres allowed three hits in the next three innings and Ugueth Urbina worked the ninth for his 14th save.</p>
<p>Kevin Brown (7-5) pitched well but lost.</p>
<p>In Cincinnati, Willie Greene hit his first career grand slam in the bottom of the sixth and three pitchers combined on a five-hitter as the Reds defeated the St Louis Cardinals 5-3 for their third win in four games.</p>
<p>Starter Brett Tomko (4-1) won his fourth straight decision. Jeff Shaw got the last four outs while allowing three hits for his 15th save. Alan Benes (7-7) took the loss.</p>
<p>In Colorado, Kirt Rueter allowed three runs over eight innings and J.T. Snow, Barry Bonds and Jose Vizcaino hit solo home runs as the San Francisco Giants beat the Rockies 6-3.</p>
<p>Rueter (5-2), who won his third straight, allowed six hits with no walks and two strikeouts before tiring in the ninth. Rod Beck got his league-leading 26th save.</p>
<p>John Thomson (2-6) took the loss.</p>
<p>Neifi Perez hit a two-run homer for Colorado, which has dropped four of six.</p>
<p>In Pittsburgh, Jason Schmidt pitched a five-hitter for his first complete game of the season and Kevin Young and Dale Sveum hit two-run homers, powering the Pirates to a 6-1 victory over the New York Mets.</p>
<p>Schmidt (3-4) walked two and recorded a season-high nine strikeouts and his second career complete game.</p>
<p>Pittsburgh beat the Mets for the first time in five games this season.</p>
<p>Dave Mlicki (4-6) took the loss.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATLANTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
