<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694304" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: TENNIS-HINGIS HURRIES ON AS WIMBLEDON RESUMES AT LAST.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-HINGIS HURRIES ON AS WIMBLEDON RESUMES AT LAST.</headline>
<byline>Clare Lovell</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>World number one Martina Hingis briskly dispatched Olga Barabanshchikova 6-2 6-2 on Saturday, hurrying to beat the ever-present threat of more rain at Wimbledon.</p>
<p>The 16-year-old Swiss prodigy scuttled around the court under overcast skies as the rain-ravaged All England championships saw tennis for the first time since Wednesday evening.</p>
<p>&quot;I couldn't believe I was really getting on court&quot; she said. &quot;It was pretty cold at the beginning -- we were both freezing.&quot;</p>
<p>Hingis won the first three games of the first set, largely from the baseline, her fearsome forehand leaving the 17-year-old Belarussian standing.</p>
<p>But Barabanshchikova fought back, attacking the net even though her serve was seldom penetrating and winning a series of points on the volley.</p>
<p>Hingis's haste forced her into several errors and hurried serving meant she managed to put only 58 per cent of her first serves in.</p>
<p>But her timing and speed about the court made up for her mistakes and she displayed her superiority over the 80th-ranked Belarussian by motoring to 4-0 up in the second set before a wobble in concentration conceded her two games.</p>
<p>Hingis's Centre Court second-round match followed a first-round win for Russia's Elena Likhovtseva over Barabanshchikova's compatriot Natasha Zvereva. The pair had waited 64 hours to resume their rain-interrupted match but the Russian needed only 14 minutes to wrap it up 6-2 6-2.</p>
<p>It was only the second time in the championship's history -- the last was 1909 --that rain had washed out two days in succession.</p>
<p>Hingis, the first woman to reach the third round, said she spent her time practising on indoor courts, shopping in the trendy King's Road and watching videos. She was not worried that she might have to play her matches without the normal rest days as organisers try to catch up lost time.</p>
<p>&quot;On grass the points are short. You don't get worn out. It will be like a normal tournament,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Venus Williams's long-awaited Wimbledon debut proved less happy. The towering American teenager had waited since Monday for her first round match, but she went out 4-6 6-2 6-4 to Poland's Magdalena Grzybowska.</p>
<p>Williams, her beaded hair decorated in Wimbledon green and purple colours, proved very powerful but less accurate. She served 11 double faults and netted numerous volleys.</p>
<p>Grzybowska, aged 18 and ranked 91 in the world to Williams's 59, matched the tall American for power, beat her at the net and played an intelligent grasscourt game.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm not too disappointed. It is only my first Wimbledon. There will be many more to come,&quot; Williams said.</p>
<p>&quot;She's a better player than her ranking and I think she played pretty good.&quot;</p>
<p>Williams, 17 last week, is now going back home to California and school.</p>
<p>The first man to reach the third round was Cedric Pioline of France who earned a walkover against Javier Frana. The Argentine pulled out with an ear problem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
