<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694347" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Reuters historical calendar - July 5.</title>
<headline>Reuters historical calendar - July 5.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Following are some of the major events to have occurred on July 5 in history:</p>
<p>1791 - George Hammond was appointed as Britain's first ambassador to the United States.</p>
<p>1810 - P.T. Barnum, U.S. showman, born; together with James Bailey, he founded the Barnum and Bailey Circus.</p>
<p>1811 - Venezuela declared independence from Spain.</p>
<p>1826 - Sir Thomas Stamford Raffles, British East Indian administrator and founder of Singapore in 1819, died.</p>
<p>1830 - France began an invasion of Algeria and took Algiers.</p>
<p>1853 - Cecil Rhodes, British colonial administrator in whose honour Rhodesia was named, born.</p>
<p>1865 - William Booth founded the Christian Mission, later renamed the Salvation Army, in London.</p>
<p>1865 - The world's first speed limit, of two miles perhour, was imposed in Britain under the Locomotives and Highways Act.</p>
<p>1872 - Edouard Herriot, French statesman, radical socialist and prime minister, born. Imprisoned by the Germans in 1942, he was not released until Russian troops entered Berlin in 1945.</p>
<p>1879 - Dwight Davis, U.S. tennis player and politician, born; he founded the Davis Cup tennis competition and served under President Coolidge as secretary of war (1925-29).</p>
<p>1889 - Jean Cocteau, a major figure in French culture, born. A poet, film director, novelist and artist, he made the films &quot;Orpheus&quot; and &quot;Beauty and the Beast&quot;</p>
<p>1911 - Georges Pompidou, French statesman, prime minister and president of France (1969-74), born.</p>
<p>1932 - Antonio de Oliveira Salazar became premier of Portugal and drafted a new constitution that established the country as an authoritarian state.</p>
<p>1945 - U.S. General MacArthur announced the liberation of the whole of the Philippines.</p>
<p>1945 - John Curtin, prime minister of Australia during most of World War Two, died.</p>
<p>1948 - The National Health Service came into being in Britain.</p>
<p>1959 - Indonesian President Sukarno dissolved parliament and assumed dictatorial powers for himself.</p>
<p>1965 - Maria Callas gave her last stage performance, singing Tosca at London's Covent Garden.</p>
<p>1969 - The Rolling Stones gave a free concert in Hyde Park, London, in memory of Brian Jones, who had died two days before.</p>
<p>1969 - Thomas Mboya, Kenyan statesman, assassinated.</p>
<p>1975 - American Arthur Ashe beat countryman Jimmy Connors to become the first black tennis player to win the Wimbledon men's singles title.</p>
<p>1975 - Independence from Portugal was granted to the Republic of Cape Verde, with Aristides Pereira becoming the country's first president.</p>
<p>1977 - In Pakistan, General Mohammad Zia-ul-Haq overthrew the government of Zulfikar Ali Bhutto in a bloodless coup.</p>
<p>1980 - Bjorn Borg of Sweden won the Wimbledon men's singles title for the fifth consecutive year.</p>
<p>1989 - Former White House aide Oliver North was fined 150,000 dollars for his role in the Iran-Contra scandal that rocked the Reagan administration.</p>
<p>1991 - The Bank of England said the operations of Bank of Credit and Commerce International SA (BCCI) had been suspended immediately following allegations of massive fraud.</p>
<p>1994 - Yasser Arafat travelled to the West Bank after 27 years in exile, determined to turn the self-rule areas of Gaza and Jericho into a Palestinian state with its capital in East Jerusalem.</p>
<p>1994 - In Italy, a graft trial opened with two former prime ministers heading a list of accused reading like a &quot;who's who&quot; of the country's fallen mighty.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
