<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694333" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: GOLF-GOOSEN BENEFITS FROM MONTY'S DOUBLE.</title>
<headline>GOLF-GOOSEN BENEFITS FROM MONTY'S DOUBLE.</headline>
<byline>Norman Dabell</byline>
<dateline>PARIS, France 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A late mistake by Scotland's U.S. Open runner-up Colin Montgomerie hurt his attempt to overhaul Retief Goosen in the second round of the French Open at the National club on Saturday.</p>
<p>Montgomerie, looking for back-to-back victories on the European Tour to sustain his bid for a record fifth successive Order of Merit title, double-bogeyed the short eighth hole, his 17th, to drop from three behind to five back of the South African leader,</p>
<p>Goosen leads by four shots from Englishman Martin Gates and Marc Farry of France with Montgomerie in a large group another shot behind.</p>
<p>With the second round completed after two days of interruptions, organisers have decided to try and play the third and final rounds Sunday.</p>
<p>Goosen picked up one shot in the four holes he had left in his second round on Saturday morning for a five-under-par 67 and a target total of 131 before Montgomerie began his round seven strokes behind.</p>
<p>Gates, also with a 67, was Goosen's nearest challenger in the morning as he moved to 135. But Montgomerie got to work quickly by picking up three shots in his first nine holes to trail Goosen by only four.</p>
<p>That included a fine birdie at his ninth, the long 18th, where he hit through the green onto a bridge from where he pitched from the planks over the edge of the lake to eight feet and holed the putt.</p>
<p>By the short eighth he was only three behind Goosen. But then he overhit into spectators before playing a near 'air-shot' right under his ball in the hay and double-bogeying for a round of 70, five behind Goosen and one back of Gates and Farry, who carded 68 in the afternoon.</p>
<p>&quot;My ball just took off out of the blue on the eighth,&quot; said Montgomerie. &quot;It should never have gone as far as it did and then it kicked forward violently up the hill.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the first ball I've had go forward all week in the wet conditions and then I went right underneath my ball. It's very disappointing because I should have been no worse than three behind.&quot;</p>
<p>Goosen, 28, was pleased to collect one more birdie on Saturday. &quot;It was important because I wanted to build as bigger lead as I could,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm pleased I've been able to concentrate because it's been a very messy week. I've got up at 0600 every day staying here at the course, gone back to my room and had room service, hardly leaving my room except to play golf.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
