<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694388" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian Gazprom says nonpayments mean tough future.</title>
<headline>Russian Gazprom says nonpayments mean tough future.</headline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's natural gas monopoly Gazprom said on Saturday it had cleared out its debts to the state but cautioned a struggle against nonpayments was far from over and serious problems could lie ahead.</p>
<p>Gazprom Chief Executive Officer Rem Vyakhirev said the world's largest gas company was implementing a major cost-cutting scheme to deal with the fact only half its domestic customers pay for supplies, and only a fraction in cash.</p>
<p>&quot;Behind many indisputable successes, it has become clear we are observing the ripening of problems which are extremely dangerous to our company's future,&quot; he said in a written statement, citing chronic nonpayments by customers for gas.</p>
<p>&quot;We must complete our structural overhaul without delay. While doing this, we will act according to one extremely important condition -- the strictest cost-cutting all around.&quot;</p>
<p>Gazprom's biggest debtor is Russia's national electricity monopoly, Unified Energy System (UES), with which it is working to improve collections.</p>
<p>But Vyakhirev said nonpayments were affecting Gazprom's ability to finance investment in drilling and pipeline projects. He added the company spent one third less than planned, or 40 trillion roubles ($7 billion), on capital expenditure in 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;These alarming signals have led us to a conclusion -- if we do not today undertake a search for internal reserves (financial), Gazprom may be in a very tough position tomorrow,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Gazprom, he said, had no idea of what its real production and transport costs were, but a long-awaited audit according to international standards would be completed by July.</p>
<p>Russia's arguably most powerful company is shedding non-core jobs and rationalising costs as part of an internal restructuring programme to become leaner and more efficient. A company statement said the changes would concern its work with joint ventures but gave no details.</p>
<p>Vyakhirev said the company's success on foreign capital and debt markets, where it has secured several billion dollar loans and plans to issue Eurobonds and convertible bonds, meant it could resolve its problems.</p>
<p>Gazprom, whose American Depositary Receipts are traded in London, paid off the last $608 million of its approximately $2.5 billion in tax arrears this month. The government used the cash to pay off pension arrears.</p>
<p>Gazprom had net profit of 33.22 trillion roubles ($5.7 billion) for 1996. It produced nearly 565 billion cubic metres of gas last year, over one quarter of global output, and exported 20 percent of output to Europe.</p>
<p>--Lynnley Browning, Moscow Newsroom, +7095 941 8520</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
