<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694377" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Despite snags, Albania poll plans almost complete.</title>
<headline>Despite snags, Albania poll plans almost complete.</headline>
<byline>Steve Pagani</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanians prepared to vote on Sunday in an early general election intended to heal months of internal unrest, but organisers acknowledged logistical problems in parts of the troubled Balkan state.</p>
<p>The contest itself pits the right-leaning Democrats of President Sali Berisha with the main opposition Socialists and a myriad of other political parties.</p>
<p>The Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE), which is helping Albanian authorities carry out the polling, said all 500 international observers had reached their destinations around Albania without any threat from gunmen who roam the countryside.</p>
<p>But some ballot papers had yet to arrive at outlying polling stations, posing the threat of a number of delays in a 7 a.m. (0500 GMT) start to voting. Some remote stations with a just a handful of voters may not open at all if ballots are not delivered.</p>
<p>&quot;There is still a lot of frenetic activity. The electoral commissions are under a lot of pressure...but we still hope that come tomorrow morning everything will be in place,&quot; OSCE election coordinator Tony Welch told a news conference.</p>
<p>The OSCE and other international bodies have already indicated that they do not expect the polling process to be perfect and may not meet all the requirements of a free and fair election.</p>
<p>Signalling that some flaws are to be expected, the international community has in a sense already created a let-out clause which they hope will be enough to satisfy Albania's bitter political rivals and restore some confidence among the population of 3.4 million.</p>
<p>The deputy chairman of the Central Electoral Commission Fatos Klosi appealed to political parties to ensure that all members of local commissions were able to validate the vote after some Democrats had complained they had received threats.</p>
<p>The election is being held just 13 months after Albania's last general election, the third multi-party poll since the collapse of communism in 1990.</p>
<p>Berisha gave in to pressure for the election in March after a government of his ruling Democrats gave way to a 10-party unity coalition set up to try to quell a wave of violence, looting and general mayhem.</p>
<p>Much of the south of country remains out of government control and in the sway of gangs, criminal cliques or, at best, under the control of citizens committees which have attempted to restore some semblance of order to their towns.</p>
<p>An uneasy calm descended on the country which may have more to do with the sweltering heat rather than fear of the outcome of Sunday's first round poll. In the Adriatic port of Vlore, where the March rebellion originated, townsfolk were out in the streets in the morning to buy weekend provisions, but remained indoors for much of the rest of the day.</p>
<p>At least 1,500 people have been killed in four months of unrest after hundreds of thousands of Albanians lost their life savings when five pyramid investment funds collapsed.</p>
<p>In Tirana, Lieutenant-Colonel Giovanni Bernardi of the 10-nation protection force deployed in Albania in April said on Saturday he hoped election day would be as calm as the past 48 hours.</p>
<p>He said the multinational force would escort and protect the observers from 22 countries as they carry out their duties in monitoring voting at almost half the 4,525 polling stations. Aerial surveillance would also be provided and immediate assistance can be requested through two communications networks set up through the protection force and OSCE headquarters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
