<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694368" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CENTRAL AFRICAN REPUBLIC: Malian mediator negotiates Bangui truce.</title>
<headline>Malian mediator negotiates Bangui truce.</headline>
<dateline>BANGUI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malian mediator Amadou Toumani Toure brokered a truce in the Central African Republic capital on Saturday to consolidate a lull in a week of clashes between African peacekeepers and army dissidents, officials said.</p>
<p>Toumani Toure, who brokered a January peace deal to end three army mutinies in under a year, had proposed a four-day ceasefire to enable families to bury their dead and disaffected soldiers to hand in mortars and other heavy weapons.</p>
<p>Medical workers say that the clashes have killed about 100 people, many of them civilians caught in cross fire. The fighting also triggered an exodus of more than 60,000 civilians for the relative safety of the surrounding countryside.</p>
<p>Mutinies in April and May 1996 began as pay protests but evolved into a bid to topple President Ange-Felix Patasse, a civilian from the north, elected in 1993. A third mutiny began in November and degenerated into ethnic bloodshed.</p>
<p>Most of the mutineers are members of the Yakoma tribe of former military leader Andre Kolingba.</p>
<p>Former colonial power France, which has troops in the country under a defence pact, intervened in support of the peacekeepers and one of its helicopters hit mortar batteries manned by dissident soldiers after its embassy came under fire.</p>
<p>Burkina Faso, Chad, Gabon, Mali, Senegal and Togo have troops in the 800-strong force. Patasse opponents criticise the Chadians, saying Patasse hired Chadians in a private militia.</p>
<p>Toumani Toure is Mali's widely respected former military leader.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGUI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CENTRAL AFRICAN REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
