<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694380" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Albanian election may bring peace or more mayhem.</title>
<headline>Albanian election may bring peace or more mayhem.</headline>
<byline>Steve Pagani</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1996-06-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanians vote in a make-or-break general election on Sunday under a state of emergency imposed to halt civil violence threatening to tear their country apart and destabilise the already volatile Balkan region even further.</p>
<p>European nations and the United States, which have sent hundreds of observers to monitor the poll, hope the election will restore political stability after more than 1,500 people were killed in months of disorder.</p>
<p>But the European envoy to Albania, Franz Vranitzky, has said the election is being held in unusual circumstances and will not be perfect.</p>
<p>The poll pits the right-leaning Democratic Party of Sali Berisha, president since 1992, against the main opposition Socialists and a myriad of other political groups. Both major parties have confidently predicted victory.</p>
<p>&quot;With our votes, we shall be laying a secure foundation for our future,&quot; Kristq Kume, chairman of the Central Election Commission, said in a televised appeal. &quot;Let us go to the ballot box calmly and as early as possible.&quot;</p>
<p>Most of Albania's 4,525 polling stations were due to open at 7 a.m. (0500 GMT) and close at 6 p.m. (1600 GMT), three hours earlier than previously planned because safety fears for voters and observers.</p>
<p>A 7,000-strong multinational protection force, sent into Albania in April to try to restore some calm, will escort and protect observers at polling stations and official counts.</p>
<p>A total of 1,112 candidates were standing for the 155-member parliament in which 115 seats are allocated in first-past-the-post races and the rest on a proportional basis. A runoff poll will be held on July 6 for the two top candidates in constituencies where no one wins 50 percent.</p>
<p>First results should begin trickling into Central Electoral Commission headquarters in Tirana late on Sunday but overall unofficial results were not expected until Tuesday.</p>
<p>The election, the third multi-party poll since one of Eastern Europe's harshest communist regimes collapsed in 1990, is being held only 13 months after Albania's last general election.</p>
<p>The Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE), which described the 1996 poll as seriously flawed, has sent officials to try to help authorities to ensure a fair election.</p>
<p>Last year's election laid the seeds of unrest after opposition parties, including the Socialists, accused the Democratic Party of rigging the vote and declared a boycott half way through polling day.</p>
<p>The Democrats won 122 of the 140 parliamentary seats then at stake but the OSCE endorsed most opposition accusations of voter intimidation, ballot stuffing and tampering.</p>
<p>Disgruntlement turned to protest and then to violence after thousands of people were left destitute when they lost their life savings early this year in the collapse of five dubiuos pyramid investment schemes.</p>
<p>The south of the country, where the schemes were most popular, descended into anarchy as looters ransacked deserted army and police depots for weapons and ammunition.</p>
<p>The government has yet to re-establish itself in much of the south, which is now controlled by gangs or, at best, &quot;Citizens' Committees&quot; which have attempted to restore some semblance of order.</p>
<p>In Sarande, Albania's southernmost Adriatic port, an anti-tank rocket was fired into the harbour late on Saturday.</p>
<p>Greek officials said about 10,000 of the country's 300,000 resident Albanian immigrants had crossed into Albania to vote but others were too afraid of crime to return.</p>
<p>Many Albanians blame Berisha for the turmoil and want him to step down. If the Democrats form the next government, he will remain but sources close to the president have said he will resign if the left wins power.</p>
<p>Voters were also being asked in a referendum whether they favoured restoring the monarchy. But few people believe exiled king Leka, who has toured the country extensively, has much chance of returning to the throne.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
