<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694319" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOLIVIA: SOCCER-BRAZIL BID FOR HISTORIC COPA WIN AT HIGH ALTITUDE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-BRAZIL BID FOR HISTORIC COPA WIN AT HIGH ALTITUDE.</headline>
<byline>Brian Homewood</byline>
<dateline>LA PAZ 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil will attempt to win the Copa America on foreign soil for the first time on Sunday when they face hosts Bolivia in the final at 3,600 metres above sea level.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, given their superiority over most other South American teams, the Brazilians have won the prestigious title just four times and all have been at home, the last in 1989.</p>
<p>Overcoming the physical difficulties of playing at high altitude in La Paz will not be easy for the Brazilians. They may face the game without striker Romario, who is nursing a thigh injury.</p>
<p>But coach Mario Zagallo tried to play down the worries following his team's 7-0 demolition of Peru in Thursday's semifinal.</p>
<p>&quot;Our opponents on Sunday will be Bolivia, not the altitude,&quot; he said. &quot;The altitude is there, it always has been.&quot;</p>
<p>He went on to refer to his own playing days.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1964, I went there with Botafogo. I played 90 minutes. You notice a bit of a difference but you can play perfectly well,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We knew from the start that if we reached the final and the final was against Bolivia, we would have to go there. I'm not here to complain.&quot;</p>
<p>The history of Brazil-Bolivia encounters can be divided into two sections -- matches played at sea level and matches played higher up.</p>
<p>Bolivia have never recorded a win in the former category and have suffered some severe thrashings, conceding eight goals on two occasions.</p>
<p>Matches in La Paz have been much closer, although Brazil still won there in a World Cup qualifier in 1981, prevailing 2-1.</p>
<p>Brazil's problems may be partly psychological since they suffered their first and only defeat in a World Cup qualifier on their last visit to La Paz four years ago.</p>
<p>Bolivia's only previous Copa America title was in 1963, the only other time that they have staged the competition. They beat Brazil 4-3 on the way.</p>
<p>A Bolivia-Brazil final has seemed on the cards since the tournament started, not only because of the form of both teams.</p>
<p>The two countries have enjoyed certain privileges. Bolivia have been allowed to play all their home games in their high-altitude fortress against opponents who have never had more than 72 hours to adapt to the conditions.</p>
<p>This contradicts the policy of world soccer's governing body FIFA, which allows visiting teams 10 days to acclimatize before World Cup qualifiers in the city.</p>
<p>While Bolivia have won all their games in the Copa, they have won only three out of seven World Cup qualifiers in La Paz and have drawn four.</p>
<p>During the first round, the Copa America organisers even announced a change to the rules which would have allowed Bolivia to continue playing in La Paz if they finished second in their first-round group rather than first, as had been expected.</p>
<p>This prompted Argentina, who would have been Bolivia's quarter-final opponents if they had finished second, to threaten a walk-out. This was averted when Bolivia won their group.</p>
<p>Brazil, meanwhile, have played all their games in the eastern city of Santa Cruz, which is almost at sea level.</p>
<p>Brazilian striker Romario, who has scored three goals, may have to miss the final after limping off with a pulled hamstring on Thursday.</p>
<p>Zagallo announced that if Romario could not play, Vasco da Gama striker Edmundo would take his place. Otherwise, no changes are likely to the team which demolished Peru.</p>
<p>The world champions have changed their style of playing during the competition and the defence, which looked wobbly in their first two games, has not conceded a goal for 3-1/2 matches.</p>
<p>Their attack has looked lethal throughout, scoring 18 times in five games.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LA PAZ"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOLIVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
