<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694391" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Mir crew to start training soon for risky repairs.</title>
<headline>Mir crew to start training soon for risky repairs.</headline>
<byline>Viktor Anoshkin</byline>
<dateline>KOROLYOV, Russia 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The situation on the damaged space station Mir was &quot;completely&quot; under control on Saturday and the crew were told they would start training soon for difficult repair work, a Russian official said.</p>
<p>The American and two Russians on Mir, which collided with a cargo craft on Wednesday, were due to check how the station's batteries were charging and try to increase their oxygen supply before beginning their practice exercises.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation on Mir is completely under the control of mission control and the crew,&quot; said Vladimir Solovyov, who is responsible for flight coordination at Korolyov mission control near Moscow.</p>
<p>He told reporters that 30 to 40 percent of Mir's electric power potential had been lost in the collision and added: &quot;We plan that the crew will begin the training (to restore the power supply) on Monday.&quot;</p>
<p>Commander Vasily Tsibliyev, 43, flight engineer Alexander Lazutkin, 39, and American physicist Michael Foale, 40, enjoyed a good night's sleep and were relaxing on Saturday morning.</p>
<p>&quot;We are well but I did not sleep for two nights after the collision. The first time I had a good night's sleep was last night,&quot; Tsibliyev told mission control during a radio conversation which reporters were able to listen to.</p>
<p>But he had some doubts about the risky repairs that lie ahead after the worst accident of Mir's 11 years in space.</p>
<p>&quot;I have never done this kind of work. Without training, it will not be possible to do this job,&quot; Tsibliyev said.</p>
<p>Solovyov said: &quot;We will help you do all the jobs&quot;.</p>
<p>The two Russians will don spacesuits to enter the Spektr scientific module, holed by a cargo craft during docking manoeuvres, while Foale sits in the escape capsule for safety.</p>
<p>They will have to install a modified hatch in Spektr's doorway so that cables can be connected to tap electricity from the module's solar arrays.</p>
<p>According to NASA officials, if the hatch to Spektr cannot be resealed, the crew will have to abandon ship.</p>
<p>Solovyov said a cargo craft would be launched on July 5 to take equipment to Mir. He expected the repairs to be done between July 10 and 14.</p>
<p>One piece of good news for Foale was that his wife was being allowed to send him a small package with personal effects, photos and toiletries.</p>
<p>He lost his toothbrush in the collision but another one had already been found for him in Mir's supplies, Solovyov said.</p>
<p>Mission control told the crew on Friday to relax and rest, but also set them some chores for Saturday and Sunday to try to improve the environment on Mir.</p>
<p>These included checking Mir's batteries are charging -- Wednesday's collision robbed it of its most efficient batteries -- and turning on equipment that produces oxygen automatically. They also hoped to reduce humidity on Mir.</p>
<p>Additional systems are being activated as Mir's batteries charge, including the station's toilet.</p>
<p>&quot;As Mike (Foale) said, that was a great relief,&quot; Frank Culbertson, who oversees NASA's missions to Mir, told reporters at Cape Canaveral in Florida.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KOROLYOV, Russia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
