<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694326" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-JAYS EDGE ORIOLES AS ALOMAR BLUNDERS ON BASEPATH.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-JAYS EDGE ORIOLES AS ALOMAR BLUNDERS ON BASEPATH.</headline>
<dateline>BALTIMORE 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ed Sprague and Orlando Merced each knocked in their 33rd runs of the season as the Toronto Blue Jays edged the Baltimore Orioles 2-1, thanks in part to a ninth-inning baserunning blunder by Roberto Alomar.</p>
<p>Toronto starter Robert Person (3-5) allowed one run over 7 2/3 innings. He retired the first 12 batters of the game before Cal Ripken singled leading off the fifth. Person gave up three hits, struck out three and walked one, winning for the third time in four starts.</p>
<p>In the ninth, with one out, Alomar and Ripken singled to put men on first and second. B.J. Surhoff flied out to right and Alomar tried to take third but Orlando Merced threw him out easily, ending the game.</p>
<p>&quot;I was surprised Robbie took off, but I was playing deep and was throwing to third base regardless,&quot; Merced said. &quot;No, I didn't have time to think about whether he might run or not. Just catch the ball, get set and throw it. Throwing a guy out always makes you feel good.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I think the big play, the last play, I should have stayed at second base,&quot; Alomar said. &quot;It was a mistake of mine of making the third out at third base knowing that Orlando Merced has a good arm. But that's part of baseball. I think I'll learn from the mistake and I learned something today.&quot;</p>
<p>Scott Kamieniecki (6-4) had his two-game winning streak snapped, allowing both runs and five hits over seven innings.</p>
<p>At Minnesota, Albert Belle went 5-for-5 with two RBI and four runs scored and Jorge Fabregas had three hits and four RBI as the Chicago White Sox won their seventh straight, 10-6 over the Twins.</p>
<p>Belle, 11-for-22 in his last five games, had three singles, a double and a solo homer for his first career five-hit game. Fabregas tied career highs in hits and RBI, helping Chicago climb within one game of first-place Cleveland in the American League Central.</p>
<p>Belle, who raised his average from .283 to .295, has 55 RBI in his last 56 games.</p>
<p>Ron Coomer hit two homers for the Twins, who have lost five of their last six.</p>
<p>In Seattle, Alex Rodriguez returned to the lineup and hit a two-run homer in his first at-bat and Jeff Fassero allowed one run over seven innings to lead the Mariners to their eighth win in nine games, 8-1 over the Anaheim Angels.</p>
<p>Rodriguez, activated from the 15-day disabled list before the game, extended his hitting streak to 10 games. The 21-year-old shortstop missed 14 games after bruising his chest on June 11.</p>
<p>Fassero (8-3) won for the fourth time in his last five decisions. Scott Sanders pitched two hitless innings.</p>
<p>Chuck Finley (3-6) took the loss.</p>
<p>The Mariners moved 5 1/2 games ahead of Anaheim atop the A.L. West for the largest lead in franchise history.</p>
<p>In Oakland, Rafael Bournigal went 3-for-3 and Matt Stairs and Jose Canseco drove in two runs apiece as the Athletics beat the Texas Rangers 7-4 for their third win in four games.</p>
<p>Bournigal posted his fourth straight multi-hit game, has 12 hits in his last 15 at-bats and is batting .640 (16-for-25) during a seven-game hitting streak.</p>
<p>Ivan Rodriguez had four hits, including his 10th homer, and two RBI for the Rangers, who have lost nine of their last 10 games and fell eight games behind Seattle.</p>
<p>In Kansas City, Jay Bell hit a grand slam and Craig Paquette also drove in five runs as the Royals bombed the Milwaukee Brewers 16-3.</p>
<p>Paquette homered twice as the Royals racked up 15 hits and a season high in runs.</p>
<p>Kevin Appier (6-5) allowed an unearned run in six innings as Kansas City won its fifth in six games.</p>
<p>Ben McDonald (6-5) was rocked for a career-high nine earned runs and eight hits over three-plus innings.</p>
<p>In New York, Dwight Gooden allowed one run in seven innings and Paul O'Neill had a two-run double in a three-run first as the Yankees won their fourth straight, 3-2 over the Cleveland Indians.</p>
<p>Gooden (3-0) scattered five hits without a walk and struck out four. He is 4-0 in as many starts against the Tribe.</p>
<p>Mariano Rivera surrendered Jim Thome's 22nd homer in the ninth but struck out two to notch his 26th save and became the third Yankee to save four straight games, joining John Wetteland (1996) and Sparky Lyle (1973).</p>
<p>In Boston, Tony Clark doubled home Travis Fryman with one out in the top of the 11th as the Detroit Tigers edged the Red Sox 2-1 to escape the A.L. East cellar.</p>
<p>Clark, 15-for-37 (.405) since breaking out of a slump, drove in both Detroit runs.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BALTIMORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
