<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694334" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: GOLF-RICHARDSON ENDS NIGHTMARE SPELL.</title>
<headline>GOLF-RICHARDSON ENDS NIGHTMARE SPELL.</headline>
<byline>Norman Dabell</byline>
<dateline>PARIS, France 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former Ryder Cup player Steven Richardson of England ended a nightmare run of missed cuts on the European Tour on Saturday by qualifying for the final two rounds of the French Open.</p>
<p>After 15 successive failures from the start of this year, Richardson ended the agony by posting a second round four-under-par 68 to total two-under-par 142, one better than the cutoff, after play restarted following rain stoppages on the first two days.</p>
<p>Richardson, who celebrated his 31st birthday four days ago, was hailed as Britain's bright young hope when he won twice in 1991 and earned his Ryder Cup place at Kiawah Island that year against America.</p>
<p>But after following up with a 1993 success in the German Masters his tour career has gone into serious decline.</p>
<p>He finished 112th with 19 missed cuts in 30 events on the 1996 European Tour when his best result, ironically was when he tied for fourth on this same National course.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a great relief to make a birdie on my last hole because I thought I needed that to get in,&quot; said Richardson.</p>
<p>&quot;But it was a struggle when we finished off the round because I didn't play well at all, nerves from knowing how close I was to making it at last, I suppose.</p>
<p>&quot;In the end I made it on heart more than technique.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
