<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694372" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>UGANDA: Uganda ready to swap Sudanese prisoners for girls.</title>
<headline>Uganda ready to swap Sudanese prisoners for girls.</headline>
<dateline>KAMPALA 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Uganda says it will free 114 Sudanese prisoners if Khartoum pressed Ugandan rebels to release 35 girls abducted from their school last October.</p>
<p>&quot;No schoolgirls, No prisoners,&quot; President Yoweri Museveni told a news conference in the Ugandan capital Kampala late on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;The Sudanese government has been playing tricks on Uganda and this answers those who believe we can engage in dialogue with Sudan,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The girls were part of a group of 150 people abducted in October last year by rebels of the northern Uganda-based Lord's Resistance Army (LRA) led by Joseph Kony.</p>
<p>Uganda sent its head of external intelligence and the headmistress of the school to Khartoum last week to negotiate for the girls' freedom. The two returned to Kampala on Wednesday empty-handed.</p>
<p>It was not known when the 114 Sudanese were captured. Uganda's army says the Sudanese were captured while fighting alongside Ugandan rebels.</p>
<p>Uganda and Sudan accuse each other of supporting rebel groups fighting their governments. Both deny the allegations.</p>
<p>Museveni said Sudan's President Hassan Omar al-Bashir raised the question of the Sudanese prisoners and resumption of diplomatic relations at recent summits in Kenya and Zimbabwe. He said he set the return of the girls as a condition for both and would not negotiate any further on the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;Uganda has done all that is possible to secure the release of the girls, including calling upon the international community to put pressure on Sudan. All has failed and the only hope lies in exchanging the soldiers with the girls,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Museveni also said the temporary capture of the southwestern Ugandan town of Bundibugyo by rebels was caused by poor military planning and leadership. He said the army knew of the impending attack but had deployed troops in the wrong places.</p>
<p>Bundibugyo, a remote town at the foot of the Ruwenzori mountains, was cut off from the rest of the east African country for more than 10 days by the rebels, aid officials said.</p>
<p>The rebels of the Moslem-based Allied Democratic Forces (ADF) attacked the usually sleepy town from the neighbouring Democratic Republic of the Congo and sporadic fighting with government troops has displaced more than 30,000 people, according to aid and local government officials.</p>
<p>Museveni suggested the rebels were from the Moslem group Tabliqs, which he says receives direct support from Sudan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UGANDA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KAMPALA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UGANDA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
