<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694396" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: UN assisted in capture of war crimes suspect.</title>
<headline>UN assisted in capture of war crimes suspect.</headline>
<byline>Zoran Radosavljevic</byline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.N. peacekeepers helped the International War Crimes Tribunal in former Yuoslavia (ICTY) capture a war crimes suspect for the first time, a U.N. official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>ICTY officials arrested Slavko Dokmanovic in Croatia's Eastern Slavonia region on Friday. The predominantly Serb region, monitored by a provisional U.N. Administration (UNTAES), is due to revert to Croatian rule soon.</p>
<p>&quot;We gave support to the ICTY officials on the ground within instructions from a U.N. resolution that says the UNTAES shall cooperate with the Tribunal,&quot; a U.N. official in the enclave told Reuters. &quot;It's the first time that has happened&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;But (the ICTY) did the actual arrest,&quot; the official who asked to remain anonymous said, refusing to elaborate on the kind of support some of the 5,000 UNTAES soldiers provided.</p>
<p>The Tribunal, established in May 1993 has indicted 75 suspects, mostly Serbs, but holds only nine in custody. The two main indictees at liberty are are former Bosnian Serb leader Radovan Karadzic and his military commander Ratko Mladic.</p>
<p>Both are at large somewhere in Bosnia, which is patrolled by thousands of NATO troops with no powers of arrest.</p>
<p>Dokmanovic was immediately transferred to the Netherlands.</p>
<p>He was president of Vukovar municipality, the largest in Eastern Slavonia, in November 1991, when the JNA (Yugoslavia People's Army) and Serb paramilitaries allegedly abducted and killed around 260 men from Vukovar hospital after a brutal three-month siege of the city.</p>
<p>The official sad Dokmanovic had left the area some six months ago and settled in Serbia's northern province of Vojvodina, across the Danube river.</p>
<p>&quot;We gather he has been in and out of the area, but he owned some property here (in Eastern Slavonia),&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Dokmanovic was indicted on March 26 last year in an unpublished amendment to the so-called &quot;Vukovar indictment&quot; earlier issued against three Yugoslav People's Army (JNA) officers for their involvement in the alleged massacre.</p>
<p>The three officers are now believed to be living in Yugoslavia, which has so far made no move to hand them over to the Tribunal.</p>
<p>Details of the charges against Dokmanovic had not been made public at the time in order to facilitate his arrest. &quot;It was a so-called sealed indictment,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>&quot;It sends a signal that international community cares that individuals who committed crimes against humanity are brought to justice,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
