<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694437" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: U.N. official calls for more food aid to N.Korea.</title>
<headline>U.N. official calls for more food aid to N.Korea.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A top United Nations official said on Saturday that North Korea's food crisis was serious and called for more international food aid.</p>
<p>&quot;I was able to assess the extent of the food crisis in the North as very serious and prevailing,&quot; U.N. Undersecretary General Yasushi Akashi told a press conference.</p>
<p>Akashi paid a four-day visit to North Korea, which has been hit by famine following poor harvests due to massive flooding in 1995 and 1996.</p>
<p>Although foreign had helped alleviate the crisis,  North Korea still had a shortage of between 700,000 and 800,000 tonnes of food, Akashi said.</p>
<p>He dismissed arguments that Pyongyang was relying on outside food aid and making no efforts of its own to tackle the crisis, saying: &quot;I have the distinct impression that they are making their own efforts, they are very proud people.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;They were trying to be self-reliant, but they cannot,&quot; he said, adding that a shortage of fertilisers and insecticides was hampering their efforts.</p>
<p>The UN aims to collect $126 million worth of food aid during the year to March 1998, and around 40 percent of the target had already been reached, Akashi said.</p>
<p>The United States has pledged $25 million and South Korea $16 million in response to the UN's appeal for aid.</p>
<p>On Friday, North Korea's official Korean Central News Agency quoted Akashi as saying 60 to 65 percent of children in flood-hit areas were suffering from malnutrition.</p>
<p>Akashi was the first high-ranking U.N. official to visit North Korea to investigate the food crisis since mid-March, when a mission was sent by the World Food Programme.</p>
<p>He is scheduled to meet South Korea government officials in Seoul before travelling to Tokyo on Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
