<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694412" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Historic crowds &quot;Say No to China&quot; at Taiwan rally.</title>
<headline>Historic crowds &quot;Say No to China&quot; at Taiwan rally.</headline>
<byline>Lawrence Chung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Tens of thousands of Taiwanese braved Saturday downpours to join massive &quot;Say No to China&quot; rallies, demanding their island not be swallowed up like Hong Kong but granted a U.N. seat as a new Republic of Taiwan.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan is Taiwan, China is China!&quot; protesters chanted in the rain in an afternoon march on the presidential office and at a far bigger evening rally outside Taipei City Hall.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan independence!&quot; they shouted. &quot;Say no to China!&quot;</p>
<p>A festive throng estimated by police at well over 70,000 -- one of the biggest in Taiwan history -- packed a downtown square to denounce communist China's longtime claim to their island and assail the 1984 Sino-British pact by which Hong Kong, without popular consent, will be handed to Beijing on July 1.</p>
<p>&quot;We do not oppose China, but if they want to swallow us up, that's different,&quot; said retiree Hwu Han-Min, 70, who lamented what he regarded a light turnout. &quot;There should be 500,000.&quot;</p>
<p>Organisers spoke of a defining moment for Taiwan democracy.</p>
<p>&quot;In this important moment we must tell the world that Taiwan is not Hong Kong, that Taiwan is not part of China,&quot; said Peng Min-ming, a Democratic Progressive Party leader who lost to Nationalist Lee Teng-hui in the 1996 presidential election.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not the same. People are not the same. Taiwan is a sovereign, independent democratic country. ... We want to use this moment to tell the world not to trust China.&quot;</p>
<p>Though the rain began to let up after dark, many people were drenched in their &quot;Say No to China, Say Yes to Taiwan&quot; T-shirts.</p>
<p>&quot;Republic of Taiwan&quot; flags fluttered everywhere.</p>
<p>Reflecting the political complexity of Taiwan's boisterous decade-old democracy, rival groups were staging counter-rallies at the weekend to hail the end of colonial rule in Hong Kong and advocate Taiwan's eventual reunification with China.</p>
<p>Whatever their stand on independence, Taiwan political groups universally reject what Beijing regards as a generous offer -- union under the &quot;one country, two systems&quot; model of local autonomy that underlies Hong Kong's handback.</p>
<p>Beijing, which has viewed Nationalist-ruled Taiwan as a rebel province since a 1949 civil war split, vows to attack if Taipei stops advocating reunion and pursues independence.</p>
<p>Yet Taiwan independence was Saturday's rallying cry.</p>
<p>&quot;The Hong Kong people had no choice and are being forced to reunite with China,&quot; said protest organiser Hsu Ching-hsiung.</p>
<p>&quot;As for Taiwan's people, we still have a choice. We came today to prove to people that we differ from Hong Kong.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan needs to survive. That's why we want to join the United Nations,&quot; Hwu said. &quot;Only when we become an independent nation can we enjoy our due rights.</p>
<p>A U.N. charter member, the Republic of China was expelled in 1972 and replaced by Beijing as the sole Chinese member.</p>
<p>Taipei has applied for a separate Republic of China seat, saying Taiwan's 21 million people deserve representation, but Beijing has shot down the annual efforts.</p>
<p>&quot;It's only a matter of hours now before Hong Kong becomes a part of China. And under China's plan, they would like to make Taiwan another Hong Kong,&quot; said protest leader Lin Shan-Tien.</p>
<p>&quot;This is very dangerous and that's why we've come out today to unify under the name 'Republic of Taiwan' to join the United Nations. Once we are in the U.N., we will have the international security system to safeguard us.&quot;</p>
<p>A 12-year-old sixth grader named Huang agreed.</p>
<p>&quot;I understand the issue perfectly well. I've read all about it,&quot; she said. &quot;I know Taiwan should join the United Nations.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
