<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694411" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: old and new in day of stark contrasts.</title>
<headline>old and new in day of stark contrasts.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's future leader sought to assure its people on Saturday that they had nothing to fear from the Chinese Army while Britain's Prince Charles bade a nostalgic farewell to a once mighty empire.</p>
<p>With the clock ticking away to Monday's midnight handover after 156 years of colonial rule, Hong Kong's legislature closed for the last time after a marathon session with the cry &quot;The King is dead, long live the king.&quot;</p>
<p>Tremors of concern went through Hong Kong after China announced that 4,000 troops will be sent in by helicopters, warships and armoured vehicles as dawn breaks on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Tung Chee-hwa, the new chief executive handpicked by Beijing to run this capitalist goldmine for communist China, was quick to calm local fears about the People's Liberation Army troops, so feared since they crushed the 1989 Tiananmen uprising.</p>
<p>He said Beijing had every right to assert its new sovereignty by posting PLA forces to Hong Kong and insisted the troops would not be used against Hong Kong's 6.4 million people without his orders.</p>
<p>&quot;They will not, they cannot,&quot; he told the U.S. television network NBC, stressing that the PLA was a disciplined army that would soon be part of the community.</p>
<p>British Foreign Secretary Robin Cook, who flew into Hong Kong with heir-to-the-throne Prince Charles for the handover ceremonies, was swift to attack China's troop deployment.</p>
<p>&quot;We regret the scale at which the initial deployment is being made and in particular we regard the provision of armoured personnel carriers as unnecessary and inappropriate.&quot;</p>
<p>Margaret Thatcher, who negotiated the 1984 treaty handing over Hong Kong, agreed with Cook: &quot;The 4,000 seem to be coming in with armoured personnel carriers. After all, it was the kind of carrier that was, I believe, used in Tiananmen Square.&quot;</p>
<p>Thatcher and Cook joined Prince Charles to say farewell at the last elegant garden party marking Queen Elizabeth's birthday before the handover.</p>
<p>Governor Chris Patten, vilified by Beijing for bringing democratic reforms to Hong Kong, wiped a tear from his eye as the band struck up &quot;Amazing Grace.&quot;</p>
<p>Prince Charles, whose great-great-grandmother Queen Victoria once reigned over a global empire, did not glance up as the Union Jack flag was lowered from the mast and a lone bagpiper struck up &quot;Afore ye Go.&quot; It may have been too painful.</p>
<p>The final reception beneath the elegant chandeliers of government house attracted the Hong Kong elite from billionares to bishops who quaffed champagne and nibbled canapes.</p>
<p>Hong Kong Democrat Martin Lee was in reflective mood: &quot;It is the fear that we may lose some of our freedoms that makes people so nervous. There is one thing lacking in China -- the rule of law -- and this was given to us by the British.&quot;</p>
<p>Amnesty International said China's influence could creep in and &quot;chip away&quot; at human rights if the world media and governments lost interest in Hong Kong. More than 8,000 journalists have flown in for this moment of history.</p>
<p>The human rights group said it was concerned China would slowly close its grasp on Hong Kong and stifle civil liberties once it had taken control.</p>
<p>The Legislative Council, which is being replaced by a Beijing-selected body, ended its last marathon session with a flourish. Its President Andrew Wong declared: &quot;The King is dead, long live the king. Life must go on in Hong Kong and it will.&quot;</p>
<p>And the cause of democratic activists was given one last-minute boost.</p>
<p>The new authorities said pro-democracy legislators would be allowed to read out protest statements from the assembly's gallery during the handover ceremony.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
