<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694447" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Rashid completes part of restructuring.</title>
<headline>Rashid completes part of restructuring.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia's Rashid Hussain Bhd said it has partially completed a group restructuring involving its securities and asset management firms, and its fianancial services units.</p>
<p>RHB Capital Bhd, formerly DCB Holdings Bhd, has completed the acquisition of the entire equity interest in RHB Bena Sdn Bhd, the securities and asset management arm of Rashid Hussain and the group's property assets.</p>
<p>The Rashid Hussain group of companies said in a statement issued by their merchant bankers that Kwong Yik Bank Bhd has also completed the acquisition of RHB Capital's entire equity interest in DCB Bank Bhd and DCB Finance Bhd.</p>
<p>Under the new structure, Rashid Hussain owns 58 percent equity in RHB Capital, which in turn owns 92 percent interest in Kwong Yik.</p>
<p>The remainder of the restructuring involves the merger of the banking operations of Kwong Yik with DCB Bank, and the merger of the finance company operations of Kwong Yik Finance and DCB Finance.</p>
<p>These mergers are expected to be completed next month, the statement said.</p>
<p>It said Kwong Yik, which is now substantially owned by RHB capital, is tentatively scheduled to be de-listed from the Kuala Lumpur Stock Exchange on August 11.</p>
<p>On completion of the mergers, the merged bank will be renamed RHB Bank Bhd and the finance company, RHB Finance Bhd.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-201 4813)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
