<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694452" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: ASIA WEEK AHEAD - Stocks seen quiet on Hong Kong.</title>
<headline>ASIA WEEK AHEAD - Stocks seen quiet on Hong Kong.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asian stocks are expected to trade easier next week, with the region's markets taking a breather as foreign investors stay sidelined for the Hong Kong handover.</p>
<p>But Hong Kong's stock market is expected to move higher on Thursday after staying closed for three trading days to mark the transfer of sovereignty.</p>
<p>Bullish sentiment about the territory's prospects under China is expected to lift the market higher from Friday's record closing high in anticipation of the July 1 transfer of sovereignty from the British, which will end 156 years of colonial rule.</p>
<p>Among other markets, Singapore looks poised to plunge further on worries about economic fundamentals while the battered bourse in Bangkok is not expected to hold onto last week's gains of 10 percent following central bank measures to sort out the financial sector.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>HONG KONG - Hong Kong stocks are expected to open higher on Thursday after soaring to a record closing high on the last colonial trading day last Friday.</p>
<p>The market closed 68.77 points higher at a record close of 15,196.79 points in anticipation of the July 1 transfer of sovereignty to China. The stock market will be closed for three working days to celebrate the event, which ends 156 years of British colonial rule.</p>
<p>Further strength is forecast when the market reopens on Thursday, with Friday's announcement that 4,000 People's Liberation Army troops will cross the border in the early hours of July 1 dismissed as expected and largely irrelevant.</p>
<p>&quot;The market will open stronger I think on Thursday because people will want the first day of trading under a new government to be successful. I think the market will be pushed up higher,&quot; said Miles Remington sales trader at SocGen-Crosby Securities.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>TOKYO - Tokyo stocks are likely to be propped up this week by an upturn in economic indicators as shown in the Bank of Japan's &quot;tankan&quot; business survey and May industrial production data released last week, brokers said.</p>
<p>The relief from worries about the economy could encourage market participants to test the key 21,000 point in the Nikkei 225 average, but strong profit-taking pressure at that level may limit the upside, the brokers said.</p>
<p>On Friday, the 225-share Nikkei average closed at 20,523.75, down 61.79 points or 0.30 percent from its closing on June 20.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>TAIPEI - Taiwan share prices are expected to consolidate next week after a persistent uptrend in the past two weeks, but brokers said the consolidation would be limited, basically to reflect the previous gains.</p>
<p>The market, buoyed more by psychological ebullience than improving fundamentals, rose more than 300 points in the week starting June 16. It broke the 9,000-point resistance level on Saturday to settle at 9,024, setting a new high since April 30, 1990 when the index hit 9,292.37.</p>
<p>Brokers said the government was reluctant to take measures to cool the market ahead of Britain's return of Hong Kong to China, ending more than 150 years of British rule.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a politically sensitive time. A stock market plunge would be considered an embarrassment for the government since it's like a lack of public confidence,&quot; analyst Tsao Chung-ping of Ting Kong Securities said.</p>
<p>A 8,800-9,000 stock range was seen for next week.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>BANGKOK - Thai shares are seen moving lower in the week ahead as the market returns to focus on concerns surrounding Thailand's precarious economic situation and continuing turmoil in the finance sector, analysts said.</p>
<p>Measures to bolster the beleaguered finance sector which saw the central bank identify the 16 financially distressed finance firms on Friday could spark retail sales but foreign-led technical buying which supported the market last week was expected to slow, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;Next week I think the market will be coming down,&quot; said Susheel Narula, an analyst at Nava SC.</p>
<p>The SET index jumped 48 points or 10 percent over the last week to close on Friday at 528.18.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>MANILA - Manila shares are likely to tread in a narrow range next week amid light volume as foreign fund managers would be watching Hong Kong after the handover and some would stay away ahead of the release of corporate earnings, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody's waiting for the second quarter earnings and with the recent rally in property, we may see some downside next week,&quot; said Norman Villamin, research head at UBS Securities (East Asia) Ltd.</p>
<p>The main index ended a shade down on Friday by 2.07 points at 2,835.03. It was 46.7 points or 1.62 percent lower from the previous week's 2,881.73.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>JAKARTA - The Jakarta stocks are likely to be mixed next week on local profit-taking and weak foreign interest because of the three working days holidays in Hong Kong, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;But some secondary stocks might continue gaining on speculative interest or possible corporate actions,&quot; one local broker said.</p>
<p>Brokers expect the index to range in the level of 711-720 points. On Friday, the Jakarta composite index closed 7.42 points higher at 716.83 points, against last week's close of 712.22 points.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>KUALA LUMPUR - Malaysian stocks are expected to trade sideways or slightly higher next week.</p>
<p>&quot;If we're not going to get fundamental news, we will have a trading market,&quot; said Leong Yoon Siang, of TA Securities' international division.</p>
<p>Ami Moris, a vice president in dealing at Capitalcorp said the market may get a lift from month-end window-dressing.</p>
<p>But an institutional dealer said the closure of the Hong Kong stock market could temper activity in Kuala Lumpur, said an institutional dealer at a local brokerage firm.</p>
<p>&quot;I think next week is going to be very, very quiet.&quot;</p>
<p>For the week, the Composite Index of 100 large-capitalised stocks closed 27.48 points or 2.50 percent lower from Friday a week ago. On Friday the index ended at 1,070.06, up 3.32 points from Thursday's close.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SINGAPORE - Singapore stocks ended the week in a bearish mood, setting new 45-month lows on a wave of selling by foreign institutional investors and local dealers.</p>
<p>Dealers said recent evidence that the local economy had still not recovered from a nine-month slump, jitters over the fate of the nearby Thai market and lacklustre corporate earnings all contributed to the plunge.</p>
<p>The unweighted benchmark Straits Times Industrials Index ended down 15.43 points at 1,974.37, a new year closing low and just above a fresh 45-month trough of 1,968.66.</p>
<p>Dealers said the market was likely to take a breather on Monday due to the public holiday in Hong Kong but stocks were likely to tumble again later in the week with new lows seen.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SEOUL - Seoul stocks will move in a 720-760 range next week, with buying by foreign investors and off-shore funds alternating with selling on worries about margin loans, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Buying will be focused on securities firms and others perceived to have big earnings growths in the half year to June,&quot; said Hyundai Securities analyst Koh Kyung-bae. &quot;But worries about margin loans will limit any rises.&quot;</p>
<p>The composite index closed at 746.89 on Saturday, down 13.51 points or 1.78 percent from 760.40 last Saturday.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>SYDNEY - Australian shares are expected to hold their ground next week after a sharp run-up earlier this month ahead of the June 30 financial year-end on Monday.</p>
<p>The All Ordinaries index closed at 2,702.4, down 10.2 points on a week earlier in strong options-related trade, as the market retained most of a 100-point surge in the previous two weeks.</p>
<p>Peter Morgan, head of equities at Perpetual Funds Management, said the investors would focus on interest rates, with the Reserve Bank of Australia meeting on Tuesday amid rate cut speculation, and U.S. authorities meeting later in the week.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>WELLINGTON - New Zealand shares staged a broad-based rally on Friday to close 1.37 percent stronger as investors welcomed a new, friendlier monetary environment set out by the central bank in its June Monetary Policy Statement.</p>
<p>Brokers said they expected further gains next week on the new platform of lower interest rates and a lower currency.</p>
<p>&quot;What the market has reacted to is the greater certainty. The market perceives interest rates remaining lower,&quot; said John Rattray at Ord Minnett.</p>
<p>The NZSE-40 Capital Index closed the week at 2,443.22, 16.62 points firmer than last Friday's close.</p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>DHAKA - Shares on the Dhaka Stock Exchange (DSE) are likely to remain mostly flat next week with investors under pressure from banks to repay their loans, brokers said.</p>
<p>&quot;The market is unlikely to maintain its upward trend next week because of pressure for repayment of bank loans,&quot; one broker said. Besides, investors would be cautious about making fresh commitments before parliament formally approves the 1997/98 (July-June) budget next Monday.</p>
<p>The DSE benchmark index gained 4.89 points at 1,123.18 in the week to Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
