<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694416" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Albright lays cornerstone in day of reconciliation.</title>
<headline>Albright lays cornerstone in day of reconciliation.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>HO CHI MINH CITY, Vietnam 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright signalled American determination for post-war reconciliation with Vietnam when she laid the cornerstone for a new consulate here on Saturday.</p>
<p>Against the backdrop of the old U.S. embassy in the former Saigon which fell to the communist North in 1975, she hailed broadening ties between the U.S. and its old enemy and said the new consulate -- with its focus on economic ties and tourism -- symbolised the future.</p>
<p>Albright was the first U.S. secretary of state to visit Ho Chi Minh city -- once the capital of U.S.-backed South Vietnam -- since the Americans lost the war.</p>
<p>Images of the wartime past remained but Albright focused attention on the future in a centre where Americans, once the imposing military force, now see major opportunities for business ventures.</p>
<p>&quot;What has really moved me so deeply here in the last couple of days is that it's very hard to get away from the past,&quot; Albright told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly we all, whether Americans or Vietnamese, are never going to be fully able to put the past behind us, but what I have been deeply moved by is the desire of the people to look toward the future,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;To be able to look forward toward the future while standing in the shadow of the past is a very special event,&quot; she said after laying the cornerstone for the consulate.</p>
<p>The consulate is not expected to open for at least another 18 months.</p>
<p>Albright made a stop in Hanoi at the U.S. office searching for 1,584 American servicemen missing from the Vietnam War, saying that Americans had some way to go before they could put away painful memories of the war.</p>
<p>But she repeatedly cited Pete Peterson, a former prisoner of war who took up his post two months ago as the first U.S. ambassador since the war, as the example to follow and the perfect mender of U.S.-Vietnam ties.</p>
<p>&quot;I haven't forgotten&quot; about the difficult war experiences when he was held for six years by the North Vietnamese, Peterson told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;I've forgiven ... And I feel very strongly about that.&quot;</p>
<p>He described Albright's visit to Ho Chi Minh City as a milestone. &quot;She's symbolic of the commitment to carry on.&quot;</p>
<p>After the cornerstone laying, Albright visited two non- profit programmes that receive U.S. assistance and seek to help Vietnamese with physical problems, including disabilities caused by landmines laid during the war.</p>
<p>The first stop was at Operation Smile, founded and funded by Americans with U.S. government assistance, that has operated on thousands of Vietnamese children with facial deformities like cleft palates.</p>
<p>Albright toured the hospital and posed for photographs with a group of children.</p>
<p>Later, she drove 30 minutes outside the city to a facility, partially funded by the United States, which fits Vietnamese with artificial limbs and wheelchairs and provides jobs training.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm deeply moved by what I have seen here,&quot; she said, praising the cooperation of private individuals, the U.S. government, businesses and the Vietnamese government.</p>
<p>Despite Albright's attempt to focus on the future, the United States yearly spends only $3 million for U.S. aid projects while the annual cost of searching for a diminishing number of missing servicemen is three times that, at $10 million.</p>
<p>&quot;It's always difficult to assess how best to spend money,&quot; Albright said when asked about the disparity. &quot;I think one can't discount the emotional impact of the POW/MIA issue on the American people.&quot;</p>
<p>She also took a tour of the crowded local market. Her other stop was a reception at the American Chamber of Commerce, where she drew applause for her efforts to push Vietnam on lagging economic reforms.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HO CHI MINH CITY, Vietnam"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
