<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694400" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexican army out in force on massacre anniversary.</title>
<headline>Mexican army out in force on massacre anniversary.</headline>
<byline>Gerardo Magallon</byline>
<dateline>AGUAS BLANCAS, Mexico 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Soldiers swarmed across this poor farming region on Saturday on the first anniversary of a rebel uprising and second anniversary of a bloody peasant massacre at the hands of police.</p>
<p>Scores of troops combed fields and forests around Aguas Blancas, a tiny ford deep in the trouble-torn state of Guerrero that has become synonymous in Mexico with peasant struggles.</p>
<p>A Reuters correspondent said at least 10 light tanks were also patrolling the surrounding dirt roads.</p>
<p>Soldiers stood guard as 1,500 protestors gathered to pay homage to 17 peasants gunned down two years ago, and to warn off a repeat appearance of armed rebels which overshadowed the first anniversary.</p>
<p>Then, gun-toting Marxists of the self-styled Popular Revolutionary Army (EPR) stole the show at Aguas Blancas, making their first public appearance and officially launching their rebellion.</p>
<p>Wearing olive green uniforms with their faces covered with handkerchiefs, around 70 armed men catapulted themselves onto the Mexican political scene, calling for the overthrow of President Ernesto Zedillo.</p>
<p>Zedillo has branded the EPR a &quot;terrorist&quot; organisation and has vowed to hunt down its members. Army and police have arrested dozens of alleged EPR collaborators, although few have been formally charged.</p>
<p>EPR rebels operate in a handful of central southern states and have carried out dozens of attacks and raids in the past year. They claim to have killed 98 police and soldiers. Official figures are much lower.</p>
<p>Human rights protestors, many weeping openly, placed flowers at the stone momument erected at Aguas Blancas to remember the dead. &quot;Long live the EPR,&quot; protestors called out at a discreet ceremony alongside the monument.</p>
<p>&quot;In two years, little has been done to bring justice for this crime,&quot; said Amalia Tornes, the president of the Guerrero state Human Rights Commission.</p>
<p>Mexico's central southern states, especially wild mountainous regions such as Guerrero and Oaxaca, are hotbeds of violence and politically trouble-torn. But few incidents have compared to the Aguas Blancas massacre.</p>
<p>Two years ago, police ambushed and opened fire on dozens of peasants riding in the back of trucks.</p>
<p>The unexplained attack outraged Mexico, as video footage showed police placing guns in the hands of their victims in a bid to claim the police had fired in self-defence. Guerrero's Gov. Ruben Figeroa was forced to resign over the incident.</p>
<p>Guerrero authorities have jailed 30 police officers for the massacre but peasant leaders claim those who ordered the attack remain free.</p>
<p>Peasant leader Benigno Guzman, himself in jail accused of being an EPR guerrilla, told Reuters late Friday he would not stop in his fight for justice for the Aguas Blancas massacre.</p>
<p>&quot;I will never stop,&quot; Guzman said in a telephone interview from inside the Las Cruces prison in Acapulco, the luxury tourist resort 250 miles south (400 km) of Mexico City.</p>
<p>To add weight to his fight and to mark the second anniversary, Guzman and nine other jailed peasants started a hunger strike on Wednesday, also demanding they be released along with other political prisoners in Mexico.</p>
<p>Guzman is president of the Organisation of Peasants of the Sierra Sur (OCSS). The peasants killed in the Aguas Blancas massacre were OCSS members.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AGUAS BLANCAS, Mexico"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
