<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694448" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Drugs culprits should die, say Vietnam prosecutors.</title>
<headline>Drugs culprits should die, say Vietnam prosecutors.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>State prosecutors in Hanoi have recommended that appeals for leniency by 19 people involved in a major drugs scandal should be turned down, and sentences including the death penalty should stand.</p>
<p>The ruling Communist Party's Nhan Dan newspaper said prosecutors had told members of a judgement board on Friday that statements made during an appeals trial over the past week, did not provide grounds for a significant softening of sentences against any of the 19.</p>
<p>&quot;In fact, some defendants still deny the verdicts against them and say that other people are to blame,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>The appeals trial, into a case which has ensnared several senior members of Vietnam's powerful security establishment, began on Tuesday and is not expected to end for several more days.</p>
<p>Around half of those involved are former police or border guards. They were found guilty in May of involvement in a syndicate which is said to have flooded Vietnam with hundreds of kilograms of heroin.</p>
<p>Eight were sentenced to death, while the rest were given lengthy jail terms. In addition, most had property, cash and homes confiscated. Nhan Dan said prosecutors had suggested some of that could be returned to family members.</p>
<p>The case has attracted widespread media coverage in Vietnam. Hundreds of people gathered outside the court building in May as court proceedings were taking place.</p>
<p>Voice of Vietnam radio said on Saturday that statements made by the defendants had indicated clearly that other people were involved, and called for the authorities to question other police and customs officials.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
