<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694470" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Timor Bishop says Clinton supports dialogue.</title>
<headline>Timor Bishop says Clinton supports dialogue.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>East Timor Bishop Carlos Belo said U.S. President Bill Clinton and U.N. chief Kofi Annan expressed support for planned talks aimed at negotiating a settlement of the territory's problems, Indonesia's official Antara news agency reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;In principle, U.S. President Bill Clinton and U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan are for a fair, comprehensive and internationally acceptable solution to the East Timor question without armed conflict, which may claim lives and cause material losses,&quot; Belo told Antara in Dili, capital of East Timor, on Friday.</p>
<p>Belo could not be reached for comment.</p>
<p>The foreign ministers of Portugal and Indonesia, after an initial two days of U.N.-sponsored meetings, agreed last Friday that senior officials of the two sides would hold intensive talks beginning on July 28.</p>
<p>Belo, who just returned to Indonesia from a two-month peace mission to Europe and the United States, said he also hoped the East Timorese people would support efforts toward a peaceful solution.</p>
<p>&quot;Let us avoid anything which does not support a solution to the East Timor issue while we are trying to solve it in international fora,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Antara gave no further details.</p>
<p>The latest discussions between Portuguese Foreign Minister Jaime Gama and his Indonesian counterpart, Ali Alatas, were the ninth in a series that began in 1983 and the first since Annan took office in January.</p>
<p>They are aimed at finding an internationally acceptable solution to the problem of East Timor, which occupies half of the island of Timor in the Indonesian archipelago.</p>
<p>Indonesia occupied East Timor in 1975 after civil war erupted following Portugal's withdrawal from its former colony. Indonesia later annexed the territory.</p>
<p>The territory has been hit recently by the worst upsurge of violence in years, which began when separatists seeking to disrupt Indonesia's May 29 general elections carried out a series of attacks in East Timor. At least 35 people have died in the violence.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, David Alex, a key East Timor rebel believed to have masterminded some of the attacks, died of gunshot wounds after being captured in a gunbattle. He was buried in Dili on Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TIMOR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
