<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694477" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Gold Bridge wins property contract.</title>
<headline>Gold Bridge wins property contract.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gold Bridge Engineering &amp; Construction Bhd said it has been awarded a contract to design and build a 680 million ringgit residential and recreational development in western Negeri Sembilan state.</p>
<p>The Emerald Coast project when completed in three years' time will include residential areas in a marina setting, the civil and construction firm said in a statement to the Kuala Lumpur Stock Exchange.</p>
<p>The 200-acre tourism project was awarded by private firm Liberty Bay Sdn Bhd and its joint venture partner Perbadanan Menteri Besar, a firm owned by the Negeri Sembilan state government.</p>
<p>&quot;The whole project is expected to take five years to complete and Gold Bridge is projecting a gross profit of 12 percent or 82 million ringgit for the duration of the contract period,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Gold Bridge expects total sales from the project to be in excess of one billion ringgit.</p>
<p>The company asked the stock exchange to extend the suspension of its shares, saying it was still in the final of negotiations of a corporate exercise.</p>
<p>The stock was last traded on June 20 at 11.70 ringgit.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-201 4813)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
