<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694453" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Albright sidesteps answer on China troop moves.</title>
<headline>Albright sidesteps answer on China troop moves.</headline>
<byline>Carol Giacomo</byline>
<dateline>HO CHI MINH CITY 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright refrained on Saturday from criticising China's decision to send troops into Hong Kong hours after the wealthy British colony reverts to Beijing at midnight on Monday.</p>
<p>Speaking to reporters during a visit to Ho Chi Minh City, she said: &quot;What is important here is for the Chinese to live up to their commitments in the Sino-British agreement (handing the colony back to China) and provide reassurances to the people of Hong Kong that their way of life will continue to exist.&quot;</p>
<p>She also stressed that what is important is not just adherence to agreements but &quot;the signals that are sent&quot; by actions taken.</p>
<p>Asked directly if China's announcement it is sending 4,000 troops into Hong Kong by land, sea and air just hours after the handover sent a negative message, she replied: &quot;We have to make some judgements as we watch this.&quot;</p>
<p>The troops, backed by helicopters, ships and armoured personnel carriers, will cross the northern border at three points early on July 1, Hong Kong's first day of Chinese rule since Britain seized the territory in 1841.</p>
<p>Outgoing British Governor Chris Patten denounced the decision as the &quot;most appalling signal&quot; to Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Albright, winding up a two-day visit to Vietnam, was due to fly to Hong Kong on Saturday to show support for the territory's continued economic and political freedoms under Chinese rule.</p>
<p>But the message was clouded, according to some democrats, by her decision to have the United States be represented at the swearing-in of the territory's unelected provisional legislature, despite her own boycott of the ceremony.</p>
<p>Albright has already made clear the territory had become a litmus test of U.S.-China relations.</p>
<p>&quot;I will bring to Asia a message of vigorous American support for the continued freedom and autonomy of the Hong Kong people,&quot; she said during a stop in San Francisco.</p>
<p>She said the new legislature, hand-picked by Beijing to replace the current elected one until new polls are held, was unjustified and at odds with the popular will because it contains 10 members defeated in the 1995 elections.</p>
<p>As a result, she said she would not participate in the swearing-in ceremony for the assembly, set for after midnight (1600 GMT) on June 30 when Hong Kong returns to Chinese control for the first time in more than 150 years.</p>
<p>British Prime Minister Tony Blair and Foreign Secretary Robin Cook also announced similar plans.</p>
<p>But despite the absence of top officials, Washington and London later said they would still be represented at the controversial ceremony by senior-level aides.</p>
<p>Hong Kong democrats condemned the decision.</p>
<p>In Hanoi on Friday, Albright brushed aside the flap.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe my being present at the reversion ceremony, but not being present for the swearing-in of the Legislative Council, is a significant political act, and one which I think carries a fairly important message,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>But for practical reasons, Washington cannot totally shun Hong Kong's new leaders, she told a news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;We have large numbers of ship visits. There are American citizens and businesses that are in Hong Kong, and it will be important to carry on business with the authorities in Hong Kong,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>However, she dodged answering a question about the impact of the decision for Hong Kong democrats, who accused both the United States and Britain of betrayal for softening their stance over the new, unelected body.</p>
<p>During a stay of nearly four days in Hong Kong, Albright is to attend the handover ceremonies and have bilateral talks with key figures like Chinese Foreign Minister Qian Qichen, Cook and C.H. Tung, Hong Kong's first China-appointed chief executive.</p>
<p>The United States has much at stake in Hong Kong. Some 1,100 U.S. firms based there employ 250,000 workers and 36,000 Americans live there. Hong Kong is the 13th largest U.S. trading partner with two-way trade of more than $24 billion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HO CHI MINH CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
