<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694419" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Final gavel falls on Hong Kong's colonial assembly.</title>
<headline>Final gavel falls on Hong Kong's colonial assembly.</headline>
<byline>Kurt Schork</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The final gavel fell on Hong Kong's colonial legislature on Saturday as members concluded a marathon 23-hour session with emotional valedictory speeches.</p>
<p>Farewells at parliament's last session were laced with snatches of song and verse, two days before Queen Elizabeth's son Prince Charles hands Hong Kong to China at midnight June 30 after 156 years.</p>
<p>&quot;As a Chinese I am proud to see the closing of the colonial era, which began with pain and which ends with pomp and pageantry,&quot; said legislator David Chu Yu-lin.</p>
<p>&quot;For a long time our ancestors, ourselves and our children have been stared down at by the Queen's portrait. Her picture and other symbols of our subjugation have bred in us both an alien feeling and self-contempt.&quot;</p>
<p>Many legislators paid tribute to the civil service, legal system and booming economy which Britain leaves behind.</p>
<p>Also obvious, despite uncertainty about a future under Beijing, was an undertow of resentment at the British regime and relief that Hong Kong's long colonial era is drawing to a close.</p>
<p>The territory's elected Legislative Council will be replaced within hours of the handover by a Provisional Legislature whose members have been hand-picked by Beijing.</p>
<p>Altogether 27 members of the 60-strong Legislative Council will not have seats in the new Provisional Legislature, a target of criticism by pro-democracy campaigners and the West.</p>
<p>Most of those kicked off a &quot;through train&quot; system which Beijing promised would preserve Hong Kong's separate identity are legislators known as independents or democratic activists.</p>
<p>One of those losing a seat, Christine Loh, said the final session was full of human emotion. &quot;It is difficult to say goodbye because some of us are on the through train and others of us aren't,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Provisional Legislature is a &quot;lose-lose&quot; proposition. It has no legitimacy with the Hong Kong people because none of its members has been elected. Both Hong Kong and Beijing are hurt.&quot;</p>
<p>The Legislative Council's final session was held in a handsome 19th-century domed building with colonnades, originally built as the waterfront chambers of Hong Kong's Supreme Court.</p>
<p>Reclamation projects have since pushed the harbour back several hundred metres (yards). The Legislative Council building is now surrounded by soaring office towers and hotels signifying Hong Kong's transformation from a &quot;barren rock&quot; that Britain first settled into today's world financial centre.</p>
<p>&quot;The King is dead, long live the King,&quot; Legislative Council President Andrew Wong said when asked his feelings. &quot;Life must go on in Hong Kong and it will.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
