<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694433" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Few signs of HK political unrest as handover looms.</title>
<headline>Few signs of HK political unrest as handover looms.</headline>
<byline>Clifford Coonan</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's fear of widescale insurrection in Hong Kong after the handover looked seriously exaggerated this weekend, with the burning of a plastic-coated Union Jack counting as the main act of political subversion.</p>
<p>With only hours to go before the wealthy colony reverts to Chinese rule, evidence of significant political subversion in Hong Kong is thin on the ground.</p>
<p>The territory's new masters are taking no chances, however, and China announced on Friday that, at dawn on Tuesday, it is sending 4,000 troops in ships, helicopters and armoured cars into the colony it is taking back after 156 years of colonial rule.</p>
<p>Among the agents of anarchy and disorder on Saturday were ten members of the pro-democracy, anti-colonial April 5th Group, who burned the small British flag while chanting &quot;Colonialists go to hell&quot;. They demanded an apology from the British government for what it termed crimes against the Chinese people.</p>
<p>&quot;We want the British government to apologise to the Chinese people for their invasion of China and we condemn the Hong Kong British government for suppressing political and human rights for over 140 years,&quot; group leader Leung Kwok Hung said.</p>
<p>Leung, wearing a red Che Guevara tee shirt, also said that he wanted democratic elections in the territory.</p>
<p>The flag itself proved difficult to set alight and there were anxious moments before the flames picked up. Leung presented the embers of the burned flag and a statement in a bucket to a police officer outside the building.</p>
<p>Leung and the police officer then posed for photographs for waiting cameramen and photographers, who outnumbered the protesters by around four-to-one.</p>
<p>Earlier, half a dozen protesters tried to bustle their way past security guards at offices of Hong Kong's future chief executive, Tung Chee-hwa.</p>
<p>The protesters, who belonged to a group called Democratic Progress for Hong Kong and China, said they had come to Tung's offices to fight for broad-based democracy on the mainland.</p>
<p>&quot;Only if there is democracy in China can there be democracy in Hong Kong,&quot; Chan Sze-kuen, a spokesman for the group, said.</p>
<p>Tung said earlier in the day that Chinese troops cannot move against the local population without his order and that the PLA presence was a &quot;symbol of sovereignty&quot;.</p>
<p>Outgoing British Governor Chris Patten denounced the decision to deploy the troops as the &quot;most appalling signal to send to the people of Hong Kong&quot;, sparking painful memories of the crushing of unarmed students by the People's Liberation Army (PLA) around Beijing's Tiananmen Square in 1989.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
