<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694460" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Burmese exiles deny SLORC bomb accusations.</title>
<headline>Burmese exiles deny SLORC bomb accusations.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Burma's self-proclaimed government in exile on Saturday denied accusations by Burmese military government that it had masterminded recent bomb attacks in Rangoon.</p>
<p>The Washington-based National Coalition Government of the Union of Burma (NCGUB), said in a statement the charges were fabrications aimed at discrediting pro-democracy forces fighting the country's military rulers.</p>
<p>The ruling State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) on Friday accused a number of exiled groups, including the NCGUB, of plotting and carrying out bomb attacks in the Burmese capital in recent months.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear that by its fabricated lies the SLORC is attempting to discredit the pro-democracy forces and, at the same time, to find a pretext for increasing its repression against the NLD and Daw Aung San Suu Kyi,&quot; the NCGUB said.</p>
<p>Opposition leader Suu Kyi and other senior National League for Democracy officials were not available for comment on Saturday.</p>
<p>Access to Suu Kyi has been blocked by the SLORC and curbs placed on opposition gatherings.</p>
<p>The NCGUB reaffirmed its commitment to resolving Burma's political impasse by peaceful means.</p>
<p>Suu Kyi's party won a landslide election in 1990 which the SLORC has never recognised.</p>
<p>&quot;It has always been the consistent policy of the NCGUB to avoid involvement in, or encouragement of, acts of violence for any purpose. It has never believed that transition to democracy should be, or could be, achieved by violence,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>SLORC officials said on Friday that a series of attacks, including a parcel bomb which killed the daughter of SLORC Army Chief of Staff Tin Oo in April, had been carried out in collaboration with the NLD.</p>
<p>They also said on Friday that the United States and France had helped train dissident groups to use explosives and that covert American agencies were helping to fund Suu Kyi and her party.</p>
<p>The United States, which imposed economic sanctions on Burma in early June citing the SLORC's &quot;severe repression&quot; and poor human rights record, has denied any involvement in the events cited by the military government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BURMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
