<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694423" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Teenager arrested in brutal Japan slaying of boy.</title>
<headline>Teenager arrested in brutal Japan slaying of boy.</headline>
<dateline>KOBE, Japan 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A 14-year-old seeking revenge on Japan's strict education system confessed on Saturday to strangling an 11-year-old acquaintance and beheading him in a crime that shocked the nation, police said.</p>
<p>The head of the boy was found at the gates of a junior high school in this western Japan city on May 27 with a rambling note stuffed in his mouth that said in part: &quot;Well, this is the beginning of the game...it's great fun for me to kill people.&quot;</p>
<p>The killing of the boy, Jun Hase, shocked the nation, not only for its brutality but also because the victim was in a special education program for children with learning problems.</p>
<p>The killer's writings also put a harsh spotlight on an educational system that instils great pressures to succeed.</p>
<p>&quot;The suspect and Jun Hase are believed to be acquaintances&quot;, Seishi Yamashita, a detective at the Hyogo Prefectural Police, said in a televised news conference on Saturday night.</p>
<p>&quot;We searched intensively around the site of the murder and asked the 14-year old suspect to accompany us to the station. The suspect confessed to committing the murder. We found a knife at his house,&quot; Yamashita said.</p>
<p>Police said they are still questioning the youth for a motive.</p>
<p>But in a letter to a local newspaper a week after the body was found, the killer said that he would murder three people a week to &quot;take revenge on the compulsory education system.&quot; No other deaths have since been linked to the murder.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not forgetting revenge for the compulsory education that has produced me as an invisible existence and on the society that has produced this compulsory education.&quot;</p>
<p>Education  Minister Takashi Kosugi said in Tokyo on Saturday that authorities would investigate whether there was any link between the killing and the education establishment.</p>
<p>Police said the letter provided important leads in identifying the alleged killer.</p>
<p>The severed head and body of the victim were found three days after he left home to visit his grandfather, who lived a few blocks away. The body was found dumped in a forest near a television transmission facility.</p>
<p>Since the killing, children in the area have been armed with noise-emitting devices and walk to school with adult escorts, a rare measure in a country renowned for its low rate of violent crime.</p>
<p>The arrest comes just a few days after police said they had few leads in the case. They had looked into a possible Internet connection to the crime after similar words to those used by the killer were found on a public bulletin board.</p>
<p>But police did not say on Saturday whether the Internet leads had produced anything.</p>
<p>Police sources told NHK television that among the strongest clues were the finding of headless pigeons and cats with amputated legs in the neighbourhood where Hase and the suspect lived.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KOBE, Japan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
