<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694425" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: Philippine fighting ebbs, evacuees trek back home.</title>
<headline>Philippine fighting ebbs, evacuees trek back home.</headline>
<dateline>COTABATO, Philippines 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Some 300 families returned to their villages in the southern Philippines on Saturday after more than a week of fighting that has killed over 80 people, officials said.</p>
<p>The Moro Islamic Liberation Front (MILF) has cancelled talks on a possible ceasefire, originally scheduled for Saturday and Sunday, saying the situation was not conducive to negotiations.</p>
<p>Defence Secretary Renato de Villa said soldiers had driven the rebels out of their lairs in three towns in North Cotabato province and would stay there despite MILF threats of reprisals.</p>
<p>&quot;Every encounter is a prelude to a lasting peace,&quot; armed forces chief General Arnulfo Acedera, who accompanied de Villa in an inspection trip of southern provinces, told reporters.</p>
<p>De Villa said the government had approved the release of $385,000 for more equipment to bolster military capability.</p>
<p>Military officials said 76 guerrillas and seven soldiers had died in the fighting that began on June 16. The MILF put its losses at 12 dead.</p>
<p>On Thursday, rebels seized about 60 bus passengers at an MILF roadblock but the hostages escaped when soldiers attacked.</p>
<p>The fighting displaced over 30,000 villagers, officials said.</p>
<p>The MILF is the biggest of three groups fighting for an Islamic state on Mindanao island, which Moslems in this largely Christian country regard as their ancestral homeland.</p>
<p>The mainstream Moro National Liberation (MNLF) signed a peace deal with Manila last year and its leader, Nur Misuari, now runs a semi-autonomous region composed of four Moslem provinces.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COTABATO, Philippines"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
