<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694446" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Russian Navy proposes joint exercise with Japan.</title>
<headline>Russian Navy proposes joint exercise with Japan.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior officer of Russia's Pacific Fleet who arrived aboard the first Russian warship to visit Japan in 103 years said on Saturday the Russian and Japanese navies should conduct joint exercises in the future.</p>
<p>&quot;The era has now moved to building a relationship of cooperation between the Japanese Maritime Self-Defence Force (navy) and the Russian Navy,&quot; Vice Admiral Valery Chirov, deputy chief of the Russian Pacific Fleet, said.</p>
<p>&quot;This includes exchanging visits by combat ships, officers and holding joint naval manoeuvres,&quot; Chirov told a news conference aboard the 8,500-tonne destroyer Admiral Vinogradov.</p>
<p>Chirov did not elaborate on the proposed naval exercises, but said the Japanese navy was not against the idea.</p>
<p>Last year, during a visit to Vladivostok by the Japanese destroyer Kurama, the two navies for the first time conducted joint communications and search-and-rescue training operations.</p>
<p>Admiral Vinogradov arrived at Tokyo's Harumi Pier on Friday. The last Russian warship to pay a courtesy visit to Japan was the armoured cruiser Admiral Kornikov which took part in events in 1894 marking the 25th wedding anniversary of Emperor Meiji.</p>
<p>Japan fought Russia four times this century and during the Cold War years, Japan's navy regarded the Vladivostok-based Soviet Pacific Fleet as its biggest potential enemy.</p>
<p>&quot;I was asking myself why it took us more than 100 years to come here,&quot; Chirov said.</p>
<p>&quot;Friendship is superior to competition and now is the time to build a spirit of cooperation across the bridge called the Sea of Japan. I really must thank the Maritime Self-Defence Force for this.&quot;</p>
<p>Chirov said Russia's latest cutback of 200,000 military personnel, announced by former Defence Minister Igor Rodionov in May, would affect the strength of the Pacific Fleet but said there were no concrete plans.</p>
<p>Chirov also said there were no immediate plans to close some bases, such as the strategic submarine base at Petro-Pavolovsk in Kamchatka.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
