<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694427" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Human rights groups fear for HK under China control.</title>
<headline>Human rights groups fear for HK under China control.</headline>
<byline>Stephen Weeks</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Human rights groups said on Saturday they were concerned China would slowly close its grasp on Hong Kong and stifle civil liberties after taking control of the British colony next week.</p>
<p>London-based Amnesty International said China's influence could creep in and &quot;chip away&quot; at human rights if the world media and governments lost interest in Hong Kong's plight.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a big risk that after keeping Hong Kong under an intense spotlight this week... the media pack will move on,&quot; Amnesty programme director for Asia, Rory Mungoven, told a news conference.</p>
<p>He also noted that as human rights deteriorated in China in recent years, there was less international concern or pressure to stop abuses because countries put commercial interests first.</p>
<p>One example of this was a decision by Britain and the United States to attend the swearing-in of Hong Kong's new legislature, handpicked by Beijing and replacing an elected assembly.</p>
<p>Both countries had said at first that they would boycott the ceremony next Tuesday, just after Britain cedes the wealthy colony following more than 150 years of colonial rule.</p>
<p>&quot;The action by the U.S. and British governments shows the degree of accommodation towards China in this consideration at the outset,&quot; Mungoven said.</p>
<p>In comments after the news conference, Mungoven said China's decision to put on a show of military force after taking control of Hong Kong was also an ominous sign.</p>
<p>&quot;China's decision to ignore the sensitivities of the local and international communities on this point is an assertion that behind Hong Kong's autonomy there will always be the very heavy hand of Chinese control,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Under agreements reached in 1984, fiercely capitalist Hong Kong is to be an autonomous Special Administrative Region of China for the next 50 years.</p>
<p>It should run its own affairs except on matters of foreign policy and national security.</p>
<p>Citing national security, China will send 4,000 troops, along with armoured cars and helicopters, streaming across the border in a high-profile deployment just six hours after Britain cedes control.</p>
<p>Diplomats said this was Beijing's way of stressing its sovereignty over Hong Kong's 6.4 million residents but the size and speed of the troop deployment have caused alarm among some pro-democracy groups.</p>
<p>Another group, the Hong Kong Human Rights Monitor, expressed concern that China's corruption and disregard for Hong Kong's Western legal system could undermine stability and prosperity in the territory.</p>
<p>&quot;The fear is that powerful and corrupt officials and their families from China will try to subvert the legal system in Hong Kong to increase their wealth and influence,&quot; a report by the Human Rights Monitor group said.</p>
<p>It feared that the independence of the Hong Kong judiciary, both for commercial and civil law, could be compromised under China's influence.</p>
<p>&quot;The independence of the judiciary is a wholly alien concept in China,&quot; it said. &quot;The traditional communist position is that judges are servants of the state who carry out the state's orders.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
