<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694418" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Tung says PLA needs order - but China holds trigger.</title>
<headline>Tung says PLA needs order - but China holds trigger.</headline>
<byline>Peter Humphrey</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's future ruler Tung Chee-hwa says China's military garrison cannot move against citizens without his order--but the territory's new constitution sets Beijing's finger firmly on the trigger.</p>
<p>Tung was asked if People's Liberation Army troops sweeping in after next week's handover could act against the people.</p>
<p>&quot;They will not, they cannot,&quot; he told NBC interviewer Tom Brokaw on Saturday.</p>
<p>And separately a key aides in the incoming administration, security chief Peter Lai, insisted there was no &quot;grey area&quot; between PLA-controlled external defence and internal security handled by police.</p>
<p>The former shipping magnate, picked by Beijing to take over the reins of Hong Kong from Britain after Monday's midnight handover, said people should not be worried as the Chinese were a very disciplined army.</p>
<p>China announced that it is sending 4,000 troops in ships, helicopters and armoured cars at dawn on Tuesday into the territory it is taking back after 156 years of colonial rule.</p>
<p>Political commentators say Beijing clearly will control the garrison stationed in the territory from next Tuesday, but it is a defence force and not responsible for internal security.</p>
<p>The Hong Kong Basic Law, promulgated by China in 1990, says Beijing will be responsible for foreign affairs and defence in post-handover Hong Kong.</p>
<p>But the Hong Kong government will be in charge of all other affairs including public order as a Special Administrative Region (SAR) with autonomy in China.</p>
<p>It is a highly sensitive political issue as Hong Kong people still vividly recall 1989 images of Beijing's Tiananmen student demonstrations crushed by PLA troops.</p>
<p>Asked about the psychological effect on the people of Hong Kong, Tung told NBC: &quot;I think the PLA presence in Hong Kong is a symbol of sovereignty. It is necessary to show that symbol of sovereignty.</p>
<p>&quot;So they will be here and from what I have seen they are a very well disciplined people, a very well disciplined army. They will be there to do what is necessary to demonstrate sovereignty and I think the Hong Kong people will get to know the PLA well and in due time they will be part of our community.&quot;</p>
<p>Tung was laughing and in good humour during the interview.</p>
<p>&quot;I am laughing because I have said many times this is a very happy event.&quot; He said nobody could spoil the handover party.</p>
<p>&quot;If anybody feels they can achieve martyrdom they will be very disappointed. People really must behave themselves in accordance with the law,&quot; he warned.</p>
<p>Commentators recall that the new Basic Law says troops sent by Beijing to be stationed in Hong Kong &quot;shall not interfere in the local affairs of the region&quot;.</p>
<p>However, it adds: &quot;The government of the Hong Kong SAR may, in times of need, ask the Central People's Government for assistance from the garrison in the maintenance of public order and disaster relief.&quot;</p>
<p>Members of the garrison have to abide by Hong Kong laws and national Chinese laws.</p>
<p>China has passed a garrison law clarifying their rights, duties and restrictions.</p>
<p>The Basic Law also makes China bear the cost of the garrison. Hong Kong pays nothing for it.</p>
<p>&quot;The entry of the Chinese garrison is a consequence of provisions in the Basic Law,&quot; Lai, Secretary for Security, said.</p>
<p>&quot;The PLA is responsible for defence. The Basic Law says the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region government is responsible for internal security,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not a question of priorities, it is a question of roles. The PLA is assuming defence duties of Hong Kong from July 1. Our 28,000-strong police force is one of the best trained and most professional police forces in the world.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not expect any likelihood of a clash between the PLA, which will be responsible for defence, and the Hong Kong SAR police who will be responsible for internal security.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;There is no grey area.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
