<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694478" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: British heir may sell picture, besides hand over HK.</title>
<headline>British heir may sell picture, besides hand over HK.</headline>
<byline>Justin Jin</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A Chinese tycoon is negotiating to buy a Hong Kong landscape by British royal heir Prince Charles, a skilled amateur artist, who hands the territory back to China at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>The pastel-coloured picture depicts a mountain view from the stern of the royal yacht Britannia, with the Union Jack flag fluttering in the centre.</p>
<p>A &quot;very rich&quot; Hong Kong businessman is bargaining for the HK$170,000 (US$22,000) lithograph featured in an exhibition marking the British colony's transition to Beijing rule.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the tycoon wants something to hang in his yacht,&quot; the show's organiser Geoffrey Dobbs told Reuters.</p>
<p>In two days, the prince will hand Hong Kong's sovereignty to President Jiang Zemin, ending more than 150 years of Chinese national shame which started with defeat in the Opium Wars.</p>
<p>&quot;The Chinese are not meant to be buying British at the moment, are they?&quot; Dobbs said.</p>
<p>The painting, titled &quot;View of Double Haven from HMY Britannia&quot;, was created during the prince's 1989 visit.</p>
<p>&quot;I rather feel that this painting should be entitled &quot;Farewell to Empire&quot; or &quot;Poor Britannia!&quot; the prince was quoted by the organisers as saying.</p>
<p>Two things mark the work from 120 or so others in the &quot;Visions of Hong Kong&quot; show.</p>
<p>For start, it is the most expensive. An ink drawing by Dave Parker lags far behind at HK$100,000. Parker framed his painting of an old junk with wood planks he said came from a boat similar to that in the drawing.</p>
<p>The prince is also the only one, of about 40 artists featured, who does not live in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Some would add a third difference.</p>
<p>&quot;Really, the painting is the dullest of all,&quot; said a photographer. &quot;But for an amateur, it is not bad,&quot; Dobbs said.</p>
<p>About 10 of the pieces have been sold by the first day, and Dobbs said he was confident more buyers are in the pipeline.</p>
<p>&quot;But the tycoon is not considering the other paintings because they are all too cheap,&quot; Dobbs said.</p>
<p>(US$1 = HK$7.74)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
