<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694499" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MOROCCO: Mobutu has operation for serious bleeding problems.</title>
<headline>Mobutu has operation for serious bleeding problems.</headline>
<dateline>RABAT 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ailing former leader of Zaire, Mobutu Sese Seko, underwent an operation for serious bleeding complications on Saturday in Rabat's Avicene Hospital and was in good condition afterwards, the official news agency MAP said.</p>
<p>Mobutu, 66, already suffering from prostate cancer, was brought to the Moroccan capital from the northern town of Tanger on Friday and admitted to the cardiology ward of Avicene hospital.</p>
<p>MAP said Mobutu had &quot;serious bleeding complications&quot; and underwent &quot;radiological vascular intervention&quot; on Saturday morning.</p>
<p>&quot;The operation passed in good conditions and the patient was well,&quot; the agency said, quoting an authorised medical source.</p>
<p>Mobutu was in the fifth floor of the hospital where tight security was imposed. A senior doctor earlier refused to make any comment on the ousted leader's health and security officials later told Reuters correspondents to leave the floor, largely devoted to cardiology.</p>
<p>Police were on duty at the hospital and at least half a dozen official cars were parked outside the entrance to the hospital building.</p>
<p>Mobutu, ousted in May after a seven-month-long rebellion following three decades in power, has already had extensive treatment in Europe for his cancer.</p>
<p>Just one week ago, staff at another hospital, the Mohamed V in the northern town of Tangier, had been preparing to receive Mobutu for chemotherapy for his cancer.</p>
<p>&quot;A Tangier's Mohamed V hospital senior doctor on Friday visited President Mobutu for the second consecutive day...We expect him (Mobutu) to undergo chemotherapy treatment here in the coming days,&quot; a spokesman said last week.</p>
<p>Sophisticated medical equipment was recently purchased by the hospital for cancer treatment and several rooms arranged for this purpose, the spokesman said, but gave no other details.</p>
<p>But the bleeding forced his medical advisors to have Mobutu flown to the capital, 280 km (175 miles) south.</p>
<p>Late on Friday, a senior Moroccan doctor who declined to be named, said: &quot;President Mobutu was admitted on Friday night into the cardiology department at the Avicene hospital.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that in Tangiers, &quot;for health reasons doctors advised him to undergo a medical examination in the sophisticated Avicene hospital.&quot;</p>
<p>The doctor said Mobutu was taken to the fifth floor in a wheelchair as he could not walk. He declined to give further details.</p>
<p>Zaire's former president moved to the sea resort at Cap Spartel, about 20 km (12 miles) from Tangier last week, where he had been expected to spend up to six weeks, officials said.</p>
<p>He arrived in the kingdom last month with an entourage of around 30 people and had been staying in a hotel south of Rabat and near a palace of King Hassan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RABAT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MOROCCO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
