<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694484" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: HK colony parliament dies as China masses garrison.</title>
<headline>HK colony parliament dies as China masses garrison.</headline>
<byline>Brian Williams</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's colonial legislature ended its final session on Saturday shortly after Beijing revealed it will send 4,000 troops here within hours of Britain's June 30 handover to China.</p>
<p>Legislative Council President Andrew Wong summed up a marathon 23-hour farewell session with the words &quot;The King is dead, long live the King.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Life must go on in Hong Kong and it will,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Wong is one of 33 members of the 60-seat Council who will join a Provisional Legislature, appointed by Beijing, which takes over when Hong Kong formally reverts to China at midnight on Monday.</p>
<p>The parliamentary switch has been criticised by the West and pro-democracy campaigners who want early elections.</p>
<p>There was no mention in the farewell session, marked by valedictory speeches laced with songs and poems, of China's decision to send 4,000 People's Liberation Army troops into Hongong on ships, helicopters and armoured cars just six hours after the British handover.</p>
<p>Future leader Tung Chee-hwa's office said late on Friday that the troops would arrive at dawn, ensuring they will sweep in as the city slumbers following all-night handover parties.</p>
<p>The announcement was made after Hong Kong's stock market had just closed at a record high on the last trading day of British rule, underlining a wave of public optimism for a prosperous future under China.</p>
<p>However outgoing Governor Chris Patten condemned the troop move as &quot;a most appalling signal to send to the people of Hong Kong&quot;, still chilled by images of armoured personnel carriers and green-uniformed troops used in the massacre of unarmed students around Beijing's Tiananmen Square in 1989.</p>
<p>Britain's Foreign Office said it may send a &quot;negative signal&quot; to the world.</p>
<p>Although Beijing will be responsible for Hong Kong's defence, and was expected at least to match Britain's 10,000-strong force, few had expected it to risk inflaming local sensitivities so rapidly with such a blunt military statement.</p>
<p>Apart from Britain's concern, the news was mainly received calmly both at home and abroad.</p>
<p>Washington took the announcement in its stride, saying China was acting within its rights.</p>
<p>&quot;They've always said they were going to put Chinese troops where the British troops were. That's not anything unusual. It's their territory,&quot; said a White House official, who declined to be identified.</p>
<p>The South China Morning Post said &quot;a more low-profile entry, staggered over a longer period would have eased sensitivities.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The PLA will do much to dispel the uncertainties created by its arrival if it ensures that its troops are rarely seen once they are here and that they stick strictlty to both the letter and spirit of the law,&quot; the Post's editorial said.</p>
<p>The Hong Kong Standard, the colony's other main English-language newspaper, said in its editorial that Patten had overreacted to the troop move and there was nothing surprising or frightening about it.</p>
<p>&quot;Dawn is symbolic of a new beginning,&quot; the editorial said.</p>
<p>With everyone striving to avoid rows in the last two full days before the handover, a media report on Saturday said future leader Tung, selected by China, may have to miss Britain's separate farewell ceremony.</p>
<p>The Post quoted a spokesman for Tung as saying the arrival in Hong Kong possibly at the same time of Chinese President Jiang Zemin and Premier Li Peng could keep Tung away from the sunset farewell at the end of 156 years of rule.</p>
<p>The main ceremony at midnight features Britain's heir to the throne Prince Charles formally handing over control of Hong Kong to President Jiang.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
