<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694434" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thailand's Finance One seeks foreign investor.</title>
<headline>Thailand's Finance One seeks foreign investor.</headline>
<byline>James Mclean</byline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thailand's Finance One Plc wants a foreign investor to take a stake in the ailing company but is considering consolidation with local finance firms, the company's president said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment for Finance One we are looking at the possibility of merging and the possibility of bringing in a new foreign shareholder,&quot; Pin Chakkapak told Reuters.</p>
<p>It was too early to say who a potential new foreign buyer might be, he said.</p>
<p>Finance One was also studying the possibility of being absorbed or purchased by another local finance company and applying for a bank licence, he added.</p>
<p>Pin's ailing Finance One, once Thailand's most successful finance company, was one of 16 financially distressed finance firms whose operations were suspended by the central bank on Friday as part of package of measures aimed at stabilising the troubled sector.</p>
<p>Central bank measures, which could compel financially distressed firms to consolidate with one another into groups led by five selected stronger firms, should boost confidence in the sector, Pin said.</p>
<p>But doubts surrounded the detail and execution of the measures, he added.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we really have to see how it effects the industry over the next few days, but it should help stabilise the overall situation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We still have to see what other measures come in terms of the detail and implementation,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A much-touted merger between Finance One and commercial bank Thai Danu Bank Plc collapsed earlier this year. The firms blamed legal difficulties for the collapse.</p>
<p>Following the central bank's failure earlier this week to buy into Finance One's 8.28 billion baht ($330 million) capital increase the company said it was in talks to reschedule debts of around $46 million to foreign creditors.</p>
<p>Though the central bank's latest measures have been broadly welcomed some analysts have cautioned the 16 closures could lead to a run on deposits and a sell-off in finance sector shares by retail investors who fear more compulsory closures.</p>
<p>The Thai finance and securities sector is struggling to cope with declining revenues, high funding costs and a deterioration in asset quality as Thailand goes through its worst economic downturn for more than a decade.</p>
<p>Earlier this week a leading local executive estimated that up to 31.5 percent of the nearly $60 billion of loans extended by Thai finance firms may be non-performing.</p>
<p>(US$ = 25 baht)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
