<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694455" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Albright sets cornerstone for new Saigon consulate.</title>
<headline>Albright sets cornerstone for new Saigon consulate.</headline>
<byline>John Chalmers</byline>
<dateline>HO CHI MINH CITY, Vietnam 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>After talking tough on speeding reform and improving human rights, U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright spoke warmly on Saturday of a new future in relations with Vietnam.</p>
<p>Laying a cornerstone brick for a new American consulate in an empty lot next to the dilapidated U.S. embassy of wartime Saigon, Albright said another milestone had been reached.</p>
<p>&quot;To look to the future while standing in the shadow of the past makes it a very special occasion today,&quot; she told reporters later as she walked through a bustling market in the heart of what became Ho Chi Minh City after the communists took over in 1975.</p>
<p>But, speaking to American business executives later, Albright returned to calls she had made on Friday for trade barriers to be lowered, the state sector to be revamped and political reform.</p>
<p>The consulate will stand in the shadows of the old embassy, which was both the U.S. diplomatic nerve centre of the Vietnam War and a scene of frantic retreat in helicopters by thousands during the conflict's last days.</p>
<p>&quot;The old building was built for an entirely different purpose,&quot; said one official. &quot;This building is going to be a little more user-friendly.&quot;</p>
<p>The United States raised its flag at an embassy in Hanoi two years ago, when relations between the former foes were normalised.</p>
<p>But it needs a consulate in Ho Chi Minh City, the powerhouse of a reform-led economic boom, for the 3,000-plus American business people living there, and to meet demand for visas.</p>
<p>Albright walked out of the site and into a crowd of local people on the Le Duan Boulevard.</p>
<p>There was some pushing and raised voices, and one man waved a copy of the official Saigon Giai Phong (Saigon Liberation) daily in front of Albright, but she was soon hurried back into her car, and two men hustled by police into their motorbike sidecar.</p>
<p>Her next stop was the Ben Thanh market, where she bought a purse and one of the ubiquitous Vietnamese conical hats, before heading on to an &quot;Operation Smile&quot; hospital for children with facial deformities.</p>
<p>At a meeting with the American Chamber of Commerce she said that although Vietnam was moving in the right direction, it was not always as fast as Washington would like to see.</p>
<p>She said the United States would like to waive the Jackson-Vanik amendment, which stands in the way of most-favoured nation trading status, soon. But she said Hanoi still had steps to take to reach a bilateral trade agreement with Washington, especially on improving access to for investment and trade.</p>
<p>Albright's critical comments, especially on human rights, were either left out or played down in the tightly-controlled Vietnamese press on Saturday.</p>
<p>The official army newspaper, Quan Doi Nhan Dan, ran a front-page article on the harmful effects of Agent Orange, the herbicide sprayed by U.S. troops during the war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HO CHI MINH CITY, Vietnam"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
