<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694458" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Lee Kuan Yew warns against US-China clash on Asia.</title>
<headline>Lee Kuan Yew warns against US-China clash on Asia.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Asia looks to a continuing United States presence in the region but this could change if America clashes with China over Hong Kong or Taiwan, Singapore Senior Minister Lee Kuan Yew said.</p>
<p>&quot;A strong U.S. presence in the Asia-Pacific region has provided the basis for stability and growth of East Asia,&quot; Lee told industry leaders at a Pacific Rim Forum on Friday night.</p>
<p>&quot;And this presence is more likely to endure if America and China do not clash over Hong Kong or Taiwan,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said that a &quot;locking of horns&quot; with China on an issue concerning China's relations with its own Chinese in Hong Kong or Taiwan was not tenable in the longer run.</p>
<p>It could shorten the much valued U.S. presence here, he said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong, a British colony for 150 years, will revert to Chinese rule on July 1.</p>
<p>Lee, predicting a change in the global order, said that in 20 years China could achieve the per capita gross domestic product of Taiwan or South Korea.</p>
<p>He added that if growth continues at present rates, China's gross national product could become the largest in the world.</p>
<p>&quot;Such a massive change will be cause for discomfort to the existing world order as China will need some room at the top,&quot; Lee said.</p>
<p>He commented that while U.S. President Bill Clinton had decided to pursue a policy of deep engagement with China, it could be disrupted by domestic politics in the United States.</p>
<p>Lee said some groups wanted the United States to adopt a more confrontational policy for different reasons. Some wished to see China stumble before it becomes powerful.</p>
<p>&quot;Was democracy and human rights in Hong Kong an issue before the collapse of the Soviet Union? I venture to suggest that if the Soviet Union still existed, the question would never have been raised.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
