<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694436" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Thousands join Taiwan's &quot;Say No to China&quot; march.</title>
<headline>Thousands join Taiwan's &quot;Say No to China&quot; march.</headline>
<byline>Lawrence Chung</byline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of Taiwanese braved summer downpours on Saturday for a &quot;Say No to China&quot; march, demanding their island not be swallowed up like Hong Kong but granted a U.N. seat as a sovereign Republic of Taiwan.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan independence!&quot; the protesters cried as they approached barriers erected outside the downtown presidential office, creating an ugly traffic snarl.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan is Taiwan, China is China!&quot;</p>
<p>The rally was one of several organised to express Taiwanese disdain for the 1984 Sino-British pact by which Hong Kong, without its people's consent, will be handed to Beijing on July 1.</p>
<p>&quot;The Hong Kong people had no choice and are being forced to reunite with China,&quot; said march organiser Hsu Ching-hsiung.</p>
<p>&quot;As for Taiwan's people, we still have a choice. We've come out today to prove to people that we are different from Hong Kong. The rain cannot stop us.&quot;</p>
<p>Police informally estimated the crowd at several thousand, many drenched to the bone in their &quot;Say No to China&quot; T-shirts for lack of raingear.</p>
<p>Many waved the green and white &quot;Republic of Taiwan&quot; flag.</p>
<p>Reflecting the political complexity of Taiwan's boisterous decade-old democracy, rival groups were staging counter-rallies on Saturday and Sunday to hail Hong Kong's handover and advocate Taiwan's eventual reunification with China.</p>
<p>Whether for or against independence, Taiwan political groups universally reject communist China's offer of union under the &quot;one country, two systems&quot; model of local autonomy that underlies Hong Kong's change of sovereignty.</p>
<p>Beijing has vowed to attack Taiwan if it drops its advocacy of reunification and pursues an independence course.</p>
<p>Yet Taiwan independence was the dominant mood on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's only a matter of hours now before Hong Kong becomes a part of China. And under China's plan, they would like to make Taiwan another Hong Kong,&quot; said activist Lin Shan-Tien.</p>
<p>&quot;This is very dangerous and that's why we've come out today to unify under the name 'Republic of Taiwan' to join the Untied Nations. Once we are in the U.N., we will have the international security system to safeguard us.&quot;</p>
<p>Businessman Y.P. Huang said it was irrelevant that Taiwan's people were mainly descendants of Chinese immigrants who crossed the Taiwan strait over the past 400 years.</p>
<p>&quot;Taiwan already is a sovereign, independent country and is not a part of China,&quot; Huang said. &quot;It's like people from other countries who immigrated to the United States, they would never say they belonged to their original countries.&quot;</p>
<p>A 12-year-old sixth grader named Huang said she already had made up her mind in favour of independence</p>
<p>&quot;I understand the issue perfectly well. I've read all about it,&quot; she said. &quot;I know Taiwan should join the United Nations.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
