<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694465" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: Mycom plans cash raising via bond issue.</title>
<headline>Mycom plans cash raising via bond issue.</headline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia's Mycom Bhd has proposed a fund raising exercise to raise 150 million ringgit to be used to build palm oil mills, cultivation of oil palm and for land improvement.</p>
<p>The exercise will involve an issue of 150 million ringgit worth of bonds with detachable warrants, and an offer for sale and private placement of the warrants, Mycom said in a statement issued by its merchant bankers.</p>
<p>It plans to issue the five-year redeemable bank guaranteed unsecured bonds with a coupon rate of 2.0 percent, with 50 million detachable warrants on a bought deal.</p>
<p>The diversified firm would then put up for sale the provisional allotment of 49.085 million warrants by the primary subscriber to Mycom shareholders on a one-warrant for every eight shares basis at a price to be determined later.</p>
<p>The remaining 914,740 warrants will be placed out privately by the primary subscriber at a price to be determined.</p>
<p>The proposals will need regulatory and shareholders' approvals.</p>
<p>Mycom is involved in gaming, hotel, property investment and development, plantations and stockbroking.</p>
<p>-- Kuala Lumpur newsroom (603-201 4813)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C172">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
