<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694445" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>HONG KONG: Experts say Hong Kong graft fears unfounded.</title>
<headline>Experts say Hong Kong graft fears unfounded.</headline>
<byline>Sarah Davison</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1996-06-29</dateline>
<text>
<p>Corruption fears may be prevalent in Hong Kong as it waits to return to China, but there is little evidence so far there is anything to worry about, a panel of experts told Reuters Financial Television on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think this is a key point,&quot; said Richard Margolis, policy analyst at Merrill Lynch in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;High-level connections are much sought-after but there is very little evidence yet that they pay dividends other than to people who are part of the system inside China.&quot;</p>
<p>Although corruption is frequently cited as the number one concern for both business and ordinary people in Hong Kong after it returns to Chinese control at midnight on June 30, there is virtually no evidence to support these fears, the experts said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it's true that investing in China in social and political relationships has not paid off,&quot; said Miron Mushkat, chief economist at Lehman Brothers. &quot;Perhaps this reflects the weaknesses of the institutional environment in China, the fact that things are in a state of flux.&quot;</p>
<p>Connections are important the world over, but they become vital in countries where ordinary people have no recourse to an established rule of law, said Diane Yowell, director at the Hongkong and Shanghai Banking Corp.</p>
<p>&quot;I've stopped looking at this as some perverse cultural aspect. It is really a defence mechanism for people in countries where there is no sound legal system,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Margolis argued that if the Chinese system of guanxi, or connections, had already infected Hong Kong, chief executive Tung Chee-hwa would have appointed different people to his Executive Council, or inner cabinet.</p>
<p>In the past, the British colonial governor automatically appointed the heads of Jardine Matheson and Hongkong and Shanghai Bank to the inner circle, but Tung has not appointed either of their Chinese equivalents -- the heads of the Bank of China and China Resources -- to his inner circle, Margolis said.</p>
<p>&quot;I also dispute the idea that it is massively profitable to cooperate with China. The lesson has been that the people who have made money out of investing in China are relatively ordinary, unpolitically-connected manufacturers who have shifted manufacturing into China,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Everybody on the panel agreed that Hong Kong's civil service and the rule of law were Britain's greatest legacy to the territory, which was seized by the British following the Opium Wars more than 150 years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The Brits overall did a good job,&quot; said Stephen Vickers, senior managing director of Kroll Associates (Asia) Ltd.</p>
<p>&quot;You can't justify history 150 years on, none of us can. But the legacy is that we have a legal system that works, I hope it continues to work, we have a civil service that is effective and we have a very strong and vibrant economy. So that certainly is a superb start to a new regime.&quot;</p>
<p>Hongkong Bank's Yowell said: &quot;I think that what Britain gave to Hong Kong in the sense of institutions is invaluable. I think it's what made Hong Kong stand out among Asian cities -- the sense of fair play, the sense of rule of law here.&quot;</p>
<p>Mushkat agreed, urging China &quot;not to throw out the British baby with the British bathwater&quot; in order to ensure the territory's continued success.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-06-29"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
