<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694443" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Cambodia's Hun Sen appeals to country's poor.</title>
<headline>Cambodia's Hun Sen appeals to country's poor.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cambodia's Second Prime Minister Hun Sen said in an election-campaign style speech on Saturday that only a person from a poor background could understand the poor.</p>
<p>Hun Sen and his uneasy coalition partner, First Prime Minister Prince Norodom Ranariddh agreed last week that Cambodia's next election will be on May 23.</p>
<p>Ranariddh and Hun Sen share power in a coalition formed after United Nations-supervised elections in 1993 but relations between the two have been deteriorating since last year when Ranariddh demanded a greater share of power.</p>
<p>Hun Sen said in his speech in Kompong Cham province, north of Phnom Penh, that someone born in a palace could never understand poor people.</p>
<p>&quot;Only the poor can understand the poor. People born in the high class, people born in a royal palace, they don't know the poor,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hun Sen comes from a humble background while Ranariddh, whom he did not name in his speech, is the son of King Norodom Sihanouk.</p>
<p>Political analysts expect a close and hard-fought campaign for the May general election.</p>
<p>The splintering Khmer Rouge guerrilla group has also become a major source of friction between the two men with both vying for political gain as the guerrilla group breaks up.</p>
<p>There has been mounting international concern about political violence in the country since bodyguards loyal to the two men fought a gun battle in central Phnom Penh earlier this month.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
