<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694542" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: 1997/98 world coffee exports at 84.4 mln bags-USDA.</title>
<headline>1997/98 world coffee exports at 84.4 mln bags-USDA.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Agriculture Department Friday estimated 1997/98 world coffee exports at 84.4 million 60-kilogram bags, up from a revised 82.9 million bags seen in 1996/97.</p>
<p>USDA previously pegged 1996/97 world coffee exports at 79.6 million bags.</p>
<p>In its semi-annual look at coffee in the Tropical Products: World Markets and Trade report, USDA said total coffee supply in producing countries in 1997/98 is forecast at 130.5 million bags, down 2.5 percent from the prior year largely due to lower beginning stock levels.</p>
<p>The department estimated beginning stocks in producer countries in 1997/98 at 26.0 million bags, the lowest level since 1980/81 and down 6.1 million bags from 1996/97. USDA pegged the decline on the significant increase in exports.</p>
<p>It forecast 1997/98 ending stocks in producer countries at 20.0 million bags.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, USDA forecast 1997/98 world coffee production at 103.7 million bags and estimated the Brazil crop at 28.0 million bags.</p>
<p>USDA left those forecasts unchanged in Friday's report.</p>
<p>USDA pegged Brazil 1997/98 coffee exports at 19.5 million bags, up nearly 1.3 million bags from the 1996/97 forecast.</p>
<p>Coffee consumption in Brazil was forecast at 12.0 million bags in 1997/98, a nine percent increase the 1996/97 estimate.</p>
<p>USDA said the increase in coffee prices may temper the increase in demand through higher domestic coffee prices.</p>
<p>&quot;Strong world prices for coffee have led Brazil's exporters to export coffee to capture these lucrative prices, possible resulting in lower domestic availabilities,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>In the report, USDA said U.S. coffee stocks at the end of May totalled 1.977 million bags, up from 1.855 million bags at the end of April and versus 2.271 million bags in May 1996.</p>
<p>On Colombia, USDA forecast 1997/98 ending stocks would dip to 3.1 million bags from 4.1 million bags estimated for 1996/97. Total consumption was seen at 1.55 million bags versus 1.53 million bags in 1996/97.</p>
<p>USDA forecast Indonesia coffee exports would drop to 4.6 million bags in 1997/98 from a revised 6.1 million bags forecast for 1996/97 due to the expected smaller crop.</p>
<p>Mexico coffee exports were seen at 4.8 million bags in 1997/98, an increase from 1996/97's 4.73 million bags.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
