<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694588" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Clariant says year going well as of Q2.</title>
<headline>Clariant says year going well as of Q2.</headline>
<dateline>ZURICH 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Swiss specialty chemicals maker Clariant AG said the second quarter of 1997 continued to be good in terms of sales and profits for it and its acquisition from Germany's Hoechst AG, according to a Swiss newspaper.</p>
<p>The business bi-weekly Finanz und Wirtshaft quoted Clariant chairman Rolf Scwheizer as saying the year was going well for both businesses.</p>
<p>Clariant plans to buy Hoechst Speciality Chemicals (HSC) as of July 1, retroactive to the start of the year, under a deal announced in December and approved by the European Commission on June 10. In return, Hoechst will get a minority stake in Clariant and cash.</p>
<p>&quot;Both parts, Hoechst and Clariant, started (1997) very well in regards to sales as well as profits,&quot; Scweizer said in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;This pleasing development has continued in the second quarter,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>&quot;We are fully within our ambitious plans,&quot; he said without elaborating.</p>
<p>Schweizer said detailed planning for the merger was being wrapped up and work would soon start.</p>
<p>&quot;In two weeks we will present our goals, strategies and measures to the entire international management, then we can start with the necessary work,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In the end, three existing Clariant divisions and six business areas at Hoechst will be merged into six divisions in the new Clariant, he said.</p>
<p>Clariant has said it expects the combination with HSC to result in synergies saving some 500 million Swiss francs over a period of two and a half to three years.</p>
<p>Clariant itself was created in 1995 as a spin-off from pharmaceuticals and chemicals group Sandoz AG ahead of the megamerger with Ciba-Geigy that created life sciences giant Novartis AG.</p>
<p>Clariant's 1996 net profit was 137 million Swiss francs on sales of 2.33 billion francs, up nine percent from pro forma 1995 figures.</p>
<p>-- Zurich Newsroom, +41-1-631 7340</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZURICH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
