<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694596" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: Bankrupt Belgian mine shareholders to get windfall.</title>
<headline>Bankrupt Belgian mine shareholders to get windfall.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Holders of shares in bankrupt Belgian coal mine SA des Charbonnages Neerlandais Willem Sophia are in line for a windfall payment before the company is finally wound up, its liquidators said on Saturday.</p>
<p>In a notice published in Belgian newspapers, the liquididators said shareholders would receive around 4,700 Belgian francs per share in September and the company would then be delisted.</p>
<p>Willem Sophia last traded on the Brussels bourse at 1,400 francs, meaning shareholders stand to make a 236 percent gain.</p>
<p>Willem Sophia is one of several former bankrupt coal mines that are still listed because they stand to benefit from funds set aside when they were still working to cover the cost of clearing up environmental and other damage.</p>
<p>Willem Sophia last paid a dividend in 1991. Its biggest shareholder is Societe des Participations Industrielles, a privately-held investment vehicle of Belgium's Boel family.</p>
<p>-- Nick Antonovics, Brussels Newsroom +32 2 287 6817, Fax +32 2 230 7710</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
