<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694511" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>QATAR: Qatar to allow foreigners majority stake in firms.</title>
<headline>Qatar to allow foreigners majority stake in firms.</headline>
<byline>Kedar Sharma</byline>
<dateline>DOHA 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Qatar is expected to enact a law soon allowing foreigners to own majority shares in local projects and companies, a senior Qatari official said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;The draft law...allows foreign entities and individuals to own more than 51 percent in projects set up with local partners in Qatar,&quot; said Youssef Hussein Kamal, undersecretary at the Ministry of Finance, Economy and Trade.</p>
<p>&quot;The law also deals with incentive schemes and provides for exemption of customs duties for five to 10 years for projects set up in industrial zones,&quot; he told a Qatari businessmen's meeting.</p>
<p>The draft law has to be approved by the cabinet and Emir Sheikh Hamad bin Khalifa al-Thani before it becomes law. Kamal did not give a precise date when he expected the approval.</p>
<p>The meeting, organised by the Qatar Chamber of Commerce and Industry, was described by officials as a &quot;kick-off event&quot; for the Middle East and North Africa Economic Summit (MENA), which Doha is to host in November.</p>
<p>Qatar, pursuing an aggressive industrialisation policy, plans to offer 15 medium and 16 small-scale projects for foreign investment at the summit, in addition to a number of heavy and capital-intensive gas projects for which Qatar is seeking foreign equity.</p>
<p>The existing law prohibits foreigners from holding more than a 49 percent stake in a Qatari project or firm.</p>
<p>Kamal said the amended law would serve as an incentive for foreign firms to invest in the Gulf Arab state and asked Qatari businessmen to scout out foreign partners with cash and technical know how to set up medium and small projects.</p>
<p>&quot;A new industrial zone covering an area of 10 million square metres (3.9 square miles) is being set up west of (the capital) Doha where plots will be given at a nominal rent&quot;, he said.</p>
<p>Kamal said 22 foreign companies had invested heavily in oil and gas sectors in the past two years in Qatar, but did not give the exact amount of their investments. Other officials have said $5.5 billion was invested by U.S. firms and around $10 billion by Japanese, Italian, French and other Western firms.</p>
<p>Minister of State for Foreign Affairs Ahmad bin Abdullah al-Mahmood, chief coordinator for the Mena summit, said preparations were proceeding smoothly to hold the summit on November 16 to 18.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="QATAR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DOHA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="QATAR"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
