<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694539" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Texas man charged with clubbing 22 emus to death.</title>
<headline>Texas man charged with clubbing 22 emus to death.</headline>
<dateline>COLLEYVILLE, Texas 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Penned in and unable to escape, 22 emus were clubbed to death by a Texas man frustrated by his financial losses in breeding the once-valuable flightless birds, police said on Saturday.</p>
<p>The man and his brother were trying to relocate the emus to a rural property from a ranch in Colleyville, near Fort Worth, on Friday but could not move the birds so they allegedly began beating them with an aluminum baseball bat.</p>
<p>Sgt. Clyde Davis said police responded to a neighbour's call and found a pile of dead emus lying inside a trailer with more scattered around a pen.</p>
<p>&quot;There was one bird still alive which had to be euthanized when I got there,&quot; said Reed Young of the Humane Society of North Texas. &quot;It was vomiting blood and had blood on its face, and was staggering around, and then it fell to the ground and couldn't get up anymore.&quot;</p>
<p>The market for emu meat, oil and eggs boomed several years ago but quickly became saturated as large numbers of people started buying them and breeding them in the hope of getting rich quickly.</p>
<p>Young said a pair of emus, which once fetched thousands of dollars, are now worth about $200.</p>
<p>&quot;The owner told us he couldn't even take them to the slaughterhouse in this area, because the slaughterhouse already had all the meat and oil they needed,&quot; he said. &quot;He told me he didn't feel like he had done anything wrong.&quot;</p>
<p>Police confiscated a baseball bat and Davis said the men could be charged with cruelty to animals. The charge carries a maximum one year in prison and a fine of up to $4,000.</p>
<p>Eighty-six more emus, all alive, were found on the 10-acre property. They were taken from the owner's custody and a judge will decide next week whether to auction them off, give them to the Human Society for placement or return them to the owner.</p>
<p>Davis said the men may have had little idea of how to handle the birds.</p>
<p>&quot;What they were apparently doing is grabbing them around the neck but, from what I understand from the animal control people, the best way is to grab them by their wingettes and then you're able to guide them wherever you want them to go,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLLEYVILLE, Texas"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
