<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694512" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: Jordan plans state sell-off fund, stock scheme.</title>
<headline>Jordan plans state sell-off fund, stock scheme.</headline>
<byline>Suleiman al-Khalidi</byline>
<dateline>AMMAN 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Jordan unveiled on Saturday plans to set up a fund to invest privatisation revenues, raise incomes of ordinary Jordanians and offer them a discounted stake in sell-offs of state assets.</p>
<p>Jawad Anani, Deputy Prime Minister for development issues, told reporters the cabinet approved the steps to help Jordanians benefit from an accelerated sell-off of the government's multi-billion dollar assets in stocks and state utilities.</p>
<p>&quot;We will be setting up a special account, call it a generations fund, to be opened in the state treasury, depositing all the revenue from the government's sale or transfer of utilities to commercial entities or sale of these companies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Profits or interest from the fund would be channeled towards raising living standards, he said.</p>
<p>Officials say the moves are crucial to soften the social impact of a drive to divest state holdings, a key component of a privatisation drive and IMF-directed structural reforms.</p>
<p>Government officials say 21 percent of Jordan's 4.3 million people are living in poverty, though independent economists say the level is much higher.</p>
<p>The role of the state in Jordan's economy has been dominant and the government's vast portfolio includes an estimated 40 percent of the Amman Financial Market's capitalisation of 3.2 billion dinars.</p>
<p>It also retains full control of state utilities such as electricity, water and the state airline which it plans to eventually partially privatise.</p>
<p>The jewel in its privatisation plans so far is a 26 percent stake it plans to divest in its telecommunications monopoly to foreign investors. Anani said there was no timetable beyond the sale of most cement and telecommunication holdings this year.</p>
<p>The fund would eventually have transferred to it all the state's holdings in firms and utilities, Anani said.</p>
<p>Anani said a bylaw would be promulgated soon to cover the fund's operations and where it will invest its revenues, adding that its success hinged on the committee running it making high returns.</p>
<p>To help Jordanians take a stake in privatisation, Anani said the proposed stock ownership scheme would let state employees buy shares at a discount to market prices.</p>
<p>&quot;This is so that benefits of the privatisation process can be spread to the widest section of Jordanians,&quot; Anani said.</p>
<p>Some Jordanians have expressed unease about the social repercussions of privatisation and economists said the new government plans could ease fears.</p>
<p>The government also approved setting up a ministerial committee to guarantee rights of employees in privatised state utilities such as electricity and communications.</p>
<p>Anani said the government planned to speed up moves to sell a 33 percent stake in Jordan Cement Factories, expected to go to a foreign investor. A share ownership scheme would be offered to Jordanians, Anani said. $1=0.709 dinars -- Amman newsroom +9626 623 776</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I24200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AMMAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
