<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694513" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Hizbollah says two fighters killed in Israel raid.</title>
<headline>Hizbollah says two fighters killed in Israel raid.</headline>
<dateline>BEIRUT 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Lebanon's pro-Iranian Hizbollah said on Saturday that Israel's air raid on southern Lebanon late on Thursday killed two of its guerrillas.</p>
<p>&quot;A second martyr was killed in action (in the Israeli raid) while doing his national duty,&quot; a spokesman for the group said.</p>
<p>On Friday, Hizbollah (Party of God) reported its first casualty in the attack -- 25-year-old Youssef Ismail Mahdi -- whom it said was fighting against an attempted raid by enemy helicopters when &quot;martyred&quot;.</p>
<p>Israel said earlier its forces killed at least one Hizbollah guerrilla during a clash in its south Lebanon occupation zone.</p>
<p>Hizbollah guerrillas are fighting to oust Israeli troops and their local militia allies from a 15-km (nine miles)-wide border zone they hold in south Lebanon.</p>
<p>Israel has held the border strip since its first invasion of Lebanon in 1978. It set the current boundaries of the zone in 1985 after withdrawing the bulk of its forces following a second invasion in 1982.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIRUT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
