<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694534" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Senate passes biggest tax cut in 16 years.</title>
<headline>U.S. Senate passes biggest tax cut in 16 years.</headline>
<byline>Tabassum Zakaria</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Senate joined the House on Friday in approving the biggest tax cut for Americans in 16 years, but some hurdles remain before the legislation can become law.</p>
<p>The Senate voted 80-18, with a majority of Democrats on board, to approve a five-year net tax cut of about $77 billion. The House, in a much more partisan manner, approved its tax bill Thursday by 253 to 179.</p>
<p>Congress passed the tax bills on the heels of spending legislation approved earlier this week. Combined, they would implement a highly touted agreement between congressional leaders and the White House to balance the budget over five years.</p>
<p>&quot;We have, indeed, made history,&quot; William Roth, chairman of the Senate Finance Committee, said. &quot;We have passed a ... package that balances the budget while offering American families their first real tax cut in 16 years,&quot; the Delaware Republican said.</p>
<p>But ahead lie intense negotiations and efforts to overcome White House objections.</p>
<p>House and Senate negotiators in coming weeks will seek to work out differences in their tax bills, so they can send a final package to President Bill Clinton.</p>
<p>The White House reiterated on Friday that both bills were unacceptable to the president in their present form.</p>
<p>Clinton, however, said he was &quot;quite optimistic&quot; the White House and Congress could reach agreement on the details. &quot;We should expect a little of this skirmishing. We're going to offer our thoughts on Monday,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>A 20-cent-per-pack tobacco tax increase in the Senate bill but not in the House version could become contentious. Senate Majority Leader Trent Lott said he preferred not to see the tobacco increase in the tax legislation, but he declined to predict how it would fare in negotiations.</p>
<p>The Senate defeated a proposal by Sen. Edward Kennedy, a Massachusetts Democrat, to raise the cigarette tax by another 23 cents per pack to pay for children's health programmes.</p>
<p>Pete Domenici, the New Mexico Republican who chairs the Senate Budget Committee, was angered by the administration's support of Kennedy's plan, saying it violated the budget agreement.</p>
<p>Lott, a Mississippi Republican, said, &quot;I want to thank all the members of the Senate -- both Republican and Democrat -- for working together in a bipartisan way to provide American taxpayers with the largest tax reduction since Ronald Reagan was president.&quot;</p>
<p>The Senate bill would provide a $500 tax credit for each child under the age of 17 and require that the credit be deposited in a sort of Individual Retirement Account for education for children aged 13 to 16.</p>
<p>Also included were tax relief for college education costs and expanded Individual Retirement Accounts.</p>
<p>Married couples would be allowed to exclude from taxation up to $500,000 in gains made from selling a home. The bill would cut the capital gains tax on profits on investments such as stocks to 20 percent from a maximum rate of 28 percent for individuals.</p>
<p>The bill would raise the threshold at which the estate tax is imposed to $1 million in 2006 from $600,000 now and immediately exclude $1 million from tax when a family-owned business accounts for more than 50 percent of an estate.</p>
<p>Higher taxes and the elimination of certain tax breaks would raise $66 billion in revenue over five years. Airline ticket taxes would be extended and higher passenger fees charged, the federal cigarette tax would go up, and there would be a gradual reduction in an ethanol subsidy starting in 2001.</p>
<p>The Senate rejected a proposal to eliminate the ethanol subsidy after it expired at the end of 2000, as the House tax bill would. Oil companies currently get a tax credit of 5.4 cents per gallon when they blend alcohol derived from grain with gasoline.</p>
<p>The Senate approved an amendment to increase gradually to 100 percent the tax deduction self-employed individuals can take for health insurance.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
