<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694590" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Luxembourg's Juncker says rules out EMU delay.</title>
<headline>Luxembourg's Juncker says rules out EMU delay.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Luxembourg Prime Minister Jean-Claude Juncker has ruled out a delay of monetary union and warned France to take heed of German concerns about lowering budget deficits to qualify for Europe's single currency.</p>
<p>In an interview with the news weekly Der Spiegel, distributed on Saturday ahead of publication on Monday, Juncker said that although the Maastricht treaty allowed for a delay of monetary union, such a move would have dire consequences.</p>
<p>&quot;In practice I completely rule out a delay,&quot; he said, adding: &quot;This would have as a consequence higher unemployment, higher inflation and higher interest rates.&quot;</p>
<p>Juncker said that the Maastricht treaty allowed for European Union members to set a new timetable for monetary union, but the new date must be set by the end of 1997 or before the EU decides in 1998 which members qualify for EMU.</p>
<p>&quot;If we were to determine in March or April 1998 that we could not start monetary union, then monetary union would be gone,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Rather than speculate on a delay of monetary union, Juncker, who becomes EU president on July 1, said EU members should instead do everything possible to rein in budget deficits to three percent of gross domestic product.</p>
<p>That is the key fiscal target contained in the Maastricht treaty and even key EMU advocates like Germany are having difficulty meeting it. The French government said this week that it did not expect to meet the target this year.</p>
<p>Juncker warned Paris to try with &quot;extraordinary seriousness&quot; to reduce its budget deficit this year.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope that there are no illusions in Paris over the reaction of Germany and other EU members,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Helmut Kohl will not agree to monetary union at any price. If necessary he will be rock solid in protecting German interests and be very careful to respect German concerns.&quot;</p>
<p>Juncker praised German Finance Minister Theo Waigel for putting pressure on EU members to cut deficits by insisting on a strict interpretation of the Maastricht treaty.</p>
<p>But he said it was wrong to focus narrowly on the three percent criterion and instead spoke of a &quot;strict interpretation of the treaty&quot;.</p>
<p>A strict interpretation of the treaty would also allow Germany to join EMU even if its budget deficit were 3.2 percent, Juncker indicated.</p>
<p>&quot;The treaty says three percent,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;If a member temporarily veers from this reference value but then clearly moves in the direction of the value again and one had committed oneself lastingly to stability then even 3.2 percent conform to the treaty,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A French government source said on Friday &quot;first signs&quot; showed the public deficit could exceed 3.4-3.5 percent of gross domestic product this year but that Paris would do everything to launch a European single currency on time in 1999.</p>
<p>-- william.boston@reuters.com (Bonn Newsroom, 49 228 26097150)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LUX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G151">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
