<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694541" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Biting winds, freezing waters and they paid for it.</title>
<headline>Biting winds, freezing waters and they paid for it.</headline>
<byline>Leslie Gevirtz</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Some 200 volunteers who paid up to $30,000 each to face biting winds, freezing waters and 10 months away from their families and friends are nearing the end of their quest -- to sail around the world the wrong way.</p>
<p>&quot;Well, I'd always been a Saturday sailor and this was my chance -- my only chance really -- to sail around the world. Wrong way, right way. Whatever way,&quot; explained Tony Hollingsworth as he helped maneuver one of the 14 42-tonne yachts in Boston harbor.</p>
<p>Hollingsworth, a 37-year-old electrical engineer from Queensland, Australia, is one of 14 crewmembers who set off from Southampton, England, in September to sail around the world against the currents and the tides as part of the BT/MCI Global Challenge.</p>
<p>The last leg of the race begins on Sunday when the million-dollar yachts glide out of Boston and head across the North Atlantic for Southhampton.</p>
<p>The vessels, each sponsored by a corporation or a charity, are identical and the crews are balanced as well, so the race &quot;is really a test of seamanship,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In most cases the seamanship is learned on the job. &quot;Some 70 percent of these crews had never sailed before. They just wanted a challenge,&quot; said Phil London, one of the race organizers.</p>
<p>&quot;It's been that,&quot; Hollingsworth said. He has lost about 20 pounds since the start and the upper part of his long, lanky torso &quot;is really in the best shape it's ever been,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The steel-hulled vessels met 70-foot (21 metre) seas in the Southern Ocean sailing from Rio de Janeiro to Wellington, New Zealand, through low-pressure areas &quot;that look like a thumb print on your map, but give you quite a kick when you're in them,&quot; Hollingsworth said, remembering the time a rogue wave knocked the boat flat.</p>
<p>&quot;It's horrible wet work. Really physically demanding. Changing the headsails, reefing the main. You're absolutely wacked,&quot; he said of sailing through a hurricane.</p>
<p>It was so cold in the lower latitudes that aboard his vessel, the Ocean Rover, sponsored by the makers of Land Rover cars, two of the crew would spend 15 to 20 minutes on deck &quot;then be dragged down by the next pair. It was just brutal,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But by far the hardest part of the journey is &quot;getting along with people. And that is a challenge for the skipper,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>His skipper is Paul Bennett, 38, of Newcastle, England, who has sailed all of his life, but never around the world the wrong way. An easy-going man always ready with a quick quip, Bennett had only one firm rule -- no alcohol aboard. &quot;Ocean racing and booze don't mix. You can go down to the pub anytime you're ashore,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>To make the most of the limited space aboard, the crew was divided into seven-member shifts, but &quot;Privacy, forget about it,&quot; Bennett said. Mindful that weight would be a factor, the crew limited themselves to 14 items each. Socks counted as two items.</p>
<p>Hollingsworth, who intends to return to a consulting firm in Queensland when the journey is through, estimated his total cost for the adventure at about $112,500 ($150,000 Australian). &quot;It's been worth every penny,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Ocean Rover was in 9th place overall leaving Boston some nine days, nine hours and 36 minutes behind the lead ship sponsored by the company Group 4.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
