<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694526" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Anti-Moslem posters glued to Hebron storefronts.</title>
<headline>Anti-Moslem posters glued to Hebron storefronts.</headline>
<dateline>HEBRON, West Bank 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Palestinian shopkeepers found hate posters on Saturday depicting the Prophet Mohammad as a pig stamping on the holy Koran glued to their storefronts near a Jewish settlement enclave in Hebron.</p>
<p>&quot;The settlers have placed the posters on our shops. They lack ethics and religious beliefs because Judaism doesn't allow them to infringe on religious feelings of others,&quot; said shopkeeper Abadallah Hassouneh, 60.</p>
<p>There was no immediate comment from settler leaders, religious Jews who do not speak to the media on the Jewish Sabbath.</p>
<p>The crudely drawn posters depicted Islam's prophet Mohammad as a large pig wearing a Palestinian chequered headdress stepping on the Koran. Islam and Judaism view pigs as unclean and ban the eating of pork.</p>
<p>&quot;We appeal to all those concerned to put an end to the provocations of the settlers,&quot; said another shopkeeper, Idris al-Hroub, 30.</p>
<p>Shopkeepers said they forwarded copies of the posters to mosques and the Islamic religious affairs authority for consultation on a course of action.</p>
<p>Israel handed over most of Hebron to Palestinian self-rule in January but kept troops in about 20 percent of the city to guard some 400 Jewish settlers who live and study in fortified enclaves in the heart of the city of 100,000 Palestinians.</p>
<p>The dividing line has become a scene of regular confrontations since the handover.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers shot and wounded at least seven Palestinians in Hebron on Friday during clashes with Arab demonstrators.</p>
<p>The violence came against the backdrop of a freeze in Israeli-PLO peacemaking following Israel's groundbreaking in March on a new Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HEBRON, West Bank"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
