<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694529" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>DUBAI: Rights group calls on Iran to release journalist.</title>
<headline>Rights group calls on Iran to release journalist.</headline>
<dateline>DUBAI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S.-based human rights group urged Iran to release a newspaper editor arrested in April unless evidence was produced in a fair trial to support espionage charges against him.</p>
<p>&quot;We fear that the charges may have been brought  against Mr. Sarkuhi to punish him for his activities as a writer and to intimidate other independent-minded writers in Iran,&quot; Human Rights Watch wrote in an open letter to the head of Iran's judiciary Ayatollah Mohammad Yazdi.</p>
<p>The copy of the letter received by Reuters on Saturday was dated June 26.</p>
<p>Faraj Sarkuhi, editor of the monthly Adineh (Friday), was arrested in April for trying to leave the country illegally.</p>
<p>He had alleged in a letter smuggled out of Iran that he was held for six weeks and tortured by the Iranian secret service in Tehran late last year to force him to confess to spying to Germany.</p>
<p>Yazdi on Tuesday said Sarkuhi had been charged with espionage and would be tried soon.</p>
<p>Human rights and press freedom groups have since said that the trial had begun and that Sarkuhi was being deprived of legal representation.</p>
<p>Sarkuhi's wife, Farideh Zebarjad, who lives in Germany, has expressed concern that her husband is being held as a bargaining chip to put pressure on Germany.</p>
<p>A German court in April ruled that Iran's leadership ordered the killings of a group of Iranian Kurdish exiles in Berlin in 1992. Iran denied the charges.</p>
<p>Germany downgraded relations with Tehran and, along with most EU members, recalled its ambassador for consultations after the verdict. Germany's ambassador has still not returned.</p>
<p>&quot;Human Rights Watch calls for Mr. Sarkuhi's immediate release, unless credible evidence is produced in a fair trial to support the serious charges against him,&quot; the letter said.</p>
<p>&quot;If he is to be tried, Human Rights Watch seeks your (Yazdi's) assurance that the trial will be open to the public and will comply with international law...,&quot; the letter added.</p>
<p>The London-based human rights group Amnesty International said it believed Sarkuhi was a prisoner of conscience.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DUBAI"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
