<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694561" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: European homosexuals in carnival for recognition.</title>
<headline>European homosexuals in carnival for recognition.</headline>
<byline>Francois Raitberger</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Huge crowds of gays and lesbians in garb ranging from the colourful to the lewd marched through Paris on Saturday to demand equal recognition for same-sex couples in what they said was the biggest ever homosexual rally in Europe.</p>
<p>Transvestites in high heels mixed in a carnival atmosphere with lesbians, some topless or in wedding dress. Gays with their faces painted, or wearing huge plastic breasts, blew kisses to onlookers.</p>
<p>Ropewalkers and strip-teasers performed on floats, one of them in the shape of a giant penis several metres (yards) long. &quot;Ignorance is your enemy,&quot; proclaimed a black-draped float of anti-AIDS activists Act Up.</p>
<p>Organisers said 300,000 people took part in the festive Europride parade on the five-km (three mile) route from Place de la Republique to Reuilly in the east of the capital for an all-night concert. Police said at least 120,000 took part.</p>
<p>Despite the provocation, the parade rang of respectability and success as France, shedding Latin prejudice against homosexuality, promised to give homosexual couples the same legal rights as heterosexual couples.</p>
<p>&quot;What we want is happiness for all, the right to live our little life together,&quot; said one heavily made-up gay in a top hat and frock coat.</p>
<p>The march also smacked of business opportunities. Europride peddled trinkets, T-shirts and CD records, and tickets for the concert sold at 130 to 150 francs ($23 to 26).</p>
<p>More than 20 firms sponsored the rally, from food groups to the state railway company SNCF and Paris Transport Authority RATP who offered cut rates to participants.</p>
<p>RATP issued a special pink ticket to travel cheap on the capital's bus and underground railway network, prompting protests from some right-wing politicians.</p>
<p>Greens Environment Minister Dominique Voynet, a single mother, and Socialist ex-culture minister Jack Lang joined the march.</p>
<p>Representatives of the Lesbian and Gay Pride movement were officially received by Health Minister Bernard Kouchner, and by the junior minister for European Affairs Pierre Moscovici, who pledged to monitor implementation of a non-discrimination clause introduced in European Union legislation at this month's Amsterdam summit.</p>
<p>Socialist Justice Minister Elisabeth Guigou said earlier this week that the newly-elected left-wing governent would deliver on its pledge for a &quot;contract of social union&quot; granting legal status to gay and lesbian couples.</p>
<p>Left-wing deputies on Friday tabled a bill to create the contract ensuring any unmarried couple &quot;with a joint and lasting life project&quot; get the same legal rights as heterosexual couples on housing, inheritance and taxes.</p>
<p>Socialist MP Marie-Noelle Lienemann has asked the European Commission to extend the &quot;contract of civil union&quot; throughout the 15-state EU.</p>
<p>French law does not now recognise homosexual marriage although some cities issue certificates of cohabitation that entitle gay couples some of the rights which heterosexual couples are granted, such as discounts on the national railway system.</p>
<p>An opinion poll published in the weekly L'Evenement du Jeudi showed prejudice against homosexuality gradually disappearing in France, with 59 percent of people questioned saying it was the homosexuals' own business, up from 33 percent eight years ago.</p>
<p>Twelve percent approved of homosexuality, and 28 percent found it shocking or scandalous.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
