<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694572" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy to make 13.3 trln lire from Eni sale.</title>
<headline>Italy to make 13.3 trln lire from Eni sale.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Italian Treasury said on Saturday it will make a maximum 13.3 trillion lire ($7.8 billion) from the third tranche sale of energy giant Eni in one of the biggest placements the world has ever seen.</p>
<p>Treasury Minister Carlo Azeglio Ciampi said there had been much greater demand than expected for the sale, which closed on Friday, and added that the Treasury now expected to reduce its holding in Eni to 51.5 percent from the current 69.1 percent.  </p>
<p>Italy had originally planned to cut its holding to just 54.6 percent, but Ciampi told a news conference that demand for the stock was three times the original offer, with some 830,000 Italian retail investors signing up for Eni shares.</p>
<p>He said given the huge demand, additional shares would be offered to institutional investors, under a so-called greenshoe option, which if accepted, would cut the Treasury stake to the 51.5 percent level. A director for one of the sale global coordinators said the shares would almost certainly be bought.</p>
<p>Ciampi said the sale price had been pegged at 9,288 lire per share for the small retail investors, while institutional investors will have to pay 9,575 lire -- Eni's closing price on the Milan bourse on Friday.</p>
<p>It was the biggest single sell-off in Italian history, with the two previous Eni offers in 1995 and 1996 raising 6.3 trillion lire and 8.8 trillion lire respectively. Later this year Italy plans to sell its controlling stake in telecoms group Stet and in motorway operator Autostrade.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
