<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694540" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Army justice has curious twist - fewer lawyers.</title>
<headline>Army justice has curious twist - fewer lawyers.</headline>
<byline>Dan Trotta</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Americans fed up with one of the most hated professions would love the military justice system. Sometimes, there are no lawyers.</p>
<p>A high-profile hearing in Washington has called attention to this curious twist of military justice. Here, the man who plays the role that would be the judge in civilian court is not a lawyer but a logisitics officer specialising in oil supplies.</p>
<p>Col. Robert Jarvis is the investigating officer presiding over the so-called Article 32 hearing into charges of sexual misconduct against Gene McKinney, the Army's top enlisted soldier who holds the title sergeant major of the Army.</p>
<p>The hearing adjourned Friday and will start again Monday.</p>
<p>Legal experts say that in some Article 32 hearings, which determine whether a defendant must face court-martial, neither the trial counsel (as the prosecutors are called) nor the defence counsel are lawyers either.</p>
<p>Jarvis was chosen by a superior who &quot;just reaches down in his command and picks an officer,&quot; Jim Phalen, a former Army lawyer who now works as an aide to a congressman, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Experts also defend the system as more fair than its civilian equivalent, the grand jury investigation, in which a prosecutor presents evidence with neither judge nor defence present.</p>
<p>Lawyers have a saying that a prosecutor could indict a ham sandwich if he wanted to.</p>
<p>&quot;You've got to remember if it was a grand jury, the defence lawyer wouldn't even be there,&quot; Phalen said.</p>
<p>McKinney is charged with 18 counts including sexual misconduct, indecent assault and adultery. Because of McKinney's high post, the national media have flocked to the case, thrusting Jarvis, a gentlemanly officer from Youngstown, Ohio, into the national spotlight.</p>
<p>Jarvis must recommend to superiors whether McKinney, who denies all the charges, should be sent up for court-martial, a decision legal experts said is mostly a matter of common sense.</p>
<p>But he also must make rulings on complex rules of evidence. For that he must rely on a legal adviser, a junior officer who is a lawyer. Jarvis periodically puts testimony on hold to consult with his legal adviser.</p>
<p>Sometimes, his homespun aphorisms have provided brilliant comic relief. When one lawyer spoke in a stream of legalese unrecognizable outside of a courtroom, Jarvis paused and said, &quot;Say that in English.&quot;</p>
<p>But other times, the courtroom has lacked even a low level of control.</p>
<p>With an alleged victim of sexual abuse on the stand, a defence lawyer was hammering away at her credibility while the prosecution and the witness herself fought back. At one point, all three people were talking at once.</p>
<p>&quot;Col. Jarvis, my words are being twisted and it is very frustrating,&quot; the witness said.</p>
<p>Since then, Jarvis has demanded, and received, what he calls &quot;civil behaviour.&quot;</p>
<p>Army lawyers made available to provide background information to reporters covering the McKinney hearing have stressed that this is a highly unusual case.</p>
<p>Jarvis faces scrutiny from three lawyers for each side, including an aggressive and highly paid civilian defence attorney, plus the national media.</p>
<p>&quot;In an Article 32 hearing we don't usually have a full-blown trial,&quot; one Army lawyer said. &quot;A lot of times you're just making sure there's enough evidence to support the charges.&quot;</p>
<p>For that, an investigating officer relies on common sense, mostly to judge the credibility of witnesses.</p>
<p>&quot;That's why you have officers with understanding of the ways of the military, with understanding of the ways of the world,&quot; the Army lawyer said. &quot;Certainly he's capable of understanding that a child sex abuse case is more serious than the theft of a candy bar.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
