<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694516" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>MOROCCO: Mobutu in hospital in Moroccan capital.</title>
<headline>Mobutu in hospital in Moroccan capital.</headline>
<dateline>RABAT 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ousted leader of Zaire, Mobutu Sese Seko, remained in Rabat's Avicene Hospital on Saturday, a day after he was admitted to the cardiology ward.</p>
<p>A senior doctor on the fifth floor of the Moroccan hospital where Mobutu was admitted refused to make any comment to Reuters. Security officials later told correspondents to leave the floor and government officials were not available for comment.</p>
<p>A medical source later confirmed Mobutu remained in the hospital but would not say whether he had undergone an operation or other treatment.</p>
<p>Late on Friday, a senior Moroccan doctor who declined to be named, said: &quot;President Mobutu was admitted on Friday night into the cardiology department at the Avicene hospital.&quot;</p>
<p>Mobutu was staying with his family in the northern province of Tangier but &quot;for health reasons doctors advised him to undergo a medical examination in the sophisticated Avicene hospital,&quot; the doctor said.</p>
<p>&quot;At this stage, Mobutu's health is not too bad,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But he added that Mobutu was taken to the fifth floor in a wheelchair as he could not walk. He declined to give further details.</p>
<p>Zaire's former president moved to the sea resort at Cap Spartel, north of Tangier last week, where he was expected to spend up to six weeks, officials said. He arrived in the kingdom last month with an entourage of around 30 people.</p>
<p>Mobutu, ousted after a seven-month-long rebellion following three decades in power, has been suffering from prostate cancer for which he had extensive treatment in Europe.</p>
<p>According to a Western diplomat based in Tangier &quot;Mobutu was seeking political asylum in the neighbouring European countries of Portugal or Spain&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MOROC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RABAT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MOROCCO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
