<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694565" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Iraq says ready to resume crude sales in August.</title>
<headline>Iraq says ready to resume crude sales in August.</headline>
<byline>Elif Kaban</byline>
<dateline>CRANS MONTANA, Switzerland 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iraq's key negotiator for a U.N. oil-for-food deal said on Saturday that Baghdad was ready to resume new oil sales in August under the second round of the accord approved this month if New York did not delay agreement.</p>
<p>Abdul Amir al-Anbari told Reuters at a business forum here that Baghdad was ready to resume crude shipments pending submission of its medicine and food distribution plan, likely to be ready within two weeks, and its Security Council approval.</p>
<p>&quot;Everything is really in place. It depends on how cooperative the other party is,&quot; said the envoy.</p>
<p>Al-Anbari led Iraq's talks with the United Nations for December's accord allowing Baghdad to sell up to $2 billion of oil over six months to purchase food, medicine and other goods for civilians.</p>
<p>World oil markets have been nervously waiting for word on the resumption of Baghdad's oil sales amid lingering worries about the absence of Iraqi crude.</p>
<p>Iraq received Security Council approval for new oil sales starting June 8 after the approval of the second round of the accord, but has yet to resume liftings because it still has to submit a finalised aid distribution plan.</p>
<p>The Security Council did not approve Iraq's demand for the ceiling to be raised to $4 billion under the oil-for-food accord, which is a humanitarian exception to sanctions slapped on Baghdad for its invasion of Kuwait in 1990.</p>
<p>If all went smoothly, al-Anbari said: &quot;End of July, beginning of August we would resume our oil discussions. We'll have to sign contracts and they have to be approved by the oil experts in New York.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Then, the shipments would start,&quot; said the soft-spoken envoy, who is Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein's diplomatic trouble-shooter abroad and is now Iraq's ambassador to UNESCO, the U.N. Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation.</p>
<p>Al-Anbari said Iraq believed it had met the key conditions for sanctions to be removed and said he hoped the U.N.-imposed economic ban on its oil sales would be lifted by the end of 1997.</p>
<p>He dismissed recent comments by Charles Duelfer, deputy chairman of the U.N. Special Commission in charge of eliminating Iraq's prohibited weapons, who said Baghdad had given no sign that it would allow U.N. weapons teams to inspect all sites.</p>
<p>&quot;The embargo should be lifted. We keep on trying,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We might say the resolution is becoming a pretext to postpone the removal of sanctions and we're not going to implement it. That could also happen. We might reject the oil-for-food renewal,&quot; he declared.</p>
<p>Al-Anbari said Iraq was working on its humanitarian distribution plan and that its Undersecretary of Health was in New York discussing the issue. Asked when the plan could be ready, he said: &quot;I assume, ten days, two weeks.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;It seems reasonable, if we submit our aid distribution plan within ten days, I assume two weeks would be enough for the U.N. secretariat and the Security Council to study it. That would add up to a month.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CRANS MONTANA, Switzerland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
