<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694520" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>JORDAN: Accused killer of Israelis mentally ill - family.</title>
<headline>Accused killer of Israelis mentally ill - family.</headline>
<dateline>MARJ AL-HAMAM, Jordan 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Relatives of a Jordanian soldier charged with premeditated murder of seven Israeli schoolgirls told a military court on Saturday he had a history of mental illness.</p>
<p>Kamila Daqamsa, mother of Private Ahmed Daqamsa who shot the girls at a border post in March, said her son was unstable, easily enraged, and had twice tried to kill himself after family arguments.</p>
<p>&quot;He has been to psychiatrists. He's ill,&quot; she said. &quot;When he is angered, he gets enraged.&quot;</p>
<p>Military psychologists have said Daqamsa suffered from an &quot;anti-social personality disorder&quot; which made him impulsive, but that he knew the difference between right and wrong and was not mentally ill.</p>
<p>Daqamsa's wife and sister-in-law told the court he had hit them both in fits of rage on separate occasions and his cousin Radi said he reacted violently to any provocation.</p>
<p>&quot;If anyone harrasses him he reacts in a way that he does not know what he is doing,&quot; Radi Daqamsa said. He said Daqamsa also sometimes blacked out under stress.</p>
<p>Daqamsa has said he was praying at Baqoura on the day of the shooting, when the Israeli girls started mimicking him and laughing at him. He said he went to his car, picked up his rifle, but could not recall what happened next.</p>
<p>Jordanian and Israeli witnesses said he fired off around 70 bullets from his automatic rifle at the group of Israelis, killing seven of them, aged 11 to 13.</p>
<p>Military prosecutors charged that Daqamsa plotted to kill Israelis for months ahead of the shooting and volunteered extra guard duties so he would have the chance to strike.</p>
<p>But his family said he never spoke about killing Jews.</p>
<p>They also refuted testimony from prosecution witnesses that Daqamsa was irreligious and obsessed by sex.</p>
<p>&quot;He prayed since he was a child. Sometimes he took the microphone to lead the prayers at the mosque,&quot; said Wael Salem, Daqamsa's neighbour from the village of Ibdr in north Jordan.</p>
<p>Daqamsa was stationed in Jordan's northern border territory of Baqoura, formally returned by Israel under a 1994 peace treaty but leased back to Israeli farmers.</p>
<p>The shooting of the Israelis and Daqamsa's subsequent trial has highlighted the deep divisions in Jordan over the accord.</p>
<p>King Hussein said Daqamsa had shamed Jordan's army and said he should have been shot dead on the spot. But opponents of the peace treaty with Israel have rallied to defend him.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JORDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MARJ AL-HAMAM, Jordan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JORDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
