<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694535" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Narrowing arb keeps lid on Brent movement to USG.</title>
<headline>Narrowing arb keeps lid on Brent movement to USG.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Brent/WTI spread narrowed on Friday keeping action in crude markets confined to the North Sea and away from the U.S. Gulf Coast at least until the arb widens a bit, traders said.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the arb needs to open up for trade to pick up. Meanwhile the (domestic) grades are going to keep getting stronger,&quot; said one trader referring to strength in both Light Lousiana Sweet/St James and in West Texas Sour/Midland grades.</p>
<p>The arb narrowed Friday by 3 cents to $1.29 a barrel, a level still out of the money for many players.</p>
<p>Also adding upward pressure to domestic grades and to the attractiveness of foreign grades other than Brent was the waiting game around the renewal of the UN-Iraq oil-for-deal.</p>
<p>Colombia's state-owned Ecopetrol, in a widely awaited move, was said to have unveiled on Friday a nine or 10-cargo loading program in August, depending on whether one counts the tenth cargo that loads in late August to early September.</p>
<p>While all the loading dates could not be confirmed, Total was said to have set the loading of its sole cargo for August 16-20, and to be looking hard at offering at the $1.00 under September WTI/Cushing fob price BP is thinking of as well.</p>
<p>The remaining nine cargoes were split between BP and Ecopetrol, with the Colombian company seen taking over half of them.</p>
<p>In other non-Brent foreign action, a West African cargo of Angolan Cabinda was said to have been sold on a delivered basis by an East Coast trader at around minus $1.40-$1.30 to August WTI/Cushing.</p>
<p>Also offers on Nigerian Qua Iboe crude continued to be heard on a delivered basis at around Dated Brent plus $1.82-$1.84 a barrel, traders said.</p>
<p>Additionally, Nigerian Bonny Light was said to be workable, if not actually offered, into the LOOP (Lousisiana Offshore Oil Port) at minus 10 cents to August WTI/Cushing or at around Dated Brent plus $1.61, traders said.</p>
<p>While there are not yet any clear signals Iraqi crude sales will not resume by the widely expected mid-to-late-July target range, some players are guessing the barrels won't arrive that soon, which would have bullish effects on prices.</p>
<p>Brent offers, apparently benefiting from the tightness some say is now emerging at the Gulf Coast due to the tight Brent/WTI arb, were again heard as high as minus 25 cents to minus 20 cents to August WTI/Cushing, after unconfirmed rumors circulated earlier in the week that a Brent cargo was actually sold into the U.S. Gulf Coast at minus 35 cents to August WTI.</p>
<p>Some traders, expressing surprise at the duration of the lull in action that has befallen the market for foreign crudes into the U.S., said they were hoping something would break the ice soon.</p>
<p>&quot;This market is rangebound and something needs to give it a shot in the arm,&quot; said one trader.</p>
<p>-- Oliver Ludwig, New York Oil Desk +1 212 859 1633</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
