<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694560" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Renault to shut Belgian plant, embarrass govmt.</title>
<headline>Renault to shut Belgian plant, embarrass govmt.</headline>
<byline>Brian Love</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>French carmaker Renault decided on Saturday to shut down its Belgian assembly plant employing 3,000 workers by the end of the year, despite government criticism and trade union protests in Belgium, France and beyond.</p>
<p>The move is likely to embarrass France's new Socialist-led government, which swept to power on June 1 on promises to fight unemployment and promote greater solidarity on jobs in Europe.</p>
<p>Chairman Louis Schweitzer said following a board meeting to examine an independent report on possible alternatives that the closure of the Vilvoorde plant near Brussels would go ahead.</p>
<p>&quot;The chairman (Schweitzer) indicated that the procedure with a view to closing the plant in 1997 will be pursued,&quot; the company said.</p>
<p>The loss-making group caused a political storm on both sides of the border when it abruptly announced in February the closure of the plant. It later said it would make it conditional on the report into the viability of alternatives.</p>
<p>&quot;(The report) confirms that the problem addressed by the decision to close in 1997 is a structural one, and that reducing work hours at the site and other Renault assembly sites does not constitute an alternative,&quot; the company said.</p>
<p>A Renault spokeswoman said the July 31 closure date announced originally could be &quot;pushed back, perhaps to October&quot; but that the plant would be shut down this year.</p>
<p>Belgian Renault union leader Karl Gacoms, who waited outside the suburban Paris offices of Renault for the decision, said he was disappointed and that the workers felt left down by the new French government of Prime Minister Lionel Jospin.</p>
<p>&quot;We had hoped that a new Socialist government would take our side,&quot; Gacom told France Info radio.</p>
<p>&quot;Neither Schweitzer nor Jospin are off the hook with Renault staff, nor before French and European public opinion,&quot; the Communist-led CGT union said.</p>
<p>Renault ordered the independent report following a strike at Vilvoorde and sympathy stoppages at plants in France and Spain, as well as criticism from Belgian political leaders, the former centre-right French government and the new left-wing government.</p>
<p>Jospin said in his maiden parliamentary speech on June 19 that he would review French law on company lay-offs in the wake of the Renault move.</p>
<p>Ex-Socialist party leader Henri Emmanuelli said after confirmation of the closure plan that he wanted the matter raised in the Socialist group at the National Assembly.</p>
<p>The decision was &quot;very bad news for the Vilvoorde employees, but also for all those who expect a different vision and action from the new (Socialist-led) coalition&quot;, he said in a statement.</p>
<p>The Renault CFDT union said the report drawn up within a few weeks by consultant Danielle Kaisergruber was flawed and had served as an &quot;alibi for the public authorities&quot;.</p>
<p>Renault is still 46 percent owned by the state, which has representatives on the board.</p>
<p>Renault said Schweitzer would continue talks with unions on a plan including financial compensation and offers of employment to Vilvoorde workers at other Renault factories in France.</p>
<p>Renault would also ensure some form of industrial activity was continued at Vilvoorde by Renault or other firms, creating &quot;around 400 jobs&quot;. It would also try to find a buyer willing to devote the site to automobile business.</p>
<p>The spokeswoman said 3,100 workers were concerned. Unions had been informed in previous meetings with Renault management that it would be possible to offer 272 jobs in French factories to Vilvoorde employees -- 210 workers' jobs and 62 office posts.</p>
<p>There were also tentative offers from firms in Belgium and Luxembourg which could employ 230 Vilvoorde workers, she said.</p>
<p>The Vilvoorde plant assembles the popular Renault Megane but the firm says the closure is part of an essential reorganisation of an assembly network which is more scattered and costly than those of European rivals.</p>
<p>Renault said in March it made a 1996 loss of 5.25 billion francs -- its first loss in 10 years -- including 3.91 billion francs put aside to pay for the Belgian withdrawal.</p>
<p>Industry sources said management at Renault's Belgian subsidiary would meet unions on Monday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
