<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694545" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Distant wildfires envelop Anchorage with smoke.</title>
<headline>Distant wildfires envelop Anchorage with smoke.</headline>
<byline>Yereth Rosen</byline>
<dateline>ANCHORAGE, Alaska 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Smoke from wildfires raging in the interior Alaska wilderness spread 300 miles southeast on Friday to envelop Anchorage in a blue haze.</p>
<p>The lightning-sparked fires, burning in the Innoko National Wildlife Refuge near Galena, had grown to more than 156,000 acres by Friday, said the Alaska Division of Forestry.</p>
<p>The fires, which started early this month and were not considered threats to communities or private property, were for the most part being allowed to burn on their own, said division spokesman Don Pitcher.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a natural situation,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The fires were located in areas designated for limited supression, Pitcher said.</p>
<p>Summer wildfires of similar sizes burn often in that part of interior Alaska, but winds do not usually carry the smoke as far away as the state's largest city, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Normally, it doesn't affect people in Anchorage,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The smoky haze, which blotted out views of Mount McKinley and other peaks, prompted Anchorage municipal officials to issue an air pollution health advisory late Friday.</p>
<p>Firefighters were doing limited work to control the Innoko Refuge blazes, protecting a fuel cache and an administrative cabin there, said Larry Vanderlinden, Alaska fire management coordinator for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.</p>
<p>The spead of smoke to Anchorage may spur more aggressive fire suppression, Vanderlinden said.</p>
<p>&quot;That will certainly be a factor in determining future actions on those fires out there,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But officials hope wind shifts will spare Anchorage and make further action unnecessary, he said.</p>
<p>Statewide, lightning strikes caused five new fires since Thursday, humans sparked another five new blazes and dry and warm weather caused several wildfires to grow, officials said.</p>
<p>In all, 43 wildfires were burning on Friday, and firefighters were deployed on 10 of them, the fire information centre said.</p>
<p>Statewide, 403 fires had burned 189,000 acres as of Friday, the fire information centre said.</p>
<p>The largest wildfires were sparked by lightning. But some blazes have been small and human-caused, sparked by escaped campfires or other accidents.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANCHORAGE, Alaska"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
