<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694563" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: OSCE envoy-West's troops must stay in Bosnia.</title>
<headline>OSCE envoy-West's troops must stay in Bosnia.</headline>
<dateline>CRANS MONTANA, Switzerland 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Europe's security envoy to Bosnia called on Saturday for a Western peacekeeping presence to stay in the divided country for the &quot;indefinite future&quot; to handle a potentially explosive situation.</p>
<p>&quot;The international community has to stay there for years to help stabilise the situation,&quot; said Robert Frowick, head of the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) mission to Bosnia.</p>
<p>&quot;Both civil and the military need to commit for the indefinite future. We have to commit to a significant number,&quot; he told a news conference during an international business forum in the Swiss mountain resort of Crans Montana.</p>
<p>&quot;These people were engaged in genocide. What happened in Sarajevo can happen again if we're not careful.&quot;</p>
<p>The 35,00-strong NATO-led peace force SFOR (Stabilisation Force) is due to leave in June 1998. It replaced the NATO-led Implementation Force which at its height had 60,000 troops.</p>
<p>Frowick, whose organisation is also overseeing Bosnia's local polls in September, said it was up to Western commanders to decide the size of a future force, but stressed that it had to be credible.</p>
<p>&quot;This force has to be able to fulfil a strategy of flexible response. I see no reason why the countries involved with the resources they have can't be brought to do this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;To be credible it has to be clear that it's backed up by air power and if need be by sea power with cruise missiles to meet any threat.&quot;</p>
<p>Frowick said the OSCE, whose mandate expires at the end of this year, could end up staying &quot;for years&quot; in Bosnia. &quot;There is no way the OSCE can leave that country in 1998,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the single biggest obstacle to the success of the U.S.-brokered Dayton peace accord that ended the 1992-1995 war was the the lack of political will to arrest leading suspects indicted by the U.N. criminal tribunal for former Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>&quot;According to the rules of the game that we have now, the parties are supposed to have their police go arrest them. But this is a complete illusion. Something needs to be done -- an international police effort of some kind,&quot; Frowick said.</p>
<p>&quot;The viability of the peace process depends on bringing war criminals to justice. As long as they stay there, there will be ultra-nationalism undermining the peace process.&quot;</p>
<p>The NATO troops have refused to round up war crimes suspects who continue to work in positions of power.</p>
<p>The two most prominent suspects, former Bosnian Serb president Radovan Karadzic and former Bosnian Serb military commander Ratko Mladic, still remain at large.</p>
<p>The United States, Britain, France and other troop-contributing countries have been urged to arrest indicted war criminals, and have considered sending in &quot;snatch squads&quot;, but they fear this could cause security problems for their troops.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CRANS MONTANA, Switzerland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
