<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694559" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: FOCUS - Italy hails huge Eni share sale.</title>
<headline>FOCUS - Italy hails huge Eni share sale.</headline>
<byline>Crispian Balmer</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italy will make up to 13.3 trillion lire ($7.8 billion) from the third tranche sale of shares in energy giant Eni after one of the biggest global offers ever seen, Treasury Minister Carlo Azeglio Ciampi said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Ciampi told a news conference that the placement, which closed on Friday, had been three times oversubscribed. He added that the Treasury now expected to reduce its holding in Eni to 51.5 percent from the current 69.1 percent.</p>
<p>Italy originally intended to cut its stake to 54.6 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;The sale has been an extraordinary success,&quot; Ciampi said.</p>
<p>Some 830,000 Italian retail investors signed up for Eni shares and there was also huge interest from institutional investors around the world.</p>
<p>&quot;This is one of the biggest (sell-off) operations ever carried out in the world,&quot; Treasury Director General Mario Draghi told the news conference.</p>
<p>Given the demand, additional stock will be offered to the institutions under a so-called greenshoe option, which if accepted, will cut the Treasury stake to the 51.5 percent level.</p>
<p>Treasury officials said they fully expected the extra shares to be snapped up by investors hungry for a stake in one Italy's most successful companies, which has posted consistently stronger profits over recent years.</p>
<p>Ciampi said the sale price had been pegged at 9,288 lire per share for the small retail investors, while institutional investors will pay 9,575 lire -- Eni's closing price on the Milan bourse on Friday.</p>
<p>Some 858 million Eni shares have been earmarked for retail investors in Italy, while institutional investors at home and abroad will receive 407 million shares with a further 143 million being offered under the greenshoe option.</p>
<p>A director at one of the two global coordinators for the sale said demand from the United States and Italy had been especially strong and had helped generate interest elsewhere.</p>
<p>&quot;By now, Eni has established itself as one of the world's most important oil and gas companies,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Rome-based group, which is Italy's largest company by market capitalisation and is headed by Franco Bernabei, chalked up a record net profit of 4.45 trillion lire in 1996 and has promised further profit growth for 1997.</p>
<p>The government launched the Eni privatisation in 1995, placing 15 percent of the company on the market at a price of 5,250 lire per share. In 1996, a further 16 percent was sold off at 6,910 lire per share.</p>
<p>The share has risen sharply over the past year and in the last two weeks alone it has gained 10 percent on the back of a bull-market which coincided perfectly with the sale.</p>
<p>The big success of the third tranche sale has come as a relief for the Treasury, which has struggled to shift its privatisation programme into first gear in the face of political manoeuvrings and often limited investor interest.</p>
<p>Later this year Italy plans to sell a chunk of telecoms group Stet, in an operation which has for long been dubbed 'the mother of all privatisations'.</p>
<p>It is also poised to put motorway operator Autostrade on the market and a fourth Eni tranche is widely expected sometime next year.</p>
<p>Ciampi said he did not want to meet all the demand for Eni shares given that further Italian sell-offs were on the way.</p>
<p>&quot;One shouldn't satisfy the market with every last drop of water it asks for,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>But even without giving the investors all they wanted, the Treasury has still managed to exceed its target for privatisation proceeds in one operation.</p>
<p>In its 1997 budget, the Treasury predicted that it would raise just 10 trillion lire this year from privatisations.</p>
<p>All the cash from the Eni offer will go into a special fund used to cut Italy's mammoth debt mountain. $1 = 1,700 lire</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I72300">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C171">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
