<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694514" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Resignations boost Yilmaz's Turkey government bid.</title>
<headline>Resignations boost Yilmaz's Turkey government bid.</headline>
<byline>Servet Yildirim</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime minister designate Mesut Yilmaz's hope of winning a confidence vote for his secularist coalition has been boosted by resignations from Turkey's Islamist-led government parties.</p>
<p>&quot;Confidence vote has been secured&quot; the mass- circulation Hurriyet headlined after five MPs quit the ruling Islamist-led coalition on Friday.</p>
<p>Two more MPs from deputy Prime Minister Tansu Ciller's True Path Party (DYP) resigned on Saturday, reducing the Islamists and their allies to 272 MPs on paper. This compares with 274 deputies who are likely to support Motherland Party (ANAP) leader Yilmaz's left-right coalition.</p>
<p>Haluk Muftuler, who abandoned the DYP earlier this week, and Ali Duyar, who resigned on Saturday, joined the Motherland, Anatolian news agency said.</p>
<p>Ciller claimed that Yilmaz would fail to get a vote of confidence from the assembly.</p>
<p>&quot;This government cannot get a vote of confidence. It is not possible to maintain it even if it gets a confidence vote,&quot; Ciller told reporters hours after the resignations.</p>
<p>Political analysts say more MPs are expected to join the resignation wave as Yilmaz intensified his efforts to replace care-taker Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan, who resigned after a stormy year as modern Turkey's first Islamist premier.</p>
<p>A three-party commission, including members of ANAP, the Democratic Left Party (DSP) and right-wing Democratic Turkey Party (DTP), met on Saturday to draw up the new government's programme.</p>
<p>Murat Basesgioglu, a senior ANAP deputy, said the commission would conclude the programme by Tuesday. Yilmaz is expected to present the new cabinet list to President Suleyman Demirel next week.</p>
<p>The confidence vote is due within two weeks.</p>
<p>The Motherland now has 132 seats in the 550-member assembly. Yilmaz's possible coalition partner DSP controls 67 and DTP 11 seats. The 49-member left-wing Republican People's Party has pledged support for Yilmaz but said it would not take part in his government.</p>
<p>ANAP sources say 15 of the 18 independent deputies would back Yilmaz in the confidence vote. Two of those who resigned who joined the far-right Nationalist Action Party on Friday are expected to remain neutral or support Yilmaz.</p>
<p>Two seats are empty in the assembly in which the anti-Yilmaz front controls 272 seats -- 154 RP, 107 DYP, eight from the far-right Grand Unity Party and three independent MPs.</p>
<p>The parliament speaker Mustafa Kalemli, an MP from ANAP, does not vote.</p>
<p>The wave of resignations came shortly after Erbakan and his allies presented a petition against Yilmaz, signed by a majority of deputies, to Demirel on Wednesday as part of a move to urge Yilmaz to return the mandate.</p>
<p>Demirel described the move on Saturday as undemocratic and unconstitutional.</p>
<p>Around a fifth of the True Path's deputies have quit since Ciller, under pressure from corruption charges, dropped strong criticism of the Islamists and joined Erbakan in government last year.</p>
<p>Businessmen, labour unions and bankers have expressed their support for Yilmaz, a free-market conservative.</p>
<p>They say pro-western Yilmaz, 50, may take the necessary measures to solve chronic economic problems and reduce the political tension.</p>
<p>These tensions have been aggravated by frequent rows with secularists, led by the army, over the role of religion in public life and NATO-member Turkey's ties to the Moslem world.</p>
<p>&quot;We are ready to give full support if the new government seeks to solve the major economic problems. We will be its soldiers,&quot; Mehmet Yildirim, head of Istanbul's Chamber of Commerce, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Husamettin Kavi, chairman of the Istanbul Chamber of Industry, said the new government would face severe economic problems, inherited from Erbakan's coalition.</p>
<p>The troubled Turkish economy has been struggling with high annual inflation, running at around 75 percent, and a huge public deficit, at over nine percent of the country's gross domestic product.</p>
<p>Istanbul shares jumped by more than six percent on Friday on rising hopes that Yilmaz would form the new government.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
