<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694554" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Oklahoma ethics panel votes to take governor to court.</title>
<headline>Oklahoma ethics panel votes to take governor to court.</headline>
<dateline>OKLAHOMA CITY 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Oklahoma's state ethics commission voted on Friday to take Gov. Frank Keating to court to face 32 civil charges of using state-owned cars and an airplane for political campaigning.</p>
<p>The commission alleged that Keating, a Republican, on 31 occasions used a state car to attend fundraising events for Republican candidates during Oklahoma's state legislative election campaign last year.</p>
<p>He also faces one charge of using a state-owned airplane for the same purposes, in violation of strict ethics rules introduced in 1995.</p>
<p>Keating said the State Ethics Commission's 4-1 vote to file charges against him was &quot;vindictive&quot; and that he hoped the issue would be quickly resolved in the courts.</p>
<p>&quot;That is irresponsible, silly and completely unjustified,&quot; Keating told reporters, adding that the state attorney general, a Democrat, has already sided with him on the issue of whether he is entitled to state transportation, security arrangements and communications even when campaigning.</p>
<p>All four Democrats on the ethics commission voted against the governor and the sole Republican, a Keating appointee, voted the other way.</p>
<p>If found guilty in court, Keating would only face a fine of $15,000 plus legal fees but the state's Democrat-dominated legislature could theoretically say the alleged rules violations are serious enough to warrant his impeachment.</p>
<p>Keating last week filed his own lawsuit against the ethics commission after learning he was under investigation. He says state law guarantees his right to transportation and security at all times, and said on Friday that state law should outweigh the rules of any commission.</p>
<p>&quot;To place me in a position to not have any contact in the event of a natural disaster, or a man-made disaster, or not have any communication with state agencies or officers, or not have any security is in my opinion beyond comprehension,&quot; he said on Friday.</p>
<p>Keating plans to run for re-election next year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OKLAHOMA CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
