<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694500" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israeli troops wound two Arabs in Hebron - witnesses.</title>
<headline>Israeli troops wound two Arabs in Hebron - witnesses.</headline>
<dateline>HEBRON, West Bank 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Israeli soldiers shot and wounded at least two Palestinians in clashes that erupted in Hebron on Saturday after anti-Moslem hate posters were glued to Arab shops in the divided West Bank city, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Dozens of protesters took the streets after Palestinian shopkeepers found posters depicting the Prophet Mohammad as a pig stamping on the holy Koran on about 20 storefronts near a Jewish settlement enclave. Islam and Judaism view pigs as unclean and ban the eating of pork.</p>
<p>Israeli police said a 25-year-old Jewish woman from Jerusalem had pasted the posters.</p>
<p>&quot;We arrested her after she threw a rock through the windshield of an Arab car in Hebron. Ten posters were found in her possession. She wanted to stir up trouble,&quot; a police spokesman said.</p>
<p>Along a confrontation line dividing the Palestinian and Israeli-controlled parts of the city, rock-throwing Arab demonstrators shouted &quot;the army of Mohammad will return&quot;.</p>
<p>At least two Palestinians were hit by rubber-coated metal bullets fired by Israeli troops and one was taken to hospital with a head wound, Arab witnesses said.</p>
<p>An Israeli army spokeswoman said she had no information about Palestinian wounded.</p>
<p>&quot;During the disturbances, rocks were thrown at Israeli soldiers but none was hurt. The security forces responded with anti-riot measures,&quot; she said, without elaborating.</p>
<p>The violence, which subsided by the evening, began with stone-throwing between Palestinian youths on the street and Israeli students on the rooftop of their Jewish seminary.</p>
<p>A Jewish teenager stood on top of a decorative arch on the roof and waved an Israeli flag. Palestinians took aim but their stones fell short.</p>
<p>Israel handed over most of Hebron to Palestinian self-rule in January but kept troops in about 20 percent of the city to guard some 400 Jewish settlers who live and study in fortified enclaves in the heart of the city of 100,000 Palestinians.</p>
<p>Israeli soldiers shot and wounded at least seven Palestinians in Hebron on Friday during clashes with Arab demonstrators.</p>
<p>The violence came against the backdrop of a freeze in Israeli-PLO peacemaking following Israel's groundbreaking in March on a new Jewish settlement in Arab East Jerusalem.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HEBRON, West Bank"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
