<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694580" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Second big merger hits Austrian banking sector.</title>
<headline>Second big merger hits Austrian banking sector.</headline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-06-27</dateline>
<text>
<p>Austria's overcrowded banking sector took another big step towards consolidation on Friday when savings bank Die Erste officially signed a merger deal with GiroCredit .</p>
<p>With combined assets of almost 670 billion schillings and a total of 360 branches across Austria, the two savings banks now form the country's second biggest banking group and rank among Europe's top 70 banks. The merger is expected to go through by September 30, Die Erste said.</p>
<p>The deal comes hot on the heels of the disputed acquisition by market leader Bank Austria in January of its rival Creditanstalt, which was expected at the time to trigger a wave of mergers in the sector.</p>
<p>Experts said the fusion would force other Austrian banks to seek partners to shore up their market position or risk being swept away by a tide of increased competition at the start of a single European currency.</p>
<p>In fact, while a raft of minor savings banks have joined forces, most of the larger ones have preferred to sit tight for the time being.</p>
<p>Austria's more than 4,000 bank branches serve on average only 1,300 people each, putting the country firmly at the bottom of the EU league in terms of branch efficiency.</p>
<p>Die Erste, also known as First Austrian, was part of an international consortium led by insurer EA-Generali which made an unsuccessful bid for the government's 70 percent stake of Creditanstalt-Bankverein ordinary voting shares.</p>
<p>Then in March Die Erste acquired a majority stake in Bank Austria's sister bank GiroCredit for 8.24 billion schillings.</p>
<p>The acquisition of the stake from Vienna City holding AVZ raised Die Erste's stake in GiroCredit to 82 percent of ordinary voting shares.</p>
<p>Earlier this month Moody's Investor Service said it would consider upgrading GiroCredit's A2 long-term deposit rating following the bank's announcement of plans for a merger with Die Erste.</p>
<p>Moody's said it may also downgrade Die Erste's long-term rating and its bank financial strength rating following the deal.</p>
<p>The Vienna bourse earlier today suspended trading in the shares of both banks until July 4, when Die Erste's supervisory bodies will decide further measures concerning the preferred shares, Die Erste said.</p>
<p>Ordinary shares of the two banks are not listed on the Vienna stock market.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81403">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-27"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
