<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694643" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada's Inco miners accept labor deal.</title>
<headline>Canada's Inco miners accept labor deal.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Union representatives said on Saturday that striking Inco Ltd miners in Sudbury voted 80 percent in favor of accepting the latest labor deal from the giant nickel miner to end a four-week strike.</p>
<p>&quot;The membership agreed that the bargaining committee did a good job to get this agreement, and now it's back to work. Some of the guys are going back to work tonight,&quot; said Larry Toner, an official of Local 6500 of the United Steelworkers of America.</p>
<p>Union leaders said the settlement met the demands of their members, who rejected an earlier tentative deal on June 2 and went on strike.</p>
<p>&quot;When the strike began, we set out four issues that had to be addressed in a settlement; wages, pensions, vacation pay (and) contracting out,&quot; said union chief negotiator Wayne Fraser. &quot;This proposed settlement delivers on every one.&quot;</p>
<p>Highlights of the agreement include an increase in pension benefits, an across-the-board wage increase, effective June 1, 1997, of C$0.56 (US$0.40) an hour, a nickel-price bonus projected to generate an average of C$1.25 (US$0.90) an hour over the life of the agreement, a rise in vacation bonuses and a rise in in sickness and accident coverage.</p>
<p>Inco has also said it will establish a special mine reconditioning crew of 18 miners, which will do work currently being done by contractors.</p>
<p>Inco's Ontario division president Jim Ashcroft said the settlement package included improvements to wages, vacation bonuses, pensions and terms for contracting out work that striking miners sought.</p>
<p>&quot;Our offer is fair and addresses the needs of both young employees and those nearing retirement,&quot; Ashcroft said. &quot;It is also vital to the division's competitive future and promises that the community of Sudbury will continue to benefit from a strong and competitive nickel industry.&quot;</p>
<p>The unionized Sudbury workers went on strike at midnight on June 2 after voting 60 percent against a previous contract offer endorsed by union leaders.</p>
<p>According to Inco's 1997 production plan, the Ontario division was expected to produce about 230 million pounds of nickel, 200 million pounds of copper and about four million pounds of cobalt this year.</p>
<p>Inco's Port Colborne, Ontario refinery, which processes cobalt, precious metals and electro-nickel, was unaffected by the Sudbury strike. Unionized workers at the refinery approved the contract on June 2.</p>
<p>Inco shares fell C$0.05 (US$0.03) to C$41.90 (US$30.35) on the Toronto Stock Exchange on Friday.</p>
<p>(Reuters Toronto Bureau, 416-941-8100)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
