<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694632" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>BANGLADESH: Bangladesh guards push back Burmese Moslems.</title>
<headline>Bangladesh guards push back Burmese Moslems.</headline>
<dateline>COX'S BAZAR, Bangladesh 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bangladeshi border guards have sent back over 1,000 Burmese Moslems who illegally crossed into Bangladesh in recent weeks, police said on Saturday.</p>
<p>They said over 400 &quot;Rohingya&quot; Moslems, inhabitants of west Burma's Arakan province, were arrested on Thursday when security forces raided their forest hideouts and put them on several boats across the Naf border river.</p>
<p>Over 500 Rohingyas were sent back earlier this month after they fled to Bangladesh's Cox's Bazar district, which borders Arakan, Burma's only Moslem-majority province.</p>
<p>The arrested Rohingyas told police and officials that the influx was triggered by rising food prices, unemployment, torture by security forces and forced labour.</p>
<p>Eight Rohingyas were drowned on Tuesday as they crossed the Naf river in an attempt to reach Bangladesh, police said.</p>
<p>The new influx began while some 21,500 Burmese Rohingyas were still huddled in two large camps, awaiting their return home after a long-running repatriation process was disrupted on May 1, officials said.</p>
<p>The officials blamed the suspension on delay by Burmese immigration authorities in giving clearance for the home-bound Rohingyas.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BANDH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="BURMA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COX'S BAZAR, Bangladesh"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BANGLADESH"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
