<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694621" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Pakistan rupee seen gradually losing value.</title>
<headline>Pakistan rupee seen gradually losing value.</headline>
<byline>Amir Zia</byline>
<dateline>KARACHI, Pakistan 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Pakistani rupee, adjusted downwards on Saturday, is likely to slide gradually in the next few months due to weak economic fundamentals and a strong dollar, analysts said.</p>
<p>The State (central) Bank of Pakistan (SBP) moved the rupee down to 40.4600/40.6623 to the dollar from 40.3900/40.5920 fixed on May 23. It did not explain its action.</p>
<p>Most bankers said it was a technical adjustment made necessary by the dollar's surge against most major currencies.</p>
<p>Some said the rate change had been expected as it was in line with the government's policy of periodically adjusting the rupee's value to keep Pakistani exports competitive.</p>
<p>The rupee has now lost 15.26 percent of its dollar value since the begining of fiscal 1996/97 (July-June), compared to a depreciation of 13.2 percent in the year-ago period.</p>
<p>It was the SBP's fourth depreciation since Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif's government came to power in February.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect a creeping downward adjustment of about 0.10 to 0.12 rupee against the dollar every month till December,&quot; one banker said.</p>
<p>The central bank has pursued a crawling peg depreciation policy to match the rupee to a basket of currencies.</p>
<p>Pervaiz Shahbaz, a foreign exchange dealer at Banque IndoSuez, said depreciation was inevitable because of Pakistan's economic woes.</p>
<p>&quot;When you have inflation running at 11 to 12 percent, then a one percent devaluation becomes necessary every month,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But he said minor technical depreciation of the rupee would not help to stimulate exports or make them more competitive.</p>
<p>&quot;Past experience shows it has not helped because to boost exports, the product's quality is a must, not just its price.&quot;</p>
<p>Pakistan's trade deficit soared to $254 million in May compared $148 million in the corresponding period a year ago.</p>
<p>Bankers said the rupee's slide was no surprise in view to the widening trade gap and a rising dollar.</p>
<p>Abdullah Ahmed of Bank of America said Finance Minister Sartaj Aziz was fulfilling his promise that there would be no major devaluation till September.</p>
<p>&quot;The government will go for a gradual depreciation of the rupee and we see at least a five percent devaluation of the Pakistani currency in the coming months because the economy has not improved, nor has the growing trade deficit been checked.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;All the banks are running long dollar positions to hedge against rupee depreciation,&quot; he said, adding that depreciation was the government's handiest weapon in its export drive.</p>
<p>Shahbaz said the government would be reluctant to order a sharp devaluation because of its harsh social consequences.</p>
<p>&quot;Pakistan is an import-oriented country and prices of daily commodities would soar, which would be a highly unpopular step for the government,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bankers said the IMF wanted the government to maintain a realistic rupee exchange rate, making it likely that small downward adjustments would continue.</p>
<p>An International Monetary Fund mission is expected in Islamabad early next month to start talks on a new medium-term loan from the IMF's enhanced structural adjustment facility.</p>
<p>Owais Kalia, a money changer, said the rupee would remain under pressure in the kerb market on fears that the SBP would keep depreciating it. &quot;But in the near term, the dollar could take a dip on profit-taking,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>($1 = 40.56 rupees)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARACHI, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
