<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694616" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: At least five Kashmiri militants killed in clash.</title>
<headline>At least five Kashmiri militants killed in clash.</headline>
<dateline>SRINAGAR, India 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>At least five separatist guerrillas were killed on Saturday in a gunbattle with Indian security forces near the Pakistani border in India's troubled state of Jammu and Kashmir, a defence spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;Army soldiers laid ambush to a group of militants who inflitrated from Pakistan. In the encounter, which lasted for several hours near Rangwar Gali of Kupwara district, at least five militants were killed,&quot; the Indian spokesman said.</p>
<p>Rangwar Gali lies in the forests of Kupwara district, 85 kms (55 miles), north of state's summer capital Srinagar.</p>
<p>A large quantity of arms and ammunition was recovered, he added.</p>
<p>It was the fourth major clash in the dense forests of Kupwara near the border this month.</p>
<p>Over a dozen militant groups are fighting New Delhi's rule in Jammu and Kashmir, India's only Moslem majority state.</p>
<p>India accuses Pakistan of arming Kashmiri militants, but Islamabad says it only provides political and diplomatic support to separatists.</p>
<p>Police and hospitals say more than 20,000 people have been killed in seven-year-old rebllion. Abdullah says the toll is nearer to 50,000.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SRINAGAR, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
