<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694605" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India hopes to play host to 5 mln tourists by 2000.</title>
<headline>India hopes to play host to 5 mln tourists by 2000.</headline>
<byline>Sunil Kataria</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>India intends to give a strong boost to its tourist trade by the turn of the century, Tourism Minister Srikanta Kumar Jena said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;We plan to double the number of foreign tourists from the 2.3 million in 1996/97 (April-March) to more than five million by the year 2000,&quot; he told reporters in a briefing on a draft of national tourism policy.</p>
<p>Ministry officials said the government proposed meeting the target by removing visa restrictions, cutting red tape for the inbound travellers and by giving bilateral and unilateral concessions to certain countries.</p>
<p>The minister said that tourism was India's single biggest foreign exchange earner in the year 1996/97 (April-March), bringing in $3.1 billion.</p>
<p>&quot;We plan to cater to the middle-income traveller, and encourage smaller hotels, motels and roadside facilities,&quot; Jena said.</p>
<p>Domestic tourism was also a big force that needs to be addressed with better facilities, the minister said. In 1996/97, there were about 141 million domestic tourists.</p>
<p>M.P. Bezbaruah, secretary of the department of tourism, said the improvement of the existing facilities and better marketing would enable the department to meet some of its targets.</p>
<p>&quot;Image building of India is one major exercise that we are focusing on,&quot; Bezbaruah said.</p>
<p>Foreign tourists and tour operators say India's weak infrastructure puts a huge bottleneck in the development of country as a major tourist destination.</p>
<p>India's current share in the world tourist traffic is less than 0.4 percent, a Tourism Ministry paper said.</p>
<p>&quot;Considering the dimensions of the country and the multitude of attractions it possesses, the potential of India in attracting international tourists is yet to be realised,&quot; the ministry said in its study draft.</p>
<p>Jena said he welcomed the entry of foreign capital in the sector. &quot;Multinationals are welcome to come and invest in the infrastructure, build hotels and make roads,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He said the ministry, in its estimates, submitted to the Planning Commission, had said the country needs nearly 480 billion rupees in the next five year plan (1997-2002) to spruce up its creaking tourism-related infrastructure.</p>
<p>&quot;Investment in aviation, roads, railways, ports and accommodation will facilitate tourist traffic,&quot; the minister said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
