<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694619" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian police hunt militants after raid.</title>
<headline>Indian police hunt militants after raid.</headline>
<dateline>JAMMU, India 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian security forces have launched a large-scale search for suspected Kashmir militants who held nearly two dozen people captive for a day before releasing them in exchange for money, authorities said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Three armed guerrillas forced 23 villagers to pay 500 rupees ($14) each for their freedom after being held for 14 hours on June 23 in the region straddling Jammu and Kashmir state and Himachal Pradesh province, they said.</p>
<p>Tarun Kapoor, commissioner of Chamba district in Himachal Pradesh, told Reuters that the villagers were gathering medicinal herbs in the heavily wooded border area between the two states when they were taken captive by three separatist militants.</p>
<p>&quot;They said, 'We are poor, why are you doing this to us?'&quot; Kapoor said. &quot;The militants said, 'We, too, have to survive.' It was more like extortion than kidnapping.&quot;</p>
<p>Dozens of guerrilla groups are fighting Indian rule in Jammu and Kashmir state. Some of them operate in the Jammu region in the southern part of the state, and the militants who held the villagers this week were from Doda district in Jammu, Kapoor said.</p>
<p>Kapoor said a special battalion of 500-odd armed Himachal Pradesh police had been moved closer to the area. &quot;We're stepping up patrols and telling people not to go there,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Police in Doda were cooperating.</p>
<p>&quot;A massive joint combing operation has been launched since yesterday to weed out the presence of militants in the area,&quot; said Kuldeep Khuda, inspector general of police in the Jammu region.</p>
<p>Kapoor said officials feared militant groups might step up efforts to find new recruits among Moslems in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
<p>Jammu and Kashmir is mostly Hindu India's only Moslem majority state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAMMU, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
