<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694606" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Hong Kong could go way of Tibet - Dalai Lama.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong could go way of Tibet - Dalai Lama.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>The office of Tibet's spiritual leader, the Dalai Lama, predicted on Saturday that China would violate human rights and trample democracy once it regains control of Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;In Hong Kong, human rights and democracy will be the first casualty of reunification with China,&quot; the Dalai Lama's office in the Indian capital said in a 15-page statement on Hong Kong's reversion to China at midnight on June 30.</p>
<p>The statement said Chinese rulers could not be trusted to keep their promises to ensure a high degree of autonomy for Hong Kong under an arrangement called &quot;one country, two systems&quot;.</p>
<p>It said &quot;one can't help wondering if China can be trusted to adhere to any agreement which does not serve its purpose,&quot; accusing Beijing of violating a 1951 accord which it said promised the same one-country, two-systems formula for Tibet.</p>
<p>The Dalai Lama, Tibet's spiritual leader, fled his homeland to India in 1959 after an abortive uprising against Chinese rule. Currently over 100,000 Tibetans live in exile in India.</p>
<p>Tibet and China signed a 17-point agreement in 1951 that promised to leave Tibet's political, cultural and religious system unchanged by communist reforms.</p>
<p>But the Dalai Lama's office said China violated &quot;each and every provision of the agreement that was favourable to Tibet&quot;.</p>
<p>It said China had proposed a similar agreement with Taiwan, but the Taiwanese rejected it. The statement said &quot;the people of Hong Kong would do well to understand the Taiwanese fear&quot;.</p>
<p>It said &quot;the Tibetan experience with the 17-point agreement does not give the people of Hong Kong much cause for optimism. As it is, China has already started interfering politically in the economic life of the territory&quot;.</p>
<p>The statement said China would replace Hong Kong's democratically-elected legislature with one dominated by handpicked nominees.</p>
<p>It said Hong Kong's future chief executive, Tung Chee-hwa, &quot;has alluded that human rights and democracy activists will find the going tough under the new masters&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;His (Tung's) proposals for legal reforms provide for the curtailment of democratic rights and civil liberties in the territory,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The statement said China did not have a history of tolerating dissent and criticism. &quot;Is it, therefore, any wonder that fears for a Tiananmen Square-type massacre persist despite the assurance of Tung-Chee-hwa to the contrary?&quot;</p>
<p>It was referring to the crackdown against pro-democracy demonstrators in Beijing's Tiananmen Square in 1989.</p>
<p>Hong Kong will be the litmus test for China's willingness to allow the devolution of power, the statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;If Chinese leadership could demonstrate the necessary vision and wisdom, it will undoubtedly open up better prospects for resolving outstanding problems like Tibet,&quot; it said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
