<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694651" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Gulf Air, Kuwait Airways told to sell stakes in Je.</title>
<headline>Gulf Air, Kuwait Airways told to sell stakes in Je.</headline>
<byline>Sabyasachi Mitra</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's Civil Aviation Ministry has given Gulf Air and Kuwait Airways until October 15 to sell their 20-percent stakes in private Indian carrier Jet Airways, a Jet spokesman said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;We have been given time by the Civil Aviation Ministry till October 15 to disinvest,&quot; a Jet Airways spokesman told Reuters.</p>
<p>The cabinet in April barred foreign airlines from holding equity stakes in the domestic aviation sector. The policy effectively scuttled a proposed $600-million tie-up between Singapore Airlines Ltd and India's Tata group.</p>
<p>The cabinet also upheld a rule limiting foreign firms which are not airlines to 40 percent equity stakes in domestic airlines.</p>
<p>&quot;The process has already started. The board has already decided to disinvest 40 percent foreign equity,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Gulf Air and Kuwait Airways each own a 20-percent stake in Jet Airways and are the only foreign airlines with equity stakes in an Indian carrier.</p>
<p>Asked who will buy the stakes owned by the two foreign airlines, the spokesman said: &quot;That process is not known at the moment.&quot; There was no estimate of the value of the stakes.</p>
<p>India's Civil Aviation Ministry has recently come under attack from investors for its flip-flop stance on key policy issues.</p>
<p>&quot;Even now it is not a clear and lucid policy,&quot; H.K. Malik, an aviation analyst, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Local newspapers reported last week that the Civil Aviation Ministry was considering a review of the policy announced in April.</p>
<p>The main opposition Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party on Thursday attacked the government for a plan that envisaged foreign airlines taking equity in domestic carriers.</p>
<p>But a Civil Aviation Ministry spokeswoman on Saturday denied the newspaper reports and allegations by the BJP.</p>
<p>There is no rethinking in the government on the recent cabinet decision barring foreign airlines from holding equity stakes in the domestic aviation sector, the spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>&quot;All reports to this effect appearing in a section of the press appear to be in the nature of kite flying,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>-- New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KUWAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
