<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694607" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Opposition planes bomb northern Afghan city.</title>
<headline>Opposition planes bomb northern Afghan city.</headline>
<dateline>ISLAMABAD 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>Opposition jets staged two bombing raids on the Taleban-held city of Kunduz in northern Afghanistan on Saturday, a Pakistan-based Afghan news service said.</p>
<p>The Afghan Islamic Press (AIP) said it had no immediate word on casualties or damage from the air strikes.</p>
<p>It quoted Taleban sources as saying its forces in Kunduz had beaten back five opposition ground attacks in the past four days, capturing 218 fighters and four of their commanders.</p>
<p>The Taleban sources said at least 16 opposition guerrillas had been killed and 50 wounded in the battles, while 11 Taleban fighters had been killed.</p>
<p>Opposition spokesmen could not be contacted for comment and no independent account of the fighting was available.</p>
<p>Dr Abdullah (one name), an aide to ethnic Tajik opposition commander Ahmad Shah Masood, said on Thursday that the Taleban forces in Kunduz must surrender or fight.</p>
<p>&quot;Our groups are stationed close to Kunduz and if the Taleban and their allies don't leave the area...then we will be forced to take it by military means,&quot; Abdullah said.</p>
<p>He said Masood, whose forces are loyal to ousted president Burhanuddin Rabbani, could not tolerate the Taleban's presence in Kunduz, which fell to the purist Islamic militia last week after a local opposition commander, Arif Khan, switched sides.</p>
<p>Abdullah had said talks were under way with Khan to persuade him to hand over Taleban fighters, who had come to Kunduz from Baghlan province further south.</p>
<p>The Taleban, who seized Kabul in September, are trying to impose strict Islamic rule throughout Afghanistan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AFGH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISLAMABAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
