<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="694613" id="root" date="1997-06-28" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian Oil corp set for well-oiled growth.</title>
<headline>Indian Oil corp set for well-oiled growth.</headline>
<byline>Sunil Kataria</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-06-28</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's biggest refiner, Indian Oil Corporation Ltd (IOC) is poised for smooth growth in coming years, analysts said on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;According to our forecast, Indian Oil's profits should rise by 16 percent in the year to March 1998 and 26 percent in the year to March 1999,&quot; said P. Dhileepan, an analyst with Natwest Markets in Bombay.</p>
<p>The IOC said in a statement on Saturday that its 1996/97 (April-March) net profit rose to 14.08 billion rupees ($393.3 million), or 12.7 percent, from last years' 12.49 billion rupees.</p>
<p>But anaylsts predicted even better profits in 1997/98 and 1998/99.</p>
<p>&quot;The year to March 1999 will be particularly strong because of the commencement of the Panipat Refinery,&quot; Dhileepan said.</p>
<p>IOC's 6.0 million tonne refinery at Panipat in the northern state of Haryana is slated for commissioning in 1998. It had previously been expected to start up by August 1997, a company statement said.</p>
<p>A 3.0 million tonne refinery in the northeastern state of Assam, is expected to be operational by 1998/99.</p>
<p>The company sold 41.97 million tonnes of petroleum products in 1996/97, an increase of 5.3 percent over the previous year.</p>
<p>The statement quoted IOC Chairman M.A. Pathan as saying: &quot;Projects worth 100 billion rupees are under implementation and schemes of about 300 billion rupees have been identified for implementation during the ninth plan (1997-2002).&quot;</p>
<p>IOC's other projects under various stages of implementation include the Haldia-Barauni crude oil pipeline, matching secondary processing facilities at Mathura, and a 3.0 million tonne expansion of the Gujarat refinery.</p>
<p>&quot;A 9.0 million tonnes grassroots refinery is proposed to be set up in collaboration with Kuwait Petroleum Corporation at Paradeep on the east-cost,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>The company also plans to set up four diesel hydro-desulphurisation units at the Gujarat, Haldia, Mathura and Panipat refineries.</p>
<p>The company said its net interest cost had gone up to 3.10 billion rupees in 1996/97 from 1.49 billion in 1995/96 because of increased borrowings to meet a shortfall due to funds blocked with the Oil Coordination committees.</p>
<p>Analysts said a rise in interest costs was expected by the market and it would continue if the oil pool was not raised.</p>
<p>The ruling United Front coalition is set to meet on July 2 to take a decision on whether to raise prices to plug the government's mounting debt to state oil companies, estimated at 155 billion rupees ($4.3 billion) at the end of March.</p>
<p>Dhileepan said the Indian Oil Corporation would be a major beneficiary if the government totally deregulated the oil sector by the year 2000.</p>
<p>But another analyst, who did not want to be named, with a leading Franco-American investment house said the company would benefit in the short run only. &quot;The company will benefit from deregulation in the initial few years but after 10 to 15 years things might change with some of the biggest names coming in.&quot;</p>
<p>Currently, a multitude of price and distribution controls place the Indian oil industry in a tightly regulated position.</p>
<p>The Indian government holds 91 percent of IOC's equity, employees have 5.02 percent and financial institutions and others hold the remaining stock, an official said.</p>
<p>IOC is India's sole importer of crude oil and refined products. It is listed among Fortune 500 companies. ($1 = 35.8 rupees)</p>
<p>-- New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-06-28"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-06-28"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
