<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="709576" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Centennial Technologies' case leads SEC to U.K.</title>
<headline>Centennial Technologies' case leads SEC to U.K.</headline>
<dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
<text>
<p>A British court Monday froze the assets of a shell company allegedly used by the former head of Centennial Technologies Inc. for insider trading, the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission said.</p>
<p>Deputy Baliff Francis Hamon of the Royal Court of Jersey in the Channel Islands ordered $965,000 in assets of Felix Inc., an offshore corporation headquartered in Jersey, frozen after the SEC filed its complaint with the court Friday.</p>
<p>The SEC, which regulates U.S. securities markets, charged in its complaint that Emanuel Pinez, the 58-year-old former chairman and chief executive officer of Centennial Technologies -- once the darling of Wall Street -- used Felix as a shell corporation to engage in illegal insider trading.</p>
<p>Pinez, in jail awaiting trial on insider trading and fraud charges in the United States, has had his assets frozen. But, according to the SEC, Felix holds about $965,000 from the sale of Centennial stock in early February.</p>
<p>Asked if Felix was used by any other investors, SEC counsel Linda Bridgman replied, &quot;No. He seems to be the only investor.&quot;</p>
<p>The SEC also alleged that the money was transferred from an account at Lehman Brothers Inc. to an account at Hill Samuel Bank Ltd. in Jersey, Channel Islands, despite a U.S. judge's order barring any transfers.</p>
<p>The bank was ordered not to allow any transfers or any disposition of Felix's funds without prior written consent from the SEC.</p>
<p>Pinez is accused of inflating the revenues of the Billerica, Mass.-based maker of computer memory cards by booking phony sales that he secretly financed himself. Knowing the financial reports were false, he then allegedly bought and sold stock options to benefit from a decline in the company's stock price, according to U.S. court documents.</p>
<p>Centennial was 1996's biggest gainer on the New York Stock Exchange, zooming to $55.50 a share on Dec. 30, a gain of 447 percent. The exchange subsequently delisted Centennial less than three months later, after the charges against Pinez were filed.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
