<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="709583" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: American Home must pay university $45 mln.</title>
<headline>American Home must pay university $45 mln.</headline>
<dateline>DENVER 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A federal court judge on Monday ordered American Home Products Corp's American Cyanamid to pay the University of Colorado and others more than $45 million for defrauding them of a patent for a pre-natal multi-vitamin supplement.</p>
<p>The university, its non-profit foundation and two of its professors sued Cyanamid in 1993 claiming that the company took the professors' formula and patented it as its own.</p>
<p>The amount represents Cyanamid's actual and projected net sales of the vitamin &quot;Materna&quot; from 1981, when the fraud began, until 2001, when the patent expires, including $1 million for punitive damages, U.S. District Court Judge John Kane wrote in his decision.</p>
<p>Cyanimid, which merged several years ago with Home Products, had denied the claim and argued that its employees invented the formula.</p>
<p>The company had hired the two professors to reformulate the vitamin supplement because a competitor was claiming that &quot;Materna&quot; was an inferior product because the iron in the supplement could not be absorbed in patients as well as the competitor's product, Kane wrote in his decision.</p>
<p>Kane concluded that &quot;Cyanamid's fraud and concealment robbed plaintiffs of their valuable idea and allowed Cyanamid to obtain profits and market advantages (that) justice precludes it from retaining.&quot;</p>
<p>Home Products' attorney Roger Thomasch said neither he nor the company had read the judge's decision. He expected the company to comment on the lawsuit on Tuesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DENVER"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
