<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="709898" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: N.Irish Catholics demean Protestant accordionist.</title>
<headline>N.Irish Catholics demean Protestant accordionist.</headline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Rampaging Catholic youths bent on revenge in Northern Ireland's weekend violence forced a 17-year-old Protestant to parade around an Irish nationalist estate playing hymns on his accordion while they stoned him.</p>
<p>Northern Ireland's Ulster Television (UTV) interviewed the youth, his face blacked out for security reasons, as he recounted his ordeal on Sunday when Catholics protested against the routing of a Protestant march down a Catholic street.</p>
<p>He showed his tattered shirt covered in blood from the beating he took when a masked gang of five caught him in his car in a street in Newry, 40 miles (60 km) south of Belfast.</p>
<p>&quot;They beat me. Then they made me drive over to the other side and continued to beat me. Then they took my car and drove off,&quot; said the youth.</p>
<p>They probably wanted to ride it around for a while before torching it as youths did all over the province at the weekend to draw in security forces and then throw petrol bombs at them.</p>
<p>According to police figures, more than 200 vehicles were hijacked in Newry over the weekend in an orgy of violence that included the looting of the town's biggest supermarket.</p>
<p>But the gang opened the boot first.</p>
<p>The accordion was the give-away. It is an instrument often used by Protestant bands which accompany parades such as the Orange Order march which sparked the weekend violence.</p>
<p>Then they found the uniform which definitely labelled him a member of a Protestant marching band.</p>
<p>&quot;They came back and and took me to a nationalist estate and made we walk round the estate playing the accordion,&quot; the youth said. As they marched him there in front of the car, they clipped his heels with the front wheels from time to time.</p>
<p>He said he felt &quot;absolute fear.&quot;</p>
<p>All the while his fingers beat out gospel tunes and hymns including &quot;Nearer my God to thee&quot; while youths pelted him with bricks and stones.</p>
<p>The youth said he believed he was saved from further punishment because an army &quot;spy in the sky&quot; helicopter spotted the incident.</p>
<p>The youths fled. The accordion player needed stitches to a head wound.</p>
<p>His car has not been recovered.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
