<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="709880" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FOCUS-BA braces for strike, Blair keeps out.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-BA braces for strike, Blair keeps out.</headline>
<byline>Paul Keller</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Airways Plc on Monday kicked into action its contingency plan aimed at keeping the majority of its aircraft flying as a 72-hour strike by cabin crew, starting on Wednesday, looked almost certain to go ahead.</p>
<p>The strike threat later prompted British Prime Minister Tony Blair to say he had no intention of trying to mediate in the dispute between BA's management and some of its cabin crew over pay and conditions.</p>
<p>&quot;It's to be sorted out by those involved in it,&quot; a senior government official said.</p>
<p>Questions about a possible role for Blair were raised because he is a good friend of the airline's chief executive, Robert Ayling.</p>
<p>The Labour party, while building closer links with business, has also sought to distance itself from the unions, its historical paymasters.</p>
<p>Andrew Murray, a spokesman for the main union involved in the dispute, said on Monday: &quot;We are an independent union and BA is a private enterprise, we would not expect the government to get involved.&quot;</p>
<p>As union leaders urged more talks, a BA spokesman said he held out little hope for averting the strike after negotiation broke down on Sunday between BA and the cabin crews' Transport and General Workers' Union (T&amp;G).</p>
<p>&quot;The union seems determined to go ahead with this dispute...unless they're prepared to change their position fundamentally it seemed to us yesterday there was no point in continuing the dialogue because the gap was too wide,&quot; the BA spokesman said in an interview.</p>
<p>BA's chief executive Robert Ayling is pushing ahead with a plan to save one billion pounds ($1.7 billion) by the end of the century, but cuts have been opposed by the unions who attack Ayling's aggressive management style.</p>
<p>The strikes will be the first major industrial action under the new Labour government.</p>
<p>BA is also in dispute with ground staff over its plans to sell its catering division at London's Heathrow. Caterers will decide later this week on whether to accept management's proposals or to go ahead with strikes agreed last week in a ballot of union members.</p>
<p>The T&amp;G union told Reuters it was still ready to negotiate with BA but would call further cabin crew strikes if no agreement was reached. Talks were held on Sunday through the arbitration service ACAS.</p>
<p>&quot;We remain ready to talk. If (BA chief executive) Bob Ayling wants to end the confrontation all he has to do is pick up the phone but they have to be talks on the substance of the dispute,&quot; T&amp;G spokesman Murray said in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>BA said it has started putting its contingency plans in place with the result that only 20 percent of flights worldwide would not operate. BA was unable currently to estimate how much the strike would cost the airline.</p>
<p>&quot;Yesterday (Sunday) was a deadline for us and we made it clear that from then on we would have to start the programme of contingency,&quot; the BA spokesman said.</p>
<p>The worst-affected flights will be BA intercontinental services from London's Heathrow and Gatwick Airports and its European services out of Heathrow, BA said on Sunday.</p>
<p>The airline said in a statement that all its domestic and European flights from Gatwick would continue to operate as would international flights from regional airports in the United Kingdom. ($ = 0.591 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
