<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="709921" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Catholic anger scorches British N.Ireland.</title>
<headline>Catholic anger scorches British N.Ireland.</headline>
<byline>Martin Cowley</byline>
<dateline>LONDONDERRY, Northern Ireland 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Smoke billowed from a torched car in a nationalist stronghold on Monday as Catholic anger at Britain continued after a night of violence across Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>&quot;We are more polarised than ever,&quot; said a middle-aged man about the perennially fragile state of Protestant and Roman Catholic relations after the pro-British Orange Order was allowed to hold a parade in rural Portadown, triggering a wave of bitterness.</p>
<p>In Londonderry's Bogside, the crucible of a struggle 28 years ago for Catholic civil rights, people complained about Britain's use of stealth and strength on Sunday to ensure that &quot;Orangemen&quot; could parade through a Catholic zone of Portadown.</p>
<p>As motorists gingerly negotiated a chicane of burnt out hulks, a scene repeated in many towns in the British-ruled region, Catholics said the new Labour government had failed what they regarded as a test of sincerity over their rights.</p>
<p>They and others in Northern Ireland's minority had hoped that Labour would take a different attitude from the Conservatives, whom they ousted in a May election, about the contentious Protestant parade through Catholic districts.</p>
<p>Catholics say Protestants are marching to teach them who is master. Protestants say they have a right to unfettered free assembly on &quot;the Queen's highway&quot;.</p>
<p>British attempts to broker a compromise failed and before dawn on Sunday its security forces flooded into the Garvaghy Road enclave in Portadown, taking most Catholic residents off-guard.</p>
<p>&quot;The British exchanged one word for another in their election, Labour for Conservative -- but they're both the same,&quot; said a man in the Bogside.</p>
<p>&quot;At least the Conservatives sent in the police in daylight, when they could be seen by everyone, he declared. &quot;Labour -- the party of the working class -- waited until it was after dark.&quot;</p>
<p>Royal Ulster Constabulary commander Ronnie Flanagan, apologising to the Catholics, said he had given the go-ahead for operation.</p>
<p>He said he had feared that if the Orange march was not allowed to go ahead Protestant &quot;Loyalist&quot; guerrillas would have killed Catholics in retaliation.</p>
<p>But as IRA gunfire broke out overnight in riot zones, Catholic resentment continued unabated.</p>
<p>John Hume, the Catholic moderate nationalist leader, made fervent appeals for people to keep off the streets and for an end to violence. Two wrongs did not make a right, he said.</p>
<p>But in republican areas there were fears the IRA might crank up violence.</p>
<p>Residents said that Britain, by appearing in the eyes of nationalists to side with Protestants, had played into the hands of IRA commanders who had said no British government could be trusted.</p>
<p>&quot;The young turks are on the march,&quot; said an affluent moderate Catholic fearing more violence.</p>
<p>&quot;It looks like the IRA have got the ball at their feet now,&quot; said a old-time republican supporter.</p>
<p>&quot;It depends on how they jump. They could either start it up or they could draw back, and I would suspect that people would back them no matter what way.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDONDERRY, Northern Ireland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
