<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="709966" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Prosecutor seeks 10 years jail for Algeria FIS leader.</title>
<headline>Prosecutor seeks 10 years jail for Algeria FIS leader.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Abdelkader Hachani, who headed the Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) at the height of its power in 1991, went on trial on Monday in Algiers accused of trying to undermine state security, for which the prosecutor demanded 10 years' jail.</p>
<p>Appearing after five years in detention without trial, Hachani told a tightly-guarded Algiers criminal court that a FIS call for Algerian troops to disobey their officers and leave radical Moslem activists alone was aimed at avoiding &quot;confrontation&quot;.</p>
<p>Armed soldiers and gendarmes ringed the building in Abane Ramdane street, running parallel to the seafront, and traffic was diverted and the street blocked as the trial opened.</p>
<p>&quot;The aim of the appeal was to avoid confrontation and involvement of the ANP (army) in political struggles,&quot; Hachani said in a statement to the court reported by Algeria's official news agency APS.</p>
<p>It said Hachani was questioned at length by the judge, to whom he declared he had &quot;always worked within the law&quot; while he headed the FIS.</p>
<p>Hachani was arrested on January 22, 1992 after a statement in his name appeared in Al Khabar paper in the emotionally-charged days after the authorities had cancelled a general election in which the FIS had taken a massive lead.</p>
<p>APS said the court president told Hachani: &quot;The appeal was addressed to members of the ANP and not its command, which implies inciting disobedience and a denial of the public authorities' right to preserve public order in the event of trouble.&quot;</p>
<p>Late on Monday, the prosecutor-general asked the court to sentence Hachani to 10 years in prison and loss of civil rights.</p>
<p>Hachani's arrest -- in a police swoop in the south Algiers suburb of Badjarah -- came after the Defence Ministry accused him of &quot;launching an appeal for rebellion in the army&quot;.</p>
<p>A former oil engineer, Hachani led the FIS to its landslide first-round victory in Algeria's first multi-party general election in 1991. The next month the authorities cancelled the poll, sparking violence in which about 60,000 people have died.</p>
<p>In court, Hachani, now aged around 40, was represented by a legal team headed by Ali Yahia Abdennour and Mustapha Bouchachi.</p>
<p>In London, the human rights group Amnesty International said it had been refused permission by Algerian authorities to send observers to the trial.</p>
<p>Hachani, shortly after the 1992 cancellation of the election, forecast his arrest, saying: &quot;I know that in the next few days I could be jailed and I am prepared for that.&quot;</p>
<p>He has since been held in Sirkadji high security prison near the Casbah, the ancient heart of old Algiers. Soon after his arrest, the FIS was outlawed.</p>
<p>Viewed as a relative moderate who had urged FIS activists to avoid violence, he termed the cancellation of the poll &quot;a coup d'etat against the Islamic state&quot; which the FIS planned for the North African country and its 29 million people.</p>
<p>His party had won 188 of the 232 seats decided outright in the first round.</p>
<p>Hachani is being tried along with three journalists from Al Khabar. All are charged with publishing &quot;erroneous and tententious information likely to harm national interest and national unity.&quot;</p>
<p>The prosecutor asked for four years' imprisonment for the journalists, Al Khabar's director, editor and deputy editor.</p>
<p>Hachani took over the FIS leadership temporarily after party president Abassi Madani and his deputy Ali Belhadj were arrested, six months before the election. They were tried on charges of subversion and each sentenced in July 1992 to 12 years' jail.</p>
<p>Last week, the FIS executive in exile said in a statement that Hachani should be released: &quot;This would certainly contribute to an easing of tensions required to promote the necessary climate for a return to peace and stability.&quot;</p>
<p>Algeria last month held the first multi-party general election since the 1992 poll cancellation. Radical Islamists were barred but two moderate Islamist parties were allowed to take part. They won a total of 103 seats in the 380-seat National Assembly.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
