<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710050" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Four reported dead in Polish flooding.</title>
<headline>Four reported dead in Polish flooding.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four people have been killed  in floods in southern Poland, Polish TV reported on Monday, after days of heavy rain swelled some major rivers to danger levels.</p>
<p>The Polish cabinet held a crisis meeting to discuss the floods and Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz was leading an official delegation to observe developments in the worst affected provinces of Katowice, Walbrzych and Opole, government spokeswoman Aleksandra Jakubowska told a news conference.</p>
<p>The PAP news agency said some 400 people were evacuated in Opole province and over 120 houses were flooded in Katowice province.</p>
<p>Other reports from the affected areas told of many homes under threat, children evacuated from holiday camps, and underground gas, electricity and telecommunications facilities swamped in the Upper Silesia industrial area.</p>
<p>Army cadets, soldiers and police were being called in to reinforce fire brigades dealing with the emergencies.</p>
<p>Jakubowska said Czech officials, themselves battling floods, were emptying reservoirs into the Odra river which flows north into southwestern Poland.</p>
<p>&quot;On July 6 the Czech side began emptying retention reservoirs into the Odra, which has worsened the situation,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Police in the Czech Republic said a Vienna-Warsaw express train careered off a bridge and some of its cars plunged into floodwaters in the northeast on Monday, injuring at least 64 passengers.</p>
<p>The bridge had apparently been weakened by floods.</p>
<p>The incident occurred on the Odra river south of Ostrava, the third biggest Czech city.</p>
<p>The Czech news agency CTK said torrential rain since the weekend was believed to have caused six deaths -- two women and four men -- but it stressed no casualty report had been independently confirmed.</p>
<p>About one-third of Ostrava was inundated, Czech radio said.</p>
<p>A state of emergency was declared as road, railway, electricity, and telephone services were disrupted in many parts of the northeast and sources of drinking water tainted.</p>
<p>Officials issued appeals for potable water and emergency supplies as rivers kept rising.</p>
<p>Czechs marooned by flood waters had to scramble onto their rooftops in numerous towns and villages lining tributaries to the Opava and Morava rivers.</p>
<p>Forecasts throughout much of the region were for heavy rain through at least Tuesday, threatening low-lying regions including Ostrava and the city of Zlin further downstream.</p>
<p>Polish government spokeswoman Jakubowska gave no details of financial losses caused by the rain, but said special budget reserves totalling 300 million zlotys ($90 million) might not suffice to pay out possible compensation claims, and that some of the burden would have to be carried by insurers. ($ = 3.293 Polish Zlotys)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
