<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710066" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russian government says wages may have to wait.</title>
<headline>Russian government says wages may have to wait.</headline>
<byline>Philippa Fletcher</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's cash-strapped government told workers and soldiers on Monday they might have to wait up to six months to get all their back pay, twice as long as President Boris Yeltsin promised them last week.</p>
<p>While Yeltsin spent the first day of his summer holiday fishing in the wild northwestern Karelia region, his reformist protege Boris Nemtsov was preparing to report to him on how the government planned to net enough funds to pay the arrears.</p>
<p>&quot;Tomorrow we'll discuss this again with the president -- paying doctors, teachers, librarians, scientists, soldiers and officers,&quot; Interfax news agency quoted Nemtsov as saying in an interview with Russian Public Television.</p>
<p>Yeltsin, recognising the threat posed by the pent-up frustrations of the millions whose wages have been delayed for periods of up to six months over the past two years, last week gave the government three months to solve the problem.</p>
<p>But, in the first open disagreement between the Kremlin leader and the liberals leading his reshuffled government, First Deputy Anatoly Chubais told him not all the wage debts could be paid off by October 1.</p>
<p>Nemtsov did not elaborate on how the cabinet would raise the money to pay the wage arrears, built up through a combination of low tax collection, a web of inter-company debt and economic stagnation.</p>
<p>But he was quoted as saying that ministers, who had to shake down some powerful tax debtors to meet Yeltsin's July 1 target for overdue pensions, might have to move the wages deadline.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not want to be a dreamer and make unrealistic promises. I think that the time period must be realistic: if we can do this in five months -- we should do it in five, if we can do it in six -- we'll have to do it in six,&quot; Nemtsov said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's better not to lie,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>It was not clear whether the climbdown had been agreed with Yeltsin, who left for a state residence in Karelia on Sunday.</p>
<p>The 66-year-old Kremlin leader spent the first full day of his holiday touring the holiday complex and fishing on a lake. Nemtsov is due to fly to Karelia to meet him on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Boris Yeltsin looked around the covered tennis court built in time for his visit and hit a ball around with a racquet a few times,&quot; Itar-Tass news agency reported from the region.</p>
<p>Yelstin was a keen tennis player before he was struck down with serious heart disease last year, but he has not returned to the game despite his apparent recovery from a multiple heart bypass last November.</p>
<p>Since he returned to full-time work in February, he has injected a new vigour into foreign and domestic policy, which had drifted for months during his illness.</p>
<p>But the wage arrears are the biggest challenge yet.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it will be a real test for the authorities,&quot; Nemtsov said, adding that it was an extremely complicated and expensive task that would require mobilising the entire government and presidential apparatus.</p>
<p>Ministers have squeezed big tax debtors like gas monopoly Gazprom to raise new funds and say they are continuing to press companies to pay up. But the web of debts makes this difficult.</p>
<p>The government is also seeking other ways to raise funds, although the Kremlin press service denied a report that Yeltsin had said Russia would ask foreign governments for help.</p>
<p>In a sign that Moscow was cautiously confident that it would find ways to raise more revenues, Deputy Finance Minister Mikhail Kasyanov said it might not have to seek funds on international markets to fill the 1997 budget gap.</p>
<p>&quot;By the end of the year Russia might not issue any more bonds as the situation with tax collection is improving,&quot; Kasyanov, in charge of Russia's foreign debt, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Russia had planned to issue a fourth Eurobond this autumn.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
