<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710079" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Walesa says three new NATO states enough for now.</title>
<headline>Walesa says three new NATO states enough for now.</headline>
<dateline>GDANSK, Poland 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's former President Lech Walesa said on Monday that NATO expansion should be restricted for the moment to his own country, the Czech Republic and Hungary.</p>
<p>Walesa's comments backed U.S. President Bill Clinton's stance that only these three former Soviet bloc states should be invited to join at the alliance's Madrid summit starting on Tuesday.</p>
<p>However, France and other European states want Slovenia and Romania to be admitted too and the transatlantic dispute threatens to overshadow the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;I am for the enlargement of NATO, at the present stage, to include Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary,&quot; said Walesa, who founded Solidarity as the Soviet bloc's first free trade union in 1980.</p>
<p>As Polish president from 1990-1995, he doggedly campaigned for his own country's NATO entry.</p>
<p>&quot;I understand the fears of the West, especially Americans, that enlarging NATO by a greater number of countries will mean a need to increase the financial effort required for full integration,&quot; Walesa told reporters in his home city, Gdansk.</p>
<p>Walesa, who is to have a meeting on Thursday with Clinton when the U.S. President visits Warsaw to underline the significance of decisions made in Madrid, said further enlargement of NATO might unnecessarily alarm Russia.</p>
<p>&quot;To admit other countries (now) would mean the pact would become stronger and such a strengthened pact may be too powerful for third countries such as Russia, and may arouse fears and anxieties,&quot; said Walesa, who lost 1995 presidential elections to the ex-communist Aleksander Kwasniewski.</p>
<p>He said that once the three new members were in, if Russia was a partner cooperating with NATO, the pact would change its focus from the military to the political.</p>
<p>Walesa is keeping a low profile in politics before elections on September 21, but retains influence in the Solidarity Election Action (AWS), an alliance led by the trade union which hopes to win power from the ruling ex-communists.</p>
<p>Solidarity's current leader Marian Krzaklewski told reporters during a break in a conference in Gdansk that the AWS wanted other countries in NATO -- including Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia, whose admission is fiercely opposed by Russia.</p>
<p>&quot;The AWS is a supporter of a NATO enlarged by the Baltic states, Romania and Bulgaria,&quot; Krzaklewski said.</p>
<p>Krzaklewski called for the 1998 budget, now being drafted by the government, to show clearly that Poland can afford the costs associated with NATO entry such as army modernisation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GDANSK, Poland"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
