<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710120" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>LATVIA: Latvia urges clear NATO sign for Balts.</title>
<headline>Latvia urges clear NATO sign for Balts.</headline>
<dateline>RIGA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Latvian Foreign Minister Valdis Birkavs has sent a letter to NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana urging him to send a clear signal the alliance's doors would remain open for the Baltic states after the Madrid summit.</p>
<p>The historic summit is expected to invite the former Warsaw Pact states of Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic to join the Western alliance.</p>
<p>Slovenia and Romania have the backing of at least nine of the alliance's 16 members but Latvia and Baltic neighbours Lithuania and Estonia have been written out of the first wave of enlargement as Russia vehemently objects to their inclusion.</p>
<p>&quot;Foreign Minister Birkavs has sent a letter to General-General Solana outlining Latvia's position on NATO membership,&quot; the foreign ministry press spokesman said.</p>
<p>&quot;Latvia wants a very strong commitment from NATO at Madrid that its door will be open for the Baltic states,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We want it to be clearly spelt out that after Madrid, the enlargement process will continue, and will include Latvia and the other Baltic states,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Moscow has threatened to tear up its recent agreement with NATO if the Baltic states, which formed its Western flank during the Cold War and are home to large Russian minorities, are admitted into the alliance.</p>
<p>Birkavs' request to Solana was partly answered by a senior U.S. official on Sunday, who also said that the summit this week would send a very strong signal that the Baltic states were welcome to seek NATO membership in the future.</p>
<p>Western diplomats in the Baltics say the U.S. is sympathetic to the three nations' efforts to get NATO membership and reintegrate with the West but is not willing to jeopardise the fragile accord it has reached with Moscow on alliance expansion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LATV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="LITH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIGA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LATVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
