<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710116" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgarian reforms will lead to NATO - president.</title>
<headline>Bulgarian reforms will lead to NATO - president.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgarian President Petar Stoyanov said on Monday Bulgaria expected no miracles from the Madrid summit but was firmly on a path that would eventually lead to integration in NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not expecting miracles and we all know why,&quot; said Stoyanov in a national address on the eve of his departure for the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;While the current star pupils of the former Eastern Bloc chose the right way without a doubt, we spent years dithering in front of Europe's gates. Today we are making up lost time with a 'Bulgarian storm.'&quot;</p>
<p>The summit which opens on Tuesday is expected to invite the former Warsaw Pact states of Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic to join the Western alliance.</p>
<p>Stoyanov said he would remind the summit of his country's strategic position, its good relations with its neighbours and its role as a factor for Balkan stability.</p>
<p>&quot;Our intentions for European and Euro-Atlantic integration are very serious and the first obstacle will not stop us,&quot; he said. &quot;NATO's southern flank is not complete without Bulgaria.&quot;</p>
<p>The Socialist government, ousted from power by month-long street protests in January and February, had been ambivalent on NATO membership for fear of upsetting its traditional allies in Moscow.</p>
<p>The interim cabinet in February made a clear statement of Bulgaria's desire to join NATO, and the reformist government which took office in May reaffirmed this aim.</p>
<p>&quot;Bulgaria's aspiration to join NATO is not a fashionable infatuation but a strategic aim,&quot; said Stoyanov, who is due to meet U.S. President Bill Clinton on Tuesday afternoon.</p>
<p>&quot;The North Atlantic Treaty for us means not only reforms in the army, but democracy, a developed economy, a standard of living, free journalists, motivated young people and most of all a way of life which has been chosen on the eve of the 21st century.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
