<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710169" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: Losing bidder for Hungary TV channels to sue.</title>
<headline>Losing bidder for Hungary TV channels to sue.</headline>
<byline>Denes Albert</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The losing bidder for two new Hungarian commercial TV channels said on Monday it would challenge the Hungarian radio and television body's decision to award a concessions contract to Magyar RTL and MTM-SBS.</p>
<p>But Orszagos Radio es Televizio Testulet (ORTT) said on Monday the court challenge would not delay signing of the 10-year concession contracts with Luxembourg-based CLT's Magyar RTL and MTM-SBS.</p>
<p>&quot;ORTT will shortly sign the contracts with the winners,&quot; ORTT Chairman Mihaly Revesz told Reuters. ORTT announced the winners on June 30.</p>
<p>Loser Irisz TV, a consortium led by U.S.-based Central Media Enterprises with Hungarian companies, Mediacom, Intercom and DDTV Kft, said it challenged the decision and asked a court to forbid the signing of the concession contracts.</p>
<p>&quot;The ORTT seriously breached the regulations when assessing the bids and violated the tender procedures,&quot; Irisz TV said in a statement.</p>
<p>The CLT-led consortium, Magyar RTL, is owned by a consortium of CLT-UFA, Raiffeisen Unicbank, UK Pearson group, publisher of the Financial Times, and Hungarian telecom company Matav.</p>
<p>MTM-SBS is a consortium of the Hungarian-registered company MTM Kommunikacios Rt, TeleMunchen and majority U.S.-owned company Scandinavian Broadcasting System.</p>
<p>Magyar RTL offered 9 billion forints ($47.9 million) for the commercial channel it won, while MTM-SBS offered the set minimum of 8 billion forints for the other commercial channel.</p>
<p>Irisz TV offered 12.5 billion and 12 billion forints, respectively.</p>
<p>The eight-member ORTT board's first attempt to select the winners failed.</p>
<p>Opposition parties delegate five of the eight-person board, two are delegated by the ruling parties and the president is neutral.</p>
<p>During the second round, newspapers quoted an opposition member of the board talking about an expert's opinion that Irisz TV's business plan was not consistent with the higher price it offered.</p>
<p>But a conosrtium of four independent companies had earlier assessed the tenders and said all four offers were consistent with the business plans.</p>
<p>ORTT said at the time of the decision that one important factor in the decision was diversifying Hungary's future media scene. It said the verdict was unanimous aside from one abstention.</p>
<p>The decision ended seven years of political wrangling that has left Hungary's media privatisation trailing other former communist countries such as Poland and the Czech Republic, which already have commercial national television stations. ($ = 187.7 Hungarian Forints)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
