<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710125" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOSNIA: Joulwan says NATO to enforce rule of law in Bosnia.</title>
<headline>Joulwan says NATO to enforce rule of law in Bosnia.</headline>
<dateline>SARAJEVO 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO commander General George Joulwan said on Monday peacekeeping troops were determined to uphold a peace agreement and the rule of law in Bosnian Serb territory, scene of a power struggle.</p>
<p>Asked about the Serb political turmoil, Joulwan told reporters the NATO-led Stabilisation Force (SFOR) would ensure compliance with the Dayton peace accords and democratic norms.</p>
<p>&quot;We will support Dayton and we will support the democratic process. I would urge that there be no miscalulation by any of the parties on SFOR's intent to carry out its mandate.&quot;</p>
<p>Bosnian Serb President Biljana Plavsic and hardliners loyal to indicted war criminal Radovan Karadzic have been locked in a bitter confrontation since Plavsic tried to suspend the interior minister a week ago.</p>
<p>The confrontation has not turned violent but NATO has deployed additional troops to the northwest Banja Luka region to prevent possible clashes between Plavsic supporters and Karadzic loyalists.</p>
<p>&quot;Madame Plavsic is the democratically elected president of Republika Srpska (Serb republic) and the intent of SFOR is to ensure that the democratic process is complied with,&quot; Joulwan said.</p>
<p>The U.S. general, on a farewell visit to Bosnia before he steps down as NATO Supreme Allied Commander, said there had been no new orders issued to the alliance to go after Karadzic or other suspects wanted by the U.N. war crims tribunal.</p>
<p>&quot;I truly do believe that indicted war criminals, particularly Radovan Karadzic, belong in the Hague. I hope that will happen. &quot;Again, the principal responsibility for this lies with the (Bosnian) parties themselves,&quot; Joulwan said.</p>
<p>NATO has ruled out launching &quot;manhunts&quot; for indicted war criminals for fear of possible casualties or a hostile reaction by local armies, but says its troops will arrest a suspect if encountered during the course of their peacekeeping duties.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAJEVO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOSNIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
