<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710133" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Hospitals in crisis in Croatia's last Serb enclave.</title>
<headline>Hospitals in crisis in Croatia's last Serb enclave.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Smith</byline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hospitals in the last Serb region of Croatia lack basic medicines and cannot treat patients because the Croatian government has not paid for promised supplies, doctors and the United Nations said on Monday.</p>
<p>Croatian Health Minister Andrija Hebrang said the ministry planned to send supplies to the Eastern Slavonia region but cited financial problems because hospitals there had not been reintegrated into the Croatian health system.</p>
<p>Rade Miljenovic, a doctor in the emergency ward of Vukovar hospital, said by telephone: &quot;The situation has been really difficult for the last two months. We lack basic medicines -- painkillers, aspirins, syringes, oxygen...Very often a patient comes in and all we can give him is practical advice.</p>
<p>&quot;We are getting by thanks to humanitarian organisations, but it's far from enough. Croatia is reportedly going to take care of financing the hospital but nothing has come out of it yet...We haven't even signed employment contracts.&quot;</p>
<p>The enclave of Eastern Slavonia, taken by local Serb nationalists and the Yugoslav army in 1991, is now administered by 5,000 United Nations peacekeepers whose mission is due to start winding down soon. The U.N. has to leave by January next year, when the area will be fully reintegrated in Croatia.</p>
<p>U.N. mission spokesman Douglas Coffman said it had had to buy oxygen in neighbouring Yugoslavia with its own money because the hospital had none and Croatia was not supplying it.</p>
<p>&quot;We are over a barrel, we are using our own money to buy oxygen, we are going to international organisations to buy medical supplies. These are things that are clearly the responsibility of the Croatian government,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a shortage of medical supplies. We have applied to the Red Cross to supply the hospital and they have. We have pleaded with the Croatian government for months to give these emergency medical supplies, which we gave them a list of.&quot;</p>
<p>Hebrang said: &quot;Following a request by the UN...the Health Ministry has decided to ship off a donation of medicines and medical supplies including some 1,000 kg of oxygen.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the ministry would send the supplies to the UN who would &quot;distribute them as they see fit&quot;.</p>
<p>The minister signed an agreement with the U.N. in June which said the ministry would immediately start to finance Vukovar Hospital and a health centre in the town of Beli Manastir. It has so far failed to fulfil the agreement.</p>
<p>Hebrang said Croatia was not financing the hospitals but blamed officials -- presumably Serbs -- who he said were &quot;not observing Croatian legislation and ... not willing to talk directly to the Health Ministry despite repeated requests&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;If we were to send in money now we would have no legal way of vouching for this money as the Vukovar hospital has not been reintegrated into the Croatian health system,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>In a June 23 report to the U.N. Security Council, Secretary General Kofi Annan said there had been serious difficulties in absorbing Serb health workers into the Croatian system as the region is transferred gradually back to Croatian rule.</p>
<p>&quot;After eight months of opposition, the Croatian minister of health was ordered by President (Franjo) Tudjman, on 6 June, to sign an agreement on reintegration of the health system...and to assume financial responsibility for the Vukovar hospital and the Beli Manastir health centre.</p>
<p>&quot;Meanwhile a critical situation has developed in both medical institutions, including a lack of basic medicines and equipment, owing to the failure of the Ministry of Health to meet its commitments,&quot; Annan said.</p>
<p>The agreement signed by Hebrang and the U.N. mission said work contracts for employees of the regional health care service in Eastern Slavonia were to be completed and ready for distribution no later than June 16.</p>
<p>This has not happened, Coffman said.</p>
<p>A nurse in Vukovar hospital said patients were going to great lengths to buy medicine on their own, so they could bring it to the hospital. &quot;As far as I can see we have received neither medicine nor money from Croatia,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
