<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710265" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Coffee firms try new tack to recover Patricia debt.</title>
<headline>Coffee firms try new tack to recover Patricia debt.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Bulloch</byline>
<dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Four coffee trading firms have adopted a new approach to force Brazil's government to pay back an estimated 100 million sterling owed after an operation called Patricia in the London market more than 10 years ago.</p>
<p>A lawyer for one of the companies, Swiss firm Intercontinental de Cafe, said Monday in Milan a sequestration order had been served June 19 on the Milan branch of Germany's Deutsche Bank ordering the seizure of Brazilian assets.</p>
<p>This would include the proceeds of a June 2 500 billion lire bond issue, he added.</p>
<p>Intercontinental is one of four companies seeking compensation overseas from the Brazilian government after the now-defunct Brazilian Coffee Institute (IBC) failed to pay up after instructing them to purchase coffee on its behalf in 1986.</p>
<p>A group of 18 trade houses in total were involved in the so-called &quot;Operation Patricia&quot;, buying futures contracts on the London coffee futures market in order to boost world prices.</p>
<p>The idea was to maximise Brazil's revenue from its coffee exports which were sharply down that year because of a drought.</p>
<p>Trade houses were to buy futures contracts, take delivery of coffee and then in theory were to be paid back either in coffee or in cash by the government.</p>
<p>However the government only paid the firms $15 million at the beginning of 1987, supposedly only one tenth of what they were owed, as well as giving as a guarantee coffee stored in Trieste, dealers said.</p>
<p>Traders estimate that in total the government owes around 200 million sterling to all the firms involved.</p>
<p>In April 1990, four companies - Intercontinental, Citoma Trading, E.D. and F. Man and Procafe/Rothfos - won a judgement against the IBC in the U.K High Court which ordered the IBC to compensate the four firms.</p>
<p>The same year the IBC was liquidated, with the Brazilian government assuming all outstanding obligations.</p>
<p>The British court's ruling was later ratified by an appeals court in the northeast Italian seaport of Trieste which in 1996 allowed the four firms to remove 338,000 bags of coffee left in warehouses from Operation Patricia.</p>
<p>But given this was insufficient to cover the total debt, the firms decided on a new tack which resulted in the sequestration order, said a director from Citoma Trading in Brazil.</p>
<p>&quot;The latest act is based on the fact there is still very substantial monies owing,&quot; said John Whittaker, partner at international law firm Clyde &amp; Co in London who is acting for Citoma Trading.</p>
<p>He added that Citoma is actively looking at other countries to see what relief it can obtain there.</p>
<p>&quot;Wherever the Brazilian government has assets, the companies will be,&quot; said a director at Citoma Trading.</p>
<p>Deutsche Bank in Milan declined official comment on the sequestration order but a source there said the bank would not be required to disclose whether it is holding any Brazilian assets until the case comes to court next year.</p>
<p>Today Brazilian business daily Gazeta Mercantil said that Brazil was delaying the launch of a 10-year 200 million sterling Eurobond partly because of concerns over the legal situation following the Milan sequestration order.</p>
<p>The paper cited Central Bank officials who said another reason for the delay was an expected rise in British interest rates this week which would increase the cost of the bond issue.</p>
<p>((-Rio de Janeiro newsroom, 5521 5074151))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I63000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C16">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="RIO DE JANEIRO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
