<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710242" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>BOLIVIA: Scientists work to identify &quot;Che&quot; Guevara's bones.</title>
<headline>Scientists work to identify &quot;Che&quot; Guevara's bones.</headline>
<byline>Nataniel Alvarez</byline>
<dateline>SANTA CRUZ, Bolivia 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A team of Latin American scientists on Monday began the slow task of identifying what they believe are the bones of legendary guerrilla Ernesto &quot;Che&quot; Guevara, 30 years after he was shot by Bolivian troops.</p>
<p>A skeleton, including a skull which the Cuban scientific team leader said bore the heavy features of the charismatic revolutionary, was taken from a mass grave in a mountain village on Sunday to the east Bolivian city of Santa Cruz.</p>
<p>While Dr. Jorge Gonzalez insisted final verification of the remains would take five days, his Cuban, Argentine and Bolivian team members did not hide their optimism that they had found Guevara.</p>
<p>The skeleton -- one of the remains of seven supposed leftist guerrillas buried in a mass grave near the village of Vallegrande in 1967 -- was found without its hands.</p>
<p>The Bolivian troops who executed the communist icon in October 1967 cut off his hands so his fingerprints would serve as proof he was dead. They buried him in a secret location.</p>
<p>&quot;We maintain our rigorously scientific position that still does not allow us to say anything for certain,&quot; said Gonzalez, &quot;Everything said today about the identification of the bones is purely the responsibility of journalists.&quot;</p>
<p>But Gonzalez said over the weekend he felt a &quot;personal conviction&quot; that the bones were Guevara's.</p>
<p>He said work at Santa Cruz's Japanese Hospital was beginning with a meticulous cleaning of the bones from the seven sets of skeletons and that scientists would begin to measure and reconstruct broken pieces on Tuesday.</p>
<p>There is abundant data about Guevara's appearance and dental records, including the results of an official autopsy, which recorded that he was executed with a burst of nine bullets.</p>
<p>The Argentine-born doctor and hero of Cuba's 1959 revolution was trying to export communism to South America's mainland when he was captured, wounded and starving, on Oct. 8, 1967, and shot by a soldier in Vallegrande's school.</p>
<p>Bolivia began the quest for Guevara's bones in December 1995 after retired Gen. Mario Vargas Salinas broke two decades of military silence to say he could identify the spot where he ordered the burial of the guerrillas.</p>
<p>But he failed to locate the spot and the search has since been repeatedly suspended and resumed, with excavations centering on an airstrip outside Vallegrande, 480 miles (775 km) southeast of La Paz.</p>
<p>The search was relaunched in May based on new evidence, including the statement of a truck driver who said he had transported the bodies of Guevara and his comrades.</p>
<p>Bolivia's government has said it will honour a request by Guevara's Cuban wife, Aleida March, who asked that his bones be sent back to the Caribbean island for final burial.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTA CRUZ, Bolivia"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BOLIVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
