<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710389" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: FOCUS-Indonesia cuts tariffs, limits property loan.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Indonesia cuts tariffs, limits property loan.</headline>
<byline>Muklis Ali</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia unveiled a fresh economic deregulation package on Monday, cutting tariffs on 1,600 items but introducing measures to limit the property sector.</p>
<p>Coordinating Minister for Economics, Finance and Supervisor of Development Saleh Afiff told a news conference with five other ministers that the package was aimed at increasing efficiency.</p>
<p>Afiff said the government was cutting tariffs on 1,600 items, covering 1,461 manufactured products, 136 agricultural products and three items in the health sector.</p>
<p>&quot;In order to maintain the development momentum for the next century, Indonesia has to undertake strategic steps to improve the competitiveness of domestic producers,&quot; Afiff said.</p>
<p>He said the aim was to improve efficiency and the dynamics of the economy as a whole, not just those sectors that produced exports or competed with imports.</p>
<p>The Jakarta stock exchange has hit record levels over the past few days, and brokers and analysts expect the deregulation package -- unveiled after the market closed on Monday -- to give a further boost to sentiment.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the market still needs some time to digest the package and its impact on certain sectors. But in general it should give positive sentiment on the Indonesian economy,&quot; a senior market analyst said.</p>
<p>Afiff said the measures confirmed Indonesian commitments in the World Trade Organisation, the Association of Southeast Asian Nations Free Trade Area (AFTA) and the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) forum.</p>
<p>The move cut the average tariff rate to 11.9 percent from 13.0 percent and brought 62.55 percent of the tariff codes to a range between nil and 10 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;This means a lot. Please compare with ASEAN countries. I think this ranks us number two after Singapore,&quot; Coordinating Minister for Production and Distribution Hartarto said.</p>
<p>ASEAN nations Brunei, Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam are committed to cutting tariffs between the group's members to zero to five percent by 2003, with the exception of certain strategic items.</p>
<p>Indonesia's last economic reform package was in June 1996 when it cut import tariffs on 1,497 items, simplified trade procedures and offered incentives for export-oriented firms.</p>
<p>Industry and Trade Minister Tunky Ariwibowo said the sugar import monopoly held by state commodities regulator BULOG was scrapped, and now producers were allowed to make direct imports if they used raw sugar as raw materials.</p>
<p>The government also announced a regulatory move to contain the property sector due to rising property loan exposure among Indonesian banks -- an area of concern to the World Bank in its annual report on Indonesia last month.</p>
<p>&quot;...in an effort to anticipate undesirable conditions, (the central) Bank Indonesia is prohibiting new credit allocations (from July 14) for land procurement and improvement for real estate developers,&quot; Afiff said.</p>
<p>Central bank governor Sudradjad Djiwandono said property loans accounted for 19.7 percent of outstanding credit in May, compared with some 13 percent four years ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The rapid rise of property loans could endanger the health of a bank and monetary stability,&quot; Djiwandono said, adding that problems could rise from financing mismatches.</p>
<p>&quot;We introduce those rules to limit the sector,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Indonesia also revised export tax structures for palm oil and its derivatives to an 'ad valorem tax' from a specific tax.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
