<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710426" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>MALAYSIA: FOCUS-Malaysia sees May trade surplus, exports slump.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Malaysia sees May trade surplus, exports slump.</headline>
<byline>Azhar Sukri</byline>
<dateline>KUALA LUMPUR 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Malaysia on Monday reported a trade surplus for the year to May following a deficit in April, but economists said export growth remained sluggish and tipped a wide shortfall for calendar 1997.</p>
<p>The Statistics Department said Malaysia posted a 156.8 million ringgit ($62.7 million) surplus in May, compared to a 2.13 billion ringgit deficit in April.</p>
<p>Exports totalled 17.25 billion ringgit, a slight rise from 15.63 billion ringgit in April, while imports slipped to 17.10 billion ringgit from 17.76 billion ringgit.</p>
<p>&quot;In absolute terms, Malaysia showed a 157 million ringgit surplus. But the figures show that exports have not come back in a strong or clear way yet,&quot; said Lum Chee Soon, general manager of economic research at Phileo Allied Securities in Kuala Lumpur.</p>
<p>The May surplus was more a reflection of a dip in imports rather than broad strength in exports, and most economists expect exports to remain soft over the year, weighed down by weakness in the country's electronic manufacturing sector.</p>
<p>&quot;Malaysia showed a surplus in May as some big-ticket (import) items were not brought in during the period,&quot; said Andy Tan, economist and general manager of research house MMS International in Singapore.</p>
<p>Those items included aircraft and military purchases, said Tan.</p>
<p>Brokers Thong &amp; Kay Hian said they expected Malaysia's overall trade deficit to widen to 1.5 billion ringgit for 1997, compared with a deficit of 619 million ringgit in 1996.</p>
<p>In the first five months of 1997, export earnings totalled 81.8 billion ringgit, a marginal rise from 80.3 million ringgit in the same period last year.</p>
<p>The key factors affecting Malaysia's trade balance are imports of large &quot;lumpy&quot; items such as ships and aircraft, and an electronics sector that remains in the doldrums following a global slowdown in demand for micro-processors.</p>
<p>The national carrier Malaysian Airline Systems Bhd (MAS) will take delivery of four Boeing Co aircraft over the course of 1997. It has ordered a total of 25 aircraft from the U.S.-based manufacturer.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect the imports of lumpy items such as MAS aircraft and shipping vessels to significantly increase in the remaining months of 1997,&quot; said Thong &amp; Kay Hian in a daily market report.</p>
<p>&quot;I have not seen any signs of a recovery in the electronics sector,&quot; said Lum at Phileo Allied.</p>
<p>Electronics account for over 50 percent of Malaysia's manufactured exports.</p>
<p>Exports of thermionic valves and tubes, photocells brought in 15.1 billion ringgit, or 18.5 percent of total export value, in May.</p>
<p>Electronic integrated circuits accounted for 11.2 billion ringgit, or 13.7 percent of total export earnings, while palm oil exports contributed 3.8 billion ringgit, accounting for 4.7 percent of total exports.</p>
<p>Imports of intermediate goods totalled 54 billion ringgit, representing 66 percent of imports.</p>
<p>Malaysia's largest trading partners in the first five months to May were Japan (29.2 billion ringgit), United States (27.8 billion ringgit), Singapore (27.7 billion ringgit), Taiwan (7.8 billion ringgit), and South Korea (7.0 billion ringgit).</p>
<p>($1=2.5 ringgit)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MALAY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KUALA LUMPUR"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MALAYSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
