<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710440" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesia releases economic deregulation package.</title>
<headline>Indonesia releases economic deregulation package.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia on Monday unveiled its latest economic deregulation package, cutting tariffs on 1,600 items.</p>
<p>The announcement was made by Coordinating Minister for Economics, Finance and Supervisor of Development, Saleh Afiff.</p>
<p>Indonesia's last major economic reform package was in June last year when it cut import tariffs on 1,497 items, simplified trade procedures and offered incentives for export-oriented firms.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Mar'ie Muhammad said the tariff cuts covered 1,461 industrial items, 136 agricultural products and three items from the health sector.</p>
<p>He said the number of tariff-free items rose to 1,419 from 1,399 under the new list. In other reductions, the number of items covered by a five percent tariff rose to 2,275 from 2,066 and by a 10 percent tariff to 844 from 610.</p>
<p>He said items covered by a 20 percent import tariff rose to 1,156 from 834.</p>
<p>Only 55 items now were subjected to a 30 percent import tariff and 82 items to over 30 percent.</p>
<p>Mar'ie's initial announcement did not spell out the specific items.</p>
<p>The seven member states of the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN) are due to cut tariffs to between zero and five percent by the year 2003 with certain strategic exceptions. ASEAN groups Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, Singapore, Vietnam, the Philippines and Brunei.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
