<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710452" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean economy seen recovering but at slow pace.</title>
<headline>S.Korean economy seen recovering but at slow pace.</headline>
<byline>Yeom Yoon-jeong</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korea's central bank on Monday forecast economic growth would accelerate to 6.3 percent in the second half of this year, boosted by rising exports and construction investment.</p>
<p>The Bank of Korea (BOK) said in a report that the export-led economy would benefit from both an improving world economy and the yen's strength, which should allow Korean exports to be more competitive in the region.</p>
<p>&quot;The worst is over. The economy will improve in the second half, but only at a slow pace,&quot; said Park Jung-kyu, a central bank economist.</p>
<p>Gross domestic product (GDP) rose by 5.6 percent in the first half of 1997.</p>
<p>The central bank also revised its full-year current-account deficit forecast to $17 billion from an earlier projection of $18 billion.</p>
<p>The deficit includes a $9.5 billion invisible trade shortfall this year.</p>
<p>Slowing wage rises, weeks of strikes over labour reforms and a slew of corporate debt defaults dampened consumption and corporate investment in the first half of the year.</p>
<p>This prompted the BOK to revise its growth forecast for the whole of 1997 down to 6.0 percent from 6.4 percent projected in November.</p>
<p>Kim Ju-hyung, director of the LG Economic Research Institute, said he expected further signs of recovery to emerge in the third quarter.</p>
<p>&quot;But this time, hitting the bottom does not mean a quick recovery. The economy is expected to show a gradual &quot;U-shaped&quot; turnaround,&quot; said Cho Hong-rae, an economist at Hyundai Research Institute.</p>
<p>Some economists believe the central bank's projections on growth are too optimistic. Lee Han-koo, president of Daewoo Economic Research Institute, said the bank appeared to have based its optimism on rising export prices.</p>
<p>&quot;The impact from a strong yen would be limited,&quot; Lee said. &quot;I would caution against the central bank's optimism.&quot;</p>
<p>Daewoo has forecast 5.5 percent GDP growth for the whole of 1997 and Hyundai Economic Research Institute 5.9 percent.</p>
<p>Goldman Sachs puts growth at 5.3 percent this year, while LG is more optimistic with a projection of between 6.1 and 6.2 percent growth.</p>
<p>Lim Choon-soo, head of research at Goldman Sachs, cautioned against what he described as a mood of &quot;euphoria&quot; over the recent improvement in economic data seen in the past few months.</p>
<p>The country's customs-cleared trade deficit showed a surplus of $97.6 million in June, the first monthly surplus in 30 months.</p>
<p>The central bank said it expected a 15 percent increase in the value of its exports in the July-December period year-on-year because of rising prices of key export items, such as semiconductor, steel and petrochemical products.</p>
<p>But Lee disagreed, saying spot prices for 16-megabit dynamic random access memory (DRAM) chips, accounting for 17 percent of South Korea's total exports, were likely to fluctuate further.</p>
<p>Some economists said it was uncertain if export prices of petrochemical products would move in favour of South Korea.</p>
<p>Lim at Goldman Sachs said the impact from a strengthening yen would be limited as only 30 percent of South Korean exports compete with Japanese products on world markets.</p>
<p>&quot;It will give a psychological boost. But the real impact will not be as big as many expect,&quot; he added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
