<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710537" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Clinton seeks U.S. public backing on larger NATO.</title>
<headline>Clinton seeks U.S. public backing on larger NATO.</headline>
<byline>Laurence McQuillan</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton, determined to limit NATO expansion to only three countries, on Monday admitted he faced a tough fight convincing the U.S. Congress and the American public to back any enlargement of the alliance.</p>
<p>Behind-the-scenes negotiations were under way as aides to the 16 NATO leaders sought to defuse a test of wills between the camp led by Clinton which wants to admit only Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic, and a faction led by French President Jacques Chirac that wants to add Romania and Slovenia too.</p>
<p>Clinton called the two-day summit, which begins on Tuesday, &quot;a milestone in our work to adapt NATO to a new Europe and a new century, so it can meet new security challenges&quot;.</p>
<p>Although Washington had hoped a decision on expansion would be announced on Tuesday, one senior U.S. official acknowledged that &quot;it may slide until Wednesday ... We want to do this right, not fast&quot;.</p>
<p>Clinton, however, left no doubt about what he expected the outcome would be. &quot;I believe that the consensus decision will be for three, but I hope and believe there will be a clear message that the door to NATO remains open,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Speaking with reporters after a meeting with a bi-partisan delegation of Republican and Democratic members of the U.S. Congress, in Spain for the summit, Clinton said he faced a challenge at home to win support for any expansion of the military alliance at all.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a ways to go to convince the American people of the momentous importance of the decisions we are making here and the need for them to support it,&quot; Clinton said.</p>
<p>Enlarging the alliance has generated some opposition in Congress and among the American public as questions have been raised about the increased costs that go with expansion and the added military obligations.</p>
<p>In a pre-summit editorial, the New York Times declared: &quot;Given the absence of a clear threat to Europe and the possibility of so many unpredictable consequences, NATO expansion seems a gratuitous risk.&quot;</p>
<p>Discussing his talk with lawmakers, Clinton said: &quot;They pointed out to me in no uncertain terms that we've got a sales job to do, but we think we can do it.&quot;</p>
<p>Senator Joseph Biden, a Democrat from Delaware who backs expansion, said afterwards that a Senate vote on approval was likely to come when the United States hopes to withdraw its peacekeeping forces from Bosnia next June.</p>
<p>Other Europeans participating in the NATO-led mission in Bosnia have threatened to withdraw too if U.S. forces pull out.</p>
<p>&quot;If at the time the United States withdraws its combat forces the Europeans all pull out, it is going to be a very difficult sell in the United States of America,&quot; Biden said.</p>
<p>Clinton clearly sought to soften the blow of his opposition to allowing Romania and Slovenia NATO membership now, saying he was &quot;very enthusiastic about the developments that have taken place&quot; in both countries.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm glad they want to be in NATO, and I think that they should get consideration. I just don't think at this time that they should be admitted,&quot; said Clinton, who plans to visit Poland and Romania after the summit.</p>
<p>Clinton was asked about the possibility of eventually extending the alliance to Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia and said he opposed closing the door to any democracy.</p>
<p>Russia, which has grudgingly accepted NATO expansion to include some East European states, has threatened to review its ties with the alliance if the Baltic states, which were under Soviet rule from World War Two to 1991 and have large Russian minorities, are admitted.</p>
<p>&quot;My position is that no European democracy should be excluded from ultimate consideration,&quot; Clinton said, adding: &quot;My personal position is that that should apply to Russia as well.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
