<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710561" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Antitrust probe reviewing Internet registrations.</title>
<headline>Antitrust probe reviewing Internet registrations.</headline>
<byline>Aaron Pressman</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Justice Department has opened an antitrust investigation into the business of registering Internet addresses, a spokeswoman for the agency said Monday.</p>
<p>Last week the leading registration company, Network Solutions Inc., revealed it had received a request for documents from the Justice Department as part of the investigation.</p>
<p>&quot;We're looking at the possibility of anticompetitive practices in the Internet address registration industry,&quot; a spokeswoman for the agency said.</p>
<p>All Internet addresses end with a short designation, usually three letters, known as a top-level domain.</p>
<p>Under a contract with the National Science Foundation, Herndon, Va.-based Network Solutions has a monopoly to register Internet addresses in the most popular domains, including &quot;.com&quot; for commercial sites and &quot;.org&quot; for sites run by non-profit organisations.</p>
<p>The company has struggled to cope with surging demand for Internet addresses, dozens of lawsuits arising from alleged trademark infringements in address names and difficulty collecting fees from some Internet users.</p>
<p>In documents filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission in preparation for a public stock offering, Network Solutions said it received on June 27 a &quot;civil investigative demand&quot; from the Justice Department.</p>
<p>The demand requested documents and information from the company and its corporate parent, Science Applications International Corp. The government investigation followed a private lawsuit filed against the company in March alleging violations of the Sherman Antitrust Act.</p>
<p>Antitrust actions can proceed even in cases where the government has granted a monopoly franchise, attorneys noted.</p>
<p>&quot;If a city contracts with somebody, for example, to do things with respect to garbage, that does not authorise the company that has the contract to do whatever it pleases,&quot; said David Turetsky, former deputy assistant attorney general for antitrust. &quot;As we all know, in the hauling industry there have been a lot of antitrust, among other problems.&quot;</p>
<p>Turetsky, now vice president at Teligent LLC, said government investigators typically would gather information from the company and make an evaluation whether or not to proceed with the probe in a matter of months.</p>
<p>Network Solutions officials declined to comment, citing securities laws prohibiting an issuer from discussing a pending stock offering.</p>
<p>In its filing, the company said it is not aware of the scope or nature of the investigation. The company also said the NSF has asked it to refrain from creating new top-level domains, a practice at the centre of the lawsuit filed in March.</p>
<p>NSF officials also declined to comment on the investigation. Network Solution's decision to go public has &quot;no effect&quot; on the company's contract with NSF, a spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>In its initial public offering, the company plans to raise $35 million, but has not revealed how many shares would be sold or at what price.</p>
<p>For the three months ending March 31, the company had income of $516,000 on revenues of $8.7 million, compared with a loss of $1.1 million on revenues of $2.3 million for the same period a year earlier.</p>
<p>The filing comes amidst a period of upheaval and uncertainty for Internet address registrations. The National Science Foundation has said it will not renew its exclusive agreement with Network Solutions when the contract expires in March 1998.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
