<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710793" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO leaders in tussle over enlargement process.</title>
<headline>NATO leaders in tussle over enlargement process.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Clayton</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO leaders gathered in Madrid on Monday for a summit designed to erase the Cold War division of Europe, openly quarrelling over how many former communist enemies to invite to join the Western military alliance.</p>
<p>Only a day before the start of the historic meeting sealing NATO's triumph, the United States and a majority of its European allies remained deeply split over U.S. insistence on limiting enlargement to Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton, one of the first to arrive for the July 8-9 summit in the Spanish capital, has said only the three leading contenders out of 12 applicants were politically and economically ready to assume the burdens of membership.</p>
<p>France and Italy, backed by seven other European allies, want Slovenia and Romania included as a reward for progress in establishing democracies and market economies and to inject stability to the edge of the Black Sea and Balkan regions.</p>
<p>NATO officials said the argument, which goes to the heart of the justification for enlarging the most powerful military alliance ever assembled into central and eastern Europe, would not be resolved until the summit started.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment the discussion on who (gets in) continues, that decision has not been taken,&quot; a senior NATO official told reporters, but said he was confident the issue would be resolved to the satisfaction of all.</p>
<p>Senior diplomats would try and narrow differences at a meeting later on Monday, but the final decision would be taken by heads of government -- a rare event for a NATO summit where contentious issues are normally settled well in advance.</p>
<p>Clinton, who has made alliance expansion the foreign policy centrepiece of his second term, flew into Madrid's military airport in bright sunshine after a weekend relaxing with King Juan Carlos on the Spanish holiday island of Majorca.</p>
<p>Keenly aware of mounting domestic opposition to the plan, which has to be ratified by the Republican-led Congress, Clinton has ruled out any compromise, angering Europeans sensitive to charges they are mere spectators at a U.S.-run NATO show.</p>
<p>U.S. officials said they were braced for a blast from President Jacques Chirac who has also said Paris' conditions for rejoining NATO's military wing have not yet been met, but said Franco-American differences would not spoil the party.</p>
<p>Chirac's spokesman said last week Paris would not &quot;take hostage&quot; the leading three countries about which all agreed, just to press for the inclusion of Romania and Slovenia.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen predicted on Monday that NATO leaders would reach agreement easily and initially limit the invitations to the three former Warsaw Pact foes.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't expect it to be very tough or contentious,&quot; Cohen told reporters ahead of the two-day meeting.</p>
<p>Clinton too predicted there would be a consensus on admitting just the three front-runners.</p>
<p>NATO officials said attention was now focused on the exact language of a pledge to keep the NATO door open after the first enlargement -- the fourth time the alliance has expanded since its creation in 1949 to defend the West from the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>France and Italy, also keen to maintain the alliance's geographical balance between northern and southern European members, want firm commitments for a second summit.</p>
<p>But NATO sources said there was no more agreement on how to proceed with future enlargements than on how to deal with the existing one.</p>
<p>The expansionists say a second enlargement summit could take place on NATO's 50th anniversary in April 1999 when the first three new members will formally be admitted, but others are reluctant to tie their hands in advance.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1999, we will have a good picture, a good perspective from which to launch the second wave, or at least to start thinking about when to launch the second wave and to develop a concept of how to manage that,&quot; a senior NATO official said in comments reflecting the debate raging inside the alliance.</p>
<p>He added it was also still not decided if any countries which failed to win an invitation in the first round would be named in Tuesday's communique as potential members next time.</p>
<p>Clinton held talks with Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar and NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana later on Monday while alliance foreign ministers planned to debate the issue over dinner.</p>
<p>The United States is not alone. Denmark and other Scandinavian countries have made clear they would oppose a wider enlargement if it did not include the three Baltic States -- Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia.</p>
<p>Russia, which signed an agreement with NATO on a new partnership in May effectively agreeing to a limited enlargement, vehemently opposes membership for the former Soviet republics on its western flank.</p>
<p>On Monday, the European Union (EU) appeared to come to the help of NATO in softening the blow to at least some states left out of the first alliance expansion since 1982 when Spain joined.</p>
<p>EU officials in Brussels said the European Commission, the EU's executive, would recommend next week opening accession talks with Slovenia and Estonia as well as Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>EU and NATO enlargements were originally described as &quot;parallel but separate&quot; processes designed to make the new democracies in former communist Europe feel part of the West, but recently the EU's enlargement has fallen behind.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
