<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710787" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Clinton urges new NATO negotiations with France.</title>
<headline>Clinton urges new NATO negotiations with France.</headline>
<byline>Paul Taylor</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called on Monday for new negotiations between NATO and France on reintegrating Paris into the Western alliance's military wing, which it quit in 1966.</p>
<p>But Clinton did not yield on Washington's insistence that NATO's southern command, which controls the Mediterranean, should remain in American hands and not be handed over to the European allies, as France has demanded.</p>
<p>At a joint news conference after talks with Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar on the eve of a NATO summit, Clinton said: &quot;I hope as soon as the summit is over, NATO can resume negotiations with the French and at the end of the year, both Spain and France will be in the integrated command structure.&quot;</p>
<p>His statement contrasted with comments by U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen in Brussels last month, suggesting the talks were at an end following the election of a Socialist-led French government more hostile towards NATO.</p>
<p>Clinton's comments, which won a cautious welcome from a French spokeswoman, sounded sympathetic but offered no concessions on the substance of French President Jacques Chirac's call for a &quot;rebalancing&quot; of power in Europe's favour.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that more of the command positions should be given over to Europe and to everybody that is in the command structure, including France, should France decide to do that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;What we have said is we do not believe that the United States should give up one single command, the command of AFSOUTH, because that's where the U.S. Sixth Fleet is,&quot; he said, noting that it was the region's biggest asset and one of Washington's biggest overseas military assets.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe the French, if they join the military structure, should be part of the commands, and we want to support that,&quot; Clinton added.</p>
<p>Chirac's spokeswoman, Catherine Colonna, gave a cautious welcome to Clinton's statement.</p>
<p>&quot;These remarks by President Clinton show that both sides are available to continue the far-reaching reform of the Atlantic Alliance, as France stated last week.</p>
<p>&quot;This readiness in principle expressed by the American president is a sign in the right direction, but let us take the time to see what exactly the content of the American proposals is and whether they indeed correspond to that objective (of far-reaching reform),&quot; Colonna told Reuters.</p>
<p>France said last week its conditions for rejoining the allied command had not been met, but welcomed progress made so far towards building a European defence identity within NATO and said it was available for further talks.</p>
<p>French officials said Clinton's call for fresh negotiations would be helpful to the conservative Chirac, who initiated France's rapprochement with NATO in 1995, but could be more problematic for Socialist Prime Minister Lionel Jospin.</p>
<p>Jospin criticised the rapprochement while in opposition, accusing Chirac of making unilateral concessions to Washington and achieving nothing in return.</p>
<p>His rainbow coalition includes Communists, anti-nuclear Greens and left-wing Socialists opposed to NATO as well as moderate Socialists more positive towards integration.</p>
<p>Chirac argued that France would never persuade the Europeans to build their own defence capability outside NATO, as his predecessor Francois Mitterrand had sought to do, and could only achieve that goal within the alliance's military structure.</p>
<p>Chirac also differs strongly from Clinton on NATO enlargement. The French have campaigned vociferously for Romania and Slovenia to be added to the three countries to which the United States wants to limit the first wave of NATO expansion -- Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
