<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710710" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: White House pushes for urban breaks in tax bill.</title>
<headline>White House pushes for urban breaks in tax bill.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The White House Monday urged lawmakers not to forget the nation's inner cities in tax cut legislation now pending in Congress.</p>
<p>Vice President Al Gore and a group of mayors complained at a White House briefing that the tax bills passed by the Senate and House failed to include President Clinton's tax proposals aimed at giving the nation's inner cities a much needed economic boost.</p>
<p>Gore and the mayors vowed to continue to push for the proposed tax benefits that would help clean up abandoned contaminated urban manufacturing sites known as &quot;brownfields&quot;, encourage businesses to hire welfare recipients and promote business investment in inner cities.</p>
<p>&quot;We're here this morning, to say to the Congress as they prepare to craft a final tax package, please do not forget America's cities,&quot; Gore said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Clinton-Gore administration has proposed, but Congress has failed thus far to deliver on a community empowerment agenda that fights for our nation's cities, our nation's counties and our nation's families,&quot; said New Orleans Mayor Marc Morial.</p>
<p>&quot;I want to pledge here and now that the mayors of this nation, in concert with local and other county officials, will fight and work and advocate and speak out for the enactment of these proposals,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Final negotiations were expected to start this week in which one bill would be carved largely from the three proposals offered by Clinton, the House and Senate.</p>
<p>The House bill and Clinton proposed $85 billion in cuts over five years, while the Senate passed a $77 billion tax cut bill.</p>
<p>The Senate bill includes a brownfields tax break for a smaller number of communities than the president's proposal. The House tax bill includes a reduced version of Clinton's welfare-to-work tax credit.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
