<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710711" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Three Starbucks employees shot to death.</title>
<headline>Three Starbucks employees shot to death.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Three young Starbucks Corp employees were found shot to death early Monday in a gruesome scene at a Starbucks coffee shop in Washington's luxury Georgetown area, police said.</p>
<p>Two men aged 18 and 25 and a 24-year-old woman, all with at least one gunshot wound to the head, were discovered shortly after 0515 EDT/0915 GMT by a colleague arriving for work.  Police shut down busy Wisconsin Avenue, a major traffic artery into downtown Washington and home to exclusive art galleries and upmarket stores, for more than six hours while they investigated the triple homicide.  </p>
<p>Sgt. Joe Gentile of the D.C. Metropolitan police said the three victims were employees of Starbucks, a nationwide coffee shop chain. They were later identified as Aaron David Goodrich, 18; Mary Caitrin Mahoney, 24; and Emory Allen Evans, 25, all of whom lived in Northwest Washington.</p>
<p>The coffee cafe had closed at 2000 EDT/2400 GMT Sunday but it was not immediately known when the three died.  Police said an employee of Starbucks flagged down a bus driver on Wisconsin Avenue after finding the bodies in a back room of the two-story building.  Gentile said there were no suspects or possible motives at this time.  </p>
<p>Local television reported that no money appeared to be missing from the store and said all the doors were locked when the employee who discovered the bodies arrived before dawn.</p>
<p>Each of the victims was shot in the head at least once and they most likely were killed shortly after closing on Sunday night, according to WRC-TV.</p>
<p>Starbucks said it was &quot;deeply saddened&quot; by the tragedy and offered to provide whatever assistance necessary to families of the victims.</p>
<p>The murders came a day after Washington's Mayor Marion Barry declared the streets of the nation's capital were the safest in the United States.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42390">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
