<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710810" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO, split on expansion, to open Madrid summit.</title>
<headline>NATO, split on expansion, to open Madrid summit.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1996-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO leaders open a historic summit on Tuesday determined to thrash out serious differences over how far and how fast to expand into territory once ruled by their former Cold War foe, the Warsaw Pact.</p>
<p>In what promises to be the most contentious NATO gathering in years, U.S. President Bill Clinton is expected to come under fire from European allies incensed at his attempt to unilaterally limit the first wave of new members to Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>But the debate, which will give French President Jacques Chirac and Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi a chance to vent irritation over what they see as American heavy-handedness, is all but certain to yield a consensus in support of Clinton's three favourites, NATO diplomats say.</p>
<p>&quot;There's only going to be three new members because the U.S. wants three and they'll get it,&quot; a NATO diplomat said.</p>
<p>With Clinton likely to prevail in NATO's first eastward thrust, European allies were pressing hard for a commitment from the alliance on a timetable for taking in a second wave of post-communist countries.</p>
<p>The French government, which had led a European charge to have Romania and Slovenia included in the first round, wants a strong statement to give encouragement to future NATO aspirants.</p>
<p>But the Clinton administration, mindful of the opposition it will face when the Republican-led Congress begins debating NATO expansion, wants to avoid specific promises beyond pledging that the alliance will take in new members at some future date.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe that the NATO doors should remain open,&quot; Clinton told reporters on Monday before attending a dinner with alliance leaders. &quot;We do not believe we should close the door to the aspirations of any democracy.&quot;</p>
<p>Senior NATO diplomats met late into the night to narrow differences over the wording of the expansion communique, but the final decision was to be made by the heads of government -- a rare event for the normally choreographed alliance summits.</p>
<p>After weeks of transatlantic bickering over the issue, a NATO official said alliance leaders were certain to announce an agreement on Tuesday, the first day of a two-day summit.</p>
<p>But a senior U.S. official said: &quot;It may slide until Wednesday...We want to do this right, not fast.&quot;</p>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin, who had bitterly opposed NATO's expansion but admitted he was powerless to stop it, chose not to attend. His signing of a landmark Russia-NATO cooperation treaty in May paved the way for enlargement while giving Moscow a voice -- but not a veto -- in alliance affairs.</p>
<p>Invitations to even three ex-communist states would be the biggest expansion in NATO history. Only once, in 1952, was more than than one new country admitted at once, when Greece and Turkey joined.</p>
<p>It would be the first push into the former East Bloc by a Western defence organization that was created nearly 50 years ago as a bulwark against Soviet communism.</p>
<p>Speaking to reporters after a meeting with a bipartisan congressional delegation in Madrid for the summit, Clinton said he faced a challenge at home to win support for NATO expansion.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a way to go to convince the American people of the momentous importance of the decisions we are making here and the need for them to support it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton said the lawmakers &quot;pointed out to me in no uncertain terms that we've got a sales job to do&quot;.</p>
<p>In recent weeks, Clinton has dug in his heels about limiting NATO's growth, saying Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic were the only applicants ready politically, militarily and economically to join the 16-member alliance.</p>
<p>But on Monday he sought to soften the expected blow to shunned applicants Romania and Slovenia, saying he was &quot;very enthusiastic about the developments that have taken place&quot; in the two countries.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm glad they want to be in NATO and I think they should get consideration. I just don't think at this time they should be admitted,&quot; the president said.</p>
<p>Clinton also tried to ease tension with France. Paris has suspended its return to NATO's military wing after Washington rejected its demand for the key southern command, which controls the Mediterranean, to be handed over to a European.</p>
<p>Without changing his position on the Naples-based command, he said: &quot;I hope as soon as the summit is over, NATO can resume negotiations with the French and at the end of the year, both Spain and France will be in the integrated command structure.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
