<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710820" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Angola's Dos Santos makes four-day visit to Italy.</title>
<headline>Angola's Dos Santos makes four-day visit to Italy.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Angolan President Jose Eduardo Dos Santos arrived in Rome on Monday for a four-day official visit during which he was to meet Italian leaders and have an audience with Pope John Paul.</p>
<p>Dos Santos has faced increasing foreign pressure recently to meet former rebel leader Jonas Savimbi to discuss ongoing fighting in the country's diamond-rich northeast.</p>
<p>He was due to meet the Pontiff on Tuesday at the Vatican, and then to hold talks with his Italian counterpart Oscar Luigi Scalfaro.</p>
<p>He was scheduled to visit the Italian business confederation Confindustria and energy group Eni on Tuesday afternoon, and to hold talks with the leaders of both houses of Italy's parliament and the mayor of Rome on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Before departing on Thursday, Dos Santos was to have talks with Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi.</p>
<p>The government launched an offensive in northeastern Angola in May that analysts say is a pretext for an assault on Savimbi's UNITA, the once-powerful rebel movement which fought a 20-year civil war against the government and still controls Angola's main diamond-producing areas.</p>
<p>Observers and diplomats fear heavy fighting between the parties threatens a ceasefire signed in 1994.</p>
<p>Dos Santos has said the raid was against armed Hutu and Rwandan refugees in UNITA-held areas.</p>
<p>One intelligence source said last month that Dos Santos had promised the United States, Portugal and other governments that he would contact Savimbi on his return from a three-week holiday in Sardinia. The date of his trip was not immediately known.</p>
<p>In response to an appeal from U.N. Secretary-General Kofi Annan, UNITA has said Savimbi is ready to meet Dos Santos in Italy. But Luanda insists any talks must take place in Angola.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
