<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="710801" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: U.S., NATO hint at force to snatch Bosnian Serbs.</title>
<headline>U.S., NATO hint at force to snatch Bosnian Serbs.</headline>
<byline>Charles Aldinger</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen and a senior NATO official refused on Monday to rule out using allied troops to capture indicted war criminals in Bosnia, including former Bosnian Serb president Radovan Karadzic.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing has been ruled in or ruled out,&quot; Cohen told reporters. &quot;There has been no decision made. It has been the position of the (U.S.) administration that we will do whatever we can to strengthen the War Crimes Tribunal.&quot;</p>
<p>Cohen, who arrived in Madrid on Monday for a NATO summit, cited the sensitivity of &quot;intelligence matters&quot; in declining to confirm reports that U.S. special forces and the Central Intelligence Agency had a secret plan to capture Karadzic.</p>
<p>&quot;We hope that some of these criminals can be brought to justice,&quot; he told reporters during the flight from Washington.</p>
<p>The NATO official, briefing reporters before the summit, said: &quot;There is considerable frustration in the international community at the fact that Mr Karadzic and not only him, the 50-odd other indicted war criminals that have so far escaped justice, have not been taken to the tribunal in The Hague.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked whether NATO leaders might order action to capture the wanted suspects when they discuss Bosnia on Tuesday, the official said: &quot;Nothing is excluded. I think we should simply see what the heads of state and government will decide to do.&quot;</p>
<p>Cohen accused Karadzic, who is locked in a power struggle with his successor, Bosnian Serb President Biljana Plavsic, of trying to disrupt the peace process in Bosnia.</p>
<p>&quot;I think he is probably doing, behind the scenes, his best to unravel it. As long as he continues to exercise influence, he is going to continue to present a problem,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Cohen and other U.S. officials had hitherto emphasised that a 31,000-member NATO-led peacekeeping force in Bosnia, SFOR, should not be used to arrest war criminals.</p>
<p>&quot;I think there is always a concern about repercussions against troops by Serb sympathisers,&quot; said Cohen on Monday.</p>
<p>The NATO official said SFOR's mandate, which did not include actively hunting down war criminals, was unchanged &quot;for the time being&quot;, and NATO would continue to use all available methods to push the Bosnian Serb republic into handing over the suspects.</p>
<p>But the Los Angeles Times reported on Sunday that there had been active planning to use the military to make arrests.</p>
<p>Quoting U.S. intelligence sources, the newspaper said the plan was a response to Washington's concern that Karadzic was a major threat to long-term peace in former Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton had not formally approved the plan and hoped increased diplomatic pressure would prompt the Bosnian Serb government to surrender Karadzic peacefully, it said.</p>
<p>Secretary of State Madeleine Albright told reporters in Madrid she expected NATO leaders to discuss both political support for Plavsic and economic measures to force the Bosnian Serbs to comply with the Dayton peace accords.</p>
<p>&quot;It is our hope that as we discuss Bosnia here in the next couple of days, it will become evident that extra-legal activities by Mr Karadzic and others will be viewed as unacceptable and that there will be support given for Mrs Plavsic, the duly-elected leader of Republika Srpska,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;...The international support for her position and for the constitutional structures that she represents will point up the importance of isolating those who do not support those constitutional processes,&quot; Albright said after talks with Spanish Foreign Minister Abel Matutes.</p>
<p>The Times said planning between Special Forces and the Central Intelligence Agency Directorate of Operations began last year on an operation to capture Karadzic and take him to The Hague for trial by the United Nations war crimes tribunal.</p>
<p>Karadzic and his former military commander, General Ratko Mladic, were indicted during the 1992-95 Bosnian war but no serious effort has been made to arrest them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
