<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711171" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BA to count cost as strike countdown starts.</title>
<headline>BA to count cost as strike countdown starts.</headline>
<byline>Paul Keller</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Airways faces a damaging and potentially drawn-out industrial dispute as it prepares this week for a three-day strike by cabin crew, the first in what could be a series, airline industry analysts said on Monday.</p>
<p>BA, which is bidding to complete a one billion pound ($1.7 billion) restructuring by 2000, risks losing 20 million pounds a day in costs and lost bookings.</p>
<p>It is also in danger of being dragged into a bloody public relations battle which may damage in the long run its image with customers and investors.</p>
<p>&quot;Public sympathy is not greatly weighted on either side, but the longer the strike goes on the more chance there is it will hurt BA's image as an efficient, caring airline,&quot; said a senior analyst at a European bank who asked not to be named.</p>
<p>BA will be keen to avoid a confrontation on the scale of the one faced by state-run Air France four years ago when its restructuring plans sparked fierce public demonstrations and strikes which crippled the airline, the London-based analyst said.</p>
<p>Ever image-conscious, BA spent 60 million pounds earlier this year on new markings for its aircraft. The airline is one of the UK's biggest advertisers.</p>
<p>Union representatives, stepping up their attack on BA's handling of the dispute, accused it on Monday of being too aggressive and high-handed in pushing through cuts.</p>
<p>&quot;We feel BA's conduct raises public concern in relation to employment law and employee rights. Issues have been raised that sooner or later the (British) parliament will want to look at,&quot; Andrew Murray, a spokesman for Transport and General Workers' Union (T&amp;G), said in a telephone interview.</p>
<p>BA said earlier it had launched contingency plans to continue to operate up to 80 percent of its flights if cabin crew go ahead with their planned three-day strikes from Wednesday. It is also threatening striking cabin crew with a range of sanctions, including legal action.</p>
<p>The contingency plan follows the breakdown of talks with the cabin crews' Transport and General Workers' Union (T&amp;G) in a dispute over pay and conditions.</p>
<p>BA accuses the T&amp;G of being determined to hold a strike and of making no attempt to co-operate on helping the company meet its cost-cutting goals.</p>
<p>The showdown between a tough management team led by BA chief executive Robert Ayling and Britain's main transport union is the first major dispute under the new Labour government. It comes as another major British employer, banking giant Barclays, faces a strike ballot by its workers over a new pay structure.</p>
<p>City analysts estimate the threat of strikes has already cost BA some 25 million pounds in lost bookings.</p>
<p>&quot;Airlines are very operationally geared so if you have a strike the effect on profits is pretty significant and pretty rapid,&quot; the airline analyst said.</p>
<p>Rival airline Virgin said it was already enjoying knock-on sales from the strike threat: &quot;...Passengers have already voted with their feet. We looked at the idea of running a (advertising) campaign, but our level of bookings and enquiries has already risen,&quot; a spokesman said.</p>
<p>T&amp;G spokesman Murray said &quot;independent&quot; reports reckoned the strikes could halve BA's profits this year. Last year BA earned 470 million sterling in pre-tax profits.</p>
<p>&quot;If the dispute stops all flights then the cost to BA per day is about 20 million pounds, though it's unlikely that the whole fleet will stop, so the figure would be a portion of that&quot; the City analyst said.</p>
<p>So far, however, the investment community is taking a sanguine view of the dispute. BA shares shed a modest 2-1/2p to 677-1/2 in a falling market by 1445 GMT.</p>
<p>&quot;The way the City sees it is strike costs are a one-off and unless the strikes go on for a long-time investors won't get too concerned,&quot; the industry analyst said, adding the main worry was BA losing its competitiveness against other European airlines.</p>
<p>&quot;If the strikes drag on, investors, not to mention the customers, will find that increasingly upsetting.&quot; ($ = 0.591 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
