<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711185" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: UK's BBC defends executive pay rises.</title>
<headline>UK's BBC defends executive pay rises.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The chairman of the BBC on Monday defended a pay rise of almost 20 percent awarded to the corporation's director-general last year.</p>
<p>Director-general John Birt, whose cost-saving and restructuring measures have provoked great controversy, received 354,000 pounds ($598,000) in salary, bonus and benefits in 1996/97 -- up from 299,000 pounds last year.</p>
<p>The increase provoked criticism from sections of the media and angered unions who accused the BBC, mainly funded by an annual licence fee levy on the public, of paying &quot;private sector wages&quot;.</p>
<p>BBC chairman Sir Christopher Bland, part of the committee which awarded the rise, said the BBC had to pay figures which were broadly in line with the market.</p>
<p>&quot;We used extensive outside surveys. These figures were not lightly arrived at. We think it was appropriate to fix these salary levels,&quot; he said. Bland said that almost all of the BBC's leading executives could command higher salaries if they were to seek jobs outside the corporation.</p>
<p>He noted that Birt's salary was roughly comparable to that of Richard Eyre, chief executive of commerical broadcaster Capital Radio Plc or Nigel Walmsley, a director of commercial TV company Carlton Communications Plc.</p>
<p>Members of the BBC's 10-strong executive committee also enjoy perks such as chauffeur-driven cars for business use and a company car and free petrol for private use. Bland said these fringe benefits were in line with the average in industry.($ = 0.591 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
