<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711255" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Key dates in run-up to latest Northern Ireland violence.</title>
<headline>Key dates in run-up to latest Northern Ireland violence.</headline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Northern Ireland was gripped by violence again on Sunday night as nationalist rioters vented their fury at a Protestant Orange Order march through Catholic areas in the town of Portadown.</p>
<p>The drive for peace in Northern Ireland is again on a knife edge. Here is a chronology of the past three years:</p>
<p>Sept 1, 1994 - The outlawed Irish Republic Army, fighting to oust Britain from the province, starts ceasefire.</p>
<p>Oct 14 - Pro-British &quot;Loyalist&quot; guerrillas start truce.</p>
<p>Dec 9 -  British officials hold first public meeting with Sinn Fein, political wing of IRA, in 22 years.</p>
<p>Feb 22, 1995 - British Prime Minister John Major and Irish Premier John Bruton unveil joint framework document on a Northern Irish political settlement.</p>
<p>March 22 - British minister holds first talks with leaders of Protestant political parties linked to loyalist guerrillas.</p>
<p>May 10 - Britain ends 23-year ban on ministerial talks with Sinn Fein.</p>
<p>June 18 - Sinn Fein breaks off exploratory peace talks with Britain, angered at British attitude to IRA arms.</p>
<p>Sept 5 - Ireland abruptly postpones summit talks with Britain, refusing to link future all-party peace talks to London's insistence that IRA guerrillas disarm.</p>
<p>Sept 19 - Spokesmen for loyalist gunmen hold their first peace talks with the Irish government.</p>
<p>Nov 28 - London and Dublin announce &quot;twin-track&quot; process setting end of February 1996 for start of all-party talks and announcing commission to study arms issue.</p>
<p>Nov 30 - U.S President Bill Clinton visits Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>Dec 15 - International commission under former U.S. senator George Mitchell tries to resolve weapons row.</p>
<p>Dec 19 - Sinn Fein holds first ministerial talks under twin-track process.</p>
<p>Jan 24, 1996 - Mitchell proposes talks alongside phased surrender of guerrilla weapons. Instead, Major proposes elections in Northern Ireland to pave way for talks.</p>
<p>Feb 9 - An IRA statement says it is abandoning the ceasefire. A bomb blast in the docklands in the east of London area injures 100 people and kills two.</p>
<p>Feb 18 - IRA bomb explodes on bus in London killing the guerrilla who was carrying it and injuring eight others.</p>
<p>Feb 28 - Major and Bruton revive peace process and announce June 10 date for all-party talks. They say Sinn Fein will stay outside unless the IRA ceasefire restarts.</p>
<p>May 30 - Elections in Northern Ireland for Peace Talks Forum, to run alongside all-party peace talks, see Sinn Fein increase their share of vote to 15 percent.</p>
<p>June 10 - Multi-party talks on the future of Northern Ireland begin in Belfast, but Sinn Fein is excluded.</p>
<p>June 15 - IRA bomb explodes in the centre of Manchester, northern England injuring more than 200.</p>
<p>July 6 - Police ban Protestant Orange Order march planned for the next day through a Catholic area of Portadown. Northern Ireland is gripped by a wave of rioting.</p>
<p>July 11 - In an about-turn police reverse their ban on the march and allow 2,000 Protestants to walk along the Garvaghy Road area of Portadown.</p>
<p>July 12 - After a night of Catholic riots in which three policemen were shot and wounded, tens of thousands of Protestants parade their British loyalty.</p>
<p>Oct 7 - IRA stages first bombing in Northern Ireland for more than two years, attacking British army headquarters. A soldier is killed and 30 other people injured.</p>
<p>May 1 - Labour wins landslide British election victory, ousting John Major's Conservatives. Sinn Fein President Gerry Adams and his lieutenant Martin McGuiness win seats but refuse to swear oath of allegiance to Queen Elizabeth and are barred from using parliamentary facilities.</p>
<p>May 21 - Britain's new Labour government ends 16-month ban on contacts with Sinn Fein and holds talks.</p>
<p>June 6 - Centre-right opposition led by Bertie Ahern's Fianna Fail wins narrow victory in Irish election.</p>
<p>June 21 - British Prime Minister Tony Blair warns Sinn Fein time is running out for it to join talks after a restoration of the IRA ceasefire. A bomb explodes in Belfast under a car carrying a prominent member of an Irish republican group, injuring three.</p>
<p>June 16 - IRA guerrillas shoot dead two Northern Irish policemen. Britain breaks off contact with Sinn Fein.</p>
<p>June 25 - Blair unveils new proposals including an independent commission to oversee the scrapping of guerrilla arms in parallel with talks on a political settlement, echoing original suggestions by Mitchell.</p>
<p>June 26 - Ahern becomes prime minister in minority Irish government after winning the backing of independents including Sinn Fein.</p>
<p>June 30 - Blair meets Ahern to discuss Northern Ireland.</p>
<p>July 6 - The Orange Order march goes ahead after talks to avert it fail. The march sparks new rioting.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
