<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711201" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Barclays urges anti-strike vote.</title>
<headline>Barclays urges anti-strike vote.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Barclays Plc Plc on Monday urged its staff to vote against strike action in a ballot called by banking unions UNiFI and BIFU.</p>
<p>The bank accused the unions of ignoring the views of the &quot;silent majority&quot; and said it estimated that only one in six members of Barclays staff voted in favour of holding the strike ballot.</p>
<p>&quot;Such a low turnout does not suggest that union members have any enthusiasm for industrial action,&quot; a Barclays spokesman said in a statement. &quot;The silent majority of members clearly tore their ballot papers up.&quot;</p>
<p>The spokesman warned that staff who take industrial action will be in breach of their contracts.</p>
<p>Barclays said union claims it is instigating a pay and pensions freeze were &quot;simply untrue&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;All staff have the potential to increase their earnings in the future through salary increases and/or performance related bonuses,&quot; the Barclays spokesman added.</p>
<p>The ballot, being conducted by unions UNiFI and BIFU, asks members if they are prepared to take industrial action including two- or three-day strikes and a ban on overtime, BIFU said in a statement earlier.</p>
<p>Balloting is due to finish on July 24.</p>
<p>The unions, which together represent more than three quarters of all Barclays staff, opposed what they called Barclays' plan to impose a new pay and grading structure based on performance which will result in a pay and pensions freeze for over half of staff.</p>
<p>The motive behind the company's plan is to cut staff costs and to cap staff's potential earnings, the unions said.</p>
<p>&quot;To cap pay at a time when Barclays are making 2.35 billion stg profit is immoral,&quot; Jim Lowe, assistant secretary at BIFU, said.</p>
<p>Barclays denied its plan will produce a pay freeze but has conceded that staff whose pay is at the top of a particular salary band would not get a pay rise regardless of whether they exceeded their agreed performance plan.</p>
<p>But the Bank said over time, salary bands will move, allowing staff headroom to receive a performance-related increase.</p>
<p>-- Joe Ortiz, London Newsroom +44 171 542 8864</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
