<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711235" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: N.Ireland violence puts off peace for months.</title>
<headline>N.Ireland violence puts off peace for months.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hill</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's handling of a Protestant parade has alienated the Catholic minority in Northern Ireland and set back fragile hopes of a new IRA guerrilla ceasefire for months, analysts said on Monday.</p>
<p>It has blown holes in the credibility of the new Labour government among Catholics, undermined the position of the IRA's political wing, Sinn Fein, among its own rank and file, and rendered current Anglo-Irish peace irrelevant, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see a new IRA ceasefire until September at the earliest, and that's probably being ultra-optimistic,&quot; said Paul Arthur, professor of politics at the University of Ulster.</p>
<p>The explosion of anger, still smouldering at street corners across the province in the wrecks of cars hijacked and torched by rioters overnight, seems to have blackened the once-bright credentials of Britain's new government among Catholics.</p>
<p>The name of Mo Mowlam, Labour's Northern Ireland Secretary, joined that of her Conservative predecessor, Patrick Mayhew, in obscene murals painted on gable ends of Catholic ghettos during the night in a display of Catholic fury.</p>
<p>Analysts said the challenge posed by Sunday's Orange Order march from a church at Drumcree down the Catholic Garvaghy Road was a big test of Blair's promise to respect the rights of the Protestant majority and Catholic minority equally.</p>
<p>And it failed, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;Drumcree was Northern Ireland in a microcosm. By allowing it down Garvaghy Road, it confirmed that Labour is like every other government and will take the Protestant side,&quot; said Henry Patterson, reader in politics at Queens University.</p>
<p>Analysts said the weekend violence, some of the worst for decades, had created a chasm of mistrust between Irish nationalists and Blair's government as well as between Blair and the new Irish government of Prime Minister Bertie Ahern.</p>
<p>Ahern, whose Fianna Fail party sees itself as the mainstream voice of Irish nationalism, pledged to &quot;stand up for nationalists&quot; in his election campaign and barely hid his anger at the Portadown parade in a weekend diplomatic statement.</p>
<p>It expressed &quot;disappointment&quot; at the decision to sanction the march route the Orange Order chose. Early talks between Blair and Ahern to put on a united front against violence and for their Anglo-Irish peace talks was likely, they said.</p>
<p>But in the immediate future, prospects on the streets of Northern Ireland were for Catholic riots and attacks by the Irish Republican Army (IRA) in the countdown to the July 12 climax of the Protestant &quot;marching season&quot; and beyond.</p>
<p>&quot;It's difficult to see how any progress can be made while we count down to the 12th of July and beyond. It will take an awful lot of private, confidential, confidence-building talks with Irish Republicans,&quot; Patterson told Reuters.</p>
<p>The rioting also posed serious problems for the leadership of Sinn Fein in trying to persuade the Irish Republican Army and hardline nationalists that it was worth joining Anglo-Irish peace talks both governments tout as the only route to peace.</p>
<p>The IRA, which has fought since 1969 to end British rule of Northern Ireland and merge it with neighbouring Ireland, and various splinter groups were on the streets of Belfast overnight in a show of armed force not seen since the 1970s.</p>
<p>Sinn Fein president Gerry Adams and his de facto deputy, Martin McGuinness, have been struggling to persuade hardline IRA elements that the Anglo-Irish peace talks with their pro-British Unionist foes are worth joining at all.</p>
<p>The price of admission Blair has asked is a credible ceasefire and a commitment to democracy, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;The mistrust of the British government is deeper at the rank and file level and their leaders won't move until they can bring the rank and file on board,&quot; Arthur told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;This weekend's problems underline the problems McGuinness and Adams have in persuading their own people that the British government is serious about change in Northern Ireland when they can't even get a march (Drumcree) rerouted,&quot; Patterson said.</p>
<p>On the negotiating table is a set of Anglo-Irish proposals called Framework Documents to blur the border the IRA wants to tear down by creating cross-frontier parliamentary and trade bodies to create new trust between the two Irelands.</p>
<p>&quot;The Framework Documents aren't enough for the IRA but Adams and McGuinness know that that's all there is on offer. They will have awful problems trying to sell that now,&quot; Patterson said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
