<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711204" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Rare show of sympathy for UK's royal mistress.</title>
<headline>Rare show of sympathy for UK's royal mistress.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>For years she was the woman Britons loved to hate, blamed for turning the fairtyale marriage of Prince Charles and Princess Diana into a nightmare of divorce.</p>
<p>But Camilla Parker Bowles, the commoner whose 20-year love affair with Britain's future king has both appalled and fascinated the nation, may at last be winning some friends.</p>
<p>Two television programmes over the weekend seriously aired the possibility of Charles at last marrying Parker Bowles, 26 years after they first met.</p>
<p>And after years of vilification in the media, public sympathy seems at last to be turning her way.</p>
<p>&quot;A re-marriage may not be ideal but it is better than an affair outside marriage,&quot; the Archdeacon of York George Austen told a BBC debate on the future of Charles's relationship with Parker Bowles, who turns 50 later this month.</p>
<p>&quot;I believe there are grounds for accepting a second marriage, even though it may not be the kind of moral lead we might have expected from a king,&quot; Austen added.</p>
<p>The BBC debate, bringing together politicians, constitutional experts and churchmen, was broadcast on the same night as an hour-long documentary about Parker Bowles that was seen as a watershed.</p>
<p>Although short on revelations and made without any cooperation from Parker Bowles or her close friends, it painted a picture of a woman wronged by a public still all too ready to embrace the younger and infinitely more glamorous Diana.</p>
<p>In a surprising about-turn, several British newspapers on Monday lined up with Parker Bowles who has never spoken publicly about her love for Charles, heir to the British throne, nor complained about her treatment in the press.</p>
<p>&quot;Surely it is time to take a fresh look at this troubling state of affairs. We should accept that Camilla is the one person in this unfortunate royal love triangle who has behaved with perfect decorum,&quot; wrote Ingrid Seward, editor of Majesty magazine, in the Daily Mail newspaper.</p>
<p>Seward dismissed suggestions the television programmes were part of an attempt by Charles and his friend to make Parker Bowles more acceptable to the public.</p>
<p>&quot;What is more likely is that events have simply caught up with this humorous, laid-back sturdy woman who is the cynosure of Charles's affections,&quot; she wrote.</p>
<p>Charles and Camilla first met in 1971 but after a two-year love affair she married cavalry officer Andrew Parker Bowles. In a fateful 1994 television confession, Charles admitted that they had resumed their affair but said it happened once his marriage to Diana had irretreviably broken down.</p>
<p>Even Diana's own admission a year later of adultery with cavalry officer James Hewitt failed to save Charles and Camilla from a wave of public scorn which extended to the entire institution of monarchy.</p>
<p>Charles and Diana divorced a year ago and Parker Bowles is also now divorced but until now, Diana has won the lion's share of the sympathy vote.</p>
<p>Penny Junor, a former biographer of prince Charles, said few women had been so seriously and unfairly misjudged.</p>
<p>The real Parker Bowles, Junor wrote in the Sun, &quot;says what she thinks, laughs long and loud when something amuses her, has no pretensions, no guile; she is mildly chaotic, refreshingly uncomplicated and totally uninterested in style.&quot;</p>
<p>Charles has made clear that he has no intention of giving up Parker Bowles, despite overwhelming hostility evident in opinion polls to the idea of a Queen Camilla. He has also said he has no plans to remarry.</p>
<p>But he and Camilla see each other frequently, hold private dinner parties and the media report that Charles plans to take a holiday with her for the first time later this year.</p>
<p>Constitutional experts and churchmen recently posed the idea of a morganatic marriage between Charles and Parker Bowles, under which she would be precluded from becoming queen and from having any claims on the monarchy.</p>
<p>However the situation is complicated by Charles' position when he becomes king as Supreme Governor of the Church of England -- which frowns on divorce.</p>
<p>&quot;A morganatic marriage solves the State's problem but not that of the Church of England...It will have to take a view as to whether its own Supreme Governor can not only be divorced but be married to somebody who is divorced,&quot; said Conservative MP Anne Widdecombe.</p>
<p>Charles Benson, the only &quot;friend&quot; to break the silence from Parker Bowles's circle, appealed to Britons to abandon hypocrisy and apply the same standards to Charles and Camilla as they do to their own lives.</p>
<p>&quot;I think they are entitled to each other. They've had all the hell, why should they not have some pleasures?&quot; he said in the documentary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
