<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711266" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Flood swamps Devil Fish in European poker showdown.</title>
<headline>Flood swamps Devil Fish in European poker showdown.</headline>
<byline>James Saft</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A turn of a single card -- a lowly four -- sent Liam Flood back to Ireland 44,125 pounds ($74,600) richer and champion of the European Festival of Poker.</p>
<p>Flood had built an insurmountable lead and it was only a matter of time before he knocked out his last opponent, Dave Ulliott of Hull, a poker pro dubbed &quot;Devil Fish&quot; by Asian gamblers in Las Vegas. The four clinched it.</p>
<p>Billed as the biggest poker tournament outside the U.S, the weekend event saw 71 players put up 1,500 pounds each to compete at no-limit Texas Hold 'em.</p>
<p>Hold 'em is the Cadillac of poker games, a fast-paced version of stud where each player holds only two cards and makes a hand from five shared cards dealt onto the table.</p>
<p>At the highest level, tournament Hold 'em is played no limit, meaning players can bet their entire stack of chips at any time, and play continues until one player has won all the chips.</p>
<p>It took two days, with breaks for food and sleep, to get down to the final three contestants -- Flood, Ulliott and Surinder Sunar, a former electrical engineer from Wolverhampton whose skill at the table has long since eased him from his profession.</p>
<p>Early Sunday evening Flood had a marginal lead over Sunar, with Ulliott a distant third. Flood kept firing away at Sunar, who has a reputation of bluffing wins on small pots, making large raises almost every time Sunar bet.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of the time I wasn't holding anything,&quot; Flood, a retired bookmaker from County Kildare said. &quot;But I had the chips and I bet.&quot;</p>
<p>On the final hand Flood had nothing more than a four and a seven, a truly terrible hand, but his huge advantage in chips meant he would play them to the showdown.</p>
<p>Ulliott, a vision of Vegas dripping in diamond encrusted gold and wearing sunglasses, had a king and a nine, a good hand for this stage of the game.</p>
<p>The first four cards dealt improved no one's hand, so when the last card was a four Flood walked away the winner with just a pair of fours.</p>
<p>Ulliott got second place money of 22,062 pounds and Sunar won 13,237.</p>
<p>At this level the top players are all extremely aggressive, said Al Alvarez, the poet and author, whose book &quot;The Biggest Game in Town&quot; is a classic poker text.</p>
<p>&quot;Everybody knows the odds but the classy players know how to intimidate and they know how to charm,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The big money players are men, mostly, who are given to the vices of those who spend all their time indoors and stay up late every night. Pot bellies are common, though less so than in Las Vegas, and a pall of cigarette smoke floats over the tables.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
