<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711209" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Pru to move management of Scotam funds.</title>
<headline>Pru to move management of Scotam funds.</headline>
<text>
<p>LONDON, July 7 (Reuter) British insurance giant Prudential Corp Plc said on Monday it had decided to transfer management of Scottish Amicable's policyholders' funds from Glasgow to its London investment operation PPM, following the acquisition of the mutual insurer in March.</p>
<p>The Pru also said it would accept Britannia Investment Managers' offer for its 800 million pound ($1.4 billion) third party institutional funds.</p>
<p>Fear of job losses in Scotland was a contentious issue during the battle for control of ScotAm and the Pru's winning bid included a guarantee that job levels at ScotAm's Craigforth headquarters near Stirling would be maintained for three years.</p>
<p>However, those assurances did not include the investment mangement operation.</p>
<p>The Pru had said it would consider the possibility of continuing a fund mangement activity in Glasgow but Derek Higgs, chairman of PPM said it had concluded it was not &quot;economically supportable&quot; for ScotAm's investment business to continue in its present form.</p>
<p>Nor was there a basis for locating particular investment functions of an enlarged PPM in Glasgow, he added.</p>
<p>ScotAm managing director Roy Nicolson said he regretted that the fund management operation could not have been retained in Glasgow.</p>
<p>&quot;However, it was not viable to do so and therefore not in our policyholders interests,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>ScotAm's investment business (SAIM) employs 125 staff including 25 fund managers. Of those 15-20 will move to Britannia.</p>
<p>The Pru said it would be discussing work opportunities in London with SAIM's other professional staff and had guaranteed jobs to the balance of back office staff until the end of the year. It said it hoped there would be no compulsory lay-offs as a result of today's move.</p>
<p>The formal transfer of management of Scottish Amicable's 15 billion pound ($25.4 billion) investments to PPM takes place on September 30 subject to court and regulatory approval of the takeover. ($ = 0.591 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81501">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I8150103">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
