<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711343" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkish coalition to push anti-Islamist schooling.</title>
<headline>Turkish coalition to push anti-Islamist schooling.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's new secularist government said on Monday it would extend primary education at the expense of religious schools in an apparent effort to curtail the next generation of Islamists.</p>
<p>&quot;Eight years of uninterrupted, obligatory education will be put into practice,&quot; the government said in a policy document to be read out in parliament later in the day.</p>
<p>Turkish children currently spend five years in primary schools after which they can enroll in Islamic schools. Islamists fear that plans to increase the period of basic education would force the closure of religious schools.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a basic aim (of the government) to train people equipped with the knowledge and capability to deal with the information age...and assimilate Ataturk's principles and reforms,&quot; the document said in reference to Turkey's secularist founder Kemal Ataturk.</p>
<p>The number of religious schools, known as Imam Hatips, has grown in recent years but they are still in the minority.</p>
<p>Deputy Prime Minister Bulent Ecevit said the government, a left-right coalition forged last week to keep the Islamists from power, would ask parliament to pass a secularist education bill soon.</p>
<p>&quot;We are determined on this issue, both as a government and a party,&quot; Anatolian news agency quoted Ecevit as telling his Democratic Left Party.</p>
<p>&quot;We will put forward a bill to parliament after the confidence vote,&quot; he said. Yilmaz faces a confidence vote in parliament on July 12. He is expected to win.</p>
<p>The Islamist-led government of former prime minister Necmettin Erbakan stalled on army demands to extend secularist education to eight years in a row over Islamist activism.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
