<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711318" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkey's Yilmaz sets out anti-Islamist policies.</title>
<headline>Turkey's Yilmaz sets out anti-Islamist policies.</headline>
<byline>Hidir Goktas</byline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Turkish Prime Minister Mesut Yilmaz pledged to boost secularist education and knock harder on the European Union's door in a Monday keynote speech that set out his anti-Islamist policies.</p>
<p>&quot;Our nation does not want to go through the hardship it went through in the previous period,&quot; Yilmaz told parliament. &quot;Our government's fight is that of democracy and virtue,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Yilmaz, a conservative, took office last week to replace Necmettin Erbakan who resigned under army pressure after a stormy year as Turkey's first Islamist prime minister.</p>
<p>He said his left-right coalition would curtail the next generation of Islamists by extending primary education at the expense of religious schools.</p>
<p>&quot;Eight years of uninterrupted, obligatory education will be put into practice,&quot; he said, reading out a government blueprint for future action.</p>
<p>Turkish children spend five years in primary schools after which they can enroll in Islamic schools. Islamists fear that plans to increase the period of basic education would force the closure of religious schools.</p>
<p>The new government, set up to prevent an Islamist return to office, is expected to win a confidence vote set for July 12 and then stay in power for around a year until early elections.</p>
<p>The army's demands to extend secularist education were one of the main causes of a row over Islamist activism between the previous government and the powerful generals.</p>
<p>The number of religious schools, known as Imam Hatips, has grown in recent years but they are still in the minority.</p>
<p>Deputy Prime Minister Bulent Ecevit said the government would ask parliament to pass a secularist education bill soon.</p>
<p>&quot;We are determined on this issue, both as a government and a party,&quot; Anatolian news agency quoted Ecevit as telling his Democratic Left Party.</p>
<p>Yilmaz said his government would persevere with the country's difficult bid for membership of the EU. &quot;Turkey will ensure its rightful place in the new Europe that is being drawn up,&quot; he told MPs.</p>
<p>Erbakan's coalition was slow in making needed legislative changes to comply with a customs union that gives Turkey some of the closest ties to the EU of any non-member country.</p>
<p>A shaky economy, disputes with EU member Greece and a poor human rights record all stand in the way of Turkish membership.</p>
<p>Yilmaz said he would give a high priority to reducing inflation and cuttting a budget deficit that reached 720 trillion lira ($4.8 billion) in the first half of this year.</p>
<p>He promised to speed up privatisation, despite previous objections to sell offs from Ecevit's leftist party.</p>
<p>The Islamists poured scorn on the government's programme. &quot;Socialist, statist thought has been applied in some places, while other bits outline unrepentant capitalism,&quot; said Islam-based Welfare Party spokesman Oguzhan Asilturk.</p>
<p>The government gave strong backing to the self-declared Turkish Cypriot state in northern Cyprus and said the divided island was vital to Turkey's security, in an apparent hardening of Ankara's stance.</p>
<p>&quot;Cyprus is important not just because of the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus but because it is of crucial important from the point of view of Turkey's own security,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Leftist Ecevit, a former prime minister, gave the order for Turkey to invade the island in 1974 after a Greek Cypriot coup and he is still known as a hawk on the Cyprus issue.</p>
<p>Cypriot President Glafcos Clerides and Turkish Cypriot leader Rauf Denktash are to hold talks in the United States this week in their first meeting for three years. ($1 = 150,150 lira)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
