<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711419" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Healthdyne seeking alternatives to Invacare bid.</title>
<headline>Healthdyne seeking alternatives to Invacare bid.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Healthdyne Technologies Inc. said Monday that it was actively pursuing alternatives to a hostile takeover bid by Invacare Corp. after a federal judge denied an Invacare request to overturn part of Healthdyne's shareholder rights plan, or &quot;poison pill.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;While nothing is certain, we hope to announce a value enhancing transaction in the next several weeks,&quot; said Parker Petit, chairman of Marietta, Ga.-based Healthdyne.</p>
<p>Invacare has launched a $200 million hostile bid for Healthdyne, which the maker of advanced medical devices has repeatedly rejected as inadequate.</p>
<p>A federal judge in Atlanta ruled last Thursday that Invacare, a medical equipment manufacturer, had failed to prove it would suffer irreparable harm if the preliminary injunction it sought was not issued.</p>
<p>Elyria, Ohio-based Invacare had sought the preliminary injunction to invalidate the portion of the pill known as a &quot;continuing directors,&quot; or &quot;deadhand&quot; provision.</p>
<p>The provision prohibits a new slate of directors from overturning Healthdyne's poison pill, which makes it prohibitively expensive for an investor to amass more than 5 percent of the company.</p>
<p>Invacare, which argued that the Healthdyne provision is illegal, has launched a proxy fight to install its own directors in order to take control of the company and abolish the poision pill.</p>
<p>&quot;Now, Invacare, even if it wins the proxy contest, can't eliminate our shareholder rights plan to facilitate its grossly inadequate tender offer,&quot; Pettit said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe Judge Cooper's ruling enhances the ability of our board of directors to continue to increase shareholder value.&quot;</p>
<p>Healthdyne stock rose 50 cents to $17.125 and Invacare was unchanged at $23.125 early on Nasdaq.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I37200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
