<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711492" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spanish metal workers prepare for Thurs stoppage.</title>
<headline>Spanish metal workers prepare for Thurs stoppage.</headline>
<byline>Elisabeth O'Leary</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spanish trade unions have called a one-day strike on Thursday, outraged at government privatisation plans they fear threaten jobs in the metals sector.</p>
<p>&quot;We're protesting at industrial policy in the public sector, where there is no defined outlook for the role these companies are going to play in the future,&quot; a spokesman for leading trade union UGT told Reuters on Monday.</p>
<p>He said 52,000 workers at Spanish metal sector companies, including aerospace firm Construcciones Aeronauticas (CASA), Babcock &amp; Wilcox Espana and shipbuilders Astilleros will be participating in this 24-hour strike.</p>
<p>Other public sector employees are expected to join in a protest outside the Industry Ministry, unions said.</p>
<p>At present the dispute centres on plans to sell integrated aluminium producer Inespal and steel producer Corporacion Siderurgica Integral (CSI) to foreign entities.</p>
<p>The government is negotiating the sale of Inespal to Aluminium Company of America (Alcoa) by the end of this year.</p>
<p>Separately, offers for an initial 35 percent stake of CSI have been presented by France's Usinor and Italy's Ilva has also expressed interest.</p>
<p>According to unions, all employees at CSI and Inespal stopped work last Thursday for 24 hours, and further strikes for those two companies alone are planned for July 17 and 24.</p>
<p>&quot;We want to express opposition to how the privatisations are being carried out, with the state willing to lose control of these companies...and with unions having had no access to information showing what the new owners will do with them,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>Industry sources gauged last week's strike turnout at nearer 40 percent, and Inespal said the impact on aluminium output was minimal.</p>
<p>&quot;I wouldn't say it had hampered production too much,&quot; an Inespal spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>A spokesman for state holding company Sociedad Espanola de Participaciones Industriales (Sepi) agreed, adding that in any case, Alcoa's plans for Inespal did not entail any job cuts.</p>
<p>But this was met with scepticism.</p>
<p>&quot;We really don't believe that no jobs will be lost... Inespal and Alcoa doesn't want (the unions) to see their industrial plan for the firm,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>-- Madrid newsroom +341 585 2160</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22450">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I32000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C183">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
