<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711572" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO steals a march on EU in eastern Europe.</title>
<headline>NATO steals a march on EU in eastern Europe.</headline>
<byline>Paul Taylor</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>By being first to open its doors to former communist east European states, the U.S.-led NATO alliance has stolen a march on the European Union (EU), which is not due to start laborious entry negotiations until next year.</p>
<p>Partly as a result, NATO is widely popular across the former Warsaw Pact states west of the Russian border, while the EU is often criticised from Warsaw to Bucharest as being arrogant, inward-looking and stingy.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe failed to pass the test of the end of the Cold War,&quot; said Dominique Moisi of the French Institute for International Relations.</p>
<p>&quot;After the Berlin Wall fell, the EU was narcissistically obsessed with its own internal problems and failed to intervene effectively in Bosnia.&quot;</p>
<p>The fact that only American intervention eventually stopped the slaughter in former Yugoslavia reinforced a tendency in former Soviet satellite states to look to the United States and NATO for their security and prosperity.</p>
<p>While NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organisation) put enlargement at the top of its agenda, the EU concentrated first and foremost on a drive to establish a single European currency in 1999.</p>
<p>Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary can expect to be fully fledged members of the Western alliance in 1999. But they face years of haggling over farm subsidies, labour migration and transitional arrangements before they join the 15-nation EU.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac, backed by German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, charged around central Europe last year telling the most economically developed new democracies he wanted them in the EU by the year 2000.</p>
<p>But the European Commission estimates the first newcomers cannot realistically expect to join before 2002, and even then they will face a long transition period before enjoying full membership benefits.</p>
<p>&quot;Joining the EU is much more complex because it involves adopting thousands of regulations, harmonising standards and negotiating transition periods,&quot; a German said. &quot;But to east Europeans, it looks like the west Europeans are deliberately dragging their feet.&quot;</p>
<p>That impression may have been compounded by the failure of last month's Amsterdam EU summit to agree on a reform of the Union's cumbersome decision-making system, which will now have to be revisited before the east Europeans can join.</p>
<p>EU officials complain that the Union has not reaped the rewards in east European public opinion of the billions of dollars it has ploughed into eastern Europe since 1989 to promote modernisation, democracy and market economies.</p>
<p>The fact that NATO enlargement is moving faster than EU expansion has raised questions about the link between the two.</p>
<p>Some west European officials resent what they say is a feeling that Washington is trying to push them into reaching out to the countries it does not want NATO to embrace.</p>
<p>For example, diplomats say the United States is pressing the EU, and the 10-nation Western European Union defence grouping, to build special ties with the Baltic states because they are unlikely to be granted NATO membership for the foreseeable future due to fierce Russian opposition.</p>
<p>But some analysts see NATO expansion as driven partly by the need to fill a vacuum left by the EU's inward focus.</p>
<p>Jonathan Eyal of Britain's Royal United Services Institute said a debate among policymakers over what to do for those countries that did not join NATO immediately resulted from the EU's failure to begin &quot;separate but parallel&quot; enlargement.</p>
<p>&quot;NATO is partly a casualty of the EU's paralysis. NATO enlargement has come about as a result of a U.S. attempt to inject some coherence into (post-Cold War Europe).</p>
<p>&quot;Old division lines will be erased, but enlargement does not provide additional security for other states, notably the Baltics,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Eyal argued NATO's expansion should have &quot;shamed the EU into action&quot; that would have helped reassure those states left out of the first wave.</p>
<p>He also said the Europeans had failed to address the future relationship between the EU and NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the missing link, there is no debate yet between the two,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
