<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711515" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German health insurers mull invoice fraud action.</title>
<headline>German health insurers mull invoice fraud action.</headline>
<dateline>COLOGNE 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>German private health insurers should join with doctors' associations to set up a settlement company for private practice invoices to force out companies using doubtful business practices.</p>
<p>This was proposed by Dr Jan Boetius, management board chairman of Deutsche Krankenversicherung (DKV) in Cologne, on Monday.</p>
<p>A standardised and tested process for dealing with private bills for doctors would simplify the payment process, said Boetius.</p>
<p>At the same time it would make more difficult the manipulation practised by some settlement companies, of which private health insurers frequently complain. A few weeks ago, DKV brought charges of invoice fraud against the Saarbruecken company Unimed.</p>
<p>Boetius is convinced that such an offer would quickly be accepted by doctors, because it would reduce their paperwork considerably.</p>
<p>&quot;In addition, doctors would receive their money more rapidly, since many plausibility checks which we now make on invoices would be dropped.&quot;</p>
<p>Boetius said the project is at a very early stage, but he is confident of obtaining agreement from the medical profession.</p>
<p>The legal form which the new settlement company would take has not yet been decided.</p>
<p>&quot;I would imagine that we cannot choose a public-law system, because then the private health insurers could not take part. And with their knowledge of invoice preparation, they have to be included. It will probably not be a co-operative, but most likely a limited company.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Ilse Schlingensiepen, +49 221 512 007</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I82001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="COLOGNE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
