<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711605" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO split on enlargement hours ahead of summit.</title>
<headline>NATO split on enlargement hours ahead of summit.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Clayton</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO leaders headed to Madrid on Monday for a summit called to inaugurate a new European security order and seal the West's Cold War victory by admitting former communist enemies into the alliance.</p>
<p>But with only a day to go before the start of the historic meeting, a transatlantic row over how many countries to invite to join the most powerful military alliance ever assembled threatened to overshadow the birth of a &quot;new NATO&quot;.</p>
<p>France and Italy, backed by seven other European allies, are leading a campaign for Slovenia and Romania to be admitted to the club along with former Warsaw Pact foes Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>The United States, which has led the campaign to expand the 16-nation NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organisation), has made clear it will only back the accession of the three main candidates in the first wave.</p>
<p>&quot;The heads of government are going to have a really serious discussion on their hands,&quot; a senior alliance diplomat said. &quot;Only they are going to be able to resolve this.&quot;</p>
<p>The dispute goes to the heart of moves to build a new European security architecture by spreading NATO's &quot;zone of stability&quot; further east in parallel with new cooperative relationships with Russia and Ukraine.</p>
<p>Supporters of the wider enlargement say both Romania and Slovenia fulfill the basic criteria of a functioning democracy and market economy and their inclusion would have a positive impact on the edge of the Black Sea and Balkan danger areas.</p>
<p>They argue failure to include the two will create new divisions in Europe and leave precisely the type of security vacuum enlargement was meant to eradicate.</p>
<p>But President Bill Clinton, who says only Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic are ready for the burdens of membership, has to face growing domestic opposition to enlargement in the Republican-led Congress which must ratify the plan.</p>
<p>In a pre-summit editorial the New York Times declared: &quot;Given the absence of a clear threat to Europe and the possibility of so many unpredictable consequences, NATO expansion seems a gratuitous risk.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton, who spent the weekend relaxing with King Juan Carlos on the Spanish holiday island of Majorca, has ruled out any compromise, angering Europeans sensitive to accusations they are mere spectators at a U.S.-run NATO show.</p>
<p>Before the two-day summit officially kicks off on Tuesday, a series of high-level meetings has been slated to try to agree the consensus by which NATO operates.</p>
<p>Clinton was to hold talks with Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar and NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana later on Monday while alliance foreign ministers planned to debate the issue over dinner.</p>
<p>NATO officials say they do not expect the differences to go so far as to derail the summit. They predict a &quot;lively discussion&quot; with the Europeans pushing for strong commitments of future enlargements before backing down.</p>
<p>Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi urged Clinton on Monday to trust European judgement on the issue.</p>
<p>&quot;Europe cannot be denied its views on problems in its own region,&quot; he told the International Herald Tribune.</p>
<p>&quot;We should not forget that ethnic rivalry inside Romania was one of our nightmares regarding the future of Eastern Europe, and they have resolved the issue,&quot; he added, saying Italy would stick to its position.</p>
<p>Germany, Europe's wealthiest and largest state, could be crucial to the final outcome, but -- reflecting divisions between military and political advocates -- is itself divided.</p>
<p>Defence Minister Volker Ruehe said on Sunday the first wave should be limited to three members even though Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel said Bonn could support adding five.</p>
<p>&quot;There are not five but 12 states wanting to enter NATO and there is no way we could take in all 12 at once,&quot; Ruehe said. &quot;That is why I favour starting with a small group. That would be easier for NATO to digest.&quot;</p>
<p>NATO's military experts fear a wider enlargement could make the alliance unwieldy and reduce its effectiveness, particularly as it comes at the same time as an overhaul of its command structures equipping it for more Bosnia-style peace missions.</p>
<p>Solana said on Saturday there was no consensus yet on the number of states to be let in, nor on any assurance to be given to those who do not join in the first wave, probably in 1999.</p>
<p>But he said the summit would still be a success.</p>
<p>&quot;Out of this alliance and out of this summit, everybody will be a winner from the point of view of security. No country will be a loser,&quot; he told a Madrid news conference.</p>
<p>&quot;We are not going to create new divisions in Europe. On the contrary, we are going to erase them.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. officials said they were braced for a blast from President Jacques Chirac who has said Paris' conditions for rejoining NATO's military wing have not yet been met.</p>
<p>Chirac's spokesman said last week, however, that Paris would not &quot;take hostage&quot; the leading three countries about which all agreed, just to press for the inclusion of Romania and Slovenia.</p>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin who signed the Founding Act of a new, cooperative relationship with NATO at a summit in May, has stayed away from Madrid to avoid giving the impression of endorsing the expansion Russia still dislikes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
