<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711684" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: LOSING BIDDER FOR HUNGARY TV CHANNELS TO SUE.</title>
<headline>LOSING BIDDER FOR HUNGARY TV CHANNELS TO SUE.</headline>
<byline>Denes Albert</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The losing bidder for two new Hungarian commercial TV channels said on Monday it would take legal action against Hungary's radio and television body ORTT but ORTT said this will not delay the signing of the concession contracts.</p>
<p>The losing Irisz TV, a CME-led consortium made up of US-based Central Media Enterprises and Hungarian companies, Mediacom, Intercom and DDTV Kft, announced on Monday it was challenging the decision and asked a court to forbid the signing of the concession contracts.</p>
<p>&quot;The ORTT seriously breached the regulations when assessing the bids and violated the tender procedures,&quot; Irisz TV said in a statement.</p>
<p>ORTT announced on June 30 that the ten-year concessions were awarded to Luxembourg-based CLT's Magyar RTL and MTM-SBS and on Monday said the lawsuit would not delay finalising the deal.</p>
<p>&quot;ORTT will shortly sign the contracts with the winners,&quot; ORTT Chairman Mihaly Revesz told Reuters.</p>
<p>The CLT-led consortium, Magyar RTL, is owned by a consortium of CLT-UFA, Raiffeisen Unicbank, the UK Pearson group , publisher of the Financial Times, and Hungarian telecom company Matav.</p>
<p>MTM-SBS is a consortium of the Hungarian-registered company MTM Kommunikacios Rt, TeleMunchen and the majority US-owned company Scandinavian Broadcasting System.</p>
<p>Magyar RTL offered 9 billion forints for the commercial channel it won, while MTM-SBS offered the set minimum of 8 billion forints for the other commercial channel.</p>
<p>Irisz TV offered 12.5 billion and 12 billion forints, respectively.</p>
<p>The eight-member ORTT board's first attempt to select the winners failed.</p>
<p>Five of the eight-person board are delegated by opposition parties, two other members are delegated by the ruling parties while the president of the board is neutral.</p>
<p>During the second round, newspapers reported that an expert's opinion quoted by an opposition member of the board, was that Irisz TV's business plan was not consistent with the higher price it offered.</p>
<p>However, an earlier assesment of the tenders by a consortium of four independent companies judged all four offers to be consistent with the business plans.</p>
<p>ORTT said at the time of the decision that one important factor in the decision was the future diversity of Hungary's media scene and that the verdict was unanimous but for one abstention.</p>
<p>The decision brings to an end seven years of political wrangling which has left Hungary's media privatisation trailing behind other former communist countries such as Poland and the Czech Republic, which already have commercial national television stations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47510">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
