<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711740" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: ONS says UK export levels held up in May.</title>
<headline>ONS says UK export levels held up in May.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Office for National Statistics said on Monday that UK export levels held up in May and were not responsible for the monthl-on-month fall in manufacturing ouput.</p>
<p>&quot;The proportion of exports remains in line with recent experience, that is with the levels seen in  the last year or so,&quot; a statistician said.</p>
<p>He said the sharp monthly drop in manufacturing output of 1.1 percent -- the biggest since June 1993 -- was a result of a fall in sales both at home and abroad.</p>
<p>In the three months to May, output of non-durable goods fell  </p>
<p>by 0.2 percent compared with the previous three.</p>
<p>There were decreases in all sub-sectors -- a 0.3 percent fall in the ouput of clothing and footwear and 0.2 percent in the output of both food, drink and tobacco and in other non-durable goods industries.</p>
<p>Output of investment goods rose by 1.0 percent in the three months to May versus the previous three. Intermediate goods output fell by 0.6 percent in the period and increase of 0.1 percent in the ouput of materials was not enough to offset a fall of 1.8 percent in the output of fuels.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
