<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711799" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia coal industry has worst disputes record-govt.</title>
<headline>Australia coal industry has worst disputes record-govt.</headline>
<dateline>BRISBANE 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian Industrial Relations minister Peter Reith said on Monday he backed efforts by the Rio Tinto Ltd-owned Coal and Allied Industries Ltd to push for work-place reform at its Hunter Valley coal mine in New South Wales.</p>
<p>&quot;I'd like to see the company work to overcome inefficiencies in the industry,&quot; Reith told reporters on Monday.</p>
<p>Reith stressed he was not telling Rio Tinto how to run its dispute from the sidelines &quot;but if they are focussing on inefficiencies in the industry, there's a lot to look at.&quot;</p>
<p>The dispute involves Coal and Allied and the Construction, Mining, Forestry and Energy (CFMEU) union over individual work contracts at the group's No 1 coal mine near Scone.  </p>
<p>Reith said the coal industry had a poor record in terms of the number of disputes annually.</p>
<p>&quot;In fact they have the worst record in the country,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Reith said coal industry figures showed the number of days lost was 7,707 days per 1,000 employees per year compared with between 120 and 130 days lost for the rest of the Australian workforce.</p>
<p>&quot;The unions have to ask themselves if their political gamesmanship is in the long-term interests of their members,&quot; Reith said.</p>
<p>Reith said the use of secondary boycott provisions in the new Industrial Relations Act was a matter for the company.</p>
<p>Many companies in the coal sector had already used provisions now available under new legislation which came into force on January 1.</p>
<p>&quot;We certainly encourage parties to use the full range of options available under the Industrial Relations Act,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Unless they can get things onto a more efficient productive level, we are going to lose jobs, we are going to lose export income,&quot; Reith said.</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800 (c) Reuters Limited 1997</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRISBANE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
