<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711795" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Britain's foxhunters stage &quot;peasants' revolt&quot;.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Britain's foxhunters stage &quot;peasants' revolt&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>FERNHILL HEATH, England 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's foxhunters are staging what they call a Peasants' Revolt to fight plans by a member of the new Labour government to ban their sport.</p>
<p>Michael Foster, who represents the city of Worcester in the heart of England, came top of a ballot held to allow members of parliament to introduce their own legislation and he has put forward a bill to ban hunting.</p>
<p>Foster, whose bill would ban the hunting of foxes, deer, hares and mink with dogs, has denounced hunting as a &quot;cruel and barbaric practice which should have ended centuries ago along with cock-fighting, bear-baiting and dog-fighting&quot;.</p>
<p>Although its passage through parliament is by no means sure, Foster's bill is probably the gravest threat that foxhunting, an integral part of country life for thousands of people, has faced over the centuries.</p>
<p>Now the country is coming to the town, in the form of a mass rally expected to bring 100,000 protesters together in London's Hyde Park on July 10.</p>
<p>Buses, trains and even aircraft are being chartered to bring hunt supporters to the capital for a day they hope will convince the government that opposition to a ban is stronger than many MPs believe.</p>
<p>Hardier hunt supporters have already begun marching on London from Scotland, Wales and Cornwall and are due to arrive on the day of the rally. Those who cannot spare the time to march the whole way are joining in for one-day relays.</p>
<p>COUNTRY JOBS AT RISK</p>
<p>At the neat 19th century red-brick kennels of the Worcestershire Hunt at Fernhill Heath, only a few miles (km) from the city Foster represents in parliament, things appear much as they have always been.</p>
<p>Caption, an elderly foxhound bitch, is rather distractedly looking after her four puppies lying on straw under a heat lamp.</p>
<p>The rest of the hounds, whose bloodlines go back 200 years, bound up to the entrance of their run to greet visitors. Some start to bark excitedly but are silenced by a word from huntsman Julian Barnsfield.</p>
<p>The picture of normality is misleading.</p>
<p>Barnsfield, 34, has worked in hunting since he was 16 but he knows now that his livelihood is under imminent threat from the Labour Party's landslide victory in the May 1 election, which gave it a huge majority of 179 seats in the House of Commons.</p>
<p>&quot;I just hope common sense will prevail,&quot; he told Reuters in an interview. &quot;My biggest worry is the sheer power the Labour Party have got. They can do whatever they want.&quot;</p>
<p>He and his family face an uncertain future if hunting is banned as there will by few vacancies for men whose whole working life has been spent with the hunt.</p>
<p>&quot;It will tip my world upside down,&quot; he said. &quot;I get up seven days a week and I'm ready to go to work. There's nothing I'd rather do. It's absolutely wonderful.&quot;</p>
<p>Foxhunting supporters report a mood of growing anger in their ranks that Foster, through his bill, is attempting to ban an activity which they feel should be a matter of personal choice. Liberal commentators have joined conservatives in urging the government to take a less authoritarian stand.</p>
<p>CIVIL DISOBEDIENCE A POSSIBILITY</p>
<p>Some foxhunters say they will not go easily if their sport is banned, predicting civil disobedience along the lines of the paralysing roadblocks staged by French truck drivers and farmers when their interests are threatened.</p>
<p>Members of the Worcestershire Hunt complain that Foster has not responded to their efforts to discuss the matter with him.</p>
<p>Robert Brierley, a Worcestershire Hunt stalwart for more than 20 years, says he spent so much time warning the rest of the members of the political dangers they faced that they eventually made him their spokesman.</p>
<p>Brierley runs his public relations campaign from the office of his house plant importing business. The walls are lined with bookcases listing the lineage of every foxhound in Britain.</p>
<p>He says the time has come for the foxhunting fraternity to stop apologising for itself and to start taking the argument to the enemy. He points out, for example, that Foster is a keen angler.</p>
<p>&quot;We have only just started to get ourselves organised,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>HORSES AND HOUNDS ALSO UNDER THREAT</p>
<p>Animal rights groups are generally much better organised and funded than the fox hunters. One group last year made a one million pound ($1.6 million) donation to Labour Party funds.</p>
<p>Brierley agrees that a ban on hunting is closer now than it has ever been but refuses to accept that the Foster bill will pass through parliament without being watered down. He suggests the Labour government should set up a commission to examine the whole question of hunting.</p>
<p>Apart from the animal rights arguments, hunting's supporters say a ban will cause the loss of thousands of jobs in the country and would almost certainly mean that thousands of hounds and hundreds of horses will have to be put down.</p>
<p>Although Labour is in favour of allowing MPs to vote on hunting according to their consciences, the bill has come at a time when the new government is pressed to work through an already ambitious legislative programme in the parliamentary time available.</p>
<p>There have also been suggestions that the bill could be held up by the unelected upper House of Lords, where pro-hunting Conservatives are in a majority. But it remains the case that the House of Commons is overwhelmingly anti-hunting.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the rural masses are heading for the capital, some of them bearing placards with a quotation from the poet G.K. Chesterton: &quot;Do not quite forget. We are the people of England that have not spoken yet&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FERNHILL HEATH, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
