<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711873" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan's trade surplus keeps surging.</title>
<headline>Japan's trade surplus keeps surging.</headline>
<byline>George Nishiyama</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's contentious trade surplus is continuing to grow, boosted by the yen's weakening earlier this year and a drop in domestic demand following a tax rise in April, which has encouraged Japanese firms to export more.</p>
<p>The Finance Ministry announced on Monday that the trade surplus in the first 20 days of June more than doubled from the same period a year earlier, making it likely that the figure for the whole of June will post a year-on-year rise for the third straight month.</p>
<p>The customs-cleared trade surplus for the 20-day period was 453.20 billion yen ($4.01 billion), up 129.3 percent from the same period a year earlier. Exports rose 19.1 percent, while imports increased 8.5 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;The yen's weakening a while ago is still having an effect (on exports),&quot; a ministry official said after the announcement.</p>
<p>Although he said the effect of currency movements was becoming smaller in nominal terms, he said the yen's weakness early this year was still affecting Japan's exports.</p>
<p>Some currency dealers were prompted by his comments to buy yen, surmising that Japanese authorities view the yen as being still too weak to curb the trade surplus.</p>
<p>Finance Ministry mandarins are seen eager to keep the surplus from growing any further amid renewed pressure from Japan's trade partners.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto heard concerns about the surplus from both the United States and Europe at last month's summit of the Group of Seven (G7) industrial nations in Denver.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton said after the summit that Japan would risk an economic war with the United States if its trade surplus started exploding again.</p>
<p>But some economists said the surplus is likely to have peaked and the contentious indicator may show a much smaller increase later this year.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen the worst surge in trade surpluses behind us. We are probably going to see a decline in the trade surplus in the second half of this year on the back of a rebound in import growth,&quot; said Andrew Shipley, an economist at Schroder Securities (Japan).</p>
<p>Economists say the recent rise in the surplus was brought about by temporary factors including the effects of a rise in the sales tax to five percent from three percent on April 1.</p>
<p>The tax rise depressed imports by dampening domestic private consumption. At the same time, Japanese manufacturers boosted exports to make up for lost sales at home.</p>
<p>The rise in exports &quot;is in response to the the decrease in domestic demand, which in turn is in reaction to the tax rise&quot;, the ministry official said.</p>
<p>But some economists said signs of a rise in imports were already evident.</p>
<p>Michael Hartnett, a senior economist at Merrill Lynch Japan, said the import growth seen in Monday's data was encouraging.</p>
<p>He said: &quot;Possibly more of a surprise is the pickup in import growth we saw this morning -- 8.5 percent year-on-year. I think that's the strongest number in year-on-year terms since February 1996, so that might quell some fears that the trade surplus is going to go inexorably upwards.&quot; ($1=113 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
