<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711864" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean president's son denies bribery charges.</title>
<headline>S.Korean president's son denies bribery charges.</headline>
<byline>Yoo Choon-sik</byline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean President Kim Young-sam's second son on Monday denied taking bribes at the outset of a trial that political analysts said would further damage the embattled head of state.</p>
<p>On the first day of Kim Hyun-chul's trial on charges of bribery and tax evasion, he admitted accepting a total of 6.61 billion won ($7.4 million) from business associates.</p>
<p>But he told the court: &quot;I was never asked for favours in return for money I received. They told me they were giving me money to fund my activities.&quot;</p>
<p>The younger Kim ran a political organisation that helped get his father elected as the country's first civilian head of state in 1992.</p>
<p>Kim Hyun-chul is charged with taking kickbacks worth 3.22 billion won in return for favours, including obtaining a cable television licence, a highway fast-food franchise and fixing a court case.</p>
<p>He is also charged with evading taxes on 3.39 billion won he accepted as gifts.</p>
<p>Dressed in pale blue prison garb and with his head lowered, he arrived in the courthouse in a prison bus.</p>
<p>Political analysts said the scandal had dealt a serious blow to President Kim by limiting his political influence ahead of presidential elections in December.</p>
<p>The president is barred from seeking re-election by the constitution.</p>
<p>&quot;The scandal has already made it almost impossible for the president to wield any influence in selecting his party's candidate,&quot; said Kwon Moo-soo, president of the Graduate School of Politics and Leadership at Seoul's Kookmin University.</p>
<p>&quot;The trial will not have a major additional impact but will keep limiting the president's political power by reminding the people of the scandal.&quot;</p>
<p>Kim Young-sam's ruling New Korea Party plans to elect a presidential candidate on July 21.</p>
<p>The younger Kim, nicknamed &quot;the crown prince&quot; by the local media, took his first kickback shortly after his father came to office in February 1993, according to the prosecution.</p>
<p>Also on trial was a former top intelligence official, Kim Ki-sup, an associate of the president's son who is charged with receiving 150 million won in bribes to help obtain a lucrative cable television licence.</p>
<p>Kim Ki-sup pleaded guilty to the charge.</p>
<p>Prosecutors said Kim Hyun-chul evaded taxes of 1.4 billion won on the gifts from businessmen and hid the money in dozens of false-name accounts.</p>
<p>One of his father's first acts on taking power was to ban false-name accounts as part of his anti-graft campaign.</p>
<p>At a separate trial on Monday, one of Kim Hyun-chul's associates, Park Tae-joong, pleaded guilty to taking 870 million won from businessmen.</p>
<p>Opposition parties have alleged Kim Hyun-chul pressured banks to keep loans flowing to Hanbo Steel, South Korea's second largest steelmaker.</p>
<p>The steelmaker's collapse in January shed light on a web of corruption involving politicians, bankers and businessmen.</p>
<p>Last month the founder of Hanbo, key presidential aides, politicians and top bankers were jailed for their roles in the Hanbo scandal. Prosecutors have cleared Kim Hyun-chul of any wrongdoing in the Hanbo affair.</p>
<p>South Korean law calls for a maximum penalty of life in jail for tax evasion. Under the bribery charges brought against him, Kim Hyun-chul faces a maximum five years in jail.</p>
<p>($1 = 887 won)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
