<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711826" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Coal &amp; Allied train remains blocked.</title>
<headline>Coal &amp; Allied train remains blocked.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Coal and Allied's attempt to use non-union labour to load up a coal train and bypass a union picket line at its strike-bound Hunter Valley Number One mine remained stalled on Monday afternoon.</p>
<p>Coal and Allied's General Manager of Operations at the mine, Allan Davies, said picketers were still blocking the railway track and stopping the train from loading.</p>
<p>&quot;The train is waiting to proceed in to load,&quot; Davies told Reuters from the Hunter Valley site.</p>
<p>&quot;The police are tying to clear the line. The train won't proced until the line is clear,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Coal &amp; Allied, 71 percent owned by Rio Tinto Plc/Ltd, has estimated each strike day costs the company about A$1 million in lost revenue.</p>
<p>The strike is now four weeks old.</p>
<p>Coal and Allied's attempt to negotiate more flexible enterprise bargains, the key reason for the strike, is seen a key battle in the industry's drive to improve profitability.</p>
<p>Davies said he was optimistic the train would be allowed to pass the picket line and load up later on Monday.</p>
<p>Police were asking picketers to move off the line, he said.  </p>
<p>&quot;I would have expected that's not an unreasonable thing to ask for,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Coal and Allied tried to get the train through the picket line on Friday, but was stopped when the engine driver refused to cross the line.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Industrial relations mininster Peter Reith said Coal and Allied's attempt to improve productivity was perfectly reasonably.</p>
<p>&quot;In the coal industry we have very low productivity and efficiency levels,&quot; Reith told reporters.  </p>
<p>&quot;That is costing us nationally both jobs and export income. It is a perferctly reasonable proposotion whether you are an employer or employee to change work practices in the coal industry to boost productivity,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;People are well paid in the coal industry. It is not as if they have been short-changed.&quot;</p>
<p>Reith said the government's Workplace Relations Act, which took effect in January, included strong provisions secondary boycotts and primary boycotts.</p>
<p>But Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union National President John Maitland said feeling was strong at the mine.  </p>
<p>&quot;This train is going to load coal produce by non-union labour at a time when unionists are conducting legal industrial action,&quot; Maitland told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said part of the coal industry's problem was the price settled with overseas buyers.</p>
<p>Maitland said buyers laugh at lack of unity among Australian producers.</p>
<p>&quot;Quite often, they go overseas and cut each other's throats,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Coal and Allied's shares were untraded on Monday, having closed unchanged at A$9.20 on Friday.  </p>
<p>Prime Minister John Howard said there may be legal remedies for Coal and Allied under secondary boycott laws, which are designed to stop workers in other industries striking in sympathy.</p>
<p>&quot;There may be remedies available under the secondary boycott laws. They may be able to go to court and get an order that the obstruction be removed.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Sydney Newsroom 61-2 9373-1800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
