<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="711908" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>PHILIPPINES: ASEAN stand on Cambodia can still change -Manila.</title>
<headline>ASEAN stand on Cambodia can still change -Manila.</headline>
<dateline>MANILA 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippine Foreign Secretary Domingo Siazon said on Monday ASEAN's decision to admit Cambodia as a member this month can still change depending on the internal situation in that country.</p>
<p>&quot;That decision could still change depending on how bad the situation turns out,&quot; he told reporters, referring to recent fighting in the Cambodian capital Phnom Penh.  </p>
<p>&quot;If this fighting does not stop, obviously, ASEAN members will have to rethink this seriously...because they may not be capable of dealing with a situation of war inside the country,&quot; Siazon said. Under an earlier agreement among Association of South East Asian Nations states, Cambodia was to be formally accepted as a member at a meeting of the seven-nation group this month.</p>
<p>In Kuala Lumpur earlier on Monday, Malaysia's Acting Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim said the ASEAN position on Cambodia's membership &quot;has not changed because the commitment has already been made.&quot; ASEAN, which groups Malaysia, the Philippines, Indonesia, Singapore, Thailand, Brunei and Vietnam, has agreed to simultaneously accept Cambodia, Laos and Burma as new members.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASEAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MANILA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PHILIPPINES"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
