<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712084" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: MOF declines comment on DKB suspension report.</title>
<headline>MOF declines comment on DKB suspension report.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Ministry of Finance (MOF) declined on Monday to confirm a newspaper report that it was considering ordering Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank Ltd to suspend part of its operations as a penalty for its alleged illegal loans to a corporate racketeer.</p>
<p>The financial daily Nihon Keizai Shimbun reported on Saturday that the ministry was likely to order the major Japanese bank to halt operations such as extending new loans and refrain from running advertisements.</p>
<p>The newspaper also said, without quoting sources, that the ministry may also press criminal charges against the bank for its alleged failure to report its loans to the sokaiya as bad loans.</p>
<p>A ministry official said the ministry could not immediately confirm or comment on the newspaper report.</p>
<p>A total of 11 DKB officials have so far been arrested for suspected involvement in illegal loans to racketeer Ryuichi Koike. The latest of the arrests was of former chairman Tadashi Okuda on Friday for allegedly giving the go-ahead for dubious loans totaling about 11.7 billion yen.</p>
<p>A Finance Ministry source said late last week it would be difficult to impose penalties that affected the bank's core lending and deposit-taking business.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
