<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712085" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: S.Korean president's son goes on trial for bribery.</title>
<headline>S.Korean president's son goes on trial for bribery.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>South Korean President Kim Young-sam's son went on trial on Monday on charges of bribery and tax evasion.</p>
<p>Kim Hyun-chul entered a Seoul criminal court in prison uniform and with his head down, witnesses said. His arrest last May dealt a serious blow to his father's credibility in the run-up to presidential elections in December.  </p>
<p>State prosecutors accused the president's second son of taking kickbacks totalling 3.22 billion won ($3.6 million).</p>
<p>The younger Kim, nicknamed by the local media the &quot;crown prince&quot;, took his first kickback in March 1993, only one month after his father came to office, according to the prosecutors.</p>
<p>They said he evaded taxes of 1.48 billion won on gifts from businessmen, hiding the money in accounts using borrowed names. One of his father's first acts on taking power was to ban false-name accounts as part of his anti-graft campaign.</p>
<p>South Korean laws call for a maximum penalty of life in jail for tax evasion. Under bribery charges brought aginst him, Kim Hyun-chul could be jailed for five years. ($1 = 887 won)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
