<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712081" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Surge in Japan surplus may have peaked - economists.</title>
<headline>Surge in Japan surplus may have peaked - economists.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
<text>
<p>Growth in Japan's trade surplus is likely to have peaked, and the contentious indicator may show a much smaller year-on-year increase later this year, economists said on Monday.</p>
<p>The Finance Ministry announced on Monday morning that Jpaan posted a customs-cleared trade surplus of 453.20 billion yen ($4.01 billion) in the first 20 days of June, up 129.3 percent from the same period a year earlier. Exports rose 19.1 percent year-on-year, while imports increased 8.5 percent.</p>
<p>Economists said temporary factors such as an increase in Japan's consumption tax on April 1 were still affecting imports, but prospects of a slowdown in the U.S. economy may help curb Japan's exports, slowing growth in the overall surplus.</p>
<p>&quot;We've seen the worst surge in trade surpluses behind us. We are probably going to see a decline in the trade surplus in the second half of this year on the back of a rebound in import growth,&quot; said Andrew Shipley, an economist at Schroder Securities (Japan).</p>
<p>Michael Hartnett, senior economist at Merrill Lynch Japan, said: &quot;Possibly more of a surprise is the pickup in import growth we saw this morning -- 8.5 percent year-on-year -- I think that's the strongest number in year-on-year terms since February 1996, so that might quell some fears that the trade surplus is going to go inexorably upwards.&quot;</p>
<p>($1=113 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
