<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712150" id="root" date="1997-07-07" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bonn urges lifting restrictions on encryption.</title>
<headline>Bonn urges lifting restrictions on encryption.</headline>
<byline>William Boston</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>German Economics Minister Guenter Rexrodt on Monday called for the removal of restrictions on encryption technology when he kicked off a two-day conference on Internet commerce attended by 40 government ministers from the European Union, the United States, Russia, Japan and Canada.</p>
<p>The issue is expected to be one of the most hotly debated at the conference as industry leaders from the United States, western and eastern Europe, Asia and developing countries, as well as the ministers, discuss global issues on doing business on the Internet.</p>
<p>In contrast to the United States, which failed to relax rules on technology that allows Internet users to code messages and business transactions, Germany has been leaning toward keeping such coding and decoding software unregulated.</p>
<p>&quot;Users can only protect themselves against having data manipulated, destroyed or spied on through the use of strong encryption procedures,&quot; Rexrodt said according to the text of his opening statements.</p>
<p>&quot;That is why we have to use all of our powers to promote such procedures instead of blocking them,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Objection to allowing free trade in encryption technology has come mainly from security and law enforcement officials in both the United States and Europe. They fear that the technology will be used by organised crime to hide their activities from the law.</p>
<p>&quot;This argument doesn't hold,&quot; said one U.S. industry executive, who asked not to be identified. Referring to illegal exports from the United States of the most secure encryption software, he said:&quot;The way it works now is that only those engaging in illegal activities have access to strong encryption.&quot;</p>
<p>The European hosts of Global Information Networks saw some of their thunder stolen by U.S. President Bill Clinton last week when he issued a call to create an Internet &quot;free trade zone&quot; within a year.</p>
<p>Washington wants to carve out such a zone within the context of the World Trade Organisation (WTO), with a group of core countries ready and able to carry it out.</p>
<p>The proposal has met only a lukewarm response from European Union states and some developing countries who fear that any deal would disproportionately benefit U.S. industry.</p>
<p>But Clinton's unexpected foray into the hazy area of Internet regulation is also a hot topic in informal meetings at the Bonn conference.</p>
<p>This is the second international conference that aims to deal with Internet regulatory issues. The first was held in Brussels in 1995 and sponsored by the Group of Seven industrial nations and the European Union. The G7 was supposed to sponsor the Bonn conference, but this was dropped over U.S. objections.</p>
<p>After more than two years of international debate on issues such as taxing Internet trade, encryption and controlling the spread of pornography and extremist materials, world leaders have made little progress in setting up a global framework.</p>
<p>There are four main themes to be discussed in plenary sessions at the conference on Monday and Tuesday: &quot;Building Confidence&quot;, &quot;Empowering the User&quot;, &quot;Making the Most of Content Resources&quot; and &quot;Creating a Favourable Environment for Electronic Commerce&quot;.</p>
<p>The Bonn Declaration to be made at the end of the event will be based on a theme paper that can already be read on the Internet at the address http://www.echo.lu/bonn/conference.htm.</p>
<p>It is expected to contain statements underscoring the goal of keeping regulation to a minimum, protecting the integrity of regional and national cultural identity, and not erecting barriers to network-based commerce.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I33030">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83940">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-07"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
