<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712239" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FOCUS-Int'l Paper to sell assets, cut 9,000 jobs.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Int'l Paper to sell assets, cut 9,000 jobs.</headline>
<byline>Dan Burns</byline>
<dateline>PURCHASE 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>International Paper Co's move Tuesday to slash its workforce, close struggling operations and sell off $1 billion in assets was hailed by Wall Street as long overdue.</p>
<p>The world's largest paper company said it will cut as many as 9,000 jobs -- about 10 percent of its workforce -- will close, scale back or convert operations at five mills in four states, and will sell two businesses and some timber holdings as part of efforts to refocus on core businesses and reduce its mammoth debt load.</p>
<p>&quot;We will be divesting or closing operations that no longer meet the company's financial or strategic objectives,&quot; company chairman John Dillon said.</p>
<p>International Paper had become too diversified, and for some time it has needed to shed operations that have contributed to its recent reputation as a sluggish performer, Smith Barney analyst Josh Kapp said.</p>
<p>&quot;They had diversified into businesses that haven't been successful,&quot; Kapp said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is great. They're finally starting to do what they need to do,&quot; Bear, Stearns analyst Linda Lieberman said. &quot;It's something they've been needing to do for a long while.&quot;</p>
<p>On a day when other paper company stocks performed well, shares of International Paper jumped 9.1 percent to close at $56 on the New York Stock Exchange, up $4.69 from Monday.</p>
<p>The surge in its stock price was viewed by analysts as a response to word of the company's restructuring plans more than a reaction to better-than-expected second quarter operating results.</p>
<p>International Paper posted a second quarter loss of $419 million, or $1.39 per share, because of $685 million in pre-tax charges associated with the restructuring. Excluding the charges, the company had on operating profit of $59 million, or 20 cents per share, beating estimates by 5 cents per share.</p>
<p>In a conference call with analysts, company officials said they will apply most of gain from the sale of assets to cutting its $9.905 billion debt load. It also expects to realize about $100 million in savings from the job cuts and plant closings and another $80 million in savings from reduced interest from debt, analysts said.</p>
<p>While the company plans to shed 9,000 workers, fewer than half of those cuts will come as lay-offs, company spokesman Phillip Giaramita said. For instance, nearly 4,800 jobs will be transferred with the sale of its imaging and multi-wall kraft, or strong brown paper, businesses, he said.</p>
<p>Firmly identified layoffs now total fewer than 400, Giaramita said. About 200 people will be let go with the closing of three production lines at its Erie, Pa., mill; another 175 jobs will be lost with the closing of the mill in Woronoco, Mass.; and about 20 people will be laid off with the closing of its de-inking pulp facility in Lock Haven, Pa.</p>
<p>The company also is selling 175,000 acres of timberland in western regions of Pennsylvania and New York.</p>
<p>Giaramita said the assets identified for sale Tuesday do not make up all of the $1 billion in assets the company expects to shed this year. Other businesses will be sold as the company continues its review of operations.</p>
<p>The plans announced Tuesday should contribute to earnings later this year, the company said, but neither it nor analysts would estimate how significant a contribution it would be.</p>
<p>The company said demand for its products remains strong. It recorded sales for the quarter of $5.034 billion, down slightly from the $5.093 billion in sales it posted in the second quarter a year ago.</p>
<p>&quot;The good demand we are experiencing should lead to increased profitability over the next six months,&quot; Dillon said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I47100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C182">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PURCHASE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
