<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712250" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: HMOs send more stroke victims to nursing homes.</title>
<headline>HMOs send more stroke victims to nursing homes.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Stroke victims covered by managed care were more likely than those covered by fee-for-service plans to be sent to nursing homes rather than more expensive rehabilitation facilities, a study said Tuesday.</p>
<p>The study of 810 patients by researchers at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond did not examine the outcomes for stroke victims sent to the two types of care facilities, but the findings appeared to support the view that Health Maintenance Organizations (HMOs) tend to minimize costs.</p>
<p>Of the 402 stroke victims covered by HMO plans, 42 percent were discharged to nursing homes and 16 percent to rehabilitation facilities. Among 408 fee-for-service patients, 28 percent were sent to nursing homes and 23 percent to rehabilitation.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not known whether the higher use of nursing homes and the lower rate of rehabilitation facility use among HMO stroke patients in this study represent a judicious use of expensive resources or a withholding of necessary care,&quot; study author Sheldon Retchin wrote in the Journal of the American Medical Association.</p>
<p>But he noted that previous research showed patients admitted to rehabiliation hospitals generally showed improved functional status and were more likely to return to the community than those sent to nursing homes.</p>
<p>Strokes hit more than half a million patients annually and are the leading cause of adult disability in the United States.</p>
<p>In an editorial accompanying the study, James Webster Jr. and Joseph Feinglass of Northwestern University Medical School in Chicago urged physicians to retake the initiative from insurers in prescribing care.</p>
<p>&quot;Physicians have a golden opportunity to regain a leadership role in health care by publicly advocating for and practicing quality of care assurance, especially when such measures pertain to steadfast care of vulnerable, high-cost, high-risk patients,&quot; they wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;We must protest the ethically compromising restrictions on our skill or competence that deny patients the bountiful fruits of biomedical research and clinical advances that can relieve suffering and improve health status,&quot; they added.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I95100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
