<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712540" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Late talks fail to avert BA strike disruption.</title>
<headline>Late talks fail to avert BA strike disruption.</headline>
<byline>Paul Keller</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Disruption came early to British Airways flights on Tuesday despite late talks with unions ahead of Wednesday's expected three-day strike by cabin crew, as 350 staff reported sick and caused 14 services to be cancelled.</p>
<p>The cancelled flights were all from London Heathrow to domestic and short-haul European destinations. BA said it was doing its best to transfer passengers to other BA services or to rival airlines.</p>
<p>BA said it held further talks with the main union involved, the Transport &amp; General Workers Union (T&amp;G) on Tuesday afternoon aided by conciliation service ACAS after earlier discussions on pay and conditions broke down on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;The ball is now in the unions' court...all our attention now is focused on minimising disruption to our passengers tomorrow,&quot; a spokesman for the airline said.</p>
<p>There was no one at the T&amp;G immediately available for comment.</p>
<p>Cabin crew plan to start a 72-hour strike in earnest at 0500 GMT on Wednesday. It is potentially the first of many, which could strand thousands of tourists and business travellers.</p>
<p>British travel agents reported on Tuesday they had been flooded with calls from travellers trying to find alternative flights on rival airlines.</p>
<p>BA said Wednesday's strike now looked almost certain to go ahead. &quot;We're working on the assumption that there will be a strike and we're doing our best to minimise the impact on our customers,&quot; a spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>BA said its contingency plan, aimed at keeping as many of its flights running as possible, would now swing into action but it admitted thousands of passengers may still be grounded.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if the strike is cancelled today, there is likely to be disruption,&quot; the BA spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be more strikes unless BA comes to an agreement with the unions,&quot; said T&amp;G spokesman Andrew Murray. The cabin crew would receive &quot;solid&quot; support from workers in foreign aviation unions, he said.</p>
<p>BA has cancelled half of its long-haul Wednesday services from Britain's main Heathrow airport and some two-thirds of intercontinental flights from Gatwick. Even worse hit will be short-haul and domestic services from Heathrow.</p>
<p>The airline, which operates 1,000 flights a day worldwide, aims to run all its domestic and European flights to and from London Gatwick; all international flights to and from UK regional airports; domestic flights except those serving London Heathrow; and all those operated by partner airlines.</p>
<p>BA says it expects 3,500 staff belonging to a smaller, non-striking union, Cabin Crew 89, to turn up for work on Wednesday as well as an estimated 1,500 other staff who are prepared to cross the picket line.</p>
<p>Under British civil aviation law, any flight carrying more than 20 passengers must have at least one cabin crew member per 50 passengers.</p>
<p>BA is ensnared in a separate dispute with ground crew over the sale of its catering division at Heathrow. The workers are expected to announce later today whether they have accepted BA's offer to resolve the row.</p>
<p>The disputes follow the airline's plans to save one billion pounds ($1.7 billion) by 2000 through a major restructuring. ($ = 0.594 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
