<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712554" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BA strikers to lose perks, face lockout.</title>
<headline>BA strikers to lose perks, face lockout.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-07-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>British Airways Plc (BA) has said cabin crew who join an impending 72-hour strike will lose perks and face a lockout unless they promise to work normally in the future.</p>
<p>The promise of immediate sanctions came as cabin crew prepared to begin the first of a series of three-day strikes on Wednesday, threatening chaos to thousands of travellers.</p>
<p>&quot;We are asking them to give us an assurance they will work normally before we will roster them for further flights,&quot; BA spokesman Michael Blunt said late on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;If people are going on strike they are preventing our customers enjoying their hard earned holidays, and preventing our business travellers from getting to destinations to win contracts for their companies and we just feel it's inappropriate for people who do that to benefit from their own staff travel privileges,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Blunt said strikers would not be scheduled for work from Saturday and would not be paid unless they telephoned BA and gave an assurance they would not strike in the future.</p>
<p>He also said that anyone striking on Wednesday would lose their staff travel concessions until March 2000, become ineligible for promotion until the same date, and lose the option of applying for early retirement.</p>
<p>Members of the Transport and General Workers' Union (T&amp;G) were set to begin the strike at 0500 GMT on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Blunt said that last year when a strike threat from its pilots was settled at the last minute it lost 15 million pounds in future bookings.</p>
<p>BA, which operates 1,000 flights a day worldwide, said earlier on Tuesday it would ask an independent arbitrator to consider the cabin crew union's proposals for saving millions of pounds.</p>
<p>The dispute with its employees follows the airline's plans to save a billion pounds by 2000 through major restructuring. Earlier negotiations broke down on Sunday.</p>
<p>BA had hoped to save 42 million pounds from its cabin crew operations. But the union's proposals were thought to recommend smaller savings.</p>
<p>T&amp;G has said unless a solution was found it would call for further 72-hour strikes.</p>
<p>BA said its contingency plan, aimed at keeping as many of its flights running as possible, would now swing into action but admitted thousands of passengers may still be grounded.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if the strike is cancelled today, there is likely to be disruption,&quot; a BA spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>The airline has cancelled half of its long-haul services from Heathrow on Wednesday and some two-thirds of its intercontinental flights from Gatwick. But worst hit will be short-haul and domestic services from Heathrow.</p>
<p>BA is involved in a separate dispute with ground crew over the sale of its catering division at Heathrow. The workers are expected to announce soon whether they have accepted BA's offer to resolve the row.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-07-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
