<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712629" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NIGERIA: Nigerian oil community chief arrested, group says.</title>
<headline>Nigerian oil community chief arrested, group says.</headline>
<byline>Matthew Tostevin</byline>
<dateline>WARRI, Nigeria 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nigerian authorities on Tuesday arrested the leader of a restive oil-producing community hours before a deadline he set for the local unit of oil giant Shell to pay a compensation or leave expired, his group said.</p>
<p>The Niger Delta Oil-Producing Development Organisation said in a statement that state security police seized its president, Matthew Eregbeng, and took him to Asaba, capital of the midwestern Delta state.</p>
<p>&quot;We have not been informed of any arrest,&quot; Shell's western division general manager Joshua Udofia said, adding: &quot;We are not involved in any arrest.&quot;</p>
<p>There was no confirmation of the arrest from Nigerian authorities, who have so far said nothing on the ultimatum to Shell by four communities to leave their area or be forced out.</p>
<p>The four communities recently won a tussle against Shell in local courts over compensation of around 30 million naira ($353,000) for environmental damage, but say Shell is now planning to appeal to a higher court.</p>
<p>&quot;Worried that the said payments will encourage other legitimate compensation demands, Shell has alerted the security forces and this morning Mr Matthew Eregbeng has been whisked away,&quot; his group said, adding: &quot;For now we are watching to see what will happen to Mr Eregbeng.&quot;</p>
<p>In an ultimatum they served on Shell through a letter widely reported in local newspapers last Wednesday, the ethnic Ijaw communities near Sokebelou in Delta state said Shell had until the end of Tuesday to pay up or quit their oil-producing area.</p>
<p>Shell has two flow stations in the area, which is in Burutu local government and each normally pumps around 20,000-30,000 barrels per day of crude oil.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing happened today in the area. We are working normally. We have gone to the communities. We have spoken to them and they claim these people are not talking for them,&quot; Udofia said.</p>
<p>The company has said no compensation can be paid for the 1982 oil spill, from the trans-Forcados pipeline, because it was found to have been caused by sabotage.</p>
<p>The company also says it cleared up the spilled oil and that it is exercising its right of appeal by contesting the verdict.</p>
<p>&quot;Shell can appeal but her oil flow stations will be shut down because it cannot use our money to fight us in the appeal court,&quot; the community state said, adding: &quot;We would rather die.&quot;</p>
<p>Ethnic clashes in March between Ijaw and Itsekiri tribesmen in the Warri area killed scores of people and forced Shell to close several oil wells earlier this year after fighting erupted over the relocation of a local government headquarters.</p>
<p>Warri still bears scars of the tribal clashes. Burnt buildings adorn the town while people not from the warring tribes have painted their ethnic origins on their homes to show their neutrality to avoid the destruction of their homes.</p>
<p>There was no special evidence of tension in Warri on Tuesday as the deadline for Shell to leave nearby Sokebelou approached.</p>
<p>Residents said Warri was much calmer than a few weeks ago.</p>
<p>&quot;Just because today is calm doesn't mean there will be nothing tomorrow or in the future,&quot; said one local official.</p>
<p>&quot;That is how these people work to try to catch the authorities off guard,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Shell came under fire from campaigners in 1995 after the execution for murder of author Ken Saro-Wiwa and eight other activists who campaigned for rights for the southeastern minority Ogoni community and against alleged pollution by Shell.</p>
<p>Shell Nigeria is a joint venture between Royal Dutch Shell group and state-run Nigerian National Petreoleum Corporation.</p>
<p>It pumps around half of the nation's roughly two million bpd crude oil production.</p>
<p>But unlike most other oil firms it operates onshore and is vulnerable to attacks by oil communities which feel short-changed for lack of amenities in their areas even though Nigeria depends almost entirely on oil exports for its income.</p>
<p>&quot;It is becoming clear that it is a curse to have oil in our soil,&quot; said one community leader in Warri.</p>
<p>($1=85 naira)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NETH">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NIGEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I13000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I1300003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARRI, Nigeria"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NIGERIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
