<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712655" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ANGOLA: Angolan army accuses UNITA of ambushing soldiers.</title>
<headline>Angolan army accuses UNITA of ambushing soldiers.</headline>
<dateline>LUANDA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Angolan army on Tuesday reported fresh clashes between government troops and the former rebel UNITA movement, which is officially part of the country's government of national unity.</p>
<p>Angolan Armed Forces (FAA) spokesman Major Joao Carvalho told the state news agency Angop five government soldiers had been killed and four wounded in several ambushes in the central Huila province in the past few days.</p>
<p>It blamed UNITA (National Union for the Total Independence of Angola) soldiers for the attacks which happened around the district of Caconda, south of the central highlands capital of Huambo.</p>
<p>&quot;In response to these actions the FAA captured in the area of Uaba, Caconda, five UNITA soldiers...with diverse war material,&quot; Carvalho told Angop.</p>
<p>He said the UNITA soldiers had been handed over to the United Nations observer mission in the southern capital of Lubango.</p>
<p>The government has accused UNITA of still having several thousand armed soldiers in the countryside, even though the movement declared at the end of last year it had dismantled its entire guerrilla force under U.N. supervision.</p>
<p>Both sides signed a peace treaty in 1994 to end two decades of civil war and under the accord agreed to merge their armies and create a single national army.</p>
<p>But the government in May attacked UNITA diamond areas in the northeast in efforts to extend their control over the country as agreed in the peace treaty, causing panic among members of the movement.</p>
<p>Attacks on civilans and vehicles on roads in central Angola have been on the increase since the signing of the peace agreement as areas are cleared of landmines laid by both sides during the civil war.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LUANDA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ANGOLA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
