<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712662" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: IATA urges Africa to expand airspace capacity.</title>
<headline>IATA urges Africa to expand airspace capacity.</headline>
<byline>Wambui Chege</byline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Aviation authorities said on Tuesday expanding Africa's capacity to cope with a rapid rise in air traffic should be the top priority for the world's poorest continent.</p>
<p>Pierre Jienniot, director-general of the International Air Transport Association (IATA), said the introduction of South Africa after the end of apartheid had boosted the African market with healthy growth in both trade and tourism earnings.</p>
<p>But it had also highlighted the region's need for improved infrastructure to cope with the increase in air traffic.</p>
<p>&quot;Opening up South Africa has put pressure on air space capacity. The question of capacity will affect the rapidity with which air traffic can grow and is related to growth in the economy,&quot; Jienniot told a news conference in Nairobi.</p>
<p>Trevor Fox, IATA'S director of infrastructure in Africa and Indian Ocean Islands, said IATA had reports of incidents, some of them near misses, from pilots related to the route from South Africa to Europe because of the increased airline traffic.</p>
<p>He said an airspace highway from Algeria including the Democratic Republic of the Congo, Chad, the Congo Republic and Niger through to Angola was the most affected by the problems.</p>
<p>&quot;Poor communication between pilots and air traffic controllers on the ground is a major problem,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Jienniot said introduction of satellite-based navigation was the solution to the continent's problem of monitoring traffic.</p>
<p>&quot;The progressive introduction of Communication Navigation Surveillance (CNS) will allow more airspace capacity to be used,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>CNS involves the replacing a radio communication system running on High Frequency (HF) with Very High Frequency (VHF).</p>
<p>&quot;We hope to complete the VHF implementation by November 1997 in Chad, while in Angola, we at least hope to update the HF equipment by the end of the third quarter of this year,&quot; Fox told Reuters.</p>
<p>Jienniot said until Africa had a greater capacity to handle air traffic IATA would have to be content with maintaining a minumum longitudinal separation of 20 minutes flying time between aircraft.</p>
<p>But he said a minimum separation of 10 minutes would be ideal.</p>
<p>He added IATA was pushing for greater transparency in the handling of funds collected by governments in landing fees.</p>
<p>&quot;A lot of this money goes back to the treasury and we never get to hear about it after that. Governments need to separate user charges (collected from airlines) with taxes and plough back the funds to the airports,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>--Nairobi Newsroom ++254-2 330-261</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I76400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
