<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712640" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO: New Congo hosts conference on wildlife.</title>
<headline>New Congo hosts conference on wildlife.</headline>
<byline>Arthur Malu-Malu</byline>
<dateline>KINSHASA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Democratic Republic of the Congo appealed on Tuesday for urgent action to save its dwindling wildlife, but an environmental conference failed to agree any major initiatives because of the country's recent political upheaval.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation is dramatic. We have to act, we have to act swiftly before it is too late,&quot; Environment Minister Eddie Angulu of the former Zaire told the one-day conference.</p>
<p>&quot;At the Virunga national park (in Eastern Congo), the population of hippopotamus has been reduced. It went down to 1,500 in 1996 from 30,000 in 1990,&quot; Angulu told delegates from major international conservation organisations and donors.</p>
<p>The Democratic Republic of the Congo has the largest share of the continent's tropical forest and vertebrates, but poaching and lack of effective environmental policies have brought a number of species to the brink of extinction.</p>
<p>The Swiss-based World Wide Fund For Nature and the Howard Gilman Foundation of the United States took part in the Kinshasa conference.</p>
<p>Claude Martin, director general for the World Wide Fund for Nature, told Reuters that many projects were held in abeyance in Africa's third-largest state because of political instability.</p>
<p>Former dictator Mobutu Sese Seko was ousted by rebel forces under Laurent Kabila in May, putting an end to Mobutu's 32-year rule and installing Kabila as head of state.</p>
<p>Martin said some steps had to be taken to protect wildlife, but that they could only be short-term.</p>
<p>&quot;The minister has cried for help. Urgent measures have to be taken in the short term. Initially we will spend about $3 million on an emergency programme with this country,&quot; he said without elaborating.</p>
<p>&quot;The only population of northern white rhinoceros is in this country. It has to be protected. It has gone down to 30,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Over 1.5 million Rwandan refugees crossed the border into former Zaire in 1994 during the civil war in Rwanda, causing considerable damage to wildlife in Zaire as they felled trees and carelessly hunted animals.</p>
<p>Mobutu's government said in 1995 that the &quot;ecological catastrophe&quot; was estimated at $2 billion. It appealed in vain for international assistance.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ZAIRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KINSHASA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
