<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712671" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>COTE D'IVOIRE: Donors want to help draft Ivory Coast timber plan.</title>
<headline>Donors want to help draft Ivory Coast timber plan.</headline>
<byline>Desire Alladoum</byline>
<dateline>ABIDJAN 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>International aid donors want to play a part, alongside the government, in drawing up Ivory Coast's second timber sector plan, a World Bank official said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;It is important to define objectives for the second forest sector plan on which all the partners are in agreement,&quot; Giuseppe Toppa, a senior natural resources management specialist at the Bank, told a seminar here.</p>
<p>Donors are withholding funds because the first 1988-96 plan failed to meet a production target of four million cubic metres of timber, which, with replanting, should have been compatible with preserving the forest stock.</p>
<p>A donor source said recently that production was just two million cubic metres in 1996 and &quot;falling rapidly&quot;.</p>
<p>Currently, all the funding for the state forestry agency, SODEFOR, comes from aid donors.</p>
<p>The main aim of the second plan, Toppa said, should be &quot;the preservation of a critical mass of protected areas representative of the Ivorian ecosystems, within a perspective of national and global conservation&quot;.</p>
<p>That entailed an end to the destruction of Ivorian forests and measures to encourage the general protection and management of non-protected wooded areas in the countryside.</p>
<p>Donors are keen to see specific tax measures in the sector that would encourage durable management and discourage waste.</p>
<p>However, one donor source said the government was averse to measures that would raise taxes specifically for SODEFOR, beyond the reach of the state budget.</p>
<p>Donors are unhappy with a lack of transparency at SODEFOR in the sale of wood, serious problems with finance management and accounting, and the imbalance between the 400 employees that work on the ground and the 828 administration staff.</p>
<p>Total forest area in Ivory Coast has decreased to around 3.9 million hectares from 12 million in 1957, three years before independence from France.</p>
<p>In 1996 timber exports brought in 161.9 billion CFA francs, making it Ivory Coast's third biggest export, behind cocoa and petroleum products but in front of coffee.</p>
<p>-- Abidjan newsroom +225 21 90 90</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ICST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ABIDJAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="COTE D'IVOIRE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
