<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712675" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SUDAN: Sudan church leader says state demolished chapels.</title>
<headline>Sudan church leader says state demolished chapels.</headline>
<byline>Alfred Taban</byline>
<dateline>KHARTOUM 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The head of one of Sudan's largest churches said on Tuesday the government had demolished three churches in Khartoum state and was trying to take away some land from his parish.</p>
<p>&quot;On January 8, 1997 an organised armed force commanded by a police captain came to Thoura area (in Khartoum state) and indiscriminately demolished all three churches,&quot; the Rev. Bulus Idris Tia, of the Protestant Episcopal Church of Sudan, told Reuters. The damage was worth more than $11,000, he added.</p>
<p>He also said government troops on Saturday pulled down a wall fencing 2,000 square metres (21,500 square feet) of land claimed by his church and the Health Ministry.</p>
<p>&quot;We were suprised to see armed police come to our premises on Saturday. They started to knock down the wall. Soon bricks and sand were brought in by the Khartoum state for construction to begin,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Tia said he had papers to prove that the disputed land belonged to the church while an official at the Health Ministry told Reuters that the land belonged to the ministry.</p>
<p>Builders at the site were busy digging and said they had been instructed to build pharmacies on the property.</p>
<p>Human rights groups say the Islamist government of Lieutenant-General Omar Hassan al-Bashir persecutes Christians. The state denies the charges.</p>
<p>For the past 13 years, the rebel Sudan People's Liberation Army (SPLA) has been fighting the government for autonomy of the mainly Christian and animist south from the Arabised north.</p>
<p>Over two million mainly Christian Sudanese have been displaced by the fighting to the north.</p>
<p>Sudan's Social Planning Minister Mohammad Osman Al-Khalifa said recently the state was demolishing both mosques and churches built in shanty towns but members of the Christian community rejects their explanation.</p>
<p>Christian leaders say the government does not give them permits to build churches in other areas and that most of the displaced southern Christians live in these shanty towns anyway.</p>
<p>&quot;In the area of Thoura where our church was pulled down, there is a mosque that was not demolished and a market and nothing happened to it,&quot; Tia said.</p>
<p>&quot;Our problem is that when the government demolishes a church it does not provide an alternative. Where do we Christians pray?&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SUDAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KHARTOUM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SUDAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
