<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712654" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: Kenya opposition shows its strength over reforms.</title>
<headline>Kenya opposition shows its strength over reforms.</headline>
<byline>Manoah Esipisu</byline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Kenya's fractured opposition has found a rallying point in demands for constitutional reforms and is intent on showing its strength with protests outlawed by the government.</p>
<p>But on top of fears Kenya's fragile economy will be battered by repeated violent clashes before this year's general election, diplomats and business advisers are concerned confrontation will only stiffen President Daniel arap Moi's resistance to reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;The very fact that Kenyans must witness once again pre-election confrontations indicates that persistent and serious problems still exist in its transition to full democracy,&quot; said U.S. Ambassador Prudence Bushnell on Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Even more troubling in the current atmosphere of confrontation is the absence of the spirit which promotes peaceful, free and fair elections and a healthy democratic culture,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>But after her side swipe at Kenya's rulers, she went on to warn the advocates of unrest. &quot;Confrontation and violence ...carries a heavy burden. The cost is always high and the results unintended.&quot;</p>
<p>Nine people were killed on Monday during the most violent clashes between police and protesters in Kenya. Opposition activists said they had reports as many as 12 people were killed on Monday.</p>
<p>The ferocity with which police, wielding clubs, on Monday beat anyone they could get their hands on shocked even long-time foreign residents of Kenya and in some ways played into the hands of the opposition.</p>
<p>Opposition leaders were denied the rallies they had called by the police action but they said the brutality of the way in which the protests were put down exposed the foundation of Moi's government.</p>
<p>Britain, the largest foreign investor in Kenya, on Tuesday criticised Kenyan authorities for using excessive force in clashes with demonstrators on Monday and urged the government to ensure elections later this year are peaceful.</p>
<p>&quot;We expect the forthcoming election to be conducted without violence so the Kenyan people can express their democratic verdict,&quot; Foreign Office minister Tony Lloyd told parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;The events over the weekend (are) yet one further serious blow to that process,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;All parties in Kenya have a responsibility to refrain from confrontation. We are urging them to resolve their differences by means of dialogue,&quot; Lloyd said.</p>
<p>Opposition parties, human rights groups and other bodies demanding constitutional reforms before elections ordered a new demonstration on Wednesday to put more pressure on the Moi government.</p>
<p>They said they planned a national strike and protests at provincial administration centres as part of its non-violent campaign to force reforms, which Moi says cannot be introduced before the polls.</p>
<p>But the opposition is well aware that the campaign for reforms is in many ways the only thing holding together groups deeply split along personal and ethnic lines who are so far incapable of agreeing on a single candidate against Moi.</p>
<p>&quot;The struggle is going to move to a higher level. We will ensure that whatever it takes to change Kenya is taken,&quot; said Kivutha Kibwana, a constitutional law professor.</p>
<p>&quot;Monday demonstrated what kind of determination there is from the people. We must move forward,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>A switch to pluralist politics united many Kenyans against Moi in 1991 but that change was forced partly by donors which froze aid to Kenya until multi-party politics was allowed.</p>
<p>Moi, 73, nevertheless won the 1992 elections and is still widely expected to take another five-year term later this year. The crucial strong Western backing for reforms has so far not appeared.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
