<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712726" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia denounces NATO expansion as big mistake.</title>
<headline>Russia denounces NATO expansion as big mistake.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Heritage</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia denounced NATO's expansion into formerly ommunist eastern Europe on Tuesday as the worst mistake on the continent since World War Two.</p>
<p>Pre-empting a formal declaration on expansion at the NATO summit in Madrid, Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov said Moscow still opposed enlargement despite signing a partnership deal with its former Cold War foe in May.</p>
<p>&quot;Regarding the question of NATO expansion, I can only say that we confirm our stand,&quot; Primakov told reporters in Moscow.</p>
<p>&quot;Despite the fact that we have signed a broad, balanced agreement with NATO, we still consider expansion the biggest mistake in Europe since the end of World War Two.&quot;</p>
<p>Primakov, speaking after talks with Pakistani Foreign Minister Gohar Ayub Khan, made no further comment on the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation's summit.</p>
<p>He was repeating Moscow's already routine opposition to NATO's plans to admit Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic.</p>
<p>Russia, fearing isolation from decision-making on European security matters, says enlargement threatens its security and creates new divisions instead of building a security system that encompasses all European countries.</p>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin resisted NATO's expansion plans until he signed what is known as the Founding Act with the alliance in May. The agreement created a joint council which gives Moscow a say, but not a veto, in some security matters.</p>
<p>Yeltsin was on holiday in northwestern Russia on Tuesday and made no immediate comment on the Madrid summit.</p>
<p>Yeltsin's communist and nationalist opponents have accused him of betraying national interests by making a deal with NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;July 8, 1997, will go down forever as a day of national shame for Russia,&quot; the pro-communist newspaper Sovietskaya Rossiya said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>It said NATO's border was moving closer to Russia's frontier &quot;as a result of the Kremlin's line of capitulation&quot;.</p>
<p>But a government official, who declined to be named, portrayed Russia's recent diplomacy in a positive light.</p>
<p>The official told Interfax news agency that Russia had outplayed the eastern European countries seeking admission to NATO. They would become full members in two years, he said, but Russia had secured an immediate say in alliance affairs.</p>
<p>&quot;As for Russia, it already has an opportunity to really influence alliance policy in the framework of the permanent council which, in line with the Founding Act, will get down to business no later than September 27,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Some Western analysts have said NATO enlargement might strengthen ultra-nationalists and communists in Russia who are opposed to significant democratic reform and closer relations with the West while dreaming of a restored Russian empire.</p>
<p>But even Yeltsin's immediate circle and liberals in his reformist government are troubled by NATO expansion.</p>
<p>A Russian military official told Interfax that Moscow regretted NATO's refusal to make written guarantees that it will not offer membership at some time in the future to former Soviet republics.</p>
<p>&quot;The refusal to state this in the text of the Russia-NATO Founding Act raises doubts about the sincerity of the NATO leaders' intentions,&quot; said the official, who was not named.</p>
<p>Moscow has said it will review relations with NATO if the alliance lures in former Soviet republics and has expressed particular concern that it will reach out to the Baltic states of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
