<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712787" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Mixed feelings in Albania on foreign troops going.</title>
<headline>Mixed feelings in Albania on foreign troops going.</headline>
<byline>Belinda Goldsmith</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Albanians had mixed feelings on Tuesday about the withdrawal of a multinational security force, stressing the need for foreign help to rebuild their devastated country after months of bloody anarchy.</p>
<p>The Italian-led force of more than 7,000 soldiers from 11 nations will pull out of Albania completely by August 12 after a four-month mission to oversee aid deliveries and ensure elections on June 29 and July 6 ran smoothly.</p>
<p>&quot;It would be better if they stayed longer,&quot; said taxi driver Ylli Mezini. &quot;The situation is still tense and the troops help calm things down.&quot;</p>
<p>Tirana student Nerajda Berisha said the troops should stay until the new left-centre coalition government, to be appointed later this month after a landslide election victory by the opposition Socialists, settles in.</p>
<p>&quot;The situation here is still bad. The Albanian police have not got the strength to do anything,&quot; Berisha said.</p>
<p>&quot;Everyone here has guns and they are not scared of the police. The police are scared of the people. We need help in getting Albanian authorities working again.&quot;</p>
<p>Franz Vranitzky, head of an Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe mission overseeing the vote, said an international working group would be set up to help restore law and order and start economic reconstruction in Albania.</p>
<p>&quot;We should help the Albanians to set up a functioning and convincing police force and a judiciary,&quot; Vranitzky told Reuters in a telephone interview on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I have also suggested...we should invite the Albanians to join us in this working group so we do not come up with some academic proposition.&quot;</p>
<p>Multinational troops were deployed across Albania in April in Operation Alba (Italian for dawn) after a violent uprising sparked by the collapse of get-rich-quick savings funds left the army and police in disarray and state authority in tatters.</p>
<p>President Sali Berisha's Democratic government was forced to resign, blamed for allowing the shady savings funds to flourish, and an interim 10-party government was appointed to bridge the gap ahead of a new election.</p>
<p>The interim authorities immediately requested Western military intervention from NATO's European members -- the Western European Union -- but the United Nations Security Council approved only a protection force to oversee aid.</p>
<p>In the following months, as the death toll rose over 1,500 and paramilitary gangs terrorised swathes of the country, the multinational force was criticised by some for not intervening.</p>
<p>The pro-Democratic newspaper Albania on Tuesday published an damning editorial about the operation.</p>
<p>&quot;The multinational protection force is leaving in shame. Since April they never experienced the smell of gunpowder.&quot;</p>
<p>Lieutenant Colonel Giovanni Bernardi, spokesman for the multinational force, declined to comment on the article, repeating the force's mandate was to secure ports and airports for aid deliveries and the safety of humanitarian groups.</p>
<p>He said the mission, which has been declared a success by the United States' Secretary of State Madeleine Albright, was relatively peaceful with only one direct incident.</p>
<p>An Albanian shot at a guard at Elbasan in central Albania two weeks ago after trying to sell him drugs. The guard returned fire, hitting the man who later died in hospital.</p>
<p>&quot;This was the only man who lost his life in an incident with the multinational force,&quot; Bernardi said.</p>
<p>He said less than 10 soldiers were injured in the four months and none in conflicts. Most were hit by falling bullets.</p>
<p>Most Albanians agreed the presence of the troops had helped to stabilise the situation across the chaotic Balkan nation.</p>
<p>&quot;The troops did help calm the situation but now things are a lot quieter,&quot; said Qirjako Kocollair, manager of an international courier company in Tirana.</p>
<p>&quot;Now money should be spent not on troops but on organising the police, training and finding the right people to get the country working again.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
