<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712748" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech PM Klaus says NATO call climax to reforms.</title>
<headline>Czech PM Klaus says NATO call climax to reforms.</headline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Czech Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus on Tuesday welcomed NATO's decision to invite the Czech Republic to join the alliance, saying the enlargement decision was the culmination of post-Communist reforms.</p>
<p>Speaking to reporters minutes after receiving the news from the Madrid NATO summit, Klaus said his country was ready to bear the responsibility and costs of membership, scheduled for 1999.</p>
<p>&quot;For this country it is an historic moment...an exceptionally important step was made for our future, for our security, for our position in Europe and in the whole world,&quot; Klaus said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is the culmination of the whole process following November (1989, when communist rule ended),&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We know NATO entry is not a one-way street, we cannot be only passive participants of this security grouping, we want to be an active link.&quot;</p>
<p>Klaus added that admission negotiations would start &quot;without delay&quot;.</p>
<p>He reiterated that the Czech Republic was ready to increase military spending to two percent of gross domestic product from the current 1.7 percent over the next few years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
