<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712792" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Albanian chiefs must honour polls or lose aid-OSCE.</title>
<headline>Albanian chiefs must honour polls or lose aid-OSCE.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>OSCE monitors of Albania's elections said on Tuesday they had been acceptable, if not free and fair, and Albanian leaders now had to honour the outcome and seek reconciliation or lose international aid.</p>
<p>&quot;In our judgement, these elections can be deemed as acceptable given the prevailing circumstances,&quot; the 54-nation Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe said in a final report on the vote held on June 29 and July 6.</p>
<p>But it made clear politicians of the right and left had to show a new respect for democratic processes and pursue reconciliation -- especially as a 7,000-strong multinational security force is to leave Albania on August 12.</p>
<p>&quot;Without such reconciliation, there will be no basis for defining the terms of international aid and the continued support for the international community,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>In Albania, the ex-communist Socialists and their allies looked set for a two-thirds majority over President Sali Berisha's Democratic Party.</p>
<p>Prime minister-designate Fatos Nano was hoping to convene a new parliament by July 20, even if the delayed full results were not in by then.</p>
<p>OSCE officials admitted that the vote, during which three election officials were killed while private political armies roamed parts of the country, was far from perfect.</p>
<p>But they argued that there was far greater hope for Albania, as was the case earlier in Bosnia, in holding a vote in imperfect conditions than in delaying them.</p>
<p>&quot;We haven't said these elections were perfect, nor free and fair, but we have observed that 73 percent (of Albanians) voted in calm and seriousness,&quot; OSCE election coordinator Catherine Lalumiere told a news conference in Warsaw.</p>
<p>&quot;They wanted to come out of chaos and out of violence and they voted for that,&quot; she said, adding that Berisha and other parties had promised to abide by the results.</p>
<p>Lalumiere said that despite various irregularities, including some deliberate delays in reporting the results -- apparently by supporters of the losing side -- the difference in the results was so marked that the outcome was clear.</p>
<p>Where seriously irregular behaviour had occurred, it was at least balanced, said Gerard Stoudmann, Director of the OSCE's Office for Democratic Institutions and Human Rights.</p>
<p>&quot;In some parts of the country both major political formations had armed groups which were more or less working for them...they were very balanced in their armaments, their strengths and in the way they behaved in trying to intimidate the local population,&quot; said Stoudmann.</p>
<p>The early elections were called in March after the collapse of savings funds triggered a violent rebellion followed by armed anarchy that led to more than 1,500 deaths -- prompting the Democratic government of the ex-communist Balkan state to quit.</p>
<p>Javier Ruperez, Spanish president of the 54-nation OSCE Parliamentary Assembly, issued a warning to Albanian politicians of left and right to break with the past and put democratic stability over factional interests.</p>
<p>&quot;That is the lesson we have to tell the Albanian political elites -- to behave in a completely different way,&quot; he said, driving home the message that urgently-needed economic, military and other aid depended on it.</p>
<p>He said the OSCE Albania mission's chief Franz Vranitzky would later submit conclusions to OSCE leaders who would decide on recommendations for international aid.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
