<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712741" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Joyful Poland urges NATO to accept more members.</title>
<headline>Joyful Poland urges NATO to accept more members.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Polish government, delighted at an invitation on Tuesday to start NATO entry talks, urged the Western alliance to keep the enlargement process going and not to exclude any other country which wanted to enter.</p>
<p>&quot;The Polish government considers that the first phase of enlargement should not be the last and none of the countries aspiring to membership should be excluded from it,&quot; it said in a statement.</p>
<p>The North Atlantic Treaty Organisation's 16 leaders earlier announced that Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic were being asked to begin the talks, and named Slovenia and Romania as prime candidates for the next round.</p>
<p>They also cited the Baltic states -- Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia -- as aspiring members.</p>
<p>The issue of whether to invite three members as the United States wanted, or five as advocated by France and Italy, was highly contentious at the summit and delayed a decision for some tense hours.</p>
<p>&quot;The (Polish) cabinet expresses the conviction that the gradual enlargement of the alliance and the development of its cooperation with partner nations are key conditions for building a new European security architecture based on shared values and harmonious cooperation of all countries,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p>Echoing the first reaction of Poland's President Aleksander Kwasniewski in Madrid, the cabinet said it greeted the invitation to the first three members &quot;with deep satisfaction&quot;.</p>
<p>Poles still look back with resentment to the deal cut in 1945 after World War Two in the Crimean resort of Yalta between the Soviet Union, Britain and the United States which consigned Poland and other central European states to Moscow's sphere of control.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's decisions....constitute a symbolic closing of the Yalta era,&quot; the cabinet said.</p>
<p>Poland is conscious that it must still secure ratification for its membership from all 16 parliaments of NATO countries -- especially by two-thirds of the 100 U.S. senators, some of whom are anxious about the costs and military commitments their country may have to shoulder.</p>
<p>The statement said Poland believed NATO's enlargement was an opportunity for all the pact's members and that they would all ratify it.</p>
<p>Polish strategists see a central role for their country, a leader in post-communist economic and political reform, as a bridge for other states in the region seeking closer integration with Western structures.</p>
<p>Poland partly feels it should help to extend the benefits it enjoys itself, and partly fears that any areas of power vacuum could create instability.</p>
<p>It has scored successes in overcoming mutual historical suspicions and forging closer ties, especially with Lithuania and Ukraine.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton will spend most of Thursday in Poland, and he and Kwasniewski are both to address a large crowd in Warsaw's historic Castle Square who will celebrate the event with a street party.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
