<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712719" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Rejected Romania aims at NATO membership next time.</title>
<headline>Rejected Romania aims at NATO membership next time.</headline>
<byline>Ron Popeski</byline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Romanian leaders gracefully acknowledged on Tuesday their bid for early NATO membership had failed and predicted the country would be accepted in the next wave of the alliance's expansion.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Victor Ciorbea said Romania's last-minute campaign to win entry in the first eastward enlargement had been thwarted by delays in implementing his country's post-communist reforms.</p>
<p>&quot;Romania's efforts to promote reforms are clear to all and lead us to a clear conclusion,&quot; he told a Romanian television station from a conference north of Bucharest. &quot;If we complete reforms, and I'm sure we will, in 1999 we'll be NATO members.&quot;</p>
<p>NATO's 16 leaders announced in Madrid that Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic had been invited to join the alliance.</p>
<p>But the summit left the door open for a review of further expansion in 1999 and specifically praised the efforts of Romania and Slovenia. The three ex-Soviet Baltic states were also mentioned as &quot;aspiring members&quot;.</p>
<p>Romanian President Emil Constantinescu had before the summit all but abandoned hope of securing first-wave admission and had argued instead for a &quot;reasonable compromise&quot;, giving assurances that countries turned away now would be considered later.</p>
<p>The United States had insisted on limiting initial expansion to the three more developed front-runners. France led European states pressing for a broader expansion. That secured a commitment for a 1999 review of enlargement.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton is due to visit Bucharest on Friday to tell Romanians they stood to win membership in a subsequent wave.</p>
<p>Deputy Defence Minister Constantin Dudu Ionescu said he expected Clinton &quot;to put some political meat on the Madrid announcement&quot; during his eight-hour visit.</p>
<p>&quot;At least we got something if not everything we wanted. We had wanted more -- a firm commitment for 1999,&quot; Ionescu said by telephone. &quot;But politics is the art of compromise and we understand what happened there, even if we don't like it.&quot;</p>
<p>Ciorbea told Romanian radio that his centrist government could not, during its seven months in office, close the economic gap with the three more advanced neighbours after seven years of slow reforms under ex-communists.</p>
<p>&quot;We all wish we were part of the first wave but we must admit that although in the past seven months we did everything humanly possible, we could not catch up the years of delay,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Fast-track reforms drawn up by Ciorbea's government after centrists ousted ex-communists in last November's elections had turned Romania from a no-hoper for first round admission into a longshot with a chance.</p>
<p>The conclusion of treaties with Hungary and Ukraine, burying long-standing disputes over borders and minorities, also improved its chances.</p>
<p>Opinion surveys show Romanians overwhelmingly support NATO membership but are not disheartened by the setback in Madrid.</p>
<p>Constantinescu had left for the NATO summit after signing into law the treaty clinched last month with Ukraine -- less than 24 hours after it secured parliamentary approval.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac made a strong plea for Romania in Madrid, as did Italy's Prime Minister Romano Prodi for Slovenia, the only ex-Yugoslav state vying for early admission. Both were backed by nine of the 16 alliance members.</p>
<p>&quot;Some are raising questions about Romania, which has made a clear choice for democracy and the market economy,&quot; Chirac said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
