<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712746" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish trade gap not to widen on '98 budget-finmin.</title>
<headline>Polish trade gap not to widen on '98 budget-finmin.</headline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's budget deficit next year will be sufficiently small not to cause any further widening of the country's large trade gap, Finance Minister Marek Belka said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the reduction of the budget deficit that we were planing for next year is sufficient to arrest the growth of the trade deficit,&quot; Belka said.</p>
<p>After the first four months of the year Poland's trade gap was $4 billion, twice as much as in the same period last year.</p>
<p>The finance ministry wants to cut the deficit to 1.9 percent of the gross domestic product from 2.8 percent planned for 1997, but the independent central bank says that Poland can only afford a 1.5 percent budget gap and should aim at a balanced budget as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>The National Bank of Poland has said the government should balance its books in 1999 or face a Czech-style currency crisis stemming from a ballooning trade gap which would be fuelled by high domestic demand for imports.</p>
<p>But the Polish Peasant Party (PSL), the junior partner in the ruling left-wing coalition with the ex-communist Democratic Left Alliance (SLD), wants the deficit at 2.8 percent of GDP, saying otherwise the economy's growth would be throttled.</p>
<p>Belka, speaking at a reception after Poland's successful Yankee bond launch, said he was confident the government would resist pressure from the PSL to raise the deficit.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not concerned about that (political pressure from PSL on spending ahead of September elections). It is easier to construct and defend the budget in 1997, a few months before the elections, than it was last year,&quot; Belka said. @</p>
<p>Asked if government subsidies for the inefficient mining and energy sectors would get the axe Belka said:</p>
<p>&quot;We are proposing cuts in real terms and in some cases even in nominal terms.&quot;</p>
<p>-- Wojciech Moskwa +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
