<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712721" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Yeltsin sets longer deadline to pay wage arrears.</title>
<headline>Yeltsin sets longer deadline to pay wage arrears.</headline>
<byline>Anatoly Verbin</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Boris Yeltsin succumbed to pressure from reformist ministers on Tuesday to delay paying huge wage arrears to public-sector workers and his government got down to the job of finding the money.</p>
<p>Yeltsin met liberal First Deputy Prime Minister Boris Nemtsov, a firm presidential favourite these days, at the lakeside residence near the Finnish border where he has been holidaying since Sunday.</p>
<p>The president signed a decree saying wage arrears to the armed forces should be paid in two months, as he had wished, but that a deadline for clearing the backlog to other employees on the state payroll would be moved back to January 1, 1998.</p>
<p>On Friday Yeltsin had said he wanted these other arrears to be paid by October 1.</p>
<p>&quot;In two months we cover the debt to the army and in three months more -- to the rest of the public sector,&quot; he said in televised remarks.</p>
<p>&quot;(The debt) is a disgrace for our country,&quot; said Yeltsin, recognising the threat posed by the pent-up frustrations of the millions whose wages have been delayed for periods of up to six months over the past two years.</p>
<p>Yeltsin had come under strong pressure to extend his original deadline from Nemtsov and the other first deputy prime minister, Anatoly Chubais.</p>
<p>Nemtsov, feeling clearly at ease, told Yeltsin that only a date of January 1 was realistic.</p>
<p>&quot;I do not want to mislead the people,&quot; he said, adding the government had worked round the clock to prepare the plan.</p>
<p>&quot;The government is young and can do without sleep,&quot; Nemtsov, 37, added with a laugh.</p>
<p>Yeltsin radically reshuffled the government in March, keeping veteran Prime Minister Viktor Chernomyrdin in place but giving him an effectively new team, led by Chubais, 41, and Nemtsov, to give fresh impetus to market reforms.</p>
<p>Their first public success was finding the money to pay the backlog of pensions by July 1 and the next task is wage arrears.</p>
<p>The total amount of the debt remains unclear.</p>
<p>Chubais has said the wage backlog to the armed forces alone is more than five trillion roubles ($860 million).</p>
<p>The Finance Ministry's press service said on Tuesday that the central government's debt to those working in federal institutions was 7.7 trillion roubles, while the overall debt of regional authorities amounted to 25.6 trillion roubles ($4.4 billion). It was not clear whether these figures included the debt to the armed forces.</p>
<p>Chubais is on holiday while Chernomyrdin preferred to stay in Moscow and chair a meeting of a special commission whose task is to boost state revenues.</p>
<p>Russian news agencies said the commission had drawn up a list of the 50 biggest companies that are not paying their taxes and discussed taking tough action against them.</p>
<p>Yeltsin told Nemtsov that there could be no question of printing money to cover the state's debts.</p>
<p>&quot;We must determine ways of finding finances...how we can cut spending and increase revenues, where to use borrowing, the sale of property and securities,&quot; Interfax news agency quoted him as saying.</p>
<p>Interfax said Yeltsin also signed decrees on production sharing, which covers the rights of foreign investors, and on oil industry debts to the state budget. The latter document also covered quotas on oil sales.</p>
<p>No details were immediately available but Interfax quoted Yeltsin as saying both documents were &quot;of global importance&quot;. He said in televised remarks the two documents would be &quot;appreciated by the whole world.&quot;</p>
<p>Nemtsov was quoted as saying the new rules were aimed at making it impossible &quot;for crooks to do nothing but earn money&quot;. ($=5,791 roubles)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
