<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712866" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>RUSSIA: Russia regrets NATO expansion as summit starts.</title>
<headline>Russia regrets NATO expansion as summit starts.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Heritage</byline>
<dateline>MOSCOW 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia routinely denounced NATO's eastward expansion as its former Cold War foe began a summit on Tuesday at which it will offer membership to selected countries from former communist eastern Europe.</p>
<p>One Russian opposition newspaper said July 8 would go down as a day of national shame because of the Kremlin's &quot;capitulation' in allowing enlargement to go ahead.</p>
<p>But official criticism was muted and newspaper commentaries mainly concentrated on Russia's improved relationship with NATO and the Western defence alliance's internal divisions.</p>
<p>&quot;Today NATO is expanding. From our point of view, this is a mistake,&quot; Ivan Rybkin, secretary of Russia's policy-making Security Council, told the daily Moskovsky Komsomolets in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Of course the Russia-NATO Founding Act removes many of our concerns but not all.&quot;</p>
<p>The Founding Act, signed by President Boris Yeltsin and NATO leaders in Paris in May, created a joint council which gave Moscow a say but not a veto in some security matters.</p>
<p>Russian officials say NATO expansion is a security threat and creates new divisions in Europe.</p>
<p>Yeltsin failed to persuade NATO to halt its plans to enlarge but a government official, who declined to be named, portrayed Russia's recent diplomacy in a positive light.</p>
<p>The official told Interfax news agency on the eve of the Madrid summit that Russia had outplayed the eastern European countries seeking admission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation by securing an immediate say in alliance affairs.</p>
<p>He said Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic, which are expected to be formally invited to join NATO, would become full members only after two years of talks.</p>
<p>&quot;As for Russia, it already has an opportunity to really influence alliance policy in the framework of the permanent council which, in line with the Founding Act, will get down to business no later than September 27,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>Yeltsin, who opted not to go to Madrid for the summit, has said repeatedly that signing the Founding Act does not mean Russia has dropped its opposition to NATO expansion.</p>
<p>He was on holiday in northwestern Russia on Tuesday and made no immediate comment.</p>
<p>Yeltsin's communist and nationalist opponents have accused him of betraying national interests by making a deal with NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;July 8, 1997, will go down forever as a day of national shame for Russia,&quot; the pro-communist newspaper Sovietskaya Rossiya said.</p>
<p>It said NATO's border was moving closer to Russia's frontier &quot;as a result of the Kremlin's line of capitulation&quot;.</p>
<p>The daily Nezavisimaya Gazeta concentrated on the divisions in NATO over how many countries should be invited to join now, but said the alliance was likely eventually to offer membership to the Baltic states despite protests by Moscow.</p>
<p>&quot;In this way, Moscow's concerns about former Soviet republics joining NATO will in practice be ignored,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>Moscow has said it will review relations with NATO if the alliance lures in former Soviet republics and has expressed particular concern that it will reach out to the Baltic states of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania.</p>
<p>Commercial NTV television said the summit coincided with the anniversary of an agreement signed between Tsar Alexander I and Napoleon at Tilsit in 1807. Russia and France formed an alliance under the agreement but went to war only five years later.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MOSCOW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="RUSSIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
