<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712833" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ROMANIA: Romania president seeks compromise at NATO summit.</title>
<headline>Romania president seeks compromise at NATO summit.</headline>
<byline>Roxana Dascalu</byline>
<dateline>BUCHAREST 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Romanian President Emil Constantinescu left for the NATO summit in Madrid on Tuesday to press for a last-minute compromise guaranteeing his country would win entry to the Western alliance at some point.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm going to Madrid to represent Romania's fundamental and strategic interests,&quot; Emil Constantinescu told reporters at Bucharest's Otopeni airport. &quot;I am confident of a favourable result for Romania, in the long term.&quot;</p>
<p>In the face of U.S. demands that initial expansion be limited to Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic, Constantinescu has all but abandoned hope that Romania will gain entry in NATO's first eastward enlargement.</p>
<p>He has been arguing instead for a &quot;reasonable compromise&quot; under which Romania -- and probably Slovenia -- will be given some assurance that their bids will be considered next.</p>
<p>Constantinescu rushed to the airport an hour ahead of his scheduled departure, but officials gave no reason for the change of plan.</p>
<p>Sources close to the president said he had signed into law a treaty clinched last month with neighbouring Ukraine -- less than 24 hours after it secured parliamentary approval.</p>
<p>NATO leaders went into a restricted session -- attended only by delegation leaders and two aides each -- after France repeated calls for Romania and Slovenia to be considered now.</p>
<p>The treaty with Ukraine was endorsed late on Monday by centrists who dominate parliament. It settles disputes over borders and minorities with the former Soviet republic and was seen as a key point in Romania's NATO membership hopes.</p>
<p>In Madrid, French President Jacques Chirac made a strong plea for Romania, as did Italy's Prime Minister Romano Prodi for Slovenia, the only ex-Yugoslav state vying for early admission. Both are backed by nine of the 16 alliance members.</p>
<p>&quot;Some are raising questions about Romania, which has made a clear choice for democracy and the market economy,&quot; Chirac said, citing progress made since Constantinescu and centrists took office last year.</p>
<p>The coalition government has pledged to speed up reforms that were kept at snail's pace during seven years of rule by former communists.</p>
<p>Chirac praised Bucharest for treaties with both Ukraine and Hungary, saying they had ended centuries-old disputes. He also pointed to Romania's role in peacekeeping missions in Bosnia and Albania. He said Romania could strengthen the alliance's southern flank, in the sensitive Black Sea and Balkan region.</p>
<p>Opinion surveys show Romanians overwhelmingly support NATO membership but are not disheartened by the apparent setback of its immediate bid to join.</p>
<p>Newspapers of all political persuasions ran front-page headlines on the Madrid summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Romania must get assurances for second-wave admission&quot; the top-selling daily Evenimentul Zilei said. &quot;Madrid -- the last station for our disillusion?&quot; asked Dimineata, which backs the ex-communist opposition.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUCHAREST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ROMANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
