<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712812" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ALBANIA: Europe offers stick and carrot to shaky Albania.</title>
<headline>Europe offers stick and carrot to shaky Albania.</headline>
<byline>Colin McIntyre</byline>
<dateline>TIRANA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>As talks begin on forming a new government in Albania to rebuild the shattered country after months of anarchy and bloodshed, the rest of Europe looks on anxiously waving both a carrot and a stick.</p>
<p>Alarmed at the near-meltdown in Europe's poorest country earlier this year which sent thousands of refugees fleeing to Italy and Greece, other countries are falling over themselves to offer help.</p>
<p>But the West, which organised and monitored the elections won by the ex-communist Socialists, has made it clear there will be no aid unless Albania's fractious politicians bury their old enmities and cooperate in getting the country back on its feet.</p>
<p>The Organisation of Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE) called on Tuesday for the politicians to seek reconciliation, saying otherwise &quot;there will be no basis for defining the terms of international aid, and the continued support of the international community&quot;.</p>
<p>The Spanish president of the OSCE's parliamentary assembly, meeting in Warsaw, told a news conference: &quot;Probably the Albanians don't deserve their own political elites...I can tell you frankly we were at times utterly fed up with the show of unreliability of those political elites, both of the left and right. They should learn a hard lesson...&quot;</p>
<p>Election monitors have openly criticised delays in counting the votes from the June 29 election -- final official results are still not in -- and of protest rallies by royalists backed by the defeated Democratic Party of President Sali Berisha, which threatened to raise tension.</p>
<p>Diplomats fear that Berisha, who will step down after his party was decimated in the elections, might opt for an obstructive rather than a constructive opposition.</p>
<p>The first test of his good intentions could come in a few days, after prime minister-designate Fatos Nano said he hoped to convene the new parliament by July 20, even if final poll results are not available by then.</p>
<p>With seven electoral districts still unaccounted for and others subject to recounts and challenges, it is possible the final count will not be known for several weeks, offering Berisha the chance to delay the political process.</p>
<p>Berisha could also embarrass the new government by insisting that Nano honour a campaign pledge to give people back the money they lost in shady pyramid savings schemes that collapsed earlier this year, sparking a violent uprising and leading to the elections.</p>
<p>There are also concerns that Nano, with a likely two-thirds majority in the 155-seat parliament, could be tempted to settle old scores, particularly with Berisha who jailed him in 1993 on corruption charges which appeared politically motivated.</p>
<p>Despite Nano's huge majority, enabling his government to push through legislation, diplomats do not expect him to try anything very radical.</p>
<p>&quot;He has little room to manoeuvre, starting from a sub-zero base,&quot; a senior Western diplomat said.</p>
<p>&quot;The tasks he faces -- rebuilding the police and armed forces, liberalising the economy and dealing with international financial organisations -- are the same any Albanian government would face.&quot;</p>
<p>A major problem facing the new government is the estimated one million guns in private hands after army barracks were looted as the country slipped into anarchy in March.</p>
<p>This constant threat of armed violence could put off potential foreign investors, particularly in tourism, which analysts say offers the best prospects for growth in the short term.</p>
<p>However diplomats believe that while some guns will probably never be recovered in a country with a long tradition of self-protection, the restoration of law and order would isolate those using them for crime.</p>
<p>&quot;With no law and order, there is no illegal behaviour,&quot; one diplomat said. &quot;You can walk through Tirana now with a Kalashnikov (automatic rifle) and no one will stop you.&quot;</p>
<p>Diplomats said the most crucial aid the West will be providing, particularly in the short term, is expertise.</p>
<p>Experts in all fields will be sent in to key ministries and departments, as well as the police and armed forces, to oversee major reforms of systems inherited from four decades of isolationist Stalinist rule.</p>
<p>&quot;We also need to change the way these people think,&quot; one senior diplomat said. &quot;There is no tradition of civic responsibility, or of cooperation. Here it is every man for himself.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TIRANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ALBANIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
