<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712967" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>ECUADOR: Two dead, 180 injured in Ecuador barracks blast.</title>
<headline>Two dead, 180 injured in Ecuador barracks blast.</headline>
<dateline>QUITO, Ecuador 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>At least two people were killed and about 180 injured in an explosion that tore through an Ecuadoran army ammunition store on the outskirts of the capital Quito on Tuesday, witnesses and medical sources said.</p>
<p>&quot;Approximately 180 injured and two dead is the regrettable toll. About 50 people with serious injuries, all of them military officials, have been admitted to a military hospital,&quot; police said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;About 300 medics are working to help the injured. Further explosions cannot be ruled out,&quot; police said. A fire official said two firefighters were missing and three others were seriously injured.</p>
<p>Army officials blamed the blast, which caused damage over more than a mile (1.6 km) radius, on a fire in an ammunitions storage area in the Las Balvinas military complex, about 12 miles (20 km) outside Quito.</p>
<p>&quot;We can't get to the area because a clean-up is under way and explosives are being taken away by teams. We are evaluating the damage,&quot; Gen. Jorge Salinas, the army's chief of staff, said.</p>
<p>A Reuters photographer said he saw two corpses being taken into a military hospital in Quito and dozens of injured people being rushed in for treatment.</p>
<p>&quot;There are people with shrapnel wounds from the explosion,&quot; the photographer said. &quot;Most of the injured are from the military, but there are civilians too,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>An eyewitness told Radio Quito: &quot;It was a tremendous explosion. Then I saw the bodies lying on the ground. There are civilians' homes near the site of the explosion.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ECU">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="QUITO, Ecuador"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ECUADOR"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
