<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712923" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico cocaine king's death won't affect supply.</title>
<headline>Mexico cocaine king's death won't affect supply.</headline>
<byline>Michael Stott</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The sudden death of Mexico's leading drug lord will not affect cocaine smuggling from Mexico to the United States and Europe, a U.S. anti-drug agent said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I like to use the analogy -- when Henry Ford died, the Fords just kept coming out of the factory,&quot; said the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) official, speaking on condition of anonymity. &quot;I don't see any change.&quot;</p>
<p>Cocaine king Amado Carrillo Fuentes died last Friday, apparently in a Mexico City hospital from complications following extensive plastic surgery to alter his appearance.</p>
<p>Described last year by the DEA as the most powerful figure in the Mexican drug trade, Carrillo Fuentes headed a narcotics cartel, smuggling tons of cocaine into the United States.</p>
<p>Asked for reaction to the capo's death, the DEA official said: &quot;Good riddance.&quot;</p>
<p>Carrillo Fuentes's death leaves a huge vacuum in the Mexican drug trade, but past experience suggests that as long as Americans and Europeans continue to buy drugs, the supply will continue regardless of who is in charge.</p>
<p>The DEA official said it was impossible to say which of the Mexican capos might take over from the &quot;Lord of the Skies,&quot; as Carrillo was nicknamed.</p>
<p>&quot;I truly believe if we put every major drug trafficker in this room, they couldn't tell us,&quot; he said. &quot;We could probably foresee a period of unrest, probably a period of violence as people prevent others from taking over this multibillion dollar process.&quot;</p>
<p>The DEA official said he had heard reports that Carrillo Fuentes was a cocaine user, though he did not know to what extent. Doctors say cocaine use would increase the risk for a patient undergoing long surgery under general anaesthesia.</p>
<p>Mexican authorities have still not officially confirmed that the body is Carrillo's, though they have spoken of a &quot;probable&quot; death of the drug lord and invited reporters on Monday to photograph and film the body, lying dressed in a suit in a coffin on a mortuary slab.</p>
<p>The DEA official, however, said he was &quot;convinced&quot; the body was that of Carrillo Fuentes. &quot;As we say in DEA: 'Bet your badge.' I'll bet my badge, I'll say it's him,&quot; he told a small group of reporters.</p>
<p>U.S. officials matched fingerprints taken from the corpse to a U.S. border crossing card in Carrillo Fuentes' name, he added. Border crossing cards are commonly issued to residents of the Mexico-U.S. border zone.</p>
<p>Mexican authorities say investigations so far suggest Carrillo Fuentes checked into the Santa Monica hospital in the smart Polanco district of the capital last Thursday for extensive plastic surgery under a false name.</p>
<p>After a long operation he was taken to his room, where a duty doctor later found him dead.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
