<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712913" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: New era in Mexico as opposition surges.</title>
<headline>New era in Mexico as opposition surges.</headline>
<byline>Caroline Brothers</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A new epoch of multi-party politics opened in Mexico on Tuesday after early results from landmark elections gave opposition parties an unprecedented voice in the country's political future.</p>
<p>President Ernesto Zedillo of the long-ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI) sought to open the dialogue with his political opponents even before final results were available from Sunday's polls that broke the 68-year PRI grip on power.</p>
<p>While voters handed victory to the PRI's bitter political opponent Cuauhtemoc Cardenas of the left-wing Party of the Democratic Revolution (PRD) in the race for Mexico City mayor, the final composition of the lower house of Congress was still uncertain on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The newly independent Federal Electoral Institute (IFE) gave its last preliminary count late on Monday indicating the PRI had lost its absolute majority in Congress' lower house -- in the past no more than a rubber stamp for the budget and other legislation proposed by the president.</p>
<p>IFE officials were not scheduled to begin processing final results until Wednesday.</p>
<p>Of the 300 directly elected seats in the lower house, IFE gave the PRI 161 against 71 for the PRD and 67 for the conservative National Action Party (PAN), with almost 87 percent of votes counted.</p>
<p>The remaining 200 seats will be allocated by proportional representation and newspapers on Tuesday had already begun guessing the colours of the new chamber, all of them predicting the PRI would lose its longtime majority in the 500-seat body.</p>
<p>El Universal daily forecast 236 deputies for the PRI against 132 for the PAN and 116 for the PRD. La Cronica predicted 235 deputies for the PRI but put the PRD ahead of the PAN, with 126 and 124 seats respectively.</p>
<p>The results so far show the PRI losing its absolute majority in its biggest upset since it came to power after Mexico's 1910-17 revolution.</p>
<p>The last few percent to be counted left open the chance the PRI could muster enough votes in the remaining rural districts to retain control of the Chamber of Deputies, but even its own party leaders doubted it would achieve that and Zedillo began the delicate task of courting the opposition to prevent legislative gridlock when Congress opens in September.</p>
<p>&quot;Following (Sunday's) elections all parties are entering a new era in which ... we must promote dialogue, agreement and consensus,&quot; Zedillo said in a post-electoral speech at the presidential mansion of Los Pinos.</p>
<p>In an unusual gesture, he held out the hand of friendship to main opposition parties, which he tirelessly attacked during the election campaign, and paid special tribute to an unlikely bedfellow -- the leftist PRD.</p>
<p>The PRD, a party on the brink of collapse just a few years ago, made a huge leap in the elections, its strength largely buoyed by Cardenas's landslide victory.</p>
<p>Of all Mexican parties, the PRD has been most stubborn in its opposition to Zedillo's economic reform agenda, though Cardenas and other party leaders softened some of their radical left-wing views leading up to the elections.</p>
<p>&quot;I have always thought that a party of the left, a strong one, as the PRD showed it was yesterday, is good for Mexico,&quot; Zedillo said, reiterating his offer to work with Cardenas.</p>
<p>Cardenas has been similarly conciliatory, acknowledging the president's political reforms helped level the playing field in a country long considered a one-party state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
