<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="712995" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: Chile salmon raisers mull talks in U.S. trade spat.</title>
<headline>Chile salmon raisers mull talks in U.S. trade spat.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chilean salmon raisers are studying ways of reaching a negotiated solution to a brewing trade dispute over claims by U.S. producers that their Chilean counterparts are dumping fish on the American market.</p>
<p>&quot;Our objective is to come out of the situation in the best way possible by obtaining the lowest tariffs or a negotiated solution,&quot; Francisco Ruiz, president of the Salmon and Trout Producers Association, told a news conference.  </p>
<p>The association, which represents private salmon companies, has started talks with the Chilean economy ministry which would have to present proposals to end the spat to the Clinton administration, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are analyzing with the government ways of reaching an agreement during the investigation. This must (by law) be a government to government pact and not one between private companies,&quot; said Ruiz.  </p>
<p>Economy Minister Alvaro Garcia was due to travel to Washington next week for talks with Commerce Secretary William Daley over the dispute, the most serious trade row between the two countries in recent years.</p>
<p>The International Trade Commission (ITC) began investigations this month into claims from U.S. salmon producers that Chilean companies received hidden subsidies and were dumping fresh Atlantic salmon in the U.S.</p>
<p>Fresh Chilean salmon enters the U.S. with no tariff and U.S. producers are demanding duties of up to 40 percent.  </p>
<p>One suggestion under study could be to limit future growth of salmon exports to the United States -- Chile's second largest export market, said Ruiz.</p>
<p>Chilean producers fear that they could suffer the same fate as Norwegian firms who were accused of dumping in 1991 and then were effectively banished by high tariffs from the U.S. market.</p>
<p>&quot;It's the lesser of two evils. The worst of all would be what happended to Norway which is now out of the market,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>If a negotiated solution is reached, the probe into the dumping and subsidy claims would be suspended, said Ruiz.</p>
<p>Chilean salmon exports to the United States rose 25 percent to $45 million compared with the same period last year. American supermarkets and restaurants are Chile's largest market for fresh salmon exports. ((-- Margaret Orgill, Santiago newsroom, 562-699-5595 x212))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
