<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713036" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexican leader seeks to bury hatchet with opponents.</title>
<headline>Mexican leader seeks to bury hatchet with opponents.</headline>
<byline>Henry Tricks</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Ernesto Zedillo extended the hand of friendship to opposition parties late on Monday, the day after mid-term elections that dealt his party its biggest setback in 68 years of rule.</p>
<p>Responding to the new political landscape in Mexico, in which preliminary results showed his party was likely to have lost its decades-old majority in the lower house of Congress, Zedillo praised all political parties and spoke of a &quot;new era&quot; of cooperation between them.</p>
<p>He paid a special tribute to the leftist Party of the Democratic Revolution (PRD), which won control of the capital of Mexico in mayoral elections and gained unexpected ground in the national legislative vote.</p>
<p>It was a huge advance on its 1994 performance in the presidential race, after which the party almost crumbled, and signalled a resurgence of the left in Mexico.</p>
<p>&quot;I have always thought that a party of the left, a strong one, as the PRD showed it was yesterday, is good for Mexico,&quot; Zedillo said, in a suprising show of support from a leader whose government had often sparred openly with the PRD.</p>
<p>He also praised the conservative National Action Party (PAN), considered closer to Zedillo ideologically, as a party with broad national support.</p>
<p>His remarks, during a speech at the presidential mansion of Los Pinos, reflected his obvious desire to work with the opposition, so that congressional gridlock does not block his legislative agenda.</p>
<p>&quot;Following yesterdays's elections, all parties are entering a new era in which contest has been left behind and in which now we must promote dialogue, agreement and consensus,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In the lower house race, with more than 85 percent of the votes counted, the PRI had 38.9 percent of the vote -- not enough to give it an absolute majority -- followed by the PAN with 27 percent and the PRD with 25.6 percent.</p>
<p>Zedillo also sought to highlight the role of his own party in the elections, saying it had pushed through the electoral laws that levelled the political playing field in Mexico and that underscored the PRI's own democratic credentials.</p>
<p>&quot;After these elections, now no one call call the PRI the only party, the party of the state or an appendix of government,&quot; Zedillo said.</p>
<p>He noted that it remained the biggest party and retained a majority in the Senate, and had achieved that in elections widely considered to be clean.</p>
<p>In the past, the PRI was often accused of using fraud to maintain its grip on power, that it has held unbroken since 1929.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
