<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713097" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Lutherans open world meeting in China-run HK.</title>
<headline>Lutherans open world meeting in China-run HK.</headline>
<byline>John O'Callaghan</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Lutheran church began its ninth international assembly in Hong Kong on Tuesday, just a week after the territory became part of communist China, ignoring fears about freedom of religion after the transition.</p>
<p>&quot;We are getting good vibrations that the churches have no business of being afraid,&quot; Lutheran World Federation general secretary Ishmael Noko told Reuters after the opening Eucharist.</p>
<p>Noko, who has visited Hong Kong regularly since 1988, met incoming leader Tung Chee-hwa in April to discuss civil liberties and religious freedoms.</p>
<p>At Tung's invitation he also attended last week's ceremony marking the British colony's handover to China.</p>
<p>&quot;For Hong Kong, he has told me that there will be no change,&quot; said Noko.</p>
<p>Tung plans to address the nearly 1,000 delegates, advisers and observers at the assembly on Wednesday morning, Noko said.</p>
<p>Religion has enjoyed a revival in China in recent years as Beijing relaxes controls on religious groups, which were once suppressed as subversive.</p>
<p>But Beijing still keeps a tight watch on religious activities and insists the faithful worship through officially controlled or sponsored organisations.</p>
<p>Further relaxation in China will come eventually, Noko said, with Hong Kong easing the way.</p>
<p>A request from China to postpone the assembly had at one time looked like a problem for the Lutheran federation. But China's concerns that the meeting would overlap with handover celebrations were resolved by a visit to Beijing, Noko said.</p>
<p>The nine-day assembly is a forum for delegates from 68 countries to discuss social justice, doctrine and other issues that will be distilled into a policy to be passed along to the church's 58 million followers.</p>
<p>The delegates will also elect a new president and council.</p>
<p>The goal of the meeting, Noko said, is &quot;to move closer to one another given the fact that we are a multitude of cultures&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not easy to keep together given the global situation of regionalism, nationalism and racism,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;The global community will never succeed unless churches are playing a role in building a sense of community,&quot; he said. &quot;We can no longer let politicians decide the future of this global village.&quot;</p>
<p>Sessions over the nine days include discussions on Christian unity with Roman Catholic Cardinal Edward Cassidy and social justice with Hanan Ashrawi, minister of higher education of the Palestinian National Authority.</p>
<p>Bao Jia-yuan and Chen Xi-da of the China Christian Council will lead Friday's open forum on the church in China.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
