<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713040" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Dead Mexican drug lord presented to press.</title>
<headline>Dead Mexican drug lord presented to press.</headline>
<byline>David Luhnow</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>Unable to catch him when he was alive, Mexican officials wheeled out the disfigured corpse of a man they believe was Mexico's most notorious drug kingpin on Monday to a horde of waiting photographers.</p>
<p>U.S. authorities have said the body is that of Amado Carrillo Fuentes, head of the powerful Juarez Cartel who reportedly died on Friday in Mexico City after a botched plastic surgery operation to alter his appearance.</p>
<p>But Mexican officials say they want to carry out conclusive DNA tests on the corpse just to be sure. Either way, the presumed cocaine capo's body was on display on Monday for a grisly photo-op.</p>
<p>Dressed in a dark blue suit and a red tie, the embalmed body was shown off in a green-tiled autopsy room of the Attorney General's office. The corpse was lying in a grey metallic coffin, the arms crossed over the chest.</p>
<p>His throat and skull were lined with stitches and his sunken face was badly bruised, apparently from the surgery he was undergoing to change his appearance.</p>
<p>U.S. Drug Enforcement Agency head Thomas Constantine on Sunday confirmed what Mexican officials had so far been reluctant to say -- that a man calling himself Antonio Flores Montes who checked in for plastic surgery and liposuction in a Mexico City hospital on Thursday was indeed the cocaine baron.</p>
<p>&quot;The so-called 'Lord of the Skies' may have escaped Earthly justice but I'm sure there is a special place in hell reserved for those like him who have destroyed countless human lives,&quot; the DEA chief said in a statement.</p>
<p>Carrillo Fuentes was known as the &quot;Lord of the Skies&quot; for his tactic of using commercial aircraft to fly cocaine undetected to Mexico from South America. The DEA said he was Mexico's most powerful drug trafficker.</p>
<p>Mexican officials maintained on Monday they could not be sure they had finally caught a man who thumbed his nose at authorities on both sides of the U.S.-Mexico border during an eight-year manhunt.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to complete our studies in order to be absolutely sure the body you see in front of you is that of Mr. Carrillo Fuentes,&quot; Mariano Herran Salvatti, head of Mexico's anti-drug agency, told reporters.</p>
<p>Surrounding Salvati, dozens of state pathologists dressed in white lab coats watched photographers snap pictures of the body.</p>
<p>U.S. authorities said on Monday they had offered to perform post-mortem tests on the body to dispel any lingering doubts about its identity, but that Mexican officials had not accepted the offer.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
