<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713032" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: Mexico enters new era of multi-party politics.</title>
<headline>Mexico enters new era of multi-party politics.</headline>
<byline>Henry Tricks</byline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico on Tuesday embarked on a new era of multi-party politics as President Ernesto Zedillo sought to reach out to the opposition in the wake of his party's biggest election setback in 68 years of rule.</p>
<p>Latest preliminary results from Sunday's election for the lower house of Congress gave Zedillo's ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI) 38.86 percent -- short of the 42 percent it needed to keep its decades-old majority.</p>
<p>Authorities suspended the count late on Monday with almost 87 percent of the votes tabulated, saying final results would not begin to be calculated until Wednesday.</p>
<p>That left open the possibility that the PRI could muster enough votes in the remaining rural districts to retain its control of the Chamber of Deputies, which since 1929 has made it a rubber stamp for presidential rule.</p>
<p>But even its own party leaders doubted it would achieve the feat, and Zedillo began the delicate task of courting the opposition to prevent legislative gridlock when the new Congress opens in September.</p>
<p>&quot;Following yesterdays's elections all parties are entering a new era in which ... we must promote dialogue, agreement and consensus,&quot; Zedillo said in a post-electoral speech at the presidential mansion of Los Pinos.</p>
<p>In an unusual gesture, he held out the hand of friendship to main opposition parties that he had tirelessly attacked during the election campaign, and paid special tribute to an unlikely bedfellow -- the leftist Party of the Democratic Revolution (PRD).</p>
<p>The PRD, a party on the brink of collapse just a few years ago, made a huge leap in Sunday's elections, its strength largely bouyed by the landslide victory of its populist candidate Cuauhtemoc Cardenas as mayor of Mexico City.</p>
<p>Of all Mexican parties, the PRD has been most stubborn in its opposition to Zedillo's economic reform agenda, though Cardenas and other party leaders had softened some of their radical left-wing views leading up to the elections.</p>
<p>&quot;I have always thought that a party of the left, a strong one, as the PRD showed it was yesterday, is good for Mexico,&quot; Zedillo said, reiterating his offer to work alongside Cardenas and congratulating him on his victory.</p>
<p>Cardenas has been similarly conciliatory to Zedillo since his remarkeable win in the capital, acknowledging that the president's political reforms had helped level the playing field in a country long considered a one-party state.</p>
<p>&quot;We have finally succeeded in having real elections in Mexico, elections in which the votes are what decides who governs and who represents the people,&quot; Cardenas said in an interview with Reuters on Monday.</p>
<p>The race for the lower house of Congress put the conservative National Action Party (PAN) in second place with 27 percent, and the PRD just behind with 25.6 percent.</p>
<p>In the Mexico City mayor elections -- a post so important it had for decades been held by a presidential appointee -- Cardenas won 47.79 percent, compared to 25.56 percent for the PRI candidate and 15.93 percent for the PAN.</p>
<p>Economists said both main opposition parties would demand concessions from Zedillo if he wanted support for his legislative agenda, the PAN in the form of tax cuts and the PRD in seeking greater social spending.</p>
<p>But they also noted that Zedillo, in his first three years in office, had already pushed through some of his most ambitious reforms, such as privatisation of the state pension system, which made gridlock less likely.</p>
<p>Far from taking fright at the PRI's poor performance in the Sunday race -- it also lost two key state governorships to the PAN though it retained its control of the Senate -- foreign investors charged into Mexico on Monday on a buying spree that pushed the stock market to a new record high.</p>
<p>Part of their excitement, like that of many Mexicans, was evidence that the country could hold clean, peaceful elections. For years, the PRI has been accused of using fraud to maintain its grip on power.</p>
<p>&quot;It's as if we have woken up from a long nightmare,&quot; said Jose Ramon Ortiz, a 55-year-old shopowner in Mexico City's bohemian Condesa neighbourhood.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm shocked. It's always been PRI, PRI, PRI and nothing but the PRI,&quot; Raul Ramirez, a shoeshiner on the city's Reforma Avenue, said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
