<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713117" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Vietnam's Minh Phung scandal still spreading.</title>
<headline>Vietnam's Minh Phung scandal still spreading.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A senior state prosecutor in Vietnam's Ho Chi Minh City has upped the amount of debt owed by scandal-plagued conglomerate Minh Phung to nearly $430 million, significantly worse than previously thought.</p>
<p>Tuesday's Tuoi Tre newspaper quoted Dang The Hong, Ho Chi Minh City's chief prosecutor, as saying delays by banks in reporting and dealing with the troubles surrounding loans to Minh Phung had exacerbated the problem.</p>
<p>&quot;The debt owed by the Minh Phung company is put now at 5,000 billion dong ($428.4 million),&quot; he said. &quot;The recovery of that money, owed by Minh Phung and its subsidiaries, is unlikely.&quot;</p>
<p>Previous estimates of the debt owed by the company, given to police by its director Tang Minh Phung, were put at $370 million.</p>
<p>He was arrested in March, together with the head of another major local firm EPCO on fraud charges, as a scandal surrounding shady and interrelated borrowing to finance vast property deals surfaced.</p>
<p>The company is alleged to have used contacts and influence to obtain huge loans from both state-owned and private commercial banks, mostly through letters of credit.</p>
<p>The scandal has sent shockwaves through Vietnam's domestic banking system, which has been left counting the costs.</p>
<p>But the affair has also adopted more sinister overtones following the grisly death, shortly after the case emerged, of a Minh Phung deputy director on the premises of one of the banks involved.</p>
<p>The Tuoi Tre newspaper quoted a senior city official on Tuesday as calling for a probe of another major conglomerate, Huy Hoang, in order to prevent a recurrence of the scandal.</p>
<p>&quot;The public are very concerned by the real situation of another big private company, Huy Hoang,&quot; said Le Hieu Dang, a social and cultural department official.</p>
<p>&quot;A financial check of the situation at this company should be carried out soon...to prevent a recurrence of the situation at Minh Phung and Epco.&quot;</p>
<p>Huy Hoang has previously denied problems.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C173">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
