<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713147" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAIWAN: Taiwan to hold war games between April-June 1998.</title>
<headline>Taiwan to hold war games between April-June 1998.</headline>
<dateline>TAIPEI 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Taiwan, eager to show it can defend itself amid tense relations with arch-rival China, said on Tuesday it planned to stage a large-scale military exercise between April and June in 1998.</p>
<p>The exercise would be called &quot;Han Kwang&quot; (Chinese Glory) -- the same name as the June 22-24 war games held by Taipei despite international concerns that the manoeuvres would raise tension prior to China's July 1 reassertion of control over Hong Kong.</p>
<p>The 1998 Han Kwang exercise would include four smaller drills and would involve all branches of Taiwan's armed forces, the defence ministry said in a statement.</p>
<p>In addition to Han Kwang, the ministry said it also had plans for three smaller exercises before May 1998 and several more troop drills.</p>
<p>Seeking to head off criticism, the ministry said the war games are routine annual exercises.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like to eliminate the unnecessary speculation and association the outside world has due to the sensitivity of exercises,&quot; the ministry said without elaborating.</p>
<p>Taipei had said repeatedly that its exercises last month were unrelated to the Hong Kong handover even though the manoeuvres allowed the island to test new weapons purchased to counter China's military modernisation.</p>
<p>Among the weapons tested during that exercise were F-16 and Mirage fighter jets purchased respectively from the United States and France over fierce objections from Beijing.</p>
<p>China, which has regarded Taiwan as a renegade province since a civil war split them in 1949, vows to attack the island if it makes a bid for independence.</p>
<p>In 1996, Taiwan suspended its annual joint-forces exercise to avoid exacerbating tensions with China after Beijing staged several war games and missile tests near the island.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TAIWAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TAIPEI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAIWAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
