<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713153" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: HK's Tung maps out immigration, election policies.</title>
<headline>HK's Tung maps out immigration, election policies.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong's new leader Tung Chee-hwa met his senior advisers on Tuesday to discuss policies governing illegal children immigrants and next year's legislative elections.</p>
<p>It was Tung's first meeting with his 15-member Executive Council since Britain handed Hong Kong back to Communist China a week ago, ending 156 years of colonial rule.</p>
<p>Emerging from a marathon five-hour session, Tung told reporters the council had reached consensus on a long string of pressing issues.</p>
<p>&quot;Regarding children born in the mainland (China) to Hong Kong people and the first legislative elections, we have come to conclusions,&quot; he said, but declined to give details.</p>
<p>Some members of Tung's administration, who were meeting the region's law-making chamber, or provisional legislature, on Tuesday, were expected to ask lawmakers to rush through a bill allowing mainland children to be deported despite a claim to residency.</p>
<p>The bill was also expected to be retroactive to July 1, the day that Hong Kong became a special region under China, the South China Morning Post reported.</p>
<p>Hong Kong has been inundated with young illegal immigrants from the mainland over the past year and there are an estimated 60,000 people in China awaiting clearance to move to Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Also high on the council's agenda was the framework for Hong Kong's first legislative elections, which Tung has promised to hold in the second quarter of 1998.</p>
<p>The region's current law-making body is a controversial China-backed provisional legislature, which was sworn in in the small hours of July 1 to replace the elected colonial chamber.</p>
<p>Just before the handover, that chamber passed a string of laws to give workers more rights and to make it more difficult to jail dissidents.</p>
<p>Tung, widely known to be dissatisfied with the way the laws were passed by the now defunct chamber, said the council had also discussed ways to deal with the new laws.</p>
<p>&quot;Regarding the many laws passed before the handover...they leave a very large impact on Hong Kong in the long term.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We have also come to a conclusion on how to manage these issues,&quot; he told reporters, but gave no further details.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
