<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713132" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan prosecutors seek more Nomura evidence.</title>
<headline>Japan prosecutors seek more Nomura evidence.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prosecutors on Tuesday pored over more than 2,000 boxes of documents seized from Japan's biggest brokerage Nomura Securities Co Ltd to see if the scandal-plagued firm was involved in more dealings with racketeers, media reports said.</p>
<p>Several top Nomura executives are already under arrest on charges of making payoffs to &quot;sokaiya&quot; racketeer Ryuichi Koike to stop him from disrupting annual shareholder meetings.</p>
<p>But Kyodo news service said on Tuesday prosecutors have found possible evidence to prove that Nomura gave 110 million yen ($973,000) to two other racketeers in the early 1990s.</p>
<p>Quoting unnamed sources, Kyodo said the cash was used to make up losses from stock transactions made by Nomura dealers for the accounts of the two racketeers.</p>
<p>Although the payments violate Japan's Commercial Code, the two racketeers could escape prosecution because a three-year statute of limitations has run out, the sources told Kyodo.</p>
<p>Sokaiya extort money from companies by threatening to disclose management misdeeds or disrupt annual shareholders meetings.</p>
<p>Payoffs to the corporate extortionists have been illegal since 1983 but many firms have found it hard to cut ties to the racketeers.</p>
<p>Nomura Securities itself has been indicted for violating the securities transaction law by illegally compensating a firm run by Yoshinori Koike, younger brother of Ryuichi Koike.</p>
<p>The affair is the second to involve Nomura since a 1991 brokerage scandal, when then-chairman Setsuya Tabuchi and president Yoshihisa Tabuchi (no relation) left their posts after revelations that the firm had ties to gangsters and had improperly compensated favoured clients.</p>
<p>Financial sources said that Japan's securities watchdog, the Securities and Exchange Surveillance Commission, could make its recommendations on administrative punishment of Nomura to the Finance Ministry in the next few days.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto said last week that Japan needed stronger penalties for financial institutions which commit illegal acts.</p>
<p>The penalties could include suspension of some of the brokerage's business for up to six months.</p>
<p>Apart from Nomura, the scandal has ensnared one of Japan's biggest banks, Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank Ltd (DKB).</p>
<p>Several former top DKB executives have been arrested on suspicion of extending massive loans to racketeer Ryuichi Koike in exchange for his pledge to ensure smooth proceeding at shareholders' meetings.</p>
<p>Because of the unfolding scandal, both DKB and Nomura have suffered customer defections.</p>
<p>There has been speculation that as prosecutors probe deeper into the Nomura and DKB cases, more top firms could be drawn into the scandal. ($1=113 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
