<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713154" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thanong says to focus on Thai export recovery.</title>
<headline>Thanong says to focus on Thai export recovery.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thai Finance Minister Thanong Bidaya told a seminar on Tuesday he would concentrate on pushing for a recovery in exports to exploit Thailand's de facto devaluation of the baht last week.</p>
<p>Thanong told an economic seminar that Thai business would face a tough time in the next one or two months but he was confident the government would be able to bring inflation under control.</p>
<p>&quot;A weaker baht and high inflation do not necessarily go hand in hand,&quot; he said.  </p>
<p>Thanong said that in the previous baht devaluation in 1984, when the currency was devalued by 14.8 percent, Thailand managed to keep its inflation down to 2.4 percent the following year.</p>
<p>He projected that Thailand's inflation could be restrained to only about six percent year-on-year in the next one to two months, against 4.4 percent in June and 5.9 percent in the whole of 1996.</p>
<p>He said the biggest problem currently facing Thai business was tight liquidity and the government should do its best to try to alleviate this.</p>
<p>&quot;We must focus on pushing for exports after the baht's floatation otherwise the benefits which we should get will be negated. For the time being we need to help business operate.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We should not let liquidity problems hold back productive business,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Thanong said it was fortunate that current inflationary pressure was being offset by relatively low oil prices.</p>
<p>He said the baht's floatation was a turning point for the Thai economy because the earlier baht exchange rate mechanism, which was put in place in 1984 and tied the currency to a dollar-dominated basket of currencies, had become outdated.</p>
<p>He said the previous baht regime had been inflexible while the Thai economy faced contraints including high production costs and wages in recent years.</p>
<p>Thanong said Thailand should reset its priorities after the baht floatation and that he would concentrate on rebuilding both Thai business and foreign confidence in the economy.</p>
<p>He said Thais also would have to save more and work with the government during the current austerity period.</p>
<p>He pledged to pursue fiscal and monetary discipline, restructure taxes and review Thai economic strategy.</p>
<p>He said he expected the pain from baht and interest rate volatility to last only about two months before both stabilise.</p>
<p>Thanong earlier predicted that Thailand's economy would grow by six percent or more in 1998 after slowing down below projected targets this year following the baht floatation.</p>
<p>-- Bangkok newsroom (662) 652-0642</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E131">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
