<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713134" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: FOCUS-Indonesia continues to liberalise its economy.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-Indonesia continues to liberalise its economy.</headline>
<byline>Mantik Kusjanto</byline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indonesia has taken another crucial step in liberalising its trade regime by unveiling a fresh package of economic deregulation measures, economists and analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>In a move to maintain growth momentum and revive sluggish export recovery, Indonesia on Monday cut import tariffs, reduced the cost of doing business and gave incentives for exports.</p>
<p>The measures reduced average tariffs down to 11.9 percent from 13 percent and brought 62.55 percent of the tariff codes to a range of between zero and 10 percent.</p>
<p>Economists said the move made Indonesia one of the most liberal trade regimes in the region. Coordinating Minister for Production and Distribution Hartarto said Indonesia's tariffs were the lowest in the region after Singapore.</p>
<p>Some economists said they were not surprised by the package because the government had been expected to bring Indonesia closer to tariff reduction schedules set by regional and international trade pacts.</p>
<p>But other economists said the package was not enough to stimulate the country's exports because structural impediments were behind the lethargic export performance.</p>
<p>Indonesia's year-on-year export growth slowed to 3.1 percent in April, compared with 18.0 percent in the 1996 period.</p>
<p>Non-oil exports fell to 3.1 percent from 22.0 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think this will help our exports because tariffs here are already so low that further cuts will not help,&quot; Rizal Ramli, economist at the independent Econit advisory group, said. &quot;Our problem is structural,&quot; Ramli told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said labour-intensive export products had suffered a slowdown in the past few months and they could not be rectified with deregulative measures.</p>
<p>&quot;What they need is a restructuring of the labour-intensive industry,&quot; Ramli said, citing the textile industry as an example where spinning machines from the 1970s were still in use.</p>
<p>He said small to medium-sized textile industries, one of the pillars of Indonesian exports, could not be helped with reform packages because of their low productivity.</p>
<p>&quot;If you lower import tariffs, you will get more imports from China and Hong Kong,&quot; Ramli said, adding that there should be measures to help restructure sectors to boost competitiveness.</p>
<p>But Ramli welcomed the move by the central bank to ban commercial banks from allocating new loans to property developers for land procurement and development, except those for the building of low-cost housing.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a good preventive move to avoid troubles faced by Thailand now,&quot; Ramli said.</p>
<p>Thailand's economic woes started with the failure in the property sector and later spread to the finance sector.</p>
<p>The Jakarta Post said in its editorial on Tuesday the package was worth waiting for. It said the content and scope it covered proved the government had not suffered from reform fatigue as some had alleged.</p>
<p>Analysts said the package addressed many of the concerns raised in the latest World Bank report on Indonesia released last month. The bank had said Indonesia needed further deregulation to give another boost to growth and increase labour demand and real wages.</p>
<p>Indonesia forecast an economic growth of 7.1 percent in the 1997/98 (April-March) budget.</p>
<p>It said tariff cuts were highly desirable because they will keep Indonesia's tariffs among the lowest for large developing countries and strengthen competitiveness by compressing costs.</p>
<p>&quot;Overall it is reasonably positive for the economy and the stock market,&quot; Stephen Rogers, research director of UBS Securities in Jakarta, said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
