<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713224" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kennedy babysitter sex scandal probe ends.</title>
<headline>Kennedy babysitter sex scandal probe ends.</headline>
<dateline>DEDHAM, Mass 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The prosecutor probing whether Michael Kennedy, son of the late Sen. Robert Kennedy, had sex with his family's teenage babysitter said on Tuesday charges will not be filed because the alleged victim refused to cooperate.</p>
<p>&quot;I have considered the victim's desires, her emotional well-being and her current state of mind ... I have determined that we will honour the victim's desire and not commence a grand jury investigation at this time,&quot; Norfolk County District Attorney Jeffrey Locke told reporters.</p>
<p>Locke denied he had been pressured by the politically powerful Kennedy family, members of which have been involved in a number of highly publicised scandals in the past. He said the cooperation of the victim and her family would be &quot;a critical component&quot; in any prosecution of Kennedy.</p>
<p>The prosecutor began his probe in April when media reports said Kennedy, 39, head of the nonprofit Citizens Energy Corp., had a five-year affair with the babysitter that started when she was under 16 years of age. Now 19 and a Boston University student, the woman turned 16 at the end of January 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;Our investigation focused on two critical issues: first, whether Michael Kennedy engaged in sexual intercourse with the babysitter of his children at any time before the end January 1994, and second, whether there is sufficient evidence admissible in a court of law in order to sustain such a charge,&quot; Locke said.</p>
<p>His investigators met with the victim, her father and members of the Kennedy family, he said, adding, &quot;Michael Kennedy declined our invitation to be interviewed.&quot;</p>
<p>After reviewing the evidence, Locke said, &quot;It is clear that the cooperation and involvement of the victim and her family in this case would be a critical component of any prosecution. However, without the willing involvement of the victim, there is no basis to proceed further.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;This is because when all is said and done, we have not determined the existence of any independent, compelling and direct evidence demonstrating a sexual relationship prior to the end of January 1994,&quot; Locke said.</p>
<p>Anticipating charges of favouritism, he added, &quot;To those who suggest that we've caved into the pressures of the Kennedy family in not going forward at this time, I respond that I will not sacrifice the emotional well-being of a young woman for private, political or prosecutorial gain.</p>
<p>&quot;I have, however, informed the victim ... that this office stands ready, willing and able to pursue this investigation should she and her family feel prepared to participate in it.&quot;</p>
<p>The state's statute of limitations on statutory rape is 15 years and Locke said that gives the victim another 12 years in which to change her mind.</p>
<p>Michael Kennedy, through his lawyer, released a statement saying, in part, &quot;I apologise for the pain I have caused. I intend to do all I can to make up for the serious mistakes I have made, and to continue to obtain the help I need.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I know that it will be difficult, but I hope that in time the ... family will forgive me. I also hope that my wife and children will forgive me, and that I can someday earn and deserve their confidence again,&quot; Kennedy's statement said.</p>
<p>The scandal surfaced shortly after Kennedy separated from his wife of 16 years, Victoria, daughter of sportscaster Frank Gifford.</p>
<p>In a statement released through her lawyer, Mrs. Kennedy said, &quot;The district attorney's decision to close his investigation will help put an end to a nightmare for me and my children. As I told the district attorney's office, I have no knowledge, and I do not believe that Michael ever committed any criminal wrongdoing.&quot;</p>
<p>The scandal has played havoc with the political aspirations of his older brother, Representative Joseph Kennedy, who is expected to seek the Democratic nomination for Massachusetts governor next year. The congressman's popularity has plummeted. Once the clear front-runner, polls now show him running even with his main Democratic rival, Attorney General Scott Harshbarger.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DEDHAM, Mass"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
