<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713223" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Jury selected in New York in Cosby extortion case.</title>
<headline>Jury selected in New York in Cosby extortion case.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>By Gail Appleson, Law Correspondent</p>
<p>Six men and six women were chosen as jurors on Tuesday in the trial of a woman accused of trying to extort $40 million from actor Bill Cosby by claiming to be his illegitimate daughter and threatening to sell her story to a tabloid newspaper.</p>
<p>Opening statements in the case against Autumn Jackson, 22, were scheduled to begin on Wednesday morning in Manhattan federal court.</p>
<p>A key issue in the trial will be whether Jackson actually believes she is the popular entertainer's daughter and saw her actions as those of a child trying to exercise her rights, rather than an extortion.</p>
<p>Cosby has admitted to having had an affair with Jackson's mother but has denied being her father. According to court papers, Jackson was one of many young people whose educational expenses Cosby paid for several years.</p>
<p>The case is being widely watched because the government plans to call Cosby as a witness and he is expected to be questioned thoroughly about his relationship with both Jackson and her mother.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, U.S. District Judge Barbara Jones ruled Jackson cannot argue during the trial that she has what is known as a legal &quot;claim of right&quot; to Cosby's money.</p>
<p>However defence lawyers said they would pursue their strategy of trying to show Jackson's state of mind and intent.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe we have a story to tell the jury,&quot; Robert Baum, one of Jackson's lawyers, told reporters. &quot;Our defence has not changed.&quot;</p>
<p>Jones was expected to rule early Wednesday on other motions including a request by the defence team that it be allowed to introduce as evidence results of a lie detector test taken by Jackson last weekend.</p>
<p>Baum said in court that Jackson had passed questions on the test that showed she believes Cosby to be her father.</p>
<p>Jackson and her alleged accomplice, Jose Medina, 51, are on trial on charges of trying to obtain money from Cosby by threatening to reveal to The Globe tabloid newpaper Jackson's claim that Cosby is her out-of-wedlock father.</p>
<p>A third defendant, Boris Sabas, 42, also known as Boris Shmulevich, is on trial on charges that he helped Jackson and Medina by driving them to the airport and assisting in travel arrangements as part of the scheme.</p>
<p>The three are accused of conspiracy, extortion and violating a federal law that prohibits people from engaging in interstate commerce to commit certain offences. If convicted on all counts, they face possible prison terms of 12 years and fines of $750,000.</p>
<p>The extortion plot came at a tough time for the Cosby family. The entertainer's only son, Ennis, 27, was shot to death in California on Jan. 16, just two days before Jackson was charged. Authorities have said the incidents are unrelated.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
