<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713217" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Small plane crashes off NY beach.</title>
<headline>Small plane crashes off NY beach.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A single-engine plane crashed in water off New York's popular Jones Beach on Tuesday, killing at least one person on board, authorities said.</p>
<p>Initial information about the 2 p.m. crash that indicated divers found three bodies proved to be inaccurate, Nassau County police officer Adele Burke said.</p>
<p>The plane had emerged from fog and crashed into Jones Beach Inlet, she said. Witnesses said the plane appeared to be struggling to gain altitude but failed and plunged into the water, she said.</p>
<p>Divers recovered the body of one woman, Burke said. They were still searching for other possible victims, she said.</p>
<p>Initial reports of additional victims came from the police marine aviation unit and were inaccurate, she said.</p>
<p>The wreckage was submerged in about 30 feet of water.</p>
<p>The victim was not identified, and there was no immediate information on where the plane was coming from or going, she said. The cause of the crash was under investigation, police said.</p>
<p>Jones Beach State Park is located about 25 miles from midtown Manhattan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
