<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713221" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. court rules against Chase merger opponents.</title>
<headline>U.S. court rules against Chase merger opponents.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>A federal appeals panel has rejected claims by a coalition of community groups seeking to block the merger of Chase Manhattan Corp. and Chemical Banking Corp., 15 months after the merger was completed.</p>
<p>In an opinion dated July 2, a three-judge panel of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit rejected the arguments of Inner City Press/Community on the Move and other groups, saying the groups had no legal standing to challenge regulators' approval of the merger, which created the largest banking company in the United States.</p>
<p>The opinion was written by Judge Ellsworth Van Graafeiland, who was joined by Judges Pierre Laval and Dominic Squatrito.</p>
<p>The panel also said the groups' claims that the banks' lending in low-income neighbourhoods was insufficient were meritless.</p>
<p>The lawsuit, brought against the board of the Federal Reserve and the Office of Thrift Supervision, cited the Community Reinvestment Act and the Bank Holding Company Act in challenging approval of the merger.</p>
<p>The court noted that the Fed's order approving the Chase-Chemical merger was 72 pages in length, including 45 pages of &quot;exhaustive analysis&quot; of Chase and Chemical's actions to comply with the Community Reinvestment Act.</p>
<p>Matthew Lee, executive director of Inner City Press/Community on the Move said Tuesday that the group planned to take the case to the Supreme Court.</p>
<p>&quot;We disagree with the decision,&quot; Lee said. &quot;We intend to appeal the decision and in the interim learn a lesson from it. If what is required is individual allegations of discrimination, that's the road we will take.&quot;</p>
<p>Chase Manhattan stock ended unchanged at $103 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81402">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C18">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C181">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
