<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713220" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. Army helicopter crashes, eight killed.</title>
<headline>U.S. Army helicopter crashes, eight killed.</headline>
<dateline>FORT BRAGG, N.C. 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Army helicopter crashed on Tuesday at Fort Bragg, killing eight soldiers, Army officials said.</p>
<p>The chopper went down in a wooded area near the southwest corner of the sprawling base about 20 miles (32 km) west-southwest of Fayetteville.</p>
<p>The victims were members of the elite 82nd Airborne Division, one of the U.S. military's top contingency groups called into battle at a moment's notice.</p>
<p>&quot;An Army UH-60 Blackhawk helicopter crashed ... on Fort Bragg about 2:15 p.m. today, killing eight soldiers of the 82nd Airborne Division,&quot; the Army said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;The names of the soldiers will be released after next of kin have been notified,&quot; the statement added. There was no immediate indication of what might have caused the crash.</p>
<p>The crash scene was cordoned off and military police directed traffic as work crews hauled floodlights and electrical generators into place.</p>
<p>The area of Fort Bragg where the chopper went down is open to the public and its roads are used by commuters, who were routed around the crash scene.</p>
<p>A heavy rainstorm swept through in late afternoon, muddying the site as investigators got to work. Fort Bragg's commander, Lt. Gen. Jack Keane, arrived to direct the recovery operation.</p>
<p>Corp. Carol Diggs, a public affairs officer for the 18th Airborne Corps, said an explosion and fire occurred as the helicopter crashed. Witnesses reported heavy smoke at the scene.</p>
<p>In March 1994, an Air Force F-16D jet fighter and a C-130 Hercules transport carrier were involved in an airborne collision at Pope Air Force Base, adjacent to Fort Bragg.</p>
<p>That crash killed 24 soldiers and injured at least 100 other military personnel.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FORT BRAGG, N.C."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
