<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713237" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Geraldine Ferraro weighing U.S. Senate run.</title>
<headline>Geraldine Ferraro weighing U.S. Senate run.</headline>
<byline>Ellen Wulfhorst</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former vice presidential candidate Geraldine Ferraro said Tuesday she was giving serious consideration to challenging Republican Sen. Alfonse D'Amato for his job.</p>
<p>Ferraro, 61, said in an interview that she wants to finish writing a book and then consult with various political and labour leaders before making a decision by December.</p>
<p>The former Democratic congresswoman from the New York borough of Queens rose to national political prominence as the first woman to run for vice president on a major party ticket. She was presidential hopeful Walter Mondale's running mate in 1984.</p>
<p>She lost a bid for the Democratic nomination to run against D'Amato in 1992. Most recently, she has been a political commentator on CNN's political show &quot;Crossfire.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked why she would return to public life, Ferraro cited an inscription on a coffee mug she recently was given.</p>
<p>&quot;It has a picture of the Capitol, and it says 'Democracy is not a spectator sport,' and it really isn't,&quot; she said. &quot;I'm good at legislating, at getting things done. If I were to do anything, that would be it.&quot;</p>
<p>Ferraro has been weighing a challenge to D'Amato for several months. In February she sent letters to potential supporters asking them to delay making a decision on whom to endorse to run against him.</p>
<p>The question of her candidacy was raised again publicly in an interview published Tuesday in the New York Times, in which she was quoted as saying, &quot;If it were today, I'd probably say, 'Yeah, I'm going to go.'&quot;</p>
<p>Ferraro said she thought D'Amato, after an 18-year stint in the Senate, was beatable, given his votes on such issues as the environment, education and the budget.</p>
<p>A public opinion poll in March showed Ferraro leading D'Amato 47 percent to 43 percent.</p>
<p>D'Amato last year was active in pursuing the Whitewater investigation against the Clintons and was a heavy supporter of former Sen. Bob Dole's unsuccessful Republican presidential campaign.</p>
<p>Two New York Democrats have already declared their interest in the Senate race -- Representative Charles Schumer of Brooklyn and New York City's Public Advocate Mark Green.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
