<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713360" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Former Kiss guitarist sues rock group for royalties.</title>
<headline>Former Kiss guitarist sues rock group for royalties.</headline>
<byline>Pat Harris</byline>
<dateline>NASHVILLE, Tenn. 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former guitarist Vinnie Vincent of Kiss has sued the rock group, claiming he was cheated out of millions of dollars in royalties earned on such hit albums &quot;Lick It Up&quot; and &quot;Creatures of the Night.&quot;</p>
<p>Named in the lawsuit filed on Monday in U.S. District Court in Los Angeles was Kiss' label, Polygram, which is owned by the Dutch company Philips Electronics NV.</p>
<p>&quot;They have cheated me, they have cheated my family,&quot; Vincent told Reuters after holding a news conference announcing the lawsuit in his hometown of Nashville.</p>
<p>Vincent, 44, replaced Kiss founding member Ace Frehley on lead guitar during the early 1980s when the group briefly dropped its trademark face makeup, but left in 1984 when he refused to sign an employment contract that he said would have relinquished his songwriting credits.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the equivalent of a tobacco industry scandal,&quot; Vincent said. &quot;The recording companies do an amazing cover-up job, perpetuating their fraud on unsuspecting artists who want to see their music recorded and have no power against the big money interests.&quot;</p>
<p>Vincent is among several recording artists who have tried to recover royalties from songs they had written by filing suit, many of which are settled out of court.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a case where I'm standing up not only for myself but trying to give others the courage to do the same thing,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>After Vincent quit, the group had several interim guitarists before Frehley rejoined the rejuvenated band for recent sold-out tours.</p>
<p>Vincent went on to release two solo albums on the Chrysallis label and formed his own Metaluna label.</p>
<p>A lawyer for Polygram reached in New York had not seen the lawsuit and declined to comment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34520">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NASHVILLE, Tenn."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
