<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713319" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Health critique of tobacco deal going to White House.</title>
<headline>Health critique of tobacco deal going to White House.</headline>
<byline>Joanne Kenen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A critique of the proposed $368 billion tobacco deal by leading public health advocates will be delivered to a White House task force on Wednesday, officials said Tuesday.</p>
<p>The report was drafted by a team of prominent public health experts and anti-smoking activists led by former U.S. Surgeon General C. Everett Koop and former Food and Drug Administration Commissioner David Kessler.</p>
<p>The Koop-Kessler criticisms are likely to carry weight in the White House, which is conducting a 30-day review of the proposed settlement, and in Congress, which would have to approve legislation to enact a deal.</p>
<p>Like the public health groups, President Bill Clinton has voiced concern that the proposed settlement would water down the FDA's authority to regulate tobacco and nicotine. The president has neither endorsed nor rejected the overall settlement until the task force study is complete.</p>
<p>Under the agreement reached last month between the industry and 40 states suing it, tobacco companies would pay out $368 billion over 25 years. Some of that money would fund public health anti-smoking initiatives.</p>
<p>Koop, who is recovering from knee surgery, and Kessler are scheduled to deliver the report to Vice President Al Gore, Health and Human Services Secretary Donna Shalala and White House domestic policy adviser Bruce Reed, according to a spokesman for the public health groups and task force participants.</p>
<p>Shalala and Reed are heading the White House task force, aiming to review the complex deal within 30 days.</p>
<p>The Koop-Kessler panel found at least seven major objections to the proposed deal. The most significant criticisms were that the proposal restricted FDA authority and that the penalties cigarette makers would pay if they failed to meet targets for reducing teen smoking are too small.</p>
<p>Many of the health panel members were also concerned that the deal would cap tobacco makers' liability at $4 billion a year and would restrict the ability of plaintiffs to bring class-action lawsuits.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
