<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713371" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kuralt remembered as 'national treasure'.</title>
<headline>Kuralt remembered as 'national treasure'.</headline>
<byline>Knight Chamberlain</byline>
<dateline>CHAPEL HILL, N.C. 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Charles Kuralt, the journalist whose knack for finding and celebrating the mundane endeared him to millions, was remembered Tuesday as a &quot;national treasure&quot; and an &quot;authentic American hero.&quot;</p>
<p>Kuralt, who died July 4 from complications associated with lupus, was best known for his &quot;On The Road&quot; television series and as host of &quot;Sunday Morning,&quot; both CBS productions. He was 62.</p>
<p>Though he travelled the world, Kuralt never forgot his North Carolina roots. His last request was to be buried in the town where he felt most at home, among the renowned alumni and professors of his alma mater, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, university officials said.</p>
<p>His voice shaking with emotion, Charlie Rose, host of public television's &quot;Charlie Rose Show,&quot; bade his longtime friend goodbye, calling him a &quot;national treasure who was too young and too good to leave us.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Can't we hear just one more story?&quot; Rose asked of Kuralt, described by Time magazine as America's poet laureat of the common man. &quot;Just one more gentle reminder of who we are?&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;He believed in us and he knew us,&quot; Rose said. &quot;He knew we are more good than bad, and he used words to help reveal our souls.&quot;</p>
<p>William Friday, former chancellor of the University of North Carolina system, described the Wilmington N.C. native as &quot;an authentic American hero.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Charles was a great teacher,&quot; Friday told an audience of about 2,000 packed into an auditorium on the UNC campus. &quot;America was his subject and the small towns were his classroom. He is now back home and will never be forgotten.&quot;</p>
<p>Former CBS news anchor Walter Cronkite was scheduled to speak, but was fogbound at his home at Martha's Vineyard. CBS anchor Dan Rather attended the service but did not speak.</p>
<p>More than just a storyteller, Kuralt was &quot;the voice of avuncular reassurance,&quot; University Chancellor Michael Hooker said.</p>
<p>&quot;He tempted us with slices of humanity and was a personification of the stories he told,&quot; Hooker said.</p>
<p>North Carolina Gov. Jim Hunt said Kuralt's relaxed manner and folksy style allowed him to gain a unique perspective about those whose stories he told.</p>
<p>&quot;He was telling America's story and share America's secret -- its good, caring people -- and that they all had something positive to offer,&quot; Hunt said. &quot;Charles found it all and revelled in it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I9741102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHAPEL HILL, N.C."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
