<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713375" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Glickman says exports key to U.S. farm income.</title>
<headline>Glickman says exports key to U.S. farm income.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said Tuesday that the Clinton administration will continue to push aggressively to keep markets around the world open to U.S. farm products.</p>
<p>In a speech to agriculture industry lobbyists, Glickman said U.S. farm income is linked more than ever to agricultural exports because of recent changes in U.S. farm programs.</p>
<p>In that regard, U.S. farmers won an important victory last month when the House upheld President Clinton's decision to maintain normal trade relations with China, he said.</p>
<p>However, important negotiations with China still lie ahead regarding its bid to join the World Trade Organization (WTO).</p>
<p>&quot;We need to make sure they come in playing by the same rules as everybody else in the club,&quot; Glickman said.</p>
<p>The United States will insist that China make important market access and other agricultural trade concessions before it enters the WTO, he said.</p>
<p>The Clinton administration is also committed to securing fast-track negotiating authority from Congress so it can expand the North American Free Trade Agreement to Chile and other countries in Latin America, Glickman said.</p>
<p>Otherwise, the United States risks losing out to the European Union and other competitors vying to increase their share of the growing Latin American market, he said.</p>
<p>Because changes in U.S. farm program have made producers more vunerable to market price swings, &quot;our big challenge is to keep exports up,&quot; Glickman said.</p>
<p>Without the stabilizing influence of strong exports, &quot;the peaks and valleys of commodity prices will put a lot of smaller and medium-size (producers) in great jeopardy,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>((-- Doug Palmer, Washington newsroom, 202-898-8341))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
