<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713318" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Airlines, jet makers discuss TWA crash findings.</title>
<headline>Airlines, jet makers discuss TWA crash findings.</headline>
<byline>Martin Wolk</byline>
<dateline>SEATTLE 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Representatives of about 40 airlines met Tuesday with executives of Boeing Co. and other manufacturers to discuss ways to prevent fuel tank explosions like the catastrophic blast aboard doomed TWA Flight 800.</p>
<p>Boeing and airline industry officials said the closed meeting was a routine gathering of safety executives aimed at reaching a consensus that will be presented this month to the Federal Aviation Administration.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a great opportunity for everybody to hear everybody eles's thoughts and come to a common agreement,&quot; said Boeing spokesman Doug Webb.</p>
<p>But the meeting took on added interest with the FAA and National Transportation Safety Board divided over how to approach the fuel-tank safety issue raised by the still-unsolved crash that killed 230 people last summer.</p>
<p>In December, the NTSB recommended jet manufacturers and operators be ordered to take steps to reduce the danger of fuel tank explosions, possibly including the development of &quot;inerting&quot; systems like those used on military jets, which pump nitrogen into fuel tanks to prevent the buildup of flammable vapours.</p>
<p>The FAA so far has declined to act on the safety board's recommendation, saying more tests are needed to determine what caused the explosion in Flight 800's nearly empty centre fuel tank.</p>
<p>Some of those tests will be carried out this week, when NTSB pilots in a Boeing 747 similar to the one that crashed on July 17, 1996, retrace the flight path of the doomed jet from New York's John F. Kennedy Airport to a spot 13,800 feet (4,100 metres) above the Atlantic Ocean near the Long Island town of East Moriches, N.Y.</p>
<p>NTSB engineers will be measuring temperatures in and around the centre fuel tank and gathering fuel vapour samples, according to a board official who spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
<p>Early next month, the board will conduct another test in England, detonating a small explosive on a fuel tank from a 747 to see what might have happened if a saboteur gained access to the tank while it was on the ground.</p>
<p>While the NTSB is recommending changes to minimise the flammability of the fuel-air mixture in jet fuel tanks, the FAA appears to be leaning toward the industry's traditional approach of eliminating sources of ignition.</p>
<p>The ignition source on Flight 800 remains one of the enduring mysteries of the exhaustive crash probe, although investigators say the evidence increasingly points to mechanical failure rather than a bomb or missile as originally believed.</p>
<p>In a letter to NTSB Chairman Jim Hall, FAA Administrator Barry Valentine cautioned against taking measures that &quot;may in fact decrease safety.&quot;</p>
<p>Boeing's Webb noted that the NTSB recommendations, while aimed at the Boeing 747, could affect virtually the entire world commercial fleet and even private airplanes.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not only a question of money, its a question of the complexity of airplanes,&quot; he said. &quot;That's why we've said all along this is an industrywide issue.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I36400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3640010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEATTLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
