<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713392" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Strikes to lower Big Three second-quarter profits.</title>
<headline>Strikes to lower Big Three second-quarter profits.</headline>
<byline>Todd Nissen</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Battered by labour strikes, higher incentives and slowing sales, combined net profits for the Big Three automakers are expected to fall an estimated 11 percent from a year ago, analysts said.</p>
<p>Strikes alone will slice nearly $1 billion from the net earnings of General Motors Corp. and Chrysler Corp.</p>
<p>The Big Three as a group are expected to report combined earnings of about $4.5 billion for the April-June period, according to analysts. A year ago, they reported earnings of $5.04 billion.</p>
<p>Ford Motor Co. is forecast to post the best returns for the quarter, which would allow it to out-earn archrival GM for the first time in more than 9 years.</p>
<p>Most analysts said they expect Ford to earn between $2.2 billion and $2.3 billion. However, Merrill Lynch &amp; Co. analyst Nicholas Lobaccaro has estimated the company will earn $2.5 billion.</p>
<p>The First Call Corp., which monitors Wall Street earnings projections, said its consensus estimate for Ford's 1997 second period is $1.82 a share. A year ago, Ford earned $1.90 billion, or $1.56 a share.</p>
<p>The U.S. No. 2 automaker, which will report results July 16, the same day as GM, is on a cost-cutting roll and enjoying some of the best labour relations in the industry.</p>
<p>Ford has also benefited from the hugely profitable Expedition. The full-size sport/utility vehicle carries gross profits of $11,000 for each unit.</p>
<p>Chrysler will be the first to report when it releases results on Friday. It is expected to post net earnings of $512 million, about half of the $1.04 billion it earned in the 1996 second quarter, according to David Healy, an analyst with Burnham Securities Inc.</p>
<p>Healy estimates the No. 3 automaker will earn $512 million, or 75 cents a share, down from $1.38 a year ago, but slightly higher than the 68 cents per share analysts' consensus compiled by First Call.</p>
<p>A 30-day strike by United Auto Workers union members at a Detroit-area engine plant this spring forced Chrysler to shut down much of its light-truck output. Chrysler lost out on production of 94,000 vehicles, worth $450 million, or 65 cents a share in lost profits.</p>
<p>But Healy said even without the strike, Chrysler would probably not have matched last year's returns. One reason is bigger sales incentives. Healy estimates they climbed to an average of $1,000 as Chrysler sought to spur minivan and car sales. Last year, Chrysler said its average second period U.S. retail incentive was $625.</p>
<p>&quot;Probably the higher incentives and maybe a little less favourable mix than last year would have brought them below second-quarter earnings without the strikes,&quot; said Healy.</p>
<p>GM has said two strikes will reduce its second-quarter profits by $490 million or 67 cents a share.</p>
<p>Healy predicts that will bring GM's second-quarter earnings to $1.64 billion. On a per-share basis, the estimate works out to $2.16, slightly above the First Call consensus of $2.15.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C152">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
