<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713495" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Geraldine Ferraro likely to run for Senate-paper.</title>
<headline>Geraldine Ferraro likely to run for Senate-paper.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former vice presidential candidate Geraldine Ferraro has given the strongest indication yet that she will seek the Democratic nomination to run against Republican Sen. Alfonse D'Amato next year, the New York Times reported Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;If it were today, I'd probably say, 'Yeah, I'm going to go,'&quot; the newspaper quoted Ferraro as saying in an interview. It said Ferraro, 61, would make a decision by December.</p>
<p>The former congresswoman from Queens, New York, has been a political commentator on the Cable News Network programme &quot;Crossfire,&quot; a position she would have to give up if she decided to fight for the nomination. She has been hinting for months that she would run for public office again.</p>
<p>Ferraro, who rose to national political prominence when she was presidential hopeful Walter Mondale's running mate in 1984, lost a bid for the Democratic nomination to run against D'Amato in 1992.</p>
<p>Two of the most experienced Democratic politicians in New York have already declared their interest in the race -- Representative Charles Schumer of Brooklyn and New York City's Public Advocate Mark Green.</p>
<p>Of long-time senator D'Amato, Ferraro said: &quot;I think he's eminently beatable,&quot; the Times reported. In February, Ferraro sent letters to possible supporters asking them to delay their decision on whom to endorse to run against D'Amato.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
