<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713589" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Gibraltar casts pall over Spain's NATO show.</title>
<headline>Gibraltar casts pall over Spain's NATO show.</headline>
<byline>Marjorie Olster</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A resurgent dispute with Britain over Gibraltar cast a shadow over Spain's pledge to fully integrate into NATO at a summit in Madrid on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Britain threatened to veto Spain's integration into the alliance's military command structure unless it lifted air and sea restrictions on the colony. But Spain reacted defiantly.</p>
<p>&quot;Spain will maintain air and maritime restrictions on Gibraltar,&quot; Spanish Foreign Minister Abel Matutes declared at a news conference at the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;Spain is not going to lift any restriction which could affect its legitimate demands of sovereignty over Gibraltar.&quot;</p>
<p>Spain claims sovereignty over the colony passed to Spanish hands in 1462 and seized by Britain in 1704. The rocky peninsula at the southern tip of Spain dominates the western entrance to the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>Gibraltar was ceded by Spain in perpetuity under the 1713 Treaty of Utrecht and became a British colony. Spain has claimed it ever since, and in particular the isthmus linking the rock to the mainland where the airstrip is located.</p>
<p>In principle there is an agreement between the two countries for joint use of the airstrip but Gibraltar refused to sign it and the issue is a constant irritant in Spain's relations with Britain.</p>
<p>Senior Spanish officials say privately that access to sea lanes might be negotiable but airspace is not.</p>
<p>British Foreign Secretary Robin Cook said at the summit that his government would veto Spain's integration into the NATO military command unless there was a deal on Gibraltar.</p>
<p>&quot;Our case is that if Spain wishes to come fully into the alliance and into the integrated command structure, then it must behave as an ally when we want our military aircraft to go in and out of Gibraltar,&quot; Cook told BBC radio.</p>
<p>&quot;Spain, at the moment, makes that very difficult because it does not provide the proper air space for our military planes, or indeed our civilian planes, to take off there,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Matutes said the summit was not the appropriate forum to discuss the conflict over Gibraltar.</p>
<p>In negotiations with NATO on integration into the military command, Spain has demanded a sub-regional command over all Spanish territory and control of access to the Mediterranean through the Straits of Gibraltar.</p>
<p>Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar opened the summit on Tuesday morning by pledging to join NATO's military command in the near future, a signal that his country was setting aside historical ambivalence toward the Western defence alliance.</p>
<p>&quot;As you know, Spain decided to take the necessary steps for participating fully in the alliance's new command structure, in accordance with the decision taken by the Spanish parliament,&quot; Aznar told leaders of the 15 other NATO members.</p>
<p>&quot;We have started to do this and will continue to do so. We view the progress made with satisfaction and I trust that everything will be completed as soon as possible,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Aznar said on Monday there were still problems that needed to be ironed out in the Spain-NATO negotiations but he expected to resolve them by the end of the year.</p>
<p>Spain joined NATO in 1982 but a strong pacifist tradition made it difficult to fully embrace the organisation so it stayed out of the military command structure.</p>
<p>Spain also sympathised with French complaints the alliance was American-dominated and Europeans should have a bigger say.</p>
<p>In November, Spain parted ways with France, which continues to resist military integration. Parliament voted to participate in the military command but stipulated the country must remain free of nuclear weapons.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GIB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
