<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713583" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: FOCUS-EU says CAP reform needed before enlargement.</title>
<headline>FOCUS-EU says CAP reform needed before enlargement.</headline>
<byline>Janet McEvoy</byline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Commission will recommend next week that the European Union reforms its costly Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) before enlarging the bloc into eastern Europe, according to a document obtained by Reuters.</p>
<p>The document says reforms would improve the competitiveness of EU agriculture, allow it to participate in the expansion of world markets and prepare it for the next world trade liberalising round and for the EU's eastward enlargement.</p>
<p>&quot;It is now time to formulate concrete proposals to reshape the common agricultural policy and prepare it for the next century,&quot; according to the document, part of a so-called &quot;agenda 2000&quot; package assessing how the EU's expansion plans will affect a series of EU policies.</p>
<p>The thrust of the EU policy will be to shift the emphasis of EU support from price support to direct payments to help farmers, according to the document, which has still to be agreed and could still be changed by the 20-member EU executive in Strasbourg next Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;The EU, with its continuing high price support in some sectors runs a risk of becoming more and more isolated among the main agricultural exporters,&quot; the document says, pointing also to international pressure to set environmental and social standards and to meet consumer concerns.</p>
<p>The Commission predicts that unless there are reforms, the market balance in the beef and cereals sector will deteriorate.</p>
<p>The Commission says that if the EU took in all the 10 eastern European countries which have applied for membership the bloc would have an extra million consumers, with an average purchasing power roughly only one third that of the current EU consumer.</p>
<p>Agricultural land would expand by one half and the agricultural labour force double.</p>
<p>As things stand, a draft prepared by the EU's External Relations Commissioner Hans van den Broek for discussion by the executive at the same time as the farm reform package proposes opening entry talks with five eastern countries -- Poland, the Czech Republic, Hungary, Slovenia and Estonia.</p>
<p>Slovakia, Latvia, Lithuania, Bulgaria and Romania have also applied, but are expected to join later.</p>
<p>The Commission estimates that if the EU system were applied as it is by the joining countries, there would be income disparities and social distortions and surpluses would increase for sugar, milk and meat worsening the growing imbalances predicted after 2000 for the existing EU.</p>
<p>Among the measures expected to be proposed are fixing the cereals intervention price at a safety net level of 95.35 Ecus per tonne (from 119.19 Ecus) from the year 2000.</p>
<p>A non-crop-specific area payment would be set at 68 Ecus per tonne and the reference rate for compulsory set-aside would be fixed at zero percent.</p>
<p>According to the document, silage cereals -- mainly silage maize -- would be excluded from the regime. For protein crops extra aid would be set at 13 Ecus per tonne to preserve their competitiveness with cereals, and current supplements would be kept for durum wheat.</p>
<p>The document also sees a drop in price support, but an increase in income payments for beef and dairy products under enlargement. It foresees new yearly payments of 145 Ecus for dairy cows and the dairy quota regime extended at current levels until the year 2005.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
