<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713575" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: France's Le Pen to stand trial for campaign brawl.</title>
<headline>France's Le Pen to stand trial for campaign brawl.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>(By Christian Curtenelle</p>
<p>Jean-Marie Le Pen, leader of France's far-right National Front, will stand trial in November for an alleged election-campaign assault on a female Socialist parliamentary candidate, justice sources said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>They said Le Pen would be tried before a criminal court in Versailles southwest of Paris on charges of violence at a public gathering and public insult.</p>
<p>Le Pen was fined by a Paris court just last Friday for calling the Senegalese-born French director of an anti-racism organisation a &quot;mad fat zebu&quot;. A zebu is a hump-backed domestic ox found in Africa, India and China.</p>
<p>Two days before the June 1 National Assembly election in which his daughter was a candidate, the burly 68-year-old Le Pen was involved in an election campaign brawl in a Paris suburb.</p>
<p>He could clearly be seen in videotapes of the incident tussling with Socialist candidate Annette Peulvast, who opposed Le Pen's daughter Marie Caroline Le Pen in the election.</p>
<p>Le Pen's daughter ultimately lost her bid for the National Assembly seat while Peulvast won.</p>
<p>Le Pen has denied any wrongdoing in the disturbance and said he had no reason to apologise for his conduct.</p>
<p>In a statement issued on Tuesday, Le Pen said he was annoyed to find out about the trial from news reports and said the courts should move more quickly on corruption matters which he considered more important.</p>
<p>&quot;We can see that the speed in this banal matter...contrasts with the slowness which attends the questions surrounding many politicians of the Communist Party, the (Gaullist) RPR as well as the Socialist party and the (centrist) UDF, who were implicated in much more serious corruption affairs,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>According to a local government spokesman, Le Pen had been confronted by protesters while campaigning for his daughter.</p>
<p>He &quot;caught the first person at hand who was being pushed by the crowd -- Mrs Peulvast. He seized her by her blouse and threw her to the ground,&quot; the spokesman said at the time.</p>
<p>Le Pen promptly branded the spokesman's comment &quot;slanderous&quot; and said he would sue him as well, though he acknowledged having &quot;slightly pushed&quot; individuals who he said tried to prevent him from &quot;walking freely&quot;.</p>
<p>In the &quot;zebu&quot; case, a Paris court fined Le Pen 5,000 francs ($850) after concluding that he had violated French laws barring racial slurs with the remark aimed at Fode Sylla, a Frenchman of Senegalese origin.</p>
<p>The xenophobic National Front wants to ship home millions of immigrants and reserve jobs and state benefits for native-born French. It won 14.94 percent in the first round of the National Assembly election, its highest score in a legislative vote.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVOTE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
