<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713573" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO invites old communist foes to join alliance.</title>
<headline>NATO invites old communist foes to join alliance.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Clayton</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO leaders, in an historic move to erase Europe's Cold War division, invited Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic to join the alliance on Tuesday and held out real membership prospects to other former communist states.</p>
<p>A NATO summit climaxed a day of wrangling by reassuring Slovenia, Romania and the Baltic states that they would be considered seriously in future expansions and pledged that all the new democracies had the right to join the defence body.</p>
<p>&quot;Today the heads of state and government have agreed to invite the Czech Republic, Hungary and Poland to begin accession talks with NATO,&quot; Secretary-General Javier Solana told assembled leaders and world media.</p>
<p>NATO's 16 leaders endorsed the biggest expansion in the alliance's 48-year history after France, which led a bloc of seven states urging a wider enlargement, won assurances the door would be left open and the situation reviewed in two years.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac, who twice insisted on changes to the final communique, was warmly applauded by Romanian journalists when he arrived for a post-summit press conference.</p>
<p>&quot;That's the least I can expect,&quot; he beamed, adding that he was satisfied with the final outcome.</p>
<p>&quot;There were some difficulties but finally we got a clear perspective set out in a single paragraph which sets the date 1999 and specifically names just two countries, Romania and Slovenia,&quot; the French president said.</p>
<p>Solana said the allies' goal was to admit formally the new members in April 1999 on the occasion of the alliance's 50th anniversary and mentioned Slovenia and Romania as prime candidates for the next round of expansion.</p>
<p>Braving Moscow's wrath, the official declaration also gave favourable mention to the Baltic states as &quot;aspiring members&quot; without specifically naming the former Soviet republics of Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia.</p>
<p>&quot;We recognize the progress achieved towards greater stability and cooperation by the states in the Baltic region who are also aspiring members,&quot; the declaration said.</p>
<p>Solana stressed that NATO remained &quot;open to new members&quot; and expected to extend further invitations in coming years as NATO seought to cement a post-Cold War European security order to keep the continent at peace in the 21st century.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton told reporters the invitation marked a &quot;giant stride&quot; towards a new Europe that was undivided, democratic and at peace.</p>
<p>During one of the most contentious NATO summits for years, France and Italy argued strongly the inclusion of Romania and Slovenia would inject stability into some of Europe's most turbulent zones, the Balkans and the edge of the Black Sea.</p>
<p>But Clinton, keenly aware he has to have expansion ratified by a sceptical Republican-led U.S. Congress, said only the three leading candidates were currently ready to meet all the responsibilities of membership.</p>
<p>&quot;They have met the highest standards of democratic and market reform. They have pursued those reforms long enough to give us confidence they are irreversible, just as our offer of NATO membership is irreversible,&quot; Clinton told fellow leaders.</p>
<p>The U.S. administration is bracing itself for tough questions over how much expansion -- the centrepiece of Clinton's foreign policy -- will cost and about the wisdom of extending America's nuclear defence shield to cover three more European states.</p>
<p>Article V of NATO's 1949 founding Washington treaty commits each country to treat an attack on one of them as an attack on all of them, effectively placing the Europeans under U.S. protection -- a long-dreamt goal of Moscow's former satellites.</p>
<p>While key aides frantically worked on the &quot;open door&quot; language, Clinton and Chirac engaged in animated, finger-wagging exchanges while other heads of state and government milled aimlessly around the conference centre.</p>
<p>Clinton was backed by British Prime Minister Tony Blair and four other leaders, concerned too rapid an expansion could make the most powerful military alliance ever assembled unwieldly and ineffective.</p>
<p>German aides said Chancellor Helmut Kohl, a strong ally of both countries, was instrumental in bridging the gap between the opposing camps and helping to find the compromise wording.</p>
<p>Russia has warned that it would consider NATO membership by the Baltic republics, which have substantial Russian minorities, as a threat to its own security.</p>
<p>It condemned Tuesday's enlargement announcement by its former Cold War foe as &quot;the biggest mistake in Europe since the end of World War Two&quot;.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov said Moscow had not changed its position despite signing a new cooperation accord with NATO last May by which it grudgingly accepted it was powerless to stop the process.</p>
<p>&quot;Regarding the question of NATO expansion, I can only say that we confirm our stand,&quot; Primakov told reporters in Moscow.</p>
<p>But Polish President Aleksander Kwasniewski was delighted. &quot;After this decision, Europe will be more secure and it's a good decision for Poland,&quot; he told Reuters, after waiting all afternoon in a hotel across town for the phone call from Solana.</p>
<p>NATO's enlargement decision is likely to increase pressure on the European Union to speed up its own eastwards expansion as a way of softening the blow to unsuccessful alliance applicants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BALTST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
