<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713535" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: More U.S. kids being drugged for behavior problems.</title>
<headline>More U.S. kids being drugged for behavior problems.</headline>
<byline>Kevin Drawbaugh</byline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Eric's mind was wandering and his grades were down, but rather than changing 8-year-old Eric's world everyone suggested changing Eric -- with a drug.</p>
<p>Ritalin was prescribed for the Indianapolis boy based on a teacher's recommendation, four hours of tests, 20 minutes with a psychologist and a diagnosis of attention deficit-hyperactive disorder (ADHD). With few questions, Eric's parents gave their son the drug -- given annually to millions of children in the United States -- and waited.</p>
<p>&quot;I had high hopes for Ritalin, I really did ... This was supposed to be the magic stuff,&quot; said Eric's mother, who asked that their real names not be used. After three weeks, Eric was miserable and showed no improvement, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;He told me when he was on the medicine he didn't feel like a whole person, that he felt weird,&quot; said his mother, who took him off the drug, reordered her family's priorities and started a home-schooling program.</p>
<p>&quot;He's my kid again ... It's going great. His attention span is unbelievable. It's just a matter of someone giving him a few minutes,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Stories like Eric's are becoming more common as busy parents, overcrowded schools and cost-conscious healthcare providers look increasingly to drugs for quick, cheap help in coping with an age group becoming known as Generation Rx.</p>
<p>Ritalin, a stimulant known as &quot;the shutup-and-sit-down drug,&quot; was prescribed to three million U.S. children and teen-agers last year, up from 2.1 million in 1993, according to IMS America Ltd., a market research firm in Pennsylvania. Nearly 700,000 U.S. children and adolescents between six and 18 years old got prescriptions last year for Prozac, Zoloft or Paxil -- the three top-selling antidepressants. That was up from just over 300,000 prescriptions in 1993, IMS reported.</p>
<p>No studies have determined the long-term health effects of these drugs on childrens' growing brains and bodies and most of the antidepressants are being prescribed without official pediatric approval from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.</p>
<p>&quot;It's an incredible commentary on our society that instead of addressing the basic needs of our kids we drug them,&quot; Dr. Peter Breggin, director of the Center for the Study of Psychiatry in Bethesda, Maryland, said. &quot;Instead of addressing their needs for better family life, better education, more spiritual direction, safer environments, better television and videos -- instead of addressing all of that, we're simply drugging them,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Mood-altering drugs, used by millions of U.S. adults, are seen by some in medicine as a major boon to child psychiatry.</p>
<p>&quot;Drugs like ... Prozac are extremely helpful in treating depression and related disorders in children,&quot; said Dr. Peter Stokes, professor of psychiatry and medicine at Cornell Medical College in New York and author of a soon-to-be-published review of research in the field.</p>
<p>Even advocates, however, expressed concern about overuse of the drugs in children. &quot;There's a real sense that these kids have lots of problems and need much more than just the medicine,&quot; said Dr. Graham Emslie, professor of psychiatry at the University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center in Dallas.</p>
<p>Emslie headed a landmark study being published this month that was the first to show that Prozac works better than placebos in treating childhood depression. Backed by such studies, the world drug industry is marching cautiously into the juvenile mental health market, seen by Wall Street analysts as a growth area for products that are saturating the adult population.</p>
<p>&quot;The market potential is huge ... Kids get depressed about pimples, grades, who knows what,&quot; said independent drug industry analyst Hemant Shah in New Jersey.</p>
<p>The FDA is evaluating mountains of data submitted last year by drug firms answering the agency's appeal for better information on pediatric use of the drugs. Several drugmakers are awaiting or about to seek FDA clearance to sell antidepressants as federally approved treatments for children.</p>
<p>The medical diagnoses are diverse -- oppositional-defiant disorder, clinical depression, separation anxiety, conduct disorder and obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD). Precise symptoms for some of these problems, especially the newer ones, vary, but estimates of sufferers run to the millions.</p>
<p>Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn Inc. and marketing partner Solvay Pharmaceuticals Inc. of Belgium won FDA approval in March to sell Luvox as a treatment for OCD in children.</p>
<p>Pfizer Inc. has submitted an FDA application for Zoloft, a drug similar to Prozac, as a treatment for pediatric OCD, a spokesman said. SmithKline Beecham Plc is analyzing data from a recent study of using Paxil, an antidepressant, in 12- to 18-year-olds and plans to apply for FDA clearance, a spokeswoman said. Eli Lilly and Co., maker of Prozac, has submitted pediatric data to the FDA, too.</p>
<p>Dr. Joe Woolston, director of childrens' psychiatric in-patient services at Yale-New Haven Hospital in Connecticut, said overuse of these drugs in children is a problem sometimes compounded by overlapping prescriptions for them.</p>
<p>&quot;Every week I see at least one child who is on a regimen of something like Ritalin, Depakote, Haldol and Zoloft. It's just a ridiculous medication regimen,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a brand-new chapter&quot; in child psychiatry, Woolston said. &quot;The problem is people are using medications instead of doing full evaluation and treatment. Medication should be part of intervention, but it can't be stand-alone.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
