<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713592" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Former Warsaw Pact states thrilled to join NATO.</title>
<headline>Former Warsaw Pact states thrilled to join NATO.</headline>
<byline>Erik Kirschbaum</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leaders of three of NATO's former communist foes embraced and raised clasped arms in triumph on Tuesday after receiving invitations to join the defence alliance that won the Cold War.</p>
<p>Shortly after NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana extended the long-awaited offer, the ecstatic leaders of one-time Warsaw Pact allies Hungary, Poland and the Czech Republic shared the stage at a celebratory press conference.</p>
<p>Hungary's Prime Minister Gyula Horn, Czech President Vaclav Havel and Poland's President Aleksander Kwasniewski expressed delight over the historic offer issued by a summit of NATO leaders in the Spanish capital.</p>
<p>&quot;We express our deepest satisfaction for the invitation. This is an historic decision paving the way to a more stable and secure Europe,&quot; said Havel, the dissident poet-turned-statesman who was jailed by his country's communist rulers.</p>
<p>The three, smiling broadly, repeatedly huddled together and expressed pride the changes in their countries had made them eligible for inclusion in the Western club.</p>
<p>&quot;We see the invitation as recognition for tremendous support undertaken by our societies following the changes of 1989 and 1990,&quot; he said, referring to the collapse of communism.</p>
<p>The three states, which share similar tragic histories of long periods of foreign occupation by eastern or western neighbours, are expected to be formally included in the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation in 1999 after parliaments in all current 16 states ratify the enlargement process.</p>
<p>The three countries, which prefer to call themselves central rather than eastern European, said they hoped Romania and Slovenia along with other democratic nations in the formerly communist region would later join the alliance.</p>
<p>Kwasniewski, who spent a long afternoon waiting for the phone call from Solana in a luxury hotel on the other side of Madrid, said enlargement was good for Europe and for Poland.</p>
<p>&quot;After this decision, Europe will be more secure and it's a good decision for Poland,&quot; Kwasniewski told Reuters.</p>
<p>Poland, a nation of 38 million people, was particularly eager to join NATO after having been controlled or occupied by its mighty neighbours for centuries and benefit from its mutual defence pledge, backed by U.S. military might.</p>
<p>In this century, Germany occupied Poland for World War Two and the Soviet Union dominated it during the Cold War era.</p>
<p>Asked if Poland had sought NATO membership primarily because the alliance could spare the country from falling under foreign domination again, Kwasniewski said that that was history and Poland was looking toward the future.</p>
<p>&quot;We should look to the future, and the future should be without such fears. If we want to have an effective security system in Europe, we have to open up NATO.</p>
<p>Both Hungary and the Czech Republic, with populations of 10 million each, are much smaller than Poland. But all three neighbouring states emerged from the shackles of communism with fast-growing economies and clear commitments to democracy.</p>
<p>Laszlo Kovacs, Hungary's foreign minister, said he hoped the NATO entry would soon be followed by membership of the prosperous European Union. But he said NATO membership was not any less important than the EU, which Hungary, Poland and the Czech Republic hope to join within the next few years.</p>
<p>&quot;NATO provides security that the EU certainly cannot provide,&quot; Kovacs said in an interview with Reuters. &quot;The EU provides conditions for growth, economic stability and prosperity. The two should go together. NATO membership should certainly increase the chances of Hungary joining the EU.&quot;</p>
<p>In Bucharest, Prime Minister Victor Ciorbea said Romania had failed in its bid for early NATO membership because of delays in implementing post-communist reforms but predicted it would be accepted in the next expansion wave.</p>
<p>&quot;Romania's efforts to promote reforms are clear to all and lead us to a clear conclusion,&quot; he said. &quot;If we complete reforms, and I'm sure we will, in 1999 we'll be NATO members.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
