<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713637" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO launches historic expansion into East Europe.</title>
<headline>NATO launches historic expansion into East Europe.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Clayton</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A NATO summit invited Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic to join the alliance on Tuesday and gave clear commitments to Romania, Slovenia and the Baltic states they would be seriously considered in future.</p>
<p>&quot;Today the heads of state and government have agreed to invite the Czech Republic, Hungary and Poland to begin accession talks with NATO,&quot; NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana told the assembled alliance leaders and the news media.</p>
<p>NATO's 16 leaders agreed the biggest expansion in the alliance's 48-year history after France, which led a bloc of seven states urging a wider enlargement, won assurances the door would be left open and the situation reviewed in 1999.</p>
<p>Announcing the decision, which breaches Europe's Cold War division, Solana said the allies' goal was to admit formally the new members in April 1999 on the occasion of the alliance's 50th anniversary.</p>
<p>President Bill Clinton told reporters the invitation marked a &quot;giant stride&quot; towards a new Europe that was undivided, democratic and at peace.</p>
<p>Solana, reading a text which had been subject of intense day-long wrangling, mentioned Slovenia and Romania as prime candidates for the next round of expansion -- a concession by the United States which wanted a vaguer commitment.</p>
<p>Braving Moscow's wrath, the official declaration also gave favourable mention to the Baltic states as &quot;aspiring members&quot; without specifically naming the former Soviet republics of Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia.</p>
<p>&quot;We recognize the progress achieved towards greater stability and cooperation by the states in the Baltic region who are also aspiring members,&quot; the declaration said.</p>
<p>Solana, stressing NATO remained &quot;open to new members&quot; and expected to extend further invitations in coming years, said any working European democracy would be considered for membership.</p>
<p>Russia has warned that it would consider NATO membership by the Baltic republics, which have substantial Russian minorities, as a threat to its own security.</p>
<p>It condemned the enlargement announced on Tuesday by its former Cold War foe as &quot;the biggest mistake in Europe since the end of World War Two&quot;.</p>
<p>Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov said Moscow had not changed its position despite signing a new cooperation accord with NATO last May by which it grudgingly accepted it was powerless to stop the process.</p>
<p>&quot;Regarding the question of NATO expansion, I can only say that we confirm our stand,&quot; Primakov told reporters in Moscow.</p>
<p>But Polish President Aleksander Kwasniewski was delighted.</p>
<p>&quot;After this decision, Europe will be more secure and it's a good decision for Poland,&quot; he told Reuters, after waiting all afternoon in a hotel across town for the phone call from Solana.</p>
<p>At one of the most contentious NATO summits for years, France and Italy pushed strongly for Romania and Slovenia to also be invited, arguing that their inclusion would inject stability into some of Europe's most turbulent zones.</p>
<p>But Clinton, keenly aware he has to have expansion ratified by a sceptical Republican-led U.S. Congress, said only the three leading candidates were currently ready to meet all the responsibilities of membership.</p>
<p>&quot;They have met the highest standards of democratic and market reform. They have pursued those reforms long enough to give us confidence they are irreversible, just as our offer of NATO membership is irreversible,&quot; Clinton told fellow leaders.</p>
<p>The U.S. administration is bracing itself for tough questions over how much expansion -- the centrepiece of Clinton's foreign policy -- will cost and about the wisdom of extending America's nuclear defence shield to cover three more European states.</p>
<p>While key aides frantically worked on the &quot;open door&quot; language, Clinton and Chirac engaged in animated, finger-wagging exchanges while other heads of state and government milled aimlessly around the conference centre.</p>
<p>Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi also expressed strong support for Slovenia, and Greek Prime Minister Costas Simitis made a strong plea for Bulgaria, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>Clinton was backed by British Prime Minister Tony Blair and four other leaders.</p>
<p>The debate gave European allies a chance to vent their resentment over what they see as American heavy-handedness not only in its NATO dealings but in other transatlantic matters.</p>
<p>Chirac seized the opportunity on Tuesday to warn Clinton that NATO would not survive if the balance of power between Americans and Europeans was not shifted in favour of Europe, the French president's spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Some critics contend that enlargement could revive Cold War tensions by isolating Russia and by breeding envy among the nations excluded from the alliance.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BALTST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
