<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713605" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: Clerides says Cyprus accord would halt missile plan.</title>
<headline>Clerides says Cyprus accord would halt missile plan.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Goodman</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A plan to install Russian-made S-300 air defence missiles in Cyprus next year would be scrapped if an agreement was reached on the Cyprus problem, President Glafcos Clerides said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>In an interview with Reuters, he said five days of U.N.-sponsored talks beginning on Wednesday with Turkish Cypriot leader Rauf Denktash will provide an opportunity for &quot;an exchange of views on some of the main issues, perhaps agree on an agenda for the next talks, and measure how flexible the other side is.</p>
<p>&quot;More than likely there would be another session some time in August,&quot; he said, but noted a presidential election campaign in the Greek Cypriot-administered south of the island would make further negotiations difficult later on.</p>
<p>Clerides, 78, said he was still considering running for re-election in February 1998 and will make a decision after September.</p>
<p>Cyprus has been virtually partitioned since troops from Turkey took over the north of the island in 1974 in reaction to a coup in Nicosia backed by the junta then ruling Greece.</p>
<p>Adding urgency to the latest effort to end the division of the island are plans by the Nicosia government to install S-300 missiles some time in 1998. Turkey, which is only 40 miles (65 km) from Cyprus and would lose air superiority over the island, has vowed to prevent this.</p>
<p>Asked whether there were any circumstances that would result in scrapping the deployment of missiles, he replied, &quot;Yes. If we reach an agreement on the solution of the Cyprus problem, the agreement would also contain a provision for demilitarization of the island. And therefore ... there would be no S-300s, or any missiles or any armies.&quot;</p>
<p>Questioned about Denktash's insistence on recognition of the Turkish Cypriot community's sovereign equality with that of the Greek Cypriots, he said, &quot;I don't think that the sovereignty of a nation springs from the number of communities that there are in that country.&quot;</p>
<p>Clerides, whose Greek Cypriot-led administration is recognised internationally as the legitimate government of the whole of Cyprus, said, &quot;I see it as the U.N. sees it, as the whole world sees it. There is one sovereign state and that is the Republic of Cyprus.&quot;</p>
<p>Referring to repeated efforts by the United Nations to establish a bi-zonal, bi-communal federation, he said, &quot;What we are about to do is to change the constitution ... from that of a unitary state to a federal state.&quot;</p>
<p>The 1963 breakup of a government in which both communities had been represented made no difference. &quot;If a government collapses, the sovereignty of a country does not collapse,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
