<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713608" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO chief guides alliance beyond Cold War.</title>
<headline>NATO chief guides alliance beyond Cold War.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>By spearheading NATO's eastward expansion, Secretary-General Javier Solana has erased any doubts about his commitment to the military alliance he once fiercely opposed.</p>
<p>The former Spanish foreign minister, an outspoken critic of NATO in the early 1980s, has achieved back-to-back diplomatic triumphs in recent weeks, paving the way for bringing in new members from the former communist bloc.</p>
<p>Accomplishing what many thought could never be done, Solana hammered out a landmark post-Cold War treaty on May 14 between Russia and the Western allies, laying the groundwork for a new European security order.</p>
<p>He made history once again on Tuesday when NATO leaders put aside their bitter differences on how far and how fast the alliance should be enlarged and invited three countries -- Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic -- to join.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the dawning of a new future for Europe,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>It was yet another critical test of Solana's ability to navigate between opposing sides and find common ground. The United States had lobbied hard to limit the first wave of enlargement to the three favorites, but France and other NATO countries had pressed for including Romania and Slovenia.</p>
<p>Solana had barely settled into the alliance's top civilian job last year when he was mandated to convince Russia, NATO's former Cold War enemy, that its security would not be threatened by NATO's enlargement.</p>
<p>Known as a patient but tough negotiator, Solana held six rounds of meetings with Russian Foreign Minister Yevgeny Primakov, an ex-Kremlin spymaster.</p>
<p>Primakov voiced bitter opposition to NATO's expansion but Solana made clear the alliance would go ahead whether Russia liked it or not. What emerged was the &quot;Founding Act&quot;, a treaty that allowed Russia to save face while clearing the way for NATO to accept new members from Eastern Europe.</p>
<p>It marked a dramatic counterpoint to Solana's younger days. As a militant Socialist, he opposed the presence of U.S. military bases in Spain during the dictatorship of General Francisco Franco.</p>
<p>In the early 1980s, after the restoration of democracy, Solana spoke out against Spanish membership in NATO while the Socialists were in opposition.</p>
<p>But later as a Socialist government spokesman, he had a change of heart and backed a successful 1986 referendum campaign in favour of keeping Spain in the alliance.</p>
<p>His anti-NATO past came back to haunt him when he was nominated secretary-general in late 1995. Conservative U.S. congressmen protested to President Bill Clinton, calling Solana a &quot;dedicated Socialist&quot; with a &quot;record of hostility to NATO&quot;, and some European NATO officials also expressed reservations.</p>
<p>But, in the words of one Spanish diplomat, NATO leaders found Solana guilty only of &quot;juvenile delinquency&quot; and went on to ratify him to replace Willy Claes, who had resigned because of a corruption scandal in his native Belgium.</p>
<p>Solana -- a veteran politician credited with helping Spain emerge from the isolationism of Franco's rule -- was the compromise choice after the United States and its European allies failed to agree on two other candidates.</p>
<p>But the bearded Spaniard immediately won praise for his skilful handling of negotiations with Bosnian leaders over the implementation of the Dayton peace accords. Insiders say the personal rapport he developed with NATO leaders saw him entrusted with the task of hammering out a deal with Russia.</p>
<p>&quot;International organizations, like people, have to adapt to changing times to continue being relevant,&quot; Solana told the Spanish magazine Cambio 16 of the changes unleashed by the treaty signing.</p>
<p>Nearly two months after that accomplishment, Solana is still basking in the afterglow. &quot;This is an austere job,&quot; he recently told the Spanish daily El Mundo. &quot;But recently I have had cause for great celebration.&quot;</p>
<p>A close ally of former Spanish prime minister Felipe Gonzalez, the 54-year-old Solana was the clear favorite of the Socialist rank-and-file last month when Gonzalez stepped down after more than two decades as party chief.</p>
<p>However, Solana quickly took himself out of the running, saying he wanted to see NATO through the first phase of its expansion.</p>
<p>But with his NATO term ending in 1999, party insiders think he is all but certain to run for prime minister in elections scheduled for the year 2000. &quot;He has never made a secret of his ambition, and he may never get a better chance,&quot; a longtime colleague said.</p>
<p>An articulate speaker with an academic air, Solana was educated in physics at Madrid University and in the United States. He is an avid sportsman, married with two children and has written more than two dozen books.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
