<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713633" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Ex-Soviet Azerbaijan applies to join WTO.</title>
<headline>Ex-Soviet Azerbaijan applies to join WTO.</headline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The oil-rich ex-Soviet state of Azerbaijan has submitted a formal request to be considered for membership of the World Trade Organisation (WTO), trade officials said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The request is to be discussed at the next meeting of the 131-member WTO's ruling General Council on July 16.</p>
<p>If there are no objections, the Council is likely to set up a working party to provide a forum for negotiations and preparation of a protocol of accession, a process likely to take at least two years, according to trade diplomats.</p>
<p>Azerbaijan will have to demonstrate that it is bringing its once strictly state-controlled economy onto open market lines and make detailed commitment to open up to goods and services from other countries.</p>
<p>But trade sources said that in initial contacts with the WTO it had already promised to work to ensure that its trade practices were in line with the body's rules and declared it had already moved to liberalise.</p>
<p>The Caspian Sea state is the 13th of the 15 republics of the old Soviet Union -- which itself stood aloof from the WTO's predecessor, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade or GATT -- to apply to join the body.</p>
<p>Russia has been in negotiations for over four years and trade diplomats say it is unlikely to be admitted until well into next year.</p>
<p>Of the other two big ex-Soviet states, Ukraine has been negotiating for nearly four years, and Kazakhstan began formal talks in a working party earlier this year.</p>
<p>The only former Soviet republics who have not yet applied are Turkmenistan, with which Azerbaijan is in dispute over a Russian-Azeri oil deal agreed last week, and Tajikistan which has been torn by civil conflict since independence in 1991.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AZERB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
