<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713620" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Central Europe slides away from Russia to West.</title>
<headline>Central Europe slides away from Russia to West.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Worsnip</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>With NATO's invitation on Tuesday to Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary to apply to join the alliance, Central Europe began a historical slide out of the Russian orbit and into the Western camp.</p>
<p>The North Atlantic Treaty Organisation summit where the inivitation was issued &quot;will change the politics of Europe for ever&quot;, U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright said.</p>
<p>Although the application process will take two years, the three invitees -- and neighbouring countries expected to follow their path -- could now see themselves finally emerging from a long night of domination by Moscow.</p>
<p>Polish Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz called the invitation the &quot;end of the Yalta order in Europe&quot;, a reference to the 1945 big power agreement which assigned eastern Europe to the Soviet sphere of influence.</p>
<p>The Kremlin-appointed communists who ruled the states in the region after World War Two said they were bound eternally to the Soviet Union -- politically, economically and through the now defunct Warsaw Pact military alliance.</p>
<p>But since the Soviet empire collapsed at the end of the 1980s, and democratic governments took over, countries from Estonia in the north to Albania in the south have been united by one idea: to join the West as fast as possible.</p>
<p>For them this promised not just security from Russia and other historical oppressors, but also riches if they could join the European Union and get a piece of Western Europe's prosperity.</p>
<p>The Central and East European countries -- small and medium- sized states speaking a Babel of languages unknown elsewhere -- have known little freedom, crunched for centuries between Germans to the West and Russians to the East.</p>
<p>The major powers marched across these countries whenever they went to war with each other. The largest and most populous state in the region, Poland, was partitioned between Russia, Prussia and Austria from the late 18th to early 20th centuries.</p>
<p>Independence was thrust once before on the states in the area, when the Austro-Hungarian and Turkish Ottoman empires collapsed after World War One.</p>
<p>But, unsupported by any collective security or economic system, many became dictatorships and all eventually fell to Adolf Hitler's German armies before coming under the sway of Josef Stalin's Soviet Union.</p>
<p>Western leaders say the key to avoiding a repeat of this type of scenario is integrating these vulnerable states into Western organisations like NATO, a process now starting, and the EU, which will take longer. These groupings have kept Western Europe at peace and can do the same for the East, they say.</p>
<p>As evidence, they point to efforts already made by Hungary and Romania, Poland and Ukraine, and the Czech Republic and Germany, to patch up long-standing ethnic and other disputes.</p>
<p>But although NATO leaders say expansion is not aimed against Russia in the post-Cold War era, they have failed to avoid antagonising their former adversary, already humiliated by its collapse from world superpower to economic basket case.</p>
<p>Russia has been mollified by a charter signed in May which will give it a voice, though not a veto, in NATO affairs. But Moscow is drawing a new line in the sand, saying it will fiercely oppose the entry of the Baltic states into NATO.</p>
<p>But the East European states, including the Baltics, insist that they have always been culturally part of the West and espouse &quot;Western values&quot; -- a view shared by Western politicians supporting NATO expansion.</p>
<p>&quot;These nations will bear the cost of defending freedom because they know the price of losing freedom,&quot; Albright wrote in a newspaper article on Tuesday. &quot;They are ready, willing and able to contribute to our common agenda for security... and we should be ready to welcome them.&quot;</p>
<p>Critics of the move argue, however, that NATO expansion makes no political or military sense, and is motivated essentially by guilt over Western countries' failure to support or defend their East European neighbours earlier this century.</p>
<p>According to Edward Luttwak of the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington, giving the East Europeans NATO membership is a &quot;cruel deception&quot; since no major Western country would send troops to help them in a crisis.</p>
<p>&quot;Neither Americans nor Western Europeans will fight Russia for the sake of Poland, the Baltic states or Ukraine. Giving them NATO membership cannot change geographic and political reality,&quot; Luttwak wrote in the Washington Post on Sunday.</p>
<p>The Czech-born Albright conceded in her article that enlarging NATO was intended in part to &quot;right the wrongs of the past&quot; but said that not to do it would display Cold War thinking.</p>
<p>&quot;If we were creating NATO today, we would not even consider making the old Iron Curtain its permanent eastern frontier. We would not say to any new democracy that having been subjugated in the past, it must be excluded in the future,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
