<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713672" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: Vranitzky says to carry on in Albania for OSCE.</title>
<headline>Vranitzky says to carry on in Albania for OSCE.</headline>
<byline>Julia Ferguson</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Franz Vranitzky, head of the OSCE mission to Albania, said on Tuesday he would continue his work for Europe's top security body in the Balkan state even after the withdrawal of a multinational security force next month.</p>
<p>The former Austrian chancellor told Reuters in an interview the Organisation for Security and Cooperation in Europe's chairman in office, Danish Foreign Minister Niels Helveg Petersen, had asked him to stay on to coordinate the body's measures to restore a functioning economy and judiciary system.</p>
<p>The Balkan state has been riven by months of violence and bloodshed triggered by the collapse of shady investment funds.</p>
<p>An 11-nation Italian-led force of 7,000 troops was deployed in April to guard the distribution of aid and help secure free and fair elections in Europe's poorest country.</p>
<p>The ex-communist Socialists won a landslide victory in the elections called to end the anarchy, but Albania now needs financial help from the West to rebuild its shattered economy and ensure the violence does not resurface, Vranitzky said.</p>
<p>&quot;I have suggested to Mr Petersen that he might come up with a decision to set up a working group quickly to deal with the financial and economic reconstruction of Albania with the restoration of public order and with a good deal of support for the Albanians as far as security is concerned,&quot; Vranitzky said.</p>
<p>But how to best tackle Albania's problems was tricky.</p>
<p>&quot;Should it be only concentrating on setting up a police force? But then one could criticise that Albania is going to be a police state,&quot; he said in English.</p>
<p>&quot;Should we only come up with financial support? But then many people would say we need security and safety before we put money into the country. It's a vicious circle,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Therefore a package which incorporated the two was the logical solution, although it would be &quot;very tough work&quot;.</p>
<p>Vranitzky stressed the importance of involving Albanians in negotiations as much as possible, for example with the International Monetary Fund, the World Bank and the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development.</p>
<p>&quot;We should set up this cooperation very quickly otherwise private investors will not spend a moment's thought of going to Albania,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
