<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713623" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Kwasniewski calls NATO move good for Poland, Europe.</title>
<headline>Kwasniewski calls NATO move good for Poland, Europe.</headline>
<byline>Erik Kirschbaum</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's President Aleksander Kwasniewski said on Tuesday he was delighted that NATO had extended membership to the former Warsaw Pact nation, calling it an historic decision that would make Europe a safer place.</p>
<p>Kwasniewski told Reuters just moments after receiving word that NATO leaders were welcoming Poland into the alliance that it was a good decision for Europe and for Poland.</p>
<p>&quot;After this decision, Europe will be more secure and it's a good decision for Poland,&quot; said Kwasniewski, who had waited all afternoon in a Madrid hotel across town for the phone call from NATO Secretary General Javier Solana.</p>
<p>The phone call was expected in the early afternoon but was delayed when NATO leaders were unable to reach an agreement on the precise details of NATO enlargement during their morning session as had been expected.</p>
<p>&quot;This decision is a very historic one,&quot; added Kwasniewski, who was smiling broadly after the long, nerve-racking wait. &quot;We need the next step and we are prepared to make the next steps, these preparations (for membership) and negotiations.&quot;</p>
<p>Poland is expected to be formally included in the North Atlantic Treaty Alliance in 1999 after parliaments in all 16 states ratify the decision reached in Madrid.</p>
<p>Poland, a nation of 40 million people, was eager to join NATO after having been controlled or occupied by its mighty neighbours to the east or west for centuries.</p>
<p>Russia for centuries held Poland under its influence or control. Nazi Germany occupied it for much of World War Two and the Soviet Union dominated it for most of the Cold War era before it escaped the grip of the Iron Curtain with the collapse of communism.</p>
<p>Asked if Poland had sought NATO membership primarily because the alliance could spare the country from falling under foreign domination again, Kwasniewski said that that was history and Poland was looking toward the future.</p>
<p>&quot;This a very traditional approach,&quot; Kwasniewski said.</p>
<p>&quot;But we should look to the future, and the future should be without such fears. If we want to have an effective security system in Europe, we have to open up NATO.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Poland, because of our potential and because of our geographic location, is a very important partner in such a common security system, a new architecture for security in Europe.&quot;</p>
<p>Kwasniewski said he was confident Russia would not try to stop the enlargement even though some Polish officials have expressed concerns. Poland has long worried about Russian opposition.</p>
<p>Marek Siwiec, Kwasniewski's top foreign policy aide, said in Warsaw in April: &quot;There was a time when we spoke with Russia on our knees...Now the time has come when we can talk with Russia looking deep into each other's eyes.&quot;</p>
<p>Moscow had long opposed Poland's NATO membership because of fears it would increase a threat to its own security from the Western alliance and because Poland borders its Kaliningrad enclave.</p>
<p>&quot;I think Russia has already accepted this (enlargement),&quot; Kwasniewski said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
