<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713754" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEPAL: Ten injured in clashes over Nepal oil price hike.</title>
<headline>Ten injured in clashes over Nepal oil price hike.</headline>
<byline>Gopal Sharma</byline>
<dateline>KATHMANDU 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ten people were injured when demonstrators protesting against an increase in oil prices clashed with police in the Nepali capital on Tuesday during a day-long strike, union officials said.</p>
<p>Taxis, buses and three-wheeled auto-rickshaws participated in the strike and shops remained shut in response to a call by the Nepal Students' Union (NSU), a wing of the centrist opposition Nepali Congress party.</p>
<p>&quot;The oil price increase has affected every one. The poor people are the hardest hit,&quot; said NSU President Govinda Bhattarai.</p>
<p>Last month the communist-dominated coalition government raised the domestic price of diesel by 25 percent, kerosene by 15.7 percent and petrol by 14.7.</p>
<p>The increases in diesel and kerosene were partly rolled back after strong protests from coalition partners. Organisers of the strike also called on schools, factories and businesses to remain closed to protest against what they alleged was the communists' rigging of local elections in May.</p>
<p>At least 24 people were killed and 350 injured, most of them in clashes between rival groups, during the polls for local councils.</p>
<p>The Unified Marxist-Leninist (UML) party, which dominates the ruling coalition, has won 94,000 positions in local bodies against 53,000 places held by the Nepali Congress. The UML denies the polls were rigged.</p>
<p>NSU chief Bhattarai said Tuesday's strike was the first in a series of protests his group planned to stage throughout the Himalayan kingdom to press for educational reforms, increasing fertiliser supplies and eliminating corruption in one of the world's 10 poorest countries.</p>
<p>Hundreds of demonstrators marched in torch-light processions on Monday in the Kathmandu Valley's three ancient cities, dotted with pagoda-topped temples.</p>
<p>Torch-light processions by Nepali Congress and communist activists were common during a pro-democracy struggle in 1990 which replaced Nepal's 30-year old partyless assembly system with multi-party democracy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NEPAL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I72102">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I72200">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KATHMANDU"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEPAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
