<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="713801" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: BA passengers face strike disruption.</title>
<headline>BA passengers face strike disruption.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of British Airways passengers face disruption on Wednesday when cabin crews are due to begin the first of a series of three-day strikes.</p>
<p>The airline said late on Tuesday that it would ask an independent arbitrator to consider the cabin crew union's proposals for saving millions of pounds.</p>
<p>But the announcement came too late to avert the first stoppage due to begin at 0500 GMT on Wednesday.</p>
<p>BA, which operates 1,000 flights a day worldwide, said it held last minute talks with the cabin crews' Transport and General Workers' Union (T&amp;G) aided by the conciliation service ACAS, after earlier negotiations broke down on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;The ball is now in the union's court...all our attention now is focused on minimising disruption to our passengers tomorrow,&quot; a BA spokesman said.</p>
<p>BA had hoped to save 42 million pounds ($70.7 million) from its cabin crew operations. The union proposals are thought to recommend smaller savings.</p>
<p>There was no one at the T&amp;G available for comment.</p>
<p>This week's strike is likely to strand thousands of tourists and business travellers.</p>
<p>British travel agents said on Tuesday they had been flooded with calls from customers trying to find alternative flights on rival airlines.</p>
<p>BA said its contingency plan, aimed at keeping as many of its flights running as possible, would now swing into action but it admitted thousands of passengers may still be grounded.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if the strike is cancelled today, there is likely to be disruption,&quot; the BA spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Unless a solution is found, the T&amp;G is threatening to call further 72-hour strikes.</p>
<p>The airline suffered early disruption on Tuesday when 350 staff reported sick, causing 14 flights to be cancelled.</p>
<p>BA has cancelled half its long-haul services from Heathrow on Wednesday and some two-thirds of intercontinental flights from Gatwick. But worst hit will be short-haul and domestic services from Heathrow.</p>
<p>The airline aims to run all its domestic and European flights to and from London Gatwick; all international flights to and from UK regional airports; domestic flights except those serving London Heathrow; and all those operated by its alliance partners.</p>
<p>BA says it expects 3,500 staff belonging to a smaller, non-striking union, Cabin Crew 89, to turn up for work on Wednesday as well as estimated 1,500 staff who are prepared to cross the picket line.</p>
<p>Under British civil aviation law, any flight carrying more than 20 passengers must have at least one cabin crew member per 50 passengers.</p>
<p>BA is involved in a separate dispute with ground crew over the sale of its catering division at Heathrow. The workers are expected to announce later today whether they have accepted BA's offer to resolve the row.</p>
<p>The disputes follow the airline's plans to save one billion pounds by 2000 through a major restructuring. ($ = 0.594 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
