<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714080" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: N.Ireland Secretary talks of Garvaghy &quot;failure&quot;.</title>
<headline>N.Ireland Secretary talks of Garvaghy &quot;failure&quot;.</headline>
<byline>Des Wright</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Northern Ireland Secretary Mo Mowlam said on Tuesday that Catholics opposed to weekend Orange Order parades were no longer talking to her after what she called &quot;my failure&quot; over Sunday's march in Portadown.</p>
<p>&quot;(Irish) nationalists are very angry. Nationalists are thinking about whether to talk to me or not so my use may be limited after my failure in Garvaghy. I accept that,&quot; she told reporters.</p>
<p>Mowlam said she was trying to negotiate an agreement on two weekend parades which police fear may repeat the pattern of Protestant-Catholic deadlock which led to the holding of an Orange Order parade along Portadown's Catholic Garvaghy Road.</p>
<p>That Saturday march plunged Northern Ireland into the worst outbreak of Catholic Irish nationalist anger for years. More than a hundred people have been injured in nightly riots and scores of bullets fired by IRA guerrillas.</p>
<p>Mowlam said she was conducting talks with the Orange Order to try to find an &quot;accommodation&quot; on a flashpoint parade to be held along Belfast's Lower Ormeau Road on Saturday and another march by the Apprentice Boys in Londonderry the same day.</p>
<p>But Catholic residents groups in the Lower Ormeau Road are refusing contact with Mowlam because of her failure to get the Portadown parade rerouted or to tell Garvaghy Road residents personally of a decision to permit it</p>
<p>The parades are held on July 12, the most hallowed date in the Orange Order's calendar because it marks a 1690 victory by a Protestant King over an invading Catholic monarch which assured that a Protestant came to the throne in London.</p>
<p>Mowlam held talks on Monday night with the Orange Order to see if it would agree to any modification in its plans to parade through the Catholic Lower Ormeau enclave, scene of violent protest last year and in 1995.</p>
<p>But in the absence of talks with Catholics, it would be difficult to make progress. &quot;It is only by accommodation that we will avoid the Chief Constable having to make a decision on Saturday as he did in Drumcree (Portadown),&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Mowlam disputed media reports based on a leaked Northern Ireland Office (NIO) document which purported to show that her advisers decided to permit the Orange Order march on June 20, 15 days before a decision was announced and greeted by riots.</p>
<p>The embattled British minister did not dispute the authenticity of the NIO document but said it was merely a summary of options drawn up by security advisers.</p>
<p>&quot;If you read the document carefully you will see it sets out a whole host of options and my desired option was always an accommodation, a negotiated agreement because that is the one way we would have stopped the violence of the past two nights.&quot;</p>
<p>The document, now circulating among Belfast media, said that allowing the parade as planned was the &quot;least worst option.&quot;</p>
<p>It said that Orange officials had rejected proposals to defuse Catholic anger by agreeing to limit their parade numbers and dispense with heraldry and bands.</p>
<p>Such steps might have appeased Northern Ireland's minority Catholics who say the parades are sectarian, triumphalist and intimidatory.</p>
<p>Mainstream Catholic politicians of the Social Democratic and Labour Party (SDLP) reacted bitterly to the document.</p>
<p>&quot;If the Government thought that was the least worst option, that's incredible. It was because the march was taking place down the Garvaghy Road that there was so much tension,&quot; SDLP leader John Hume told local radio.</p>
<p>Mitchel McLaughlin, chairman of Sinn Fein, the IRA's political wing, said the document showed Britain was guilty of &quot;an outrageous example of double speak.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The sense of betrayal felt by nationalists will be reinforced by tonight's news. This was a planned betrayal.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
