<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714048" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: N.Ireland Secretary faces Catholic ire over leak.</title>
<headline>N.Ireland Secretary faces Catholic ire over leak.</headline>
<byline>Giles Elgood</byline>
<dateline>BELFAST 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Northern Ireland Secretary, Mo Mowlam, faced mounting Roman Catholic anger on Tuesday over a leaked official document which suggested she had ignored their objections to a weekend Protestant parade.</p>
<p>Mowlam went into a new round of talks on the faltering Northern Ireland peace process overshadowed by Catholic anger over the leaked document, which concluded that allowing the parade was &quot;the least worst outcome&quot;.</p>
<p>The latest round of the year-old multi-party talks was being held in the wake of some of the worst unrest seen in Northern Ireland for years. Participants say the negotiations are marking time, overshadowed by the alarming security situation.</p>
<p>Shooting and rioting erupted after authorities decided to allow the Orange Order to parade along Portadown's Garvaghy Road over the objections of its Catholic residents.</p>
<p>Mowlam said Roman Catholics opposed to Orange Order parades were no longer talking to her after what she called &quot;my failure&quot; over last Sunday's Portadown march.</p>
<p>Catholic politicans reacted furiously to the leaked government document which they said showed the government had already decided in advance of negotiations to send the march by the Protestant Orangemen along the Garvaghy Road.</p>
<p>&quot;Nationalists are very angry. Nationalists are thinking about whether to talk to me or not so my use may be limited after my failure in Garvaghy. I accept that,&quot; Mowlam told reporters.</p>
<p>John Hume, leader of the mainstream Catholic Social Democratic and Labour Party called for a moratorium on all marches, something unlikely to find much echo with the Orangemen as they approach the high point of the annual &quot;marching season&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;We have very strong anger to express. We believe that what has happened is intensifying the tensions in our community and those tensions, unfortunately as we know, have in the past given rise to confrontation and to violence on our streets,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hume's deputy, Seamus Mallon, added: &quot;Those who are trying hardest to get a solution to this problem have a right to feel very deeply hurt.&quot;</p>
<p>Nationalist anger was sparked in part by a reference in the leaked document to the best means of &quot;getting some Orange feet on the Garvaghy Road&quot;.</p>
<p>Mowlam said she was trying to negotiate an agreement over two weekend parades which police fear may repeat the pattern of Protestant-Catholic deadlock which led to the holding of an Orange Order parade along Portadown's Catholic Garvaghy Road.</p>
<p>That Saturday march plunged Northern Ireland into the worst outbreak of Catholic, Irish nationalist anger for years in which more than a hundred people have been injured in nightly riots and scores of bullets fired by IRA guerrillas.</p>
<p>Mowlam said she was conducting talks with the Orange Order to try to find an &quot;accommodation&quot; over a flashpoint parade to be held along Belfast's Lower Ormeau Road on Saturday and another march by the Apprentice Boys in Londonderry the same day.</p>
<p>But Catholic residents groups in the Lower Ormeau Road are refusing contact with Mowlam because of her failure to get the Portadown parade rerouted or to tell Garvaghy Road residents personally of a decision to permit it</p>
<p>The parades are held on July 12, the most hallowed date in the Orange Order's calendar which commemorates a 1690 victory by a Protestant King over an invading Catholic monarch which assured that a Protestant came to the throne in London.</p>
<p>Mowlam denied that her advisers decided to permit the Orange Order march on June 20, 15 days before a decision was announced and greeted by riots.</p>
<p>The embattled British minister said the leaked Northern Ireland Office document was merely a summary of options drawn up by security advisers.</p>
<p>Mitchel McLaughlin, chairman of Sinn Fein, the IRA's political wing, said the document showed Britain was guilty of &quot;an outrageous example of double speak.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The sense of betray felt by nationalists will be reinforced by tonight's news. This was a planned betrayal,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELFAST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
