<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714034" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Genetic tomato could help beat cancer - scientists.</title>
<headline>Genetic tomato could help beat cancer - scientists.</headline>
<byline>Maggie Fox</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>European scientists said on Tuesday they had bred a vitamin-rich tomato they hope can eventually help prevent heart disease and cancer.</p>
<p>They also hoped the genetically engineered tomato would be more acceptable to Europeans frightened by the idea of transgenic food.</p>
<p>The tomato has increased levels of carotenoids, nutrients important to health. It has about four times the normal levels of beta-carotene, which the body uses to make vitamin A, and twice the levels of lycopene, the compound that helps make tomatoes red and a close cousin of beta-carotene.</p>
<p>&quot;The reason for that is there are a number of reports that lycopene reduces the risks of some cancers,&quot; said Peter Bramley, a professor of biochemistry at the Royal Holloway Hospital in Egham near London.</p>
<p>&quot;Therefore, the idea is if we can increase the amount of lycopene in the diet through tomatoes this can reduce the incidence of these cancers,&quot; Bramley, who coordinated the European Union-funded study, told Reuters.</p>
<p>Bramley's team report their results in a report to the European Commission this week. They are among 130 European laboratories funded by a 50 million Ecu ($56 million) project known as the Project of Technological Priority (PTP).</p>
<p>Barmley's group used the same technology used to breed Calgene Inc's Flavr Savr tomato -- using a bacteria to deliver a new gene into the plant.</p>
<p>&quot;What we have done is to take the gene that encodes the enzyme to produce lycopene and we have introduced that into the tomato so it only works in the ripening fruit,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Tomatoes already have the gene, so the idea is to amplify its effects. So far it has worked.</p>
<p>&quot;It actually does express and we have increased lycopene levels and we also have a plant that has increased beta-carotene as well,&quot; Bramley said.</p>
<p>Other teams in Spain and Germany are working with peppers, Bramley said.</p>
<p>The next step would be to test the tomatoes on people, Bramley said.</p>
<p>&quot;What we can't be sure of is precisely what amount one would have to take into the diet to achieve the effects we are looking for,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Bramley said he had eaten his transgenic tomatoes. &quot;They don't taste any different,&quot; he said. &quot;They are quite normal. They may look a little redder or a little more orange.&quot;</p>
<p>But he was acutely aware of the fears people had about genetically engineered food.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we need to explain what we do and why we do it,&quot; he said. &quot;But this is, I would say, a potential health benefit as opposed to things that may be more for animal feed or herbicide resistance, so I would guess that the public would be more receptive to it.&quot;</p>
<p>Street demonstrations broke out in several European cities earlier this year over news that Monsanto's Round up Ready soybean, genetically engineered to resist herbicides, would be imported without labelling.</p>
<p>But Bramley noted that the genes inserted into the tomatoes and peppers were genes for substances already eaten by people, so the safety implications were different.</p>
<p>He said work was being done in other labs to create rice rich in beta-carotene and lycopene for growing in countries where naturally vitamin-rich vegetables are scarce.</p>
<p>Research has shown that beta-carotene supplements can reduce the risk of prostate cancer in men.</p>
<p>Other studies have shown that supplements do not reduce the risk of cancer in smokers, so experts think fruit and vegetables contain other substances that enhance the effects of the nutrients.</p>
<p>Beta-carotene and lycopene are anti-oxidants -- they counteract the effects of molecules known as free radicals which can damage cells, leading to cancer, heart disease and other harmful effects.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100206">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C23">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
