<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714161" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>LEBANON: Fiery cleric grabs Lebanese political stage.</title>
<headline>Fiery cleric grabs Lebanese political stage.</headline>
<byline>Michael Georgy</byline>
<dateline>BAALBEK, Lebanon 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former Hizbollah leader Sheikh Sobhi Tufaili, who last week launched a &quot;hunger revolt&quot; against the government, has emerged as a potent force in Lebanese politics, analysts said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The radical Shi'ite Moslem cleric's campaign has deepened divisions between Hizbollah factions, one choosing to work within the political system and the other fighting what it says is government neglect of poor areas, one analyst said.</p>
<p>But the analysts wondered if Tufaili, who condemns Hizbollah's (Party of God) leaders as too soft, will press ahead with his civil disobedience campaign to ease economic hardship or trip political landmines.</p>
<p>They say Tufaili will not be able to carry on without a green light from Syria, the main power broker in Lebanon with 35,000 troops in the country, many manning Bekaa checkpoints.</p>
<p>&quot;His campaign will never really get out of hand because the Syrians don't want to look like they have lost any control over the Bekaa or anywhere else in Lebanon,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>The 51-year-old cleric launched his campaign in this Bekaa Valley town last Friday at a rally of several thousand supporters who called for the downfall of the government.</p>
<p>The campaign has grabbed newspaper front pages, alarming the government and raising questions about the current political complexion of Hizbollah, which he headed until 1991.</p>
<p>&quot;Tufaili has emerged from oblivion into politics. The result is he is a force to be reckoned with,&quot; said a Lebanese analyst who requested anonymity.</p>
<p>Tufaili is urging Bekaa residents to refuse to pay utility bills and taxes to pressure the government to tackle poverty in the area which is suffering economically from a crackdown on illegal drug crops.</p>
<p>The charismatic cleric holds no post in Hizbollah but is still a member. He left his post as secretary-general in 1991 and fell out with the new leadership when it took a desicion to take part in the 1992 parliamentary elections.</p>
<p>Hizbollah now has a nine-member base in the 128-seat parliament.</p>
<p>Hizbollah officials agree that economic problems should be tackled. But they disagree with Tufaili's methods, saying his campaign will only trigger a confrontation with the government threatening the national peace.</p>
<p>Tufaili has been at odds with the Hizbollah leadership for years and analysts said his campaign had allowed him to regain lost political leverage within the movement.</p>
<p>&quot;Tufaili was relatively marginalised after disagreeing with Hizbollah over the 1992 elections which were a success for Hizbollah,&quot; said another Lebanese analyst.</p>
<p>&quot;His power was on the wane...I think he was looking for a chance to regain lost ground. That's why the populist message was beneficial.&quot;</p>
<p>The first analyst said: &quot;There is now a definite split within Hizbollah into two factions. The mainstream Hizbollah is busy fighting the Israelis and Tufaili is concentrating on the 'hunger revolt'&quot;.</p>
<p>Tufaili's message carries weight in a country where the government is criticised for spending billions on reconstruction and ignoring rural development and social problems.</p>
<p>Parliament Speaker Nabih Berri, who heads the mainstream Shi'ite movement Amal, said the government had to move swiftly to ease hardship. His comment on the day of Tufaili's protest underscored official concerns over the &quot;hunger revolt.&quot;</p>
<p>The question now is whether the campaign will steam ahead or will the government, which has already threatened legal action against Tufaili, undermine it.</p>
<p>&quot;Tufaili has set a serious precedent. Protests and gatherings are banned but the government allowed him to hold the gathering on Friday which went peacefully,&quot; said one analyst.</p>
<p>But there are signs that the authorities could crack down on a man whose firebrand speeches stir emotions.</p>
<p>Interior Minister Michel al-Murr sacked the acting national police chief for meeting Tufaili and coordinating security in Baalbek before Friday's protest.</p>
<p>And in an apparent warning, troops carried out scores of detentions in Baalbek and the Bekaa Valley immediately after the rally. All those held were freed within hours.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAALBEK, Lebanon"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="LEBANON"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
