<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714158" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAQ: U.N. germ warfare team starts mission in Iraq.</title>
<headline>U.N. germ warfare team starts mission in Iraq.</headline>
<dateline>BAGHDAD 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A United Nations germ warfare team is in Baghdad trying to close remaining gaps in Iraq's bilogical weapons file, a U.N. arms official in Baghdad said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Jo Lomas, special assistant to the head of Iraq's ongoing monitoring programme, said the 12-member team arrived on Sunday and had a meeting with the head of Iraq National Monitoring Department (IND) Hussam Ameen.</p>
<p>She said since last month's standoff when a U.N. weapons team was denied access to three sensitive Iraqi sites, the Iraqis had been cooperating with visiting teams.</p>
<p>She said a chemical arms group ended its Iraq visit last week with &quot;no major incident&quot;. The current biological team has already started inspection of Iraq's biological weapons sites.</p>
<p>&quot;So far we have not been denied access to any site,&quot; Lomas told Reuters.</p>
<p>Last month's standoff on inspection rights prompted the Security Council to issue a warning to Iraq that it would clamp more sanctions on Baghdad if it did not comply fully with obligations under the 1991 Gulf War ceasefire.</p>
<p>Under the Gulf War terms Iraq has to rid itself of weapons of mass destruction and long-range missiles along with the means to produce them. It is also compelled to accept long term surveillance of its mass weapons industries.</p>
<p>Lomas said the current biological team, headed by Briton David Kelly, would stay for two weeks in Iraq.</p>
<p>The U.N. Special Commission (UNSCOM) disarming Iraq under the ceasefire conditions says Iraq has not yet revealed all secrets about its past biological warfare capabilities. Baghdad says it has nothing left to hide.</p>
<p>The removal of curbs on Iraq's oil exports largely depends on testimony from UNSCOM that Iraq's weapons of mass destrcution have been annihilated or rendered harmless.</p>
<p>The U.N. has allowed Iraq partial oil exports worth $2 billion over six months to raise money to meet Iraqis' urgent needs. Iraq completed the limited exports late in June and the U.N. renewed them on June 8.</p>
<p>But Baghdad has not yet resumed the exports pending the completion of food procurement and distribution programmes.</p>
<p>U.N. relief officials in Baghdad said recently the distribution plans were ready and would be sent to the U.N. secretary-general for approval in the next few days.</p>
<p>Lomax also said the newly appointed U.N. chief arms inspector would make his first visit to Iraq on July 21.</p>
<p>On July 1, Butler replaced Rolf Ekeus of Sweden, who had led UNSCOM since its inception in 1991.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAQ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BAGHDAD"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAQ"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
