<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714155" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Serious BA N.Atlantic cargo delays unlikely.</title>
<headline>Serious BA N.Atlantic cargo delays unlikely.</headline>
<byline>David Gersovitz</byline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Many of British Airways' North Atlantic cargo customers will have to reroute shipments to circumvent the strike planned for 72 hours from 0500 GMT on Wednesday by the airline's cabin crew, but serious delays are unlikely, say industry observers.</p>
<p>One reason is the timing of the strike, which will  ground at least 55 percent of BA's intercontinental operations.</p>
<p>July is the low season for air cargo, but peak season for passenger operations, so other carriers have a fair bit of cargo space to offer, industry analysts said.</p>
<p>After the U.S. July 4 holidays, manufacturers on both sides of the Atlantic begin shutting down for holidays, Mark Najarian, vice-president for sales at American Airlines Cargo told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;If this (strike) had happened in March or even June, we wouldn't have had any space to offer BA cargo customers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;At least today we have some space we're going to be able to offer.&quot;</p>
<p>BA is a preferred carrier for Seattle-based freight forwarder Expeditors International. Barry Richard, Expeditors' director of pricing, said the strike's timing means more leeway to get freight to and from the UK.</p>
<p>He said Expeditors' staff are working with local BA  cargo officials at each airport to determine if they can handle the forwarders' shipments.</p>
<p>&quot;In some cases they can, in some cases they can't, and where they can't we're making alternative arrangements,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Some airlines, including Air Canada and Canadian Airlines are adding flights to fill in for BA's schedule, and that will add more cargo capacity.</p>
<p>American flies most of the same U.S.-U.K. routes as BA, said Najarian. It also provides cargo space within the U.S. for BA and moves &quot;a tremendous amount of volume&quot; from western to eastern U.S. airports to feed BA's international flights.</p>
<p>&quot;We're getting a tremendous number of calls, as you can imagine, and we're going to do what we can to help them,&quot; added Najarian.</p>
<p>Dana Bates, cargo marketing manager for Continental Airlines reported a similar experience, but said Continental won't know until the weekend how much business results.</p>
<p>Najarian said American will offer BA cargo customers alternative capacity where possible, though in a case like Charlotte, North Carolina, the nearest American UK departure from Raleigh-Durham, planes are going out full and the airline cannot accommodate BA's business.</p>
<p>In that case, those BA customers will have to truck further to airports like New York, he said.</p>
<p>BA hopes to maintain 16 U.S. flights daily during the strike. All flights to Canada are cancelled.</p>
<p>There will be services to London from New York, Boston, Pittsburgh, Dallas, Houston, Chicago, Miami and Los Angeles.</p>
<p>All services from Philadelphia, Baltimore, San Francisco, Detroit, Orlando, Washington, D.C., Tampa, Phoenix, Seattle and Atlanta are cancelled.</p>
<p>-- Reuters Air Cargo Service Tel+ 44 171 542 7706 Fax +5017</p>
<p>-- www.racs.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I77003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
