<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714114" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Amstrad to appeal Seagate ruling.</title>
<headline>Amstrad to appeal Seagate ruling.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Amstrad Plc said on Tuesday it would appeal a court decision to award the British electronics group 85.45 million pounds ($144 million) in an alleged fraud case against U.S. hard disk drive manufacturer Seagate Technology Inc.</p>
<p>Amstrad, which is seeking a total settlement of around 105 million pounds on a claim dating back to 1989, was awarded 57 million pounds last month and the latest British hearing was to determine interest and costs.</p>
<p>&quot;We will be appealing against the interest and tax calculations,&quot; a company spokesman said.</p>
<p>The company, which alleges that the U.S. group sold it faulty disk drives, also said it was meeting with its British and U.S. lawyers to consider bringing a new action in America against Seagate for punitive damages.</p>
<p>Under American law, a court can award four times damages as a punitive measure if cases such as fraud are proven.</p>
<p>&quot;The lawyers are in a huddle at the moment,&quot; the spokesman said. &quot;Litigation is, if nothing else, a slow process.&quot; However, a decision might be taken within a month, he said.</p>
<p>Amstrad, whose shares bucked a weak market trend and rose 2.5p to 286p, is also taking action against Western Digital Corp -- again for allegedly faulty disk drives. A hearing is set for later this year in California.</p>
<p>Amstrad, whose reputation under outspoken founder and chairman Alan Sugar has taken a roller coaster ride since the group reported its first losses in the early 1990s, announced a break-up plan earlier this month which will wipe the name from the stock market.</p>
<p>It will be replaced by a company called Viglen Technology. The Amstrad name will remain only as a Viglen subsidiary. ($ = 0.594 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302003">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I3302019">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
