<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714263" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Conn. may get $3.6 bln in tobacco case - report.</title>
<headline>Conn. may get $3.6 bln in tobacco case - report.</headline>
<dateline>HARTFORD, Conn. 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Connecticut would receive about $129 million this year -- and a total of $3.6 billion over 25 years -- under a proposed tobacco settlement being considered by Congress, the state's legal chief said in a newspaper interview published Tuesday.</p>
<p>Attorney General Richard Blumenthal told the Hartford Courant that half the money received by the state would have to be spent on health insurance for uninsured children.</p>
<p>This was in keeping with an agreement negotiated between tobacco companies and attorneys general for 40 states, Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>The other half of the settlement, or nearly $65 million in the first year, could be used however the state saw fit -- including tax cuts, Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>The landmark agreement rerquires tobacco firms to pay the states some $368 billion over 25 years to offset the effects of smoking. The agreement also puts unprecedented government limits on the way cigarettes are advertised and sold.</p>
<p>The agreement requires Congressional approval, which is not a certainty, as well as President Bill Clinton's signature.</p>
<p>Blumenthal predicted that the agreement would be adopted in some form.</p>
<p>Blumenthal, a Democrat, was one of five attorneys general who led negotiations that resulted in the June 20 settlement.</p>
<p>He said it was likely that Connecticut would receive about 1.8 percent of the total payments made by tobacco companies to the 50 states. This translates to an upfront payment of $129.2 million as soon as Congress gives the go-ahead, and annual payments starting at $73.9 million thereafter, Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>The annual payment to Connecticut would peak at $147.7 million in 2003, he said.</p>
<p>The windfall due Connecticut is greater than a ballyhooed settlement reached last week by Mississippi, but it comes with a catch, Blumenthal said. It is contingent on approval by the president and Congress of a national settlement.</p>
<p>If there is no national settlement, &quot;Connecticut would be in much the same position (as Mississippi) in negotiating its own figure with the tobacco companies directly,&quot; Blumenthal said.</p>
<p>((--Hartford bureau, (860) 727-0224))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HARTFORD, Conn."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
