<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714347" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Younger Kennedys admit alcohol problem - magazine.</title>
<headline>Younger Kennedys admit alcohol problem - magazine.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-07</dateline>
<text>
<p>A member of the Kennedy family said in an interview published on Monday it was easier for the young generation of the Kennedys to &quot;get an Alcoholics Anonymous (A.A.) meeting together than a touch-football team.&quot;</p>
<p>In an interview with Vanity Fair as part of an article on the troubles afflicting some of the children of the late Sen. Robert Kennedy, 34-year-old son Christopher said his siblings were well aware of the moral ramifications of their actions and that alcohol definitely played a role.</p>
<p>Christopher Kennedy, whose brother Michael has been accused in press reports of having an affair with his children's teenage babysitter, was quoted as saying: &quot;No one has hidden behind alcoholism as an excuse for inappropriate behaviour.</p>
<p>&quot;But all of us clearly understand the link. And in cases where alcohol contributed to inappropriate behaviour -- in every case -- these people don't drink anymore.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that least eight or nine members of his immediate family of 28 siblings and cousins or their spouses attend daily A.A. meetings.</p>
<p>&quot;And clearly a number of them have spent time in rehab clinics around the country. And there's a fair number who've sought conclusive advice from doctors and pyschiatrists,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>He added: &quot;The combination of those is an almost unparalleled examination into the forces that affect our lives, a much more serious one than you could imagine. It's done individually, it's done as a group and it's almost ... endless.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that at the family compound in Hyannis Port, &quot;It's easier to get an A.A. meeting together than a touch-football game now.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-07"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
