<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714361" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Chirac says NATO won't survive without new balance.</title>
<headline>Chirac says NATO won't survive without new balance.</headline>
<byline>Paul Taylor</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac, in a clear warning to the United States, told NATO leaders on Tuesday their alliance would not survive if the transatlantic balance of power did not change in Europe's favour.</p>
<p>Spokeswoman Catherine Colonna quoted Chirac as telling a closed-door NATO summit: &quot;Since the reasons behind the creation of the alliance have largely disappeared, our alliance would not durably survive with an unbalanced Euro-American relationship, both in the sharing of power in the military structure and in the political decision-making process.&quot;</p>
<p>The French leader expressed frustration that there had not been more progress in reforming NATO's structures, with clearer political control over military activities and a major role for a European defence identity within the command structure.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called on Monday for new negotiations between NATO and France with the aim of bringing Paris back into the integrated command by the end of the year.</p>
<p>But he again rejected Chirac's key demand that Washington hand over NATO's Naples-based southern command, which controls the Mediterranean and hence access to the Balkans and the Middle East, to a European.</p>
<p>Clinton said that while Washington wanted more commands to go to the Europeans, he would not yield on AFSOUTH, since it controlled the U.S. Sixth Fleet, one of Washington's most important military assets abroad.</p>
<p>Diplomats quoted him as telling the summit that the United States wanted France, which quit NATO's military wing in 1966, to have a full place in the integrated structure but the new command arrangements had to make military sense.</p>
<p>Chirac told the summit that Paris would decide whether or not to return to the allied command depending on the degree of what the French call &quot;Europeanisation&quot;.</p>
<p>His remarks appeared to be an attempt to raise pressure on Washington without slamming the door to a compromise. While Germany has backed France on the southern command issue, most European allies have declined to support Chirac's campaign.</p>
<p>The Greeks and Turks are happy to have an American admiral helping arbitrate their frequent disputes. Neither the Italians nor the Spanish would relish coming under French command.</p>
<p>Chirac said a new partnership between Americans and Europeans was necessary to preserve the alliance's vital transatlantic security link.</p>
<p>&quot;To give it full meaning, we will have to achieve a better sharing of responsibilities within the Alliance,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Referring to his 1995 decision to move France back towards the military wing of NATO, Chirac said: &quot;I said it 18 months ago and I will say it again today: France will evaluate the results achieved in this direction when the time comes.</p>
<p>&quot;It will decide then what conclusions to draw for its relationship with NATO.&quot;</p>
<p>The French authorities said last week that their conditions for rejoining the integrated command had not yet been met but that France remained available for further negotiations.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen had appeared to slam the door on further talks last month when he said that following the election of a Socialist-led government in France more hostile to NATO, the negotiations were over.</p>
<p>President Charles de Gaulle withdrew from the military structure and ordered NATO headquarters out of France in 1966, protesting against U.S. domination of the alliance.</p>
<p>Chirac launched the rapprochement shortly after he was elected, arguing that France would never persuade the Europeans to establish their own defence outside NATO, as his predecessor, Francois Mitterrand, had tried to do.</p>
<p>But his room for manoeuvre was seriously restricted by the election of a left-wing government last month including anti-NATO Communists, anti-nuclear Greens and left-wing Socialists.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
