<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714344" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE - Foodborne diseases on rise in U.S..</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Foodborne diseases on rise in U.S..</headline>
<byline>Suzanne Rostler</byline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>While the United States is believed to have the world's most stringent laws when it comes to food safety, more Americans than ever before are suffering from foodborne diseases, health experts say.</p>
<p>Salmonella, E. coli and cyclospora are just some of the pathogens that have turned up recently in the U.S. food supply, causing everything from mild stomach cramps to chronic liver disease, paralysis and even death. The incidents have called attention to a rise in the number and severity of food-related illnesses over the past 20 years, prompting new federal food safety initiatives designed to halt the surge.</p>
<p>&quot;Food poisoning is not just a bellyache anymore,&quot; Caroline Smith DeWaal, director of food safety with the private consumer health group Centres for Science in the Public Interest (CSPI) said. &quot;Bacteria and pathogens are tougher and stronger and they are surviving efforts to kill them.&quot;</p>
<p>Some scientists deny that the U.S. food supply has become more contaminated, or that enforcement is lax. Rather, better laboratory techniques for identifying foodborne diseases have fostered the illusion that the number is on the rise.</p>
<p>&quot;If doctors know cyclospora is out there they will ask for the test,&quot; Marta Ackers, a medical epidemiologist with the Centres for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), said. &quot;It is always hard to tell if we are seeing more of something or if surveillance has increased.&quot;</p>
<p>Better detection may be part of the story but increased food imports, more frequent restaurant dining and greater use of animal antibiotics are also to blame. Scientists say several of the bacteria that infect farm animals have become resistant to certain antibiotics. When these organisms infect humans, they are harder to fight because of their acquired resistance.</p>
<p>INFECTIONS MAY NOT RESPOND TO ANTIBIOTICS</p>
<p>&quot;An infection a physican would have treated with an antibiotic in the past may not respond today,&quot; Joseph Madden, a microbiologist with the Food and Drug Administration, said.</p>
<p>Other health experts blame the trend on a steady increase in restaurant dining, exposing more Americans to contaminated food more often. CSPI said 46 percent of all food dollars were spent in restaurants in 1993, up from 27 percent in 1960.</p>
<p>&quot;Consumers are eating out more than ever before and they are relying on restaurants to control the safety of their food,&quot; Smith DeWaal said.</p>
<p>That is precisely what worries health experts, who charge that inspection and enforcement standards are lax.</p>
<p>While the FDA issues safety recommendations every two years addressing everything from cooking temperatures to hand washing, it is the state, county or city health department that decides which regulations to adopt and how to enforce them. The result can be a lack of uniformity that leaves consumers in some areas vulnerable to bacteria and disease.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very random,&quot; said CSPI's Elizabeth Dahl, who led a national survey last year on food safety in restaurants. &quot;(Food safety) depends on what county, city or state you happen to live in, how well the local department is funded, and which standards it chooses to enforce.&quot;</p>
<p>The FDA's Madden agreed that limited resources can mean fewer restaurant inspections but he said most health departments adopt the entire code or the major portions.</p>
<p>STANDARDS STILL NOT ENFORCED</p>
<p>Still, three years after the widely publicised deaths of three children from eating hamburgers contaminated by E. coli at a national restaurant chain, a third of health departments surveyed did not set a minimum cooking standard for ground beef. Only only 31 percent enforced the recommended cooking temperature for pork, while 89 percent did not follow the FDA's advice on refrigerator temperatures.</p>
<p>&quot;The enforcement of basic food safety requirements should not be optional,&quot; Smith DeWaal said. &quot;Consumers are paying for lax enforcement with unacceptably high numbers of foodborne illnesses.&quot;</p>
<p>The private Council for Agricultural Science and Technology says as many as 33 million foodborne illnesses occur each year and up to 9,000 people die as a result.</p>
<p>Medical and productivity costs associated with foodborne diseases range from $6.5 billion to $35 billion a year, Tanya Roberts, an economist with the U.S Department of Agriculture, said. &quot;We are no longer going to the pathogens, the pathogens are coming to us,&quot; she said, adding that food imports allow contaminants to spread swiftly from one country to another.</p>
<p>Just one infected food handler could transmit bacteria to thousands of people across the globe, as was seen this year when 236 people in the United States contracted hepatitis A and thousands of others became sick after eating contaminated strawberries from Mexico.</p>
<p>Economic and human costs associated with food-related illnesses have spotlighted the need for more effective safety procedures on all fronts. In January, President Bill Clinton asked Congress to earmark $43 million towards a national food safety initiative that would reinforce existing food safety programmes and allow health experts to identify outbreaks early.</p>
<p>About $23 million will be used to upgrade FDA inspection, research and risk assessment facilities for seafood. The USDA will use $8.5 million for similar meat and poultry programmes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I42000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
