<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714399" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Fire hits Paris law courts near historic church.</title>
<headline>Fire hits Paris law courts near historic church.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A fire broke out on Tuesday in the Paris law courts, threatening the historic Sainte Chapelle, a 13th century church which stands in a courtyard of the courts building, guards said.</p>
<p>The fire broke out in a part of the building's basement in an area used to store court documents, they said.</p>
<p>The cause was not immediately known.</p>
<p>Smoke billowed over the area and the courtyard where the Sainte Chapelle stands was ordered evacuated by police, they said.</p>
<p>The law courts are located on the Cite island in the centre of the River Seine in the heart of the French capital.</p>
<p>The Sainte Chapelle, a Gothic architectural masterpiece and major Paris tourist attraction, was built by the French king Saint Louis in 1245 to house relics he gathered during the Crusades. Construction took three years.</p>
<p>The church's upper chapel has towering stained glass windows which were removed from the church in pieces and hidden during the Nazi occupation years in World War Two.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
