<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714484" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO leaders go to lunch without expansion deal.</title>
<headline>NATO leaders go to lunch without expansion deal.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO leaders broke for lunch at their enlargement summit on Tuesday without an agreement on the scale and pace of the Western alliance's expansion into former communist eastern Europe, officials said.</p>
<p>Spanish Foreign Minister Abel Matutes said the 16 leaders had made progress towards a consensus but there was no decision yet. The United States, backed by five other allies, insisted that only three central European states -- Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary -- be in the first wave of enlargement.  </p>
<p>Seven other allies, led by France and Italy, supported adding Romania and Slovenia to the first wave.</p>
<p>After failing to reach a consensus in a restricted session, the leaders sent their foreign ministers to meet separately to draft assurances of a second wave of enlargement if only three were admitted before 1999, the officials said.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton, asked during a photo session how the morning's talks had gone, smiled and said: &quot;So far so good.&quot;</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac had earlier told the closed session that NATO would undermine its credibility and breach its own cohesion if it left out two countries that met the criteria the alliance had set.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
