<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714458" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VATICAN: Vatican establishes diplomatic links with Angola.</title>
<headline>Vatican establishes diplomatic links with Angola.</headline>
<dateline>VATICAN CITY 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Vatican said on Tuesday it was opening diplomatic links with Angola in recognition of efforts by the MPLA of President Jose Eduardo Dos Santos and former rebel group UNITA to bury 20 years of bitter civil war.</p>
<p>The Vatican announced the move after Pope John Paul held a short private audience with Dos Santos, who is visiting Italy.</p>
<p>&quot;The Holy See's decision to grant the request of the Angolan government to establish diplomatic relations represents a just reward to the parties, for so long adversaries, which patiently and at high cost have removed the many obstacles on the road to peace,&quot; the Vatican said in its daily bulletin.</p>
<p>The Vatican said its decision to appoint a Papal Nuncio to the former Portuguese colony followed the swearing-in of a government of national unity in April &quot;which has enabled the country to turn a new page in its history&quot;.</p>
<p>Dos Santos, who is on a four-day official visit to Italy, has faced increasing foreign pressure recently to meet Jonas Savimbi, leader of the once-powerful rebel movement UNITA, to discuss ongoing fighting in Angola's diamond-rich northeast.</p>
<p>The government launched an offensive in northeastern Angola in May that analysts say is a pretext for an assault on UNITA.</p>
<p>While both sides are members of the government of national unity, UNITA has refused to give up its 80 percent stake in Angola's diamond wealth which analysts say earns it an annual income of up to $800 million.</p>
<p>Observers and diplomats fear heavy fighting between the parties threatens a ceasefire signed in 1994. Dos Santos has said the raid into the northeast was against armed Hutu and Rwandan refugees in UNITA-held areas.</p>
<p>Dos Santos spent 15 minutes with the Pontiff at the Vatican but no details of their conversation were released.</p>
<p>The Vatican has had a delegation in Angola since independence in 1975. The Pope visited in 1992. The southern African country has more than 5.5 million Roman Catholics and the Church is active in health and education.</p>
<p>Dos Santos also met President Oscar Luigi Scalfaro and was due to meet business leaders later on Tuesday and parliamentary leaders and Rome's mayor on Wednesday. He was set to hold talks with Prime Minister Romano Prodi before flying home on Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ANGOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VATICAN CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VATICAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
