<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714428" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>PORTUGAL: Portugal copper mine official pessimistic on talks.</title>
<headline>Portugal copper mine official pessimistic on talks.</headline>
<dateline>LISBON 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A spokesman for the Neves Corvo copper mine in southern Portugal said that he was pessimistic over the outcome of talks between striking miners and company officials on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;I fear that they are going to end in failure,&quot; personnel director Raul Araujo told Reuters.  </p>
<p>Araujo said that as far as the company was concerned the talks in nearby Beja, some 250 km south of Lisbon, were aimed purely at ending the picketing of the mine, which he said was preventing employees who disagreed with the stoppage getting to work.</p>
<p>But he said the unions appeared to think that they were about the company's plans to introduce a seven-day shift, the issue behind the stoppage, which began on Monday. The mine, which is managed by state-owned Somincor, says it needs a system of permanent operation to remain competitive.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a dialogue of the deaf,&quot; Araujo said. &quot;In two hours (of discussions), there has been no progress.&quot; If the talks failed, then the company would ask police to ensure that workers who wished to return to work were allowed to do so. If the picketing were stopped, then the strike would be over in two or three days, he said.</p>
<p>Araujo confirmed that output at the 107,000-tonne per year mine was completely halted by the stoppage, with pickets allowing only routine maintenance and security work to be carried out.</p>
<p>--Lisbon bureau 3511-3150035</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I21000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22460">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LISBON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PORTUGAL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
