<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714409" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: North Korea reports 800,000 infants malnourished.</title>
<headline>North Korea reports 800,000 infants malnourished.</headline>
<byline>Stephanie Nebehay</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Some 800,000 children under five in North Korea are malnourished -- 37 percent of that age group -- the U.N. Children's Fund (UNICEF) said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Estimates from the Ministry of Public Health in Pyongyang indicate 10 percent of the 800,000 are severely malnourished, according to the United Nations agency.</p>
<p>Another 65 percent, have a &quot;moderate&quot; level of malnutrition while the rest are in the &quot;intermediate&quot; category.</p>
<p>Given the worsening famine in North Korea UNICEF expects to more than double its appeal of $4.7 million last April to fund food and medical supplies, according to a spokesman.</p>
<p>UNICEF has begun distributing high-energy milk and medical kits which it flew in on July 1. It expected to bring in another plane load next week.</p>
<p>Stalinist North Korea, which has a population of 23 million, was hit by widespread flooding in 1995 and 1996 which devastated cereal crops.</p>
<p>The spokesman said a survey which UNICEF is due to carry out with the World Food Programme will allow it to determine the level of malnutrition across the country.</p>
<p>The survey, due to start by the end of July, is to be completed in six weeks.</p>
<p>Catherine Bertini, executive director of the Rome-based WFP, is due to give a news conference in Geneva on Wednesday on the situation in North Korea.</p>
<p>WFP, the U.N. agency which plans emergency food aid distribution, cautioned after a visit last month that North Korea was within months of running out of food supplies.</p>
<p>But Ole Gronning, the Pyongyang representative of the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies, said last month that government food stocks throughout the country were virtually empty.</p>
<p>More than five million North Koreans are near starvation and could die in coming months unless food arrives, he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
