<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714426" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO summit poised to admit three new members.</title>
<headline>NATO summit poised to admit three new members.</headline>
<byline>Matt Spetalnick</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>A NATO summit was poised on Tuesday to invite Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic to join the alliance while reassuring Romania, Slovenia and the Baltic states that they would be considered in future expansion rounds.</p>
<p>Laying the groundwork for the biggest enlargement in NATO's 48-year history, foreign ministers reached a compromise on promises of an &quot;open door&quot; to be given to post-communist nations that were not admitted in the first wave, delegates said.</p>
<p>The draft agreement was to be presented on Tuesday for final endorsement by NATO leaders, who had clashed in the first day of their historic summit over how far and how fast to go in embracing new members from the former East Bloc.</p>
<p>The United States, backed by Britain, had made clear that it would only accept Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic in the first round, but France led a European charge calling for Romania and Slovenia to be included.</p>
<p>Under the compromise, NATO would identify southeastern Europe and the Baltics as areas essential to alliance interests, without setting any date for admitting those countries.</p>
<p>Russia has warned that it would consider membership for the Baltics as a threat to its security.</p>
<p>&quot;With regard to the aspiring members, we recognise with great interest and take into account the positive developments towards democracy and the rule of law in a number of southeastern European countries, especially Romania and Slovenia,&quot; the draft statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Atlantic community recognises its strategic stake in building greater stability, security and regional cooperation in the countries of southeastern Europe and promoting their increasing interests in the Euro-Atlantic community,&quot; the proposed document said.</p>
<p>&quot;Progress towards these objectives will be important for our overall goal of a free, prosperous and undivided Europe in peace and will be taken into account in our future accession process.&quot;</p>
<p>In the most contentious NATO summit in years, U.S. President Bill Clinton came under fire from some European allies incensed at his attempt to unilaterally dictate that the first round of expansion be restricted to the three favoured countries.</p>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac, joined by six other leaders, pressed hard for a broader enlargement that would include Romania and Slovenia.</p>
<p>&quot;Let us not take the risk of breaching the allies' cohesion or undermining the credibility of the alliance by excluding today two countries which meet the criteria which we ourselves set,&quot; he said bluntly.</p>
<p>Italian Prime Minister Romano Prodi also expressed strong support for Slovenia, and Greek Prime Minister Costas Simitis made a strong plea for Bulgaria, diplomatic sources said.</p>
<p>But Clinton, backed by British Prime Minister Tony Blair and four other leaders, stuck to his resolve that only three countries were politically, militarily and economically ready to join the world's most powerful defence alliance.</p>
<p>After hours of sometimes heated debate, the heads of NATO's 16 member-nations were close to a consensus on limiting the first wave of newcomers to the three favourites.</p>
<p>NATO, formed nearly five decades ago as a bulwark against Soviet communism, was opening a new era in alliance history by accepting former foes from the now-defunct Warsaw Pact.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's meeting is the defining moment for NATO,&quot; alliance Secretary-General Javier Solana declared as he inaugurated the two-day summit at Madrid's Municipal Congress Centre.</p>
<p>Following weeks of open bickering, Clinton and his European opponents on the expansion issue finally sat down to thrash out their differences face to face.</p>
<p>The debate gave European allies a chance to vent their resentment over what they see as American heavy-handedness not only in its NATO dealings but in other transatlantic matters.</p>
<p>Ever since the Group of Seven summit last month in Denver, European leaders have made no secret of their dismay over what they describe as the United States' new sense of arrogance in its role as the world's sole remaining superpower.</p>
<p>Chirac seized the opportunity on Tuesday to warn Clinton that NATO would not survive if the balance of power between Americans and Europeans was not shifted in favour of Europe, the French president's spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>Chirac expressed frustration that there had not been more progress in reforming NATO's structures, with a real political control over military activities and a real place for a European defence identity in the command structure.</p>
<p>Clinton called on Monday for new negotiations between NATO and France with the aim of bringing Paris into the integrated command, which it pulled out of in 1966.</p>
<p>Russian President Boris Yeltsin, who had bitterly opposed NATO's expansion but admitted he was powerless to stop it, chose not to attend the summit. His signing of a landmark Russia-NATO cooperation treaty in May paved the way for enlargement while giving Moscow a voice -- but not a veto -- in alliance affairs.</p>
<p>Invitations to even three ex-communist states would be the biggest expansion in NATO history. Only once, in 1952, was more than than one new country admitted at once -- Greece and Turkey.</p>
<p>Clinton has predicted he will face a challenge at home to win support for NATO expansion, which has to be approved by two-thirds of the U.S. Senate.</p>
<p>Some critics contend that enlargement could revive Cold War tensions by isolating Russia and by breeding envy among the nations excluded from the alliance.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BALTST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
