<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714413" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Chirac objection delays NATO expansion statement.</title>
<headline>Chirac objection delays NATO expansion statement.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac held up the planned announcement of NATO's decision to admit three former communist east European states on Tuesday to demand stronger assurances for those countries left out, delegates said.</p>
<p>They said Chirac had insisted that NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana redraft a statement agreed in principle by the 16 foreign ministers naming Romania and Slovenia as deserving candidates for future enlargement and promising to review the process in 1999.  </p>
<p>The leaders held their second restricted session of the day to try to meet France's objections after a scene captured by pool television cameras outside the summit chamber in which Chirac angrily pointed his finger at Solana and spoke heatedly.</p>
<p>At stake is the degree of commitment to launch a second wave of NATO enlargement in 1999. The United States, facing strong Congressional scepticism at home, does not want to be pinned down to a date for admitting further candidates.</p>
<p>The text drafted by foreign ministers named southeastern Europe and the Baltic region as areas of special interest to NATO and recognised positive developments towards democracy and the rule of law, notably in Romania and Slovenia.</p>
<p>It did not identify the three Baltic republics by name as potential members, apparently in deference to adamant Russian opposition to any ex-Soviet countries joining NATO.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ROM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
