<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714477" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRIA: East European leaders to meet on integration.</title>
<headline>East European leaders to meet on integration.</headline>
<byline>Nigel Stephenson</byline>
<dateline>VIENNA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Central and East European leaders, both winners and losers at this week's NATO summit, gather in Salzburg on Wednesday to discuss prospects for further European integration.</p>
<p>Heads of state and government, ministers, central bankers and top company officials from central Europe and Russia meet for the second Central and Eastern European Economic Summit in the alpine city for talks on priorities for the region.</p>
<p>The three-day meeting follows the NATO Madrid summit, at which former Communist countries were to be invited to join, and last month's European Union summit in Amsterdam which paved the way for enlargement of the bloc.</p>
<p>Key themes in Salzburg will include regional security after Madrid and the implications for economic ties between central Europe and the Commonwealth of Independent States.</p>
<p>Front-runners to become the first new members of both NATO and the EU are the Czech Republic, Poland and Hungary.</p>
<p>&quot;We are going to use this conference as the first step in the negotiations to join the EU,&quot; said Hungarian Industry, Trade and Tourism Minister Szabolcs Fazakas.</p>
<p>&quot;This will be the first international conference at which Hungary will be invited as a real partner for NATO and even for the EU,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>East European leaders have been keen to ensure that integration of some states with Western organisations does not lead to a new division between &quot;haves&quot; and &quot;have nots&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;All Eastern European leaders have stressed that, because they have had very bad experiences of a divided Europe,&quot; said Prague-based political analyst Jiri Pehe.</p>
<p>Czech President Vaclav Havel told Reuters last week that NATO had to be open to all democracies in the region.</p>
<p>&quot;The (NATO) summit should give everyone hope and assurance and explain in understandable terms why it is not possible to take in all the aspiring nations... It should also articulate the requirements for membership of all aspiring nations,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Some economists have said that an invitation to join NATO will also be seen as an incentive to further Western investment, at the expense of countries left out of the first wave of enlargement.</p>
<p>&quot;Being admitted to NATO means not only more security but more political stability...It is a natural invitation to more investment in these countries,&quot; said Pehe.</p>
<p>The leaders, and some top Western politicians, will devote a session on Thursday to ways to further trade and economic development and to create a regional market.</p>
<p>For states missing out on NATO, and not likely to make the first cut of new EU members, Salzburg is an opportunity to demonstrate they are still an attractive investment.</p>
<p>&quot;At the moment it is important to show Bulgaria's attractive face for investors at the discussions in Salzburg,&quot; Bulgarian Deputy Prime Minister Alexander Bozhkov told Reuters.</p>
<p>Central bankers from several states, including Russia and Ukraine, are due to take part in a discussion on the implications of the planned introduction of the euro.</p>
<p>&quot;The main issue is our relations with the Europen Union after they introduce the euro. We do not quite understand all possible consequences for us,&quot; Russian central bank spokesman Alexei Sitnin said.</p>
<p>Much of the discussion will be behind closed doors. The leaders will be holding closed talks on topics including financing privatisation, social welfare reform and fighting crime and corruption.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUST">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="VIENNA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
