<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714414" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Sacking E.German ex-communists was illegal -court.</title>
<headline>Sacking E.German ex-communists was illegal -court.</headline>
<dateline>KARLSRUHE, Germany 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's highest court ruled on Tuesday that civil servants should not have been sacked because they had been former East German communist party functionaries or had spied for the Stasi intelligence agency.</p>
<p>The Federal Constitutional Court said public employers had a duty to look at individual cases, despite laws introduced after German unification allowing employees to be dismissed if they were deemed unsuitable because of their communist pasts.</p>
<p>Passing judgment on eight cases brought by East German teachers and public administration officials who said they had been wrongfully dismissed, the court said five sackings had violated the constitution but three had been legal.</p>
<p>The judges rejected the highest-profile complaint, made by Heinrich Fink, a former rector of East Berlin's Humboldt University. It said his work for the Stasi disqualified him from running the university in a democratic united Germany.</p>
<p>&quot;The reputation of a university depends not least on the reputation its professors enjoy among students, colleagues and in public,&quot; the court said. &quot;Activity for the Ministry for State Security (Stasi) leads to a substantial loss of image.&quot;</p>
<p>Eva Maria Stange, leader of the Union for Education and Science, said she was satisfied with the judgment.</p>
<p>She admitted the appeals deadline for the vast majority of the 10,000 people dismissed under the special laws had lapsed but said she hoped the authorities would take it upon themselves to review their decisions and give people dismissed for political reasons a second chance.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="KARLSRUHE, Germany"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
