<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714448" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO hopefuls share history of foreign domination.</title>
<headline>NATO hopefuls share history of foreign domination.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The three favourites for NATO membership, Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic, have in common a history of domination by more powerful neighbours and hope to find abiding security under the alliance umbrella.</p>
<p>All three broke free from Russian domination in 1991 with the collapse of the Soviet Union and its Warsaw Pact alliance, and have embraced democracy and the free market.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton says that of the 12 applicants, these are the only ones ready politically, militarily and economically to join the 16-member alliance.</p>
<p>Article V of NATO's 1949 founding treaty effectively commits each country to consider an attack on one of them as an attack on all of them, essentially placing the Europeans under the cover of the American nuclear shield.</p>
<p>Here are profiles of the three countries: POLAND</p>
<p>Population 38 million. Armed Forces 230,000. Expected GDP growth in 1997 six percent.</p>
<p>Poland is the largest and most powerful of the three.</p>
<p>A great regional power in the 16th and 17th centuries, it was partitioned by its powerful neighbours in the 18th century and vanished from the map as a state. Despite bloody uprisings, it remained under Prussian, Russian and Austrian occupation until the end of World War One.</p>
<p>Poland was invaded by Nazi Germany and the Soviet Union in 1939. Most of its 3.5 million Jews were murdered, much of its eastern population deported, and the whole country moved westwards. It remained under Soviet domination with a communist system until 1991.</p>
<p>Independent trade union leader Lech Walesa became the first democratically-elected President in 1990 and painful reforms were launched to undo economic chaos left by the communist era.</p>
<p>In September 1993 the former communists, rapidly changed into social democrats, won parliamentary elections and remain in power along with a Peasant party. Walesa, though supported by the powerful Roman Catholic Church, lost presidential elections in 1995 to ex-communist Aleksander Kwasniewski.</p>
<p>The ex-communists have broadly continued market reforms and an all-out drive to join both the European Union and NATO.</p>
<p>HUNGARY</p>
<p>Population 10 million. Armed forces 60,000. Expected GDP growth in 1997 at least 2.5 percent.</p>
<p>Hungary has been dominated by foreign powers for most of the last five centuries. It was occupied for 150 years by the Turks and was then part of the Austrian Hapsburg Empire for almost three centuries.</p>
<p>Hungary lost two-thirds of its territory in the Versailles Treaties of 1919, but retained independence for 20 years until World War Two when it sided with Germany. Under the Yalta agreement it came into the Soviet bloc. The Kremlin crushed an anti-Stalinist uprising in 1956 and 50,000 Soviet troops were stationed there until 1991.</p>
<p>The current government, elected in 1994, is a coalition of Socialists, led by former communist Gyula Horn, and the liberal Free Democrats who have 18 percent.</p>
<p>It introduced tough austerity measures in 1995 to rein in soaring current account and budget deficits, but has regained popularity as the policy began to bear fruit in raising real wages and cutting inflation.</p>
<p>CZECH REPUBLIC</p>
<p>Population 10 million. Armed Forces 66,000. GDP growth in 1996 4.4 percent.</p>
<p>The Czech lands of Bohemia and Moravia have lived under domination for much of the millenium and most of this century. Four centuries of rule by the Habsburg Austrian empire came to an end after World War One with the foundation of the Czechoslovak Republic.</p>
<p>The Nazis marched in in 1939, ending two decades of prosperity and split off Slovakia into a puppet state. The Nazis were replaced by Soviet troops, who reunited Czechoslovakia and imposed Kremlin rule for more than four decades.</p>
<p>Reformist communists introduced &quot;Socialism with a Human Face&quot; in 1968, but the &quot;Prague Spring&quot; was crushed by Moscow.</p>
<p>Moravia and Bohemia agreed a peaceful split with Slovakia in 1993 and became the Czech Republic. Vaclav Havel, a former dissident, became president and a centre-right government was elected.</p>
<p>The Czechs are the only people in the region not to have voted reformed communists or socialists back into office, but economic difficulties and financial crime have helped sap the ruling three-party coalition's popularity. The 200-seat parliament is split 100-100.</p>
<p>The opposition Socialists support Czech membership of NATO but are demanding a referendum.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
