<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714531" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: France's Chirac demands fairer sharing in NATO.</title>
<headline>France's Chirac demands fairer sharing in NATO.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>French President Jacques Chirac on Tuesday demanded a fairer sharing of responsibility in NATO and said Paris would decide whether or not to return to the allied military command structure depending on the outcome.</p>
<p>Speaking to a closed-door first session of a NATO summit in Madrid, Chirac said according to French officials that a new partnership between Americans and Europeans was necessary to preserve the alliance's vital transatlantic security link.</p>
<p>&quot;To give it full meaning, we will have to achieve a better sharing of responsibilities within the Alliance,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Referring to his 1995 initiative to launch a rapprochement between France and the military wing of NATO which it quit in 1966, Chirac said: &quot;I said it 18 months ago and I will say it again today: France will evaluate the results achieved in this direction when the time comes.</p>
<p>&quot;It will decide then what conclusions to draw for its relationship with NATO.&quot;</p>
<p>The United States has rejected French demands that it hand over NATO's key southern command, which controls the Mediterranean, to a European as part of the &quot;rebalancing&quot; of the Western alliance.</p>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton called for fresh negotiations between NATO and France on Tuesday and said he hoped both Paris and Spain would be integrated into the military command by the end of this year.</p>
<p>But he offered no concession in substance, saying that while Washington wanted more commands to go to the Europeans, he would not yield on AFSOUTH, since it controlled the U.S. Sixth Fleet, one of Washington's most important military assets abroad.</p>
<p>The French authorities said last week that their conditions for rejoining the integrated command had not yet been met but that France remained available for further negotiations.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen had appeared to slam the door on further talks last month when he said that following the election of a Socialist-led government in France more hostile to NATO, the negotiations were over.</p>
<p>President Charles de Gaulle withdrew from the military structure and ordered NATO headquarters out of France in 1966, protesting against U.S. domination of the alliance.</p>
<p>Chirac launched the rapprochement shortly after he was elected, arguing that France would never persuade the Europeans to establish their own defence outside NATO, as his predecessor, Francois Mitterrand, had tried to do.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
