<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714503" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: NATO wrestles with Balkan crises.</title>
<headline>NATO wrestles with Balkan crises.</headline>
<byline>Jonathan Clayton</byline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO leaders, worried about the worsening situation in Bosnia, came under pressure on Tuesday to adopt a longer-term strategy for dealing with Europe's most turbulent region -- the Balkans.</p>
<p>NATO officials said NATO's 16 heads of government, meeting to expand the alliance into eastern and central Europe, would also try to agree measures aimed at stabilising south-east Europe.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a great deal of concern and a feeling we cannot stay silent,&quot; said one official.</p>
<p>Analysts say NATO states, arguing that the alliance's eastwards expansion into Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic, will extend stability in Europe, do not want to be accused of failing to have any policy for the most unstable area.</p>
<p>Albania is in turmoil amid constant fears unrest could spread to the Serb province of Kosovo where ethnic Albanians heavily outnumber Serb nationalists.</p>
<p>A fragile peace now holds in Bosnia, but the flaring up of a bitter dispute between Bosnian Serb hardliners and their president, Biljana Plavsic, was giving most cause for concern.</p>
<p>NATO countries lead a 35,000-strong peace force, which brought an end to more than three years of bitter conflict in the country which tens of thousands of people were killed.</p>
<p>But they have been criticised for failing to take action to detain indicted war criminal and ex-president Radovan Karadzic, at the centre of the stand-off with Plavsic.</p>
<p>NATO officials said alliance Secretary-General Javier Solana held urgent telephone talks with Carlos Westendorp, a fellow Spaniard and the international High Representative to Bosnia, on Tuesday morning.</p>
<p>Opponents of Plavsic have scoffed at international warnings that they were flouting the law by refusing to accept a presidential decision to dissolve parliament, threatening the prospect of two rival governments in the Bosnian Serb Republic.</p>
<p>The United States and European governments say Plavsic acted in line with the constitution last week when she dissolved the Bosnian Serb assembly and called new elections for September 1.</p>
<p>The conflict has fuelled speculation that major powers are preparing to arrest Karadzic, who has refused to face charges before the U.N. war crimes tribunal in the Hague -- a nettle they have so far failed to grasp for fear of reprisals.</p>
<p>&quot;Now the issue is more 'Can they afford not to act?',&quot; one official said, adding that the United States and its European allies were determined to pull out their forces as planned next summer.</p>
<p>&quot;Time is running out to make the (Dayton) peace accords work and with Karadzic there they will not. That is the dilemma,&quot; the official said.</p>
<p>U.S. Defence Secretary William Cohen and a senior NATO official refused on Monday to rule out using allied troops to capture indicted war criminals in Bosnia, including Karadzic.</p>
<p>&quot;Nothing has been ruled in or ruled out,&quot; Cohen told reporters. &quot;There has been no decision made. It has been the position of the (U.S.) administration that we will do whatever we can to strengthen the War Crimes Tribunal.&quot;</p>
<p>The NATO official, briefing reporters before the summit, said: &quot;There is considerable frustration in the international community at the fact that Mr Karadzic and not only him, the 50- odd other indicted war criminals that have so far escaped justice, have not been taken to the tribunal in The Hague.&quot;</p>
<p>Asked whether NATO leaders might order action to capture the wanted suspects when they discuss Bosnia on Tuesday, the official said: &quot;Nothing is excluded. I think we should simply see what the heads of state and government will decide to do.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
