<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714681" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Extra Canadian flights for BA strike.</title>
<headline>Extra Canadian flights for BA strike.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canada's two international airlines are adding flights to London this week in response to the scheduled 72-hour strike by cabin attendants at British Airways.</p>
<p>Beginning Wednesday, BA has cancelled 20 flights to and from Canada on its own aircraft over the three-day period, representing a removal of 7,000 seats and 400 tonnes of cargo space during one of the year's busiest travel weeks.</p>
<p>BA also code-shares the four daily UK flights of partner Canadian Airlines International. Those flights are not affected.</p>
<p>CAI has roughly 300 passengers a day booked on the cancelled BA flights, says spokesman Jeff Angell.</p>
<p>To accommodate them, and secondarily to handle as many BA passengers as possible, CAI is adding two London round trips - one from Vancouver on Wednesday and one from Toronto on Thursday - on 256-seat DC-10s, he said.</p>
<p>Air Canada is adding a Toronto-London trip each day during the strike, using a B-767 aircraft, said a spokeswoman.</p>
<p>To the extent that the extra flights can handle more cargo and passengers beyond what is already booked on CAI, the airline will take it, but the objective is not to try to replace BA operations, says Barry Rempell, CAI's cargo vice-president.</p>
<p>&quot;The last thing I want to see us doing is getting in the middle of their labour problems,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>BA and CAI do not share cargo capacity, so CAI should have no difficulty accommodating all of its regular cargo customers, he said.</p>
<p>Airline cargo managers don't believe BA World Cargo's Canadian customers will have great difficulty coping with a strike. Even without the additional flights, Air Canada has up to 11 flights a day from London to Canada, more than BA and CAI combined. About half of Air Canada flights for the Wednesday-Friday period this week have available cargo space, according to the airline's Internet cargo space availability listing for July 8-15.</p>
<p>Also, the flights added by CAI and Air Canada more than offset the 60-80 tonnes a day of cargo capacity removed by a BA strike. - Reuters Air Cargo Service Tel+ 44 171 542 7706 Fax +5017 - www.racs.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
