<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714781" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: HK April domestic exports down 1.9 pct.</title>
<headline>HK April domestic exports down 1.9 pct.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The volume of Hong Kong's domestic exports in April fell 1.9 percent year-on-year, while re-exports rose 8.1 percent, the Census and Statistics Department said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Total export volume rose 6.6 percent and import volume grew by 7.1 percent, it said in a statment.</p>
<p>Volume of domestic exports for the first four months of 1997 decreased by 3.3 percent while volume of re-exports leapt 6.2 percent. Total exports rose 4.7 percent and imports grew by 6.6 percent.</p>
<p>Prices of domestic exports were down 1.9 percent in April from a year earlier and re-export prices fell 1.5 percent, import prices also decreased by 2.5 percent.</p>
<p>Prices of domestic exports for the first four months of 1997 were 1.9 percent lower, while those of re-exports down 1.4 percent and import prices decreased by 2.5 percent.</p>
<p>The department said prices are based on unit values which do not take into account changes in the composition or quality of goods traded, except for some selected commodities for which specific price indices are available.</p>
<p>-- Hong Kong Newsroom (852) 2843 6441</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
