<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714720" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Thousands of dinosaur footprints found in Australia.</title>
<headline>Thousands of dinosaur footprints found in Australia.</headline>
<dateline>SYDNEY 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of dinosaur footprints have been discovered on the remote northwest coast of Australia, revealing giant creatures 30 metres (100 feet) tall, a scientist said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;In the setting sun it looks like a fresh dinosaur landscape,&quot; Australian paleontologist Tony Thulborn told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;There are at least a dozen different dinosaur tracks. By world standards it is an extremely rich, exceptionally diverse and very, very important dinosaur track site,&quot; Thulborn said.</p>
<p>The footprints range in size from a few centimetres (inches) in length, left by plant-eating two-legged dinosaurs, to 1.7-metre (five foot-seven inch) footprints, created by a giant four-legged sauropod like a brontosaurus or stegosaurus.</p>
<p>The creatures lived some 115-120 million years ago during the Cretaceous period.</p>
<p>Thulborn, from the University of Queensland, refused to reveal the exact location of what he called a &quot;dinosaur trackway&quot;, fearing vandals and thieves would plunder the scientific treasure. A 130-million-year-old stegosaurus footprint was stolen from the area in October 1996.</p>
<p>Thulborn said his team, which included Italian and Australian scientists, made the discovery in an area near the coastal town of Broome which lies on an 80 km (50 mile) stretch of coast renowned for dinosaur footprints.</p>
<p>He said recent cyclones had unearthed the &quot;dinosaur trackway&quot;, enabling the team to discover some of the smaller dinosaur tracks which are normally destroyed by erosion.</p>
<p>&quot;The sea has uncovered an ancient landscape, a dinosaur landscape with all the hills and hummocks and rises and dips, and it is strewn with dinosaur footprints and the remains of the plants and trees that used to grow there,&quot; Thulborn said.</p>
<p>&quot;What is unique about the site is the abundance of footprints -- they are all over the place, some of them superbly preserved.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SYDNEY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
