<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714844" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesia priest faces trial over fugitives.</title>
<headline>Indonesia priest faces trial over fugitives.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Indonesian Catholic priest could face trial for allegedly sheltering three activists of a banned leftist group after riots in Jakarta in July last year, one of his lawyers said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Romo (Father) Sandyawan may face trial for allegedly sheltering three activists from the People's Democratic Party (PRD), including its chief Budiman Sudjatmiko,&quot; Dwiyanto Prihartono told Reuters.</p>
<p>Prihartono of the Jakarta-based Legal Aid Institute said Sandyawan had been accused of sheltering people wanted by the police. The offence carries a maximum penalty of nine months.</p>
<p>&quot;Sandyawan has said he was only performing his duty as a priest, that is to help frightened people,&quot; Prihartono said.</p>
<p>The priest's elder brother Benny Sumardi, whose house was used to shelter the activists, could also be tried on charges of harbouring fugitives, he said.</p>
<p>The two have not been charged, Prihartono said.</p>
<p>Dossiers on both men were now being processed at the prosecutor's office before being handed to the court.</p>
<p>Sudjatmiko and the two colleagues who were hiding with him were found guilty of subversion in April.</p>
<p>A total of 14 activists from the group had been sentenced to between 18 months and 13 years in jail after being convicted of subversion, with Budiman receiving the stiffest penalty.</p>
<p>The activists were rounded up after the July 27 riots last year, the worst violence in the capital for more than two decades.</p>
<p>The violence erupted after police and a government-backed faction of the minority Indonesian Democratic Party (PDI) raided the party's headquarters and evicted supporters of its ousted leader Megawati Sukarnoputri.</p>
<p>The PRD activists were convicted on the grounds that their small left-wing group did not follow the state ideology Pancasila and they opposed a number of key government policies. The riots received only a cursory mention during their lengthy trials.</p>
<p>Lawyer Prihartono said the priest and his brother had not been detained because the penalty was less than five years.</p>
<p>After the riots, the military issued a &quot;shoot on sight&quot; order and the activists feared for their lives.</p>
<p>The military more recently also blamed the PRD as well as other unnamed &quot;third parties&quot; for sparking widespread rioting, mostly on the main island of Java, during the 27-day campaign prior to this year's May 29 general elections.</p>
<p>No arrests have been made despite the allegations.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
