<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714881" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: PLA garrison draws media fire on HK mission.</title>
<headline>PLA garrison draws media fire on HK mission.</headline>
<byline>James Flannery</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>China's elite military garrison in Hong Kong encountered media criticism on Tuesday after being accused of yet another public relations gaffe.</p>
<p>Hong Kong press commentators attacked the People's Liberation Army (PLA) for the first time since it swept into China's newest region by land, sea and air a week ago, cheered by thousands of well-wishers.</p>
<p>An enraged press said the PLA had ignored all other journalists by giving exclusive access to the mainland's China Central Television when Hong Kong's new leader Tung Chee-hwa received garrison commander Major-General Liu Zhenwu on Friday.</p>
<p>Film of the event was widely shown on Chinese television -- then offered to other news organisations a day later when it was stale news.</p>
<p>A spokesman for Tung blamed inadequate communication with the PLA, which arrived with an unexpected contingent of mainland journalists for Britain's handover of Hong Kong a week ago.</p>
<p>&quot;We assure (you) that a similar incident will not be repeated,&quot; the spokesman said after fierce criticism from photographers and reporters.</p>
<p>Tung will pay his first visit to the new Chinese garrison on Wednesday and officials say accredited journalists may cover the event at a PLA navy base on Stonecutters Island, where Britain previously had its naval headquarters.</p>
<p>In an editorial, the South China Morning Post newspaper said mainland personnel must try to conform to the Hong Kong way of working.</p>
<p>&quot;Perhaps it is routine on the mainland to give privileges to the official news service but in Hong Kong there is a level playing field for media, just as there is in business and finance,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>The newspaper said freedom of information and the press &quot;must not be eroded&quot; and backed the idea of the PLA needing a spokesman. Otherwise, its &quot;goal of creating a good image in Hong Kong will not be easily achieved&quot;.</p>
<p>The media slight was the latest in a series of perceived public relations blunders over several weeks by an army sent to &quot;love&quot; the people of Hong Kong, a metropolis with a strongly competitive press including 20 daily newspapers.</p>
<p>Here to defend this quasi-autonomous special region of China, the troops were handpicked from the world's biggest army, equipped with new uniforms and gear, and trained in both English and Cantonese. They also had lifestyle lessons, such as Hong Kong's habit of driving on the left side of the road.</p>
<p>They have displayed awesome discipline that ranges from a strange waving-in-unison to crowds to rigid sentry duty in spite of rainshowers and curious bystanders.</p>
<p>They occupy former British barracks but lack the small army of public relations officers Britain's garrison deployed.</p>
<p>The British also committed howlers, a recent one being a press statement that wrongly committed the British forces to a gun salute for Queen Elizabeth's birthday when they meant that of her husband, the Duke of Edinburgh.</p>
<p>They also referred to &quot;Her Royal Highness&quot; Prince Charles a few days before Britain's heir to the throne handed back Hong Kong to China.</p>
<p>A language mixup was blamed for the PLA's first gaffe before the handover when a general accused customs officers of an insult when they stopped his car at a closed border area.</p>
<p>The PLA upset local residents near one barracks by moving to shut down two bus routes. A misunderstanding, officials said.</p>
<p>In a bizarre incident, a photographer was manhandled while witnessing 30 PLA troops marching out of a Bank of China branch with big metal boxes. It turned out the contents were either musical instruments or presentation weapons for the handover ceremony.</p>
<p>Days before the handover, mainland troops caused a stir by appearing at the venue, prompting the government to deny they were security experts, just bandsmen on a practice mission.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
