<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="714880" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>VIETNAM: Vietnam seeks U.S. money for Agent Orange victims.</title>
<headline>Vietnam seeks U.S. money for Agent Orange victims.</headline>
<dateline>HANOI 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hanoi said on Tuesday it had asked government agencies to detail the impact of chemical defoliants used by the United States during the Vietnam War as part of a renewed drive to win compensation from Washington.</p>
<p>State-controlled media said ministries and other government bodies had been instructed to study and assess the long-term consequences of the use of Agent Orange and other toxic chemicals and propose action or solutions.</p>
<p>&quot;The Vietnamese government has instructed all concerned offices and organisations to evaluate accurately and sufficiently the aftermath caused by various toxic chemicals during the Vietnam War,&quot; state radio said.</p>
<p>&quot;The Vietnamese government also demands that the U.S. be responsible for the victims' compensation and overcoming environmental destruction caused by U.S. toxic chemicals,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>United States forces sprayed millions of litres of chemical defoliants across huge swathes of former South Vietnam during the war in a bid to reduce infiltration and other guerrilla activity.</p>
<p>Agent Orange, containing harmful dioxins, was the best known of those compounds. Hanoi says the result was some 50,000 children born with physical defects in the first 10 years after the war ended.</p>
<p>But efforts to win compensation from the United States have run into problems. A U.S. scientific team that visited in 1995 to conduct joint research had papers and samples confiscated as it was about to leave.</p>
<p>A U.S. official said on Tuesday that despite a recent offer by Hanoi's 10-80 research committee to return some of those papers and samples, none had yet been handed over.</p>
<p>&quot;When we have that we can proceed with the process of scientific discovery,&quot; the official said. &quot;Until we know more it's difficult to determine if the problems have resulted from defoliants or something else such as chemical fertilisers.&quot;</p>
<p>The United States and Vietnam normalised diplomatic ties in 1995, two decades after the war ended. Officials on both sides state publicly that enmity and memories of war are now best consigned to the past.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, the issue surfaces regularly. Last month state media catalogued the appalling and continuing cost of the conflict, just days before a visit by U.S. Secretary of State Madeleine Albright.</p>
<p>The official Vietnam News Agency, said more than three million Vietnamese had been killed, 4.4 million wounded and two million affected by toxic chemicals. It added that while the war may have ended 22 years ago it continued to place a heavy burden on Vietnam.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VIETN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HANOI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="VIETNAM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
