<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="715089" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Solana pledges NATO door will stay open.</title>
<headline>Solana pledges NATO door will stay open.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>NATO Secretary-General Javier Solana, opening a summit to invite some former communist adversaries into the Western alliance, pledged on Tuesday the door would remain open for unsuccessful applicants to join later.</p>
<p>&quot;We will make it very clear that the door of the alliance stays open for other countries,&quot; Solana said in his opening address to the summit at Madrid's Municipal Congress Centre.  </p>
<p>The summit is set to invite former Warsaw Pact foes Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic to join the alliance, disappointing Romania and Slovenia and seven other applicants desperate to come under the West's U.S.-run defence shield.</p>
<p>&quot;Today's meeting is a defining moment for NATO. We will open the doors of this alliance to the first new members from Central and Eastern Europe,&quot; Solana said.</p>
<p>France and Italy, backed by seven other European allies, had supported a wider enlargement bringing in Romania and Slovenia, while the United States was adamant the alliance's first eastwards expansion should be restricted to three.</p>
<p>NATO officials said the 16 alliance states were very close to agreement on three with the expansionists backing down in return for powerful language making it clear enlargement would remain an on-going process.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
