<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="715081" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>SPAIN: Spain's Aznar reaffirms commitment to NATO.</title>
<headline>Spain's Aznar reaffirms commitment to NATO.</headline>
<dateline>MADRID 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Spanish Prime Minister Jose Maria Aznar gave a strong commitment that Spain would join NATO's military command structure in the coming months, at the opening of an alliance summit on Tuesday in Madrid.</p>
<p>Aznar said in a speech to NATO heads of state and government he was satisfied with progress made so far in negotiations with NATO in which Spain has insisted on a sub-regional Iberian command over all its territory including the Canary islands and control of the Straits of Gibraltar.  </p>
<p>&quot;As you know, Spain decided to take the necessary steps for participating fully in the alliance's new command structure, in accordance with the decision taken by the Spanish parliament,&quot; Aznar said in a speech to open the summit.</p>
<p>&quot;We have started to do this and will continue to do so. We view the progress made with satisfaction and I trust that everything will be completed as soon as possible,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Aznar said on Monday, after a meeting with U.S. President Bill Clinton, that there were still problems to be ironed out in the Spain-NATO negotiations but he was confident he could make a final decision to join by the end of the year.</p>
<p>NATO was founded in 1949, but Spain only joined in 1982. Like France, it stayed out of the military structure because it objected to what it saw as excessive U.S. dominance of the organisation, and because of a strong pacifist tradition.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NATO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MADRID"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SPAIN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
