<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="715150" id="root" date="1997-07-08" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French printers' strike blocks national newspapers.</title>
<headline>French printers' strike blocks national newspapers.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-07-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>France's national daily newspapers were missing from news stands on Tuesday as printers' unions launched a 24-hour strike.</p>
<p>Some dailies, in statements read on the radio, urged readers desperate for the day's news to consult their internet sites.</p>
<p>A committee of Paris printers' unions called the stoppage in support of workers at the Rungis and Saint-Denis depots in the Paris suburbs employed by the Nouvelles Messageries de la Presse Parisienne (NMPP), France's largest press distribution organisation.</p>
<p>Talks between the NMPP and workers have stalled after three weeks of labour conflict over planned changes in working practice, the unions' joint statement said. They want negotiations to re-open on the reforms.</p>
<p>The NMPP said the proposed changes were aimed at securing the future of the present distribution system, which it said must be made more efficient and less costly.</p>
<p>The NMPP said the changes would not lead to sackings, but were aimed only at changing working hours for 200 workers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-08"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-08"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
