<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731322" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FDA panel backs Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn's Rogaine 5 pct.</title>
<headline>FDA panel backs Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn's Rogaine 5 pct.</headline>
<dateline>BETHESDA, Md. 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory panel on Wednesday voted 13-4 to approve Pharmacia and Upjohn's minoxidil five-percent solution (Rogaine) as an over-the-counter treatment for male-pattern baldness.</p>
<p>It is a stronger version of OTC Rogaine two-percent solution.  </p>
<p>The panel said Rogaine five percent should not be sold to women due to lack of efficacy. Members were initially skeptical that women would heed warnings to not use the product despite several P&amp;U studies showing women would understand the warnings.</p>
<p>However after a debate, the panel voted 16-2 that women would comprehend the warnings. The panel had no other major concerns, but said that P&amp;U could not claim that Rogaine five percent grew hair faster than the two-percent solution.</p>
<p>The FDA is not bound by its panels' advice, but usually follows it.  </p>
<p>P&amp;U hopes to increase Rogaine users and sales -- $162 million in the United States in 1996 -- with the five-percent solution.</p>
<p>If approved, Rogaine five percent could have up to three years of marketing exclusivity.  Generic versions of Rogaine two percent appeared a month after introduction in April 1996, surprising the company, according to P&amp;U spokesman John Ruane.</p>
<p>Even so, the OTC launch increased U.S. users five-fold to about two million, said Michael Valentino, president of P&amp;U Consumer Healthcare.  </p>
<p>P&amp;U is targeting the six-to-seven million men it thinks are motivated to do something about their thinning hair.</p>
<p>The five-percent solution works better and faster than the two-percent solution, claimed Valentino.  In two clinical studies, male users of the five-percent solution had 46 percent more hair growth at the end of the 48-week trial.</p>
<p>Hair growth at eight weeks in five percent users was the same as at sixteen weeks for two-percent users.</p>
<p>The panel said that did not prove faster growth.</p>
<p>Side effects, including dryness, itching, and flushing and redness, were worse than with Rogaine two percent.  </p>
<p>FDA has received similar reports since the first Rogaine was launched in 1988, but also has gotten reports of increased hair loss and that it doesn't work.</p>
<p>Fourteen patients who had taken twice the recommended dose had increased heart rates, but an FDA reviewer said the effect is likely to be very rare.</p>
<p>P&amp;U also conducted two trials in women, but in each, almost half dropped out.  The FDA said that women using the five-percent solution did not have significant hair growth compared with the two-percent solution.</p>
<p>Some also had unwanted facial hair growth.</p>
<p>P&amp;U says it is pursuing new trials.  Only about 250,000 women are currently using Rogaine two percent for Women, according to P&amp;U.</p>
<p>Rogaine five percent is approved in 19 countries for men and women, either by prescription or OTC.</p>
<p>-- Washington newsroom, ((202-898-8300))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BETHESDA, Md."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
