<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731586" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: MARKETS UNSURE OF FLOOD IMPACT ON POLISH FINANCES.</title>
<headline>MARKETS UNSURE OF FLOOD IMPACT ON POLISH FINANCES.</headline>
<byline>Tomasz Janowski</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's government on Wednesday asked parliament to rush through laws easing the flow of funds to areas ravaged by floods but it has yet to convince markets that the special measures will not hurt economic stability.</p>
<p>The government seeks to change the 1997 budget to allow it to borrow up to 2.5 billion zlotys from the central bank for flood relief and it is asking for an increase in its foreign borrowing limits to allow a $300 million World Bank soft loan.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Marek Belka reassured parliament that the measures would not pump extra cash into the economy.</p>
<p>&quot;The credit we asked from the NBP does not mean an increase in the total expenditures of the state, it only guarantees that we will not be in danger of losing liquidity,&quot; Belka said.</p>
<p>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) Warsaw representative praised the government for trying to tread a thin line between efforts to ensure sufficient funds are available to deal with the damage and maintaining financial stability.</p>
<p>But analysts said only estimates of the total costs and information on how much and in what way the government would borrow could soothe worries over the impact of the disaster.</p>
<p>Forex traders said the uncertainty over budget performance this year and possible central bank actions added to earlier concerns over Poland's trade deficit, hitting the zloty hard.</p>
<p>The zloty lost a record five percent on Tuesday and even though it recovered about 2.5 percent with central bank help on Wednesday, the market remained jittery.</p>
<p>Warsaw shares fell a total 5.2 percent in three sessions to Tuesday and, despite a one percent rebound on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Analysts saw the mood remaining subdued while the full flood impact on some firms and on the whole economy remained unknown.</p>
<p>The National Bank of Poland on Tuesday volunteered a one billion zloty emergency loan at market rates and promised to fully offset its monetary impact by drawing money from the market through accepting deposits from the public.</p>
<p>But analysts said it was not clear whether the government would accept the offer.</p>
<p>&quot;Much will depend on whether the actual borrowing will be closer to the NBP's one billion or nearer the 2.5 billion ceiling, because the latter would definitely have inflationary effects,&quot; a senior economist at foreign institution said.</p>
<p>The government aims to cut year on year inflation to 13 percent in December 1997 and to 9.5 percent at the end of next year from 15.3 percent last month.</p>
<p>Analysts were disappointed that the government had abandoned the idea of a special flood tax.</p>
<p>&quot;The decision not to finance flood reconstruction by a tax could create a certain inflationary impulse,&quot; said Tadeusz Chroscicki, chief analyst at government's Centre for Strategic Studies. &quot;The 13 percent (inflation) target for this year is still realistic but we will not get any lower,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Inflationary impulses from higher government borrowing will spill over to next year and the 9.5 percent target is threatened,&quot; Chroscicki added.</p>
<p>The government stressed it would seek to finance the reconstruction mainly by shifting funds within the budget and that it has already lined up 650 million zlotys in this way.</p>
<p>But several analysts were sceptical the 1997 budget deficit target of 2.8 percent, already under pressure from lower tax revenues and high deficit financing costs, would withstand pressure from possible revenue loss and higher spending needs.</p>
<p>Analysts said Poland's 5.5-percent growth targets for this and next year would be least affected, as losses in farming and industrial output could be offset by a building boom.</p>
<p>They said, however, that reconstruction efforts would boost demand for imports which would probably push the trade deficit this year beyond the earlier-predicted $12 billion.</p>
<p>-- Warsaw Newsroom +48 22 653 9700</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
