<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731653" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Sleepy drivers worse than drunks - study.</title>
<headline>Sleepy drivers worse than drunks - study.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sleepy drivers may be more dangerous than drunk drivers, Australian researchers reported on Wednesday.</p>
<p>They said tests on sleep-deprived volunteers showed that staying up for just over a day could hurt performance just as much as a few drinks.</p>
<p>&quot;Moderate levels of fatigue produce higher levels of impairment than the proscribed level of alcohol intoxication,&quot; they wrote in a letter to the science journal Nature.</p>
<p>Drew Dawson of the University of South Australia's Centre for Sleep Research and Kathryn Reid of the University of Adelaide tested 40 people in two experiments.</p>
<p>&quot;In one they were kept awake for 28 hours (from 8:00 until 12:00 the following day) and in the other they were asked to consume 10 to 15 grams of alcohol at 30 minute intervals from 8:00 until their mean blood alcohol concentration reached 0.10 percent,&quot; they wrote.</p>
<p>They used a computer test of hand-eye coordination in both experiments. &quot;Performance decreased significantly in both conditions,&quot; they wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;After 17 hours of sustained wakefulness...performance decreased to a level equivalent to the performance impairment observed at a blood alcohol concentration of 0.05 percent,&quot; they found.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the proscribed level of alcohol intoxication in many Western industrialised countries.&quot;</p>
<p>Being kept up for 24 hours made people react as badly as when their blood alcohol levels were 0.1 percent, Dawson and Reid found.</p>
<p>&quot;It is clear that the effects of moderate sleep loss on performance are similar to moderate alcohol intoxication,&quot; they concluded.</p>
<p>&quot;As about 50 percent of shift-workers do not sleep on the day before the first night-shift, and levels of fatigue on subsequent night-shifts can be even higher, our data indicate that the performance impairment associated with shift-work could be even greater than reported here.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSCI">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
