<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731744" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Canada relieved by latest delay in Helms-Burton.</title>
<headline>Canada relieved by latest delay in Helms-Burton.</headline>
<dateline>OTTAWA 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Canada gave a qualified welcome on Wednesday to U.S. President Bill Clinton's decision to waive for six months parts of the anti-Cuba Helms-Burton law.</p>
<p>&quot;This decision is helpful in the short term but in the long term we remain gravely concerned about the legislation and its extra-territoriality measures,&quot; a spokeswoman for Canadian Trade Minister Sergio Marchi said in a phone interview.</p>
<p>&quot;Our objective in the end is to have the U.S. repeal this legislation,&quot; spokeswoman Leslie Swartman said. &quot;We find the legislation quite odious.&quot;</p>
<p>She said the legislation continues to have &quot;a chill&quot; on investment in Cuba despite the continued suspension of parts of the law.</p>
<p>The U.S. State Department announced on Wednesday that Clinton would waive for the third consecutive time the section of the Helms-Burton law which relates to the right of U.S. citizens to sue foreign companies that utilize proporty in Cuba confiscated by the communist government there.</p>
<p>But the U.S. administration will continue to enforce another section of the act, which denies U.S. visas to senior executives of foreign companies deemed to have &quot;trafficked&quot; in confiscated property in Cuba.</p>
<p>This section has been used against executives of Toronto-based Sherritt International Corp, which is involved in mining, agriculture and oil in Cuba.</p>
<p>Canada has threatened to challenge the Helms-Burton legislation under the North American Free Trade Agreement, but government officials said on Wednesday that Canada will likely wait to see the outcome of talks between the United States and the European Union before taking any action.</p>
<p>&quot;It (action under Nafta) is still in our back pocket,&quot; Swartman said.</p>
<p>The United States and the EU are discussing the anti-Cuba measures through talks for a multilateral agreement on investment through the Organization for Economic Development and Co-operation.</p>
<p>The U.S.-EU talks are scheduled to wrap up on October 15.</p>
<p>Canada's direct investment in Cuba totalled C$105 million in 1995 and has been climbing steeply. KWG Resources Inc of Montreal said last week it has signed an agreement to develop and operate a new nickel mine and plant in Cuba.</p>
<p>In 1996, Canada imported goods worth C$411 million from Cuba, and Canada exported goods worth C$269 million.</p>
<p>One of every four foreign visitors to Cuba comes from Canada, trade officials said.</p>
<p>((Heather Scoffield, Reuters Ottawa Bureau 613 235-6745))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="OTTAWA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
