<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731799" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: Early El Nino sparks Southern Africa drought fears.</title>
<headline>Early El Nino sparks Southern Africa drought fears.</headline>
<byline>Nicole Mordant</byline>
<dateline>JOHANNESBURG 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Southern African weather and agricultural experts on Wednesday voiced concern about the early build-up of the El Nino weather phenomenon, which could spark a devastating drought in the region next year.</p>
<p>Two years of soaking rains have given rise to the best crops in years but a severe El Nino, which has the potential to cause droughts on one side of the globe while spurring floods elsewhere, would cut short the profits from this bumper run.</p>
<p>&quot;The Pacific El Nino has developed much earlier than it usually does. It usually gets going in about December and hits full steam in about January, but it is up to full strength right now,&quot; said Mark Jury, a weather specialist at the University of Zululand.</p>
<p>He said the early development could make the El Nino, which is produced by a disruption in the atmospheric system leading to changes in wind patterns and higher water temperatures in the Pacific, unstable and cause it to lose momentum.</p>
<p>&quot;On the other hand if it keeps going and developing at the rate it is, it could be just as bad as things we had more than a decade ago,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>This century's worst El Nino hit in 1982 and 1983, sparking hurricanes, droughts, fires and flooding in over 15 countries.</p>
<p>South Africa's government on Wednesday issued a warning that an El Nino was on the way.</p>
<p>This follows warnings earlier this month from international scientists that the weather phenomenon had the potential to cause billions of dollars of damage in key agricultural regions worldwide.</p>
<p>Kit le Clus, a director of South Africa's National Maize Producers Organisation, said that the early appearance of El Nino created worries over next year's maize crop, the country's biggest agricultural commodity.</p>
<p>&quot;The probability of less-than-normal maize production next year is very strong,&quot; Le Clus said.</p>
<p>He said El Nino generally brought rains during the spring planting season, which tended to stunt root development. Dry weather in January and February then hit at a time when plants were in their reproductive and most moisture-reliant phase.</p>
<p>&quot;That's when you get the devastation,&quot; Le Clus said.</p>
<p>An emerging markets analyst at a local brokerage firm said that in view of a possibly intense El Nino, he was advising caution on investment in Zimbabwe's stock market.</p>
<p>&quot;I am obviously worried about the effect, particularly in Zimbabwe where the stock market has had such a good year on the back of two consecutive rain seasons,&quot; the analyst said. The bourse soared 90 percent in U.S. dollar terms in 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;My worry is that if there is a drought the whole thing will come tumbling down again. My view is that I would be treating Zimbabwe with caution at this stage,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Weather analyst Jury said that in Southern Africa the impact of the El Nino would be felt hardest in Botswana, due to the development in summer of a high pressure cell over that country. It would then spread out affecting the northern, central and eastern parts of South Africa and Zimbabwe.</p>
<p>-- Johannesburg newsroom 27 11 482 1003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JOHANNESBURG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
