<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731868" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Poland pleased with EU report on its progress.</title>
<headline>Poland pleased with EU report on its progress.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz said on Wednesday he was very pleased by the positive tone of the EU's verdict on Poland's readiness to start membership talks, especially on agriculture.</p>
<p>&quot;I am very pleased to say the opinion is positive, more than we could have expected in recent years,&quot; he told a news conference after the EU executive Commission unveiled its Agenda 2000 document, which picked Poland among the countries to begin entry talks next year.</p>
<p>European Union associate Poland has had stormy trade disputes with the bloc and has been criticised for slowness in adjusting its laws to EU standards and making some major economic reforms including that of its pension system.</p>
<p>Poland's inefficient agriculture, with many small farms, has often been viewed as an obstacle as it would put vast strain on the EU's current Common Agricultural Policy (CAP).</p>
<p>But the Commission's comments were mild.</p>
<p>&quot;Too many trade-related problems have arisen, though most of them have been able to be resolved,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>On farming it said Poland had to make major efforts in areas from coherent rural development to veterinary rules.</p>
<p>&quot;Provided these targets can be met, the CAP could be applied in an appropriate manner on accession in the medium term, although a solution to Poland's structural problems will require a long-term approach,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>&quot;What is surprising for me is the section on agriculture,&quot; said Cimoszewicz, clearly pleased.</p>
<p>&quot;It does not conclude that we will be able to sort everything out soon, but it says that if we...have success in restructuring agriculture, it will not be an obstacle to our acceptance into the EU,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Commission's opinion was peppered with other criticisms, but Cimoszewicz said they were realistic.</p>
<p>He said dire predictions by some commentators that Poland would be near the bottom of the list of countries invited to start EU talks had been disproved and it was in fact a leading candidate.</p>
<p>Poland, which escaped Soviet domination in 1989, is eager to bind itself to the West as fast as possible for political and strategic as well as economic reasons. It hopes to begin EU talks, expected to be tough, early next year, and get in by about 2002 or 2003 which will give time to prepare well.</p>
<p>The EU verdict, following soon after this month's Madrid summit decision to include Poland in the first three nations invited to start talks on NATO entry, should have been a reason for rejoicing.</p>
<p>Polish satisfaction was clouded by sadness and worry over a major flood disaster which has smitten the country's south.</p>
<p>Danuta Huebner, minister in charge of the EU entry process, said Poland's farm problems were not as serious as often painted -- especially as the CAP was also going to be reformed.</p>
<p>&quot;There are such changes in agriculture that by the year 2000 it will be completely different from now, to say nothing of the fact that the CAP will change and the two will meet.</p>
<p>&quot;It will be a profitable, safe marriage for both sides,&quot; she told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>EU envoy to Warsaw Rolf Timans, often a stern judge of Poland's performance, told reporters: &quot;This means that the Commission has a favourable review of development in Poland.&quot;</p>
<p>But he added: &quot;The faster Poland covers those existing gaps, the better the negotiation process will progress&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
