<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731871" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Yugo '97 exports seen well below target - institute.</title>
<headline>Yugo '97 exports seen well below target - institute.</headline>
<byline>Amra Kevic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Trends in Yugoslavia's January-June trade indicate exports will not rise more than 18.5 to 20 percent in 1997, well under the official growth target, the Institute for Foreign Trade said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Official targets of 48 to 50 percent exports growth would mean we would have to export an average $290 million per month in the second half of the year,&quot; Radovan Kovacevic, director of the Belgrade-based institute told reporters.</p>
<p>According to official statistics, Yugoslav January-June exports were worth $1.028 billion and were 28.5 percent up on the same six-month period last year. Imports stood at $2.112 billion or 27.7 percent up on January-June 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;The trade gap of $1.084 billion is higher than total exports in this period,&quot; Kovacevic said.</p>
<p>Comparison with the second half of 1996 rather than the first six months gave a clearer picture of trends of stagnation in trade, the institute said.</p>
<p>The average monthly value of exports in January-June 1997 was $173 million, or practically the same level as the $171 million monthly average in the second half of 1996.</p>
<p>&quot;This means exports have not advanced much from the monthly average in the second half of last year,&quot; Kovacevic said.</p>
<p>The value of imports has been sliding downwards over the past three months at a faster rate than the slowdown in exports, the institute said in its monthly report.</p>
<p>Imports averaged $352 million per month in January-June 1997 compared to $394 million monthly average in the second half of 1996.</p>
<p>Without a drastic turnabout in their structure in H2, it will be hard to achieve the targeted $2.763 billion exports this year.</p>
<p>Kovacevic said if the present dynamics of exports-imports continue, the 1997 trade deficit could reach $2.6 billion.</p>
<p>Last year's trade gap was $2.26 billion, with imports worth $4.1 billion and exports $1.84 billion.</p>
<p>Central bank reserves, used to finance a large part of the trade gap in H1 1997, should be strengthened indirectly by credits from the Serbian Development Fund to boost export-oriented production, Kovacevic said.</p>
<p>&quot;With these foreign exchange reserves the National Bank of Yugoslavia could even finance growth of the trade deficit to $3 billion,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Development Fund is the sole recipient of some 80 percent of 1.568 billion German marks from the sale of a 49 percent stake in Serbia's telecom company Telekom Srbija to Greek and Italian partners last month.</p>
<p>But the structure of Yugoslavia's trade, dominated on both the export and import sides by raw materials and semi-finished products, was still a major limiting factor to raising exports.</p>
<p>&quot;It is obvious we cannot achieve substantial growth of exports of products of a higher level of processing. This opens the long-term question of changing the structure of exports,&quot; Kovacevic said.</p>
<p>Main obstacles to raising exports of finished products are reduced competitiveness due to high production costs, prices, poor quality and design, expensive credits and general lack of funds in the moribund economy.</p>
<p>&quot;The structure of Yugoslavia's trade is now approaching that of undeveloped countries, while in 1989-1990 we were among medium-developed countries,&quot; said the institute's Pero Perovic.</p>
<p>-- Belgrade newsroom, +381 11 311 4305</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
