<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731866" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: Czech PM says expected EU decision, will work hard.</title>
<headline>Czech PM says expected EU decision, will work hard.</headline>
<byline>Nigel Stephenson</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Czech Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus said on Wednesday a European Commission recommendation to begin EU membership talks with Prague had been expected and that his government was making intensive preparations.</p>
<p>&quot;We are glad that it happened. I have to say we expected it would happen. We are preparing...intensively for the start of the negotiations,&quot; Klaus told a news conference.</p>
<p>He said he had not read the Commission's opinion in detail but, from the reports he had seen, it seemed to be &quot;a satisfactory evaluation&quot;.</p>
<p>The Commission earlier on Wednesday recommended the European Union begin accession talks with five East European states, including the Czech Republic, and with Cyprus.</p>
<p>The EU ambassador to the Czech Republic, Joannes Ter Haar, told a news conference the commission's view was generally very positive. There were no acute problems despite some concerns.</p>
<p>The Czech Republic was long seen as in the forefront of reform in Eastern Europe but a worsening economic situation and political wobbles have taken some of the shine off its image with foreign investors.</p>
<p>Ter Haar said more needed to be done in the industrial sector including further restructuring, privatisation and streamlining. Corporate governance also must be improved.</p>
<p>He also said supervision of the capital markets needed to be enhanced and that there should be more bank privatisation.</p>
<p>&quot;The prime objective must always be that the industrial sector of the Czech Republic be optimally competitive once the single market becomes available to it on membership,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Many investors have complained about a lack of transparency in the capital markets, which have been hit by numerous scandals in recent months. They also say the lack of a developed capital market has slowed essential restructuring.</p>
<p>Ter Haar said a well-functioning civil service law was needed, as were improvements in the judicial system. There were too few judges and the courts worked too slowly.</p>
<p>One concern highlighted in the conclusion to the 104-page document concerned the Czechs' import deposit scheme, introduced in April to curb a yawning trade gap.</p>
<p>Under the scheme, importers have to deposit interest-free in banks 20 percent of the value of certain goods for 180 days.</p>
<p>&quot;We consider it should be scrapped,&quot; said EU delegation official David Ringrose, adding the Commission believed it breached the Czechs' association agreement with the EU.</p>
<p>Ringrose said the Commission was going ahead with dispute settlement procedures. &quot;This implies we consider the scheme should be withdrawn. If not we will move towards arbitration&quot;.</p>
<p>He added that the recent depreciation of the Czech crown, which was allowed to float freely on May 27 after a wave of speculative selling, made it simpler to withdraw the scheme.</p>
<p>&quot;They have touched the most important things in quite an accurate way,&quot; said analyst Vladimir Kreidl of Patria Finance.</p>
<p>&quot;The work that has to be done is enormous so the progress is only gradual but I think that in the end we will be able to adopt all the necessary legislation that is in force in the EU,&quot; he said, highlighting corporate governance, the financial and energy sectors as areas requiring more work.</p>
<p>But he also expressed concern that the Commission had identified deficiencies in Czech health and safety law. Such laws were sometimes inflexible in EU countries.</p>
<p>&quot;This would not be a big improvement for the functioning of the Czech economy,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
