<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731869" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria optimistic on EU membership targets.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria optimistic on EU membership targets.</headline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgaria will speed up market reforms to meet European Union entry criteria after being excluded from the EU's first planned eastern expansion, Foreign Minister Nadejda Mihailova said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Now that we have social support for reforms, we are optimistic that we will soon overcome our economic problems and compensate reform delays, which impeded our way to the EU,&quot; Mihailova told a news conference.</p>
<p>The European Commission, presenting its plans to expand beyond the former Iron Curtain early next century, invited Poland, the Czech Republic, Hungary, Estonia and Slovenia for EU entry talks.</p>
<p>It rejected Bulgaria and four other countries -- Romania, Lithuania, Latvia and Slovakia -- pledging to design a strategy to help them overcome their shortcomings and prepare for full membership.</p>
<p>The Commission said it would review the progress of the rejected applicants each year.</p>
<p>&quot;The individual dialogue with each country is an expression of support and will help overcome economic hardship. We are determined to cover our part of the patch as soon as possible,&quot; said Mihailova.</p>
<p>&quot;Bulgaria faces the challenge to sustain the good start from earlier this year,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>In its assessment the EU found that Bulgaria, with a new reformist government, was on its way to satisfying the political criteria for membership, but said its economic progress had been limited by a lack of commitment to market-oriented policies.</p>
<p>Despite some first steps taken in 1991, the country is still only at the start of the process of structural transformation. Early liberalisation of trade and prices was partially reversed and price controls were not removed until this year.</p>
<p>The Commission also said Bulgaria would not be able to cope with competitive pressure and market forces within the EU in the medium term.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
