<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="731985" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>POLAND: Polish parliament meets to tackle flood calamity.</title>
<headline>Polish parliament meets to tackle flood calamity.</headline>
<byline>Anthony Barker</byline>
<dateline>WARSAW 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Poland's parliament met in a special session on Wednesday to rush through laws which would ease the flow of funds and help to hundreds of communities devastated by the worst floods in centuries.</p>
<p>Parliamentarians began with a moment's silence for at least 39 people who have died and hundreds of thousands whose homes and livelihoods have been wrecked by a continuing catastrophe that began with huge downpours early last week.</p>
<p>&quot;People are dying, and the water is taking away everything they own,&quot; lower house Speaker Jozef Zych said in a televised address to the nation late on Tuesday, vowing fast decisions.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz's government was treading a political and economic tightrope.</p>
<p>While highly critical opposition parties demanded faster, more effective action to help and rebuild, economists warned against any rash fund-raising measures that might harm economic stability -- especially after the zloty plunged on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The zloty showed some recovery in early Wednesday trade.</p>
<p>Waters retreated in the hard-hit south, including the major cities of Wroclaw and Opole, to reveal smashed homes, broken bridges and chewed-up roads covered in filth threatening disease.</p>
<p>Communities further north along the raging Odra river were still being hit by a swell of flood water surging towards Germany and the sea, reaching the town of Glogow on Wednesday.</p>
<p>On Tuesday the coalition cabinet decided to submit 22 new or amended laws, including a revision of the 1997 budget to cope with a calamity that had hit around 60,000 families.</p>
<p>&quot;The government is trying to be responsive but it is also trying to remain responsible macro-economically and that is how I read the package of decisions made today,&quot; International Monetary Fund representative Markus Rodlauer said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The government proposed amending this year's budget to get an additional 2.5 billion zloty ($740 million) borrowing limit in the central bank to ensure it had enough ready money.</p>
<p>But Prime Minister Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz stressed the move would not mean pumping this amount into the economy.</p>
<p>The government was also seeking an increase in its foreign borrowing limits to allow a $300 million World Bank loan.</p>
<p>Largely by yanking money from other budget goals and halting capital projects, the government has already lined up 650 million zlotys for flood relief and was determined to rebuild as much as possible in the months before winter.</p>
<p>Among other steps, it proposed quick $600 payouts to provide essentials to all households struck by the flood and free wheat from reserves to farmers with swamped land.</p>
<p>The prime minister's Democratic Left Alliance (SLD), the dominant coalition party, is fighting an opposition bloc led by the Solidarity union in September 21 elections and analysts say its actions in coming days could spell victory or defeat.</p>
<p>The government's energy now did not prevent the opposition from accusing it of delays and blunders earlier in the crisis and it faced a rough ride despite Zych's pleas to avoid politicising the debate.</p>
<p>At the very start, centrist opposition deputy Wladyslaw Frasyniuk said the whole legislative effort in parliament was a waste of time and only the budget bill amendment was necessary.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WARSAW"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="POLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
