<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732027" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHILE: U.S. to send fast-track to Congress Sept-Chile.</title>
<headline>U.S. to send fast-track to Congress Sept-Chile.</headline>
<dateline>SANTIAGO 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The United States government will send new &quot;fast-track&quot; trade legislation to Congress in September as a first step to reactivating talks on Chile's entry to NAFTA, said Chilean Economy Minister Alvaro Garcia.</p>
<p>&quot;The president's (Clinton) advisers and ministers have told us that they will begin a very intense political campaign to have fast track legislation approved hopefully towards the end of the year,&quot; Garcia told reporters in Santiago by telephone from Washington.</p>
<p>&quot;To do this, they have told us they will send a new fast track bill (to Congress) in the first two weeks of September.&quot;</p>
<p>Chile was invited to join the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) in December 1994 but talks on its membership stalled after the Clinton administration failed to get Congress approval of fast-track negotiating powers.</p>
<p>Garcia held talks in Washington this week with U.S. Trade Representative Charlene Barshefsky and Commerce Secretary William Daley to discuss the brewing trade row over Chilean salmon exports.</p>
<p>U.S. salmon producers have complained to the International Trade Commission that their Chilean counterparts receive illegal subsidies and are dumping fresh Atlantic salmon in the American market.</p>
<p>Garcia said he was confident that the U.S. authorities would carry out a thorough investigation into the allegations which he descibed as a &quot;black mark&quot; in the countries' trade relations.</p>
<p>&quot;The government of the United States cannot prejudge, but has given us maximum certainty that it will carry out an investigation right to the bottom of the issue,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;They listened to our arguments about the precariousness of some of the grounds on which the accusations are made,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But they told us that the investigation is just beginning and they will look in great deal at the points we mentioned.&quot;</p>
<p>U.S. supermarkets and restaurants account for 30 percent of Chile's total salmon exports. Shipments to the American market are worth around $180 million a year.</p>
<p>((-- Margaret Orgill, Santiago newsroom, 562-699-5595x212))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SANTIAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHILE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
