<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732076" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CUBA: Cuba scorns Clinton move on Helms-Burton law.</title>
<headline>Cuba scorns Clinton move on Helms-Burton law.</headline>
<dateline>HAVANA 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cuba on Wednesday poured scorn on President Bill Clinton's move to waive for another six months implementation of a provision of the controversial Helms-Burton law against the Communist-ruled island.</p>
<p>The State Department in Washington announced on Wednesday that Clinton had decided to waive for another six months implementation of Title Three which allows U.S. citizens to sue in U.S. courts foreign firms deemed to have profited from American property confiscated by Cuba after its 1959 communist revolution.</p>
<p>&quot;The empire (the United States) has conceded to the world six months more sovereignty, but the law is still extraterritorial and unacceptable for us,&quot; Cuban Foreign Ministry spokesman Miguel Alfonso told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;It is more of the same thing,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>Alfonso noted the waiver applied only to Title Three and the rest of the Helms-Burton legislation was in force.</p>
<p>Clinton first suspended implementation of Title Three last July and again in January. But Cuba, which objects strongly to the whole law, was similarly cool in its reaction to these waivers.</p>
<p>Titles One and Two of Helms-Burton call for a radical political overhaul in Cuba as a condition to normal ties with the United States. These chapters have drawn less attention abroad, but Havana views them as gross interference in its internal affairs.</p>
<p>Title Four of the law provides for executives of foreign companies deemed to be trafficking on property expropriated from U.S. firms or citizens to be barred entry to the United States. It has so far been applied to executives from a Canadian mining firm and a Mexican telecommunications company.</p>
<p>The Helms-Burton bill, a tightening of Washington's 35-year economic embargo on Cuba, was passed in March 1996, three weeks after Cuban MiG fighter planes shot down two small Cuban exile-operated planes flying near the island, killing the four crew members.</p>
<p>President Fidel Castro's government, while vowing no amount of U.S. pressure will get it to change its one-party communist system, has nevertheless admitted that Helms-Burton has caused some damage to the island's frail economy.</p>
<p>Cuban officials have given no figures to quantify such damage. But one example they have frequently cited is delays in arrival of foreign financing for the 1996-97 sugar cane harvest following the passage of the law.</p>
<p>These delays were one factor in a poorer than expected harvest, Cuban officials said. An official figure has not been given for the harvest, which ended last month, but it is thought to have been about 4.2 million tonnes. This compares with an earlier official target of a slight improvement on the 1995-96 harvest of 4.45 million tonnes.</p>
<p>Havana has also said that Helms-Burton may have caused some potential investors on the island to make their decisions more slowly. Cuba is heavily reliant on foreign investment as it seeks to pull out of a five-year economic crisis caused by the collapse of its old trade and aid partner the former Soviet Union.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HAVANA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CUBA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
