<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732251" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Versace murder dismays Asia's fashion trade.</title>
<headline>Versace murder dismays Asia's fashion trade.</headline>
<byline>Carrie Lee</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The murder of fashion designer Gianni Versace sent shockwaves through Asia on Wednesday and cast gloom over one of the biggest fashion shows in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a shock to the industry,&quot; said Kenneth Fang of the Hong Kong Trade Development Council (TDC), at the opening session of Hong Kong Fashion Week.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a loss to the fashion industry. We are very sorry to hear the news. Actually he does have a very sizeable market in Hong Kong,&quot; said Fang, head of the TDC's apparel committee.</p>
<p>At the Versace flagship store in Sydney a small printed sign announced the shop was closed for trading until Thursday, and in Singapore mannequins in the designer's boutiques were dressed in black to mark his death.</p>
<p>In Tokyo, a Gianni Versace Japan company spokeswoman said staff were stunned but there were no plans to hold a commemoration ceremony.</p>
<p>&quot;We were very shocked and saddened when we heard the news this morning. We're waiting for word from the headquarters in Italy before we do anything,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The 50-year-old Italian fashion designer was shot twice on the steps of his Miami Beach mansion by a lone gunman on Tuesday.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for the five Gianni Versace boutiques in Hong Kong, where brand name snobbery reigns, said more people than usual visited the boutiques on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Today we have had a larger flow of people in the shops because some of Mr Versace's long-term fans came to chat with us and take a look at the clothes after they heard the news,&quot; the spokeswoman said.</p>
<p>&quot;Some people may have wanted to collect particular items,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong designers were shattered by his death and paid tribute to his talent.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel very sad,&quot; Kevin Yeung, chairman of the Hong Kong Designers' Association, told Reuters. &quot;It's a great pity. He was very talented. I was very shocked that such violence should have taken place when he was in such an advanced country.&quot;</p>
<p>The sentiment was echoed by Ika, an Indonesian Chinese designer based in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>&quot;I was very, very saddened, very shocked because he is one of my very favourite designers,&quot; said Ika. &quot;And I am sure that he's going to be missed, not only by customers ... (but by) all the people who love fashion,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Model Karin Holm said she was puzzled by the murder.</p>
<p>&quot;I was shocked because I didn't know his life was in danger, I couldn't see any reason for him to get killed or deserve that fate at all. Personally I think Versace is one of the greatest tailors.&quot;</p>
<p>Socialite and businesswoman Jennifer Tose, who wears Versace designs, said she was stunned by his death and expected his creations to become collectibles.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing I said was 'Oh, my God',&quot; she sighed. &quot;I wear Versace clothes myself. I feel it's a pity. Even if he has successors, the clothes won't be the same.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I think now his work will become collectible items.&quot;</p>
<p>In Sydney's busy lunchtime traffic, most passers-by only threw a quick glance at the Versace shopfront sign but some of the designer's fans stopped to remember him.</p>
<p>&quot;It's really sad that with all the violence in the world you can't even stand around outside your house. He should have stayed in Italy,&quot; said 22-year-old Gemma Colomeo, a former fashion student.</p>
<p>Sales staff at Versace's Singapore store said it was appropriate to change the colour scheme of the store to black to mark his death.</p>
<p>&quot;The entire Versace line across the world is saddened by the death. In Singapore we are donning black attire on all our mannequins,&quot; a spokesman for the Versace store said.</p>
<p>Asked if there had been any change in store sales after news of the designer's murder, he said it was business as usual.</p>
<p>&quot;The line will still sell well if not even better after his death ... we are confident his fashion empire will continue,&quot; the spokesman said.</p>
<p>In Tokyo, Jun Ashida, famed clothes designer for many of Japan's Imperial Family members, said Versace's talents were irreplaceable.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody can replace someone with the talents that he had. It's truly a big loss for the fashion world. He was a trendsetter and a pioneer. In that sense the fashion world will lose some of its vigour.&quot;</p>
<p>Versace shopper Chizuru Yoshimura, 28, said the designer's death would have an impact on fashion in Japan.</p>
<p>&quot;He was one of the major designers so I think the fashion scene here will change quite a bit,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a great loss. I really liked his style even though it's really expensive,&quot; another shopper, Atsuko Shizukawa, 21, said.</p>
<p>In Bombay, Narendra Kumar Ahmed, fashion editor of the Indian edition of Elle magazine, said the industry had lost a distinctive style &quot;which was glamorous, had shades of Hollywood-style glamour in its modern context&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
