<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732360" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: EPA unveils final new air pollution standards.</title>
<headline>EPA unveils final new air pollution standards.</headline>
<byline>Donna Smith</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Environmental Protection Agency Administrator Carol Browner Wednesday signed controversial new air pollution control rules that have been hailed by health groups and criticised by industry and local governments.</p>
<p>&quot;These new updated air quality standards are the next step in fulfilling the vision of the Clean Air Act, which directs us to set standards that protect the public health with an adequate margin of safety based on the latest, best-available science,&quot; Browner said at a White House ceremony announcing the final rules.</p>
<p>The ceremony prompted opponents of the new standards to hold their own event on Capitol Hill. The bipartisan group of House members, mostly from the industrial Midwest and Ohio Valley, said their bill to stall the new rules had 55 co-sponsors and would be acted on quickly.</p>
<p>&quot;Newt told me again today this bill is going to move. I think it's going to be on a relatively fast track,&quot; Michigan Republican Representative Fred Upton said, referring to House Speaker Newt Gingrich.</p>
<p>House Commerce Committee Chairman Thomas Bliley of Virginia said he would co-sponsor the bill &quot;in the hope of giving the debate a jump start.&quot;</p>
<p>A similar measure was expected to be offered in the Senate, and two-thirds majorities in both chambers would be needed to override an expected White House veto.</p>
<p>&quot;Like others, Democrats and Republican alike, I have been increasingly frustrated by the EPA's failure to justify these proposals, and the government's unwillingness to come forward with the information America needs to form an intelligent opinion,&quot; Bliley said in a statement.</p>
<p>But Browner said the rules would prevent about 350,000 cases of aggravated asthma and result in easier breathing for millions of children.</p>
<p>Industry and local governments have criticised the new standards for smog, or ozone, and particulate matter, or soot, as too costly. Under the plan, major producers of smog and soot such as big power plants would be required to reduce their emissions and areas violating the rules would be punished.</p>
<p>In response to some of the criticisms, the EPA changed the standards for ozone in the final rule to make it easier for businesses and local communities to be in compliance by allowing more &quot;bad air&quot; days. Also, the amount of particulate matter allowed in the air was raised in the final rules, the EPA said.</p>
<p>&quot;We've developed a plan to implement these new standards in the most flexible common-sense and cost-effective ways so that they will deliver both cleaner air and continued economic progress,&quot; Gore said at the White House event.</p>
<p>&quot;Communities and businesses will be afforded ample time to reduce pollution and bring themselves into compliance,&quot; he added. &quot;States are now working together to reduce pollutants that originate in one area and affect cities located far downwind.&quot;</p>
<p>The rules are set to take effect in 60 days, but they will not require local controls for ozone until 2004 and for soot until 2005. Compliance will not be enforced until 2007 for ozone and 2008 for soot and extensions are possible, EPA said.</p>
<p>The EPA said Tuesday that nationwide some 280 counties will fail to meet the new limits on ozone and 150 counties will fail to meet its soot standards. The numbers are lower than had been predicted by industry groups battling the new standards.</p>
<p>Under current standards, 106 counties are out of compliance with smog limits and 41 counties are violating limits on particulate matter.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
