<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732333" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>ISRAEL: Israel seen facing &quot;religious totalitarianism&quot;.</title>
<headline>Israel seen facing &quot;religious totalitarianism&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>JERUSALEM 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The chairman of Israel's largest industrial conglomerate said on Wednesday the Jewish state was moving towards &quot;religious totalitarianism&quot; and wary foreign investors might take their money elsewhere.</p>
<p>Stanley Gold, president of Shamrock Holdings Ltd, the second-biggest shareholder in Koor Industries Ltd, sounded the warning in a speech at the Reform Jewish Hebrew Union College, which awarded him an honorary doctorate.</p>
<p>An American Jew and long-time benefactor of the college, Gold attacked legislation sponsored by religious political parties -- key players in the right-wing coalition government -- to enshrine in law a monopoly of Orthodox rabbis on conversions to Judaism.</p>
<p>&quot;Investors fear that the new atmosphere in Israel could hurt share prices of all Israeli companies, Koor included,&quot; he said. &quot;If anyone thinks I'm exaggerating, then again I suggest they just look at the economy of Iran.&quot;</p>
<p>He said ultraorthodox pressure to close streets in religious neighbourhoods on the Jewish Sabbath and shut businesses on Saturday in violation of contractual commitments was &quot;just the recipe&quot; for chasing away capital.</p>
<p>&quot;The conversion law and the religious totalitarianism it represents do not just threaten to harm Israel among the Jewish community but also among the investment community,&quot; Gold said.</p>
<p>&quot;Unlike the financial support of the (Jewish) diaspora, which is based on emotion, the investment of businessmen is based on cold analysis. And the fact is that investors avoid divided societies which impose arbitrary limitations.&quot;</p>
<p>Gold, who sat next to former Labour Prime Minister Shimon Peres at the ceremony, called on the Israeli people to &quot;rise up&quot; and stop the conversion law.</p>
<p>If they don't, he said, &quot;extremists&quot; will continue to push back &quot;the forces of democracy and decency and Jews and investors around the world will increasingly turn away -- and for good reason&quot;.</p>
<p>The conversion legislation won preliminary approval in parliament in April but caused an uproar in the influential Jewish community in the United States.</p>
<p>A committee headed by Israel's new finance minister Yaacov Neeman is working to find a compromise by a target date of August 15.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ISRAEL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JERUSALEM"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ISRAEL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
