<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732375" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. waives part of anti-Cuban law again.</title>
<headline>U.S. waives part of anti-Cuban law again.</headline>
<byline>Donna Smith</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>President Bill Clinton on Wednesday waived for another six months parts of a law that toughens the U.S. embargo against Cuba, citing the cooperation of U.S. allies in seeking to end Communist rule on the island.</p>
<p>It was the third time Clinton has suspended parts of the Helms-Burton law that would allow U.S. citizens to sue foreign firms deemed to have profited from property confiscated from them by Cuba after the 1959 revolution led by Fidel Castro.</p>
<p>&quot;I have invoked this waiver for the past year in order to continue strengthening cooperation with our friends and allies toward our shared goal of ending Cuba's 38 years of oppression,&quot; Clinton said in a statement.</p>
<p>He said efforts by Undersecretary of State for Economic Affairs Stuart Eizenstat to forge an agreement with the United States' allies, mainly the European Union, on pressing for democratic change in Cuba were beginning to pay off.</p>
<p>&quot;We are making real progress in strengthening the international effort to bring democracy to Cuba,&quot; Clinton said. &quot;The Cuban people and the Castro regime hear the message more clearly than ever.&quot;</p>
<p>Clinton postponed implementation of the Title Three section of Helms-Burton that allows U.S. firms and citizens, including Cuban exiles who are now naturalised, to file law suits in U.S. courts over their confiscated properties.</p>
<p>The Cuban government poured scorn on Clinton's move.</p>
<p>&quot;The empire (United States) has conceded to the world six months more sovereignty, but the law is still extraterritorial and unacceptable for us,&quot; Cuban Foreign Ministry spokesman Miguel Alfonso told reporters in Havana.</p>
<p>The Cuban exile community condemned the waiver and said it showed that the Clinton administration never had any interest in enforcing the anti-Castro legislation.</p>
<p>&quot;The losers in the administration's duplicitious policy toward Cuba are American citizens whose private property will continue to be subject to foreign exploitation and the Cuban people who are watching U.S. support for their freedom struggle take a back seat,&quot; said Republican Representative Ileana Ros-Lehtinen, a Cuban-American who represents a section of Florida with a large exile community.</p>
<p>Helms-Burton, named for its Republican sponsors, calls for a radical political overhaul in Cuba as a condition to normal ties with the United States.</p>
<p>The law, which seeks to discourage foreign investment in Cuba, was promptly signed by Clinton last year after Cuba shot down two small planes flown by Cuban exiles from Miami.</p>
<p>Its controversial parts are Title Three, providing for law suits in U.S. courts, and Title Four, which allows executives of foreign companies deemed to be benefiting from expropriated Cuban property to be denied entry to the United States.</p>
<p>So far, executives of a Canadian mining firm and a Mexican telecommunications company have been denied U.S. visas.</p>
<p>These sections of the law annoyed the United States's main trading partners who complained that Washington was acting beyond its jurisdiction and breaking international law.</p>
<p>The European Union threatened to challenge the law before the World Trade Organisation. But the confrontation was defused by Eizenstat, with Washington agreeing to hold off implementing controversial aspects of the law in return for renewed European commitment to press for change in Cuba.</p>
<p>The two sides agreed in April they would work out an understanding on what to do with confiscated property in Cuba by mid-October, when the White House would seek a change in the law to allow the president to also waive the visa section.</p>
<p>Clinton will continue to enforce the visa provision during negotiations between the United States and the European Union.</p>
<p>Eizenstat said the White House will waive Title Three as long as U.S. allies continue taking a tougher line on Cuba.</p>
<p>&quot;The president would expect to continue to suspend it so long as our allies are stepping up their activity in support of democracy in Cuba,&quot; he told a State Department briefing.</p>
<p>Eizenstat said Cuba was more isolated than ever before and international pressure for democratic change was now at its highest level than at any time since Castro seized power.</p>
<p>&quot;Castro himself has felt it necessary to increase his diplomatic activity to counter the effects of the president's initiative,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
