<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732484" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Hong Kong farm trade outlook good, USDA aide says.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong farm trade outlook good, USDA aide says.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Agricultural trade with Hong Kong, the United States' eighth largest market, is continuing apace following the former British territory's return to China, a U.S. Agriculture Department aide said Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's pretty much business as usual,&quot; LaVerne Brabant, director of the U.S. Agricultural Trade Office in Hong Kong. &quot;I'm very optimistic about the future of trade.&quot;</p>
<p>Brabant and other overseas U.S. Agriculture Department aides are in town this week for an annual conference.</p>
<p>Despite the historic turnover on July 1 after more than a century of British rule, &quot;the truth is that really nothing has changed&quot; on the business front, Brabant said.</p>
<p>Tariffs on most agricultural imports were zero before July 1 and will stay that way, despite tariffs in the range of 40 to 50 percent elsewhere in China, he said.</p>
<p>The Hong Kong dollar also remains linked to the U.S. dollar, giving the United States an advantage, Brabant said.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, Hong Kong's population increased more in the 18 months preceding the turnover than it did in the last 10 years, Brabant said.</p>
<p>Many investors and businessmen who got the jitters after the Chinese government's bloody crackdown in Tiananmen Square in Beijing have returned because the economic opportunities in Hong Kong are better than they can find elsewhere, he said.</p>
<p>China has a powerful economic incentive to keep Hong Kong a thriving economic community because the city supplies about two-thirds of foreign investment in China, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;They don't want to mess it up,&quot; Brabant said.</p>
<p>In 1996, U.S. agricultural exports to Hong Kong totaled $1.486 billion, much of which was re-exported to China.</p>
<p>But the amount of transhipments vary by commodity. For poultry, it could be as high as 70 percent; for table grapes, it's probably in range of just 15 percent, Brabant said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's hard to say it's being smuggled. That's not the right word,&quot; Brabant said. But for a variety of reasons, agricultural products that enter China through Hong Kong generally face lower duties than elsewhere in the country.</p>
<p>Even after the turnover, Hong Kong remains an independent member of some 20 international organizations, including the World Trade Organization.</p>
<p>China is not a member of the WTO, but has applied to join.</p>
<p>As a condition for entry, the US is pushing China to lower agricultural tariffs and other trade barriers.</p>
<p>Even so, &quot;I think we're a long way from seeing zero Chinese tariffs&quot; outside of Hong Kong, Brabant said.</p>
<p>And Hong Kong will remain an important agricultural trade center even if tariffs are reduced elsewhere in China because of its port facilities and access to capital.</p>
<p>((Doug Palmer, 202 898 8341))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
