<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732402" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Ex-surgeon general - Big Tobacco unethical. [CORRECTED 20:36 GMT]</title>
<headline>Ex-surgeon general - Big Tobacco unethical. [CORRECTED 20:36 GMT]</headline>
<byline>Michael Connor</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A former U.S. surgeon general said on Wednesday in a $5 billion secondhand-smoke trial that the tobacco industry's own research in the 1960s and 1970s helped create a medical consensus that smoking caused cancer.</p>
<p>At the same time, Julius Richmond (corrects from Richardson throughout), the U.S. government's top medical official under President Carter, testified that the industry vigorously and unethically fought government anti-smoking campaigns. Big Tobacco also refused to cooperate with researchers working on sweeping Surgeon General Reports assessing studies on smoking and health risks, he said.</p>
<p>Richmond, the leadoff witness in the trial, said the tobacco industry denounced the 1979 Surgeon General's report on smoking's health dangers, one day before it was released, without ever having seen the report itself.</p>
<p>&quot;No one had seen the report,&quot; Richmond said. &quot;I was offended because it was a very unethical process.&quot;</p>
<p>The first Surgeon General's Report, issued in 1964 and reviewing all research on smoking and health up to that time, concluded that smoking was a substantial health risk and rocked the U.S. tobacco business. That report lead to a law in 1966 requiring that cigarettes sold in the United States carry health warnings.</p>
<p>The 1979 report included some health studies funded at a cost of $15 million by the tobacco industry, and Richmond said those studies helped bring about the conclusion that cigarette smoking was connected to lung cancer and other diseases among Americans. He said he agreed that smoking was &quot;slow-motion suicide.&quot;</p>
<p>Richmond, now professor emeritus at Harvard University's medical school, also testified that reports issued by the Surgeon General's office and the National Academy of Sciences in 1986 solidified scientific thinking on the dangers of secondhand, or environmental, smoke to young children and other non-smokers.</p>
<p>Secondhand smoke likely caused asthma in children and emphysema, lung and sinus cancers, and cardiac diseases in adults, Richmond said.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel that after 1986 ... it was really established scientifically that there was a relationship between environmental tobacco smoke and cancer and other disorders,&quot; Richmond told the six jurors hearing the landmark case.</p>
<p>During later questioning by Walter Cofer, a lawyer for defendants Philip Morris Inc. and Lorrillard, Richmond acknowledged that the American Cancer Society in 1988 and non-medical researchers at the Congressional Research Service in 1994 concluded that data tying secondhand smoke to disease were inconclusive. The American Cancer Society has since judged secondhand smoke a health danger.</p>
<p>Lawyers pressing the secondhand-smoke case on behalf of an estimated 60,000 non-smoking flight attendants with tobacco-related illnesses claim that U.S. tobacco companies knowingly sold a defective product and lied, deceived and conspired to hide the dangers of smoking and secondhand smoke.</p>
<p>&quot;On the basis of the scientific evidence and what we know of the composition of cigarette smoke ... breathing secondhand smoke in enclosed spaces, particularly ones like airplane cabins, (carries) a risk of disease that is considerable. It does cause disease,&quot; Richmond said.</p>
<p>Trial consultants monitoring testimony said Richmond, a bespectacled man who spoke softly and slowly to the jury, had stood up well to the cross examination.</p>
<p>&quot;He was very powerful for the plaintiffs on the tobacco industry's influence on public policy,&quot; said one consultant.</p>
<p>But, the consultants said, the tobacco lawyers successfully chipped away at his assessment that the dangers of secondhand smoke were fully accepted by mainstream scientists in the mid 1980s.</p>
<p>Testimony in the case, Norma Broin et al vs Philip Morris et al, was scheduled to continue on Thursday and was expected to last until at least September. It is both the first secondhand-smoke case and the first class-action suit against the U.S. tobacco industry to come to trial.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I42900">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
