<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732428" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. waives part of Helms-Burton law.</title>
<headline>U.S. waives part of Helms-Burton law.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. President Bill Clinton has decided to waive for another six months parts of the Helms-Burton law that toughens Washington's embargo against Cuba, the State Department announced on Wednesday.</p>
<p>It was the third time Clinton had suspended parts of the law that allows U.S. citizens to sue in U.S. courts foreign firms deemed to have profited from American property confiscated by Cuba after its 1959 communist revolution.</p>
<p>In announcing the decision, Undersecretary of State for Economic Affairs Stuart Eizenstat noted that Washington's effort to persuade allies in Europe and Latin America to take a tougher line on Cuba's human rights record had been paying off over the past six months.</p>
<p>&quot;The president would expect to continue to suspend (Title Three) so long as our allies are stepping up their activity in support of democracy in Cuba,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>While suspending that portion of the law, the Clinton administration has enforced another section that denies U.S. visas to senior executives of foreign companies deemed to have &quot;trafficked&quot; in confiscated property in Cuba.</p>
<p>The Helms-Burton Act, designed to bring pressure to bear on Cuba to adopt democratic reforms, was signed into law in March 1996, a month after Cuban warplanes shot down two civilian aircraft, killing four Cuban-Americans on board.</p>
<p>The law, named for its Republican sponsors Sen. Jesse Helms of North Carolina and Representative Dan Burton of Indiana, has been bitterly criticised by Canada and the European Union, which fears their companies may be subject to lawsuits under the provisions that Clinton suspended on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Eizenstat said international pressure on Cuba to initiate democratic change now was at its highest level than at any time since President Fidel Castro seized power.</p>
<p>&quot;Castro himself has felt it necessary to increase his diplomatic activity to counter the effects of the president's initiative,&quot; he told reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;Much more can, should and will be done but today we can genuinely say that it is Cuba's government that is increasingly isolated in the Western Hemisphere and around the world,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Eizenstat added that in order to make additional progress the United States must continue to have the cooperation of its allies.</p>
<p>&quot;As a result, the president again has decided to suspend the right to file suit under Title Three for an additional six months,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Clinton also waived the controversial portions of the law in July 1996 and January 1997. He is required to make the decision every six months and his deadline to do so was midnight EDT (0400 GMT on Thursday).</p>
<p>The waiver drew criticism from major supporters of the Helms-Burton Act. Representative Ileana Ros-Lehtinen, a Florida Republican and the first Cuban-American elected to Congress, condemned the decision, saying it showed that Clinton &quot;never had an interest in fully enforcing the legislation.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The losers in the administration's duplicitious policy toward Cuba are American citizens whose private property will continue to be subject to foreign exploitation and the Cuban people who are watching U.S. support for their freedom struggle take a back seat,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
