<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732499" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: US expects dumping ruling in Mexico sweetener case.</title>
<headline>US expects dumping ruling in Mexico sweetener case.</headline>
<byline>Julie Vorman</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexico is unlikely to pursue a dumping case against U.S. beef producers but U.S. makers of corn sweeteners are facing an uphill battle in a growing trade dispute, a U.S. agricultural attache in Mexico said Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's possible that the final decision could show no dumping but I'm inclined to think that they may follow through on it and determine that there is in fact dumping,&quot; Norval Francis, counselor for ag affairs at the U.S. Embassy in Mexico City, said in an interview at USDA headquarters.</p>
<p>On June 24, Mexico slapped import tariffs on high fructose corn syrup exports from the United States after domestic sugar producers complained U.S. firms were dumping supplies at below production cost. Last year Mexico imported about 350,000 tonnes of the sweetener, which is used in soft drinks, beverages and other food products.</p>
<p>The preliminary decision by the Mexican government also imposed duties as high as $174 per tonne on U.S. exports. A final decision is expected in October.</p>
<p>The U.S. Feed Grains Council earlier this week asked U.S. Trade Representative Charlene Barshefsky to challenge the decision.</p>
<p>But U.S. beef producers are less likely to become embroiled in a trade war, despite a clamor from Mexican cattlemen for government protection, Francis said.</p>
<p>The Mexican government has not yet responded to a request by the Mexican Feedlot Association to investigate imports of U.S. beef at below-production prices.</p>
<p>&quot;The cattle producers in Mexico are finding themselves increasingly squeezed by U.S. exports. And any industry that finds itself in that position looks for alternatives or tools to protect themselves,&quot; Francis said.</p>
<p>U.S. sales of beef to Mexico are one of the fastest-growing agricultural exports, bringing stiff competition for Mexican feedlots that typically import U.S. feedgrain for their herds.</p>
<p>&quot;It's still unlikely to proceed, but Mexico has done a number of dumping cases against the United States in both ag and industrial areas to a higher degree than they normally had done, and that worries me a bit,&quot; Francis said.</p>
<p>A recent dumping claim by apple producers in Chihuahua against U.S. producers &quot;was a real shocker,&quot; he said. That case is under investigation by the Mexican government, which has yet to issue a preliminary finding.</p>
<p>Francis also said that U.S. ag exports to Mexico could top $5 billion next year.</p>
<p>Last year, U.S. ag exports totaled some $5.5 billion, a big jump over the previous year because of a lengthy drought which forced Mexico to import more U.S. grains than normal, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Current thinking is that we should probably be about $5 billion in exports,&quot; he said. &quot;I'm optimistic, it could perhaps be even more.&quot;</p>
<p>An economic recovery in Mexico has also boosted consumer demand for meats and processed food. Mexico is the United States' third biggest market for ag exports after Japan and Canada.</p>
<p>&quot;Longer term, Mexico could easily become our second-largest trading partner in agriculture,&quot; Francis said, pointing to growth in exports of beef, pork, poultry, apples and other products.</p>
<p>&quot;Part of the benefit the United States is deriving from this economic upturn is due to NAFTA. Mexico has used NAFTA as a tool to prevent protectionist forces from taking over and pushing for protection of local industry,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>((Washington commodities desk 202 898 8467))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I41400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
