<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732539" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FDA panel backs Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn's Rogaine solution.</title>
<headline>FDA panel backs Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn's Rogaine solution.</headline>
<dateline>BETHESDA, Md. 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. Food and Drug Administration advisory panel Wednesday approved Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn Inc.'s minoxidil 5 percent solution (Rogaine) as an over-the-counter treatment for male-pattern baldness.</p>
<p>It is a stronger version of the over-the-counter Rogaine 2 percent solution currently available.</p>
<p>The panel said Rogaine 5 percent should not be sold to women due to lack of efficacy and also said Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn could not claim that Rogaine 5 percent grew hair faster than the 2 percent solution.</p>
<p>The FDA is not bound by its panels' advice but usually follows it.</p>
<p>Pharmaica &amp; Upjohn hopes to increase the number of Rogaine users and sales -- $162 million in the United States in 1996 -- with the 5 percent solution.</p>
<p>If approved, Rogaine 5 percent could have up to three years of marketing exclusivity. Generic versions of Rogaine 2 percent appeared a month after its introduction in April 1996, surprising the company, said company spokesman John Ruane.</p>
<p>Even so, the over-the-counter launch increased the number of U.S. users fivefold to about 2 million, said Michael Valentino, president of the consumer health care unit.</p>
<p>Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn is targeting the 6 million to 7 million men it thinks are motivated to do something about their thinning hair.</p>
<p>The 5 percent solution works better and faster than the 2 percent solution, Valentino said. In two clinical studies, male users of the 5 percent solution had 46 percent more hair growth at the end of the 48-week trial than those using the 2 percent solution.</p>
<p>Hair growth at eight weeks in 5 percent users was the same as at 16 weeks for 2 percent users.</p>
<p>The panel said that did not prove faster growth.</p>
<p>Side effects -- including dryness, itching, and flushing and redness -- were worse than with Rogaine 2 percent.</p>
<p>FDA has received similar reports since the first Rogaine was launched in 1988, but also has gotten reports of increased hair loss and that it doesn't work.</p>
<p>Fourteen patients who had taken twice the recommended dose had increased heart rates, but an FDA reviewer said the effect is likely to be very rare.</p>
<p>P&amp;U also conducted two trials in women, but in each, almost half dropped out. The FDA said that women using the 5 percent solution did not have significant hair growth compared with the 2 percent solution. Some also had unwanted facial hair growth.</p>
<p>Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn says it is pursuing new trials. Only about 250,000 women are currently using Rogaine 2 percent for Women, according to the company.</p>
<p>Rogaine 5 percent is approved in 19 countries for men and women, either by prescription or over the counter.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BETHESDA, Md."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
