<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732599" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Gays fear Versace suspect still in their midst.</title>
<headline>Gays fear Versace suspect still in their midst.</headline>
<byline>Jim Loney</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI BEACH, Fla 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>As police combed South Beach bars and hotels on Wednesday for Gianni Versace's killer, gays said they feared the male prostitute suspected of the crime was still in their midst and wondered why they had not had more warning of his presence.</p>
<p>Andrew Cunanan, connected with four murders during a killing spree in northern U.S. states in April and May, is the prime suspect in the execution-style slaying of the Italian designer Tuesday on the steps of his Miami Beach mansion.</p>
<p>Police, state and FBI agents fanned out across the island city, questioning people on the street, in gay bars, hotels, rooming houses, restaurants and nightclubs in the belief Cunanan might still be in the area.</p>
<p>Rumours were rampant on Wednesday that he was spotted in South Beach, the glittery model and tourist mecca Versace made his part-time home, as recently as the day of the killing and as long ago as a couple of months.</p>
<p>The FBI said Cunanan, a high-priced homosexual prostitute, was spotted in West Palm Beach two weeks ago. But authorities declined to say how long he might have been in south Florida.</p>
<p>&quot;Check the time frame of the last crime,&quot; one law enforcement source said.</p>
<p>Cunanan was suspected in the May 9 shooting death of cemetery caretaker William Reese, 45, in Pennsville, New Jersey, which could put him in south Florida as long as two months ago. Reese's late model red pickup truck was found in a Miami Beach parking garage after Versace's murder.</p>
<p>Members of the homosexual community expressed fear that Cunanan might still be here and wondered why there had not been a massive publicity campaign to notify them that a serial killer might be stalking their streets.</p>
<p>&quot;Some people I've talked to are wondering if the ball was dropped,&quot; said George Mangrum, Miami bureau chief of Scoop, a Florida gay magazine with a circulation of 22,000.</p>
<p>Mangrum said Scoop received an FBI wanted poster on Cunanan by fax during the last week of June and published it in its July 2 edition. &quot;It was the pictures and that he was wanted for murder and was possibly enroute to south Florida,&quot; he said. &quot;It was the first and only warning.&quot;</p>
<p>At Hombre, a well-known South Beach gay hangout, a wanted poster occupied a prominent position on the black-painted wall behind the bar. But a bartender said it arrived within the last 24 hours and was the first warning the bar had received.</p>
<p>&quot;There was some warning,&quot; Tim Barnum, president of the South Beach Business Guild, the gay chamber of commerce. &quot;South Beach would be the logical place for him to show up.&quot;</p>
<p>Danilo de la Torre, an actor who performs as a drag queen in South Beach clubs, said his show was nearly empty on Tuesday night as customers stayed home to watch news about the murder.</p>
<p>&quot;People are shocked it could happen. Really shocked and scared. He's still out there,&quot; de la Torre said. &quot;People were uninformed about him.&quot;</p>
<p>Carl Weersing, 36, said the gay community wondered if the killer had spent some time stalking Versace and whether other gay men were in danger.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm being really careful,&quot; Weersing said outside Club Body Tech, a gym frequented by homosexual male weightlifters. &quot;I know last night friends of mine who were out walking their dogs and they said 'we're walking in pairs.' It really puts a whole new consciousness on the situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Weersing said while Versace was not a flamboyant member of the community, he was an active visitor to gay hangouts. &quot;He was out there. He was socializing. You would hear about him having a party. It would start out at his home and end up at Liquid (a popular nightclub).&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;He was usually out with his boyfriend,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Police were flooded with tips on Cunanan Wednesday. A school principal from Montreal, Canada, gesturing at a wanted poster, told police she spotted him heading toward Versace's mansion at about 11 a.m. Tuesday, two hours after the murder.</p>
<p>Tony Hunter, a manager at the 11th Street Diner across the street from Miami Beach Police headquarters, said he thought Cunanan had eaten at the restaurant in the last month or two.</p>
<p>&quot;Frequently, actually, for me to remember his face,&quot; Hunter said. &quot;I remember seeing him in here.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI BEACH, Fla"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
