<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732511" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Brazil may buy US soybeans in 97/98-US attache.</title>
<headline>Brazil may buy US soybeans in 97/98-US attache.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil may import U.S. soybeans in the 1997/98 marketing year despite a record crop of its own, the U.S. attache posted to Sao Paulo said Tuesday.</p>
<p>High global prices have resulted in speedy sales of this year's crop. Prospects of a record U.S. soybean crop this fall could make U.S. soybeans an attractive commodity for Brazilian processors if local supplies tighten, attache Bob Hoff said in an interview.</p>
<p>&quot;This is something they're looking at,&quot; Hoff said.</p>
<p>Shipping sources say Paraguay already has sold 800,000 tonnes for delivery to Brazil, he said.</p>
<p>USDA has forecast the Brazil crop at 28.0 million tonnes and 1997/98 exports of seven million tonnes and imports of 2.25 million tonnes.</p>
<p>By comparision, Brazil's 1996/97 crop was 26.5 million tonnes with exports of 7.85 million tonnes and imports of 800,000 tonnes.</p>
<p>Hoff said private-sector groups in Brazil were likely in the near future to begin making their own estimates of domestic coffee output with the goal of producing an accurate and respected forecast.</p>
<p>There has been dispute over a U.S. Agriculture Department estimate that the current crop would total 28 million bags. Hoff's office suggested a lower figure, 24 million bags.</p>
<p>During the interview, Hoff said the only official USDA estimate was the forecast of 28 million bags. His office's report was unofficial and one component in the USDA estimating process, he said.</p>
<p>It will be a few more weeks before the Sao Paolo office takes a new look at the coffee crop, he said, and it might be December before a new attache report on the crop would be released. If a report is filed in the near term, he said, &quot;it probably would be descriptive, on what we found&quot; in a field survey.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01002">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100223">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
