<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732510" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: India may still need 1-2 mln T wheat--USDA aide.</title>
<headline>India may still need 1-2 mln T wheat--USDA aide.</headline>
<text>
<p>WASHINGTON, July 16 (Reuter) India appears to have filled its near-term need for wheat, but may still have to import an additional 1.0 to 2.0 million tonnes later this year, a U.S. Agriculture Department official said Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;For now, they seemed to have filled their needs--at least for the next few months,&quot; Thomas Pomeroy, U.S. agricultural counselor in New Delhi told Reuters. &quot;There's a possibility they might buy a million or two more tonnes, but I don't think they're going to do it for several months.&quot;</p>
<p>Pomeroy and other overseas U.S. agriculture department aides are in town this week for an annual conference.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, India bought 2.7 million tonnes of wheat from Australia, Canada and Argentina and expectations were that it would buy as much as 1.5 million tonnes more.</p>
<p>But import plans have been put on hold after cooler-than- usual weather in parts of India this year led to a larger-than- expected wheat crop, Pomeroy said.</p>
<p>The Indian government estimates the domestic wheat crop at 69 million tonnes, compared to USDA office in New Delhi's estimate of 67 million, Pomeroy said.</p>
<p>If India does return to the world wheat market, the U.S. should be in a better position to make sales than it was earlier this year, Pomeroy said.</p>
<p>In early 1997, Australian wheat prices were substantially below the U.S., but that is no longer the case.</p>
<p>Also, the United States has been working to address grain quality concerns raised by the Indian government and remove that issue as a barrier, Pomeroy said.</p>
<p>Even if India does not import more wheat this year, its growing population and economy will require it to import substantial amounts from time to time, he said.</p>
<p>((--Doug Palmer, 202 898 8341))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
