<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732557" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Versace murder shows Miami's grime and glitter.</title>
<headline>Versace murder shows Miami's grime and glitter.</headline>
<byline>Angus MacSwan</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI BEACH 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The murder of fashion king Gianni Versace has again shown the raw and violent face of Miami behind the glitter and the glamour.</p>
<p>As news flashed around the world of his killing on Tuesday on arguably the hippest sidewalk in the United States, local officials immediately sought to repair the damage to the image of their metropolis.</p>
<p>Greater Miami has struggled to reinvent itself as a glamorous, exotic travel destination and dynamic business centre, shedding its 1980s notoriety as a crime-ridden city riven by racial problems and languishing in the grip of cocaine barons.</p>
<p>With Versace's death, &quot;South Florida has once again become the place where high life and violent death dance cheek to cheek,&quot; wrote John Grogan in Wednesday's Sun Sentinel.</p>
<p>Officials hope the negative effect will be limited. Tourists gathered outside Versace's mansion on Ocean Drive in ultra-hip South Beach, where mourners created a shrine of flowers and candles.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think Miami Beach is dangerous,&quot; said Karine Ouimet, a 22-year-old swimwear representative from Montreal.</p>
<p>&quot;This is a great place to relax. Obviously there are parts of Miami you don't go to. He was killed for a reason.&quot;</p>
<p>Chadi and Amal Bazzi, a Lebanese couple from Minneapolis who arrived on Tuesday for a vacation, were less sure.</p>
<p>&quot;We were aware of Miami's reputation but the publicity said its safe, now it's not like the 'Miami Vice&quot; thing any more,&quot; Chadi, 24, who said he lived in Beirut during the Lebanese Civil War.</p>
<p>&quot;Then we get here and there's this Versace thing -- it's like the TV show. It does make you think twice. We were hesitant to come and might not have if this happened earlier.&quot;</p>
<p>Hardly had Versace's blood been washed from the mansion steps than Dade County Mayor Alex Penelas told reporters the incident could have happened in any city in the world.</p>
<p>But Miami's ugly side has never gone away. The front page of the Miami Herald on the newstands as Versace took his last walk blared &quot;Massacre on the Miami River&quot; -- four people were killed in a weekend shootout on a docked freighter.</p>
<p>Reports of gruesome murders fill crime pages, organised crime and narcotics smuggling are rife, and last year Miami was rocked by a city hall corruption scandal.</p>
<p>Miami and Miami Beach are officially separate entities -- the latter a slither of land in the Atlantic Ocean linked to the mainland by causeways -- but in the public perception they are the same place, as officials ruefully note whenever scandal or tragedy hits.</p>
<p>Since its renaissance as a pulsating playground for the young, rich and famous -- it was until the 1970s a rundown community of retirees and often criminally inclined Cuban refugees -- Miami Beach has been relatively free of bloodshed.</p>
<p>&quot;Our biggest thing is tourist crime but it's mostly low-level, car break-ins and theft, that sort of thing,&quot; said officer Eugene Petit at the Miami Beach Police Headquarters.</p>
<p>However, take the wrong turn on the expressway from Miami Airport to Miami Beach and you end up in Liberty City, one of the most violent neighbourhoods in the United States.</p>
<p>In late 1992, 10 foreign tourists were killed in Miami or elswhere in Florida, drenching it in bad publicity and scaring off visitors. A Dutch tourist was killed in 1996.</p>
<p>Mayco Villafana of the Greater Miami Visitors Convention said he was initially worried about the adverse publicity from the Versace murder but was now less so.</p>
<p>&quot;It doesn't mean there won't be a fallout. No one wants to see their city in the world news for such a horrible crime,&quot; he said. &quot;But we are not the same city as we were in 1993. There has been an incredible reduction in crime.&quot;</p>
<p>Miami Beach would nevertheless suffer, as it had lost one of its most prominent and creative citizens. Versace was &quot;one of the major forces that made Miami Beach what it is,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Chris Privert of the American Society of Travel Agents also expected no serious damage to tourism.</p>
<p>&quot;It seems this was anything but a random act so it's a different scenario,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The Sun Sentinel's Grogan even saw a somewhat macabre benefit.</p>
<p>&quot;More likely it will only add to the allure of this place where danger and fashion and beautiful people blend into one seamless steamy blur against the endless backdrop of the azure ocean,&quot; he wrote in his column.</p>
<p>&quot;That snaphsot of his bloodied doorstep becomes the ultimate South Florida souvenir.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI BEACH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
