<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732594" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: &quot;Long Island Lolita&quot; is denied prison move.</title>
<headline>&quot;Long Island Lolita&quot; is denied prison move.</headline>
<dateline>BUFFALO, N.Y. 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A judge Wednesday rejected a request by &quot;Long Island Lolita&quot; Amy Fisher to be transferred from a prison where she alleges she was raped by guards.</p>
<p>Fisher is serving a 5- to 15-year sentence for the May 19, 1992, shooting of the wife of her lover Joey Buttafuoco. Mary Jo Buttafuoco still has a bullet lodged in her face.</p>
<p>The case grabbed national headlines and was the subject of several made-for-TV movies about the love affair between Joey Buttafuoco and then 16-year-old Fisher, who was dubbed the &quot;Long Island Lolita&quot;.</p>
<p>He served four months of a 1-1/3- to 4-year sentence for the statutory rape of Fisher.</p>
<p>State officials said her lawsuit claiming unspecified damages against the New York State Department of Correctional Services and several guards for her alleged rape in jail would continue.</p>
<p>In a 109-page ruling, U.S. District Court Judge Richard Arcara in Buffalo, N.Y. refused to grant a preliminary injunction to have Fisher, 22, transferred to another prison.</p>
<p>But the Judge indicated that there is a problem with inmates and staff at Albion having sex, which is against the law but was not illegal at the time Fisher said the alleged rapes occurred.</p>
<p>Fisher, who wanted to be moved to a prison in Connecticut to be closer to home, was turned down for parole last month from Albion state prison in western New York.</p>
<p>Judge Arcara questioned the reliability of Fisher's story as well as testimony from her mother and a psychologist hired by Fisher, who alleges she was raped several times by a prison guard shortly after going to Albion.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUFFALO, N.Y."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
