<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732534" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Senate threatens Russian aid cut over religion.</title>
<headline>Senate threatens Russian aid cut over religion.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Senate on Wednesday voted nearly unanimously to cut off U.S. aid to Russia if President Boris Yeltsin signs into law a measure to curb the rights of minority religions.</p>
<p>The Senate voted 95-4 to cut U.S. foreign aid in reaction to passage by the Russian Duma of a measure that would deny legal status to new religious groups for 15 years.</p>
<p>It would give higher legal status to those religious organisations that have been in existence in Russia for 50 years, a definition that encompasses the Russian Orthodox church, Judaism, Islam and Buddhism. It also would impose new curbs on religious activities by foreign groups.</p>
<p>The threatened curb on new assistance was approved as an amendment to the $13.2 billion foreign aid bill now moving through the Senate. The bill contains about $200 million in funds for Russia.</p>
<p>Sen. Tim Hutchinson, an Arkansas Republican, praised Yeltsin's refusal to sign a similar law four years ago.</p>
<p>During Senate debate he said the Duma action was &quot;a misguided effort to protect the orthodox Russian church.&quot; Hutchinson was one of a group of U.S. lawmakers who met with the speaker of the Russian Duma at a conference in Poland last week.</p>
<p>&quot;This is potentially the greatest retreat on religious freedom and human rights since the fall of the Soviet Union and it is an ominous sign about the future of that republic,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The amendment was sponsored by Sen. Gordon Smith, an Oregon Republican.</p>
<p>The House has not yet considered its version of the foreign aid bill but several lawmakers have expressed the same strong concerns regarding the religious legislation.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
