<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732699" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Versace set seal on Miami Beach transformation.</title>
<headline>Versace set seal on Miami Beach transformation.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Zengerle</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI BEACH 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Miami Beach, the site of designer Gianni Versace's murder, has transformed itself over 20 years from a crumbling retiree backwater to one of the world's glitziest hotspots.</p>
<p>Versace's arrival five years ago seemed to set the seal on the area's makeover.</p>
<p>In 1992, the trend-setting designer bought an old apartment house on the beachfront Ocean Drive, by then a centre for jet-setting fashion and tourism. He rehabilitated the building into an award-winning Mediterranean mansion, knocking down a hotel next door to build gardens and a pool.</p>
<p>Versace became one of the first big-name designers to set up shop at the trendy southern end of Miami Beach, known as South Beach, when he established a boutique just blocks from his house. He opened the doors of his residence for glittering business, social and charitable events.</p>
<p>&quot;That such an international figure would want to make South Beach one of his homes, shows that ... the progress had reached such a point that it was worth his time and effort, that it was exciting for him,&quot; said Eugene Patron, a board member at the South Beach Business Guild.</p>
<p>&quot;It was the icing on the cake,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But Versace also won friends by acting like just another part of the community, a man who walked around his neighbourhood to buy coffee or books while other local celebrities spent their days in limousines, flanked by bodyguards.</p>
<p>It was after one of his morning walks that Versace was shot and killed on Tuesday morning, gunned down in broad daylight on the steps of his mansion by a man police called a serial killer and homosexual prostitute.</p>
<p>The loss plunged the neighbourhood into shock and mourning.</p>
<p>Community leaders rushed to remind potential visitors that the killing was an extraordinary event and the Art Deco neighbourhood remained the glamorous paradise that had attracted the fashion magnate.</p>
<p>&quot;Let me assure you that Miami Beach and Dade County are safe despite this terrible incident,&quot; Dade County Mayor Alex Penelas told a news conference after Versace's death.</p>
<p>Miami Beach was founded in the 1920s by car-dealing millionaire Carl Fisher, who dreamed of turning a mosquito-ridden swamp into Florida's version of St. Tropez.</p>
<p>It was built up in the 1930s with dozens of Art Deco hotels, featuring pastel colours and curved lines similar to the modernist style popular for automobiles of the day.</p>
<p>In the 1950s, Miami Beach saw the construction of sprawling hotel &quot;pleasure palaces&quot; such as the Fountainebleau, which attracted stars like Joan Crawford, Frank Sinatra and Jackie Gleason, who filmed his television show there.</p>
<p>But by the 1970s, Miami Beach's buildings and population were showing their age, and the one-time vacation hotspot became known as &quot;God's waiting room.&quot;</p>
<p>The rebirth began in the 1970s, when activists founded the Miami Beach Design Preservation League and urged the restoration, not demolition, of old hotels.</p>
<p>Miami Beach's historic Art Deco District was established in 1976 and South Beach became the first 20th century neighbourhood on the U.S. National Register of Historic Places.</p>
<p>By the 1990s, when Versace and other celebrities became mainstays on its streets, the area had become a white-hot vacation spot.</p>
<p>Local activists called Versace's death a tragedy, but said they disagreed with those who gave the designer all the credit for reviving South Beach.</p>
<p>&quot;He certainly played a significant role in Miami Beach, but to credit him with the renaissance of south Miami Beach is a mistake, a flat-out mistake,&quot; said Randall Robinson, preservation planner with the Miami Design Preservation League.</p>
<p>&quot;Abraham Lincoln played a huge role in American history, but he wasn't one of the founding fathers,&quot; he said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI BEACH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
