<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732780" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FBI pursues leads on fugitive in Versace killing.</title>
<headline>FBI pursues leads on fugitive in Versace killing.</headline>
<byline>James Vicini</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The FBI pursued leads on Wednesday on the whereabouts of an alleged multiple killer suspected of murdering Italian fashion designer Gianni Versace, confidently vowing to catch one of the nation's most-wanted fugitives.</p>
<p>FBI agents said an intense nationwide manhunt was under way for Andrew Philip Cunanan, who has been identified as the only suspect in Tuesday's shooting death of Versace in front of his oceanfront villa in Miami Beach, Florida.</p>
<p>The agents warned that the elusive, male prostitute, who previously had been wanted in connection with four other murders, should be considered armed and extremely dangerous.</p>
<p>They enlisted the public's help for any tips on his whereabouts and said they were checking numerous telephone calls in an effort to find the 27-year-old Cunanan.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we're going to approach this simply as a criminal investigation with a wanted fugitive and just do business as usual. We'll track him down eventually,&quot; FBI special agent Paul Philip said in Miami.</p>
<p>&quot;It's quite possible he might be holed up some place.... Just being safe, since this is the last place he was, we're going to concentrate our search right here,&quot; he told CNN.</p>
<p>&quot;In any homicide, the first 24 hours are critical. We're going to spend our time working in this community until we have a pretty verifiable sighting elsewhere .... As time goes on we may have to broaden our search, but I think he may still be here,&quot; Philip said.</p>
<p>FBI officials in Washington, D.C. said little more could be done to find Cunanan and acknowledged that investigators have no idea where he might be.</p>
<p>&quot;Nobody knows where he is. He could be in line right now outside FBI headquarters, waiting to take the tour. We just don't know,&quot; one official said.</p>
<p>&quot;There really isn't anything else extraordinary that can be done,&quot; the official said. The FBI last month placed Cunanan on its 10 most-wanted fugitives list and offered a $10,000 reward for information leading to his arrest.</p>
<p>The officials said the investigation was being run out of the FBI's office in Minneapolis, where Cunanan first was charged with the shooting death of his former lover, an architect.</p>
<p>He also is wanted for questioning in three other murders in Minnesota, Illinois and New Jersey. The Versace killing, along with the other murders, would be handled as local prosecutions without any federal involvement.</p>
<p>The FBI is seeking Cunanan on a federal arrest warrant charging him with unlawful flight to avoid prosecution since he became a fugitive in early May.</p>
<p>FBI spokesman George Grotz in San Francisco said the law enforcement agency was asking local residents to be on the alert for Cunanan, who has often visited the city in the past. He was last spotted there in late April, Grotz said.</p>
<p>&quot;He's elusive, he's bright, he's articulate, he ingratiates himself to his victims. He's just extremely dangerous,&quot; Grotz said of Cunanan.</p>
<p>He asked people to provide any information on Cunanan, no matter how insignificant.</p>
<p>&quot;If they've got a possible line on him, we'd like to know about it,&quot; he said. &quot;This is clearly an individual who needs to be taken off the street.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
