<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732741" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Bluesman Luther Allison has inoperable lung cancer.</title>
<headline>Bluesman Luther Allison has inoperable lung cancer.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Paris-based blues guitarist and singer Luther Allison, 57, has been stricken with inoperable lung cancer, his record label said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Allison was diagnosed on July 10 after suffering dizziness and loss of coordination during a recent concert tour, and was in a Madison, Wisconsin, hospital. Doctors found the lung cancer had spread to his brain.</p>
<p>&quot;We are deeply saddened that on July 10 Luther Allison was diagnosed with lung cancer and metastatic brain tumours. He is undergoing treatment and is looking forward to returning to the stage as soon as he is in remission,&quot; a statement from Allison's family and management said.</p>
<p>Allison quit smoking several years ago, and enjoys playing tennis and fishing, a spokesman said.</p>
<p>He was promoting his third album, &quot;Reckless,&quot; for Alligator Records, after recording three albums for a Motown Records subsidiary in the 1970s. His first record, &quot;Love Me Mama,&quot; was recorded on the Delmark label in 1969.</p>
<p>Born in Widener, Arkansas, Allison developed his hard-driving brand of blues in Chicago's clubs and came to prominence in the late 1960s at blues festivals.</p>
<p>Frustrated by a slide in blues' popularity amid the rise of rock-'n'-roll and his own stalled career, Allison moved to Paris in the early 1980s and continued to draw large concert audiences across Europe.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
