<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732895" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bonn bans CD calling for racist killings.</title>
<headline>Bonn bans CD calling for racist killings.</headline>
<byline>Fiona Fleck</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>German authorities have blacklisted a recording of neo-Nazi songs urging Germans to kill foreigners, a spokeswoman for the Family Ministry said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>She said Family Minister Claudia Nolte had put the CD entitled &quot;12 German Sing-Along Songs&quot; on an index of banned publications considered dangerous to young people.</p>
<p>&quot;The recording has potential to incite racial hatred,&quot; Nolte said in an internal communique to the BPJS federal office assigned to protect juveniles from dangerous publications.</p>
<p>She recommended that the BPJS should pass the recording of songs by a pop band called The Turk Hunters from Zillertal to prosecutors to launch a criminal investigation.</p>
<p>&quot;The potential for violence has reached a new dimension. We are seeing how neo-Nazi propaganda is becoming increasingly vicious and sensational,&quot; Nolte said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;Extreme right-wing groups have now started encouraging racial hatred on their CDs...and even calling for killings (of foreigners). The Turk Hunters from Zillertal is a particularly aggressive example.&quot;</p>
<p>The government has been clamping down on neo-Nazi propaganda and activities, securing several high-profile convictions including that of U.S. neo-Nazi Gary Lauck who was jailed for four years in 1996 for inciting racial hatred in Germany.</p>
<p>But the authorities are becoming particularly concerned about an increase in the use of rock music recordings and concerts to convey a neo-Nazi message of racial hatred.</p>
<p>One song on the CD includes the lines: &quot;On the North Sea coast, on the Aryan beach, we don't want any kaffers in our country.&quot;</p>
<p>A song called Kreuzberg Nights, referring to an area in Berlin with a large Turkish community, has the line: &quot;They lie there in their blood, I must say the sight of this does me good.&quot;</p>
<p>The mass-circulation Bild newspaper reported this week that the authorities had blacklisted about 130 recordings including CDs, cassettes and records by extreme right-wing groups since 1991.</p>
<p>The ban means the recordings cannot be advertised or sold or made available to under-18s.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
