<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732853" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: EU sets course to welcome ex-communist members.</title>
<headline>EU sets course to welcome ex-communist members.</headline>
<byline>Janet McEvoy</byline>
<dateline>STRASBOURG, France 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Plans for the European Union to embrace five former communist nations were formally unveiled on Wednesday in a blueprint to propel the bloc into the 21st century.</p>
<p>The EU's executive Commission said in a report entitled &quot;Agenda 2000&quot; that Poland, Hungary, the Czech Republic, Estonia and Slovenia should be selected from among 10 eastern European candidates to begin EU membership talks along with Cyprus next year.</p>
<p>Commission President Jacques Santer predicted difficult talks for the EU's latest, and most ambitious, expansion, but said the first countries from beyond the former Iron Curtain could join between 2001 and 2003.</p>
<p>&quot;The first phase of enlargement I would put around 2001, 2002, 2003. That's the period I have in mind,&quot; Santer told a news conference after unveiling to the European Parliament what he called a &quot;road map&quot; for the EU's future.</p>
<p>The plan involved enormous challenges for the five eastern European countries selected and the five disappointed easterners left out for the moment, and drastic change for the existing 15-nation bloc, Santer told the parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;We have an historic opportunity, carrying with it profound changes,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The expansion meant radical reforms of key EU policies, including a shake-up of its Common Agricultural Policy and its support programmes for poorer member countries.</p>
<p>Santer told the parliament that a further streamlining of EU decision-making procedures would also be necessary to prepare for the influx of new members.</p>
<p>The EU's recent inter-governmental conference failed to agree on the institutional changes necessary for a bloc with up to a dozen new members.</p>
<p>At pains to counter charges of discrimination from Latvia, Lithuania, Slovakia, Bulgaria and Romania -- all judged by the Commission unready to join the wealthy western bloc -- Santer said no one was being left out.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not a process of exclusion. On the contrary, it's a process of inclusion that will be pursued permanently,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But in Romania Prime Minister Victor Ciorbea said the EU was wrong to proceed with expansion in waves and he pledged to foster reforms to reverse the decision to deny his country early entry.</p>
<p>&quot;Expansion by waves...is not justified for European Union enlargement, which is a process of continuous integration,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>In Latvia, Maris Riekstinsh, foreign ministry state secretary, told a news conference his country would try to get up to scratch before EU leaders take a final decision at the year end on the extent of the EU's first eastwards expansion.</p>
<p>&quot;We have to mobilise ourselves, to prove the readiness of our state to start membership negotiations with the EU before the end of this year,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Documents prepared by the Commission to judge the readiness of the 10 eastern applicants for membership also said that, although five had not made the grade, they should be kept in what amounts to a &quot;waiting room&quot; where they can prepare for membership at their own pace.</p>
<p>In what Santer said amounted to a new Marshall Plan for the east, the Commission said it had earmarked 75 billion Ecus ($82 billion) to help the 10 applicants prepare for membership.</p>
<p>The radical reform of the Common Agricultural Policy prescribes dairy, cereals and beef intervention price cuts of 10, 20 and 30 percent respectively, to be partially compensated by direct income payments to farmers.</p>
<p>Santer said that lowering the prices would ease the integration of the eastern countries, whose prices are much lower, reduce the risk of food mountains and keep spending under control.</p>
<p>The Commission also said the EU's overall budget should be no more than 1.27 percent of the bloc's gross domestic product, relying on ecomomic growth to provide the extra funds needed in the immediate future.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CYPR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ESTNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="POL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SLVNIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="STRASBOURG, France"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
