<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732871" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Youths in short supply for Pope's Paris visit.</title>
<headline>Youths in short supply for Pope's Paris visit.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Young people may be in short supply for the Roman Catholic Church's World Day of Youth, which is scheduled to be celebrated during a Papal visit to Paris in August, French church officials said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Just 74,159 young people from across Europe have paid the fees required to participate while 300,000 had been expected to attend, Monsignor Michel Dubost, who is organising the event, told a news conference.</p>
<p>A total of 185,102 youths had pre-registered for the event but fewer than half had followed up their indication of interest with a payment, he said.</p>
<p>Particularly disappointing was the small turnout from Pope John Paul's native Poland, where 20,000 to 40,000 young people had registered their intention to come though 60,000 had been expected.</p>
<p>&quot;I am not panicking,&quot; Dubost told reporters, explaining that the numbers could well improve before the celebration's start.</p>
<p>Thus he has begun lining up volunteers to provide housing all 300,000 young people even if only a fraction of those actually show up, he said.</p>
<p>The Pontiff is scheduled to arrive in Paris for the event on August 21 and return to Rome on August 24.</p>
<p>While in France, he also will honour the French anti-poverty organisation ATD Quart Monde and beatify 19th century academic Frederic Ozanam, Dubost said.</p>
<p>Ozanam, a professor at the Sorbonne University who specialised in the history and literature of the Middle Ages, was known for his commitment to social justice.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
