<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732881" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU, US, Japan agree drugs-approval streamlining.</title>
<headline>EU, US, Japan agree drugs-approval streamlining.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union, Japan and the United States have agreed to develop a common document to streamline regulatory procedures for pharmaceutical products in the three regions, participants in the talks said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The agreement, which aims to cut down on costly duplication, came during the fourth International Conference on Harmonisation (ICH), which unites EU, Japanese and U.S. regulators and industry officials.</p>
<p>&quot;This is going to be the main project over the next two years,&quot; Patrick Deboyser, head of pharmaceuticals at the European Commission, told a news conference.</p>
<p>The parties agreed that companies seeking approval for a new drug should be able to provide technical information on a common document that could be submitted to all three regulatory authorities.</p>
<p>Alexander Giaquinto of the Schering-Plough Research Institute in the United States said a recent survey showed that European and U.S. companies spent an average of three months on adapting their drug-approval applications to the other market.</p>
<p>&quot;That's three months of lost time,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The participants decided against working toward a completely common dossier, however, because of legal and administrative differences between the three regions, he said.</p>
<p>A first meeting of experts on the &quot;common technical document&quot; has been scheduled for next January, Giaquinto said.</p>
<p>The ICH was set up in 1990 to harmonise procedures for developing and registering new medicines. The body has completed a first phase by developing about 40 guidelines on the safety, efficacy and quality of drugs, tests, studies and clinical trials. -- Suzanne Perry, Brussels Newsroom 32 2 287 6800</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I25700">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G158">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
