<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732818" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: POLL -- U.S. shows no signs of closing trade gap.</title>
<headline>POLL -- U.S. shows no signs of closing trade gap.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gaping U.S. current account and merchandise trade deficits will persist at least into 1999 as major U.S. trading partners continue to wrestle with severe economic problems, analysts said.</p>
<p>Japan faces a rolling financial sector crisis and poor economic growth while much of Europe is struggling under costly labor market structures and fiscal stringency in preparation for monetary union.</p>
<p>As a result, the robust U.S. economy will continue to suck in exports at a much faster clip than its trading partners can, analysts said.  </p>
<p>&quot;If the rest of the world were growing at something like its potential growth rate and unemployment rates were lower, you'd have the sense that we wouldn't run these imbalances,&quot; said Richard Koss, international strategist at MFR Inc.</p>
<p>In the latest quarterly Reuters survey, economists predicted on average that the annual U.S. merchandise trade gap would sit near $150 billion in 1997 and 1998, while the current account deficit would balloon past $160 billion.</p>
<p>Japan has recently vied with China as the biggest contributor to U.S. trade shortfalls even as U.S. officials have repeatedly clamored for Japanese fiscal stimulus and economic reforms to correct the problem.  </p>
<p>&quot;Treasury Secretary (Robert) Rubin has said quite emphatically that we're not going to let Japan export its way out of recession,&quot; said Christopher Rupkey, economist at Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi.</p>
<p>But despite Japan's public lip service to U.S. concerns, analysts said Japanese officials would move slowly, if at all, in curbing exports, the only significant driver in the Japanese economy.</p>
<p>&quot;It's hard to guess how long they're going to need to run these big surpluses to dig themselves out of the hole, but there's certainly no sign that we are anywhere near the point of getting that behind us,&quot; said Koss.  </p>
<p>One potential U.S. remedy is a weaker dollar and indeed the greenback has slipped off its peak above 127 yen to trade near 115 recently.</p>
<p>That decline helps U.S. manufacturers price goods more competitively, and should minimize complaints from domestic producers about the strength of the dollar, analysts said.</p>
<p>&quot;Dollar/yen between 100 and 120 makes sense. I don't think (Japan's) advantage is that great at current levels,&quot; Rupkey said.</p>
<p>In fact, the dollar's relative strength has provided U.S. consumers and businesses with a steady supply of cheaper foreign goods, keeping inflation at bay and protecting corporate profits, analysts said.</p>
<p>So despite the ubiquitous objections from automakers and some smaller firms, the trade gap raises few red flags domestically.</p>
<p>&quot;It will become an issue if we sustain sub-trend growth for several quarters in a row. Then you can really expect the political pressure to heat up,&quot; said Koss.</p>
<p>Additional inquiries should be directed to Jeff Coelho, 212-859-1562.</p>
<p>(( -- Chris Stetkiewicz, 212-859-1664 ))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
