<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732953" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Holocaust memorial goes back to drawing board.</title>
<headline>Holocaust memorial goes back to drawing board.</headline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's plans for a memorial to the six million Jews murdered under Hitler were sent back to the drawing board on Wednesday when Berlin's top culture official said he had opened a new competition for its design.</p>
<p>Peter Radunski said he was inviting another 16 international artists and architects to present ideas in the hope of finally ending the much-delayed process of finding a fitting German monument for Jews killed in the Holocaust.</p>
<p>&quot;The memorials that America, Poland, Israel or Holland have created are so different from each other -- and the German memorial will also be different,&quot; Radunski said in a statement.</p>
<p>&quot;Germany's national memorial for the murdered Jews of Europe will necessarily be defined by Germany's own present memory of the Holocaust, a complex and difficult memory,&quot; Radunski said.</p>
<p>Although an official jury had cobbled together a blueprint from winning designs in 1995, the proposed design collapsed under the weight of widespread criticism that ranged from members of the Jewish community to Chancellor Helmut Kohl.</p>
<p>That plan entailed erecting a concrete slab the size of a football field near the new Berlin government quarter, engraved with the names of 4.2 million of the Jewish Holocaust victims.</p>
<p>The new design competition will include 16 new artists and architects from across Europe, the United States and Israel and the nine finalists of the 1995 competition. A winner will be selected on October 31.</p>
<p>A series of three forums earlier this year with politicians, Jewish leaders, artists and historians intended to provide clear guidelines for the continuation of the project at times degenerated into shouting matches and ultimately failed to focus the debate.</p>
<p>Only the 15 million mark ($8 million) budget and the target date for the groundbreaking on January 27, 1999 -- the 54th anniversary of the liberation of Auschwitz -- have remained points of consensus among the project's main participants.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
